<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Pharmacol Pharmacother</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Pharmacol Pharmacother</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JPP</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Pharmacology &amp; Pharmacotherapeutics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0976-500X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0976-5018</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications &amp; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3826001</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JPP-4-256</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0976-500X.119711</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Virtual screening studies reveal linarin as a potential natural inhibitor targeting CDK4 in retinoblastoma </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sivashanmugam</surname><given-names>Muthukumaran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raghunath</surname><given-names>Chandana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vetrivel</surname><given-names>Umashankar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><italic>Center for Bioinformatics, Vision Research Foundation, Sankara Nethralaya, College Road, Chennai, Departement of Bioinformatics, Sastra University, Tirumalaisamudram, Thanjavur, Tamilnadu, India</italic></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Umashankar Vetrivel, Center for Bioinformatics, Vision Research Foundation, Sankara Nethralaya, College Road, Chennai, India. E-mail: <email xlink:href="vumashankar@gmail.com">vumashankar@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Oct-Dec</season><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © Journal of Pharmacology and Pharmacotherapeutics</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Objective: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>To find out whether linarin can be used as a potential natural inhibitor to target CDK4 in retinoblastoma using virtual screening studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec id="st2"><title><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>In this study, molecular modeling and protein structure optimization was performed for crystal structure of CDK4 (PDB id: 3G33), and was subjected to Molecular Dynamics (MD) simulation for 10 nanoseconds, as a preparatory process for docking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the stable conformation obtained in the MD simulation was utilized for virtual screening against the library of natural compounds in Indian Plant Anticancer Compounds Database (InPACdb) using AutoDock Vina. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Finally, best docked ligands were revalidated individually through semi-flexible docking by AutoDock 4.0. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec id="st3"><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Results: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The CDK4 structure was stereochemically optimized to fix clashes and bad angles, which placed 96.4% residues in the core region of Ramachandran plot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The final structure of CDK4 that emerged after MD simulation was proven to be highly stable as per different validation tools. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Virtual screening and docking was carried out for CDK4 against optimized ligands from InPACdb through AutoDock Vina. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>This inferred Linarin (Inpacdb AC.NO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>acd0073) as a potential therapeutic agent with binding energy of -8.9 kJ/mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, it was also found to be valid as per AutoDock 4.0 semi-flexible docking procedure, with the binding energy of -8.18 kJ/mol and Ki value of 1.01 μM. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec id="st4"><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Conclusion: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The docking results indicate linarin, a flavonoid plant compound, as a potential inhibitor of CDK4 compared to some of the currently practiced anticancer drugs for retinoblastoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>This finding can be extended to experimental validation to assess the in vivo efficacy of the identified compound. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>Cyclin-dependent kinase 4</kwd><kwd>InPACdb</kwd><kwd>molecular docking</kwd><kwd>molecular dynamics</kwd><kwd>retinoblastoma</kwd><kwd>virtual screening</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1-1"><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The cyclin-dependent kinases (CDKs) are a conserved family of proline-directed serine/threonine kinases that play a key role in regulation of cell cycle in eukaryotic cells.[1] The activity of CDKs is regulated most significantly through interaction with cyclins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>CDK family is known to have a high level of structural homology, especially CDK2 shares 45% sequence identity with CDK4.[2] The resemblance has helped spearhead research involving design of inhibitors for CDK4, mimicking the CDK2 inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>CDK4 associates with D-type cyclins (D1, D2, and D3), phosphorylates and inactivates the retinoblastoma protein family members (p107, p130, pRb).[1] In human beings, pRb is encoded by the RB1 gene located on 13q14.1-q14.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Phosphorylation of pRb by CDK4 inactivates pRb, causing the activation of E2F target genes, which facilitates progression through the G1 phase of the cell cycle, eventually leading to the condition of retinoblastoma.[1] </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Developing and identifying small molecule inhibitors targeting CDK4 has been a prime area of research since past two decades. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Some of the drugs that have been proven as desirable targets for cancer are flavopiridol, butyrolactone, the purine-based olomoucine and its analogues, arcyriaflavin A, and isoquinolinedione analogues.[2] Flavopiridol, the first CDK inhibitor for human beings derived from an indigenous plant from India, demonstrated potent and specific in vitro inhibition of all CDKs tested (CDKs 1, 2, 4, and 7), clearly blocking the cell cycle progression at the G1/S and G2/M boundaries.[3] However, flavopiridol is not selective for CDK4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>It inhibits other CDKs to almost the same extent as CDK4.[4] In similar lines, most CDK inhibitors suffer from low selectivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The low selectivity of these chemical compounds may cause adverse side effects.[56] This brings up the need for more potent and selective CDK4 inhibitors with better efficiency for the condition of retinoblastoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Natural compounds have their advantage over chemical inhibitors by being a safer substitute and ensure lesser/no side effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>A library of 125 natural compounds was taken from Indian Plant Anticancer Compounds Database (InPACdb) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.inpacdb.org/">http://www.inpacdb.org/</ext-link>)[7] to test them for their efficiency as therapeutic agent for CDK4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>This study aims to find out whether linarin can be used as a potential natural inhibitor to target CDK4 in retinoblastoma using virtual screening studies </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Molecular optimization was carried out for crystal structure of CDK4 as a preparative process for docking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The structure was fixed for stereochemical clashes and bumps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The modeled protein was then subjected to Molecular Dynamics (MD) simulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The decoy having lowest potential energy was chosen from MD simulation, and was found to be valid as per many validation tools. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the optimal structure was subjected to Virtual screening using the compounds from InPACdb, which were optimized using LigPrep, then, docking simulation was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>On stringent scrutinization, one of the compounds emerged to show reliable inhibitory activity as expected for a CDK4 inhibitor. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The coordinates of CDK4 was downloaded from Protein Data Bank (PDBid: 3G33).[8] The sequence for the same was retrieved from Uniprot[9]; UniprotID: P11802. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The unphosphorylated model of CDK4 (3G33:Chain A) was modeled using Modeller 9v8[10] and was refined to fix steric clashes and bumps using WHAT IF server.[11] To draw the initial starting models closer to their native state in terms of hydrogen bonds, side-chain positioning, and backbone topology, Modrefiner was used.[12] The output of the same was taken for loop refinement to obtain a structure which when evaluated using PROCHECK[13] placed 0.0% residues in the disallowed regions of Ramachandran plot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The refined protein was further subjected to MD simulation using GROMACS4.3.5[14] with GROMOS96 43a2 force field.[15] The system was solvated in a cubical box with SPCE waters and counter ions (2 Na+) were added to neutralize the charge of each system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The system was energy minimized by steepest decent for 1 000 steps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>NVT and NPT steps were processed as a part of equilibration phase for 100ps each, after which MD simulation was initiated to be run for 10ns.[15] </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The stabilized protein was validated using various tools such as Charmm-gui,[16] PatchFinderPlus,[17] Protein Quality Predictor (ProQ),[18] ProSA,[1920] Predyflexy,[21] Psipred,[22] and Qsitefinder[23] for analyzing electrostatic property, protein flexibility, and binding site analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>CDK4 is known to have ATP-binding region between 93 and 102 residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Various groups have reported drug designs targeting the same pocket.[2] </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>KinDOCK server was used to provide both potential ligands and their putative binding orientation for our optimized protein.[24] The top ten ligands binding favorably to the ATP-binding region of CDK4 were taken, and the favorable interactions made at the binding site were noted and analyzed with the data acquired from the previous works, as listed in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Virtual screening was carried out with the 125 natural compounds from InPACdb.[7] The compounds were optimized using LigPrep[25] module of Schrodinger, then were docked to our protein of interest using AutoDock Vina module through Pyrx interface.[26] Based on binding energy as the parameter, top 10 ligands having lower binding energy values were chosen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Purine-based analogues emerged as the basic structure to mimic in our drug, on analyzing the structure of flavopiridol, isoquinolinedione analogues.[62728] This gave us five ligands out of ten which mimicked purine-like analogues, for which semi-flexible docking was performed with CDK4 using AutoDock 4.0.[29] Ten conformers were generated for each of these best five CDK4 inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Binding energy, Ki value, and Hydrogen bonding interactions with the protein were used as the criteria for filtering the best inhibitor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Pymol (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pymol.org/">http://www.pymol.org/</ext-link>) and Accelrys Discovery Visualizer[30] were used to view and interpret the Protein-Ligand interactions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>List of CDK4 active site residues </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPP-4-256-g001"/></table-wrap></SecTag></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2-1"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Protein structure refinement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>3G33: Chain A was taken for homology modeling using Modeller 9v8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Single template modeling was performed on 3G33: A as the template, with CDK4 sequence as the target. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The protein was then fixed for bumps and clashes using WHAT IF server. Modrefiner was used to generate significant improvement in physical quality of local structures by drawing the initial model closer to native state in terms of hydrogen bonds, side-chain positioning, and backbone topology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The structure that was produced after refinement had Cys135 in disallowed region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>This brought in the need for loop refinement to be carried out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The loop-refined model placed 96.4% of all residues in the allowed regions with no residues in the disallowed region of Ramachandran Plot as shown in Figure 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The model after being fixed of stereochemical clashes was taken to be stabilized by running MD simulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>(a) Refined structure of the CDK4 protein, where helix is shown in red, yellow indicates beta sheets, and coil is shown in green color. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>(b) Ramachandran Plot of the protein after structural refinement </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPP-4-256-g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Molecular dynamics simulation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The refined protein was subjected to MD simulation using GROMACS 4.3.5 with GROMOS96 43a2 force field. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The system was solvated in a cubical box with SPCE waters containing 23260 molecules and 2 Na+ ions were added to neutralize the charge of each system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The system was energy minimized by steepest decent method for 1000 steps, after which the potential energy of the system dropped from -1.25970e + 06 to -9.28789e + 05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Position restraint was performed using NVT and NPT steps that were processed as a part of equilibration phase for 100ps each, after which MD simulation was initiated to be run for 10ns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>For analyzing simulation results, Xmgrace program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plasma-gate.weizmann.ac.il/Grace/">http://plasma-gate.weizmann.ac.il/Grace/</ext-link>.) was used to generate root mean square deviation (RMSD), potential energy, radius of gyration, and solvent-accessible surface graphs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>RMSD graph shows a steep incline in the deviation starting from 1Å to 3.9Å, which stabilizes at around 3.5Å, and it drops to a minimum of around 3Å at 6800ps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The deviation pattern then retraces 3.5Å level till 10ns, as shown in Figure 2a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Potential energy traces a reliable drop in value over 10ns of MD simulation, with the lowest potential energy structure observed at 6820ps as shown in Figure 2b. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Radius of gyration is indicative of compactness of the protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>There is an observable drop in its value from 2.7 to 2 nm, as shown in Figure 2c. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The lowest value of radius of gyration at around 6820ps is indicative of the high degree of compactness observed in the protein in its lowest energy state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Overall decrease in radius of gyration from 2.065 to 1.99 nm shows the increase in compactness of the protein after 10ns of simulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Solvent-accessible surface area indicates the residue's exposure to solvent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The protein in its lowest potential energy shows a dip in hydrophobicity levels (increase in hydrophilicity), clearly indicating that the protein converges in shape over time during simulation, as shown in Figure 2d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Pymol was used to visualize the 3D structure of the simulated protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Starting with the structure taken for simulation, the binding pocket cavity change in the structure was analyzed for 10ns with an interval time of 1ns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>ATP-binding site's flexibility increased with time, as shown in Figures 3a and b. The protein with the lowest potential energy (at 6 820ps) was taken as the final CDK4 structure for further studies, as shown in Figure 3b. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>(a) The RMSD graph, with deviation stabilizing close to 3.25Å at the end of 10ns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Overall deviation in rmsd over 10ns was observed close to 2.25Å. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>X-axis shows time in ps and Y-axis indicates RMSD in nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>(b) potential energy graph over 10ns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The lowest potential energy was noted at 6820ps, marked with a red circle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>X-axis shows time in ps and Y-axis indicates potential energy value in kJ/mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>(c) Solvent-accessible surface graph, showing the drop in hydrophobicity near the structure with lowest potential energy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>X-axis shows time in ps and Y-axis indicates Area in nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>(d) Radius of gyration graph, which drops in value by a good margin indicating the structure converging in shape acquiring compactness with time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>X-axis shows time in ps and Y-axis indicates Radius of gyration in nm </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPP-4-256-g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>(a) ATP-binding site cavity change observed over 5ns, with interval of 1ns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The binding site cavity (shown in Cyan) converges in shape over time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Helix is shown in red, yellow indicates sheets, and coil is shown in green color. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>(b) ATP-binding site cavity change observed 6-10ns, with interval of 1ns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The binding site cavity (shown in Cyan) converges in shape over time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The structure with lowest potential energy assumes a compact figure as shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The ATP-binding site in the structure with lowest potential energy is shown in blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Helix is shown in red, yellow indicates sheets, and coil is shown in green color </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPP-4-256-g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Validating structure of simulated protein </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>To validate the structure of the simulated protein, various tools were used to check the electrostatic properties, binding site flexibility, and interactions involved in the active site. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Protein electrostatics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The PBEQ Solver of Charmm-gui solver helped interactively to visualize the calculated electrostatic potential on the solvent-accessible surface as well as isoelectrostatic potential contours of the stabilized protein molecule by solving the Poisson-Boltzmann (PB) equation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The positive charge on the ligand was important for improving selectivity for CDK4, because of the electronegative nature of the active site.[16] The active site was confirmed to be electronegative in nature with the red patch spread over the residues in the ATP-binding region, as shown in the Figure 4a. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>(a) The electrostatic potential map generated using charmm force field using charm-gui. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The region encircled in black shows the electronegative binding pocket. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Different shades of red shows varying levels of electronegativity of the residues, white color indicates residues with neutral charge, and different shades of red shows varying levels of electropositivity of the residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>(b) the results of patch finder plus that displays the largest positive patch (indicated in blue) in the protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The largest positive patch does not include the residues in the binding site </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPP-4-256-g005"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The Pathfinder algorithm calculates the PB electrostatic potential of the protein and constructs the largest continuous positive patch on the protein surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Clarity of result was established by the absence of positively charged residues in the protein's binding site, as shown in the Figure 4b. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Quality prediction using protein quality predictor and ProSA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>ProQ is a neural network-based predictor of protein's structure quality based on a number of structural features. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>LGscore and MaxSub are the quality measures that are used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>LG score attempts to minimize P value for distribution, while Maxsub attempts to maximize Levitt Gerstein score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>As predicted for a very good model, the value of LG score was 5.380 and that of MaxSub was 0.612. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Proteins that contain long target sequences are more likely to get good LG score, while the sequences that are short by length are more likely to get a good MaxSub score, which is well correlated with our result. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>ProSA calculates the overall quality score for a specific input structure by displaying in a plot, the score of a specific model that relates to the scores computed from all experimental structures deposited in PDB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Z-score with higher negative value is indicative of a reliable result. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Z-score of our model showed a value of -8.24 post-simulation, with the structure appearing close to X-ray region on the plot. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Residue-wise stability prediction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Predyflexy Server examines flexibility according to two different descriptors, the B-factor and root mean square fluctuations, from MD simulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>It defines three flexibility classes and proposes a method based on the LSP (Line Spectrum Pair) prediction method for predicting flexibility along the sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Predyflexy Server produced the protein with good flexibility in the active site region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Predicted flexibility class is indicated by 0, 1, and 2, with 0 being the least flexible and 2, the most flexible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Most of the residues in the ATP-binding site shared moderately and highly flexible residues with high confidence index, as shown in the Figure 5a. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>(a) Predicted flexibility score as calculated by Predyflexy server (shown in Y-axis) for residues in the protein (shown in Y-axis). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>ATP-binding site residues show good flexibility, which is shown in the zoomed image. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>First column indicates the residue number and the corresponding residue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Second column shows confidence index of prediction and the third column, indicated by values 0, 1, and 2, is indicated by degree of flexibility of the residue in the increasing order of magnitude. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>(b) the output of Q-SiteFinder, with various plausible binding sites indicated in different colors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The toggled surface marked in blue is the required binding site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The structure shown in grey is the protein structure </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPP-4-256-g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Structure reliability check using PSIPRED </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>PSIPRED, a highly accurate method for protein secondary structure prediction strategy, works by observing that most conserved regions of protein sequence are the ones which are functionally important and those that are buried in protein core, and maximum variability is assumed to be in the residues forming the surface of protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>PSIPRED results showed several stretches of residues that showed deviation from the model pre-simulation; and the change in the model, post-simulation, was predicted as being positive in nature with high confidence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The structure predicted by PSIPRED well correlated with the active site region with the helix patch-LRT showing high confidence prediction by PSIPRED. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Binding site analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Q-SiteFinder is a tool that helps us locate the energetically favorable binding sites by calculating the energy between the protein molecule and simple van der Waals probe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>This tool predicts various plausible sites where the protein can favorably bind, considering protein electrostatics and spatial proximity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The sites are displayed with information of site volume, volume of the protein, precision of prediction, and the residues involved in interaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The key residues involved in interaction were noted to be Glu94, His95, Val96, Asp97, and Asp99. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Also, the residues Lys142, Glu 144, and Asn 145 were known to play important roles by contributing to the stability of the protein-ligand complex.[2729] Q site finder predicted site no: 4, with site volume of 223Å as the desired pocket to target the ligand on. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The residues Ile12, Val20, Lys22, Ala33, Lys35, Phe93, His95, Asp99, Glu144, Asn145, Ile146, Leu147, Ala157, and Ala170 made the binding pocket, displayed in dark blue color, as shown in Figure 5b. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>There was a heavy dip in the active site volume when compared to that of observed pre-simulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>However, the key residues required for interaction in the active site remained conserved. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>KinDOCK server extracts a structural library of protein kinase-ligand complexes that provide both potential ligands and their putative binding orientation for a given protein kinase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Protein–protein structural superposition is performed, following which the ligands from the template complexes are taken as a potential ligand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>SCORE software was used as the basis of evaluating the best complexes for computing theoretical affinity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Top ten best hits were taken based on the program score, and their binding interactions with the ligand were analyzed and noted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>There was a pattern observed in the type of inhibitor designed for CDK4; the best hits were largely composed of adenine-based inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Lys22, Lys35, Phe93, Asp99, Lys142, and Glu144 were found to show good H-bonding interactions, while Ile12, Val20, Lys22, Ala33, Phe93, Glu94, His95, Glu144, Asn145, and Leu147 were shown to be key residues involved in hydrophobic interactions, as mentioned in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Purine-based analogues largely dominated as the potential analogues for CDK4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Flavopiridol, the first CDK4 inhibitor and substituted isoquinoline-1,3-(2H,4H)-diones, a recently discovered CDK4 inhibitor were among the few reliable inhibitors for CDK4 that had its structure analogous to adenine moiety containing a purine ring. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2-9"><title><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Virtual screening and docking studies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>After validating the model of the simulated protein, it was taken to be docked against a library of natural compounds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>InPACdb containing 125 natural compounds were optimized using Ligprep module of Schrodinger (Version 9.0), before it was docked with the simulated structure of CDK4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>AutoDock Vina was used through PyRX interface to perform molecular docking and virtual screening, offering partial receptor flexibility providing high performance and accuracy of results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The ATP-binding site (residues-93-102) was set as flexible and Vina search space was centered around (9.8395, 46.9036, 40.9514) and the dimensions of the grid box were set to (27.2071, 28.7208, 25.0000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The docking results comprised binding energy value given in kJ/mol, as shown in Figure 6a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Top ten ligands with respect to binding energy score were taken for analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Five of these top 10 ligands were seen to compose purine-mimicking structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The compound that emerged as the best among these natural inhibitors showed a binding energy value of -8.9 kJ/mol. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>(a) The output of AutoDock Vina. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The Lines encircled in black show the top ten ligands (X-axis) from the results in terms of binding energy value given in kJ/mol (Y-axis). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Five ligands mimicking the structure purine analogues is numbered as (ligand number, binding energy). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>(b) Interactions at the binding site between CDK4 protein and Linarin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>(c) Interactions at the binding site between CDK4 protein and Flavopiridol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>(d) Interactions at the binding site between CDK4 protein, an Isoquinolinedione. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The structure in green is the ligand molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The green dotted lines indicate H-bond interactions between the residue and ligand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The residues surrounding the ligands are the ones involved in hydrophobic interaction with it </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPP-4-256-g007"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The five purine-mimicking inhibitors were revalidated individually using AutoDock 4.0 together with Flavopiridol and substituted Isoquinolinedione. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Each of the top five natural inhibitors were docked using semi-flexible docking following Lamarckian G.A algorithm, and generated 10 favorable conformations each at the end of every docking run. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Grid box was set to dimension- 62 × 62 × 62 with coordinates of 41.734, 28.76, and 66.937. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The analysis of docking results showed protein-Linarin complex to have the best binding energy and Inhibitor constant of -8.18 kJ/mol and 1.01 μM, respectively (as tabulated), correlating with AutoDock Vina result. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The highly flexible and long side chain of Linarin contributed to its 13 rotatable bonds and high rotatable torsions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>This complex was studied for interactions in the binding pocket. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The residues Lys22, Lys35, His95, Asp99, Glu144, and Asn145 were involved in H-bonding interaction and Val9, Ile12, Phe31, Ala33, Asp97, Gln98, Arg101, Leu147, and Ala157 where shown to be involved in hydrophobic interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>A comparative study was done between Linarin, Flavopiridol, and Isoquinolinedione after docking was performed, the results of which are tabulated in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The interactions involved in the active site region between the protein and these three inhibitors are individually displayed in [Figure 6b–d]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Final list of shortlisted compounds as per AutoDock 4.0 validation </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPP-4-256-g008"/></table-wrap></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>A detailed perspective from a molecular viewpoint has been provided regarding the suitability of Linarinas, the effective inhibitor of the protein kinase, CDK4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Complying to the stringent parameters of the docking programs, a reliable binding energy of -8.9 kJ/mol was obtained on using AutoDock Vina and further validation of the result using AutoDock 4.0 gave binding energy value of -8.18 kJ/mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Inhibitory constant value was 1.01 μM, better than the values shown by Flavopiridol and substituted isoquinolinedione. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, CDK4 docking interaction with Flavopiridol, substituted isoquinolinedione and Linarin at the ATP-binding were compared, wherein, the stability of interaction was observed to be better in Linarin in comparison with its counterparts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Moreover, several potential CDK4 inhibitors were observed to be Purine-based analogues and so was Linarin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Also, acd0073 (Linarin) incidentally happened to fall under the class of Flavonoids. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Flavonoids, apart from being well known for their antioxidant activity in vitro, has long been investigated for their potential as viable anti-cancer agents.[31] Flavopiridol, the first CDK inhibitor in human beings, belonging to the family of flavonoids, was found to show activity for renal, prostate, colon, and gastric carcinomas.[3] Linarin sharing the same family characteristics was shown to have potency to serve as an inhibitor for human prostate cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Linarin has shown good sensitivity to cell cycle arrest in G1 phase.[31] The acquired results could extend its effectiveness as a reliable CDK4 inhibitor for the condition of retinoblastoma. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The authors sincerely thank SASTRA UNIVERSITY for granting access to use LigPrep module of Schrodinger. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Source of Support: Nil </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Conflict of Interest: None declared. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ref1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>1DayPJCleasbyATickleIJO’ReillyMCoyleJEHoldingFPCrystal structure of human CDK4 in complex with a D-type cyclinProc Natl Acad Sci U S A200910641667019237565 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref2"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>2IkutaMKamataKFukasawaKHonmaTMachidaTHiraiHCrystallographic approach to identification of cyclin-dependent kinase 4 (CDK4)-specific inhibitors by using CDK4 mimic CDK2 proteinJ Biol Chem2001276275485411335721 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref3"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>3SenderowiczAMFlavopiridol: The first cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor in human clinical trialsInvest New Drugs1999173132010665481 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref4"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>4IshimaruTLauJJacksonALModianoJFWeissRHpharmacological inhibition of cyclin dependent kinases causes p53 dependent apoptosis in renal cell carcinomaJ Urol20101842143920850841 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref5"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>5ShchemelininISefcLNecasEprotein kinase inhibitorsFolia Biol (Praha)2006521374817116285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref6"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>6LuXYChenYDSunNYJiangYJYouQDMolecular-docking-guided 3D-QSAR studies of substituted isoquinoline-1,3-(2 H, 4 H)-diones as cyclin-dependent kinase 4 (CDK4) inhibitorsJ Mol Model2010161637319543928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref7"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>7UmashankarVNandithaSubramaniamKalabharathIndian Plant Anticancer Compound Database (InPACdb)Bioinformation200971420198172 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref8"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>8TakakiTEchalierABrownNRHuntTEndicottJANobleMEThe structure of CDK4/cyclin D3 has implications for models of CDK activationProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20091064171619237555 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref9"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>9Last accessed on 2012 Jan 17Available from: http://www.uniprot.org/uniprot/P11802 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref10"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>10EswarNWebbBMarti-RenomMAMadhusudhanMSEramianDShenM.-yPieperUSaliAComparative Protein Structure Modeling Using MODELLERCurrent Protocols in Protein Science2007502.9.12.9.31 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref11"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>11VriendGWHAT IF: A molecular modeling and drug design programJ Mol Graph199085262268628 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref12"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>12XuDZhangYImproving the physical realism and structural accuracy of protein models by a two-step atomic-level energy minimizationBiophys J201110125253422098752 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref13"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>13LaskowskiRAMossDSThorntonJMMain-chain bond lengths and bond angles in protein structuresJ Mol Biol19932311049678515464 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref14"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>14HessBKutznerCvan der SpoelDLindahlEGROMACS4: Algorithms for highly efficient, Load-Balanced, and scalable Molecular SimulationJ Chem Theory Comp2008443547 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref15"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>15MascarenhasNMBhattacharyyaDGhoshalNWhy pyridine containing pyrido[2,3-d] pyrimidin-7-ones selectively inhibit CDK4 than CDK2: Insights from molecular dynamics simulationJ Mol Graph Model20102869570620153225 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref16"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>16JoSKimTIyerVGImWCHARMM-GUI: A web-based graphical user interface for CHARMMJ ComputChem200829185965 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref17"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>17ShazmanSCelnikerGHaberOGlaserFMandel-GutfreundYPatch Finder Plus (PFplus): A web server for extracting and displaying positive electrostatic patches on protein surfacesNucleic Acids Res200735W5263017537808 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref18"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>18WallnerBElofssonACan correct protein models be identified?Protein Sci20031210738612717029 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref19"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>19WiedersteinMSipplMJPro SA-web: Interactive web service for the recognition of errors in three-dimensional structures of proteinsNucleic Acids Res200735W4071017517781 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref20"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>20SipplMJRecognition of errors in three-dimensional structures of proteinsProteins199317355628108378 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref21"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>21BornotAEtchebestCde BrevernAGPredicting protein flexibility through the prediction of local structuresProteins2011798395221287616 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref22"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>22McGuffinLJBrysonKJonesDTThe PSIPRED protein structure prediction serverBioinformatics200016404510869041 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref23"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>23LaurieATJacksonRMQ-SiteFinder: An energy-based method for the prediction of protein-ligand binding sitesBioinformatics20052119081615701681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref24"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>24MartinLCatherinotVLabesseGKinDOCK: A tool for comparative docking of protein kinase ligandsNucleic Acids Res200634W325916845019 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref25"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>25Lig Prep, version 2.52011New York, NYSchrodinger, LLC </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref26"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>26TrottOOlsonAJAuto Dock Vina: Improving the speed and accuracy of docking with a new scoring function, efficient optimization, and multithreadingJ ComputChem20103145561 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref27"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>27VeselýJHavlicekLStrnadMBlowJJDonella-DeanaAPinnaLInhibition of cyclin-dependent kinases by purine analoguesEur J Biochem1994224771867925396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref28"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>28CarlsonBADubayMMSausvilleEABrizuelaLWorlandPJFlavopiridol induces G1 arrest with inhibition of cyclin-dependent kinase (CDK) 2 and CDK4 in human breast carcinoma cellsCancer Res199656297388674031 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref29"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>29HueyRMorrisGMOlsonAJGoodsellDSA semiempirical free energy force field with charge-based desolvationJ Comput Chem20072811455217274016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref30"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>30Accelrys Software Inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Discovery Studio Modeling Environment, Release 3.12011San DiegoAccelrys Software Inc </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref31"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>31SinghRPAgrawalPYimDAgarwalCAgarwalRAcacetin inhibits cell growth and cell cycle progression, and induces apoptosis in human prostate cancer cells: Structure-activity relationship with linarin and linarin acetateCarcinogenesis2005268455415637089 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
