<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biol Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biol Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">biolopen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bio</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Biology Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2046-6390</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Company of Biologists</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Bidder Building, 140 Cowley Road, Cambridge, CB4 0DL, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3683164</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23789112</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">BIO20134242</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/bio.20134242</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Induced pluripotent stem cells derived from rabbits exhibit some characteristics of na&#x000ef;ve pluripotency</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Osteil</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tapponnier</surname><given-names>Yann</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Markossian</surname><given-names>Suzy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Godet</surname><given-names>Murielle</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schmaltz-Panneau</surname><given-names>Barbara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jouneau</surname><given-names>Luc</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cabau</surname><given-names>C&#x000e9;dric</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Joly</surname><given-names>Thierry</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Blach&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>Thierry</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000f3;cza</surname><given-names>Elen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bernat</surname><given-names>Agnieszka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yerle</surname><given-names>Martine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Acloque</surname><given-names>Herv&#x000e9;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hidot</surname><given-names>Sullivan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bosze</surname><given-names>Zsuzsanna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Duranthon</surname><given-names>V&#x000e9;ronique</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Savatier</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Afanassieff</surname><given-names>Marielle</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>INSERM, U846, Stem Cell and Brain Institute</institution>, <addr-line>18 Avenue du Doyen Jean L&#x000e9;pine, F-69500 Bron</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Stem Cell and Brain Institute</institution>, <addr-line>F-69500 Bron</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Universit&#x000e9; de Lyon</institution>, <addr-line>F-69100 Villeurbanne</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>INRA, USC1361, F-69500 Bron</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution>INRA, Biology of Development and Reproduction</institution>, <addr-line>F-78352 Jouy-en-Josas</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution>INRA, SIGENAE, UR83 Recherches Avicoles</institution>, <addr-line>F-37380 Nouzilly</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><institution>ISARA-Lyon</institution>, <addr-line>F-69007 Lyon</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff8"><label>8</label><institution>VetAgroSup, UPSP ICE</institution>, <addr-line>F-69280 Marcy l'Etoile</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff9"><label>9</label><institution>Institute of Animal Biotechnology, Agricultural Biotechnology Center</institution>, <addr-line>H-2100 Godollo</addr-line>, <country>Hungary</country></aff><aff id="aff10"><label>10</label><institution>INRA, UMR444</institution>, <addr-line>F-31326 Castanet Tolosan</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff11"><label>&#x02021;</label><addr-line>Present address: Laboratory of Molecular Diagnostics, Intercollegiate Faculty of Biotechnology, Medical University of Gdansk, Poland</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn id="fn1" fn-type="equal"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x000a7;</label>Authors for correspondence (<email>marielle.afanassieff@inserm.fr</email>; <email>pierre.savatier@inserm.fr</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2013. The Company of Biologists Ltd</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><title>Summary</title><p>Not much is known about the molecular and functional features of pluripotent stem cells (PSCs) in rabbits. To address this, we derived and characterized 2 types of rabbit PSCs from the same breed of New Zealand White rabbits: 4 lines of embryonic stem cells (rbESCs), and 3 lines of induced PSCs (rbiPSCs) that were obtained by reprogramming adult skin fibroblasts. All cell lines required fibroblast growth factor 2 for their growth and proliferation. All rbESC lines showed molecular and functional properties typically associated with primed pluripotency. The cell cycle of rbESCs had a prolonged G1 phase and a DNA damage checkpoint before entry into the S phase, which are the 2 features typically associated with the somatic cell cycle. In contrast, the rbiPSC lines exhibited some characteristics of na&#x000ef;ve pluripotency, including resistance to single-cell dissociation by trypsin, robust activity of the distal enhancer of the mouse <italic>Oct4</italic> gene, and expression of na&#x000ef;ve pluripotency-specific genes, as defined in rodents. According to gene expression profiles, rbiPSCs were closer to the rabbit inner cell mass (ICM) than rbESCs. Furthermore, rbiPSCs were capable of colonizing the ICM after aggregation with morulas. Therefore, we propose that rbiPSCs self-renew in an intermediate state between na&#x000ef;ve and primed pluripotency, which represents a key step toward the generation of <italic>bona fide</italic> na&#x000ef;ve PSC lines in rabbits.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Rabbit model</kwd><kwd>Embryonic stem cell</kwd><kwd>Induced pluripotent stem cell</kwd><kwd>Pluripotency</kwd><kwd>Cell cycle</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Pluripotent stem cells (PSCs) can exist in two morphologically, molecularly and functionally distinct pluripotent states, designated as the na&#x000ef;ve and primed states (<xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">Nichols and Smith, 2009</xref>). The first rabbit pluripotent stem cell (PSC) lines were produced from New Zealand White rabbit blastocysts in the form of embryonic stem cells [rabbit ESCs (rbESCs)] (<xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">Fang et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="b37" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2007</xref>). In their undifferentiated state, rbESCs required both fibroblast growth factor 2 (FGF2) and growth factors of the transforming growth factor (TGF) &#x003b2; family (activin, nodal) for self-renewal (<xref rid="b38" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2008</xref>). These results were confirmed in another study, which showed that activin/nodal signaling through Smad2/3 activation was necessary for maintaining the pluripotent status of rbESCs (<xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">Honda et al., 2009</xref>). These rbESCs did not colonize rabbit embryos after being injected into blastocysts (<xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">Honda et al., 2008</xref>). Honda et al. also established rabbit induced PSC lines [rabbit iPSCs (rbiPSCs)] from adult liver and stomach cells (<xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">Honda et al., 2010</xref>). Similar to rbESCs, rbiPSCs are dependent on FGF2 for self-renewal. Therefore, rbESCs and rbiPSCs seemed to exhibit the cardinal feature of primed pluripotency. However, this conclusion should be moderated because none of these studies evaluated these cell lines for other criteria that demarcate na&#x000ef;ve and primed pluripotency; moreover, these studies did not compared these cell lines with rabbit inner cell mass (ICM) cells and PSCs from other species. Therefore, the status of rbESCs and rbiPSCs is yet to be thoroughly evaluated. In our study, we compared rbESCs and rbiPSCs at both molecular and functional levels and concluded that (<italic>i</italic>) rbESCs do not exhibit all the characteristic features of pluripotency and (<italic>ii</italic>) rbiPSCs exhibit some characteristic features of na&#x000ef;ve pluripotency.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Derivation of FGF2-dependent rbESC lines</title><p>Twenty-four ICMs isolated from 52 blastocysts by immunosurgery were plated on feeder cells in rbESC medium supplemented with FGF2. Twelve of these ICMs could form outgrowths, of which 4 produced a population of highly proliferating cells that could be routinely passaged more than 40 times. These rbESC lines &#x02013; designated rbES-4, rbES-8, rbES-18 and rbES-19 &#x02013; formed flattened colonies of compact cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig.&#x02005;1A</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Fig. S1A</ext-link>). They were passaged every 3 days after collagenase II treatment of the colonies, followed by gentle dissociation into small clumps. All attempts to passage these cell lines after trypsinization into single-cell suspensions resulted in extensive differentiation and apoptosis (data not shown). All the 4 lines were positive for alkaline phosphatase activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig.&#x02005;1B</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Fig. S1A</ext-link>) and were strictly dependent on FGF2 for self-renewal, as determined by their altered morphology after FGF2 withdrawal for 24&#x02005;h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig.&#x02005;1C</xref>). Conventional Giemsa staining showed a normal chromosome number in all the selected lines (&#x0003e;50 metaphase spreads analyzed: 42XY) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig.&#x02005;1D</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Fig. S1A</ext-link>). For rbES-18 line, the cells were karyotyped using G-banding, and normal chromosome complements were observed in the 4 analyzed metaphase spreads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig.&#x02005;1E</xref>). Immunolabeling showed that all the 4 lines expressed <italic>Oct4</italic> in virtually every cell in the respective populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig.&#x02005;1F</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Fig. S3</ext-link>). All the 4 cell lines could undergo <italic>in vitro</italic> differentiation into embryoid bodies (EBs) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig.&#x02005;1H</xref>). Differentiation was accompanied by the rapid loss of <italic>Nanog</italic> and <italic>Oct4</italic> expression and upregulation of the ectodermal marker <italic>Nestin</italic> and endodermal marker <italic>Hnf3&#x003b2;</italic>. The mesodermal marker <italic>Flk1</italic> was expressed at robust levels in undifferentiated cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig.&#x02005;1G</xref>). All the 4 rbESC lines could induce teratomas after being injected under the kidney capsules in SCID mice. All teratomas contained derivatives of the 3 embryonic germ layers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig.&#x02005;1I,J</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Fig. S2A</ext-link>). Therefore, these 4 rbESC lines appeared to exhibit the characteristics of PSCs.</p><fig id="f01" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Isolation and characterization of rbESC lines.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Phase-contrast image of rbES-18 cells at passage 28 (P28). (<bold>B</bold>) Alkaline phosphatase activity in rbES-18 cells. (<bold>C</bold>) Phase-contrast images of rbES-18 cells before and after FGF2 withdrawal for 24&#x02005;h. (<bold>D</bold>) Histogram showing the distribution of chromosome numbers in rbES-4 at P13, rbES-8 at P17, rbES-18 at P15, and rbES-19 at P21. (<bold>E</bold>) G-banding karyotype of the rbES-18 line at P15. (<bold>F</bold>) Immunolabeling of rabbit Oct4. (<bold>G</bold>) RT-PCR analysis of pluripotency (<italic>Nanog</italic> and <italic>Oct4</italic>) and germ layer-specific (<italic>Hnf3&#x003b2;</italic>, <italic>Flk1</italic> and <italic>Nestin</italic>) gene expression during differentiation of rbES-18 cells induced by EB formation (days 0&#x02013;10). (<bold>H</bold>) EB produced from rbES-18 cells. (<bold>I</bold>) Teratoma 31 days after injecting rbES-18 cells under the kidney capsule of SCID mice. (<bold>J</bold>) Histological section of the teratoma with tissue components of all 3 embryonic germ cell layers. Oil red O staining to detect adipocytes. Desmin and GFAP to detect muscle and glial cells, respectively. Gland structures could be identified after HPS staining. Scale bars: 50&#x02005;&#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bio-02-06-613-f01"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Generation of iPSC lines from adult rabbit fibroblasts</title><p>Adult rabbit fibroblasts (rbF) were infected twice at a 48-h interval with a mixture of 4 retroviral vectors that expressed human Oct4, Sox2, Klf4 and c-Myc transcription factors. Three days after the second infection, the rbFs were dissociated and replated on feeder cells in an rbESC medium supplemented with 10&#x02005;ng/ml FGF2. The culture medium was changed every day thereafter until some colonies with compact morphologies appeared (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Fig.&#x02005;2A</xref>). One hundred and eleven clones were selected between the 15<sup>th</sup> and 29<sup>th</sup> day after fibroblast infection. These 111 clones were passaged by trypsin dissociation into single-cell suspensions. Twelve clones expressing alkaline phosphatase and capable of rapid proliferation were selected for further studies. At passage 6, 4 of these clones expressed rabbit <italic>Nanog</italic> and <italic>Oct4</italic> at the same level as that in rbESCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Fig.&#x02005;2B</xref>). For 3 clones &#x02013; designated rbiPS-B19, rbiPS-B24 and rbiPS-B29 &#x02013; silencing of all the 4 transgenes was achieved at passage 25 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Fig.&#x02005;2C</xref>). Line rbiPS-B25 did not show suppressed <italic>hc-MYC</italic> transgene expression even after 25 passages and was excluded from all subsequent analysis. Withdrawal of FGF2 induced dramatic morphological changes within 48&#x02005;h, suggesting differentiation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Fig.&#x02005;2D</xref>). A normal chromosome number was observed in 2 lines &#x02013; rbiPS-B19 and rbiPS-B29 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Fig.&#x02005;2E</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Fig. S1B</ext-link>). For the rbiPS-B19 cell line, cells were karyotyped using G-banding, and normal chromosome complements were observed in the 20 analyzed metaphase spreads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Fig.&#x02005;2F</xref>). The rbiPS-B24 cell line showed an abnormal 43XX karyotype. Immunolabelling showed that all the 3 cell lines expressed <italic>Oct4</italic> in virtually every cell in the respective populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Fig.&#x02005;2G</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Fig. S3</ext-link>). Differentiation induced by suspension culture resulted in the rapid loss of <italic>Oct4</italic> and <italic>Nanog</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Fig.&#x02005;2H</xref>). <italic>HNF3&#x003b2;</italic>, <italic>Flk1</italic> and <italic>Nestin</italic> were already expressed at robust levels in undifferentiated rbiPS-B19 cells. All the 3 lines induced teratomas containing cells that had differentiated into the 3 germ layers after being injected into SCID mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Fig.&#x02005;2I</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Fig. S2B</ext-link>). Most importantly, all iPSC lines could be routinely passaged every 2 days by trypsin dissociation into single-cell suspensions.</p><fig id="f02" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Generation and characterization of rbiPSC lines.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Phase-contrast images of rbFs before (<bold>a</bold>) and after (<bold>b&#x02013;e</bold>) infection with retroviral vectors expressing human transgenes; (b,c) primary colonies (P0) observed after 20 days of infection; (d) colonies observed at P6; (e) alkaline phosphatase activity at P6. (<bold>B</bold>) Expression of rabbit pluripotent genes <italic>Oct4</italic> and <italic>Nanog</italic> analyzed by RT-PCR in 12 independent rbiPSC clones at P6. (<bold>C</bold>) Expression of human transgenes analyzed by RT-PCR in 6 independent rbiPSC clones at P6 and P25. (<bold>D</bold>) Phase-contrast images of rbiPS-B19 cells before and after FGF2 withdrawal for 48&#x02005;h. (<bold>E</bold>) Histogram showing the distribution of chromosome numbers in rbiPS-B19 at P37, rbiPS-B24 at P33, and rbiPS-B29 at P31. (<bold>F</bold>) G-banding karyotype of rbiPS-B19 line at P37. (<bold>G</bold>) Immunolabeling of rabbit Oct4. (<bold>H</bold>) RT-PCR analysis of pluripotency (<italic>Nanog</italic> and <italic>Oct4</italic>) and germ layer-specific (<italic>Hnf3&#x003b2;</italic>, <italic>Flk1</italic>, and <italic>Nestin</italic>) gene expression during differentiation of rbiPS-B19 cells induced by EB formation (days 0&#x02013;14). (<bold>I</bold>) Teratoma at 30 days after injecting rbiPS-B19 cells under the kidney capsule of SCID mice, with tissue components of all the 3 embryonic germ cell layers. Histological section stained with HPS shows squamous epithelial cells. Oil red O staining to detect adipocytes. Desmin, GFAP, and glucagon to detect muscle, glial, and pancreatic &#x003b1;-cells, respectively. Scale bars: 50&#x02005;&#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bio-02-06-613-f02"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Contrasting expression patterns of stage-specific embryonic antigen (SSEAs) and cadherins</title><p>The patterns of stage-specific embryonic antigen (SSEA) expression differed between cell types, and all showed considerable heterogeneity. All the 3 rbiPSC lines showed heterogeneous expression of SSEA1, SSEA4, and TRA-1-60, whereas all the 4 rbESC lines expressed only SSEA1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Fig. S3</ext-link>). Distribution of SSEA1 and SSEA4 expression in various cell populations was quantified using flow cytometry (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Fig.&#x02005;3A</xref>). SSEA1 was expressed in 30&#x02013;60% rbESCs and rbiPSCs, compared with 94% mESCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Fig.&#x02005;3B</xref>). SSEA4 was expressed in 10&#x02013;40% rbiPSCs and the pattern was complex with these lines, which comprised 4 cell subpopulations: SSEA1<sup>+</sup> (32&#x02013;49%), SSEA4<sup>+</sup> (5&#x02013;12%), double-positive (7&#x02013;26%), and double-negative (29&#x02013;37%) cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Fig.&#x02005;3C</xref>). The distributions between these 4 sub-populations differed between lines and were constant over time in culture (data not shown). We determined whether these 4 populations represented 4 distinct cell types or whether they were capable of converting into each other in culture. To address this each subpopulation was sorted by FACS and subsequently cultured for 1 week (secondary cultures) before analysis by flow cytometry. The heterogeneity originally observed in the unsorted cell population was restored from each subpopulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Fig.&#x02005;3C</xref>). These results indicate that rbiPSCs existed in 4 interchangeable states (SSEA1<sup>+</sup>/SSEA4<sup>+</sup>, SSEA1<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/SSEA4<sup>+</sup>, SSEA1<sup>+</sup>/SSEA4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, and SSEA1<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/SSEA4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>), and that the distribution of the 4 populations was cell line specific.</p><fig id="f03" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>Expression of SSEA antigens and cadherins.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Flow cytometry analysis of SSEA1 and SSEA4 marker expressions. (<bold>B</bold>) Histograms showing the percentages of SSEA1<sup>+</sup> and SSEA4<sup>+</sup> cells in various rbESC and rbiPSC lines. (<bold>C</bold>) Flow cytometry analysis of SSEA1 and SSEA4 marker expression in rbiPSC lines before and after FACS sorting of SSEA subpopulations. Upper panels: Dot plots of SSEA1- and SSEA4-associated fluorescence in rbiPS-B19, rbiPS-B24, and rbiPS-B29 lines before cell sorting. Bottom panels: Histograms showing the percentages of SSEA1<sup>+</sup>/SSEA4<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (1<sup>+</sup>/4<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells), SSEA1<sup>+</sup>/SSEA4<sup>+</sup>(1<sup>+</sup>/4<sup>+</sup> cells), SSEA1<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/SSEA4<sup>+</sup>(1<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/4<sup>+</sup> cells), and SSEA1<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/SSEA4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>(1<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/4<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells) populations; these cell populations were derived from cultures of rbiPS lines after sorting each cell population, replating in FGF2-supplemented medium, and subsequent culture for 7 days. (<bold>D</bold>) Immunolabeling with antibodies for E- and N-cadherins. (<bold>E</bold>) Histograms showing mRNA levels (&#x00394;Ct) of the E-cadherin (<italic>Cdh1</italic>) and N-cadherin (<italic>Cdh2</italic>) as analyzed by qPCR for the entire cell population (total) and in various SSEA subpopulations, as indicated. mRNA levels were normalized to the mRNA level of <italic>Tbp</italic>. Scale bars: 50&#x02005;&#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bio-02-06-613-f03"/></fig><p>E-cadherin expression is observed in all PSCs regardless of species, whereas N-cadherin is expressed only in mouse Epiblast Stem Cells (EpiSCs) (<xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">Tesar et al., 2007</xref>). rbESC and rbiPSC lines had different patterns of E- and N-cadherin expression. Immunolabeling showed that all rbESC lines expressed both E- and N-cadherins similar to rhesus ESCs. In contrast, rbiPSC lines expressed only E-cadherin similar to mouse ESCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Fig.&#x02005;3D</xref>). Each SSEA subpopulation was sorted by FACS, and the expression of E-and N-cadherins was analyzed by qPCR. All subpopulations of rbiPSCs expressed <italic>Cdh1</italic> (E-cadherin) at levels 10- to 100-fold higher than those measured in rbESCs. In contrast, the same subpopulations expressed <italic>Cdh2</italic> (N-cadherin) at levels 10- to 100-fold lower than those measured in rbESCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Fig.&#x02005;3E</xref>). Therefore, differential expression of E- and N-cadherins was associated with the ESC <italic>vs</italic> iPSC status and not with the cell population heterogeneity observed as the SSEA expression.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Cell cycle characteristics demarcate the SSEA1<sup>+</sup> rbiPS cells</title><p>PSCs show an unusual cell cycle structure that is characterized by a short G1 phase and a high proportion of cells in the S phase. In addition, they do not undergo cell-cycle arrest at the G1 checkpoint in response to DNA damage. Instead, they undergo growth arrest only at the G2 checkpoint (<xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">Aladjem et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">Fluckiger et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">Filipczyk et al., 2007</xref>). Therefore, we investigated whether rabbit PSCs displayed the same cell cycle characteristics. For the 4 rbESC lines, the G1, S, and G2/M phases were observed in 74&#x000b1;2.7%, 20&#x000b1;2.8%, and 6&#x000b1;2.9% cell populations, respectively. For the 3 rbiPSC lines, the G1, S, and G2/M phases were observed in 43&#x000b1;2.4%, 38&#x000b1;3.5%, and 19&#x000b1;1.9% cell populations, respectively (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Table S3</ext-link>). Thus, the percentage of rbPSCs in the S phase (20&#x02013;38%) was higher than that in rbFs (7%) but lower than that in mESCs (68%), mEpiSCs (56%), and rhESCs (41%). The cell cycle distributions of the SSEA1<sup>+</sup> and SSEA4<sup>+</sup> subpopulations were also analyzed. Of all the analyzed cell lines, the SSEA1<sup>+</sup> subpopulations showed the lowest G1 and the highest S fractions than the SSEA1<sup>&#x02212;</sup> and SSEA4<sup>+</sup> subpopulations. However, no SSEA1<sup>+</sup> subpopulation from any line analyzed showed a cell cycle distribution similar to that observed for SSEA1<sup>+</sup> mESCs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Table S3</ext-link>).</p><p>To study the cell cycle response of rbPSCs to DNA damage, we analyzed the effects of doxorubicin, a DNA intercalator that induces double-strand breaks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Fig.&#x02005;4</xref>). The G1 fraction of rbFs treated with doxorubicin for 24&#x02005;h decreased from 80% to 41%, whereas the G2 fraction increased from 12% to 58%, indicating growth arrest in G1 and G2. In contrast, the G1 fraction of doxorubicin-treated mESCs decreased dramatically from 20% to 1%, whereas its G2 fraction increased from 11% to 99%, indicating a lack of G1 checkpoint in mouse PSCs and accumulation of cells at the G2 checkpoint. Similar results were obtained with rhESCs and mEpiSCs for which the G1 and S fractions virtually disappeared after doxorubicin treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Fig.&#x02005;4A</xref>). The response of rbPSCs to doxorubicin treatment was more heterogeneous. They all showed moderate decreases in their G1 fractions (rbESCs, from 74% to 70%; rbiPSCs, from 43% to 20%) and significant increase in their G2 fractions (rbESCs, from 6% to 30%; rbiPSCs, from 19% to 80%). We assumed that this might be a reflection of the heterogeneity of rbPSC populations. Therefore, we analyzed the responses of different SSEA fractions to doxorubicin treatment. Only SSEA1<sup>+</sup>/SSEA4<sup>&#x02212;</sup> and SSEA1<sup>+</sup>/SSEA4<sup>+</sup> subpopulations of rbiPSCs showed complete growth arrest in the G2 phase and did not show cell accumulation in the G1 phase; similar results were observed for mESCs, mEpiSCs, and rhESCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Fig.&#x02005;4A,B</xref>). All other fractions showed variable accumulation of cells in the G1 and G2 phases, as observed previously in the entire population. Of note, the SSEA1<sup>+</sup> subpopulation of rbESCs still showed accumulation in the G1 and G2 phases after doxorubicin treatment. Thus, these results indicate that only the SSEA1<sup>+</sup> subpopulation of rbiPSCs showed the cell cycle features of mESCs, mEpiSCs, and rhESCs (i.e. a shortened G1 phase, a high proportion of cells in the S phase, and absence of DNA damage checkpoint in G1). Neither the SSEA1<sup>+</sup> subpopulation of rbESCs nor the other subpopulations of rbiPSCs showed the cell cycle features of PSCs.</p><fig id="f04" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><title>Cell cycle analysis of rabbit PSCs.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Cell cycle profiles of rbFs, EpiSCs, mESCs, rhESCs, rbES-4, and rbiPS-B19 assessed using flow cytometry after staining with propidium iodide. Cell cycle distributions are shown for the total cell population and different SSEA subpopulations. + DOXO indicates treatment with 50&#x02005;ng/ml doxorubicin for 24&#x02005;h. (<bold>B</bold>) Histograms showing the percentage of cells in the G1, S, and G2/M phases of the cell cycle before and after doxorubicin treatment for different SSEA subpopulations. The percentages were calculated using ModFitLT.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bio-02-06-613-f04"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Mouse <italic>Oct4</italic> promoter activity and DNA methylation demarcates rbESC and rbiPSC lines</title><p>The distal element (DE) of <italic>Oct4</italic> enhancer showed robust activity in ICM cells of mouse blastocyst, primordial germ cells, and mESCs. In contrast, it is minimally active in the epiblast of mouse postimplantation embryo and its EpiSC derivatives (<xref rid="b42" ref-type="bibr">Yeom et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">Tesar et al., 2007</xref>). Thus, DE activity can be used to discriminate between the na&#x000ef;ve and primed states of pluripotency (<xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">Nichols and Smith, 2009</xref>). To evaluate the DE activity in rabbit preimplantation embryos, we used the L-SIN-EOS-C(3)-EiP lentiviral vector (designated EOS) that expressed GFP and the puromycin resistance gene under the transcriptional control of the minimal early transposon promoter and trimer of the CR4 enhancer (<xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">Hotta et al., 2009</xref>). The CR4 enhancer is a 146-bp fragment of the mouse DE element that recruits the Oct4, Sox2, and Sp1 transcription factors and recapitulates the regulation of the DE element in pluripotent and differentiated cell lines (<xref rid="b28" ref-type="bibr">Okumura-Nakanishi et al., 2005</xref>). A vector expressing GFP from the ubiquitous CAG promoter [GAE-CAG-eGFP/wpre, (<xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">Mangeot et al., 2002</xref>)] &#x02013; designated GAE &#x02013; was used as a control. Both lentiviral vectors were concentrated and injected under the zona pellucida of 8-cell-stage rabbit embryos. The embryos were then cultured to the mid-blastocyst stage before analysis with confocal microscopy. Fluorescent cells were observed in the trophoblast and ICM, with both control and EOS lentivectors, indicating the activity of the trimer of the CR4 enhancer in rabbit preimplantation embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Fig.&#x02005;5A,B</xref>). DE activity in the trophoblast cells was consistent with previous observations, indicating that <italic>Oct4</italic> was expressed in the trophoblast of the rabbit blastocyst (<xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">Kobolak et al., 2009</xref>).</p><fig id="f05" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><title>Activity and methylation of mouse <italic>Oct4</italic> promoter in rabbit PSCs.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) GFP immunolabeling of rabbit mid-stage blastocysts after injecting GAE and EOS lentivectors under the zona pellucida of 8-cell-stage embryos. (<bold>B</bold>) Serial confocal images of a blastocyst expressing EOS lentivector after GFP immunolabeling and costaining with propidium iodide. (<bold>C</bold>) Flow cytometry analysis of rbES-4, rbiPS-B19, mESCs, mEpiSCs, and rhESCs 4 days after infection with GAE and EOS lentivectors. For each dot plot, the numbers in green indicate the percentages of all GFP<sup>+</sup> cells. Numbers in red indicate the percentages of GFP<sup>+</sup> cells that had a fluorescence level of &#x02265;10<sup>3</sup> and which were normalized to the percentage of all GFP<sup>+</sup> cells. (<bold>D</bold>) Histogram showing the results for GFP expression index: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="bio-02-06-613-e02.jpg"/></inline-formula>. (<bold>E</bold>) Flow cytometry analysis of mESC-EOS, rbiPS-B19-EOS, rbiPS-B24-EOS, and rbiPS-B29-EOS before (&#x02212; Puro) and after (+ Puro) selection with puromycin for 14 days. (<bold>F</bold>) Histogram showing the percentages of methylated CpG dinucleotides evaluated after bisulfite genomic sequencing of the <italic>Oct4</italic> promoter regions (CR1 and CR4) in all rabbit PSC lines and REFs. (<bold>G</bold>) Histogram comparing the percentages of methylated CpG dinucleotides between rbESCs and rbiPSCs in CR1 or CR4 region. Statistical analyses were conducted using analysis of variance followed by Fisher's test. Differences were considered significant for <italic>P&#x0003c;</italic>0.01. Scale bars: 50&#x02005;&#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bio-02-06-613-f05"/></fig><p>To evaluate the DE activity in rabbit PSCs, rbESC, and rbiPSC lines were infected with EOS and GAE lentivectors and analyzed using flow cytometry after 4 days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Fig.&#x02005;5C</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Fig. S4A</ext-link>). All cell lines infected with GAE showed green fluorescence ranging from 12% to 54% of positive cells according to the cell type (threshold set at 2.5&#x000d7;10<sup>2</sup>). Approximately 60&#x02013;95% of these GFP-positive cells showed fluorescence levels of &#x02265;10<sup>3</sup>. In contrast, fluorescence levels in EOS-infected cells varied dramatically between cell types. mESCs had the highest level (76% GFP-positive cells had fluorescence levels of &#x0003e;10<sup>3</sup>). mEpiSCs showed no expression while rhESCs showed low expression (only 13% GFP-positive cells had fluorescence levels of &#x0003e;10<sup>3</sup>). This indicates that rbESCs and iPSCs showed intermediate expression levels (rbES-4, 32%; rbES-8, 33%; rbES-19, 30%; rbiPS-B19, 42%; rbiPS-B24, 41%; and rbiPS-B29, 48%; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Fig.&#x02005;5C</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Fig. S4A</ext-link>). This suggested that the trimer of the CR4 enhancer was more active in rbPSCs than in mouse EpiSCs and primate ESCs.</p><p>The GFP expression level in EOS-infected cells was influenced by the infection rate. Therefore, to eliminate the confounding effect of the variations in infection rates between the cell lines, we calculated an expression index (I<sub>E</sub>): <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="bio-02-06-613-e01.jpg"/></inline-formula>. %GFP<sup>+</sup>&#x02265;10<sup>3</sup> is the percentage of GFP<sup>+</sup> cells with expression levels of &#x02265;10<sup>3</sup>; %GFP<sup>+</sup><sub>T</sub> is the percentage of all GFP<sup>+</sup> cells; and I<sub>R</sub> is the percentage of infected cells. Comparison of I<sub>E</sub> values between cell lines showed that mESCs had the highest index, whereas rhESCs and EpiSCs had the lowest index. As determined from previous calculations, I<sub>E</sub> of all rabbit lines was between that of mESCs and rhESCs, with all the 3 iPSCs lines showing higher I<sub>E</sub> indices than the 3 ESC lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Fig.&#x02005;5D</xref>). From these experiments, we concluded that compared with rbESCs, rbiPSC lines could activate the <italic>mOct4</italic> DE element at a higher level.</p><p>This conclusion was strongly reinforced by the results of puromycin selection of EOS-infected cells. All ESC and iPSC lines infected with EOS were cultured for 7 days in a medium supplemented with puromycin. Puromycin-resistant cells could be readily selected and expanded from mESCs and the 3 rbiPSC lines (designated rbiPS-B19-EOS, rbiPS-B24-EOS, and rbiPS-B29-EOS) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Fig.&#x02005;5E</xref>). In contrast, no puromycin-resistant cells could be isolated from any of the rbESC lines infected with the EOS lentivector. Therefore, we concluded that only iPSCs could activate the trimer of the CR4 enhancer at a level sufficient to confer resistance to puromycin. This conclusion was supported by the observation that the mean intensity of GFP fluorescence increased during puromycin selection of iPSCs infected with EOS, suggesting that only some rare cells expressing GFP at high levels were resistant to puromycin and expanded during selection. These puromycin-resistant cells had notably higher percentages of SSEA1<sup>+</sup> and SSEA4<sup>+</sup> cells than the original cells (i.e. before puromycin selection) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Fig. S4B</ext-link>).</p><p>Regions CR1 and CR4 were chosen for the methylation study. Bisulfite genomic sequencing showed that both regions were 3&#x02013;10 times more methylated in rabbit embryonic fibroblasts (REFs) than in rabbit PSCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Fig.&#x02005;5F</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Fig. S5</ext-link>). Regions CR1 and CR4 were less methylated in rbiPSCs than in rbESCs [CR1: 3.1% methylated CpG dinucleotides in rbiPSCs <italic>vs</italic> 8.6% in rbESCs (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01); CR4: 2.3% methylated CpG dinucleotides in rbiPSCs <italic>vs</italic> 7.6% in rbESCs (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001)] (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Fig.&#x02005;5G</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Fig. S5</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Gene expression profiling demarcates rbESC and rbiPSC lines</title><p>To further define the molecular properties of rbESCs and rbiPSCs, we purified the SSEA1<sup>+</sup>/SSEA4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, SSEA1<sup>+</sup>/SSEA4<sup>+</sup>, and SSEA1<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/SSEA4<sup>&#x02212;</sup> subpopulations by FACS sorting in 4 rbESC lines and 2 rbiPSC lines and performed a global analysis of their expression profiles. For this, we used a rabbit-specific gene expression microarray containing approximately 13,000 independent genes. For each cell line (rbES-4, rbES-8, rbES-18, and rbES-19; rbiPS-B19 and rbiPS-B29) and SSEA subpopulations, 3 biological replicates were hybridized to the customized rabbit array. Hierarchical clustering of the normalized data showed that all subpopulations of rbESC lines were clustered on one side and all subpopulations of rbiPSC lines were clustered together on the other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Fig.&#x02005;6A</xref>). This indicates that despite the heterogeneity observed in the cell lines, the variability is mainly associated with the cell status (rbESC <italic>vs</italic> rbiPSC) and not with the SSEA expression status.</p><fig id="f06" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><title>Gene expression analysis for rbESCs and rbiPSCs.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Hierarchical clustering of transcriptome data (mean values/cell category) using Pearson correlation coefficient as a measure of distance between samples. (<bold>B</bold>) Correlation clustering for SSEA subpopulations of rbESCs and rbiPSCs (S1<sup>+</sup>: SSEA1<sup>+</sup>/SSEA4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>; S4<sup>+</sup>: SSEA1<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/SSEA4<sup>+</sup>; S1/S4<sup>+</sup>: SSEA1<sup>+</sup>/SSEA4<sup>+</sup>; NEG: SSEA1<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/SSEA4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>; TOT: total population) based on the RNA levels of the 22 genes (<italic>Blimp1</italic>, <italic>Cdx2</italic>, <italic>Cdh1</italic>, <italic>Cdh2</italic>, <italic>Cldn6</italic>, <italic>Dax1</italic>, <italic>Dazl</italic>, <italic>Essrb</italic>, <italic>Fbxo15</italic>, <italic>Fgf4</italic>, <italic>Gbx2</italic>, <italic>Klf4</italic>, <italic>Lefty2</italic>, <italic>Nanog</italic>, <italic>Oct4</italic>, <italic>Otx2</italic>, <italic>Pecam1</italic>, <italic>Pitx2</italic>, <italic>Piwil2</italic>, <italic>Rex1</italic>, <italic>Tbx3</italic>, and <italic>Tcfcp2l1</italic>) measured by qPCR. mRNA levels were measured in 3 biological replicates and 3 technical repeats, and normalized to <italic>Tbp</italic> expression levels. (<bold>C</bold>) Graphical representation of the first principal component of PCA for SSEA1<sup>+</sup>(S1<sup>+</sup>) and SSEA1<sup>+</sup>/SSEA4<sup>+</sup>(S1/S4<sup>+</sup>) subpopulations based on the RNA levels of the 22 genes that discriminated the 2 groups of relatively closer cell types. (<bold>D</bold>) Graphical representation of the first principal component of PCA for the 22 genes in a trigonometric circle that discriminated the 2 groups of anticorrelated genes (shown in dark blue and cyan).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bio-02-06-613-f06"/></fig><p>To further examine the transcriptome of various rbESC and rbiPSC subpopulations, we examined the expression of rabbit homologs of 22 mouse genes [<italic>Blimp1</italic>, <italic>Cdx2</italic>, <italic>Cdh1 (E-cadherin)</italic>, <italic>Cdh2 (N-cadherin)</italic>, <italic>Cldn6</italic>, <italic>Dax1 (NrOb1)</italic>, <italic>Dazl</italic>, <italic>Essrb</italic>, <italic>Fbxo15</italic>, <italic>Fgf4</italic>, <italic>Gbx2</italic>, <italic>Klf4</italic>, <italic>Lefty2</italic>, <italic>Nanog</italic>, <italic>Oct4</italic> (<italic>Pou5f1</italic>), <italic>Otx2</italic>, <italic>Pecam1</italic>, <italic>Pitx2</italic>, <italic>Piwil2</italic>, <italic>Rex1 (Zfp42)</italic>, <italic>Tbx3</italic>, and <italic>Tcfcp2l1</italic>], the mRNA levels of which have been used to evaluate stemness and demarcate the na&#x000ef;ve and primed pluripotent states in rodent cells (<xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">Tesar et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">Bao et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">Hanna et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="b39" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2012</xref>). Of note, 12 genes (<italic>Klf4</italic>, <italic>Cldn6</italic>, <italic>Otx2</italic>, <italic>Nanog</italic>, <italic>Oct4</italic>, <italic>Cdx2</italic>, <italic>Dazl</italic>, <italic>Rex1</italic>, <italic>Fbxo15</italic>, <italic>Pitx2</italic>, <italic>Tbx3</italic>, and <italic>Gbx2</italic>) were represented on the microarray. The expression levels of these 22 genes were determined by qPCR for the SSEA1<sup>+</sup>/SSEA4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, SSEA1<sup>+</sup>/SSEA4<sup>+</sup>, SSEA1<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/SSEA4<sup>+</sup>, and SSEA1<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/SSEA4<sup>&#x02212;</sup> subpopulations purified from the 4 rbESC and 3 rbiPS lines (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Table S4; Fig. S6</ext-link>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Fig.&#x02005;3E</xref>). In agreement with the microarray data, correlation clustering of the &#x00394;Ct values showed that the rbiPSC subpopulations showed fewer differences between them than with the rbESC subpopulations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Fig.&#x02005;6B</xref>). To determine which genes accounted for the variations between rbESCs and rbiPSCs, PCA was performed from the qPCR data obtained with the SSEA1<sup>+</sup>/SSEA4<sup>&#x02212;</sup> and SSEA1<sup>+</sup>/SSEA4<sup>+</sup> subpopulations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Fig.&#x02005;6C</xref>). The first 2 principal components had 78% of the total variation. The first axis that represented 56% of the total variability distinguished between rbESC and rbiPSC lines in accordance with correlation clustering analysis. The second axis represented 22% of the total variability and accounted for variability between cell lines. A graphical representation of gene dispersion in a trigonometric circle highlighted 2 clusters of genes: the first comprised <italic>Cdh2</italic>, <italic>Gbx2</italic>, and <italic>Dax1</italic> and the second comprised <italic>Otx2</italic>, <italic>Pitx2</italic>, <italic>Cldn6</italic>, <italic>Cdh1</italic>, <italic>Essrb</italic>, <italic>Klf4</italic>, <italic>Dazl</italic>, <italic>Oct4</italic>, <italic>Piwil2</italic>, <italic>Nanog</italic>, and <italic>Pecam1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Fig.&#x02005;6D</xref>). Both clusters were clearly anticorrelated over the cell lines, indicating that their relative expression levels were mutually exclusive. Both clusters appeared to be representative because most of the distances between the origin and the projected variables were globally close to the maximum distance (i.e. 1). Thus, these 14 genes explained most of the variability observed between rbESCs and rbiPSCs (first axis in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Fig.&#x02005;6C</xref>). The other 8 genes (<italic>Fgf4</italic>, <italic>Cdx2</italic>, <italic>Rex1</italic>, <italic>Tcfcp2l1</italic>, <italic>Lefty2</italic>, <italic>Fbxo15</italic>, <italic>Tbx3</italic>, and <italic>Blimp1</italic>) mostly accounted for the variability observed between lines in each group (2<sup>nd</sup> axis <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Fig.&#x02005;6D</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>rbiPSCs are closer to ICM cells</title><p>We next examined which cell types (rbESCs <italic>vs.</italic> rbiPSCs) and which subpopulations (SSEA1<sup>+</sup><italic>vs.</italic> SSEA4<sup>+</sup>
<italic>vs.</italic> SSEA<sup>&#x02212;</sup>) showed the closest proximity to ICM cells of the rabbit embryo. To this end, the expression of the 22 genes was measured in the ICM of third-day rabbit mid-blastocysts (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Table S4</ext-link>) and compared to the expression measured in the rbESC and rbiPSC subpopulations. Calculation of the Euclidean distances between the ICM sample and each subpopulations showed that SSEA1<sup>+</sup> rbiPSCs were the closest to the ICM and the SSEA1<sup>&#x02212;</sup> rbiPSCs were the farthest (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f07">Fig.&#x02005;7A</xref>). Interestingly, all rbESC subpopulations, irrespective of their SSEA1 status, were more distantly related to the ICM than the SSEA1<sup>+</sup> rbiPSCs. The relative proximity of the SSEA1<sup>+</sup> rbiPSCs with the ICM could be further evidenced in a rank histogram of the relative expression level of the 22 genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f07">Fig.&#x02005;7B,C</xref>). The R&#x0039d;A level of each gene in ICM cells were normalized to the mRNA level of <italic>Tbp</italic>, and the resultant &#x00394;Ct was ranked from the highest (<italic>Oct4</italic>: &#x00394;Ct&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;37.5) to the lowest (<italic>Dax1</italic>: &#x00394;Ct&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.0013). Most genes that were strongly expressed in rbiPSCs than in rbESCs (<italic>Oct4</italic>, <italic>Cdh1</italic>, <italic>Essrb</italic>, <italic>Cldn6</italic>, <italic>Nanog</italic>, <italic>Klf4</italic>, <italic>Otx2</italic>, <italic>Dazl</italic>, <italic>Pitx2</italic>, <italic>Piwil2</italic>, <italic>Pecam1</italic>; <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05) were highly expressed in the ICM (&#x00394;Ct&#x0003e;1). In contrast, genes that were strongly expressed in rbESCs (<italic>Cdh2</italic>, <italic>Gbx2</italic>, <italic>Dax1</italic>; <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05) were expressed at low levels in the ICM (&#x00394;Ct&#x0003c;0.1). Taken together, these results indicate that the gene expression profile of SSEA1<sup>+</sup> rbiPSCs best matched that of the ICM cells of rabbit preimplantation embryo.</p><fig id="f07" position="float"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><title>Gene expression profiling in rbESCs and rbiPSC <italic>vs.</italic> ICM cells.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Histogram showing the Euclidean distances between the ICM cells and each subpopulations, as determined from the expression profiles of the 22 genes. Euclidean distances correspond to the value of a vectorial distance in a multidimensional orthonormal basis (the number of dimensions is the number of genes analyzed). An Euclidean distance <italic>D</italic> for a PSC subpopulation <italic>a</italic> was calculated using the following formula: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="bio-02-06-613-e03.jpg"/></inline-formula> (1). <italic>x<sub>a</sub></italic>, y<sub>a</sub>, and n<sub>a</sub> represent the relative expression of each gene (<italic>x</italic>, <italic>y</italic>, and <italic>n</italic>) calculated by qPCR for the PSC subpopulation line <italic>a.</italic> (<bold>B</bold>) Histogram showing the &#x00394;Ct values calculated for each of the 22 genes in the SSEA1<sup>+</sup> rbESCs (dark blue bars) and SSEA1<sup>+</sup> rbiPSCs (cyan bars). (<bold>C</bold>) Histogram showing the &#x00394;Ct values calculated for each of the 22 genes in the rabbit ICM, normalized to the mRNA level of <italic>Tbp</italic> gene (&#x00394;Ct&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1) and ranked from the highest (left) to the lowest (right). Cyan bars: genes highly expressed in rbiPSCs, as calculated in panel B; dark blue bars: genes highly expressed in rbESCs; grey bars: genes equally expressed in rbiPSCs and rbESCs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bio-02-06-613-f07"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Colonization of pre-implantation embryos by rbESCs and rbiPSCs</title><p>To evaluate the capacity of rbESCs to colonize pre-implantation embryos and contribute to the formation of ICM, 5&#x02013;10 rbES-18 cells that expressed GFP were injected under the zona pellucida of 20 eight-cell-stage rabbit embryos. Of note rbES18 was derived from a GFP transgenic embryo (<xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">Al-Gubory and Houdebine, 2006</xref>) and GFP was expressed by all cells in this population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f08">Fig.&#x02005;8A</xref>). In a parallel experiment, rbES-18 SSEA1<sup>+</sup> cells were sorted by FACS and then injected into 67 eight-cell-stage embryos. All embryos were cultured until they reached the mid-blastocyst stage prior to GFP immunostaining and analysis by confocal microscopy (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Table S5</ext-link>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f08">Fig.&#x02005;8B</xref>). No GFP-expressing cells were observed in the 74 embryos that had successfully developed to the blastocyst stage. In contrast, when 5&#x02013;10 mES GFP<sup>+</sup> cells (line CGR8-GFP) were injected into rabbit embryos at the same stage, all the resulting blastocysts (15) exhibited extensive colonization of ICM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f08">Fig.&#x02005;8C</xref>). Thus, rabbit early-cleavage-stage embryos were permissive to colonization by na&#x000ef;ve mESCs but not by rbESCs.</p><fig id="f08" position="float"><label>Fig. 8.</label><caption><title>Colonization of pre-implantation embryos.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Flow cytometry analysis of GFP expression in rbES-18 and rbES-19 cells derived from GFP-transgenic and non-transgenic blastocysts, respectively. (<bold>B</bold>) Microinjection of SSEA1<sup>+</sup> rbES-18 cells into eight-cell-stage embryos and observation of developing embryos at the blastocyst stage. (<bold>C</bold>) Microinjection of mESCs (CGR8-GFP line) into rabbit eight-cell-stage embryos and observation of developing embryos at morula and blastocyst stages. (<bold>D</bold>) Observation of blastocyst-stage embryos resulting from the microinjection of rbiPS-B19-GFP and rbiPS-B19-GFP SSEA1<sup>+</sup> cells into eight-cell-stage embryos. (<bold>E</bold>) Left panels: Phase-contrast images showing aggregation of an eight-cell-stage embryo with a clump of rbiPS-B19-LacZ-EOS cells, and the resulting blastocyst after <italic>in vitro</italic> culture for 48&#x02005;hours. Right panels: &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity in the ICM of the blastocyst. (<bold>F</bold>) &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity in blastocysts resulting from aggregation of eight-cell-stage embryos with a clump of rbiPS-B19-LacZ-EOS cells and subsequent <italic>in vitro</italic> culture for 48&#x02005;hours. Scale bars: 50&#x02005;&#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bio-02-06-613-f08"/></fig><p>We performed a similar experiment with rbiPS-B19 line. First, rbiPS-B19 cells were infected with the GAE lentivector that expressed GFP under the CAG promoter. GFP<sup>+</sup> cells were sorted by FACS and then injected into 47 eight-cell-stage rabbit embryos. All developed to the blastocyst stage, but only one embryo exhibited GFP<sup>+</sup> cells in the ICM and in the trophoblast. Similarly, SSEA1<sup>+</sup> rbiPS-B19-GFP cells were sorted prior to injection into 65 eight-cell-stage embryos. Only one blastocyst had GFP<sup>+</sup> cells in the ICM after GFP immunostaining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f08">Fig.&#x02005;8D</xref>).</p><p>We thought that isolated rbiPSC survival would be very poor after injecting them into eight-cell-stage embryos and that this could explain the low rate of chimaeric blastocysts that was observed. To bypass the dissociation step, we generated aggregation chimaeras with 8-cell-stage embryos. Of note, this technique requires removal of the mucous coat, which prevents embryo implantation into the uterus after transfer to surrogates (<xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">Murakami and Imai, 1996</xref>). For this goal, rbiPS-B19 cells were infected with ABP-RP-TLCLACZL, a lentiviral vector that expressed the lacZ gene under the control of the EF1&#x003b1; promoter. Viable &#x003b2;-galactosidase<sup>+</sup> cells were isolated by iterative FACS sorting until a population of rbiPS-B19 cells that expressed &#x003b2;-galactosidase at a robust level could be stably expanded. The rbiPSC-B19-LacZ cells were subsequently infected with the EOS lentivector and selected with puromycin to generate a homogenous population of <italic>mOct4</italic> DE-positive cells (not shown). Clumps of 20&#x02013;25 resulting rbiPSC-B19-LacZ-EOS cells were aggregated in the zona pellucida- and mucous coat-free 8-cell-stage embryos and were subsequently cultured to the mid-blastocyst stage. We obtained 62 blastocysts, of which 10 had &#x003b2;-galactosidase<sup>+</sup> cells in the ICM. In one case, the ICM was heavily colonized by &#x003b2;-galactosidase<sup>+</sup> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f08">Fig.&#x02005;8E,F</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Table S5</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>Using the molecular and functional criteria that characterize pluripotency in rodents and primates, we demonstrated that rbESCs and rbiPSCs show some key differences. First, similar to mECSs, rbiPSCs are resistant to trypsinization to single-cell suspensions, a procedure that induces extensive cell death and differentiation when applied to rbESCs, mouse EpiSCs (<xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">Tesar et al., 2007</xref>), and primate ESCs (<xref rid="b40" ref-type="bibr">Wianny et al., 2008</xref>). Second, similar to mESCs, rbiPSCs express elevated levels of E-cadherin, whereas rbESCs express both E- and N-cadherins similar to mouse EpiSCs and primate ESCs (<xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">Tesar et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">Hawkins et al., 2012</xref>). Third, the cell cycle of rbESCs had a longer G1 phase than the S and G2 phases and similar to somatic cells, they undergo growth arrest in the G1 phase after DNA damage. This is in sharp contrast to the SSEA1<sup>+</sup> rbiPSCs as well as to all mouse and primate PSCs examined until date, which have a relatively short G1 phase and lack a DNA damage checkpoint in the G1 phase (<xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">Aladjem et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">Hong and Stambrook, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">Fluckiger et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">Filipczyk et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">Momcilovic et al., 2010</xref>). Fourth, the CR4 element of the mouse <italic>Oct4</italic> DE exhibits a more robust activity in rbiPSCs than in rbESCs. High CR4 element activity is observed in mESCs, whereas low activity is observed in mouse EpiSCs (<xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">Tesar et al., 2007</xref>). Fifth, the <italic>Oct4</italic> promoter is less methylated in the rbiPSCs than in the rbESCs. Sixth, rbESCs and rbiPSCs show distinct gene expression profiles. We identified 14 genes whose activity is different between rbiPSCs and rbESCs. Similar to that in mESCs, <italic>Essrb</italic>, <italic>Klf4</italic>, <italic>Piwil2</italic>, <italic>Cdh1</italic>, <italic>Dazl</italic>, and <italic>Pecam1</italic> are strongly expressed in rbiPSCs; however, they are expressed at low levels in rbESCs. Last, based on the expression of the 22 selected genes, rbiPSC lines are the closest to rabbit ICM, whereas the profiles of all rbESC lines are the farthest. Taken together, it can be concluded that rbiPSCs show many characteristic features of na&#x000ef;ve pluripotency as defined in rodents, i.e. resistance to single-cell dissociation, no expression of N-cadherin, robust activity of the distal enhancer of mouse <italic>Oct4</italic>, and robust expression of ICM-specific markers. However, rbiPSCs do not show all the attributes of na&#x000ef;ve pluripotency. For instance, they exploit FGF2 signaling for self-renewal, an attribute of primed pluripotency (<xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">Nichols and Smith, 2009</xref>). In addition, they do not express all the molecular markers of na&#x000ef;ve pluripotency, including <italic>Rex1</italic>, <italic>Tbx3</italic>, <italic>Gbx2</italic>, <italic>Fgf4</italic>, and <italic>Dax1</italic> (<xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">Tesar et al., 2007</xref>). Furthermore, they show a reduced capacity to colonize the ICM after injection into rabbit blastocysts. Based on these observations, we propose that rbiPSCs self-renew in an intermediate state between na&#x000ef;ve and primed pluripotency. Such an intermediate state may resemble the intermediate epiblast stem cells (IESCs) recently described in the mouse (<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">Chang and Li, 2013</xref>). Like IESCs, rbiPSCs express <italic>Rex1</italic> (na&#x000ef;ve pluripotency marker) and <italic>Otx2</italic> (primed pluripotency marker) at low levels, and express <italic>Pecam1</italic> (na&#x000ef;ve pluripotency marker) and <italic>Pitx2</italic> (primed pluripotency marker) at high levels. Moreover, both rbiPSCs and IESCs can colonize the ICM after aggregation with morulas. In the case of IESCs, the IESC-derived ICM cells failed to contribute to post-implantation development. In the case of rbiPSCs, we could not address this question because the morula aggregation technique requires removal of the mucin coat, which prevents embryo implantation into the uterus after transfer to surrogates (<xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">Murakami and Imai, 1996</xref>). However, the growth requirements of IESCs and rbiPSCs seem different. IESCs, which grow on gelatin, respond either to LIF or to activin to self-renew in the undifferentiate state. By contrast rbiPSCs grow on feeders and are strictly dependent on FGF2 signalling. Nevertheless, the possibility remains that rbiPSCs could also be dependent on LIF produced by feeder cells.</p><p>We have shown that rbESCs do not show all the attributes of pluripotent stem cells. In particular, they have a DNA damage checkpoint in the G1 phase like somatic cells. It is generally assumed that shortening the G1 phase sustains the pluripotent state by restricting the window of opportunity for differentiation cues (<xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">Mummery et al., 1987</xref>; <xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">Burdon et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="b32" ref-type="bibr">Sela et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">Coronado et al., 2013</xref>). In <italic>bona fide</italic> pluripotent stem cells, the lack of a DNA damage checkpoint in G1 might further reduce this window by preventing growth arrest at a critical point for self-renewal. Thus, rbESCs lack some key features of the pluripotent cell cycle, which might explain why they exhibit such a low proliferation rate and high spontaneous differentiation rate than rbiPSCs and primate ESCs.</p><p>To conclude, we have reported the first PSC lines in a non-rodent species that show characteristics of na&#x000ef;ve pluripotency. These cells represent a first step towards genome engineering and production of germline chimeras in rabbits.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Rabbit breeding</title><p>Sexually mature New Zealand White rabbits were purchased from Hycole (Marcoing, France) or HyPharm (Roussay, France). Superovulations of females were induced as described previously (<xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr">Salvetti et al., 2010</xref>). Sixty hours after artificial insemination, the fertilized embryos were flushed from explanted oviducts using Euroflush&#x000ae; (IMV Technologies) and cultured in TCM199 medium (Sigma) supplemented with 10% new-born calf serum (Sigma) at 38&#x000b0;C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Cell culture</title><p>Mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs) were prepared from 12.5-day-old embryos from the OF1 strain (Charles River). Rabbit embryonic fibroblasts (REFs) were prepared from 12-day-old embryos from the New Zealand White (Hycole). Rabbit fibroblasts (rbFs) were prepared from the ear skin of a 5-month-old New Zealand White female. MEFs, REFs, rbFs, the 293T cell line (ATCC, CRL 11268), the rhesus monkey ESC (rhESC) line LyonES (<xref rid="b40" ref-type="bibr">Wianny et al., 2008</xref>), and mouse ESCs [mESCs, CGR8 line (<xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">Mountford et al., 1994</xref>)] were cultured as described elsewhere (<xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">Sandrin et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="b40" ref-type="bibr">Wianny et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="b31" ref-type="bibr">Savatier et al., 1996</xref>). EpiSCs were derived from epiblasts of 6.5-day-old mouse embryos of the OF1 strain and cultured as described previously (<xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">Brons et al., 2007</xref>). rbESCs and rbiPSCs were cultured on mitomycin C-treated MEFs (1.25&#x000d7;10<sup>4</sup> MEF/cm<sup>2</sup>) in DMEM/F12 medium supplemented with 20% knockout serum replacement, 1% non-essential amino acids and 1% of a solution of 10,000&#x02005;U/ml penicillin + 10,000&#x02005;U/ml streptomycin + 29.2&#x02005;mg/ml L-glutamine, 1&#x02005;mM sodium pyruvate and 100&#x02005;&#x000b5;M 2-mercaptoethanol (Invitrogen). For rbESC and rbiPSCs culture, the medium was supplemented with 13&#x02005;ng/ml or 10&#x02005;ng/ml FGF2, respectively. rbiPSCs were routinely dissociated into single-cell suspensions after treatment with 0.05% trypsin&#x02013;EDTA. rbESCs were dissociated into small clumps of cells after treatment with 1&#x02005;mg/ml collagenase II (Sigma).</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Immunosurgery</title><p>The mucin coat and the zona pellucida of rabbit blastocysts (70 to 72&#x02005;h post-insemination; mid-blastocyst stage) were mechanically removed after brief exposure (2&#x02005;min) to 5&#x02005;mg/ml pronase (Sigma). ICMs were separated from the trophectoderm by immunosurgery after incubation of hatched blastocysts in anti-rabbit whole goat serum (Sigma) at 37&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02005;min and brief exposure (5&#x02005;min) to guinea pig complement serum (Sigma). Isolated ICMs were transferred to four-well plates on mitomycin C-treated MEFs at a concentration of 3.5&#x000d7;10<sup>4</sup> cells/cm<sup>2</sup> in rbESC medium. After 5 to 6 days, the developing outgrowths were mechanically dissociated into small clumps and transferred onto fresh feeder cells at 2.5&#x000d7;10<sup>4</sup> cells/cm<sup>2</sup>. All subsequent passages were performed by mechanical dissociation after treating colonies with collagenase II at 1&#x02005;mg/ml, followed by plating cell clumps on feeder cells at a concentration of 1.25&#x000d7;10<sup>4</sup> cells/cm<sup>2</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Virus production and cell infection</title><p>Plasmids used for producing retroviral and lentiviral vectors were either purchased from Addgene [pMXs-hOCT3/4 (17217), pMXs-hSOX2 (17218), pMXs-hKLF4 (17219), pMXs-hc-MYC (17220) (<xref rid="b34" ref-type="bibr">Takahashi et al., 2007</xref>) and pL-SIN-EOS-C(3+)-EiP (21313) (<xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">Hotta et al., 2009</xref>)] or obtained from Dr Cosset [pTG5349, phCMV-GP and pGAE-CAG-eGFP/wpre (<xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">Sandrin et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">Mangeot et al., 2002</xref>)] or Dr Suter [psPax2 and pMD2G (<xref rid="b33" ref-type="bibr">Suter et al., 2006</xref>)]. Virus production, concentration and titration were performed as previously described by transfection of 293T cells (<xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">Sandrin et al., 2002</xref>). Concentrated LacZ-expressing lentiviral particles were purchased from Allele Biotech (ABP-RP-TLCLACZL).</p><p>To generate rbiPSCs, 5&#x000d7;10<sup>5</sup> rbFs were infected twice at a two-day interval with 3&#x000d7;10<sup>6</sup> of viral particles, which contained equal parts of the four freshly produced hOct4, hSox2, hKlf4 and hMyc retroviruses [multiplicity of infection (m.o.i.)&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;8], in the presence of 4&#x02005;&#x000b5;g/ml polybrene (Sigma). Three days after the second infection, rbFs were trypsinized into single cells and replated at low density (6&#x000d7;10<sup>2</sup> cells/cm<sup>2</sup>) onto growth-inactivated MEFs in rbiPSC medium. The medium was changed every other day for 2 to 3 weeks until iPSC-like colonies appeared. To infect ESCs and iPSCs, the cells were plated on Matrigel (Beckton Dickinson) prior to infection with L-SIN-EOS-C(3+)-EiP and GAE-CAG-eGFP/wpre lentivectors at an m.o.i. of 5&#x02013;10 in appropriate media supplemented with 6&#x02005;&#x000b5;g/ml of polybrene. Rabbit eight-cell-stage embryos were infected by microinjection of 1&#x02005;nl L-SIN-EOS-C(3+)-EiP and GAE-CAG-eGFP/wpre lentivectors (2&#x000d7;10<sup>7</sup> infectious particles/ml) under the mucous coat and zona pellucida.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Alkaline phosphatase and &#x003b2;-galactosidase detection, immunolabelling, flow cytometry and confocal microscopy analysis</title><p>Alkaline phosphatase and &#x003b2;-galactosidase activities were assessed using a PAL 86R-1KT kit (Sigma) and a GALS staining kit (Sigma), respectively, according to the manufacturer's instructions. To detect &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity in viable cells, LacZ-expressing cells were analysed by flow cytometry using a FluoReporter&#x000ae; lacZ flow cytometry kit (Molecular Probes) according to the manufacturer's instructions.</p><p>For immunolabelling, the cells were grown on cover slips pre-treated with gelatin and FBS and coated with feeder cells. The cells were fixed with 2% paraformaldehyde (PFA; Sigma) in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) at 4&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02005;min, permeabilized in Tris-buffered saline (TBS, 50&#x02005;mM Tris pH&#x02005;7.6, 0.9% NaCl, 0.2% Triton X-100) and washed three times (10&#x02005;min each) in TBS. Non-specific binding sites were blocked with TBS supplemented with 10% FBS and 1% bovine serum albumin (BSA) for 1&#x02005;h and subsequently incubated overnight at 4&#x000b0;C with primary antibodies (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Table S1</ext-link>). After three rinses (10&#x02005;min each) with TBS, the cells were incubated with fluorochrome-conjugated secondary antibodies (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Table S1</ext-link>) at room temperature (RT) for 1&#x02005;h, followed by DNA staining with 0.5&#x02005;&#x000b5;g/ml Hoechst 33342 for 3&#x02005;min. Cover slips were mounted with mounting medium M1289 (Sigma), fixed with DPX medium (Cell Path), examined under a conventional fluorescence microscope (Leica DMRE) and analysed with Mercator software (Exploranova). For flow cytometry analysis, the cells were immunolabelled using the same protocols and the same antibodies used for immunostaining on coverslips, except that incubation with antibodies was at RT for 30&#x02005;min. The cells were analysed using a FACS Canto II cytometer and FACSDiva software (Becton Dickinson). The same protocol was used to detect GFP expression in rabbit blastocysts by immunolabelling, except that embryos were fixed with 2% PFA and permeabilized with 0.5% Triton X-100 in TBS. After DNA staining with 3&#x02005;&#x000b5;g/ml of propidium iodide in 1% BSA, embryos were incubated sequentially in baths (30&#x02005;min each) of 10%, 20% and 40% glycerol in TBS and then mounted on slides with mounting medium M1289 (Sigma) containing 0.1% p-phenylene-diamine (w/v) (Sigma). The embryos were observed by confocal microscopy (Leica TCS SP1 microscope with LSM software) at 488&#x02005;nm and 555&#x02005;nm (serial slices of 4&#x02005;mm).</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Real-time RT-PCR</title><p>Total RNA was isolated from cell clumps, cell pellets and embryoid bodies (EBs) using an RNeasy mini kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer's protocol and reverse-transcribed using 200&#x02005;U of M-MLV retrotranscriptase (Promega) and random primer mix (MWG). Real-time PCR used the StepOnePlus real-time PCR system (Applied Biosystems) and Fast SBYR&#x000ae; Green Master Mix (Applied Biosystems) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Following 40 amplification cycles, melt-curve analysis was used to verify that only the desired PCR products had been amplified. PCR efficiency for both target and reference genes was determined from the relative quantitative values for calibrator-normalized target gene expression using StepOnePlus Software V2.1 (Applied Biosystems). In all cases, expression of the target genes was normalized to those of rabbit TATA-box binding protein (<italic>Tbp</italic>) gene. But the same results were obtained with a normalization with the mRNA level of rabbit <italic>Gapdh</italic> gene. All primers used for RT-PCR and qPCR are shown in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/bio.20134242/-/DC1">supplementary material Table S2</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>Karyotype analysis</title><p>Chromosome spreads were prepared according to standard procedures and stained with Giemsa solution (Sigma). Thirty to fifty metaphase spreads were counted for each of the rbESC and rbiPSC lines. For karyotyping, G-banding was performed using 0.045% trypsin in Ca<sup>2+</sup>- and Mg<sup>2+</sup>-free Tyrode (Sigma). For some rbESC and rbiPSC line analysed, 4 to 20 banded karyotypes were evaluated for chromosomal rearrangements.</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>EB formation and teratoma production</title><p>For EB formation, rbESCs and rbiPSCs were dissociated into single cells using 0.05% trypsin, resuspended in rbESC medium without FGF2 and cultured in hanging drops. For teratoma formation, 2&#x02013;5&#x000d7;10<sup>6</sup> rbESCs or rbiPSCs were injected under the kidney capsules of 8-week-old severe combined immunodeficient (SCID) mice (CB17/SCID, Charles River). After 4&#x02013;7 weeks, the mice were euthanized and lesions were surgically removed and fixed in 10% neutral buffered formalin (Curtin Matheson Scientific, Inc.) for paraffin sections, or in 4% PFA for cryosections.</p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title>Cell cycle analysis</title><p>Cells were cultured for 24&#x02005;h with 50&#x02005;ng/ml of doxorubicin hydrochloride (Adriamycin&#x000ae;, Sigma). Single-cell suspensions were fixed with 70% ethanol at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C, rehydrated with PBS at 4&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02005;min, rinsed twice with PBS and incubated with 0.1&#x02005;mg/ml of RNAse A at RT for 30&#x02005;min. Propidium iodide (30&#x02005;mg/ml) was added to the cells for 1&#x02005;min before analysis with a FACS Canto II cytometer (Becton Dickinson). Data were acquired using FACSDiva software (Becton Dickinson). The percentages of G1-, S- and G2-phase cells were determined using ModFitLT software (Verity Software House).</p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title>DNA methylation analysis</title><p>The methylation profile of the rabbit Oct4 promoter (GenBank: AC235550.2) was determined by bisulfite mutagenesis and sequencing as previously described (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">Borghol et al., 2008</xref>). Two regions of the Oct4 promoter were subjected to duplex-nested PCR. Region 1 is situated between positions &#x02212;307 and +96 (25 CpG), and encompasses Conserved Region 1 (CR1) as defined by Kobolak et al. (<xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">Kobolak et al., 2009</xref>). Region 2 is situated between positions &#x02212;2060 and &#x02212;1626 (17 CpG sites), and encompasses Conserved Region 4 (CR4). Sequence of primers specific for bisulfite-converted DNA are as follows: Region 1, external forward: 5&#x02032;-GTTTTTTTAGGGAGGGGGTAGAG-3&#x02032;, external reverse: 5&#x02032;-AAAACCTTAAAAACTCAACCAAATCC-3&#x02032;, internal forward: 5&#x02032;-ATGGGGTGGAAGGGATTTTAG-3&#x02032;, internal reverse: 5&#x02032;-AAAATCCACCCAACCTAACTCC-3&#x02032;; Region 2, external forward: 5&#x02032;-GTTGGTTGGGTAGGAGTTTAT-3&#x02032;, external reverse: 5&#x02032;-TAACCCTATCAAACTTCTAAAAAACT-3&#x02032;, internal forward: 5&#x02032;-ATAAGTTAAAGAGTTTTGTTTTTGG-3&#x02032;, internal reverse: 5&#x02032;-AACTTCTAAAAAACT AAATAACCTAACTCT-3&#x02032;. The PCR products were cloned into the pNZY28-A plasmid (Nzyteh; Portugal) and 24 PCR-positive colonies were sequenced for each PCR product (Biofidal, Lyon, France).</p></sec><sec id="s4k"><title>Rabbit microarray and hybridization</title><p>A customized rabbit microarray was designed starting from the commercially available Agilent rabbit microarray (G2519F), and including genes expressed during preimplantation development in the rabbit (B.S.-P., L.J. and V.D., unpublished data). Briefly, rabbit embryonic ESTs obtained from four suppressive subtractive cDNA hybridizations (SSH) were included in the custom-made microarray. ESTs expressed during the first cleavage stages, blastocyst stage, and early gastrulation embryos were sequenced (<xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">L&#x000e9;andri et al., 2009</xref>), assembled into contigs and annotated through homology searches against nucleic and proteic databases. Furthermore, candidate genes sourced from Ensembl Genome Browser (oryCun2.0), and associated with pluripotency or embryonic development, were added to the design. The best quality probes from the commercially available Agilent transcriptome-wide rabbit microarray was added, resulting in a microarray with 62, 976 probes including positive and negative controls. The 60-mer oligosequence probes were designed by eArray (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://earray.chem.agilent.com/earray">https://earray.chem.agilent.com/earray</ext-link>), and were used for microarrays synthesis <italic>in situ</italic> using the Agilent SurePrint&#x02122; technology (Agilent Technologies, Mississauga, On, Canada) with a 8&#x000d7;60&#x02005;K format. The custom microarray design of the platform has been submitted to the NCBI GEO (Gene Expression Omnibus). The accession number of the platform is GSE43403.</p><p>For hybridization, cyanine-3 (Cy3) labeled cRNAs were prepared from 0.2&#x02005;&#x000b5;g RNA using the One-Color Microarray-Based Gene Expression Analysis Low Input Quick Amp Labeling kit (Agilent) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Dye incorporation and cRNA yield were checked with the NanoDrop ND-1000 Spectrophotometer. 0.6&#x02005;&#x000b5;g of Cy3-labelled cRNA (specific activity &#x0003e;6.0&#x02005;pmol Cy3/ug cRNA) was fragmented at 60&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02005;minutes following the manufacturer's instructions. Hybridizations were performed for 17&#x02005;hours at 65&#x000b0;C in a rotating Agilent hybridization oven. After hybridization, microarrays were washed 1&#x02005;minute at room temperature with GE Wash Buffer 1 (Agilent) and 1&#x02005;minute with 37&#x000b0;C GE Wash buffer 2 (Agilent), then dried immediately. Slides were scanned immediately after washing on the Agilent DNA Microarray Scanner using one color scan setting for 8&#x000d7;60k array slides (Scan Area 61&#x000d7;21.6&#x02005;mm). The scanned images were analyzed with Feature Extraction Software (Agilent, 7.10.3.1). Features flagged in Feature Extraction as Feature Non-uniform outliers were excluded. Normalization procedures were performed using R statistical software (R: A language and environment for statistical computing (R Foundation for Statistical Computing), Vienna, Austria; 2012, R-Core-Team; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org">http://www.r-project.org</ext-link>) and data were normalized using intra-array median substraction and log2 transformation.</p></sec><sec id="s4l"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Principal component analysis (PCA) was performed on qRT-PCR data (centered and reduced) using R statistical software (FactoMineR: Multivariate exploratory: data analysis and data mining with R; R package version 1.20, 2012, Husson et al.; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/FactoMineR/index.html">http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/FactoMineR/index.html</ext-link>). Other statistical analyses were done using the test of Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis. Normalized transcriptome data were analyzed by hierarchical clustering using the Pearson correlation coefficient as a measure of distance.</p></sec><sec id="s4m"><title>Injection of cells into pre-implantation embryos and aggregation with morulas</title><p>For microinjection, ESCs and iPSCs were dissociated into single-cell suspensions. Five to 10 cells were microinjected under the mucous coat and zona pellucida of eight-cell-stage rabbit embryos. The embryos injected with GFP-expressing cells were cultured <italic>in vitro</italic> until they reached the mid-blastocyst stage, fixed in 2% PFA and immunostained with anti-GFP antibody.</p><p>For morula aggregation, fertilized eggs were harvested 20&#x02005;hours after insemination, and cultured in RDH medium (Invitrogen), as described elsewhere (<xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">Jin et al., 2000</xref>). When they reached the eight-cell stage, embryos were treated with pronase to eliminate the zona pellucida and placed with clumps of 20&#x02013;25 PSCs in microwells to induce aggregations, as described previously (<xref rid="b41" ref-type="bibr">Wood et al., 1993</xref>). Successful aggregates were cultured for 48&#x02005;hours until they reached the blastocyst stage and subsequently analysed for &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity.</p></sec></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_2_6_613__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_bio.20134242_bio.20134242-s1.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
xlink:href="supp_bio.20134242_Table_S4_BIO.docx"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body><back><ack><p>We thank Nicolas Gadot and Jean-Yves Scoazec (ANIPATH, SFR Sant&#x000e9; Lyon-Est, Lyon, France) for teratoma histology, Thibault Andrieu and S&#x000e9;bastien Dussurgey (SFR BioSciences Gerland&#x02013;Lyon Sud) for technical assistance with flow cytometry and cell sorting, the INRA SIGENAE team (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sigenae.org">http://www.sigenae.org</ext-link>) for their help in designing the customized rabbit array, and J&#x000e9;rome Lecardonnel for technical assistance in array hybridization. This work was supported by research grants from &#x0201c;Agence Nationale de la Recherche&#x0201d; (ANR) (project PLURABBIT no. PCS-09-GEM-08), European Cooperation in Science and Technology (COST) Action (Rabbit Genome Biology (RGB)-Net no. TD1101), the HyPharm Company (PhD Grant INRA/HyPharm no. 04012010) and the &#x0201c;r&#x000e9;gion Rh&#x000f4;ne-Alpes&#x0201d; (ADR CIBLE 2010 project no. R10065CC). This work was performed within the framework of (i) the LABEX DEVWECAN (ANR-10-LABX-0061) and the LABEX CORTEX (ANR-11-LABX-0042) of Universit&#x000e9; de Lyon (&#x0201c;Investissements d&#x02019;Avenir&#x0201d; no. ANR-11-IDEX-0007), (ii) the Institute CESAME (&#x0201c;Investissements d&#x02019;Avenir&#x0201d; no. ANR-10-IBHU-003) and (iii) the &#x0201c;Infrastructure Nationale en Biologie et Sant&#x000e9;&#x0201d; INGESTEM (&#x0201c;Investissements d&#x02019;Avenir&#x0201d; no. ANR-11-INBS-0009), operated by the ANR.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> The authors have no competing interests to declare.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Gubory</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houdebine</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> imaging of green fluorescent protein-expressing cells in transgenic animals using fibred confocal fluorescence microscopy.</article-title>
<source>Eur. J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>85</volume>, <fpage>837</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>845</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejcb.2006.03.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16781011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aladjem</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spike</surname><given-names>B. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodewald</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hope</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klemm</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaenisch</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahl</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>ES cells do not activate p53-dependent stress responses and undergo p53-independent apoptosis in response to DNA damage.</article-title>
<source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>155</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(98)70061-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9443911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Surani</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Epigenetic reversion of post-implantation epiblast to pluripotent embryonic stem cells.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>461</volume>, <fpage>1292</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1295</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19816418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borghol</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blach&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lef&#x000e8;vre</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Transcriptional and epigenetic status of protamine 1 and 2 genes following round spermatids injection into mouse oocytes.</article-title>
<source>Genomics</source>
<volume>91</volume>, <fpage>415</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>422</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygeno.2007.12.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18343090</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brons</surname><given-names>I. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smithers</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trotter</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rugg-Gunn</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuva de Sousa Lopes</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Howlett</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarkson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahrlund-Richter</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Derivation of pluripotent epiblast stem cells from mammalian embryos.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>448</volume>, <fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>195</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature05950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17597762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burdon</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Savatier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Signalling, cell cycle and pluripotency in embryonic stem cells.</article-title>
<source>Trends Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>432</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>438</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0962-8924(02)02352-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12220864</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Clonal isolation of an intermediate pluripotent stem cell state.</article-title>
<source>Stem Cells</source>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/stem.1330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coronado</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Godet</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourillot</surname><given-names>P. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tapponnier</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernat</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Afanassieff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Markossian</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malashicheva</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iacone</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>A short G1 phase is an intrinsic determinant of na&#x000ef;ve embryonic stem cell pluripotency.</article-title>
<source>Stem Cell Res.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>118</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>131</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scr.2012.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23178806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gai</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>H. Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Rabbit embryonic stem cell lines derived from fertilized, parthenogenetic or somatic cell nuclear transfer embryos.</article-title>
<source>Exp. Cell Res.</source>
<volume>312</volume>, <fpage>3669</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3682</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yexcr.2006.08.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16996056</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Filipczyk</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laslett</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mummery</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pera</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Differentiation is coupled to changes in the cell cycle regulatory apparatus of human embryonic stem cells.</article-title>
<source>Stem Cell Res.</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scr.2007.09.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19383386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fluckiger</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcy</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchand</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x000e9;gre</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cosset</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitalipov</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Savatier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehay</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Cell cycle features of primate embryonic stem cells.</article-title>
<source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>547</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>556</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1634/stemcells.2005-0194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16239321</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lengner</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soldner</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassady</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muffat</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaenisch</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Human embryonic stem cells with biological and epigenetic characteristics similar to those of mouse ESCs.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>107</volume>, <fpage>9222</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9227</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1004584107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20442331</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamet</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merry</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>E-cadherin and, in its absence, N-cadherin promotes Nanog expression in mouse embryonic stem cells via STAT3 phosphorylation.</article-title>
<source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>1842</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1851</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/stem.1148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22696497</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogonuki</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimozawa</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatori</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Stable embryonic stem cell lines in rabbits: potential small animal models for human research.</article-title>
<source>Reprod. Biomed. Online</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>706</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>715</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1472-6483(10)60320-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18983757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogura</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Basic FGF and Activin/Nodal but not LIF signaling sustain undifferentiated status of rabbit embryonic stem cells.</article-title>
<source>Exp. Cell Res.</source>
<volume>315</volume>, <fpage>2033</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2042</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yexcr.2009.01.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19331817</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatori</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matoba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyoshi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogura</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Generation of induced pluripotent stem cells in rabbits: potential experimental models for human regenerative medicine.</article-title>
<source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>285</volume>, <fpage>31362</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31369</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M110.150540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20670936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stambrook</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Restoration of an absent G1 arrest and protection from apoptosis in embryonic stem cells after ionizing radiation.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>14443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14448</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0401346101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15452351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hotta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farra</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayaragavan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e9;guin</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Draper</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasceri</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maksakova</surname><given-names>I. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mager</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossant</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Isolation of human iPS cells using EOS lentiviral vectors to select for pluripotency.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Methods</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>370</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>376</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19404254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>D. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Im</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Successful pregnancy after transfer of rabbit blastocysts grown <italic>in vitro</italic> from single-cell zygotes.</article-title>
<source>Theriogenology</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>1109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1116</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0093-691X(00)00419-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11131329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobolak</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Polgar</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mamo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogel-Gaillard</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tancos</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baji</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tar</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirity</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Promoter analysis of the rabbit POU5F1 gene and its expression in preimplantation stage embryos.</article-title>
<source>BMC Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>88</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2199-10-88</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19732419</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000e9;andri</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Archilla</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peynot</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabau</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chastellier</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renard</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duranthon</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Revealing the dynamics of gene expression during embryonic genome activation and first differentiation in the rabbit embryo with a dedicated array screening.</article-title>
<source>Physiol. Genomics</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>98</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physiolgenomics.90310.2008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19001509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mangeot</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duperrier</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x000e8;gre</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigal</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cosset</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Darlix</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>High levels of transduction of human dendritic cells with optimized SIV vectors.</article-title>
<source>Mol. Ther.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>283</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>290</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/mthe.2002.0541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11863418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Momcilovic</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knobloch</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornsaglio</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Varum</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Easley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schatten</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>DNA damage responses in human induced pluripotent stem cells and embryonic stem cells.</article-title>
<source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>e13410</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20976220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mountford</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zevnik</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000fc;wel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dani</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Dicistronic targeting constructs: reporters and modifiers of mammalian gene expression.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>91</volume>, <fpage>4303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4307</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.91.10.4303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8183905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mummery</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Brink</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Laat</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Commitment to differentiation induced by retinoic acid in P19 embryonal carcinoma cells is cell cycle dependent.</article-title>
<source>Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>121</volume>, <fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0012-1606(87)90133-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2883052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Successful implantation of <italic>in vitro</italic> cultured rabbit embryos after uterine transfer: a role for mucin.</article-title>
<source>Mol. Reprod. Dev.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>170</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1098-2795(199602)43:2&#x0003c;167::AID-MRD5&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-P</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8824914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Naive and primed pluripotent states.</article-title>
<source>Cell Stem Cell</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>492</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2009.05.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19497275</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okumura-Nakanishi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niwa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Oct-3/4 and Sox2 regulate Oct-3/4 gene in embryonic stem cells.</article-title>
<source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>280</volume>, <fpage>5307</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5317</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M410015200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15557334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salvetti</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buff</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Afanassieff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu&#x000e9;rin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joly</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Structural, metabolic and developmental evaluation of ovulated rabbit oocytes before and after cryopreservation by vitrification and slow freezing.</article-title>
<source>Theriogenology</source>
<volume>74</volume>, <fpage>847</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>855</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2010.04.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20570329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandrin</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gay</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x000e8;gre</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Grand</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trono</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cosset</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Lentiviral vectors pseudotyped with a modified RD114 envelope glycoprotein show increased stability in sera and augmented transduction of primary lymphocytes and CD34+ cells derived from human and nonhuman primates.</article-title>
<source>Blood</source>
<volume>100</volume>, <fpage>823</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>832</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2001-11-0042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12130492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savatier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapillonne</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Grunsven</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudkin</surname><given-names>B. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Samarut</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Withdrawal of differentiation inhibitory activity/leukemia inhibitory factor up-regulates D-type cyclins and cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitors in mouse embryonic stem cells.</article-title>
<source>Oncogene</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>309</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>322</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8570208</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sela</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Molotski</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Golan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Itskovitz-Eldor</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Human embryonic stem cells exhibit increased propensity to differentiate during the G1 phase prior to phosphorylation of retinoblastoma protein.</article-title>
<source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>1097</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1108</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/stem.1078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22415928</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suter</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cartier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bettiol</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tirefort</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaconi</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubois-Dauphin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Rapid generation of stable transgenic embryonic stem cell lines using modular lentivectors.</article-title>
<source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>615</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>623</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1634/stemcells.2005-0226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16293575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohnuki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Narita</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichisaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomoda</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Induction of pluripotent stem cells from adult human fibroblasts by defined factors.</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>131</volume>, <fpage>861</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>872</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2007.11.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18035408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbacioru</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Surani</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Tracing the derivation of embryonic stem cells from the inner cell mass by single-cell RNA-Seq analysis.</article-title>
<source>Cell Stem Cell</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>468</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>478</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2010.03.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20452321</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tesar</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chenoweth</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brook</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>New cell lines from mouse epiblast share defining features with human embryonic stem cells.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>448</volume>, <fpage>196</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>199</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature05972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17597760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Generation and characterization of rabbit embryonic stem cells.</article-title>
<source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>481</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>489</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1634/stemcells.2006-0226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17038672</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Dissecting signaling pathways that govern self-renewal of rabbit embryonic stem cells.</article-title>
<source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>283</volume>, <fpage>35929</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35940</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M804091200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18940811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Claudin 6: a novel surface marker for characterizing mouse pluripotent stem cells.</article-title>
<source>Cell Res.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>1082</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1085</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cr.2012.77</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22565286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wianny</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernat</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huissoud</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcy</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Markossian</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortay</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giroud</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leviel</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Savatier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Derivation and cloning of a novel rhesus embryonic stem cell line stably expressing tau-green fluorescent protein.</article-title>
<source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>1444</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1453</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1634/stemcells.2007-0953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18356572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossant</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Auerbach</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Non-injection methods for the production of embryonic stem cell-embryo chimaeras.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>365</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/365087a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8361547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeom</surname><given-names>Y. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuhrmann</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ovitt</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brehm</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohbo</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000fc;bner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;ler</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Germline regulatory element of Oct-4 specific for the totipotent cycle of embryonal cells.</article-title>
<source>Development</source>
<volume>122</volume>, <fpage>881</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>894</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8631266</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>