<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">IMA Fungus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">IMA Fungus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IMA Fungus</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>IMA Fungus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2210-6340</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2210-6359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>International Mycological Association</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4941682</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5598/imafungus.2016.07.01.08</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Recommendations for competing sexual-asexually typified generic names in Sordariomycetes (except Diaporthales, Hypocreales, and Magnaporthales) </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Réblová</surname><given-names>Martina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Andrew N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rossman</surname><given-names>Amy Y.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">
*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>Keith A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Crous</surname><given-names>Pedro W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hawksworth</surname><given-names>David L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abdel-Wahab</surname><given-names>Mohamed A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>Paul F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Daranagama</surname><given-names>Dinushani A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>De Beer</surname><given-names>Z. Wilhelm</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A11">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Shi-Ke</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>Kevin D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jayawardena</surname><given-names>Ruvvishika</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jaklitsch</surname><given-names>Walter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A12">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A13">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>E. B. Gareth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A14">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>Yu-Ming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A15">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Judith</surname><given-names>Caroline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A16">
<sup>16</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maharachchikumbura</surname><given-names>Sajeewa S. N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A17">
<sup>17</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>Ka-Lai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A18">
<sup>18</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Petrini</surname><given-names>Liliane E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A19">
<sup>19</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>Huzefa A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A20">
<sup>20</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>Andrea I</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A21">
<sup>21</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shearer</surname><given-names>Carol</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Senanayake</surname><given-names>Indunil C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Voglmayr</surname><given-names>Hermann</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A13">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>Bevan S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A22">
<sup>22</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wijayawarden</surname><given-names>Nalin N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label> Department of Taxonomy, Institute of Botany of the Academy of Sciences of the Czech Republic, Prùhonice 252 43, Czech Republic</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label> Illinois Natural History Survey, University of Illinois, Champaign, Illinois 61820, USA</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label> Department of Botany and Plant Pathology, Oregon State University, Corvallis, Oregon 97331, USA;</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label> Ottawa Research and Development Centre, Biodiversity (Mycology and Microbiology), Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada, 960 Carling Avenue, Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0C6 Canada</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label> CBS-KNAW Fungal Biodiversity Institute, Uppsalalaan 8, 3584 CT Utrecht, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label> Departamento de Biología Vegetal II, Facultad de Farmacia, Universidad Complutense, Plaza de Ramón y Cajal s/n, Madrid 28040, Spain</aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label> Department of Life Sciences, The Natural History Museum, Cromwell Road, London SW7 5BD, UK</aff><aff id="A8"><label>8</label> Comparative Plant and Fungal Biology, Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, Surrey, TW9 3DS, UK</aff><aff id="A9"><label>9</label> Department of Botany and Microbiology, Faculty of Science, Sohag University, Sohag 82524, Egypt</aff><aff id="A10"><label>10</label> Center of Excellence in Fungal Research, School of Science, Mae Fah Luang University, Chiang Rai 57100, Thailand</aff><aff id="A11"><label>11</label> Department of Microbiology and Plant Pathology, University of Pretoria, Pretoria 0002, South Africa</aff><aff id="A12"><label>12</label> Institute of Forest Entomology, Forest Pathology and Forest Protection, Department of Forest and Soil Sciences, BOKU-University of Natural Resources and Life Sciences, Vienna, Austria</aff><aff id="A13"><label>13</label> Division of Systematic and Evolutionary Botany, Department of Botany and Biodiversity Research, University of Vienna, Vienna, Austria</aff><aff id="A14"><label>14</label> Department of Botany and Microbiology, College of Science, King Saud University, P.O. Box 2455, Riyadh 11451, Saudi Arabia</aff><aff id="A15"><label>15</label> Institute of Plant and Microbial Biology, Academia Sinica, Nankang, Taipei 115 29, Taiwan</aff><aff id="A16"><label>16</label> Department of Mycology, Institute of Ecology, Evolution and Diversity, Goethe-University, Max-von-Laue-Str. 13, 60438 Frankfurt am Main, Germany</aff><aff id="A17"><label>17</label> Department of Crop Sciences, College of Agricultural and Marine Sciences, Sultan Qaboos University, PO Box 8, 123 Al Khoud, Oman</aff><aff id="A18"><label>18</label> Institute of Marine Biology and Centre of Excellence for the Oceans, National Taiwan Ocean University, 2 Pei-Ning Road, Keelung 20224, Taiwan (ROC)</aff><aff id="A19"><label>19</label> Via al Perato 15c, CH-6932 Breganzona, Switzerland</aff><aff id="A20"><label>20</label> Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry, 457 Sullivan Science Building, University of North Carolina, Greensboro, NC 27402-6170, USA</aff><aff id="A21"><label>21</label> Instituto de Micología y Botánica, UBA-CONICET, Departamento de Biodiversidad y Biología Experimental, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales, Universidad de Buenos Aires, Pabellón II, Piso 4°, Lab 6, Av. Int. Güiraldes 2620. Ciudad Universitaria, C1428EHA, Buenos Aires, Argentina</aff><aff id="A22"><label>22</label> Manaaki Whenua Landcare Research, Private Bag 92170, Auckland, New Zealand</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*corresponding author e-mail: <email>amydianer@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2016 International Mycological Association</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/legalcode"><license-p>You are free to share - to copy, distribute and transmit the work, under the following conditions:</license-p><license-p><bold>Attribution:</bold> You must attribute the work in the manner specified by the author or licensor (but not in any way that suggests that they endorse you or your use of the work).</license-p><license-p><bold>Non-commercial:</bold> You may not use this work for commercial purposes.</license-p><license-p><bold>No derivative works:</bold> You may not alter, transform, or build upon this work.</license-p><license-p>For any reuse or distribution, you must make clear to others the license terms of this work, which can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/legalcode">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/legalcode</ext-link>. Any of the above conditions can be waived if you get permission from the copyright holder. Nothing in this license impairs or restricts the author’s moral rights.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>With the advance to one scientific name for each fungal species, the generic names in the class Sordariomycetes typified by sexual and asexual morphs are evaluated based on their type species to determine if they compete with each other for use or protection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Recommendations are made for which of the competing generic names should be used based on criteria such as priority, number of potential names changes, and frequency of use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Some recommendations for well-known genera include Arthrinium over Apiospora, Colletotrichum over Glomerella, Menispora over Zignoëlla, Microdochium over Monographella, Nigrospora over Khuskia, and Plectosphaerella over Plectosporium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>All competing generic names are listed in a table of recommended names along with the required action. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>If priority is not accorded to sexually typified generic names after 2017, only four names would require formal protection: Chaetosphaerella over Oedemium, Diatrype over Libertella, Microdochium over Monographella, and Phaeoacremonium over Romellia and Togninia. Concerning species in the recommended genera, one replacement name (Xylaria benjaminii nom. nov.) is introduced, and the following new combinations are made: Arthrinium sinense, Chloridium caesium, C. chloroconium, C. gonytrichii, Corollospora marina, C. parvula, C. ramulosa, Juncigena fruticosae, Melanospora simplex, Seimatosporium massarina, Sporoschisma daemonoropis, S. taitense, Torpedospora mangrovei, Xylaria penicilliopsis, and X. termiticola combs. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Ascomycota</italic></kwd><kwd>nomenclature</kwd><kwd>pleomorphic fungi</kwd><kwd>protected lists</kwd><kwd>taxonomy</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The class Sordariomycetes is composed of three subclasses and about 21 orders including many genera with species that express themselves in both their sexual and asexual morphs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Based on the obsolete version of Article 59 of the outdated International Code of Botanical Nomenclature (McNeill et al. 2006), these morphs had previously been described in different genera resulting in more than one scientific name for a single fungal species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>With the change to the International Code of Nomenclature for algae, fungi, and plants (ICN; McNeill et al. 2012), two or more names for different morphs of the same species are no longer allowed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Although determining which name to use generally follows the principle of priority of publication at the family, generic and species level, exceptions to this principle are allowed, especially in the case of economically important and widely used taxa. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In this paper generic names that appear to compete for use are reviewed to determine if their respective type species are congeneric using various resources including the USDA SMML Fungal Databases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nt.ars-grin.gov/fungaldatabases/">http://nt.ars-grin.gov/fungaldatabases/</ext-link>) and Wijayawardene et al. (2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>If so, then a number of factors are considered in deciding which generic name to recommend for use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>These factors include the number of species in each competing genus, which correlates with the number of name changes that would be required, and how widely used are species in each genus as determined by reports and peer-reviewed publications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>If these factors are about equal, then the generic name that has priority by date is recommended for use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>For each set of competing generic names, these factors are discussed based on the literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Finally, a draft of these recommendations was circulated widely amongst the community of mycologists interested in each major group of fungi to arrive at the proposals made here. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>A synopsis of data concerning each genus is provided in Table 1 listing the generic names recommended for use and competing names, the type species for each genus and the current name for the type, and action required especially if the principle of priority will not be followed, i.e. the generic name must be protected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>At present the ICN requires that names typified by sexual morphs should have priority unless protected, although it is proposed that this requirement be deleted in 2017 (Hawksworth 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Eventually all generic names proposed for protection will be evaluated by the Nomenclature Committee for Fungi (NCF), and formally accepted or not at the Nomenclature Section meeting of the next International Botanical Congress in 2017. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>For several groups of fungi having pleomorphic genera, this process has been completed, i.e. Dothideomycetes (Rossman et al. 2015b), Erysiphales (Braun 2013), Eurotiales (Samson et al. 2014, Visagie et al. 2014), Leotiomycetes (Johnston et al. 2014), yeast fungi (Daniel et al. 2014), and some orders of Sordariomycetes including Diaporthales (Rossman et al. 2015a), Hypocreales (Rossman et al. 2013, Quandt et al. 2014), Magnaporthales (Zhang et al. 2016), and Microascales and Ophiostomatales (de Beer et al. 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>This paper addresses the remaining orders of the class Sordariomycetes listed alphabetically by order as outlined in Maharachchikumbura et al. (2015): Amphisphaeriales, Calosphaeriales, Chaetosphaeriales, Coniochaetales, Conio-scyphales, Cordanales, Coronophorales, Glomerellales, Halosphaeriales, Melanosporales, Microascales, Phylla-chorales, Pleurotheciales, Savoryellales, Sordariales, Togniniales, Torpedosporales, and Xylariales. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>RECOMMENDATIONS FOR GENERIC NAMES </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>(A) = a name typified by an asexual morph, and (S) = a name typified by a sexual morph. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Amphisphaeriales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Use Dyrithiopsis L. Cai et al. 2003 (S) rather than Monochaetiopsis L. Cai et al. 2003 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The monotypic genera Dyrithiopsis, typified by D. lakefuxianensis, and Monochaetiopsis, typified by M. lakefuxiansis, were described as the sexual and asexual morph of the same species at the same time (Jeewon et al. 2003), thus they are synonyms and have equal priority. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Because Dyrithiopsis has been cited more widely in the literature, we recommend Dyrithiopsis for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Use Hyalotiopsis Punith. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>1970 (A) rather than Ellurema Nag Raj &amp; W.B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Kendr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>1985 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>When Punithalingam (1970) described the genus Hyalotiopsis, typified by H. subramanianii, he noted that the sexual morph was Massaria indica, the basionym of Ellurema indica, type of the monotypic Ellurema, thus Hyalotiopsis and Ellurema are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>This history was recounted by Nag Raj &amp; Kendrick (1986) when they described Ellurema. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>A second species of Hyalotiopsis has been redisposed in Parahyalotiopsis as P. borassi (syn. Hyalotiopsis borassi) (Nag Raj 1976), thus both genera include only one species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Given their equal use, we follow priority and recommend Hyalotiopsis for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Use Pestalotiopsis Steyaert 1949 (A) rather than Pestalosphaeria M.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Barr 1975 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The well-known genus Pestalotiopsis, typified by P. guepinii, was established for many species of Pestalotia determined to be distinct from the type of Pestalotia, P. pezizoides. Barr (1975) described the genus Pestalosphaeria, typified by P. concentrica, for the sexual morph of Pestalotiopsis guepinii var. macrotricha, both species on Rhododendron in southeastern North America. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Thus, it appears that Pestalosphaeria is a synonym of Pestalotiopsis. Pestalotiopsis has been widely used and currently includes more than 200 names with two recent accounts of the genus (Maharachchikumbura et al. 2012, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, Pestalosphaeria includes 14 names, none of which are commonly used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Given the ubiquitous and widely reported species of Pestalotiopsis as well as the number of names in that genus and its priority, we recommend use of Pestalotiopsis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Use Seimatosporium Corda 1833 (A) rather than Discostroma Clem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>1909 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The generic names Discostroma and Seimatosporium have been applied to sexual and asexual morphs of the same species based on morphological studies (Brockmann 1976, Nag Raj 1993). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The type species of Discostroma, D. rehmii, is a younger synonym of D. massarina, and has an asexual morph referred to as Seimatosporium ribis-alpini while the type of Seimatosporium, S. rosae, has a sexual morph described as Discostroma rosae (Shoemaker 1964, Brockmann 1976, Nag Raj 1993). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Although neither of the type species of Discostroma or Seimatosporium were included, Tanaka et al. (2011) used three species of Discostroma and sixteen species of Seimatosporium in their LSU tree to show that representatives of these genera form a monophyletic genus that should be regarded as Seimatosporium. Norphanphoun et al. (2015) added four more isolates of Seimatosporium including one for the type species, S. rosae, and also concluded that the genus was monophyletic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Host-specificity should be considered in studying the taxonomy of this genus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Given that Seimatosporium is the oldest name, has the greater number of species, and is more commonly used, this generic name is recommended for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>New combination: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Seimatosporium massarina (Sacc.) Jaklitsch &amp; Voglmayr, comb. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>MycoBank MB817259 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Metasphaeria massarina Sacc., Atti Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Veneto-Trent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Nat., Padova, Sér. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>6 2: 22 (1884). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Synonyms: Discostroma massarina (Sacc.) Arx, Gen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Fungi Sporul. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Cult., 2nd edn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>(Vaduz): 131 (1974). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Hendersonia ribis-alpini Fautrey, Revue Mycol., Toulouse 14: 171 (1892). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Seimatosporium ribis-alpini (Fautrey) Shoemaker &amp; E. Müll., Canad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Bot. 42: 403 (1964). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Curreya rehmii Schnabl, Ber. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Bayer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Bot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Ges., Beih. 2: 66 (1892) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Discostroma rehmii (Schnabl) Clem., Gen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Fungi: 173 (1909). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Use Seiridium Nees 1816 (A) rather than Blogiascospora Shoemaker et al. 1966 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>According to Shoemaker et al. (1966) Seiridium marginatum, the type species of Seiridium, is the asexual morph of Blogiascospora marginata, type of the monotypic genus Blogiascospora, thus Seiridium and Blogioascopsora are synonyms as confirmed by Jaklitsch et al. (2016). Seiridium is the older generic name, has the greater number of species, and is the more widely used, therefore Seiridium is recommended for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>One species of Seiridium, S. cupressi, cause of the widespread disease known as cypress canker, has previously been referred to as Lepteutypa cupressi. The type of Lepteutypa, L. fuckelii, is now placed in a distinct genus in the Amphisphaeriaceae (Jaklitsch et al. 2016), while the species previously regarded as L. cupressi belongs in Seiridium as S. cupressi in Sporocadaceae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Calosphaeriales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Use Calosphaeria Tul. &amp; C. Tul. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>1863 (S) rather than Calosphaeriophora Réblová et al. 2004 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The genus Calosphaeria, typified by C. princeps, includes 114 names while an asexual morph of C. pulchella was described in the monotypic genus Calosphaeriophora as Ca. pulchella (Réblová et al. 2004). Calosphaeria pulchella is a saprobic fungus occurring on various woody plants and has been recently isolated from wood of sweet cherry trees showing canker symptoms (Trouillas et al. 2010a, Berbegal et al. 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>If Calosphaeria princeps and C. pulchella are congeneric, then these generic names are synonyms as suggested by Réblová et al. (2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Based on priority, the number of species in the genus, and its widespread use, the generic name Calosphaeria is recommended for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Use Pleurostoma Tul. &amp; C. Tul. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>1863 (S) rather than Pleurostomophora Vijaykr. et al. 2004 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The genus Pleurostoma, typified by P. candollei, includes six names, two of which have been placed elsewhere. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>One species, P. ootheca, has an asexual morph described as Pleurostomophora ootheca, the type species of Pleurostomophora (Vijaykrishna et al. 2004). Réblová et al. (2015) explored the phylogeny of this group including one species of Pleurostoma and four species of Pleurostomophora, although the type species of Pleurostoma was not available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>While both sexual species are lignicolous, the asexual species were isolated from woody plants, soil or sewage (Schol-Schwarz 1970). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>They were also identified as etiological agents of subcutaneous phaeohyphomycosis (Meyer et al. 1975, Hironaga et al. 1989), and one asexual species of Pleurostoma, P. ochraceum, is known to cause human eumycetoma (Mhmoud et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Assuming that Pleurostoma candollei and P. ootheca are congeneric, these generic names are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Given that the name Pleurostoma has priority, has the greater number of species, and has been widely used, we recommend the use of Pleurostoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Based on these conclusions and recent molecular data, the three exclusively asexual Pleurostomophora species were transferred to Pleurostoma by Réblová et al. (2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Use Togniniella Réblová et al. 2004 (S) rather than Phaeocrella Réblová et al. 2004 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The monotypic genera Togniniella, typified by T. acerosa, and Phaeocrella, typified by P. acerosa, were described in the same article for the sexual and asexual morphs of the same species and thus are synonyms having equal priority (Réblová et al. 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Although an older epithet was discovered for T. acerosa (Réblová 2011), this was later rescinded (Réblová et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>We recommend the use of the generic name Togniniella. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Chaetosphaeriales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Use Chloridium Link 1809 (A) rather than Gonytrichum Nees &amp; T. Nees 1818 (A) or Melanopsammella Höhn.1920 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The type species of Chloridium, C. viride as C. virescens, has long been known to be a synonym of Chaetosphaeria vermicularioides (syn. Melanopsammella vermicularioides), a species that is congeneric with M. inaequalis, the type of Melanopsammella (Réblová &amp; Winka 2000, Fernández et al. 2006, Crous et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The type species of Gonytrichum, G. caesium, is the asexual morph of M. inaequalis (Hughes 1951), thus Chloridium, Gonytrichum and Melanopsammella are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Over 60 names have been placed in Chloridium, the most well-known of these three generic names. Chloridium was monographed by Gams &amp; Holubová-Jechová (1976), however, many of these names have been removed to other genera. Gonytrichum includes over 20 species while Melanopsammella consists of five species, two of which already have names in Chloridium (Réblová et al. 1999, Réblová 2000). Melanopsammella has been distinguished from Chaetosphaeria by several authors (Réblová &amp; Winka 2000, Fernández &amp; Huhndorf 2005, Fernández et al. 2006, Crous et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Given the widespread use of Chloridium and its priority, the generic name Chloridium is recommended for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>New combinations: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Chloridium caesium (Nees) Réblová &amp; Seifert, comb. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>MycoBank MB816825 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Gonytrichum caesium Nees, Nova Acta Phys.-Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Caes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Leop.-Carol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Cur. 9: 244 (1818). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Synonyms: Eriosphaeria inaequalis Grove, J. Bot., Lond. 24: 132 (1886). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Melanopsammella inaequalis (Grove) Höhn., Ann. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 17: 121 (1920). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Chloridium chloroconium (W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Gams &amp; Hol.-Jech.) Réblová &amp; Seifert, comb. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>MycoBank MB816826 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Chaetosphaeria chloroconia W. Gams &amp; Hol.-Jech., Stud. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 13: 86 (1976). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Synonyms: Melanopsammella chloroconia (W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Gams &amp; Hol.-Jech.) Réblová et al., Sydowia 51: 65 (1999). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Gonytrichum chlamydosporium G.L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Barron &amp; G.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Bhatt, Mycopath. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Mycol. appl. 32: 126 (1967). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Because the name Chloridium chlamydosporium (J.F.H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Beyma) S. Hughes 1958 already exists, and refers to a different taxon, the next older epithet for this species is taken up and placed in Chloridium. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Chloridium gonytrichii (F.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Fernández &amp; Huhndorf) Réblová &amp; Seifert, comb. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>MycoBank MB816827 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Melanopsammella gonytrichii F.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Fernández &amp; Huhndorf, Fungal Diversity 18: 42 (2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Crous et al. (2012) showed that this species is closely related to Chloridium virescens as Melanopsammella vermicularioides. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Use Menispora Pers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>(A) 1822 rather than Zignoëlla Sacc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>1878 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The genus Menispora is typified by M. glauca, which has a sexual morph referred to as Chaetosphaeria glauca (Holubová-Jechová 1973a), which is a synonym of the earlier name Zignoëlla ovoidea. The type of Zignoëlla is Z. pulviscula,which has an asexual morph known as Menispora caesia (Booth 1957, Constantinescu et al. 1995). Fernández et al. (2006) demonstrated that Zignoëlla is distinct from Chaetosphaeria based on C. innumera and that Z. pulviscula and Z. ovoidea are congeneric, thus Menispora and Zignoëlla are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Like Chaetosphaeria, Zignoëlla has been used as a repository for species that have a similar morphology, namely black non-stromatic ascomata with a papilla and hyaline, septate ascospores, but are phylogenetically diverse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Given the lack of characterization of Zignoëlla, the greater use of Menispora, and following the principle of priority, Menispora is recommended for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Use Menisporopsis S. Hughes 1952 (A) rather than Menisporopascus Matsush. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>2003 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The monotype species of Menisporopascus, M. kobensis, was described for the asexual morph Menisporopsis kobensis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Because M. kobensis is congeneric with the type species of Menisporopsis, M. theobromae, as indicated by Rodrigues de Cruz et al. (2014), Menisporopsis and Menisporopascus are synonyms. Menisporopsis includes 10 names, is widely known, and has priority, therefore, the use of Menisporopsis is recommended. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Use Sporoschisma Berk. &amp; Broome 1847 (A) rather than Melanochaeta E. Müll. et al. 1969 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The genus Sporoschisma, typified by S. mirabile, is considered the asexual morph of Melanochaeta aotearoae, while the type of Melanochaeta, M. hemipsila, is the sexual morph of S. saccardoi, now considered a synonym of S. hemipsila (Sivichai et al. 2000, Zelski et al. 2014a). Sporoschisma mirabile and S. hemipsila were shown to be congeneric (Fernández et al. 2006), thus Sporoschisma and Melanochaeta are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Of the five species in Melanochaeta, four have Sporoschisma asexual morphs (Sivichai et al. 2000, Mugambi &amp; Huhndorf 2008). Sporoschisma includes 23 names, some of which have been placed elsewhere. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>If Melanochaeta were used, many name changes would be required. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Based on priority and fewer number of name changes, we follow Zelski et al. (2014a) and recommend the use of Sporoschisma for this genus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>New combinations: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Sporoschisma daemonoropis (J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Fröhl. &amp; K.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Hyde) A.N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Mill., comb. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>MycoBank MB816828 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Melanochaeta daemonoropis J. Fröhl. &amp; K.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Hyde, Palm Microfungi: 235 (2000). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Sporoschisma taitense (Mugambi &amp; Huhndorf) A.N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Mill., comb. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>MycoBank MB816829 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Melanochaeta taitensis Mugambi &amp; Huhndorf, Sydowia 60: 263 (2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>A Sporoschisma asexual morph was noted to occur with this type specimen. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Use Stanjehughesia Subram. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>1992 (A) rather than Umbinosphaeria Réblová 1999 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Stanjehughesia hormiscioides, type of Stanjehughesia, was established with cultivation techniques as an asexual morph of Umbrinosphaeria caesariata, the monotype species of Umbrinosphaeria (Réblová 1999), therefore Stanjehughesia and Umbrinosphaeria are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>In exploring species of Sporidesmium, Shenoy et al. (2006) demonstrated the polyphyletic nature of Stanjehughesia; however, 15 species have been described in that genus and the name is well-known. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Given its priority, we recommend the use of Stanjehughesia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Coniochaetales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Use Coniochaeta (Sacc.) Cooke 1887 (S) rather than Lecythophora Nannf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>1934 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>The genus Coniochaeta, typified by C. ligniaria, was shown to be congeneric with Lecythophora, typified by L. lignicola (Weber et al. 2002, Damm et al. 2010, Khan et al. 2013, Perdomo et al. 2013). Coniochaeta is a well-known genus with almost 100 names while Lecythophora includes nine names, two of which are linked to species of Coniochaeta. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>These fungi are known as endophytes, pathogens of woody trees, saprobes in terrestrial and freshwater habitats (Raja et al. 2012) and, to a lesser degree, human pathogens (Damm et al. 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Both Khan et al. (2013) and Perdomo et al. (2013) include species of Lecythophora in a clade with the type species of Coniochaeta. Given the number of species, its widespread use, following the principle of priority, and in agreement with Khan et al. (2013), Coniochaeta is recommended for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Conioscyphales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Use Conioscypha Höhn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>1904 (A) rather than Conioscyphascus Réblová &amp; Seifert 2004 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>The genus Conioscypha, with C. lignicola as type species, includes 13 species from freshwater and terrestrial habitats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The genus Conioscyphascus, typified by Ca. varius, was originally established for fungi with Conioscypha asexual morphs (Réblová &amp; Seifert 2004a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The two sexual species, Ca. gracilis with C. gracilis as its asexual morph and Ca. varius with C. varia, were recently placed in Conioscypha (Zelski et al. 2014b, Réblová et al. 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Although C. lignicola and 10 other species of Conioscypha are known only in their asexual morph, using DNA sequence data and cultivation studies, the link between sexual and asexual morphs has been experimentally proven for C. peruviana (Zelski et al. 2014b) and C. varia (Réblová &amp; Seifert 2004a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Such a link has not yet been confirmed for the third species known to have a sexual morph, C. gracilis, however, conidia were observed on the substratum near ascomata (Réblová &amp; Seifert 2004a, Zelski et al. 2014b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The molecular data clearly show that Conioscypha and Conioscyphascus are congeneric (Réblová &amp; Seifert 2004a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Based on priority and the greater number of species, the name Conioscypha is recommended for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Cordanales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Use Cordana Preuss 1851 (A) rather than Pseudobotrytis Krzemien. &amp; Badura 1954 (A) or Porosphaerella E. Müll. &amp; Samuels 1982 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The type species of Cordana, C. pauciseptata, was linked to a sexual morph described as Porosphaerella cordanophora, type of Porosphaerella (Müller &amp; Samuels 1982), thus these generic names are synonyms. Cordana is a well-known asexual genus that includes 22 names while three species have been placed in Porosphaerella. Réblová and Seifert (2007) showed that P. borinquinensis and P. cordanophora are closely related despite the fact that P. borinquinensis has an asexual morph regarded as Pseudobotrytis terrestris which Hernández-Restrepo et al. (2014) recognized as Cordana terrestris including Porosphaerella borinquinensis as a synonym. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>They also considered the type species of Pseudobotrytis, P. fusca, to be a synonym of C. terrestris, thus this generic name with four species is also a synonym of Cordana. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Given its priority, fewer number of name changes required, and widespread use, we recommend the use of Cordana rather than Pseudobotrytis or Porosphaerella. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Coronophorales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Protect Chaetosphaerella E. Müll. &amp; C. Booth 1972 (S) over Oedemium Link 1824 (A) and rather than Veramycina Subram. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>1995 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The genus Chaetosphaerella, typified by C. phaeostroma, has an asexual morph regarded as Oedemium minus (Booth 1958, Réblová 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The type species of Oedemium, O. atrum as O. didymium, is the asexual morph of Chaetosphaerella fusca (Ellis 1971). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>These two species of Chaetosphaerella were shown to be congeneric (Mugambi &amp; Huhndorf 2010), thus Chaetosphaerella and Oedemium are synonyms. Veramycina elegans, the monotype species of Veramycina, was regarded as a later name for the asexual morph of C. phaeostroma (Réblová 1999), thus this generic name is also a synonym of Chaetosphaerella. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Because Veramycina has been rarely used, that name is not a contender for use, however, the decision of whether to use Oedemium or Chaetospharella is more difficult. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>The genus Oedemium was clarified and monographed including two species by Hughes &amp; Hennebert (1963) both of which have been linked with Chaetosphaerella. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Although more species have been described in Oedemium, some have been placed elsewhere and others remain obscure. Chaetosphaerella has been placed phylogenetically in Chaetosphaerellaceae, Coronophorales (Mugambi &amp; Huhndorf 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>In the past decade Chaetosphaerella appears in the literature much more frequently than Oedemium, thus we recommend Chaetosphaerella for protection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Glomerellales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Use Colletotrichum Corda 1837 (A) rather than Glomerella Spauld. &amp; Schrenk 1903 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The genus Colletotrichum, typified by C. lineola, is a large genus with 817 epithets (Index Fungorum 2016), many of which are considered plant pathogens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>The number of accepted species has varied over the decades with most species previously considered to be host-specific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Based on von Arx (1957) in which several hundred names were placed in synonymy with C. gloeosporioides, the number of species in Colletotrichum decreased to 11. Sutton (1980) included about 22 species in Colletotrichum for which he provided a key. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>With the use of molecular sequence data, the number of recognized species has increased with some species determined to be host-specific while others have a broad host range (Rojas et al. 2010, Damm et al. 2009, 2012, Weir et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The type species, Colletotrichum lineola, had long been considered to be a synonym of C. dematium but was recently recognized as a distinct species in the C. dematium species complex (Damm et al. 2009, Cannon et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, the sexual morphs of Colletotrichum were placed in the genus Glomerella, typified by G. cingulata, which has been considered the sexual morph of C. gloeosporioides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Recently this relationship has been questioned with C. gloeosporioides and G. cingulata regarded as distinct species in the C. gloeosporioides species complex (Weir et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Over 100 names have been described in Glomerella, many of which have names in Colletotrichum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Although considered different species, there is no question that Colletotrichum and Glomerella represent the same genus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Use of Colletotrichum over Glomerella is recommended for use for several reasons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Species of Colletotrichum are mainly associated with plants as endophytes and pathogens and have been thoroughly studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>In contrast, their sexual morphs regarded as Glomerella tend to occur on dead plant material and are less frequently encountered (Cannon et al. 2012, Maharachchikumbura et al. 2015). Colletotrichum is the older generic name and is well established in the plant pathological and plant breeder literature (Cannon et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Preference has been given to Colletotrichum by several groups working on this genus (Cannon et al. 2012, Maharachchikumbura et al. 2015) based on its widespread use, greater number of names, and priority. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Use Cylindrotrichum Bonord. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>1851 (A) rather than Reticulascus Réblová &amp; W. Gams 2011 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The type species of Cylindrotrichum, C. oligospermum, was shown to represent the asexual morph of Chaetosphaeria tulasneorum, the type species of Reticulascus (Réblová &amp; Gams 1999, Réblová et al. 2011a), thus the generic names Cylindrotrichum and Reticulascus are synonyms. Cylindrotrichum includes 23 names (Rambelli &amp; Onofri 1987) while Reticulascus includes only two names. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Between these two generic names, Cylindrotrichum is the most widely known. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Given its widespread use, priority, and greater number of names, we recommend the use of Cylindrotrichum rather than Reticulascus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Use Monilochaetes Halst. ex Harter 1916 (A) rather than Australiasca Sivan. &amp; Alcorn 2002 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>The type species of Monilochaetes, M. infuscans, was shown to be congeneric with Australiasca queenslandica, the type species of Australiasca (Réblová et al. 2011a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>The two species described in Australiasca have names in Monilochaetes, thus, if the older name Monilochaetes is used, no name changes are required. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>This generic name includes six species and has priority, thus Monilochaetes is recommended for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Use Plectosphaerella Kleb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>1929 (S) rather than Plectosporium M.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Palm et al. 1995 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>The genus Plectosporium, typified by P. tabacinum, was established for the asexual morph of species of Plectosphaerella of which the type species, P. cucumeris, is the name applied to the sexual morph of Plectosporium tabacinum (Palm et al. 1995), thus Plectosphaerella and Plectosporium are synonyms. Plectosphaerella cucumerinum is known as the cause of fruit and collar rot, and collapse of several crops including melons (Carlucci et al. 2012). Plectosphaerella includes 14 names while four species have been placed in Plectosporium. Carlucci et al. (2012) provided a molecular account of Plectosphaerella in the Plectosphaerellaceae and transferred species of Plectosporium to Plectosphaerella. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Given its priority, greater number of names, economic importance, and recent account of the genus, the use of Plectosphaerella is recommended. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Use Sporoschismopsis Hol.-Jech. &amp; Hennebert 1972 (A) rather than Porosphaerellopsis Samuels &amp; E. Müll. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>1982 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>The generic name Sporoschismopsis was introduced by Holubová-Jechová &amp; Hennebert (1972) with S. moravica as type species and it now includes eight names (Holubová-Jechová 1973b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>The generic name Porosphaerellopsis, typified by P. sporoschismophora (Samuels &amp; Müller 1978, Müller &amp; Samuels 1982), was established for the sexual morphs of Sporoschismopsis. Porosphaerellopsis sporoschismophora was transferred to Sporoschismopsis (Réblová 2014) while a second species, P. bipolaris described by Ranghoo et al. (2001), was excluded from the genus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Another sexual morph was experimentally proven for S. angustata (Réblová 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Based on DNA sequence data, the two asexual morphs, S. angustata and S. sporoschismophora, form a strongly supported monophyletic clade in the Reticulascaceae, Glomerellales. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Given that S. angustata, S. moravica, and S. sporoschismophora are congeneric, the generic names Sporoschismopsis and Porosphaerellopsis are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Based on priority and the greater number of species, Sporoschismopsis is recommended for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Halosphaeriales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Use Corollospora Werderm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>1922 (S) rather than Varicosporina Meyers &amp; Kohlm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>1965 (A) and Halosigmoidea Nakagiri et al. 2009 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Although the type species of Corollospora, C. maritima, does not appear to have an asexual morph in Varicosporina, a number of species of Corollospora are linked to varicosporina-like asexual morphs. Abdel-Wahab et al. (2009) showed that the type of Varicosporina, V. ramulosa, groups within Corollospora, thus Corollospora and Varicosporina are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>The type species of Halosigmoidea, H. luteola as Sigmoidea luteola, was shown by culture techniques to be the asexual morph of Corollospora luteola (Nakagiri &amp; Tokura, 1982). Jones et al. (2009) demonstrated that the three marine species recognized in Halosigmoidea grouped with Corollospora, thus Halosigmoidea is also a synonym of Corollospora. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Over 20 species are included in Corollospora while only three names have been described in Varicosporina, two of which have names in Corollospora, and only three names were included in Halosigmoidea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Given the number of names, widespread use, and priority, we recommend the use of Corollospora. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>New combinations: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Corollospora marina (Haythorn &amp; E.B.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Jones) E.B.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Jones, K.L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Pang &amp; Abdel-Wahab, comb. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>MycoBank MB816830 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Sigmoidea marina Haythorn &amp; E.B.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Jones, Trans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Brit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Soc. 74: 620 (1980). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Synonym: Halosigmoidea marina (Haythorn &amp; E.B.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Jones) Nakagiri et al., Bot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Mar. 52: 355 (2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Corollospora parvula (Zuccaro et al.) E.B.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Jones, K.L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Pang &amp; Abdel-Wahab, comb. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>MycoBank MB816831 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Halosigmoidea parvula Zuccaro et al., Bot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Mar. 52: 355 (2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Corollospora ramulosa (Meyers &amp; Kohlm.) E.B.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Jones &amp; Abdel-Wahab, comb. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>MycoBank MB816832 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Varicosporina ramulosa Meyers &amp; Kohlm., Canad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Bot. 43: 916 (1965). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Melanosporales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Use Melanospora Corda 1836 (S) rather than Gonatobotrys Corda 1839 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>The type species of Melanospora, M. zamiae, has been shown to be congeneric with M. damnosa (Cannon &amp; Hawksworth 1982), of which the type species of Gonatobotrys, G. simplex, is considered a synonym (Vakili 1989). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Given the widespread use of Melanospora, its priority, and the 120 names in Melanospora while Gonatobotrys includes only 32 names, Melanospora is recommended for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>New combination: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Melanospora simplex (Corda) D. Hawksw., comb. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>MycoBank MB816833 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Gonatobotrys simplex Corda, Prachtflora: 9 (1839). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Synonyms: Sphaeroderma damnosum Sacc. &amp; Berl., Riv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Patol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Veg. 4: 56 (1896) [“1895”]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Melanospora damnosa (Sacc.) Lindau, Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Pflanzenfam. 1 (1*): 353 (1897). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2k"><title><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Microascales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Use Knoxdaviesia M.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Wingf. et al. 1988 (A) rather than Gondwanamyces G.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Marais &amp; M.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Wingf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>1998 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Knoxdaviesia proteae, type of the genus Knoxdaviesia, was described as the asexual morph of Ceratocystiopsis proteae, a species that was later placed in the genus Gondwanamyces as the type species, thus Knoxdaviesia and Gondwanamyces are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Both generic names have been used about equally. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>In agreement with de Beer et al. (2013), the use of the oldest name, Knoxdaviesia, is recommended. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Use Sphaeronaemella P. Karst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>1884 (S) rather than Gabarnaudia Samson &amp; W. Gams 1974 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>The type species of Sphaeronaemella, S. helvellae, is congeneric with the type species of Gabarnaudia, G. betae, described as the asexual morph of S. fimicola (Samson 1974). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Confirmed by molecular data (Hausner &amp; Reid 2004), these generic names are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Five species of Gabarnaudia have been placed in Sphaeronaemella (De Beer et al. 2013), a genus with 30 species. Sphaeronaemella is most commonly used and has priority, thus we recommend the use of Sphaeronaemella. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2l"><title><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Phyllachorales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Use Diachora Müll. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Arg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>1893 (S) rather than Diachorella Höhn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>1918 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>The generic names Diachora, typified by D. onobrychidis, and Diachorella, typified by D. onobrychidis, are apparently based on the same type specimen, thus these names are synonyms. Diachora is considered a name for the sexual morph while Diachorella represents the asexual morph. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Both generic names include less than ten species. Müller (1986) and Cannon (1991) reviewed species in these genera including the type species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Because Diachora is more widely known and has priority, we recommend that name for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Use Ophiodothella (Henn.) Höhn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>1904 (S) rather than Acerviclypeata Hanlin 1990 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>The genus Ophiodothella, typified by O. atromaculans, now includes 26 species, which are obligate parasites of subtropical and tropical plants (Hanlin et al. 1992). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>An asexual morph of O. vaccinii, now O. angustissima, cause of flyspeck leafspot of Vaccinium arboretum in the southeastern United States, was described as the monotype species of Acerviclypeatus, A. poriformans (Hanlin 1990), thus Ophiodothella and Acerviclypeatus are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Not much is known about O. atromaculans but this species appears to be congeneric with O. angustissima (Hanlin &amp; Gonzáles 2013). Given the number of species and priority, we recommend the use of Ophiodothella. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Use Polystigma DC 1815 (S) rather than Polystigmina Sacc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>1884 (A) and Rhodoseptoria Naumov 1913 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>The generic names Polystigma, typified by P. rubrum, and Polystigmina, typified by P. rubrum, are based on the same basionym of their respective type species and, therefore, are synonyms for the sexual and asexual morphs. Cannon (1996) monographed Polystigma including five species on Prunus among others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>He also noted that the type species of the monotypic Rhodoseptoria was a synonym of Polystigma rubra, thus that generic name is also a synonym of Polystigma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Several species of Polystigma cause diseases such as red blotch of almonds caused by P. amygdalinum and red leaf spot of plum caused by P. rubrum (Habibi et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>All but two of the seven taxa placed in Polystigmina are synonyms of Polystigma rubra while Polystigma includes over 50 species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Given the greater number of species, its widespread use, economic importance, and priority, we recommend the use of Polystigma. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Use Pseudothiella Petr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>1928 (S) rather than Pseudothiopsella Petr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>1928 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>The monotypic generic names Pseudothiella, typified by P. hirtellae, and Pseudothiopsella, typified by P. hirtellae, were described at the same time for sexual and asexual morphs of the same species, thus they are synonyms with equal priority. Pseudothiella has been used slightly more often than Pseudothiopsella (Furlanetto &amp; Dianese 1998), therefore we recommend use of Pseudothiella. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2m"><title><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Pleurotheciales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Use Pleurothecium Höhn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>1919 (A) rather than Carpoligna F.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Fernández &amp; Huhndorf 1999 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>The genus Pleurothecium is typified by P. recurvatum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>A sexual morph is known for P. recurvatum for which the monotypic generic name Carpoligna, typified by C. pleurothecii, was introduced (Fernández et al. 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Of the eight species assigned to the genus Pleurothecium, only three have DNA sequence data. Pleurothecium recurvatum and P. semifecundum form a strongly supported monophyletic clade in the Pleurotheciales and represent the core of the genus (Réblová et al. 2016), while P. obovoideum (Arzanlou et al. 2007) is nested in the same order but within another clade. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Given its priority and greater number of species, Pleurothecium is recommended for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2n"><title><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Savoryellales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Use Canalisporium Nawawi &amp; Kuthub. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>1989 (A) rather than Ascothailandia Sri-indr. et al. 2010 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>The genus Canalisporium, typified by C. caribense, includes 12 species (Nawawi &amp; Kuthubutheen 1989). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>A sexual morph was described for C. grenadoideum and linked to the monotypic genus Ascothailandia, typified by A. grenadoidea (Sri-indrasutdhi et al. 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>The link between sexual and asexual morphs of this species was confirmed experimentally in axenic culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Six species of Canalisporium, including the type species, were the subject of phylogenetic analysis based on DNA sequence data of three nuclear loci by Sri-indrasutdhi et al. (2010) who confirmed that Ascothailandia and Canalisporium are congeneric. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Based on priority and the greater number of species, the generic name Canalisporium is recommended for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2o"><title><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>Sordariales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Use Chaetomium Kunze 1817 (S) rather than Trichocladium Harz 1871 (A), Botryotrichum Sacc. &amp; Marchal 1885 (A), or Humicola Traaen 1914 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Chaetomium, typified by C. globosum, is a well-known genus of cellulose-decomposing fungi some of which cause diseases of humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>The sexual morph of Botryotrichum piluliferum, type of the asexual genus Botryotrichum, was described as Chaetomium piluliferum (Daniels 1961). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Later this species was confirmed to be congeneric with C. globosum (Untereiner et al. 2001, Nonaka et al. 2012), thus Chaetomium and Botryotrichum are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Although sexual states have not been discovered for the type of Humicola, H. fuscoatra or related species such as the common H. grisea, nuc28S rDNA sequences place these species within the present concept of Chaetomium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>The type of Trichocladium, T. asperum, also lacks a sexual morph and occurs in the same clade (Hambleton et al. 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Over 500 names have been described in Chaetomium. Botryotrichum currently includes eight species. Humicola and Trichocladium each include about 20 species, but both are phylogenetically heterogeneous and most species belong to different clades. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Given its extensive use and economic importance, its priority, and the greater number of species, we recommend the use of Chaetomium. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Use Lasiosphaeris Clem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>1909 (S) rather than Lasiadelphia Réblová &amp; W. Gams 2011 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>The genus Lasiosphaeris was described by Clements (1909) with L. hispida as its type species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>The name was reestablished by Miller &amp; Huhndorf (2004) for species segregated from Lasiosphaeria based on nuc28S rDNA sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Two species were accepted in the genus, L. hispida and L. hirsuta. Gams &amp; Holubová-Jechová (1976) introduced Phialophora sect. Catenulatae, typified by the dematiaceous species Phialophora lasiosphaeriae, the asexual morph experimentally proven for L. hispida (as L. hirsuta, Gams &amp; Holubová-Jechová 1976, Gams 2000). Réblová et al. (2011b) desribed the generic name Lasiadelphia with L. lasiosphaeriae as the type species for the asexual morph of Lasiosphaeris hispida. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the type species of Lasiosphaeris and Lasiadelphia are morphs of the same species and the generic names are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Based on priority and the greater number of species, the generic name Lasiosphaeris should be used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Use Mammaria Rabenh. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>1854 (A) rather than Pseudocercophora Subram. &amp; Sekar 1986 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>The genus Mammaria, typified by M. echinobotryoides, includes two names while the monotypic genus Pseudocercophora, typified by P. ingoldii, was described for the sexual morph of M. echinobotryoides, thus these generic names are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>If the principle of priority is followed, no names changes are required, thus, the use of Mammaria is recommended. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>Use Neurospora Shear &amp; B.O. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Dodge 1927 (S) rather than Chrysonilia Arx 1981 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>The genus Neurospora, typified by N. sitophila, includes the well-known model organism, N. crassa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>The asexual morph of the type species was described in Chrysonilia with C. sitophila as the type species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>There is no question that Neurospora and Chrysonilia are generic synonyms (von Arx 1981). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>At present Neurospora includes 57 names while only three names have been placed in Chrysonilia, all of which also have names in Neurospora. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Given its priority, the number of species, and its widespread use, it is recommended that Neurospora be used rather than Chrysonilia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Use Stromatographium Henn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>1907 (A) rather than Fluviostroma Samuels &amp; E. Müll. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>1980 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>The genus Stromatographium, typified by S. stromaticum, is the asexual state of Fluviostroma wrightii, monotype species of Fluviostroma (Samuels &amp; Müller 1980). Seifert (1987) clarified the confusion between Stromatographium and Stromatostilbella and showed that the asexual morph of F. wrightii belongs in Stromatographium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Given its greater use and priority, we recommend the use of Stromatographium. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2p"><title><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Togniniales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Protect Phaeoacremonium W. Gams 1996 (A) over Togninia Berl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>1900 (S) and Romellia Berl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>1900 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>The genus Phaeoacremonium was established for P. parasiticum, first described causing phaeohyphomycosis in humans, but also causing wilts in tropical trees and an economically important disease of grapevine known as esca disease (Hawksworth et al. 1976, Crous et al. 1996). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Once this genus was described, a number of species were discovered and placed in Phaeoacremonium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Based on phylogenetic analysis and mating studies, sexual morphs were found for these species in Togninia, formerly attributed to Calosphaeriales (Mostert et al. 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>Species of Phaeoacremonium are known as vascular plant pathogens such as esca and Petri disease of grapevine as well as human pathogens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>Two monographic accounts of Phaeoacremonium have been published (Mostert et al. 2006, Réblová et al. 2015). Gramaje et al. (2015) formally proposed to protect the name Phaeoacremonium against Togninia because although Togninia has 26 epithets, half have not been reported since their description, and only nine species have been experimentally linked with Phaeoacremonium. Phaeoacremonium includes 46 species of which all are known from culture and their DNA data are available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>Also Phaeoacremonium is favoured by plant pathologists and medical mycologists and is well established in the literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>All required new combinations were made in Gramaje et al. (2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>The type species of Romellia, R. vibratilis, was sequenced and placed in Togninia by Réblová &amp; Mostert (2007) and recently moved to Phaeoacremonium by Gramaje et al. (2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>Three of the four species of Romellia have since been placed elsewhere. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>Thus, because it is widely used and has the greatest number of species, we recommend the protection of Phaeoacremonium over Togninia and Romellia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2q"><title><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Torpedosporales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>Use Juncigena Kohlm. et al. 1997 (S) rather than Moheitospora Abdel-Wahab et al. 2010 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>The monotypic genus Juncigena is typified by J. adarca for which an asexual morph was described as Cirrenalia adarca (Kohlmeyer et al. 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>Later the asexual species was placed in the genus Moheitospora as M. adarca along with the type species, M. fruticosae (Abdel-Wahab et al. 2010), thus Juncigena and Moheitospora are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>Although one name change would be required, Juncigena has priority and has greater use in the literature, thus it is recommended that Juncigena be used. Schoch et al. (2007) showed that this genus belongs in Hypocreomycetidae and later Jones et al. (2015) placed it in Juncigenaceae, Torpedosporales. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>New combination: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Juncigena fruticosae (Abdel-Wahab et al.) A.N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Mill. &amp; Shearer, comb. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>MycoBank MB816834 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Moheitospora fruticosae Abdel-Wahab et al., Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Progr. 9: 551 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>Use Torpedospora Meyers 1957 (S) rather than Glomerulispora Abdel-Wahab &amp; Nagah. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>2010 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>The monotype species of Glomerulispora, G. mangrovei, groups with the two species of Torpedospora such that these generic names are considered synonyms (Abdel-Wahab et al. 2010, Jones et al. 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>These species are marine fungi found on driftwood throughout the world. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>Given the widespread use of Torpedospora and its priority, use of Torpedospora is recommended. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>New combination: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>Torpedospora mangrovei (Abdel-Wahab &amp; Nagah.) E.B.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>Jones &amp; Abdel-Wahab, comb. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>MycoBank MB816835 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Glomerulispora mangrovei Abdel-Wahab &amp; Nagah., Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>Progr. 9: 553 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2r"><title><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>Xylariales </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>Use Arthrinium Kunze 1817 (A) rather than Apiospora Sacc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>1875 (S), Pteroconium Sacc. ex Grove 1914 (A), and Scyphospora L.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>Kantsch 1928 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>Species in the genus Arthrinium are widespread and commonly encountered as saprobes and secondary invaders especially on monocotyledonous plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>The common species, A. arundinis, is the name typified by the sexual morph of the type species of Apiospora, A. montagnei (Müller &amp; Arx 1962). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>Less is known about the type species of Arthrinium, A. caricicola, but this species is assumed to be congeneric with A. arundinis (Crous &amp; Groenewald 2013), although they were unable to find material to include in their molecular phylogeny. Crous &amp; Groenewald (2013) also showed that Pteroconium asteroides, type of Pteroconium, is a synonym of Arthrinium. Samuels et al. (1981) suggested that Scyphospora phyllostachydis was the asexual morph of Apiospora tintinnabula, now Arthrinium hysterinum, thus Scyphospora is a synonym of Arthrinium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>In agreement with both Crous &amp; Groenewald (2013) and Senanayake et al. (2015), Arthrinium has priority and is the most widely used of these generic names, thus use of Arthrinium is recommended. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>Although Hughes (1958) followed by Ellis (1965), Samuels et al. (1981) and Crous &amp; Groenewald (2013) suggested that Cordella is a synonym of Arthrinium, this is based on the assumption that C. coniosporioides is the type species. Cordella was described with two species without indicating a type. Clements &amp; Shear (1931) were the first to select a type species for Cordella and they list C. spinulosa, a species that Hughes (1958) placed in Melanographium, thus Cordella is not a synonym of Arthrinium. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>Based on the molecular sequence data provided by Crous &amp; Groenewald (2013), Apiospora sinensis is placed in Arthrinium. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>New combination: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>Arthrinium sinense (K.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>Hyde et al.) Crous &amp; J.Z. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>Groenew., comb. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>MycoBank MB816836 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Apiospora sinensis K.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>Hyde et al., Sydowia 50: 27 (1998). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>In addition a nomenclator is provided for Arthrinium hysterinum because of confusion about the correct name for this species and its numerous synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>Previously recognized in Apiospora by Tang et al. (2007), Kirk (1986) and Sivanesan (1983), Crous &amp; Groenewald (2013) and Senanayake et al. (2015) included Apiospora bambusae, A. setosa and A. tintinnabula as synonyms within the genus Arthrinium. The correct name for this species is Arthrinium hysterinum with the synonyms listed below: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>Arthrinium hysterinum (Sacc.) P.M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>Kirk, Trans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>Brit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>Soc. 86: 409 (1986). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Melanconium hysterinum Sacc., Bolm Soc. broteriana, Coimbra, sér. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>1 11: 21 (1893). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>Synonyms: Scyphospora hysterina (Sacc.) Sivan., Trans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>Brit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>Soc. 81: 331 (1983). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>Melanconium bambusae Turconi, Atti Ist. bot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>Univ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>Pavia, sér.2 16: 251 (1916). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>Scirrhia bambusae Turconi, Atti Ist. bot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>Univ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>Pavia, sér. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>2 16: 531 (1916). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>Scirrhodothis bambusae (Turconi) Trotter, in Saccardo, Syll. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>Fung. 24: 611 (1926). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>Placostroma bambusae (Turconi) R. Sprague, Diseases Cereals Grasses N. Amer.: 121 (1950). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>Apiospora bambusae (Turconi) Sivan., Trans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>Brit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>Soc. 81: 331 (1983). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>Scyphospora phyllostachydis L.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>Kantsch., Bolêz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>Rast. 17: 88 (1928). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>Cordella johnstonii M.B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>Ellis, Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>Pap. 103: 31 (1965). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>Apiospora setosa Samuels et al., New Zealand J. Bot. 19: 142 (1981). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>Apiospora tintinnabula Samuels et al., New Zealand J. Bot. 19: 142 (1981). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>Use Collodiscula I. Hino &amp; Katum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>1955 (S) rather than Acanthodochium Samuels et al. 1987 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>The genus Collodiscula, typified by C. japonica, was linked to Acanthodochium collodisculae, type of Acanthodochium, by Samuels et al. (1987), who considered these names morphs of the same species, thus these generic names are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>Three species have been added to Collodiscula (Li et al. 2015a, b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>Given that this generic name has priority and includes four species, the use of Collodiscula is recommended. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>Use Daldinia Ces. &amp; De Not. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>1863 (S) rather than Annellosporium M.L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>Davey 2010 (A) or Versiomyces Whalley &amp; Watling 1989 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>The genus Daldinia, typified by D. concentrica, has recently been monographed by Stadler et al. (2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>They showed that the monotype species of Annellosporium, A. nemorosa, belongs in Daldinia as D. nemorosa, thus Daldinia and Annellosporium are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>They also showed that the monotype species of Versiomyces, V. cahuchucosus, belongs in Daldinia as D. cahuchucosa, thus Versiomyces is a synonym of Daldinia. Daldinia is a well-known genus with many species and has priority, thus it is recommended for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>Protect Diatrype Fr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>1849 (S) over Libertella Desm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>1830 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>The genus Diatrype, typified by D. disciformis, includes over 500 names (Index Fungorum 2016), some of which cause canker diseases of hardwoods such as D. stigma associated with diseased grapevines (Rolshausen et al. 2006). Libertella betulina, type of the genus Libertella, is known to be the asexual morph of Diatrype stigma (Grove 1937, Kutorga et al. 2006) and D. disciformis has an asexual morph described as L. disciformis. Trouillas et al. (2010b) showed that D. disciformis and D. stigma are congeneric, thus Diatrype and Libertella are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>Because Diatrype is widely known, has a greater number of species, and includes important plant pathogenic fungi, Diatrype is recommended for protection over Libertella. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>Use Hypocreodendron Henn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>1897 (A) rather than Discoxylaria J.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>Lindq. &amp; J.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>Wright 1964 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>Hypocreodendron is a monotypic genus based upon H. sanguineum for which Lindqvist &amp; Wright (1964) introduced the monotypic genus Discoxylaria, typified by D. myrmecophila, as the sexual morph. Rogers et al. (1995) observed a specimen of D. myrmecophila that bore both conidial and mature perithecial morphs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>They compared their collection with the holotype specimen and obtained the conidial morph in culture initiated from ascospores to demonstrate that these were alternate morphs of the same species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>Thus, Hypocreodendron and Discoxylaria are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>In agreement with Stadler et al. (2013), Maharachchikumbura et al. (2015), and priority, we recommend the use of Hypocreodendron. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>Use Hypoxylon Bull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>1791 (S) rather than Nodulisporium Preuss 1849 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>The genus Hypoxylon, typified by H. fragiforme, is a well-known group of stromatic ascomycetes on rotting wood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>Although a number of segregated genera are now recognized such as Annulohypoxylon, Biscogniauxia, and Nemania, many species still remain within Hypoxylon sensu stricto (Hsieh et al. 2005). Von Arx (1982), fide Deighton (1985), demonstrated the relationship of the asexual morph Nodulisporium ochraceum, type of Nodulisporium, to Hypoxylon fragiforme, thus these generic names are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>Other species of Nodulisporium have been placed in various genera suggesting the artificial circumscription of this genus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain>Given the widespread use of Hypoxylon, the number of names, and priority, the use of Hypoxylon is recommended. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="550" pm="."><plain>Use Microdochium Syd. &amp; P. Syd. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="552" pm="."><plain>1924 (A) rather than Monographella Petr. later in 1924 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="553" pm="."><plain>The genus Microdochium, typified by M. phragmitis, was published a few months later than Monographella, typified by M. divergens, now regarded as a synonym of Microdochium nivale. Hernández-Restrepo et al. (2016) recognized the synonym of Microdochium and Monographella and considered Microdochium to be the best generic name to use for these fungi because Microdochium included more species and was more widely known than Monographella. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="554" pm="."><plain>They added six species to the 31 names in the genus Microdochium while Monographella includes only 15 names. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="555" pm="."><plain>In addition they epitypified the type of Microdochium, M. phragmitis, a species that had been shown to represent two sympatric species (Ernst et al. 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="557" pm="."><plain>Thus, in agreement with Hernández-Restrepo et al. (2016), we recommend the protection of Microdochium over Monographella. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="558" pm="."><plain>Use Nemania Gray 1821 (S) rather than Geniculosporium Chesters &amp; Greenh. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="559" pm="."><plain>1964 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="560" pm="."><plain>An asexual morph of Nemania serpens, type species of Nemania, was described as Geniculosporium serpens, type of Geniculosporium (Chesters &amp; Greenhalgh 1964), thus the generic names Nemania and Geniculosporium are synonyms. Nemania includes over 30 names while only four names have been placed in Geniculosporium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="561" pm="."><plain>In addition, Nemania is well-known and has priority, thus we recommend the use of Nemania. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="562" pm="."><plain>Use Rosellinia De Not. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="563" pm="."><plain>1844 (S) rather than Dematophora R. Hartig 1883 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="565" pm="."><plain>The genus Rosellinia, typified by R. aquila, is a well-known genus that has recently been monographed (Petrini 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="566" pm="."><plain>A number of plant pathogenic species are included in Rosellinia such as R. bunodes causing black root rot of tropical woody plants and R. thelena causing root collar of hardwoods. Dematophora necatrix, type of Dematophora, is considered the asexual morph of R. necatrix, cause of white root rot (Petrini 2013), thus Rosellinia and Dematophora are synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="567" pm="."><plain>The only other species of Dematophora, D. glomerata, is considered the asexual morph of R. glomerata. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="568" pm="."><plain>Given the widespread use of Rosellinia, the recent monographic account, its importance as a plant pathogen, and priority, we recommend the use of Rosellinia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="569" pm="."><plain>Use Virgaria Nees 1816 (A) rather than Ascovirgaria J.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="570" pm="."><plain>Rogers &amp; Y.-M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="571" pm="."><plain>Ju 2002 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="572" pm="."><plain>The monotypic genus Ascovirgaria, typified by A. occulta, was described for the sexual morph of the type species of Virgaria, V. nigra, by Rogers &amp; Ju (2002), thus these generic names are synonyms. Nonaka et al. (2013) demonstrated that A. occulta was a synonym of V. nigra and that Virgaria was distinct from other genera in the Xylariaceae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="573" pm="."><plain>Although some names have been transferred to other genera, Virgaria still includes 10 names and is more commonly used than Ascovirgaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="574" pm="."><plain>Given its priority and widespread use, Virgaria is recommended for use over Ascovirgaria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="575" pm="."><plain>Use Xylaria Hill ex Schrank 1789 (S) rather than Moelleroclavus Henn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="576" pm="."><plain>1902 (A), Xylocoremium J.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="577" pm="."><plain>Rogers 1984 (A), Arthroxylaria Seifert &amp; W. Gams 2002 (A) or Geniculisynnema Okane &amp; Nakagiri 2007 (A) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="579" pm="."><plain>Xylaria is a well-known genus with many species such as Xylaria polymorpha, commonly known as dead man’s fingers, also said to cause root rot of urban trees (Proffer 1988). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="580" pm="."><plain>The asexual morphs of species of Xylaria have been described in four genera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="581" pm="."><plain>The monotype species of Moelleroclavus, M. penicillioides, has a sexual morph described as Xylaria moelleroclavus (Rogers et al. 1997) and Xylocoremium flabelliforme, monotype species of Xylocoremium, is the asexual morph of Xylaria cubensis (Rogers 1984), now known to be X. flabelliformis (Ju et al. 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="582" pm="."><plain>Both Arthroxylaria and Geniculisynnema are monotypic genera proposed for asexual morphs not yet connected to a sexual morph but clearly within Xylaria based on rDNA sequences (Seifert et al. 2002, Okane &amp; Nakagiri 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="583" pm="."><plain>The type species of Arthroxylaria, A. elegans, is herein placed in Xylaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="584" pm="."><plain>Although Stadler et al. (2013) connected Geniculisynnema with Nemania, a BLAST search with the ITS sequence of G. termiticola (AB274813), type species of Geniculisynnema, showed top matches with Xylaria species associated with termite nests.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="585" pm="."><plain>These four generic names are now considered synonyms of Xylaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="586" pm="."><plain>Given its widespread use, the number of species, and priority, Xylaria is recommended for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="587" pm="."><plain>New combinations: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="588" pm="."><plain>Xylaria benjaminii Seifert &amp; W. Gams, nom. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="590" pm="."><plain>MycoBank MB816839 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="591" pm="."><plain>Replaced name: Arthroxylaria elegans Seifert &amp; W. Gams, Czech Mycol. 53: 209 (2002). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="593" pm="."><plain>Non Xylaria elegans Syd. &amp; P. Syd., Annls mycol. 5: 357 (1907). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="595" pm="."><plain>Xylaria penicilliopsis (Henn.) Y.-M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="596" pm="."><plain>Ju, comb. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="597" pm="."><plain>MycoBank MB816837 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="598" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Moelleroclavus penicilliopsis Henn., Hedwigia 41: 15 (1902). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="599" pm="."><plain>Synonym: Xylaria moelleroclavus J.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="600" pm="."><plain>Rogers et al., Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="601" pm="."><plain>Res. 101: 345 (1997). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="602" pm="."><plain>Xylaria termiticola (Okane &amp; Nakagiri) Y.-M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="603" pm="."><plain>Ju, comb. nov. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="604" pm="."><plain>MycoBank MB816838 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="605" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Geniculisynnema termiticola Okane &amp; Nakagiri, Mycoscience 48: 245 (2007). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2s"><title><text><SENT sid="606" pm="."><plain>Sordariomycetidae incertae sedis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="607" pm="."><plain>Use Brachysporium Sacc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="608" pm="."><plain>1886 (A) rather than Cryptadelphia Réblová &amp; Seifert 2004 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="609" pm="."><plain>Brachysporium, typified by B. obovatum, is a widespread and well-established asexual genus that includes 113 species and varieties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="610" pm="."><plain>The genus Cryptadelphia, typified by C. groenendalensis, was introduced for the sexual morphs of six species of Brachysporium (Réblová &amp; Seifert 2004b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="611" pm="."><plain>The link between the sexual and asexual morphs was experimentally proven only for B. nigrum, which is the asexual morph of C. groenendalensis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="612" pm="."><plain>The axenic cultures of B. obovatum and B. polyseptatum derived from ascospores yielded only sterile mycelium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="613" pm="."><plain>Recently, C. fusiformis was described with its asexual morph regarded as B. fusiformis (Markovskaja &amp; Treigiené 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="614" pm="."><plain>Based on molecular sequence data, B. nigrum and B. polyseptatum form a strongly supported monophyletic clade (Réblová &amp; Seifert 2004b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="615" pm="."><plain>If B. obovatum is congeneric with B. nigrum, then the generic names Brachysporium and Cryptadelphia should be treated as synonyms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="616" pm="."><plain>Based on priority and the greater number of species, Brachysporium is recommended for use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="617" pm="."><plain>Use Nigrospora Zimm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="618" pm="."><plain>1902 (A) rather than Khuskia H.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="619" pm="."><plain>Huds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="620" pm="."><plain>1963 (S) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="621" pm="."><plain>The monotype species of Khuskia, K. oryzae, was described as the sexual morph of Nigrospora oryzae, a well-known species of Nigrospora, by Hudson (1963). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="622" pm="."><plain>He also considered N. oryzae and N. panici, the type species of Nigrospora, to be congeneric, thus Nigrospora and Khuskia are synonyms. Nigrospora oryzae is reported from a variety of hosts including marine sponges (Ding et al. 2011) and as endophytes of plants (Peršoh et al. 2010) as well as causing plant diseases (Moshrefi-Zarandi et al. 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="625" pm="."><plain>Given that Nigrospora has priority, includes fifteen names, and is more widely known than Khuskia, the use of Nigrospora is recommended. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><text><SENT sid="626" pm="."><plain>Abdel-WahabMANagahamaTAbdel-AzizFA (2009) Two new Corollospora species and one new anamorph based on morphological and molecular data. Mycoscience 50: 147–155. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R2"><text><SENT sid="627" pm="."><plain>Abdel-WahabMAPangKLNagahamaTAbdel-AzizFAJonesEBG (2010) Phylogenetic evaluation of anamorphic species of Cirrenalia and Cumulospora with the description of eight new genera and four new species. Mycological Progress 9: 537–558. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R3"><text><SENT sid="628" pm="."><plain>ArxJA von (1957) Die Arten der Gattung Colletotrichum Cda. Phytopathologische Zeitschrift 29: 413–468. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R4"><text><SENT sid="629" pm="."><plain>ArxJA von (1981) On Monilia sitophila and some families of Ascomycetes. Sydowia 34: 13–29. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R5"><text><SENT sid="630" pm="."><plain>ArxJA von (1982) The genus Dicyma, its synonyms and related fungi. Proceedings, Koninklijke Nederlandse Akademie van Wetenschappen C 85: 21–28. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R6"><text><SENT sid="631" pm="."><plain>ArzanlouMGroenewaldJZGamsWBraunUShinHD et al. (2007) Phylogenetic and morphotaxonomic revision of Ramichloridium and allied genera. Studies of Mycology 58: 57–93. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R7"><text><SENT sid="632" pm="."><plain>BarrME (1975) Pestalosphaeria, a new genus in the Amphisphaeriaceae. Mycologia 67: 187–194. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R8"><text><SENT sid="633" pm="."><plain>BerbegalMGarcia-JimenezJArmengolJ (2014) First report of Calosphaeria pulchella causing canker and branch dieback of sweet cherry trees in Spain. Plant Disease 98: 1008. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R9"><text><SENT sid="634" pm="."><plain>BoothC (1957) Studies of pyrenomycetes: I. Four species of Chaetosphaeria, two with Catenularia conidia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="636" pm="."><plain>II. Melanopsamma pomiformis and its Stachybotrys conidia. Mycological Papers 68: 1–27. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R10"><text><SENT sid="637" pm="."><plain>BoothC (1958) The genera Chaetosphaeria and Thaxteria in Britain. Naturalist 1958: 83–90. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R11"><text><SENT sid="638" pm="."><plain>BraunU (2013) (2210 – 2232) Proposals to conserve the teleomorph-typified name Blumeria against the anamorph-typified name Oidium and twenty-two teleomorph-typified powdery mildew species names against competing anamorph-typified names (Ascomycota : Erysiphaceae). Taxon 62: 1328–1331. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R12"><text><SENT sid="639" pm="."><plain>BrockmannI (1976) Untersuchungen ueber die Gattung Discostroma Clements (Ascomycetes). Sydowia 28: 275–338. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R13"><text><SENT sid="640" pm="."><plain>CannonPF (1991) A revision of Phyllachora and some similar genera on the host family Leguminosae. Mycological Papers 163: 1–302. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R14"><text><SENT sid="641" pm="."><plain>CannonPF (1996) Systematics and diversity of the Phyllachoraceae associated with Rosaceae, with a monograph of Polystigma. Mycological Research 100: 1409–1427. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R15"><text><SENT sid="642" pm="."><plain>CannonPFDammUJohnstonPRWeirBS (2012) Colletotrichum–current status and future directions. Studies in Mycology 73: 181–213.23136460 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R16"><text><SENT sid="643" pm="."><plain>CannonPFHawksworthDL (1982) A re-evaluation of Melanospora Corda and similar Pyrenomycetes, with a revision of the British species. Botanical Journal of the Linnean Society 84: 115–160. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R17"><text><SENT sid="644" pm="."><plain>CarlucciARaimondoMLSantosJPhillipsAJL (2012) Plectosphaerella species associated with root and collar rots of horticultural crops in southern Italy. Persoonia 28: 34–48.23105152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R18"><text><SENT sid="645" pm="."><plain>ChestersCGCGreenhalghGN (1964) Geniculosporium serpens gen. et sp. nov., the imperfect state of Hypoxylon serpens. Transactions of the British Mycological Society 47: 393–401. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R19"><text><SENT sid="646" pm="."><plain>ClementsFE (1909) The Genera of Fungi. Minneapolis: H.W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="647" pm="."><plain>Wilson. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R20"><text><SENT sid="648" pm="."><plain>ClementsFEShearC (1931) The Genera of Fungi. New York: H. W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="650" pm="."><plain>Wilson. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R21"><text><SENT sid="651" pm="."><plain>ConstantinescuOHolmKHolmL (1995) Teleomorph-anamorph connections in ascomycetes: the anamorphs of three species of Chaetosphaeria. Mycological Research 99: 585–592. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R22"><text><SENT sid="652" pm="."><plain>CrousPWGamsWWingfieldMJvan WykPS (1996) Phaeoacremonium gen. nov. associated with wilt and decline diseases of woody hosts and human infections. Mycologia 88: 786–796. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R23"><text><SENT sid="653" pm="."><plain>CrousPWGroenewaldJZ (2013) A phylogenetic re-evaluation of Arthrinium. IMA Fungus 4: 133–154.23898419 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R24"><text><SENT sid="654" pm="."><plain>CrousPWVerkleyGJMChristensenMCastaneda-RuizRFGroenewaldJZ (2012) How important are conidial appendages? Persoonia 28: 126–137.23105158 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R25"><text><SENT sid="655" pm="."><plain>DammUCannonPFWoudenbergJHCCrousPW (2012) The Colletotrichum acutatum species complex. Studies in Mycology 73: 37–113.23136458 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R26"><text><SENT sid="656" pm="."><plain>DammUFouriePHCrousPW (2010) Coniochaeta (Lecythophora), Collophora gen. nov. and Phaeomoniella species associated with wood necroses of Prunus trees. Persoonia 24: 60–80.20664761 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R27"><text><SENT sid="657" pm="."><plain>DammUWoudenbergJHCCannonPFCrousPW (2009) Colletotrichum species with curved conidia from herbaceous hosts. Fungal Diversity 39: 45–87. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R28"><text><SENT sid="658" pm="."><plain>DanielH-MLachanceM-AKurtzmanCP (2014) On the reclassification of species assigned to Candida and other ascomycetous yeast genera based on phylogenetic circumscription. Antonie van Leeuwenhoek 10: 67–84.24748333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R29"><text><SENT sid="659" pm="."><plain>DanielsJ (1961) Chaetomium piluliferum sp. nov., the perfect state of Botryotrichum piluliferum. Transactions of the British Mycological Society 44: 79–86. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R30"><text><SENT sid="660" pm="."><plain>de BeerZWSeifertKAWingfieldMJ (2013) A nomenclator for ophiostomatoid genera and species in the Ophiostomatales and Microascales. CBS Biodiversity Series 12: 245–322. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R31"><text><SENT sid="661" pm="."><plain>DeightonFC (1985) Some species of Nodulisporium. Transactions of the British Mycological Society 85: 391–395. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R32"><text><SENT sid="662" pm="."><plain>DingBYinYZhangFLiZ (2011) Recovery and phylogenetic diversity of culturable fungi associated with marine sponges Clathrina luteoculcitella and Holoxea sp. in the South China Sea. Marine Biotechnology 13: 713–721.21088979 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R33"><text><SENT sid="663" pm="."><plain>EllisMB (1965) Dematiaceous Hyphomycetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="664" pm="."><plain>VI. Mycological Papers 103: 1–46. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R34"><text><SENT sid="665" pm="."><plain>EllisMB (1971) Dematiaceous Hyphomycetes. Kew: Commonwealth Mycological Institute. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R35"><text><SENT sid="666" pm="."><plain>ErnstMNeubertKMendgenKWierselSGR (2011) Niche differentiation of two sympatric species of Microdochium colonizing the roots of common reed, M. phragmitis vs. M. bolleyi BMC Microbiology 11: 242–255.22032611 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R36"><text><SENT sid="667" pm="."><plain>FernándezFAHuhndorfSM (2005) New species of Chaetosphaeria, Melanopsammella and Tainosphaeria gen. nov. from the Americas. Fungal Diversity 18: 15–57. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R37"><text><SENT sid="668" pm="."><plain>FernándezFALutzoniFMHuhndorfSM (1999) Teleomorph-anamorph connections: the new pyrenomycetous genus Carpoligna and its Pleurothecium anamorph. Mycologia 91: 251–262. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R38"><text><SENT sid="669" pm="."><plain>FernándezFAMillerANHuhndorfSMLutzoniFMZollerS (2006) Systematics of the genus Chaetosphaeria and its allied genera: morphological and phylogenetic diversity in north temperate and neotropical taxa. Mycologia 98: 121–130.16800310 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R39"><text><SENT sid="670" pm="."><plain>FurlanettoCDianeseJC (1998) Some coelomycetes from Central Brazil. Mycological Research 102: 19–29. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R40"><text><SENT sid="671" pm="."><plain>GamsW (2000). Phialophora and some similar morphologically little-differentiated anamorphs of divergent ascomycetes. Studies in Mycology 45: 187–199. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R41"><text><SENT sid="672" pm="."><plain>GamsWHolubová-JechováV (1976) Chloridium and some other dematiaceous hyphomycetes growing on decaying wood. Studies in Mycology 13: 1–99. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R42"><text><SENT sid="673" pm="."><plain>GramajeDMostertLGroenewaldJZCrousPW (2015) Phaeoacremonium: from esca disease to phaeohyphomycosis. Fungal Biology 119: 759–783.26321726 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R43"><text><SENT sid="674" pm="."><plain>GroveWB (1937) British Stem and Leaf-Fungi (Coelomycetes). Vol. 2 Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R44"><text><SENT sid="675" pm="."><plain>HabibiABanihashemiZMostowfizadeh-GhalamfarsaR (2015) Phylogenetic analysis of Polystigma and its relationship to Phyllachorales. Phytopathologia Mediterranea 54: 45–54. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R45"><text><SENT sid="676" pm="."><plain>HambletonSNickersonNLSeifertKA (2005) Leohumicola, a new genus of heat-resistant hyphomycetes. Studies in Mycology 53: 29–52. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R46"><text><SENT sid="677" pm="."><plain>HanlinRT (1990) Acerviclypeatus, a new genus for the anamorph of Ophiodothella vaccinii. Mycotaxon 37: 379–384. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R47"><text><SENT sid="678" pm="."><plain>HanlinRTGohT-KSkarshaugAJ (1992) A key to and descriptions of species assigned to Ophiodothella based on the literature. Mycotaxon 44: 103–126. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R48"><text><SENT sid="679" pm="."><plain>HanlinRTGonzálesM (2013) Ophiodothella angustissima comb. nov., a new name for Acerviclypeatus poriformans and O. vaccinii. Mycotaxon 123: 327–334. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R49"><text><SENT sid="680" pm="."><plain>HausnerGReidJ (2004) The nuclear small subunit ribosomal genes of Sphaeronaemella helvellae, Sphaeronaemella fimicola, Gabarnaudia betae, and Cornuvesica falcata: phylogenetic implications. Canadian Journal of Botany 82: 752–762. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R50"><text><SENT sid="681" pm="."><plain>HawksworthDL (2015) Proposals to clarify and enhance the naming of fungi under the International Code of Nomenclature for algae, fungi, and plants. IMA Fungus 6: 199–205; Taxon 64: 858–862.26203423 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R51"><text><SENT sid="682" pm="."><plain>HawksworthDLGibsonIASGamsW (1976) Phialophora parasitica associated with disease conditions in various trees. Transactions of the British Mycological Society 66: 427–431. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R52"><text><SENT sid="683" pm="."><plain>Hernández-RestrepoMGeneJMena-PortalesJCanoJHadridH, et al. (2014) New species of Cordana and epitypification of the genus. Mycologia 106: 723–734.24891420 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R53"><text><SENT sid="684" pm="."><plain>Hernández-RestrepoMGroenewaldJZCrousPW (2016) Taxonomy and phylogenetic reevaluation of Microdochium, Monographella and Idriella. Persoonia 36: 57–82. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R54"><text><SENT sid="685" pm="."><plain>HironagaMNakanoKYokoyamaIKitajimaJ (1989) Phialophora repens, an emerging agent of subcutaneous phaeohyphomycosis in humans. Journal of Clinical Microbiology 27: 394–399.2715315 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R55"><text><SENT sid="686" pm="."><plain>Holubová-JechováV (1973a) Lignicolous hyphomycetes from Czecho-slovakia 4. Menispora. Folia Geobotanica et Phytotaxonomic 8: 317–336. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R56"><text><SENT sid="687" pm="."><plain>Holubová-JechováV (1973b) Lignicolous hyphomycetes from Czechoslovakia 3. Sporoschisma, Sporoschismopsis and Catenularia. Folia Geobotanica et Phytotaxonomic 8: 209–218. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R57"><text><SENT sid="688" pm="."><plain>Holubová-JechováVHennebertGL (1972) Sporoschismopsis, a new genus of lignicolous hyphomycetes. Bulletin du Jardin Botanique National de Belgique 42: 385–391. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R58"><text><SENT sid="689" pm="."><plain>HsiehH-MJuY-MRogersJD (2005) Molecular phylogeny of Hypoxylon and closely related genera. Mycologia 97: 844–865.16457354 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R59"><text><SENT sid="690" pm="."><plain>HudsonHJ (1963) The perfect state of Nigrospora oryzae. Transactions of the British Mycological Society 46: 355–360. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R60"><text><SENT sid="691" pm="."><plain>HughesSJ (1951) Studies on micro-fungi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="692" pm="."><plain>XI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="693" pm="."><plain>Some hyphomycetes which produce phialides. Mycological Papers 45: 1–36. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R61"><text><SENT sid="694" pm="."><plain>HughesSJ (1958) Revisiones hyphomycetum aliquot cum appendice de nominibus rejiciendis. Canadian Journal of Botany 36: 727–836. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R62"><text><SENT sid="695" pm="."><plain>HughesSLHennebertGL (1963) Microfungi: X. Oedemium, Dimera, Diplosporium, Gongylocladium, and Cladotrichum. Canadian Journal of Botany 41: 773–809. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R63"><text><SENT sid="696" pm="."><plain>JaklitschWJGardiennetAVoglmayrH (2016) Resolution of morphology-based taxonomic delusions: Acrocordiella, Basiseptospora, Blogiascospora, Clypeosphaeria, Hymenopleella, Lepteutypa, Pseudapiospora, Requienella, Seiridium and Strickeria. Persoonia 37: 82–105. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R64"><text><SENT sid="697" pm="."><plain>JeewonRCaiLLiewECYZhangK-QHydeKD (2003) Dyrithiopsis lakefuxianensis gen. et sp. nov. from Fuxian Lake, Yunnan, China, and notes on the taxonomic confusion surrounding Dyrithium. Mycologia 95: 911–920.21148998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R65"><text><SENT sid="698" pm="."><plain>JohnstonPRSeifertKAStoneJKRossmanAYMaranovaL (2014) Recommendations on generic names competing for use in Leotiomycetes (Ascomycota). IMA Fungus 5: 91–120.25083411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R66"><text><SENT sid="699" pm="."><plain>JonesEBGSuetrongSSakayarojJBahkaliAHAbdel-WahabMA, et al. (2015) Classification of marine Ascomycota, Basidiomycota, Blastocladiomycota and Chytridiomycota. Fungal Diversity 73: 1–72. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R67"><text><SENT sid="700" pm="."><plain>JonesEBGZuccaroAMitchellJNakagiraAChatmalaI, et al (2009) Phylogenetic position of freshwater and marine Sigmoidea species: introducing a marine hyphomycete Halosigmoidea gen. nov. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="701" pm="."><plain>(Halosphaeriales). Botanica Marina 52: 349–359. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R68"><text><SENT sid="702" pm="."><plain>JuY-MHsiehH-MDominickS (2016) The Xylaria names proposed by C.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="703" pm="."><plain>Lloyd. North American Fungi 11: 1–31. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R69"><text><SENT sid="704" pm="."><plain>KhanZGeneJAhmadSCanoJAl-SwiehN et al (2013) Coniochaeta polymorpha, a new species from endotracheal aspirate of a preterm neonate, and transfer of Lecythophora species to Coniochaeta. Antonie van Leeuwenhoek 104: 243–252.23748934 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R70"><text><SENT sid="705" pm="."><plain>KirkPM (1986) New or interesting microfungi XV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="706" pm="."><plain>Miscellaneous hyphomycetes from the British Isles. Transactions of the British Mycological Society 86: 409–428. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R71"><text><SENT sid="707" pm="."><plain>KohlmeyerJVolkmann-KohlmeyerBErikssonOE (1997) Fungi on Juncus roemerianus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="708" pm="."><plain>9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="709" pm="."><plain>New obligate and facultative marine Ascomycotina. Botanica Marina 40: 291–300. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R72"><text><SENT sid="710" pm="."><plain>KutorgaERukđënienëJTreigienëA (2006) Microscopic fungi on Carpinus betulus in Lithuania 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="711" pm="."><plain>Teleomorphs and associated anamorphs. Botanica Lithuanica 12: 233–241. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R73"><text><SENT sid="712" pm="."><plain>LiQWenT-CKangJ-CHydeKD (2015a) A new species of Collodiscula (Xylariaceae) from China. Phytotaxa 205: 187–196. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R74"><text><SENT sid="713" pm="."><plain>LiQKangJ-CHydeKD (2015b) Two new species of the genus Collodiscula (Xylariaceae) from China. Mycological Progress 14: article 52. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R75"><text><SENT sid="714" pm="."><plain>LindqvistJCWrightJE (1964) Discoxylaria genero nuevo la forma perfecta de Hypocreodendron. Darwiniana 13: 138–143. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R76"><text><SENT sid="715" pm="."><plain>MaharachchikumburaSSNGuoL-DCaiLChukeatiroteEWuWP, et al. (2012) A multi-locus backbone tree for Pestalotiopsis, with a polyphasic characterization of 14 new species. Fungal Diversity 56: 95–129. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R77"><text><SENT sid="716" pm="."><plain>MaharachchikumburaSSNHydeKDGroenewaldJZXuJCrousPW (2014) Pestalotiopsis revisited. Studies in Mycology 79: 121–186.25492988 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R78"><text><SENT sid="717" pm="."><plain>MaharachchikumburaSSNHydeKDJonesEBGMcKenzieEHCHuangS-K, et al (2015) Towards a natural classification and backbone tree for Sordariomycetes. Fungal Diversity 72: 199–301. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R79"><text><SENT sid="718" pm="."><plain>MarkovskajaSTreigienéA (2007) A new and a rare species of Cryptadelphia and their Brachysporium anamorphs. Nova Hedwigia 84: 495–501. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R80"><text><SENT sid="719" pm="."><plain>McNeillJBarrieFRBurdetHMDemoulinVHawksworthDL, et al. (2006) International Code of Botanical Nomenclature (Vienna Code). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="720" pm="."><plain>[Regnum Vegetabile no. 146.] Ruggell: A. R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="722" pm="."><plain>G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="723" pm="."><plain>Gantner Verlag. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R81"><text><SENT sid="724" pm="."><plain>McNeillJBarrieFFBuckWRDemoulinVGreuterW, et al. (eds) (2012) International Code of Nomenclature for algae, fungi, and plants (Melbourne Code). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="725" pm="."><plain>[Regnum vegetabile no. 154.] Königstein: Koeltz Scientific Books. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R82"><text><SENT sid="726" pm="."><plain>MeyerWMDooleyJRKwon-ChungKJ (1975) Mycotic granuloma caused by Phialophora repens. American Journal of Clinical Pathology 64: 549–555.1199977 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R83"><text><SENT sid="727" pm="."><plain>MhmoudNAAbdallaASFahalAHde HoogGSGerrits van den EndeAH et al. (2012) Pleurostomophora ochracea, a novel agent of human eumycetoma with yellow grains. Journal of Clinical Microbiology 50: 2987–2994.22760037 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R84"><text><SENT sid="728" pm="."><plain>MillerANHuhndorfSM (2004) . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="729" pm="."><plain>A natural classification of Lasiosphaeria based on nuclear LSU rDNA sequences. Mycological Research 108: 26–34.15035502 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R85"><text><SENT sid="730" pm="."><plain>Moshrefi-ZarandiDAminaeeMMSharzeiARezaeeS (2014) First report of rosemary leaf spot caused by Nigrospora oryzae in Iran. New Disease Reports 30: 27. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R86"><text><SENT sid="731" pm="."><plain>MostertLCrousPWGroenewaldJZGamsWSummerbellRC (2003) Togninia (Calosphaeriales) is confirmed as teleomorph of Phaeoacremonium by means of morphology, sexual compatibility and DNA phylogeny. Mycologia 95: 646–659.21148974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R87"><text><SENT sid="732" pm="."><plain>MostertLGroenewaldJZSummerbellRCGamsWCrousPW (2006) Taxonomy and pathology of Togninia (Diaporthales) and its Phaeoacremonium anamorphs. Studies in Mycology 54: 1–115. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R88"><text><SENT sid="733" pm="."><plain>MugambiGHuhndorfSM (2008) A new species of Melanochaeta from Kenya. Sydowia 60: 261–266. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R89"><text><SENT sid="734" pm="."><plain>MugambiGKHuhndorfSM (2010) Multigene phylogeny of the Coronophorales: morphology and new species in the order. Mycologia 102: 185–210.20120241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R90"><text><SENT sid="735" pm="."><plain>MüllerE (1986) On the genus Diachora J. Müller. Transactions of the Botanical Society of Edinburgh 45 (Supplement 1): 69–75. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R91"><text><SENT sid="737" pm="."><plain>MüllerEvon ArxJA (1962) Die Gattungen der didymosporen Pyrenomyceten. Beiträge zur Kryptogamenflora der Schweiz 11(2): 1–922. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R92"><text><SENT sid="738" pm="."><plain>MüllerESamuelsGJ (1982) Anamorphs of pyrenomycetous ascomycetes I. Rhamphoria Niessl and Trichosphaerella Bommer et al. Sydowia 35: 143–149 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R93"><text><SENT sid="739" pm="."><plain>MüllerESamuelsG (1982) Anamorphs of pyrenomycetous ascomycetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="740" pm="."><plain>II. Porosphaerella gen. nov. and its Cordana anamorph. Sydowia 35: 150–154. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R94"><text><SENT sid="741" pm="."><plain>Nag RajTR (1975) Genera coelomycetum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="742" pm="."><plain>XI. Hyalotia, Hyalotiella, and Hyalotiopsis. Canadian Journal of Botany 53: 1615–1624. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R95"><text><SENT sid="743" pm="."><plain>Nag RajTR (1993) Coelomycetous Anamorphs with Appendage-bearing Conidia. Waterloo: Mycologue Publications. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R96"><text><SENT sid="744" pm="."><plain>Nag RajTRKendrickB (1986) Ellurema gen. nov., with notes on Lepteutypa cisticola and Seiridium canariense. Sydowia 38: 178–193. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R97"><text><SENT sid="745" pm="."><plain>NakagiriATokuraR (1982) A new marine ascomycete and its anamorph from Japan. Transactions of the Mycological Society of Japan 23: 101–110. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R98"><text><SENT sid="746" pm="."><plain>NawawiAKuthubutheenAJ (1989) Canalisporium, a new genus of lignicolous hyphomycetes from Malaysia. Mycotaxon 34: 475–487. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R99"><text><SENT sid="747" pm="."><plain>NonakaKIshitTShiomiKOmuraSMasumeR (2013) Virgaria boninensis, a new hyphomycete (Xylariaceae) from soils in the Bonin Islands, Japan. Mycoscience 54: 394–399. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R100"><text><SENT sid="748" pm="."><plain>NonakaKMiyazakiHIwatsukiMShiomiKTomodaH et al. (2012) Staphylotrichum boninense, a new hyphomycete (Chaetomiaceae) from soils in the Bonin Islands, Japan. Mycoscience 53: 312–318. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R101"><text><SENT sid="749" pm="."><plain>NorphanphounCMaharachchikumburaSSNDaranagamaABulgakovTSBhatDJ, et al. (2015) Towards a backbone tree for Seimatosporium, with S. physocarpi sp. nov. Mycosphere 6: 385–400. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R102"><text><SENT sid="750" pm="."><plain>OkaneINakagiriA (2007) Taxonomy of an anamorphic xylariaceous fungus from a termite nest found together with Xylaria angulosa. Mycoscience 48: 240–249. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R103"><text><SENT sid="751" pm="."><plain>PalmMEGamsWNirenbergHI (1995) Plectosporium, a new genus for Fusarium tabacinum, the anamorph of Plectosphaerella cucumerina. Mycologia 87: 397–406. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R104"><text><SENT sid="752" pm="."><plain>PerdomoHGarciaDGeneJSuttonDASummerbellR et al (2013) Phialemoniopsis, a new genus of Sordariomycetes, and new species of Phialemonium and Lecythophora. Mycologia 105: 398–421.23099515 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R105"><text><SENT sid="753" pm="."><plain>PeršohDMelcherMFlessaFRamboldG (2010) First fungal community analyses of endophytic ascomycetes associated with Viscum album ssp. austriacum and its host Pinus sylvestris. Fungal Biology 114: 585–596.20943170 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R106"><text><SENT sid="754" pm="."><plain>PetriniL (2013) Rosellinia – a world monograph. Bibliotheca Mycologica 205: 1–410. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R107"><text><SENT sid="755" pm="."><plain>ProfferTJ (1988) Xylaria root rot of urban trees caused by Xylaria polymorpha. Plant Disease 72: 79. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R108"><text><SENT sid="756" pm="."><plain>PunithalingamE (1970) Studies on Sphaeropsidales in culture. Mycological Papers 119: 1–24. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R109"><text><SENT sid="757" pm="."><plain>QuandtCAKeplerRMGamsWAraújoJPMBanS, et al. (2014) Phylogenetic-based nomenclatural proposals for Ophiocordycipitaceae (Hypocreales) with new combinations in Tolypocladium. IMA Fungus 5: 121–134.25083412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R110"><text><SENT sid="758" pm="."><plain>RajaHAFournierJShearerCAMillerAN (2012) Freshwater ascomycetes: Coniochaeta gigantospora sp. nov. based on morphological and molecular data. Mycoscience 53: 373–380. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R111"><text><SENT sid="759" pm="."><plain>RambelliAOnofriS (1987) New species of Kylindria and Xenokylindria and notes on Cylindrotrichum (Hyphomycetes). Transactions of the British Mycological Society 88: 393–397. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R112"><text><SENT sid="760" pm="."><plain>RanghooVMTsuiCKMHydeKD (2001) Brunneosporella aquatica gen. et sp. nov., Aqualignicola hyalina gen. et sp. nov., Jobellisia viridifusca sp. nov. and Porosphaerellopsis bipolaris sp. nov. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="761" pm="."><plain>(Ascomycetes) from submerged wood in freshwater habitats. Mycological Research 105: 625–633. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R113"><text><SENT sid="762" pm="."><plain>RéblováM (1999) Studies in Chaetosphaeria sensu lato I. The genera Chaetosphaerella and Tengiomyces gen. nov. of the Helminthosphaeriaceae. Mycotaxon 70: 387–420. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R114"><text><SENT sid="764" pm="."><plain>RéblováM (2000) The genus Chaetosphaeria and its anamorphs. Studies in Mycology 45: 149–168. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R115"><text><SENT sid="765" pm="."><plain>RéblováM (2011) New insights into the systematics and phylogeny of the genus Jattaea and similar fungi of the Calosphaeriales. Fungal Diversity 49: 167–198. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R116"><text><SENT sid="766" pm="."><plain>RéblováM (2014) Sporoschismopsis angustata sp. nov., a new holomorph species in the Reticulascaceae (Glomerellales), and a reappraisal of Sporoschismopsis. Mycological Progress 13: 671–681. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R117"><text><SENT sid="767" pm="."><plain>RéblováMBarrMESamuelsGJ (1999) Chaetosphaeriaceae, a new family for Chaetosphaeria and its relatives. Sydowia 51: 49–70. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R118"><text><SENT sid="768" pm="."><plain>RéblováMGamsW (1999) Teleomorph-anamorph connections in ascomycetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="769" pm="."><plain>1. Cylindrotrichum and Cacumisporium anamorphs of Chaetosphaeria. Czech Mycology 51: 1–40. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R119"><text><SENT sid="770" pm="."><plain>RéblováMGamsWSeifertKA (2011a) Monilochaetes and allied genera of the Glomerellales, and a reconsideration of families in the Microascales. Studies in Mycology 68: 163–191.21523193 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R120"><text><SENT sid="771" pm="."><plain>RéblováMGamsWŠtìpánekV (2011b) The new hyphomycete genera Brachyalara and Infundichalara, the similar Exochalara and species of Phialophoraʻ sect. Catenulataeʼ (Leotiomycetes). Fungal Diversity 46: 67–86. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R121"><text><SENT sid="772" pm="."><plain>RéblováMJaklitschWMRéblováKŠtìpánekV (2015) Phylogenetic reconstruction of the Calosphaeriales and Togniniales using five genes and predicted RNA secondary structures of ITS, and Flabellascus tenuirostris gen. et sp. nov. PLos One 10(12): e0144616.26699541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R122"><text><SENT sid="773" pm="."><plain>RéblováMMostertLGamsWCrousPW (2004) New genera in the Calosphaeriales: Togniniella and its anamorph Phaeocrella, and Calosphaeriophora as anamorph of Calosphaeria. Studies in Mycology 50: 533–550. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R123"><text><SENT sid="774" pm="."><plain>RéblováMMostertL (2007) Romellia is congeneric with Togninia and description of Conidiotheca gen. nov. for one species of this genus with polysporous asci. Mycological Research 111: 299–307.17350241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R124"><text><SENT sid="775" pm="."><plain>RéblováMSeifertKA (2004a) Conioscyphascus, a new ascomycetous genus for holomorphs with Conioscypha anamorphs. Studies in Mycology 50: 95–108. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R125"><text><SENT sid="776" pm="."><plain>RéblováMSeifertKA (2004b) Cryptadelphia (Trichosphaeriales), a new genus for holomorphs with Brachysporium anamorphs, and clarification of the taxonomic status of Wallrothiella. Mycologia 96: 343–367.21148858 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R126"><text><SENT sid="777" pm="."><plain>RéblováMSeifertKA (2007) A new fungal genus, Teracosphaeria, with a phialophora-like anamorph (Sordariomycetes, Ascomycota). Mycological Research 111: 287–298.17363235 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R127"><text><SENT sid="778" pm="."><plain>RéblováMSeifertKAFournierJŠtìpánekV (2016) Newly recognised lineages of perithecial ascomycetes: the new orders Conioscyphales and Pleurotheciales. Persoonia 37: 57–81. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R128"><text><SENT sid="779" pm="."><plain>RéblováMWinkaK (2000) Phylogeny of Chaetosphaeria and its anamorphs based on morphological and molecular data. Mycologia 92: 939–954. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R129"><text><SENT sid="780" pm="."><plain>Rodrigues de CruzMCMarquesMFOGuzmãoLFP (2014) Conidial fungi from the semi-arid catinga biome of Brazil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="781" pm="."><plain>The genus Menisporopsis. Acta Botanica Brasilica 28: 339–345. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R130"><text><SENT sid="782" pm="."><plain>RogersJD (1984) Xylaria cubensis and its anamorph Xylocoremium flabelliforme, Xylaria allantoidea, and Xylaria poitei in continental United States. Mycologia 76: 912–923. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R131"><text><SENT sid="783" pm="."><plain>RogersJDJuY-M (2002) Ascovirgaria occulta gen. et sp. nov., Jumillera hawaiiensis sp. nov, and Lopadostoma hawaiianum sp. nov. from Hawaii. Canadian Journal of Botany 80: 478–481. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R132"><text><SENT sid="784" pm="."><plain>RogersJDJuY-MHemmesDE (1997) Xylaria moelleroclavus sp. nov. and its Moelleroclavus anamorphic state. Mycological Research 101: 345–348. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R133"><text><SENT sid="785" pm="."><plain>RogersJDJuY-MSan Martin GonzalezF (1995) Discoxylaria myrmecophila and its Hypocreodendron anamorph. Mycologia 87: 41–45. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R134"><text><SENT sid="786" pm="."><plain>RojasEIRehnerSASamuelsGJVan BaelSAHerreEA et al. (2010) Colletotrichum gloeosporioides s.l. associated with Theobroma cacao and other plants in Panama: multilocus phylogenies distinguish host-associated pathogens from asymptomatic endophytes. Mycologia 102: 1318–1338.20943565 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R135"><text><SENT sid="787" pm="."><plain>RolshausenPEMahoneyNEMolyneuxRJGublerWD (2006) A re-assessment of the species concept in Eutypa lata, the causal agent of Eutypa dieback of grapevine. Phytopathology 96: 367–377. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R136"><text><SENT sid="788" pm="."><plain>RossmanAYSeifertKASamuelsGJMinnisAMSchroersH-J, et al. (2013) Genera in Bionectriaceae, Hypocreaceae, and Nectriaceae (Hypocreales) proposed for acceptance or rejection. IMA Fungus 4: 41–51.23898411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R137"><text><SENT sid="789" pm="."><plain>RossmanAYAdamsGCCannonPFCastleburyLACrousPW et al. (2015a) Recommendations of generic names in Diaporthales competing for protection or use. IMA Fungus 6: 145–154.26203420 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R138"><text><SENT sid="790" pm="."><plain>RossmanAYCrousPWHydeKDHawksworthDLAptrootA, et al. (2015b) Recommended names of pleomorphic genera in Dothideomycetes. IMA Fungus 6: 507–523.26734553 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R139"><text><SENT sid="791" pm="."><plain>SamsonRA (1974) Paecilomyces and some allied hyphomycetes. Studies in Mycology 6: 1–119. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R140"><text><SENT sid="792" pm="."><plain>SamsonRAVisagieCMHoubrakenJHongS-BHubkaV, et al. (2014) Phylogeny, identification and nomenclature of the genus Aspergillus. Studies in Mycology 78: 141–173.25492982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R141"><text><SENT sid="793" pm="."><plain>SamuelsGJMüllerE (1978) Life-history studies of Brazilian ascomycetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="794" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="795" pm="."><plain>Two new genera of the Sphaeriaceae having, respectively, Sporoschisma-like and Codinaea anamorphs. Sydowia 31: 126–136. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R142"><text><SENT sid="796" pm="."><plain>SamuelsGJMüllerE (1980) Life history studies of Brazilian ascomycetes 8. Thamnomyces chordalis (anam.: Nodulisporium) and Camillea bacillum (anam.: Geniculosporium) with notes on taxonomy of the Xylariaceae. Sydowia 33: 274–281. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R143"><text><SENT sid="797" pm="."><plain>SamuelsGJMcKenzieEHCBuchananDE (1981) Ascomycetes of New Zealand 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="798" pm="."><plain>Two new species of Apiospora and their Arthrinium anamorphs on bamboo. New Zealand Journal of Botany 19: 137–149. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R144"><text><SENT sid="799" pm="."><plain>SamuelsGJRogersJDNagasawaE (1987) Studies in the Amphisphaeriaceae (sensu lato) 1l. Collodiscula japonica and its anamorph, Acanthodochium collodisculae. Mycotaxon 28: 453–459. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R145"><text><SENT sid="800" pm="."><plain>SchochCLSungGHVolkmann-KohlmeyerBKohlmeyerJSpataforaJW (2007) Marine fungal lineages in the Hypocreomycetidae. Mycological Research 111: 154–162.17161942 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R146"><text><SENT sid="801" pm="."><plain>Schol-SchwarzMB (1970). Revision of the genus Phialophora. Persoonia 6: 59–94. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R147"><text><SENT sid="802" pm="."><plain>SeifertKA (1987) Stromatographium and Acrostroma gen. nov.: two tropical hyphomycete genera with distinctive synnema anatomies. Canadian Journal of Botany 65: 2196–2201. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R148"><text><SENT sid="803" pm="."><plain>SeifertKAGamsWLouis-SeizeGW (2002) Arthroxylaria elegans, a new coprophilous anamorphic fungus allied with the Xylariaceae, with notes on the genus Bisporostilbella. Czech Mycology 53: 297–307. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R149"><text><SENT sid="804" pm="."><plain>SenanayakeICMaharachchikumburaSSNHydeKDBhatJDJonesEBG, et al. (2015) Towards unraveling relationships in Xylariomycetidae (Sordariomycetes). Fungal Diversity 73: 73–144. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R150"><text><SENT sid="805" pm="."><plain>ShenoyBDJeewonRWuWPBhatDJHydeKD (2006) Ribosomal and RPB2 DNA sequence analyses suggest that Sporidesmium and morphologically similar genera are polyphyletic. Mycological Research 110: 916–928.16908125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R151"><text><SENT sid="806" pm="."><plain>ShoemakerRAMüllerEMorgan-JonesG (1966) Fuckel’s Massaria marginata and Seiridium marginatum Nees ex Steudel. Canadian Journal of Botany 44: 247–254. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R152"><text><SENT sid="807" pm="."><plain>ShoemakerRA (1964) Seimatosporium (= Cryptostictis) parasites of Rosa, Vitis, and Cornus. Canadian Journal of Botany 42: 411–421. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R153"><text><SENT sid="808" pm="."><plain>SivanesanA (1983) Studies on ascomycetes. Transactions of the British Mycological Society 81: 313–332. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R154"><text><SENT sid="809" pm="."><plain>SivichaiSHywel-JonesNLSomrithipolS (2000) Lignicolous freshwater Ascomycota from Thailand: Melanochaeta and Sporoschisma anamorphs. Mycological Research 104: 478–485. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R155"><text><SENT sid="810" pm="."><plain>Sri-indrasutdhiVBoonyuenNSuetrongSChuaseeharonnachaiCSivichaiS, et al. (2010) Wood-inhabiting freshwater fungi from Thailand: Ascothailandia grenadoidia gen. et sp. nov., Canalisporium grenadoidia sp. nov. with a key to Canalisporium species (Sordariomycetes, Ascomycota). Mycoscience 51: 411–420. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R156"><text><SENT sid="811" pm="."><plain>StadlerMKuhnertEPeršohDFournierJ (2013) The Xylariaceae as model example for a unified nomenclature following the “One fungus-one name” (1F1N) concept. Mycology 4: 5–21. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R157"><text><SENT sid="812" pm="."><plain>StadlerMLæssøeTFournierJDecockCSchmieschekB, et al. (2014). A polyphasic taxonomy of Daldinia (Xylariaceae). Studies in Mycology 77: 1–143.24790283 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R158"><text><SENT sid="813" pm="."><plain>SubramanianCVSekarG (1986) Pseudocercophora ingoldii gen. et sp. nov. and its Mammaria anamorph. Journal of the Singapore National Academy of Sciences 15: 58–60. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R159"><text><SENT sid="814" pm="."><plain>SuttonBC (1980) The Coelomycetes; Fungi Imperfecti with pycnidia, acervuli and stromata. Kew: Commonwealth Mycological Institute. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R160"><text><SENT sid="815" pm="."><plain>TanakaKEndoMHirayamaKOkaneIHosoyaT, et al. (2011) Phylogeny of Discosia and Seimatosporium and introduction of Adisciso and Immersidiscosia genera nova. Persoonia 26: 85–98.22025806 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R161"><text><SENT sid="816" pm="."><plain>TangAMJeewonRHydeKD (2007) Phylogenetic utility of protein (RPB2, beta-tubulin) and ribosomal (LSU, SSU) gene sequences in the systematics of Sordariomycetes, Ascomycota, Fungi. Antonie van Leeuwenhoek 91: 327–349.17072532 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R162"><text><SENT sid="817" pm="."><plain>TrouillasFPLorberJDPedutoFGrantJCoatesWW, et al. (2010a) First report of Calosphaeria pulchella associated with branch dieback of sweet cherry trees in California. Plant Disease 94: 1167. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R163"><text><SENT sid="818" pm="."><plain>TrouillasFPUrbez-TorresJRGublerWD (2010b). Diversity of diatrypaceous fungi associated with grapevine canker diseases in California. Mycologia 102: 319–336.20361500 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R164"><text><SENT sid="819" pm="."><plain>UntereinerWADeboisVNaveauFA (2001) Molecular systematics of the ascomycete genus Farrowia (Chaetomiaceae). Canadian Journal of Botany 79: 321–333. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R165"><text><SENT sid="820" pm="."><plain>VakiliNG (1989) Gonatobotrys simplex and its teleomorph, Melanospora damnosa. Mycological Research 93: 67–74. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R166"><text><SENT sid="821" pm="."><plain>VijaykrishnaDMostertLJeewonRGamsWHydeKD, et al (2004) Pleurostomophora, an anamorph of Pleurostoma (Calosphaeriales), a new anamorph genus morphologically similar to Phialophora. Studies in Mycology 50: 387–395. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R167"><text><SENT sid="822" pm="."><plain>VisagieCMHoubrakenJFrisvadJCHongS-BKlaassenCHW, et al. (2014) Identification and nomenclature of the genus Penicillium. Studies in Mycology 78: 343–371.25505353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R168"><text><SENT sid="823" pm="."><plain>WeberEGorkeCBegerowD (2002) The Lecythophora -Coniochaeta complex II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="824" pm="."><plain>Molecular studies based on sequences of the large subunit of ribosomal DNA. Nova Hedwigia 74: 187–200. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R169"><text><SENT sid="825" pm="."><plain>WeirBSJohnstonPRDammU (2012) The Colletotrichum gloeosporioides species complex. Studies in Mycology 73: 115–180.23136459 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R170"><text><SENT sid="826" pm="."><plain>WijayawardeneDNNMcKenzieEHCHydeKD (2012) Towards incorporating anamorphic fungi in a natural classification–checklist and notes for 2011. Mycosphere 3: 157–228. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R171"><text><SENT sid="827" pm="."><plain>ZelskiSDoCBaltoJARajaHAMillerAN, et al (2014a) Some dematiaceous freshwater microfungi from Perú and their previously unknown phylogenetic relationships based on 28S nrDNA. IMA Fungus 5: 425–438.25734032 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R172"><text><SENT sid="828" pm="."><plain>ZelskiSERajaHAMillerANShearerCA (2014b) Conioscypha peruviana sp. nov., its phylogenetic placement based on 28S rRNA gene, and a report of Conioscypha gracilis comb. nov. from Peru. Mycoscience 56: 319–325. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R173"><text><SENT sid="829" pm="."><plain>ZhangNLuoJRossmanAAokiTChumaI, et al (2016) Generic names in Magnaporthales. IMA Fungus  7: 155–159. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="830" pm="."><plain>Names of pleomorphic genera in Sordariomycetes excluding Diaporthales, Hypocreales and Magnaporthales indicating those that are proposed for protection (including those which are asexually typified and recommended for use over sexually typified genera). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="831" pm="."><plain>For each genus the citation, type species and accepted name is given. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="832" pm="."><plain>NCF = Nomenclature Committee for Fungi. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="833" pm="."><plain>Generic name recommended for use, citation and type species </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="834" pm="."><plain>Suppressed generic name(s), citation, type species and currently accepted name </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="835" pm="."><plain>Action Required </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="836" pm="."><plain>Arthrinium Kunze, in Kunze &amp; Schmidt, Mykol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="837" pm="."><plain>Hefte 1: 9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="838" pm="."><plain>1817. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="839" pm="."><plain>Apiospora Sacc. in Atti Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="840" pm="."><plain>Veneto-Trent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="841" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="842" pm="."><plain>Nat., Padova, sér. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="843" pm="."><plain>4 4: 85. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="844" pm="."><plain>1875. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="845" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="846" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="847" pm="."><plain>Typus: A. caricicola Kunze &amp; J.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="848" pm="."><plain>Schmidt 1817. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="849" pm="."><plain>Typus: A. montagnei Sacc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="850" pm="."><plain>1875, now regarded as Arthrinium arundinis (Corda) Dyko &amp; B. Sutton 1979. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="852" pm="."><plain>Pteroconium Sacc. ex Grove in Hedwigia 55: 146. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="853" pm="."><plain>1914. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="854" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. asteroides Grove 1914, now regarded as Arthrinium pterospermum (Cooke &amp; Massee) Arx 1981. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="855" pm="."><plain>Scyphospora L.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="856" pm="."><plain>Kantsch. in Bolêzni Rast. 17: 87 (1928). </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="857" pm="."><plain>Typus: S. phyllostachydis L.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="858" pm="."><plain>Kantsch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="859" pm="."><plain>1928, now regarded as Arthrinium hysterinum (Sacc.) P.M. Kirk 1986. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="860" pm="."><plain>Brachysporium Sacc., Syll. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="861" pm="."><plain>Fung. 4: 423. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="862" pm="."><plain>1886. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="863" pm="."><plain>Cryptadelphia Réblová &amp; Seifert in Mycologia 96: 348. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="864" pm="."><plain>2004. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="865" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="866" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="867" pm="."><plain>Typus: B. obovatum (Berk.) Sacc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="868" pm="."><plain>1886, basionym: Helminthosporium obovatum Berk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="869" pm="."><plain>1841. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="870" pm="."><plain>Typus: C. groenendalensis (Sacc. et al.) Réblová &amp; Seifert 2004, basionym: Zignoëlla groenendalensis Sacc. et al. 1884, now regarded as Brachysporium nigrum (Link) S. Hughes 1958. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="872" pm="."><plain>Calosphaeria Tul. &amp; C. Tul., Select. fung. carpol. 2: 108. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="874" pm="."><plain>1863. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="875" pm="."><plain>Calosphaeriophora Réblová et al. in Stud. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="876" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 50: 542. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="877" pm="."><plain>2004. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="878" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="879" pm="."><plain>Typus: C. princeps Tul. &amp; C. Tul. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="881" pm="."><plain>1863. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="882" pm="."><plain>Typus: C. pulchella Réblová et al. 2004, now regarded as Calosphaeria pulchella (Pers.) J. Schröt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="885" pm="."><plain>1897. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="886" pm="."><plain>Canalisporium Nawawi &amp; Kuthub. in Mycotaxon 34: 477. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="887" pm="."><plain>1989. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="888" pm="."><plain>Ascothailandia Sri-indr. et al. in Mycoscience 51: 414. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="889" pm="."><plain>2010. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="890" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="891" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="892" pm="."><plain>Typus: C. caribense (Hol.-Jech. &amp; Mercado) Nawawi &amp; Kuthub. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="893" pm="."><plain>1989, basionym: Berkleasmium caribense Hol.-Jech. &amp; Mercado 1984. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="894" pm="."><plain>Typus: A. grenadoidea Sri-indr. et al. 2010, now regarded as Canalisporium grenadoideum Sri-indr. et al. 2010. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="895" pm="."><plain>Chaetomium Kunze, in Kunze &amp; Schmidt, Mykol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="896" pm="."><plain>Hefte 1: 15. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="897" pm="."><plain>1817. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="898" pm="."><plain>Botryotrichum Sacc. &amp; Marchal in Bull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="899" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="900" pm="."><plain>Roy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="901" pm="."><plain>Bot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="902" pm="."><plain>Belgique 24: 66. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="903" pm="."><plain>1885. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="904" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="905" pm="."><plain>Typus: C. globosum Kunze 1817. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="906" pm="."><plain>Typus: B. piluliferum Sacc. &amp; Marchal 1885, now regarded as Chaetomium piluliferum J. Daniels 1961. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="907" pm="."><plain>Although the synonym Sepedonium albogriseum Balf.-Browne 1952 provides an older name, C. piluliferum will be proposed for conservation. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="908" pm="."><plain>Trichocladium Harz in Bull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="909" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="910" pm="."><plain>Imp. nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="911" pm="."><plain>Moscou 44: 125. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="912" pm="."><plain>1871. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="913" pm="."><plain>Typus: T. asperum Harz 1871. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="914" pm="."><plain>Humicola Traaen in Nytt Mag. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="915" pm="."><plain>Natur. 52: 31. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="916" pm="."><plain>1914. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="917" pm="."><plain>Typus: H. fuscoatra Traaen 1914. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="918" pm="."><plain>Chaetosphaerella E. Müll. &amp; C. Booth in Trans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="921" pm="."><plain>Brit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="922" pm="."><plain>Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="923" pm="."><plain>Soc. 58: 76. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="924" pm="."><plain>1972. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="925" pm="."><plain>Oedemium Link, Sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="926" pm="."><plain>Pl., edn 4 6(1): 42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="927" pm="."><plain>1824. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="928" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF for Chaeto-sphaerella 1972 over Oedemium 1824. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="929" pm="."><plain>Typus: C. phaeostroma (Durieu &amp; Mont.) E. Müll. &amp; C. Booth 1972, basionym: Sphaeria phaeostroma Durieu &amp; Mont. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="932" pm="."><plain>1846 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="933" pm="."><plain>Typus: O. atrum Link 1824, now regarded as Chaetosphaerella fusca (Fuckel) E. Müll. &amp; C. Booth 1972. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="936" pm="."><plain>Veramycina Subram. in Kavaka 20/21: 58. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="937" pm="."><plain>1995. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="938" pm="."><plain>Typus: V. elegans Subram. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="939" pm="."><plain>1995, now regarded as Chaetosphaerella phaeostroma (Durieu &amp; Mont.) E. Müll. &amp; C. Booth 1972. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="942" pm="."><plain>Chloridium Link in Mag. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="943" pm="."><plain>Gesell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="944" pm="."><plain>Naturf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="945" pm="."><plain>Freunde, Berlin 3: 13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="946" pm="."><plain>1809. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="947" pm="."><plain>Gonytrichum Nees &amp; T. Nees in Nova Acta Phys.-Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="949" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="950" pm="."><plain>Caes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="951" pm="."><plain>Leop.-Carol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="952" pm="."><plain>Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="953" pm="."><plain>Cur. 9: 244. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="954" pm="."><plain>1818. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="955" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="956" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="957" pm="."><plain>Typus: C. viride Link 1805, now regarded as Chloridium virescens (Pers.) W. Gams &amp; Hol.-Jech. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="958" pm="."><plain>1976, basionym Dematium virescens Pers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="959" pm="."><plain>1794. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="960" pm="."><plain>Typus: G. caesium Nees 1818, now regarded as Chloridium caesium (Nees) Réblová &amp; Seifert 2016 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="961" pm="."><plain>Melanopsammella Höhn. in Ann. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="962" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 17: 121. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="963" pm="."><plain>1920. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="964" pm="."><plain>Typus: M. inaequalis (Grove) Höhn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="965" pm="."><plain>1920, basionym: Eriosphaeria inaequalis Grove, in Berlese &amp; Voglino 1886, now regarded as Chloridium caesium (Nees) Réblová &amp; Seifert 2016. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="966" pm="."><plain>Colletotrichum Corda, Deutschl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="967" pm="."><plain>Fl., 3(12): 41. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="968" pm="."><plain>1837. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="969" pm="."><plain>Glomerella Spauld. &amp; H. Schrenk in Science 17: 751. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="971" pm="."><plain>1903. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="972" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="973" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="974" pm="."><plain>Typus: C. lineola Corda 1832. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="975" pm="."><plain>Typus: G. cingulata (Stoneman) Spauld. &amp; H. Schrenk 1903, now regarded as Colletotrichum gloeosporioides (Penz.) Penz. &amp; Sacc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="977" pm="."><plain>1884. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="978" pm="."><plain>Collodiscula I. Hino &amp; Katum. in Bull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="980" pm="."><plain>Fac. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="981" pm="."><plain>Agric. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="982" pm="."><plain>Yamaguchi Univ. 6: 55. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="983" pm="."><plain>1955. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="984" pm="."><plain>Acanthodochium Samuels et al. in Mycotaxon 28: 457. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="985" pm="."><plain>1987. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="986" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="987" pm="."><plain>Typus: C. japonica I. Hino &amp; Katum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="989" pm="."><plain>1955. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="990" pm="."><plain>Typus: A. collodisculae Samuels et al. 1987, now regarded as Collodiscula japonica I. Hino &amp; Katum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="993" pm="."><plain>1955. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="994" pm="."><plain>Coniochaeta (Sacc.) Cooke in Grevillea 16: 16. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="995" pm="."><plain>1887, basionym: Rosellinia subgen. Coniochaeta Sacc., Syll. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="996" pm="."><plain>Fung. 1: 269. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="997" pm="."><plain>1882. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="998" pm="."><plain>Lecythophora Nannf. in Svensk Skogsvårdsförening Tidskr. 3–4: 435. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="999" pm="."><plain>1934. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1000" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1001" pm="."><plain>Typus: C. ligniaria (Grev.) Cooke 1887, basionym: Sphaeria ligniaria Grev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1002" pm="."><plain>1824. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1003" pm="."><plain>Typus: L. lignicola Nannf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1004" pm="."><plain>1934, now regarded as Coniochaeta lignicola (Nannf.) Z.U. Khan et al. 2013. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1005" pm="."><plain>Conioscypha Höhn. in Ann. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1006" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 2: 58. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1007" pm="."><plain>1904. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1008" pm="."><plain>Conioscyphascus Réblová &amp; Seifert in Stud. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1009" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 50: 100. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1010" pm="."><plain>2004. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1011" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1012" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1013" pm="."><plain>Typus: C. lignicola Höhn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1014" pm="."><plain>1904. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1015" pm="."><plain>Typus: C. varius Réblová &amp; Seifert 2004, now regarded as Conioscypha varia Shearer 1973. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1016" pm="."><plain>Cordana Preuss in Linnaea 24: 129. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1017" pm="."><plain>1851. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1018" pm="."><plain>Porosphaerella E. Müll. &amp; Samuels in Sydowia 35: 151. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1020" pm="."><plain>1982. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1021" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1022" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1023" pm="."><plain>Typus: C. pauciseptata Preuss 1851. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1024" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. cordanophora E. Müll. &amp; Samuels 1982, now regarded as Cordana pauciseptata Preuss 1851. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1026" pm="."><plain>Pseudobotrytis Krzemien. &amp; Badura in Acta Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1027" pm="."><plain>Bot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1028" pm="."><plain>Pol. 23: 761. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1029" pm="."><plain>1954. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1030" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. fusca Krzemien. &amp; Badura 1954, now regarded as Cordana terrestris (Timonin) Hern.-Rest. et al. 2014. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1032" pm="."><plain>Corollospora Werderm. in Notizbl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1033" pm="."><plain>Bot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1034" pm="."><plain>Gart. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1035" pm="."><plain>Berlin-Dahlem 8: 248. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1036" pm="."><plain>1922. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1037" pm="."><plain>Varicosporina Meyers &amp; Kohlm. in Canad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1038" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1039" pm="."><plain>Bot. 43: 916. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1040" pm="."><plain>1965. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1041" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1042" pm="."><plain>Typus: Corollospora maritima Werderm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1043" pm="."><plain>1922. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1044" pm="."><plain>Typus: V. ramulosa Meyers &amp; Kohlm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1045" pm="."><plain>1965, now regarded as Corollospora ramulosa (Meyers &amp; Kohlm.) Abdel-Wahab 2016. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1046" pm="."><plain>Halosigmoidea Nakagiri et al. in Bot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1047" pm="."><plain>Mar. 52: 355. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1048" pm="."><plain>2009. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1049" pm="."><plain>Typus: H. luteola (Nakagiri &amp; Tubaki) Nakagiri et al. 2009, basionym: Sigmoidea luteola Nakagiri &amp; Tubaki 1982, now regarded as Corollospora luteola Nakagiri &amp; Tubaki 1982. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1050" pm="."><plain>Cylindrotrichum Bonord., Handb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1051" pm="."><plain>Allgem. mykol.: 88 (1851). </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1052" pm="."><plain>Reticulascus Réblová &amp; W. Gams in Stud. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1054" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 68: 180. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1055" pm="."><plain>2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1056" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1057" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1058" pm="."><plain>Typus: C. oligospermum (Corda) Bonord. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1059" pm="."><plain>1851, basionym: Menispora oligosperma Corda 1838. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1060" pm="."><plain>Typus: R. tulasneorum (Réblová &amp; W. Gams) Réblová &amp; W. Gams 2010, basionym: Chaetosphaeria tulasneorum Réblová &amp; W. Gams 1999, now regarded as Cylindrotrichum oligospermum (Corda) Bonord. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1064" pm="."><plain>1851. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1065" pm="."><plain>Daldinia Ces. &amp; De Not. in Comment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1066" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1067" pm="."><plain>Crittog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1068" pm="."><plain>Ital. 1(4): 197. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1069" pm="."><plain>1863. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1070" pm="."><plain>Annellosporium M.L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1071" pm="."><plain>Davey in Karstenia 50: 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1072" pm="."><plain>2010. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1073" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1074" pm="."><plain>Typus: D. concentrica (Bolton) Ces. &amp; De Not. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1075" pm="."><plain>1863, basionym: Sphaeria concentrica Bolton 1792. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1076" pm="."><plain>Typus: A. nemorosum M.L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1077" pm="."><plain>Davey 2010, now Daldinia nemorosa (M.L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1078" pm="."><plain>Davey) M. Stadler et al. 2014. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1080" pm="."><plain>Versiomyces Whalley &amp; Watling in Notes R. bot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1081" pm="."><plain>Gdn Edinb. 45: 401. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1082" pm="."><plain>1989. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1083" pm="."><plain>Typus: V. cahuchucosus Whalley &amp; Watling 1989, now regarded as Daldinia cahuchucosus (Whalley &amp; Watling) M. Stadler &amp; Læssøe 2014. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1084" pm="."><plain>Diachora Jul. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1085" pm="."><plain>Müll. in Jahrb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1086" pm="."><plain>Wiss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1087" pm="."><plain>Bot. 25: 623. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1088" pm="."><plain>1893. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1089" pm="."><plain>Diachorella Höhn. in Hedwigia 60: 192. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1090" pm="."><plain>1918. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1091" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1092" pm="."><plain>Typus: D. onobrychidis (DC.) Jul. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1093" pm="."><plain>Müll. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1094" pm="."><plain>1893, basionym: Xyloma onobrychidis DC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1095" pm="."><plain>1815. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1096" pm="."><plain>Typus: D. onobrychidis (DC.) Höhn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1097" pm="."><plain>1918, basionym: Xyloma onobrychidis DC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1098" pm="."><plain>1815, now regarded as Diachora onobrychidis (DC) Jul. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1099" pm="."><plain>Müll. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1100" pm="."><plain>1893. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1101" pm="."><plain>Diatrype Fr., Summa veg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1102" pm="."><plain>Scand. 2: 384. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1103" pm="."><plain>1849. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1104" pm="."><plain>Libertella Desm. in Ann. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1105" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1106" pm="."><plain>Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1107" pm="."><plain>(Paris) sér. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1108" pm="."><plain>1 19: 275. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1109" pm="."><plain>1830. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1110" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF for Diatrype 1849 over Libertella 1830. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1111" pm="."><plain>Typus: D. disciformis (Hoffm.) Fr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1112" pm="."><plain>1849, basionym: Sphaeria disciformis Hoffm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1113" pm="."><plain>1787. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1114" pm="."><plain>Typus: L. betulina Desm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1115" pm="."><plain>1830, now regarded as Diatrype stigma (Hoffm.) Fr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1116" pm="."><plain>1849. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1117" pm="."><plain>Dyrithiopsis L. Cai et al. in Mycologia 95: 912. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1119" pm="."><plain>2003. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1120" pm="."><plain>Monochaetiopsis L. Cai et al. in Mycologia 95: 913. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1122" pm="."><plain>2003. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1123" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1124" pm="."><plain>Typus: D. lakefuxianensis L. Cai et al. 2003. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1127" pm="."><plain>Typus: M. lakefuxianensis L. Cai et al. 2003, now regarded as Dyrithiopsis lakefuxianensis L. Cai et al. 2003. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1132" pm="."><plain>Hyalotiopsis Punith. in Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1133" pm="."><plain>Pap. 119: 12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1134" pm="."><plain>1970. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1135" pm="."><plain>Ellurema Nag Raj &amp; W.B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1136" pm="."><plain>Kendr. in Sydowia 38: 178. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1137" pm="."><plain>1986. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1138" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1139" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1140" pm="."><plain>Typus: H. subramanianii (Agnihothr. &amp; Luke) Punith. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1141" pm="."><plain>1970, basionym: Hyalotiella subramanianii Agnihothr. &amp; Luke 1970. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1142" pm="."><plain>Typus: E. indica (Punith.) Nag Raj &amp; W.B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1143" pm="."><plain>Kendr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1144" pm="."><plain>1986, basionym: Massaria indica Punith. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1145" pm="."><plain>1970, now regarded as Hyalotiopsis subramanianii (Agnihothr. &amp; Luke) Punith. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1146" pm="."><plain>1970. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1147" pm="."><plain>Hypocreodendron Henn. in Hedwigia 36: 223. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1148" pm="."><plain>1897. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1149" pm="."><plain>Discoxylaria J.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1150" pm="."><plain>Lindq. &amp; J.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1151" pm="."><plain>Wright in Darwiniana 13: 139. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1152" pm="."><plain>1964. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1153" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1154" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1155" pm="."><plain>Typus: H. sanguineum Henn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1156" pm="."><plain>1897. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1157" pm="."><plain>Typus: Discoxylaria myrmecophila J.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1158" pm="."><plain>Lindq. &amp; J.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1159" pm="."><plain>Wright 1964, now regarded as Hypocreodendron sanguineum Henn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1160" pm="."><plain>1897. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1161" pm="."><plain>Hypoxylon Bull., Hist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1162" pm="."><plain>Champ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1163" pm="."><plain>Fr. 1: 168. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1164" pm="."><plain>1791. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1165" pm="."><plain>Nodulisporium Preuss in Klotzschii Herb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1166" pm="."><plain>Viv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1167" pm="."><plain>Mycol.: no. 1272. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1168" pm="."><plain>1849. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1169" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1170" pm="."><plain>Typus: H. coccineum Bull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1171" pm="."><plain>1791, now regarded as Hypoxylon fragiforme (Pers.) J. Kickx f. 1835, basionym Sphaeria fragiformis Pers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1174" pm="."><plain>1794. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1175" pm="."><plain>Typus: N. ochraceum Preuss 1849, now regarded as Hypoxylon fragiforme (Pers.) J. Kickx f. 1835. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1178" pm="."><plain>Juncigena Kohlm. et al. in Bot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1179" pm="."><plain>Mar. 40: 291. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1180" pm="."><plain>1997. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1181" pm="."><plain>Moheitospora Abdel-Wahab et al. in Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1182" pm="."><plain>Progr. 9: 551. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1183" pm="."><plain>2010. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1184" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1185" pm="."><plain>Typus: J. adarca Kohlm. et al. 1997. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1187" pm="."><plain>Typus: M. fruticosae Abdel-Wahab et al. 2010, now regarded as Juncigena fruticosae (Abdel-Wahab et al.) A.N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1189" pm="."><plain>Mill. &amp; Shearer 2016. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1190" pm="."><plain>Knoxdaviesia M.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1191" pm="."><plain>Wingf. et al. in Mycologia 80: 26. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1192" pm="."><plain>1988. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1193" pm="."><plain>Gondwanamyces G.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1194" pm="."><plain>Marais &amp; M.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1195" pm="."><plain>Wingf. in Mycologia 90: 139. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1196" pm="."><plain>1998. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1197" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1198" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1199" pm="."><plain>Typus: K. proteae M.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1200" pm="."><plain>Wingf. et al. 1988. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1202" pm="."><plain>Typus: G. proteae (M.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1203" pm="."><plain>Wingf. et al.) G.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1204" pm="."><plain>Marais &amp; M.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1205" pm="."><plain>Wingf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1206" pm="."><plain>1998, basionym: Ceratocystiopsis proteae M.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1207" pm="."><plain>Wingf. et al. 1988, now regarded as Knoxdaviesia proteae M.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1209" pm="."><plain>Wingf. et al. 1988. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1210" pm="."><plain>Lasiosphaeris Clem., Gen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1211" pm="."><plain>Fungi: 173. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1212" pm="."><plain>1909. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1213" pm="."><plain>Lasiadelphia Réblová &amp; W. Gams in Fungal Divers. 46: 82. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1215" pm="."><plain>2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1216" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1217" pm="."><plain>Typus: L. hispida (Tode) Clem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1218" pm="."><plain>1909. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1219" pm="."><plain>Typus: L. lasiosphaeriae (W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1220" pm="."><plain>Gams) Réblová &amp; W. Gams 2011, now regarded as Lasiosphaeris hispida (Tode) Clem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1222" pm="."><plain>1909. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1223" pm="."><plain>Mammaria Ces. ex Rabenh. in Bot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1224" pm="."><plain>Zeit. 12: 190. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1225" pm="."><plain>1854. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1226" pm="."><plain>Pseudocercophora Subram. &amp; Sekar in J. Singapore Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1228" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1229" pm="."><plain>Sci. 15: 58. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1230" pm="."><plain>1986. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1231" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1232" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1233" pm="."><plain>Typus: M. echinobotryoides Ces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1234" pm="."><plain>1854. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1235" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. ingoldii Subram. &amp; Sekar 1986, now regarded as Mammaria echinobotryoides Ces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1236" pm="."><plain>1854. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1237" pm="."><plain>Melanospora Corda, Icon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1238" pm="."><plain>Fung. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1239" pm="."><plain>1: 24. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1240" pm="."><plain>1837. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1241" pm="."><plain>Gonatobotrys Corda, Pracht-Fl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1242" pm="."><plain>Eur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1243" pm="."><plain>Schimmelbild.: 9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1244" pm="."><plain>1839. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1245" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1246" pm="."><plain>Typus: M. zamiae Corda 1837. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1247" pm="."><plain>Typus: G. simplex Corda 1839, now regarded as Melanospora simplex (Corda) D. Hawks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1249" pm="."><plain>2016. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1250" pm="."><plain>Menispora Pers., Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1251" pm="."><plain>Eur. 1: 32. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1252" pm="."><plain>1822. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1253" pm="."><plain>Zignoëlla Sacc. in Michelia 1: 346. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1254" pm="."><plain>1878. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1255" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1256" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1257" pm="."><plain>Typus: M. glauca (Link) Pers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1258" pm="."><plain>1822, basionym: Camptosporium glaucum Link in Ehrenberg 1827. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1259" pm="."><plain>Typus: Z. pulviscula (Curr.) Sacc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1260" pm="."><plain>1878, now regarded as Menispora caesia Preuss 1851. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1261" pm="."><plain>Menisporopsis S. Hughes in Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1263" pm="."><plain>Pap. 48: 59. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1264" pm="."><plain>1952. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1265" pm="."><plain>Menisporopascus Matsush. in Matsush. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1266" pm="."><plain>Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1267" pm="."><plain>Mem. 10: 141. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1268" pm="."><plain>2003. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1269" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1270" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1271" pm="."><plain>Typus: M. theobromae S. Hughes 1952. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1273" pm="."><plain>Typus: M. kobensis Matsush. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1274" pm="."><plain>2003, now regarded as Menisporopsis kobensis Matsush. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1275" pm="."><plain>2003. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1276" pm="."><plain>Microdochium Syd. &amp; P. Syd. in Ann. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1278" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 22(3/6): 267. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1279" pm="."><plain>Published on 15 Nov 1924. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1280" pm="."><plain>Monographella Petr. in Ann. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1281" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 22 (1/2): 144. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1282" pm="."><plain>Published 20 Jun 1924. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1283" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF for Microdochium (Jun 1924) over Monographella (Nov 1924). </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1284" pm="."><plain>Typus: M. phragmitis Syd. &amp; P. Syd. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1286" pm="."><plain>1924. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1287" pm="."><plain>Typus: M. divergens (Rehm) Petr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1288" pm="."><plain>1924, basionym: Sphaerulina divergens Rehm 1913, now regarded as Microdochium nivale (Fr.) Samuels &amp; I.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1289" pm="."><plain>Hallett 1983. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1290" pm="."><plain>Monilochaetes Halst. ex Harter in J. Agric. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1292" pm="."><plain>Res. 5: 791. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1293" pm="."><plain>1916. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1294" pm="."><plain>Australiasca Sivan. &amp; Alcorn in Aust. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1295" pm="."><plain>Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1296" pm="."><plain>Bot. 15: 741. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1297" pm="."><plain>2002. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1298" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1299" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1300" pm="."><plain>Typus: M. infuscans Harter 1916. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1301" pm="."><plain>Typus: A. queenslandica Sivan. &amp; Alcorn 2002, now regarded as Monilochaetes camelliae (Alcorn &amp; Sivan.) Réblová et al. 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1302" pm="."><plain>Nemania Gray, Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1303" pm="."><plain>Arr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1304" pm="."><plain>Brit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1305" pm="."><plain>Pl. 1: 516. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1306" pm="."><plain>1821. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1307" pm="."><plain>Geniculosporium Chesters &amp; Greenh. in Trans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1308" pm="."><plain>Brit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1309" pm="."><plain>Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1310" pm="."><plain>Soc. 47: 400. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1311" pm="."><plain>1964. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1312" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1313" pm="."><plain>Type: N. serpens (Pers.) Gray 1821. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1314" pm="."><plain>Type: G. serpens Chesters &amp; Greenh. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1315" pm="."><plain>1964, now regarded as Nemania serpens (Pers.) Gray 1821. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1316" pm="."><plain>Neurospora Shear &amp; B.O. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1317" pm="."><plain>Dodge in J. Agric. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1319" pm="."><plain>Res. 34: 1025. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1320" pm="."><plain>1927. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1321" pm="."><plain>Chrysonilia Arx in Sydowia 34: 16. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1322" pm="."><plain>1981. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1323" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1324" pm="."><plain>Typus: N. sitophila Shear &amp; B.O. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1325" pm="."><plain>Dodge 1927. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1326" pm="."><plain>Typus: Chrysonilia sitophila (Mont.) Arx 1981, basionym: Penicillium sitophilum Mont. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1327" pm="."><plain>1843, now regarded as Neurospora sitophila Shear &amp; B.O. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1328" pm="."><plain>Dodge 1927. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1329" pm="."><plain>Nigrospora Zimm. in Centralbl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1330" pm="."><plain>Bakteriol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1331" pm="."><plain>Parasitenk., 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1332" pm="."><plain>Abt. 8: 220. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1333" pm="."><plain>1902. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1334" pm="."><plain>Khuskia H.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1335" pm="."><plain>Huds. in Trans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1336" pm="."><plain>Brit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1337" pm="."><plain>Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1338" pm="."><plain>Soc. 46: 358. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1339" pm="."><plain>1963. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1340" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1341" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1342" pm="."><plain>Typus: N. panici Zimm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1343" pm="."><plain>1902. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1344" pm="."><plain>Typus: K.oryzae H.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1345" pm="."><plain>Huds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1346" pm="."><plain>1963, now regarded as Nigrospora oryzae (Berk. &amp; Broome) Petch 1924. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1347" pm="."><plain>Ophiodothella (Henn.) Höhn. in Sitzungsber. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1348" pm="."><plain>Kaiserl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1349" pm="."><plain>Akad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1350" pm="."><plain>Wiss., Math.-Naturwiss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1351" pm="."><plain>Cl., Abt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1352" pm="."><plain>1 119: 940. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1353" pm="."><plain>1910, basionym: Ophiodothis subgen. Ophiodothella Henn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1354" pm="."><plain>1904. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1355" pm="."><plain>Acerviclypeatus Hanlin in Mycotaxon 37: 380. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1356" pm="."><plain>1990. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1357" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1358" pm="."><plain>Typus: O. atromaculans (Henn.) Höhn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1359" pm="."><plain>1910, basionym: Ophiodothis atromaculans Henn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1360" pm="."><plain>1904. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1361" pm="."><plain>Typus: A. poriformans Hanlin 1990, now regarded as Ophiodothella angustissima (Peck) Hanlin &amp; M.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1362" pm="."><plain>González 2013. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1363" pm="."><plain>Pestalotiopsis Steyaert in Bull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1364" pm="."><plain>Jard. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1365" pm="."><plain>Bot. État. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1366" pm="."><plain>Bruxelles 19: 300. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1367" pm="."><plain>1949. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1368" pm="."><plain>Pestalosphaeria M.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1369" pm="."><plain>Barr in Mycologia 67: 188. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1370" pm="."><plain>1975. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1371" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1372" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1373" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. guepinii (Desm.) Steyaert 1949, basionym: Pestalotia guepinii Desm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1374" pm="."><plain>1840. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1375" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. concentrica M.E. Barr 1975, now regarded as Pestalotiopsis guepinii var. macrotricha (Kleb.) B. Sutton 1961. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1377" pm="."><plain>Phaeoacremonium W. Gams et al. in Mycologia 88: 789. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1379" pm="."><plain>1996. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1380" pm="."><plain>Romellia Berl., Icon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1381" pm="."><plain>Fung. 3: 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1382" pm="."><plain>1900. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1383" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF for Phaeoacremonium 1996 over Romellia 1900 and Togninia 1900. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1384" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. parasiticum (Ajello et al.) W. Gams, et al. 1996. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1386" pm="."><plain>Typus: R. vibratilis (Fr.) Berl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1387" pm="."><plain>1900, basionym: Sphaeria vibratilis Fr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1388" pm="."><plain>1823, now Phaeoacremonium vibratilis (Fr.) Gramaje et al. 2015. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1389" pm="."><plain>Togninia Berl., Icon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1390" pm="."><plain>Fung. 3: 9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1391" pm="."><plain>1900. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1392" pm="."><plain>Typus: T. minima (Tul. &amp; C. Tul.) Berl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1394" pm="."><plain>1900, now regarded as Phaeoacremonium minimum (Tul. &amp; C. Tul.) D. Gramaje, et al. 2015. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1396" pm="."><plain>Plectosphaerella Kleb. in Phytopathol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1397" pm="."><plain>Z. 1: 43. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1398" pm="."><plain>1929. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1399" pm="."><plain>Plectosporium M.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1400" pm="."><plain>Palm et al. in Mycologia 87: 398. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1401" pm="."><plain>1995. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1402" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1403" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. cucumeris Kleb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1404" pm="."><plain>1929. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1405" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. tabacinum (J.F.H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1406" pm="."><plain>Beyma) M.E. Palm et al. 1995, now regarded as Plectosphaerella cucumeris Kleb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1407" pm="."><plain>1929. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1408" pm="."><plain>Pleurostoma Tul. &amp; C. Tul., Select. fung. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1410" pm="."><plain>Carpol. 2: 247. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1411" pm="."><plain>1863. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1412" pm="."><plain>Pleurostomophora Vijaykr. et al. in Stud. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1413" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 50: 390. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1414" pm="."><plain>2004. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1415" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1416" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. candollei Tul. &amp; C. Tul. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1418" pm="."><plain>1863. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1419" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. ootheca Vijaykr. et al. 2004, now regarded as Pleurostoma ootheca (Berk. &amp; M.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1420" pm="."><plain>Curtis) M.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1421" pm="."><plain>Barr 1985. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1422" pm="."><plain>Pleurothecium Höhn. in Ber. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1423" pm="."><plain>Deutsch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1424" pm="."><plain>Bot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1425" pm="."><plain>Ges. 37: 154. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1426" pm="."><plain>1919. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1427" pm="."><plain>Carpoligna F.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1428" pm="."><plain>Fernández &amp; Huhndorf in Mycologia 91: 253. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1429" pm="."><plain>1999. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1430" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1431" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1432" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. recurvatum (Morgan) Höhn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1433" pm="."><plain>1924, basionym: Acrothecium recurvatum Morgan 1895. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1434" pm="."><plain>Typus: C. pleurothecii F.A. Fernández &amp; Huhndorf 1999, now regarded as Pleurothecium recurvatum (Morgan) Höhn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1435" pm="."><plain>1924. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1436" pm="."><plain>Polystigma DC., in de Candolle &amp; Lamarck, Fl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1437" pm="."><plain>Franç., edn 3 6: 164. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1438" pm="."><plain>1815. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1439" pm="."><plain>Polystigmina Sacc., Syll. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1440" pm="."><plain>Fung. 3: 622. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1441" pm="."><plain>1884. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1442" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1443" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. rubrum (Pers.) DC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1444" pm="."><plain>1815, basionym: Xyloma rubrum Pers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1445" pm="."><plain>1800. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1446" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. rubra (Pers.) Sacc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1447" pm="."><plain>1884, basionym: Xyloma rubrum Pers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1448" pm="."><plain>1800, now regarded as Polystigma rubrum (Pers.) DC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1449" pm="."><plain>1815. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1450" pm="."><plain>Rhodoseptoria Naumov in Bull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1451" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1452" pm="."><plain>Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1453" pm="."><plain>Fr. 29: 278. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1454" pm="."><plain>1913. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1455" pm="."><plain>Typus: R. ussuriensis Naumov 1913, now regarded as Polystigma rubrum (Pers.) DC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1456" pm="."><plain>1815.. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1457" pm="."><plain>Pseudothiella Petr. in Hedwigia 68: 257. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1458" pm="."><plain>1928. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1459" pm="."><plain>Pseudothiopsella Petr. in Hedwigia 68: 259. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1460" pm="."><plain>1928. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1461" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1462" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. hirtellae (Henn.) Petr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1463" pm="."><plain>1928. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1464" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. hirtellae Petr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1465" pm="."><plain>1928, now regarded as Pseudothiella hirtellae (Henn.) Petr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1466" pm="."><plain>1928. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1467" pm="."><plain>Rosellinia De Not. in Giorn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1468" pm="."><plain>Bot. ital. 1: 334. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1469" pm="."><plain>1844. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1470" pm="."><plain>Dematophora R. Hartig in Untersuch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1472" pm="."><plain>Forstbot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1473" pm="."><plain>Inst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1474" pm="."><plain>München 3: 95. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1475" pm="."><plain>1883. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1476" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1477" pm="."><plain>Typus: R. aquila (Fr.) Ces. &amp; De Not. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1478" pm="."><plain>1844. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1479" pm="."><plain>Typus: D. necatrix R. Hartig 1883, now regarded as Rosellinia necatrix Berl. ex Prill. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1481" pm="."><plain>1904 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1482" pm="."><plain>Seimatosporium Corda, in Sturm, Deutschl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1483" pm="."><plain>Fl., 3 Abt. 3(13): 79. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1484" pm="."><plain>1833. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1485" pm="."><plain>Discostroma Clem., Gen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1486" pm="."><plain>Fung.: 50. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1487" pm="."><plain>1909. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1488" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1489" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1490" pm="."><plain>Typus: S. rosae Corda 1833. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1491" pm="."><plain>Typus: Discostroma rehmii (Schnabl) Clem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1492" pm="."><plain>1909, basionym: Curreya rehmii Schnabl 1892, a synonym of D. massarina (Sacc.) Arx 1974, basionym: Metasphaeria massarina Sacc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1493" pm="."><plain>1884, now regarded as Seimatosporium massarina (Sacc.) Jaklitsch &amp; Voglmayr 2016. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1494" pm="."><plain>Seiridium Nees, Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1495" pm="."><plain>Pilze: 22. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1496" pm="."><plain>1816. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1497" pm="."><plain>Blogiascospora Shoemaker et al. in Canad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1498" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1499" pm="."><plain>Bot. 44: 248. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1500" pm="."><plain>1966. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1501" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1502" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1503" pm="."><plain>Typus: S. marginatum Nees 1816. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1504" pm="."><plain>Typus: B. marginata (Fuckel) Shoemaker et al. 1966, basionym: Massaria marginata Fuckel 1873, now regarded as Seiridium marginatum Nees 1816. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1505" pm="."><plain>Sphaeronaemella P. Karst. in Hedwigia 23: 17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1507" pm="."><plain>1884. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1508" pm="."><plain>Gabarnaudia Samson &amp; W. Gams in Stud. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1510" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 6: 88. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1511" pm="."><plain>1974. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1512" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1513" pm="."><plain>Typus: S. helvellae (P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1514" pm="."><plain>Karst.) P. Karst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1516" pm="."><plain>1884, basionym: Sphaeria helvellae P. Karst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1518" pm="."><plain>1867. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1519" pm="."><plain>Typus: G. betae (Delacr.) Samson &amp; W. Gams, in Samson 1974, basionym: Oospora betae Delacr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1521" pm="."><plain>1897, now regarded as Sphaeronaemella betae (Delacr.) Z.W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1522" pm="."><plain>De Beer &amp; M.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1523" pm="."><plain>Wingf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1524" pm="."><plain>2013. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1525" pm="."><plain>Sporoschisma Berk. &amp; Broome, in Berkeley, Gard. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1526" pm="."><plain>Chron. 1847: 540. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1527" pm="."><plain>1847. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1528" pm="."><plain>Melanochaeta E. Müll. et al. in Revue Mycol. 33: 377. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1530" pm="."><plain>1969. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1531" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1532" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1533" pm="."><plain>Typus: S. mirabile Berk. &amp; Broome 1847. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1534" pm="."><plain>Typus: M. hemipsila (Berk. &amp; Broome) E. Müll., et al. 1969, basionym: Sphaeria hemipsila Berk. &amp; Broome 1873, now regarded as Sporoschisma hemipsila (Berk. &amp; Broome) Zelski et al. 2014. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1536" pm="."><plain>Sporoschismopsis Hol.-Jech. &amp; Hennebert in Bull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1537" pm="."><plain>Jard. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1538" pm="."><plain>Bot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1539" pm="."><plain>Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1540" pm="."><plain>Belgique. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1541" pm="."><plain>Bruxelles 42: 385. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1542" pm="."><plain>1972. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1543" pm="."><plain>Porosphaerellopsis Samuels &amp; E. Müll. in Sydowia 35: 143. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1545" pm="."><plain>1982. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1546" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1547" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1548" pm="."><plain>Typus: S. moravica Hol.-Jech. &amp; Hennebert 1972. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1549" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. sporoschismophora (Samuels &amp; E. Müll.) E. Müll. &amp; Samuels 1982, basionym: Porosphaeria sporoschismophora Samuels &amp; E. Müll. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1553" pm="."><plain>1978, now regarded as Sporoschismopsis sporoschismophora (Samuels &amp; E. Müll.) Réblová 2014. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1555" pm="."><plain>Stanjehughesia Subram. in Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1556" pm="."><plain>Indian Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1557" pm="."><plain>Sci., B, Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1558" pm="."><plain>Sci. 58(4): 184. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1559" pm="."><plain>1992. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1560" pm="."><plain>Umbrinosphaeria Réblová in Mycotaxon 71: 17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1561" pm="."><plain>1999. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1562" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1563" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1564" pm="."><plain>Type: S. hormiscioides (Corda) Subram. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1565" pm="."><plain>1992, basionym: Sporidesmium hormiscioides Corda 1838. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1566" pm="."><plain>Type: U. caesariata (Clinton &amp; Peck) Réblová 1999, basionym: Sphaeria caesariata Clinton &amp; Peck, in Peck 1878, now regarded as Stanjehughesia hormiscioides (Corda) Subram. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1567" pm="."><plain>1992. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1568" pm="."><plain>Stromatographium Höhn. in Denkschr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1569" pm="."><plain>Kaiserl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1570" pm="."><plain>Akad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1571" pm="."><plain>Wiss., Math.-Naturwiss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1572" pm="."><plain>Kl. 83: 37. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1573" pm="."><plain>1907. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1574" pm="."><plain>Fluviostroma Samuels &amp; E. Müll. in Sydowia 33: 283. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1576" pm="."><plain>1980. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1577" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1578" pm="."><plain>Typus: S. stromaticum (Berk.) Höhn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1579" pm="."><plain>1907, basionym: Stilbum stromaticum Berk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1580" pm="."><plain>1843. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1581" pm="."><plain>Typus: F. wrightii Samuels &amp; E. Müll. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1583" pm="."><plain>1980, now regarded as Stromatographium stromaticum (Berk.) Höhn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1584" pm="."><plain>1907. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1585" pm="."><plain>Togniniella Réblová et al. in Stud. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1586" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 50: 543. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1587" pm="."><plain>2004. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1588" pm="."><plain>Phaeocrella Réblová et al. in Stud. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1589" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 50: 545. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1590" pm="."><plain>2004. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1591" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1592" pm="."><plain>Typus: T. acerosa Réblová et al. 2004. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1593" pm="."><plain>Typus: P. acerosa Réblová et al. 2004, now regarded as Togniniella acerosa Réblová et al. 2004. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1594" pm="."><plain>Torpedospora Meyers in Mycologia 49: 496. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1595" pm="."><plain>1957. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1596" pm="."><plain>Glomerulispora Abdel-Wahab &amp; Nagah. in Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1597" pm="."><plain>Progr. 9: 552. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1598" pm="."><plain>2010. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1599" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1600" pm="."><plain>Typus: T. radiata Meyers 1957. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1601" pm="."><plain>Typus: G. mangrovei Abdel-Wahab &amp; Nagah. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1602" pm="."><plain>2010, now regarded as Torpedospora mangrovei (Abdel-Wahab &amp; Nagah.) E.B.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1603" pm="."><plain>Jones &amp; Abdel-Wahab 2016. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1604" pm="."><plain>Virgaria Nees, Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1605" pm="."><plain>Pilze: 54. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1606" pm="."><plain>1816. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1607" pm="."><plain>Ascovirgaria J.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1608" pm="."><plain>Rogers &amp; Y.M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1609" pm="."><plain>Ju in Canad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1610" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1611" pm="."><plain>Bot. 80: 478. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1612" pm="."><plain>2002. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1613" pm="."><plain>Asexual type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1614" pm="."><plain>Protection needed by NCF. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1615" pm="."><plain>Typus: V. nigra (Link) Nees 1817, basionym: Botrytis nigra Link 1809. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1616" pm="."><plain>Typus: A. occulta J.D. Rogers &amp; Y.M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1617" pm="."><plain>Ju 2002, now regarded as Virgaria nigra (Link) Nees 1817. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1618" pm="."><plain>Xylaria Hill ex Schrank, Baier. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1619" pm="."><plain>Fl. 1: 200. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1620" pm="."><plain>1789. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1621" pm="."><plain>Moelleroclavus Henn. in Hedwigia 41: 15. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1622" pm="."><plain>1902. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1623" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1624" pm="."><plain>Typus: X. hypoxylon (L.) Grev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1625" pm="."><plain>1824, basionym: Clavaria hypoxylon L. 1753. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1627" pm="."><plain>Typus: M. penicilliopsis Henn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1628" pm="."><plain>1902, now regarded as Xylaria penicilliopsis (Henn.) Y.M. Ju 2016. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1629" pm="."><plain>Xylocoremium J.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1630" pm="."><plain>Rogers in Mycologia 76: 913. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1631" pm="."><plain>1984. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1632" pm="."><plain>Typus: X. flabelliforme (Schwein.) J.D. Rogers 1984, basionym: Sphaeria flabelliformis Schwein., in Fries 1828, now regarded as Xylaria flabelliformis (Schwein.) Berk. &amp; M.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1633" pm="."><plain>Curtis 1868. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1634" pm="."><plain>Geniculisynnema Okane &amp; Nakagiri in Mycoscience 48: 245. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1635" pm="."><plain>2007. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1636" pm="."><plain>Typus: G. termiticola Okane &amp; Nakagiri 2007, now regared as Xylaria termiticola (Okane &amp; Nakagiri) Y.-M. Ju 2016. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1637" pm="."><plain>Arthroxylaria Seifert &amp; W. Gams in Czech Mycol. 53: 299. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1639" pm="."><plain>2002. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="1640" pm="."><plain>Typus: A. elegans Seifert &amp; W. Gams 2002, now regarded as Xylaria benjaminii Seifert &amp; W. Gams 2016. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
