<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Gen Virol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Gen. Virol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JGV</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of General Virology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1317</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1465-2099</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Microbiology Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5882086</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29165219</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">000875</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jgv.0.000875</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Animal</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Small DNA Viruses</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Porcine circovirus type 1 was undetected in vaccine but could be cultured in the cell substrate of Lanzhou lamb rotavirus vaccine </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="recto-page-foot"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jgv.microbiologyresearch.org">http://jgv.microbiologyresearch.org</ext-link></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Qingchuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Jialiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yueyue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Lili</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Tai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><institution>Division of Enteric Viral Vaccines, National Institutes for Food and Drug Control</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing 100050</addr-line>, <country>PR China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>*Correspondence:</bold> Tai Guo, <email xlink:href="enterovirus@nifdc.org.cn">enterovirus@nifdc.org.cn</email><italic>or</italic><email xlink:href="guotai@nifdc.org.cn">guotai@nifdc.org.cn</email></corresp><fn id="FN1"><label>†</label><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>These authors contributed equally to this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>99</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2018 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="jgv-99-103.pdf"/><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In 2010, Rotarix was found to be contaminated with infectious porcine circovirus type 1 (PCV1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>In China, the Lanzhou lamb rotavirus (LLR) vaccine is the only vaccine used to prevent rotavirus disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>From 2006 to September 2014, more than 54 million doses of LLR vaccines have been lot released. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>It is a safety issue whether PCV1 is present in the LLR vaccine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Although the cell substrate of LLR, bovine kidney (BK), is different from that of Rotarix, we have investigated the cell’s permissivity for PCV1 by both infectivity and full-length PCR analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We have assessed the LLR using a quantitative PCR (qPCR) assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>A total of 171 random batches of LLR final products over a period of 5 years were tested, and no PCV1 was detected (0/171). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Infectivity studies showed that two strains of PCV1, the PCV1-prototype, which was derived from PK-15 cells, and the mutant, PCV1-GSK, which was isolated from Rotarix, were capable of replicating in BK cells over a wide m.o.i. ranging from 10 to 0.01. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>After culture for 6 days, copies of PCV1-prototype DNA were higher than those of PCV1-GSK on average. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The genome of the virus was detected at 6 days post-infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In summary, the LLR vaccine is free of PCV1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, because PCV1 can replicate in the BK cell substrate, manufacturers need to be vigilant in monitoring for this adventitious agent. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>Porcine circovirus</kwd><kwd>Adventitious agents</kwd><kwd>Rotavirus vaccine</kwd><kwd>Infectivity study</kwd><kwd>Safety</kwd><kwd>LLR</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="sp1">National High Technology Research and Development Program</funding-source><award-id rid="sp1">2006AA02A206 &amp; 2012AA02A402</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="sp2">The 12th Five-year National Science and Technology Major Project</funding-source><award-id rid="sp2">2012ZX10004702</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="sp3">The Research and Development Fund for the Young and Middle-aged</funding-source><award-id rid="sp3">2011B02</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OpenAccessEmbargo</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1-2"><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>In 2010, porcine circovirus type 1 (PCV1) was discovered in Rotarix [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>While only nucleic acid of PCV1 and PCV2 was found in RotaTeq without intact PCV virions, infectious PCV1 was shown to be present in Rotarix [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The US Food and Drug Administration (FDA), vaccine manufacturers, and academic scientists confirmed the original results and investigated the source of contamination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>It turned out that the Vero cell lines used to manufacture the vaccine were contaminated with porcine circovirus (PCV) [3] and arose most likely from the porcine trypsin used in the propagation of the Vero cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>PCV was first described as an unexpected contamination in the PK-15 (porcine kidney cells) cell line [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>There are two types of PCV: PCV1 and porcine circovirus type 2 (PCV2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>PCV2 causes post-weaning multisystemic wasting syndrome (PWMS) in swine, while PCV1 has not been shown to cause any porcine disease [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>PCV DNA has been detected in 5 % of stool samples from US adults [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In another study which investigated whether PCV2 sequences could be detected in the stool of recipients of RotaTeq (which is contaminated with PCV2 DNA), 235 out of 826 samples (28.5 %) from 59 vaccine recipients were positive for PCV2 DNA [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>However, there was no evidence that this DNA shedding was associated with viable PCV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Neither PCV1 nor PCV2 is known to be pathogenic in humans [1, 7, 8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, PC?V is a novel adventitious agent that needs to be considered by the vaccine industry, especially since PCV infection is distributed worldwide in swine [9–12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Unintentional introduction of adventitious agents is a recognized potential concern due to their exposure to animal-derived raw materials, such as porcine trypsin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In addition, PCV is highly resistant to many widely used inactivation procedures [13, 14] and thus the risk of contamination is raised. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>These two rotavirus vaccines – Rotarix and RotaTeq – are widely used worldwide but not in China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In China, the LLR vaccine is produced in BK cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>From 2006 to September 2014, more than 54 million doses of the LLR vaccine have been lot released [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Considering the similarity of the attenuated live vaccines and the manufacture processes among the rotavirus vaccines, an investigation for PCV1 in the BK cell substrate was warranted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>However, there are differences between China’s LLR vaccine and the other vaccines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The Vero cell lines used to produce Rotarix and RotaTeq are consistent batch-to-batch and easier to monitor because of the stability of the cell substrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In contrast, BK cells are prepared with fresh bovine kidney (BK) cells and new cells are required for each batch of vaccine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Thus, the potential for contamination is increased and it is important to investigate whether the PCV1 was cultured in the BK cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Consequently, the LLR final products should be monitored for PCV1 at the same time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>In this study, we focused on detection of PCV1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="s1-3"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2-3-1"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>DNA sequencing andblast results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The full-length genomes of two PCV1 strains were amplified by PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The full-length amplified genomes of PCV1 were sequenced to confirm the identity. blast results showed that the PCV1-prototype was the same genome as that previously reported for PCV1 in PK-15 cells (GenBank accession number: JN133303.1), while the genome of PCV1-GSK was identical to the PCV1 in Rotarix (GenBank accession number: HM143844.1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>There are eight nucleotide differences between the two sequences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2-3-2"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Results of infectivity studies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Results of infectivity assay are shown in Fig. 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The mock-infection groups (without virus inoculation) were PCV1 negative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>After 6 days of culture, the experimental groups were PCV1 positive with or without d-glucosamine pretreatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>However, pretreatment of d-glucosamine (Fig. 1a, c) significantly enhanced the viral replication at 3 days post-infection (p.i.) compared with the group without pretreatment (Fig. 1b, d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>According to the data 6 days p.i., positive signals were detected from the infection with 106 copies ml−1 (m.o.i.=10) and 103 copies ml−1 (m.o.i.=0.01), which means that a small quantity of PCV1 could be enough to infect the BK cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>It is worth noting that using the same copies of PCV1 to infect the BK cells, the replication ratio differed between the two strains of PCV1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>At 6 days p.i., copies of the PCV1-prototype are 13.3-fold (m.o.i.=10), 40.6-fold (m.o.i.=1), 85.3-fold (m.o.i.=0.1) and 50.7-fold (m.o.i.=0.01) higher than those of PCV1-GSK. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>PCV1 quantification results after the infectivity assay on BK cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The PCV1-prototype group (a and b) and the PCV1-GSK group (c and d) were pretreatedwith d-glucosamine (a and c) or not (b and d) before inoculation. m.o.i. ranges from 10 to 0.01 with a mock-infection group which remained negative throughout. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jgv-99-103-g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The genome of PCV1 was detected 112 with full-length primers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The 3 days p.i. samples were negative results while the 6 days p.i. were partly positive (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>PCV1 full-length amplification results after the infectivity assay on BK cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>(a) Without d-glucosamine pretreatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>(b) With d-glucosamine pretreatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>P and G represent the PCV1-prototype virus and the PCV1-GSK virus, respectively. m.o.i. and sampling time points are marked above and below. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>PC and NC represent the positive and negative controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jgv-99-103-g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2-3-3"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Results of LLR vaccine surveillance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>From 2010–2012 and 2014–2015, 171 batches of the LLR vaccine were chosen at random. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>All these vaccines were stored at 2~8 °C as required. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Intact vaccine packages were confirmed before use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The whole DNA was extracted and tested by qPCR methods as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>All of these vaccine batches showed negative results for PCV1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Batch number information is listed in Table S1 (available with the online version of this article). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s1-4"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Over the years, the presence of adventitious agents in vaccines has been a recurring problem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>From SV40 in polio vaccines [(16] and bacteriophages in live viral vaccines [17, 18], to reverse transcriptase activity in measles and other vaccines [19], and PCV in rotavirus vaccines [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>It is not clear whether these adventitious agents are potential or real threats to human health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>According to subsequent studies, PCV1 infects not only porcine source cells, but also cells from other species, such as the Vero cells in the recent incident, which indicates that PCV1 is capable of using more than one kind of cell as a host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>GlaxoSmithKline (GSK) investigated Rotarix extensively and the materials used at different stages of the production process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>These assessments found the presence of PCV1 DNA in master and working cellular banks, as well as master and working viral seed stocks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Infectivity studies showed that PCV1 sequences in Rotarix bulks and final products were infectious. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Although final products of GSK’s other live viral vaccines were shown to be clear of PCV1, the inactivated poliovirus vaccine (IPV) harvest tested positive for PCV1, an unexpected contamination derived from the same cell bank as that used to produce Rotarix [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, no infectious virus was detected in IPV bulks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>It was concluded that the source of PCV-1 contamination was non-irradiated trypsin that was used in the mid-1990s to manufacture the Vero cell banks [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Once passaged cells are contaminated by the infectious and intact PCV1, which persists without causing any visible cell changes, it is almost impossible to eradicate these agents. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>PCV was reported as an unexpected contamination in the PK-15 (porcine kidney cells) cell line [4], and thus we screened PCV1 in materials for cell culture in our laboratory to avoid confusing results before we started infectivity studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Samples from the culture medium, fetal bovine serum (FBS), trypsin (for cell culture and rotavirus activation, porcine-derived and bovine-derived), l-glutamine, penicillin and streptomycin, PBS and HEPES were tested and were found to be PCV1-free (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>RD (human rhabdomyosarcoma cells), MA104 (African green monkey kidney cells), HEK293 (human embryonic kidney cells), CHO-K1 (Chinese hamster ovary cells), Vero (African green monkey kidney cells) and MRC-5 (human fetal lung fibroblast cells), which are widely used for vaccine production and in quality control assays, were also used in infectivity studies along with BK cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>PCV1 replicated significantly in Vero and BK cells while the other cell lines involved could not support PCV1 replication (data not shown), suggesting that PCV1 has a restricted host range. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>However, our results indicated that both strains of PCV1 have the ability to spread across species: from PK-15 to Vero (pig to monkey) and to BK (pig to cattle). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The capacity of PCV1 to cross host species brings new concerns to the vaccine industry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Finding that PCV1 is able to infect CD4+, CD8+, CD14+, CD19+ and CD56+ human cells [21], and the observation of productive PCV1 infection in a subclone of a human hepatocellular carcinoma cell line [22] suggests potential risks for humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The consequence of long-term contact with live PCV1 remains uncertain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>In our study, two strains of PCV1 were found to be able to infect BK cells within a range of m.o.i. from 10 to 0.01. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>This indicates the permissivity of BK cells for PCV1 and also demonstrates that PCV1 could be a contaminant in specific cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Although the virus needs some special conditions (e.g. d-glucosamine) for optimal infection and replication, previous studies demonstrate that some commonly used substances (e.g. NH4Cl) might be able to achieve the same function [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Even without d-glucosamine being used for PCV12 infection in vitro, after 6 days of cultivation the genome of PCV was detected in infected BK cells, suggesting the possible formation of the progeny virus. d-glucosamine accelerated the replication of virus at 3 days p.i. but did not increase the total amount of virus at 6 days p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>However, the toxicity of d-glucosamine on low passage cells might affect the ratio of cell survival and decrease the virus production. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The BK cells used to produce the LLR vaccine are different from Vero cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>BK cells are only used within a finite period and then changed for the next batch of the LLR vaccine, which has advantages and disadvantages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Changing the production cells allows less time for PCV1 to adapt to the heterogeneous cells and decreases the possibility of permanent contamination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Using immortalized cells such as Vero, the vaccine manufacturing process might have an increased chance of being exposed to such an adventitious agent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Once established, though, the master cell bank is not changed during manufacture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>This brings better consistency not only for vaccine quality, but also for the control of adventitious agents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>In contrast, control of BK cells consumes much more energy because the cells are frequently changed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Thus, prevention and detection of adventitious agents are challenging. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The introduction of new technologies makes it possible to detect agents that we were unable to detect before, such as the product-enhanced reverse transcriptase (PERT) assay [19] for agents with transcriptase activity, and microarrays and high-throughput sequencing [1] for other potential contaminants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The virus itself does not remain stable genomically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The PCV1-GSK strain, compared with the PCV1-prototype, has eight point mutations, which might cause attenuation or adaption to the BK cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Certainly, the PCV1-replicating capacity will require further study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The contaminated Vero cells and the vaccine final product might need to be cleansed of PCV1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Q Sepharose Fast Flow chromatography has been investigated with promising results [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Both the discovery of new adventitious agents and the solution of problems bring demands for development of technology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>We have monitored the LLR vaccine over 5 years, including 171 batches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>All of these rotavirus vaccine batches were PCV1 negative, suggesting the safety of the LLR vaccine with respect to PCV1 contamination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>This may partly be a consequence of the cells used and of conventional monitoring. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>However, the production process of the vaccine is complicated, containing animal sera and other raw biological materials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The use of BK cells as the cell substrate for vaccine production requires attention to PCV1 control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Using PCV1 test is recommended in multiple steps of LLR vaccine production and in the screening of raw materials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Long-term surveillance is still essential. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="s1-5"><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Although the BK cells are susceptible to PCV1, we have shown that 171 batches of the LLR vaccine are free from PCV1 contamination over 5 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>We should strengthen our monitoring and incorporate the PCV1 test item as routine in the future to ensure the safety of vaccines and the health of recipients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods" id="s1-6"><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2-6-1"><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>BK cells were courtesy of Lanzhou Institute of Biological Products (LIBP, Lanzhou City, Gansu Province, PR China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Vero cells (African green monkey kidney; CCL-81) were obtained from the American Type Culture Collection (ATCC, Manassas, VA, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>BK cells were grown in minimum essential medium (MEM, Invitrogen) supplemented with 10 % FBS and 100 U ml−1 of penicillin and 100 µg ml−1 of streptomycin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The second and third passages were used in vaccine manufacture of LLR, so the BK cells were confined into the first four passages in our study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The Vero cell line was cultured in Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium (DMEM, Invitrogen) supplemented with 10 % fetal bovine serum (FBS, Invitrogen), 10 µM HEPES (ThermoFisher) and 100 U ml−1 of penicillin and 100 µg ml−1 of streptomycin (Thermo Fisher). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Both of these cells were grown at 37 °C in a 5 % CO2 atmosphere. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>BK cells were passaged at a ratio of 1 : 3 every 3 days using trypsin-EDTA (0.05 % trypsin, 0.02 % EDTA-4Na; Invitrogen) while the Vero cell lines were passaged at a ratio of 1 : 8 every 6 days with the same reagents. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2-6-2"><title><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Virus </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Two PCV1 strains were used in our study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The PCV1-prototype was isolated from the PK-15 cell line, which was cultured as recommended by the suppliers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The prototype virus was harvested by freeze-thawing three times when the PK-15 cells reached 100 % confluence in flasks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>PCV1-GSK was isolated from the Rotarix vaccine as described below. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The vaccine was concentrated using a 100 000 MW centrifugal filter (Merck Millipore) and washed with DMEM (FBS-free) to increase the titre and decrease the osmotic pressure caused by the sucrose in the vaccine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The concentrated suspension was heated at 70 °C for 1 h to inactivate rotavirus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>One milliliter of virus suspension with an amount of about 10 times of the end product vaccine was applied to Vero cells in 25 cm2 flasks at 48 h after cell passaging and inoculated for 2 h in 37 °C atmosphere. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was discarded, the cells were washed three times with PBS, and 10 ml FBS-free DMEM was added to the flask as a maintenance medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Vero cells were freeze-thawed three times at 4 days p.i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The viral lysates were centrifuged at 5000 g for 30 min to harvest the supernatant for the next inoculation process using the same procedure as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The titres of both the PCV1-prototype and PCV1-GSK were determined using a qPCR assay as described below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2-6-3"><title><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>DNA preparations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Total cell DNA was prepared from cell pellets using QIAamp DNA Blood Mini Kit (Qiagen) following the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>DNA preparation of LLR vaccine-infected cells was similar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>A 200 µl sample was applied to the preparation, and 50 µl DNA was extracted, enabling the original titre of PCV1 to be calculated after the quantification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Prepared DNA was tested with NanoPhotometer (IMPLEN) and samples of A260/A280 ratio ranging from 1.80 to 2.00 were used in the PCR and qPCR assays. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2-6-4"><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>PCR and qPCR assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The primers used to amplify the full-length PCV1 genome for sequencing are listed in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The full-length PCR reaction conditions were as follows: 95 °C for 5 min, followed by 40 cycles of 95 °C for 30 s, 48 °C for 1 min, 72 °C for 2 min, and terminated by 72 °C for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The qPCR assay was performed using primers and a probe directed at the replicase gene of PCV1, which are shown in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Reaction conditions for qPCR were as follows: 50 °C for 2 min, 95 °C for 10 min, followed by 40 cycles of 95 °C for 15 s, 60 °C for 1 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The PCR and qPCR methods have been described previously [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>PCR assays were done in a Veriti 96 Well Thermal Cycler (Applied Biosystems) while qPCR assays were done in a 7500 Real Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Primers and the probe used to amplify the full-length and quantitative PCV1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Name </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Direction </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Sequence </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Position </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>PCV1-full length </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Forward </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>GCATGGATCCATCACTTCGTAATGGT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>1010–1035 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Reverse </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>GCATGGATCCAAAAAAGACTCAGTAA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>1035–1010 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>PCV1-RTPCR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Forward </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>TGGCCCGCAGTATTTTGATT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>785–804 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Reverse </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>CAGCTGGGACAGCAGTTGAG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>856–838 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Probe </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>FAM-CCAGCAATCAGGCCCCCCAGGAAT-TAMRA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>806–829 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2-6-5"><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>PCV1 sequencing and analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The amplified full-length fragments of PCV1 were analysed by agarose gel electrophoresis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The gel bands of approximately 1760 bp were excised and purified with QIAquick Gel Extraction Kit (Qiagen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The products were cloned into pEASY-T3 Vector (Transgene) and transformed into competent cells (Transgene) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Plasmids extracted from bacteria were analysed by ABI 3730 DNA Analyzer (Applied Biosystems) using M13 sequencing primers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Sequence analysis was done using nucleotide blast. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2-6-6"><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>PCV1 infectivity studies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>BK cells were passaged and counted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Cell suspensions were diluted to 105 cells ml−1 and cultured in 12-well plates, 1 ml well−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>After culture in 37 °C, 5 % CO2 atmosphere for 48 h, the cells were washed with prewarmed PBS three times. d-glucosamine 300 mM (Sigma-Aldrich) was applied to the cells and incubated in 37 °C for 30 min to promote the replication of PCV1 [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>FBS-free MEM was used in the control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was extracted and cells were washed with PBS three times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Two strains of PCV1 were serially diluted at a ratio of 1 : 10 to obtain 106 to 103 copies ml−1 virus, added to the cells and incubated at 37 °C for 2 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The mock-infection group was inoculated with FBS-free MEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, cells were washed three times with PBS and FBS-free MEM was added as the maintenance medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>This time point was set as time 0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>After 3 and 6 days incubation, the cells were freeze-thawed three times to release the viruses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The viral samples were then purified to extract total DNA which was used for in PCR and qPCR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2-6-7"><title><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Detection of PCV1 in LLR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Sampling of the LLR vaccine from 2010–2012 and 2014–2015 was performed on samples selected at random. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>DNA of each batch was purified and tested by the qPCR assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>The results were analysed using 7500 Software 2.0.5 (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack id="ack1"><title>Funding information</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>This work was supported in part by the 12th Five-year National Science and Technology Major Project (No. 2012ZX10004702) and the National High Technology Research and Development Program (2006AA02A206 and 2012AA02A402) sponsored by Ministry of Science and Technology of the PR of China, and the Research and Development Fund for the Young and Middle-aged (2011B02) sponsored by National Institutes for Food and Drug Control. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><ack id="ack2"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p content-type="COI-statement">The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest.</p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn id="FN2"><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: FDA, Food and Drug Administration; GSK, GlaxoSmithKline; IPV, inactivated poliovirus vaccine; LLR, Lanzhou lamb rotavirus; PCV, porcine circovirus; PERT, product-enhanced reverse transcriptase. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="SUPPL"><fn id="FN3"><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>One supplementary table is available with the online version of this article. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app content-type="supplementary-data"><title>Supplementary Data</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp1"><object-id pub-id-type="file-size">191</object-id><caption><title>Supplementary File 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="jgv-99-103-s001.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></app></app-group></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>1VictoriaJGWangCJonesMSJaingCMcloughlinKViral nucleic acids in live-attenuated vaccines: detection of minority variants and an adventitious virusJ Virol2010846033604010.1128/JVI.02690-09<?supplied-pmid 20375174?>20375174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R2"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>2McclenahanSDKrausePRUhlenhautCMolecular and infectivity studies of porcine circovirus in vaccinesVaccine2011294745475310.1016/j.vaccine.2011.04.087<?supplied-pmid 21569811?>21569811 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R3"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>3DubinGToussaintJFCassartJPHoweBBoyceDInvestigation of a regulatory agency enquiry into potential porcine circovirus type 1 contamination of the human rotavirus vaccine, rotarix: approach and outcomeHum Vaccin Immunother201392398240810.4161/hv.25973<?supplied-pmid 24056737?>24056737 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R4"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>4TischerIRaschRTochtermannGCharacterization of papovavirus-and picornavirus-like particles in permanent pig kidney cell linesZentralbl Bakteriol Orig A1974226153167<?supplied-pmid 4151202?>4151202 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R5"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>5AllanGKrakowkaSEllisJCharreyreCDiscovery and evolving history of two genetically related but phenotypically different viruses, porcine circoviruses 1 and 2Virus Res20121644910.1016/j.virusres.2011.09.013<?supplied-pmid 21945213?>21945213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R6"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>6HewitsonLThissenJBGardnerSNMcloughlinKSGlausserMKScreening of viral pathogens from pediatric ileal tissue samples after vaccinationAdv Virol2014201411010.1155/2014/720585<?supplied-pmid 24778651?>24778651 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R7"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>7LiLKapoorASlikasBBamideleOSWangCMultiple diverse circoviruses infect farm animals and are commonly found in human and chimpanzee fecesJ Virol2010841674168210.1128/JVI.02109-09<?supplied-pmid 20007276?>20007276 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R8"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>8KuehnBMFDA: benefits of rotavirus vaccination outweigh potential contamination riskJAMA2010304303110.1001/jama.2010.863<?supplied-pmid 20606142?>20606142 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R9"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>9RayeWMuhlingJWarfeLBuddleJRPalmerCThe detection of porcine Circovirus in the Australian pig herdAust Vet J20058330030410.1111/j.1751-0813.2005.tb12747.x<?supplied-pmid 15957393?>15957393 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R10"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>10TischerIMieldsWWolffDVagtMGriemWStudies on epidemiology and pathogenicity of porcine circovirusArch Virol19869127127610.1007/BF01314286<?supplied-pmid 3778212?>3778212 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R11"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>11DulacGCAfsharAPorcine circovirus antigens in PK-15 cell line (ATCC CCL-33) and evidence of antibodies to circovirus in Canadian pigsCan J Vet Res198953431<?supplied-pmid 2686830?>2686830 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R12"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>12ZhaiSLChenSNXuZHTangMHWangFGPorcine Circovirus type 2 in China: an update on and insights toits prevalence and controlVirol J2014124393133 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R13"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>13AllanGMPhenixKVToddDMcnultyMSSome biological and physico-chemical properties of porcine circovirusZentralbl Veterinarmed B199441172610.1111/j.1439-0450.1994.tb00201.x<?supplied-pmid 7941842?>7941842 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R14"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>14WelchJBienekCGompertsESimmondsPResistance of porcine circovirus and chicken Anemia virus to virus inactivation procedures used for blood productsTransfusion2006461951195810.1111/j.1537-2995.2006.01003.x<?supplied-pmid 17076851?>17076851 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R15"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>15duJLanZLiuYLiuYYuQEvaluation of oral Lanzhou lamb rotavirus vaccine via passive transfusion with CD4+/CD8+ T lymphocytesVirus Res201621710110610.1016/j.virusres.2016.03.006<?supplied-pmid 27025573?>27025573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R16"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>16ShahKNathansonNHuman exposure to SV40: review and commentAm J Epidemiol197610311210.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a112197<?supplied-pmid 174424?>174424 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R17"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>17MerrilCRFriedmanTBAttallahAFGeierMRKrellKIsolation of bacteriophages from commercial seraIn Vitro19728919310.1007/BF02615965<?supplied-pmid 4567658?>4567658 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R18"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>18ChuFCJohnsonJBOrrHCProbstPGPetriccianiJCBacterial virus contamination of fetal bovine seraIn Vitro19739313410.1007/BF02615986<?supplied-pmid 4201071?>4201071 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R19"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>19PyraHBöniJSchüpbachJUltrasensitive retrovirus detection by a reverse transcriptase assay based on product enhancementProc Natl Acad Sci USA1994911544154810.1073/pnas.91.4.1544<?supplied-pmid 7509077?>7509077 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R20"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>20PetriccianiJSheetsRGriffithsEKnezevicIAdventitious agents in viral vaccines: lessons learned from 4 case studiesBiologicals20144222323610.1016/j.biologicals.2014.07.003<?supplied-pmid 25135887?>25135887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R21"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>21Arteaga-TroncosoGGuerra-InfanteFRosales-MontañoLMDíaz-GarcíaFJFlores-MedinaSUltrastructural alterations in human blood leukocytes induced by porcine circovirus type 1 infectionXenotransplantation20051246547210.1111/j.1399-3089.2005.00249.x<?supplied-pmid 16202070?>16202070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R22"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>22BeachNMCórdobaLKenneySPMengXJProductive infection of human hepatocellular carcinoma cells by porcine circovirus type 1Vaccine2011297303730610.1016/j.vaccine.2011.06.097<?supplied-pmid 21742002?>21742002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R23"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>23MisinzoGNauwynckHInhibition of endosomal-lysosomal system acidification inporcine epithelial cells enhances porcine Circovirus 2 infectionIn Proceedings of the 5th International Symposium on Emerging and Re-Emerging Pig DiseasesKrakow, Poland2007p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R24"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>24YangBWangHHoCLesterPChenQPorcine circovirus (PCV) removal by Q sepharose fast flow chromatographyBiotechnol Prog2013291464147110.1002/btpr.1804<?supplied-pmid 24039195?>24039195 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R25"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>25TischerIPetersDRaschRPociuliSReplication of porcine circovirus: induction by glucosamine and cell cycle dependenceArch Virol198796395710.1007/BF01310989<?supplied-pmid 3619654?>3619654 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
