<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">R Soc Open Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">R Soc Open Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RSOS</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">royopensci</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Royal Society Open Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2054-5703</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Royal Society Publishing</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5792889</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsos.171006</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">rsos171006</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1001</subject><subject>129</subject><subject>60</subject><subject>197</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Biology (Whole Organism)</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="leader"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Paternity and kin structure among neighbouring groups in wild bonobos at Wamba </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short">Genetic structure among bonobo groups</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2194-0387</contrib-id><name><surname>Ishizuka</surname><given-names>Shintaro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kawamoto</surname><given-names>Yoshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sakamaki</surname><given-names>Tetsuya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tokuyama</surname><given-names>Nahoko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Toda</surname><given-names>Kazuya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Okamura</surname><given-names>Hiroki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Furuichi</surname><given-names>Takeshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1"><label>1</label><institution>Primate Research Institute, Kyoto University, Inuyama, Aichi 484-8506</institution>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label><institution>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science, Kojimachi, Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 102-0083</institution>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="af3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Evolutionary Studies of Biosystems, The Graduate University for Advanced Studies</institution>, <addr-line>Hayama, Kanagawa 240-0193</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Author for correspondence: Shintaro Ishizuka e-mail: <email>ishizuka.shintaro.37x@st.kyoto-u.ac.jp</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material is available online at https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.c.3980784. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>171006</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2018 The Authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>Published by the Royal Society under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license><?release-delay 0|0?></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="rsos171006.pdf"/><self-uri content-type="reviewer_comments" xlink:href="rsos171006_review_history.pdf"/><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Although both bonobos and chimpanzees are male-philopatric species, outcomes of male–male reproductive competition seem to be more closely associated with mating success in chimpanzees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>This suggests that the extent of male reproductive skew is lower in bonobos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>In addition, between-group male–male reproductive competition is more lethal in chimpanzees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>This suggests that between-group differentiation in male kinship is lower in bonobos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>We analysed the paternity of 17 offspring in two bonobo groups and estimated the relatedness of individuals among three neighbouring groups by using DNA extracted from non-invasive samples at Wamba, in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The alpha males sired at least nine of 17 offspring. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>This supports a previous finding that the male reproductive skew is higher in bonobos than that in chimpanzees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Average relatedness among males within groups was significantly higher than that among males across groups, whereas there was no significant difference among females between within and across groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>These results are consistent with male philopatry, highly skewed reproductive success of males and female dispersal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Higher average relatedness among males within groups suggest that the differences in hostility towards males of different groups between bonobos and chimpanzees may be explained by factors other than kinship. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>bonobos</kwd><kwd>male philopatry</kwd><kwd>male–male reproductive competition</kwd><kwd>reproductive skew</kwd><kwd>genetic differentiation between groups</kwd><kwd>kin structure</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>17J09827</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science Grant-in-aid for Scientific Research</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>17255005, 22255007 and 26257408</award-id><award-id>19405015, 25304019, 25257407, 16H02753</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science Core-to-Core Program</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2009–2011, 2012–2014 and 2015–2017</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Japan Ministry of the Environment Global Environment Research Fund</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>D-1007</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Promotion of Science Strategic Young Overseas Visits Program for Acceleration Brain Circulation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>S2508</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January, 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><label>1.</label><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Males of group-living animals compete to gain higher dominance ranks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>This could be explained by the fact that higher dominance ranks are associated with greater reproductive success [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>In cases where female receptivity is not asynchronous, the number of receptive females is limited at the same time, which enables a few males to monopolize breeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Therefore, in various taxa of group-living animals, reproductive success is highly skewed towards males with higher dominance ranks [2–4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Although our understandings of these systems mostly come from the previous studies on female-philopatric species, in which females remain in their natal groups and males disperse from their natal groups after reaching maturity, some species of group-living animals occur in male-philopatric societies (reviewed in [5]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In male-philopatric species, it is predicted that some males within groups are related by kinship. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Therefore, males of male-philopatric species may be able to gain the inclusive fitness via the reproductive success of other males related to them [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>This suggests that the mechanism of male–male reproductive competition may differ between male-philopatric species and female-philopatric species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>For a more complete understanding of male–male reproductive competition in group-living animals, male-philopatric species should be investigated to clarify the mechanism of reproductive competition among males which are potentially related by kinship. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Comparisons between bonobos (Pan paniscus) and chimpanzees (Pan troglodytes) are effective for understanding male–male reproductive competition in male-philopatric species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>These two species are the most closely related species with one another, and share many traits in terms of social systems, including male philopatry, female dispersal, multi-male/multi-female group composition and fission–fusion dynamics [7–10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>However, the intensity of male–male competition is remarkably different between these two species: aggression between chimpanzee males can be lethal and sometimes results in death, whereas that between bonobo males is more moderate and occurs less frequently [7,8,11,12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>One potential factor to explain the less intensive reproductive competition among bonobo males is the extended periods of female sexual receptivity and attractiveness [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>This would modulate the intensity of male–male competition for mating opportunities and would increase the potential for female choice [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>It follows, then, that the extent of reproductive skew among bonobo males is predicted to be lower than that among chimpanzee males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>A recent study from LuiKotale reported that the male reproductive skew is higher in bonobos than in chimpanzees [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>However, there have been many studies on the reproductive skew in chimpanzees compared with only two studies on the reproductive skew in bonobos [15,16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>It could be expected that comparing male reproductive skew between these two species could help to elucidate whether the intensity of male–male reproductive competition can lead to greater reproductive outcomes in male-philopatric species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is necessary to obtain more data on the reproductive skew among bonobo males. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>To understand male–male reproductive competition, it is necessary to investigate kinship patterns among males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Kinship regulates affinity or antagonism in social interactions [17,18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Therefore, kinship patterns among males could affect the intensity of reproductive competition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Although some males within groups could be related by kinship in male-philopatric species, some previous studies reported that the patterns of alliance formation or cooperative interactions among males were not explained by kinship (chimpanzees [19] and bottlenose dolphins [20]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>However, between-group male-male reproductive competition potentially can be explained by kinship. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Although both bonobos and chimpanzees are male-philopatric species and it is predicted that males are more closely related within groups than between groups, the antagonism towards males of different groups is completely different between these two species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>For example, chimpanzee males sometimes make lethal coalitionary attacks and kill males of different groups, whereas bonobo males do not make such attacks [21–24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>This difference may be explained by the fact that between-group differentiation in male kinship is greater in chimpanzees than in bonobos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>This prediction is supported by a previous study which showed that the estimated male-mediated gene flow was more frequent in bonobos than in chimpanzees [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>However, although there have been a few studies on genetic differentiation between chimpanzee groups, there have been limited studies on genetic differentiation between bonobo groups [25–28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Comparisons of between-group differentiation in male kinship may explain the differences in hostility towards males of different groups between these two species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Thus, further investigation on kinship both within and across bonobo groups is necessary to elucidate this. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>This study aimed to reveal kin structure among three neighbouring groups in wild bonobos at Wamba in the Luo scientific reserve of the Democratic Republic of the Congo, where intensive research based on individual identification has continued since 1976. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>At first, we evaluated the reproductive skew among bonobo males in two neighbouring groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Second, we estimated the pairwise relatedness among all pairs of individuals among three neighbouring groups and compared the average relatedness within groups with that across groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><label>2.</label><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Material and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><label>2.1.</label><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Study subjects and DNA sampling </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Study subjects were three neighbouring bonobo groups (E1, PE and PW) at Wamba in the Luo Scientific Reserve area of the Democratic Republic of the Congo [28]. Table 1 summarizes the composition of each group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>We categorized age classes of individuals defined in a previous study [29]: adult males (age &gt; 15 years), adolescent males (age &gt; 8 years), immigrant parous females, immigrant nulliparous females, and infants and juveniles (both sexes age ≦ 8 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The E group has been studied since 1974, which split into the E1 and E2 groups by 1983 [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Artificial food provisioning had been conducted intermittently to intensively observe behaviours of animals until 1996. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Between 1996 and 2003, a civil war prevented research in this area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>After research resumed in 2003, animals have been observed in their natural conditions without artificial provisioning [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>All individuals of the E1 group have been well habituated and identified since 1976. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>In 2014, this group consisted of 37 individuals including 10 adult and adolescent males and nine immigrant parous females. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The P group was recognized in 1976 as a neighbouring group of the E group [24,32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>In 2010, one group, whose range was in the eastern part of the range used by the P group in the past, was named as the PE group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Another group, which has been neighbouring the PE group on its west side, was named as the PW group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Intensive research on the PW group was started at that time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>All individuals of the PE group have been identified since 2011. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>In 2014, this group consisted of 26 individuals including six adult and adolescent males and nine females which have been estimated as immigrant and parous. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The E1 and PE groups have been continuously followed from bed to bed for at least 5 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Field research for the PW group has been carried out sporadically since 2011 (almost once per month). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>All individuals of this group have been identified since 2012. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>In 2014, this group consisted of 14 individuals including five adult and adolescent males and four females, which have been estimated as immigrant and parous during the sampling period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>For DNA analysis, faeces and urine were collected from 2007 to 2016. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Most samples were collected by S.I. in July 2015, and from December 2015 to February 2016. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Faecal samples were collected using cotton swabs, and urine samples were collected using a disposable plastic syringe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Both types of collected samples were conserved in lysis buffer at normal temperature [33,34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>A total of 86 faecal and seven urine samples were used for analysis. Table 1.Composition of each group when the kin structure was investigated.E1PEPWadult males751adolescent males314immigrant parous females994immigrant nulliparous females402infants and juveniles14113total372614 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><label>2.2.</label><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Dominance relationships among males </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The dominance ranks of males of the E1 and PE groups were classified based on the value of normalized David's score [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Dyadic aggressive interactions among adult and adolescent males of the E1 group were recorded by trained local assistants, and that value for each male was calculated each year from 2010 to 2013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Dyadic aggressive interactions among adult and adolescent males of the PE group were recorded by the authors and local assistants, and that value for each male was calculated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The males whose values were the highest were categorized as the alpha. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The linearity of each dominance hierarchy was calculated using Laundau's modified h′. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The value was calculated and its significance was checked, using the R package ‘Compete v. 0.1’. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><label>2.3.</label><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Genotyping </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Following a previous study, DNA was extracted from the non-invasively collected samples [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>After removing extra components in the lysate by centrifugation at 10 000g for 10 min, 600 µg of hydrolysed starch powder was added to the supernatant and then vortexed for 1 min to absorb inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The obtained supernatant was transferred to a plastic tube and cleaned using a commercially available silica column system (Wizard SV Gel and PCR Clean-Up System, Promega, Madison, IW, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>For genotyping, we analysed eight autosomal short tandem repeats [36–38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>We prepared two primer sets: set A (D6S493, D7S817 and D9S910) and set B (D2S1329, D3S1766, D3S1768, D4S1627 and D12S66) to carry out two-step multiplex PCR [39]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>To check applicability of the obtained DNA, we followed the verification system designed in a previous study [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Semi-quantitatively, DNA from the obtained samples and human placenta (SIGMA) as a positive control with known concentration was amplified targeting the c-myc proto-oncogene [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>By performing electrophoresis and comparing the intensity of PCR bands, we categorized the quantity of the samples: greater than 300 pg µl−1, greater than 100 pg µl−1 and less than or equal to 100 pg µl−1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>As the first step of two-step PCR genotyping, multiplex PCRs were performed in 20 μl reaction volumes comprising 1 µl of extracted faecal DNA or DNA mixture, 200 nM of each forward and reverse non-labelled primer (set A or B), 2× buffer, 0.4 mM of each dNTP and 0.5 U of KOD FX polymerase (Toyobo). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Amplification parameters were as follows: 94°C for 5 min; 35 cycles of 94°C for 30 s, 64°C for 30 s and 68°C for 1 min; and a final 5 min extension at 66°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Second, we carried out singleplex PCR amplifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Singleplex PCRs were performed in 13 μl reaction volumes comprising 1 µl of multiplex PCR products, 50–100 nM of forward primer, fluorescently labelled by FAM, NED or HEX, and of reverse primer, 2× buffer, 0.4 mM of each dNTP and 0.5 U of KOD FX polymerase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Amplification parameters were as follows: 94°C for 5 min; 45 cycles of 94°C for 30 s, 64°C for 30 s and 68°C for 1 min; and a final 5 min extension at 66°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The amplification products were separated using capillary electrophoresis, using an ABI 3130xl Genetic Analyzer (Applied Biosystems, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Alleles were sized using GeneMapper software v. 4.1 (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Because DNA extracted from non-invasively collected samples is typically degraded and low in concentration, we repeated genotyping, following the recommendations of previous studies to ensure accurate genotyping [34,39–41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>At each locus, we identified homozygotes when the single allele was repeatedly observed at least three times in samples whose concentrations were more than 100 pg µl−1, and at least four times in samples whose concentrations were less than 100 pg µl−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>We identified heterozygotes when each allele was repeatedly observed more than twice at each locus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><label>2.4.</label><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Paternity analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The paternity of 17 out of 20 offspring born in the E1 and PE groups from 2009 to 2014 was investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Paternity was assigned by exclusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>First, by comparing the mother and offspring genotypes, the paternal alleles of the offspring were deduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>If candidate fathers did not possess the paternal alleles, paternity was excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Paternal candidates were all adult and adolescent males within each group and when all of them were excluded, males outside each group were added. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>When one candidate was not excluded, the confidence level for assignments was analysed by a likelihood method, using CERVUS [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Allele frequency was calculated for the three groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>To simulate the paternity analysis, we assumed that mothers were known, the proportion of loci mistyped was 0.01 and the error rate in likelihood was 0.01. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The proportion of sampled candidates was estimated based on the number of existing candidate males when the offspring was conceived. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>When the most likely fathers had no mismatched alleles and the confidence level for the assignments was more than 99%, the male was concluded to be the father of the offspring. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Based on the results of paternity of offspring in the E1 group, we calculated the Nonac's B index of reproductive skew [43]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><label>2.5.</label><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Estimating pairwise relatedness </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>We estimated the pairwise relatedness values for all pairs of 43 individuals, including adult and adolescent males and immigrant parous females (10 males and nine females in the E1, six males and nine females in the PE, and five males and four females in the PW) by using the Queller and Goodnight estimator implemented in GeneAlEx6.3 [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The programme estimates relatedness values by allele sharing of pairs and allele frequency in the population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Allele frequency was calculated for all individuals used for estimating relatedness values in the three groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>To compare the average relatedness value for each category, a permutation test was conducted in R v. 3.31. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>A p-value was obtained by 999 permutations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><label>3.</label><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><label>3.1.</label><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Paternity analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Sixty-eight individuals in total were analysed at eight loci (electronic supplementary material, appendix). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>In the E1 group, the paternity of 10 offspring born between 2009 and 2013 was analysed and seven of them were assigned to single paternal candidates within each group, with a greater than 99% confidence level (table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Six out of seven offspring, whose paternity was assigned, were sired by the male NB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>From 2010 to 2014, the dominance hierarchy of males was significantly linear and NB was the alpha male during that period (electronic supplementary material, table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it can be considered that NB sired at least six offspring during his alpha period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>In addition, Ki, who is the mother of KY and Kx, was also confirmed as the mother of NB by genetic analysis and demographic data [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the reason why the father of KY was not NB might be NB's avoidance to mate with his mother Ki. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The Nonac's B index of reproductive skew in the E1 group was 0.51. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The paternity of three offspring was not successfully assigned to any paternal candidates analysed within this group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>When these offspring were conceived, two other mature males belonged to this group, but disappeared later. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Although they were paternal candidates of the three offspring, DNA was not collected from them and analysed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Therefore, these offspring were sired by such unsampled males or extra-group males. Table 2.Paternity of offspring in the E1 group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>(Nmis, number of mismatches with the most likely father.)birth of timeestimated year of conceptionoffspringmothermost likely fatheralpha male at the time of conceptionNmisΔ scoreconfidence levelno. of unsampled candidates2009.62008KYKi—?3——22009.82009HCHs—?1——22009.102009YmYk—?2——22010.122010FaFkNBNB02.77&gt;99%02010.122010OkOtNBNB03.38&gt;99%02011.122011SESlNBNB03.59&gt;99%02012.12011JlJkNBNB02.74&gt;99%02013.72012NINvNBNB05.12&gt;99%02014.12013KxKiJDNB05.10&gt;99%02014.22013HaHsNBNB03.57&gt;99%0 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>In the PE group, the paternity of seven offspring born from 2011 to 2014 was analysed and six of them were assigned to single paternal candidates within each group, with a greater than 99% confidence level (table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Four out of six assigned offspring were sired by SN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>From 2012 to 2014, although the dominance hierarchy was not significantly linear, SN had been the alpha male (electronic supplementary material, table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it can be considered that SN sired at least three offspring during his alpha period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The paternity of offspring, not assigned to SN, was assigned to different males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The paternity of one offspring was not successfully assigned to any paternal candidates analysed within this group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>When this offspring was conceived, one more mature male belonged to this group but disappeared later. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Although he was a paternal candidate of such offspring, DNA from him was not collected and analysed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Therefore, this offspring was sired by an unsampled male or extra-group males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>In the time period for which information of dominance relationships between males and all the present males at conception is available, nine out of 11 offspring were sired by the alpha males and the most successful sire's share was in total 81.8%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Although there were no absolute cases of extra-group paternity, four offspring, whose paternity was not assigned, might have been sired by unsampled males within each group or extra-group males. Table 3.Paternity of offspring in the PE group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>(Nmis, number of mismatches with the most likely father.)birth of timeestimated time of conceptionoffspringmothermost likely fatheralpha male at the time of conceptionNmisΔ scoreconfidence levelno. of unsampled candidates2011.22010HOHdSN?05.45&gt;99%12012.32011KLKb—?4——12012.32011IAIcML?09.79&gt;99%02012.112012MzMtSNSN06.94&gt;99%02013.32012PkPoSNSN07.56&gt;99%02013.52012SoSkSNSN010.95&gt;99%02014.72013MaMrGISN03.52&gt;99%0 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><label>3.2.</label><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Pairwise relatedness value of adult and adolescent males and immigrant parous females </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Because tests of deviation from Hardy and Weinberg equilibrium did not show a significant value at each locus, we pooled the three groups into one population (χ2-test, p &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Average relatedness among males within groups was significantly higher than that across groups (permutation test, p &lt; 0.01; figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The average relatedness value between males of the PE group and those of the PW group was relatively high and significantly higher than those between males of the E1 group and those of the PE group (permutation test, p &lt; 0.05; table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, there was no significant difference among females between within and across groups (permutation test, p  =  0.936; figure 1). Figure 1.Average relatedness values (R) and standard errors for pairs of individuals in each category. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Blue dots represent the average relatedness value among males within and across groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Red dots represent the average relatedness among females within and across groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The number of pairwise comparisons used to calculate each value appears in brackets.  Table 4.Average relatedness values within each group and pair of two groups.among males/ among femalesE1PEPWE10.0213/−0.0461——PE−0.0879/0.00550.0099/0.0203—PW−0.0801/0.00740.0042/−0.01900.1905/0.1291 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><label>4.</label><title><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Nine out of 11 offspring in the two study groups were sired by the alpha males and the percentage of the most successful sire's share was in total 81.8%, in the time period for which information on dominance relationships between males and all the present males at conception is available (E1: 86% and PE: 75%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The percentage of the most successful sire's share in the present study was higher than that in other multi-male/multi-female group-living primates (figure 2; electronic supplementary material, table S3; [15,16,46–54]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The percentage of the most successful sire's share in the two groups, as well as the Nonac's B index in the E1 group, was higher than that recorded in the Bompusa community at LuiKotale (most successful sire's share: 62% and Nonac's B index: 0.22 [15]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Although differences in these indices between the two study sites may be caused by some factors, such as the strength of maternal influences (discussed as below) or the stability of dominance relationships between males, at least both these results indicate that the male reproductive skew is higher in bonobos than in chimpanzees. Figure 2.The most successful sire's share of multi-male/multi-female group-living primate species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Round, square, triangle and diamond dots represent the most successful sire's share in bonobos of this study, bonobos in other populations, chimpanzees and other primate species, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Details on species, population and publications are described in the electronic supplementary material, table S3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>One reason why the alpha males were able to sire many offspring might be because they enjoy a higher mating success with strong support from their mothers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>In bonobos, the alpha males tend to be sons of high-ranking females, as in the case of NB who was a son of Ki, an old and high-ranking female in at least the E1 group [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>In bonobo society, old females tend to occupy a high social status and can defeat males in aggressive interactions [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Therefore, if males attack the alpha males, it could lead to the risk that they might be attacked and scattered by the alpha males' mothers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>That is why males may give up attacking the alpha males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Instead, the alpha males may prevent other males from attacking them by always ranging with their mothers and thus enjoy high mating success. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>This is supported by a previous study, showing that mothers and sons have high association rates and mothers provide agonistic aid to sons in conflict with other males [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>It could be assumed that such a mechanism produces a high paternity rate for the alpha males. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The paternity of four offspring was not assigned to analysed candidate fathers within the groups, suggesting that these offspring might be sired by either males of other groups, or those who looked like non-alpha males according to general observations and had disappeared later before the DNA sampling in this study (two males in the E1 group and one male in the PE group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>If these offspring were sired by extra-group males, that would be consistent with frequently observed mating among different group members during group encounters [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>A previous study reported that some of male-mediated gene flow might be produced by extra-group paternity [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>This suggests that it is probable that some offspring in each group might be sired by extra-group males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, if they were sired by unsampled males within the groups and there were few offspring sired by extra-group males, frequent mating between males and females from different groups did not seem to lead to conception as expected by its high frequency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>In bonobos, females can mate with males even if they are not in a fertile period [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>In addition, sexual interactions have other functions besides reproduction such as reducing tension [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Mating among different group individuals during group encounters may function for such purposes during group encounters and might not necessarily involve females in fertile periods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>By continuing to investigate the paternity of offspring whose candidate fathers’ samples are completely sampled, the presence or absence of extra-group paternity is expected to become clear. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Average relatedness among males within groups was significantly higher than that across groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>This difference might be caused by male philopatry and skewed reproductive success of a limited number of males with alpha status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Although male gene flow between groups could occur because of some rare reasons such as extra-group paternity, immigration of females with dependent male offspring or even adolescent or adult male dispersal, these factors might not be sufficient to eliminate the differentiation in average relatedness of males between groups [25,57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>In addition, according to long-term observations at Wamba, males do not migrate between groups, and pregnant females or independent infants also do not migrate between groups [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>These observations might explain the significant difference between average relatedness among males within groups and that across groups in our data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Higher relatedness between males of the PE group and those of the PW group might reflect a closer relationship among these two groups in the past. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Although it is confirmed that the E1 group has existed for at least 30 years as an independent group, members of the PE group were fully identified only in 2011 and those of the PW group in 2012. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Therefore, there is a possibility that the PE and PW groups had split from one group more recently than 30 years ago. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Another possibility is that such a structure might be caused by reproduction among members of these groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The frequency of inter-group encounters, which may be connected to opportunities for reproduction, is much higher between these two adjacent groups than the E1 and PE groups, or the E1 and PW groups [59]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Higher average relatedness among males within groups was also observed in a previous study on chimpanzees [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>In Tai forest, average relatedness among chimpanzee males within groups tends to be higher than that across groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Although the available data are still limited, these suggest that between-group differentiation in male kinship is similar in bonobos and chimpanzees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it might be impossible to explain differences in hostility towards males of different groups between bonobos and chimpanzees based purely on kinship. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, one study on western gorillas reported that males of neighbouring groups have kinship with each other, whereas another study reported that the single males leading groups were usually related to one or more nearby males [60,61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Most western gorilla males emigrate while they are blackbacks or young silverbacks [62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The between-group differentiation in male kinship in both bonobos and chimpanzees could be attributed to male philopatry, which is one of stable traits in the genus Pan. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>There was no significant difference in average relatedness among females between within and across groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The absence of significant difference in average relatedness among females between within and across groups was also reported in a previous study on chimpanzees [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with the prediction of female dispersal in the present study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Although a recent study reported that there were two confirmed mother–daughter dyads within the group, the effects of this on kin structure might be limited to increasing the average relatedness among females within groups [63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Our data also suggest that it is rare for females, which are related by kinship, to migrate and settle into the same group together. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>In other words, females who have settled into the same group may have come from various natal groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>This is supported by a high diversity of mitochondria DNA haplotypes within the groups [16,63,64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>In addition, our long-term observations showed that no females migrated into neighbouring groups until 2012 [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>This suggests that it might be rare for females to migrate and settle into neighbouring groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>This study found inconsistency between the highly skewed reproductive success of males and non-intense male–male reproductive competition in bonobos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>To explain such an inconsistency, quantitative data should be collected to investigate the effects of female control, such as maternal influences, on the reproductive skew among males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>This study also found evidence of between-group differentiation in male kinship in bonobos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>However, because data on genetic differentiation between groups are still scarce for bonobos, it is expected that more data will be reported from other sites. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Appendix; Tables S1 - S3 </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="rsos171006supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e1280" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>We thank the Research Centre for Ecology and Forestry and the Ministry of Scientific Research of the Democratic Republic of the Congo for permitting our research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>We also thank local assistants at Wamba that helped with fieldwork in the forest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>We thank many members of the Primate Research Institute and particularly Dr F. B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Bercovitch, Dr M.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Huffman, Dr Y. Tsuji, Dr T. Yumoto, Dr C. Hashimoto, Dr A. Sawada, Dr H. Ryu and Dr Y. Kurihara for providing valuable comments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>We also thank Dr E. Inoue, Dr T. Hayakawa and Ms E. Makinose for help in our DNA analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><sec id="s5"><title>Ethics</title><p>Our study was approved by the Ministry of Scientific Research, of the Democratic Republic of the Congo and conformed to the Guidelines for Field Research established by the Ethics Committee of the Primate Research Institute, Kyoto University.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Data accessibility</title><p>The datasets supporting this article have been uploaded as the part of the electronic supplementary material.</p></sec><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec id="s7"><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>S.I. designed this study, collected DNA samples of animals, conducted DNA experiments, analysed the genetic data, performed statistical analyses, wrote and revised the manuscript. Y.K. supervised S.I.'s DNA experiments. N.T. collected DNA samples of animals and behavioural data. T.S., K.T. and H.O. collected DNA samples of animals. T.F. supervised S.I. to design this study. All authors revised the manuscript and gave final approval for publication.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec id="s8" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p>We have no competing interests.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec id="s9"><title>Funding</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by Japan Society for the Promotion of Science Grant-in-aid for JSPS fellows (17J09827 to S.I.), Japan Society for the Promotion of Science Grant-in-aid for Scientific Research (17255005, 22255007 and 26257408 to T.F.; 19405015 and 25304019 to Chie Hashimoto; 25257407 and 16H02753 to Takakazu Yumoto), Japan Society for the Promotion of Science Core-to-Core Program (2009–2011, 2012–2014 and 2015–2017 to T.F.), the Japan Ministry of the Environment Global Environment Research Fund (D-1007 to T.F.), Japan Society for the Promotion of Science HOPE Project (to the Primate Research Institute), Japan Society for the Promotion of Science Strategic Young Overseas Visits Program for Acceleration Brain Circulation (S2508 to the Primate Research Institute), the Japan Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology Special Grant (to the Primate Research Institute) and the Leading Graduate Program in Primatology and Wildlife Science of Kyoto University. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="RSOS171006C1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>1CowlishawG, DunbarRIM 1991 Dominance rank and mating success in male primates. Anim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Behav. 41, 1045–1056. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0003-3472(05)80642-6">doi:10.1016/S0003-3472(05)80642-6</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C2"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>2KutsukakeN, NunnCL 2006 Comparative tests of reproductive skew in male primates: the roles of demographic factors and incomplete control. Behav. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Ecol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Sociobiol. 60, 695–706. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00265-006-0213-1">doi:10.1007/s00265-006-0213-1</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C3"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>3EllisL 1995 Dominance and reproductive success among nonhuman animals: a cross-species comparison. Ethol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Sociobiol. 16, 257–333. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0162-3095(95)00050">doi:10.1016/0162-3095(95)00050</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C4"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>4OstnerJ, NunnCL, SchülkeO 2008 Female reproductive synchrony predicts skewed paternity across primates. Behav. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Ecol. 19, 1150–1158. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/beheco/arn093">doi:10.1093/beheco/arn093</ext-link>)19018288 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C5"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>5HandleyLJL, PerrinN 2007 Advances in our understanding of mammalian sex-biased dispersal. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Ecol. 16, 1559–1578. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2006.03152.x">doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2006.03152.x</ext-link>)17402974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C6"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>6HamiltonW 1964 The genetical evolution of social behaviour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>I. J. Theor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Biol. 7, 1–16. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0022-5193(64)90038-4">doi:10.1016/0022-5193(64)90038-4</ext-link>)5875341 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C7"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>7FuruichiT 2011 Female contributions to the peaceful nature of bonobo society. Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Anthropol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Issues News Rev. 20, 131–142. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/evan.20308">doi:10.1002/evan.20308</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C8"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>8HareB, WobberV, WranghamR 2012 The self-domestication hypothesis: evolution of bonobo psychology is due to selection against aggression. Anim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Behav. 83, 573–585. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.anbehav.2011.12.007">doi:10.1016/j.anbehav.2011.12.007</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C9"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>9NishidaTet al. 2003 Demography, female life history, and reproductive profiles among the chimpanzees of Mahale. Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Primatol. 59, 99–121. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ajp.10068">doi:10.1002/ajp.10068</ext-link>)12619045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C10"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>10ErikssonJ, SiedelH, LukasD, KayserM, ErlerA, HashimotoC, HohmannG, BoeschC, VigilantL 2006 Y-chromosome analysis confirms highly sex-biased dispersal and suggests a low male effective population size in bonobos (Pan paniscus). Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Ecol. 15, 939–949. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2006.02845.x">doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2006.02845.x</ext-link>)16599958 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C11"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>11MullerMN, WranghamRW 2004 Dominance, aggression and testosterone in wild chimpanzees: a test of the ‘challenge hypothesis.’ Anim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Behav. 67, 113–123. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.anbehav.2003.03.013">doi:10.1016/j.anbehav.2003.03.013</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C12"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>12SurbeckM, DeschnerT, SchubertG, WeltringA, HohmannG 2012 Mate competition, testosterone and intersexual relationships in bonobos, Pan paniscus. Anim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Behav. 83, 659–669. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.anbehav.2011.12.010">doi:10.1016/j.anbehav.2011.12.010</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C13"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>13DouglasPH, HohmannG, MurtaghR, Thiessen-BockR, DeschnerT 2016 Mixed messages: wild female bonobos show high variability in the timing of ovulation in relation to sexual swelling patterns. BMC Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Biol. 16, 140 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/s12862-016-0691-3">doi:10.1186/s12862-016-0691-3</ext-link>)27356506 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C14"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>14FuruichiT 1992 The prolonged estrus of females and factors influencing mating in wild group of bonobos (Pan paniscus) in Wamba, Zaire. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>In Topics in primatology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Behavior, ecology, and conservation (eds ItoigawaN, SugiyamaY, SackettGP, ThompsonR), pp. 179–190. Tokyo, Japan: University of Tokyo Press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C15"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>15SurbeckM, LangergraberKE, FruthB, VigilantL, HohmannG 2017 Male reproductive skew is higher in bonobos than chimpanzees. Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Biol. 27, R623–R641. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2017.05.039">doi:10.1016/j.cub.2017.05.039</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C16"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>16GerloffU, HartungB, FruthB, HohmannG, TautzD 1999 Intracommunity relationships, dispersal pattern and paternity success in a wild living community of bonobos (Pan paniscus) determined from DNA analysis of faecal samples. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Lond. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>B 266, 1189–1195. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspb.1999.0762">doi:10.1098/rspb.1999.0762</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C17"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>17HamiltonWD 1966 The moulding of senescence by natural selection. J. Theor Biol. 12, 12–45. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0022-5193(66)90184-6">doi:10.1016/0022-5193(66)90184-6</ext-link>)6015424 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C18"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>18Clutton-BrockT 2002 Breeding together: kin selection and mutualism in cooperative vertebrates. Science 296, 69–72. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.296.5565.69">doi:10.1126/science.296.5565.69</ext-link>)11935014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C19"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>19LangergraberKE, MitaniJC, VigilantL 2007 The limited impact of kinship on cooperation in wild chimpanzees. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>USA 104, 7786–7790. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0611449104">doi:10.1073/pnas.0611449104</ext-link>)17456600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C20"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>20MöllerLM, BeheregarayLB, HarcourtRG, KrützenM 2001 Alliance membership and kinship in wild male bottlenose dolphins (Tursiops aduncus) of southeastern Australia. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Lond. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>B 268, 1941–1947. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2001.1756">doi:10.1098/rspb.2001.1756</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C21"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>21WranghamRW, GlowackiL 2012 Intergroup aggression in chimpanzees and war in nomadic hunter-gatherers. Hum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Nat. 23, 5–29. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s12110-012-9132-1">doi:10.1007/s12110-012-9132-1</ext-link>)22388773 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C22"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>22WilsonM, WranghamR 2003 Intergroup relations in chimpanzees. Annu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Anthropol. 32, 363–392. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.anthro.32.061002.120046">doi:10.1146/annurev.anthro.32.061002.120046</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C23"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>23HohmannG, FruthB 2003 Intra- and inter-sexual aggression by bonobos in the context of mating. Behaviour 140, 1389–1423. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/156853903771980648">doi:10.1163/156853903771980648</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C24"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>24IdaniG 1990 Relation between unit-groups of bonobos at Wamba, Zaire: encounter and temporary fusions. Afr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Stud Monogr. 11, 153–186. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.14989/68066">doi:10.14989/68066</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C25"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>25SchubertG, StonekingCJ, ArandjelovicM, BoeschC, EckhardtN, HohmannG., LangergraberKE, LukasD, VigilantL 2011 Male-mediated gene flow in patrilocal primates. PLoS ONE 6, e21514 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0021514">doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0021514</ext-link>)21747938 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C26"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>26LukasD, ReynoldsV, BoeschC, VigilantL 2005 To what extent does living in a group mean living with kin? Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Ecol. 14, 2181–2196. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2005.02560.x">doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2005.02560.x</ext-link>)15910336 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C27"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>27LangergraberKE, SchubertG, RowneyC, WranghamR, ZommersZ, VigilantL 2011 Genetic differentiation and the evolution of cooperation in chimpanzees and humans. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>B 278, 2546–2552. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2010.2592">doi:10.1098/rspb.2010.2592</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C28"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>28KanoT 1992 The last ape: pygmy chimpanzee behavior and ecology. Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C29"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>29HashimotoC 1997 Context and development of sexual behavior of wild bonobos (Pan paniscus) at Wamba, Zaire. Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Primatol. 18, 1–21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1026384922066">doi:10.1023/A:1026384922066</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C30"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>30FuruichiT 1987 Sexual swelling, receptivity, and grouping of wild pygmy chimpanzee females at Wamba Zaire. Primates 28, 309–318. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF02381014">doi:10.1007/BF02381014</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C31"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>31FuruichiT, IdaniG, IhobeH, HashimotoC, TashiroY, SakamakiT, MulavwaMN, YangozeneK, KurodaS 2012 Long-term studies on wild bonobos at Wamba, Luo Scientific Reserve, DR Congo: towards the understanding of female life history in a male-philopatric species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>In Long-term field studies of primates (eds KappelerPM, WattsDP), pp. 413–433. Berlin, Germany: Springer. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C32"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="?"><plain>32TokuyamaN, FuruichiT 2016 Do friends help each other? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Patterns of female coalition formation in wild bonobos at Wamba. Anim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Behav. 119, 27–35. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.anbehav.2016.06.021">doi:10.1016/j.anbehav.2016.06.021</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C33"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>33KawamotoYet al. 2013 Genetic structure of wild bonobo populations: diversity of mitochondrial DNA and geographical distribution. PLoS ONE 8, e59660 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0059660">doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0059660</ext-link>)23544084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C34"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>34InoueE, Inoue-MurayamaM, TakenakaO, NishidaT 2007 Wild chimpanzee infant urine and saliva sampled noninvasively usable for DNA analyses. Primates 48, 156–159. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10329-006-0017-y">doi:10.1007/s10329-006-0017-y</ext-link>)17111091 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C35"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>35de VriesH, StevensJMG, VervaeckeH 2006 Measuring and testing the steepness of dominance hierarchies. Anim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Behav. 71, 585–592. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.anbehav.2005.05.015">doi:10.1016/j.anbehav.2005.05.015</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C36"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>36BradleyBJ, BoeschC, VigilantL 2000 Identification and redesign of human microsatellite markers for genotyping wild chimpanzees (Pan troglodytes verus) and gorilla (Gorilla gorilla gorilla) DNA from feces. Cons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Genet. 1, 289–292. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1011514007741">doi:10.1023/A:1011514007741</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C37"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>37GoossensB, LatourS, VidalC, JamartA, AncrenazM, BrufordMW 2000 Twenty new microsatellite loci for use with hair and faecal samples in the chimpanzee (Pan troglodytes troglodytes). Folia Primatol. 71, 177–180. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1159/000021738">doi:10.1159/000021738</ext-link>)10828699 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C38"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>38LiuZJ, RenBP, HaoYL, ZhangHR, WeiFW, LiM 2008 Identification of 13 human microsatellite markers cross-species amplification for fecal samples from Yunnan snub-nosed monkey (Rhinopithecus bieti). Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Primatol. 29, 265–272. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10764-007-9175-z">doi:10.1007/s10764-007-9175-z</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C39"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>39ArandjelovicM, GuschanskiK, SchubertG, HarrisTR, ThalmannO, SiedelH, VigilantL 2009 Two-step multiplex polymerase chain reaction improves the speed and accuracy of genotyping using DNA from noninvasive and museum samples. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Ecol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Resour. 9, 28–36. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1755-0998.2008.02387.x">doi:10.1111/j.1755-0998.2008.02387.x</ext-link>)21564562 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C40"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>40MorinPA, ChambersKE, BoeschC, VigilantL 2001 Quantitative polymerase chain reaction analysis of DNA from noninvasive samples for accurate microsatellite genotyping of wild chimpanzees (Pan troglodytes verus). Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Ecol. 10, 1835–1844.11472550 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C41"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>41TaberletP, GriffinS, GoossensB, QuestiauS, ManceauV, EscaravageN, WaitsLP, BouvetJ 1996 Reliable genotyping of samples with very low DNA quantities using PCR. Nucleic Acids Res. 24, 3189–3194. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/24.16.3189">doi:10.1093/nar/24.16.3189</ext-link>)8774899 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C42"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>42MarshallTC, SlateJ, KruukLEB, PembertonJM 1998 Statistical confidence for likelihood-based paternity inference in natural populations. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Ecol. 7, 639–655. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1026395829818">doi:10.1023/A:1026395829818</ext-link>)9633105 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C43"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>43NonacsP 2000 Measuring and using skew in the study of social behavior and evolution. Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Nat. 156, 577–589. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086/316995">doi:10.1086/316995</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C44"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>44QuellerDC, GoodnightKF 1989 Estimating relatedness using genetic markers. Evolution 43, 258–275. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF02733490">doi:10.1007/BF02733490</ext-link>)28568555 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C45"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>45HashimotoC, TashiroY, HibinoE, MulavwaM, YangozeneK, FuruichiT, IdaniG, TakenakaO 2008 Longitudinal structure of a unit-group of bonobos: male philopatry and possible fusion of unit-groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>In The bonobos: behavior, ecology, and conservation (eds FuruichiT, ThompsonJ), pp. 107–119. New York, NY: Springer. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C46"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>46VigilantL, HofreiterM, SiedelH, BoeschC 2001 Paternity and relatedness in wild chimpanzee communities. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>USA 98, 12 890–12 895. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.231320498">doi:10.1073/pnas.231320498</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C47"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>47ConstableJL, AshleyMV, GoodallJ, PuseyAE 2001 Noninvasive paternity assignment in Gombe chimpanzees. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Ecol. 10, 1279–1300. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-294X.2001.01262.x">doi:10.1046/j.1365-294X.2001.01262.x</ext-link>)11380884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C48"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>48InoueE, Inoue-MurayamaM, VigilantL, TakenakaO, NishidaT 2008 Relatedness in wild chimpanzees: influence of paternity, male philopatry, and demographic factors. Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Phys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Anthropol. 137, 256–262. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ajpa.20865">doi:10.1002/ajpa.20865</ext-link>)18512686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C49"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>49Newton-FisherNE, ThompsonME, ReynoldsV, BoeschC, VigilantL 2010 Paternity and social rank in wild chimpanzees (Pan troglodytes) from the Budongo Forest, Uganda. Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Phys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Anyhropol. 142, 417–428. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ajpa.21241">doi:10.1002/ajpa.21241</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C50"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>50BradleyBJ, RobbinsMM, WilliamsonEA, SteklisDH, SteklisNG, EckhardtN, BoeschC, VigilantL 2005 Mountain gorilla tug-of-war: silverbacks have limited control over reproduction in multimale groups. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>USA 102, 9418–9423. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0502019102">doi:10.1073/pnas.0502019102</ext-link>)15964984 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C51"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>51AltmannJet al. 1996 Behavior predicts genes structure in a wild primate group. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>USA 93, 5797–5801. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.93.12.5797">doi:10.1073/pnas.93.12.5797</ext-link>)8650172 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C52"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>52MunizL, PerryS, MansonJH, GilkensonH, Gros-LouisJ, VigilantL 2010 Male dominance and reproductive success in wild white-faced capuchins (Cebus capucinus) at Lomas Barbudal, Costa Rica. Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Primatol. 72, 1118–1130. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ajp.22584">doi:10.1002/ajp.22584</ext-link>)20717998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C53"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>53HuckM, LottkerP, BohleUR, HeymannEW 2005 Paternity and kinship patterns in polyandrous moustached tamarins (Saguinus mystax). Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Phys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Anthropol. 127, 449–464. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ajpa.20136">doi:10.1002/ajpa.20136</ext-link>)15624210 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C54"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>54StrierKB, ChavesPB, MendesSL, FagundesV, Di FioreA 2011 Low paternity skew and the influence of maternal kin in an egalitarian, patrilocal primate. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>USA 108, 18 915–18 919. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1116737108">doi:10.1073/pnas.1116737108</ext-link>)21173276 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C55"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="!"><plain>55SurbeckM, MundryR, HohmannG 2011 Mothers matter! </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Maternal support, dominance status and mating success in male bonobos (Pan paniscus). Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>B 278, 590–598. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2010.1572">doi:10.1098/rspb.2010.1572</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C56"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>56MansonJH, PerryS, ParishAR 1997 Nonconceptive sexual behavior in bonobos and capuchins. Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Primatol. 18, 767–786. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.0962-1083.2001.01308.x">doi:10.1046/j.0962-1083.2001.01308.x</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C57"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>57HohmannG, FruthB 2002 Dynamics in social organization of bonobos (Pan paniscus). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>In Behavioural diversity in chimpanzees and bonobos (eds BoeschC, HohmannG, MarchantLF), pp. 138–150. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C58"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>58SakamakiT, BehnckeI, LaporteM, MulavwaM, RyuH, TakemotoH, TokuyamaN, YamamotoS, FuruichiT 2015 Intergroup transfer of females and social relationships between immigrants and residents in bonobo (Pan paniscus) societies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>In Dispersing primate females (eds FuruichiT, YamagiwaJ, AureliF), pp. 127–164. Tokyo, Japan: Springer. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C59"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>59SakamakiT, RyuH, TodaK, TokuyamaN, FuruichiT Submitted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Intergroup encounters in wild bonobos (Pan paniscus) at Wamba: effects of food abundance and the number of estrous females on encounter frequency. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C60"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>60InoueEet al. 2013 Male genetic structure and paternity in western lowland gorillas (Gorilla gorilla gorilla). Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Phys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Anthropol. 151, 583–588. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ajpa.22312">doi:10.1002/ajpa.22312</ext-link>)23868171 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C61"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>61BradleyBJ, Doran-SheehyDM, LukasD, BoeschC, VigilantL 2004 Dispersed male networks in western gorillas. Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>Biol.14, 510–513. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2004.02.062">doi:10.1016/j.cub.2004.02.062</ext-link>)15043817 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C62"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>62RobbinsMM, BermejoM, CipollettaC, MaglioccaF, ParnellRJ, StokesE 2004 Social structure and life-history patterns in western gorillas (Gorilla gorilla gorilla). Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>Primatol. 64, 145–159. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ajp.20069">doi:10.1002/ajp.20069</ext-link>)15470749 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C63"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>63MoscoviceLR, DouglasPH, Martinez-IñigoL, SurbeckM, VigilantL, HohmannG 2017 Stable and uctuating social preferences and implications for cooperation among female bonobos at LuiKotale, Salonga National Park, DRC. Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Phys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>Anthropol. 163, 158–172. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ajpa.23197">doi:10.1002/ajpa.23197</ext-link>)28276048 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="RSOS171006C64"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>64HashimotoC, FuruichiT, TakenakaO 1996 Matrilineal kin relationship and social behaviour of wild bonobos (Pan paniscus): sequencing the D-Loop region of mitochondrial DNA. Primates 37, 305–318. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF02381862">doi:10.1007/BF02381862</ext-link>) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
