<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><?epub February-16-2010?><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2887955</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20159995</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq081</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkq081</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Survey and Summary</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>A case study in cross-talk: the histone lysine methyltransferases G9a and GLP </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Xiaodong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Molecular Biophysics &amp; Biochemistry, Yale University, New Haven, CT 06520 and <sup>2</sup>Department of Biochemistry, Emory University School of Medicine, 1510 Clifton Road, Atlanta, GA 30322, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: <phone>+1 203 432 9841</phone>; Fax: <fax>+1 203 432 5767</fax>; Email: <email>robert.collins@yale.edu</email></corresp><corresp>Correspondence may also be addressed to Xiaodong Cheng. Tel: +1 404 727 8491; Fax: +1 404 727 3746; Email: <email>xcheng@emory.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>2</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>16</day><month>2</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>38</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>3503</fpage><lpage>3511</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>9</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The histone code hypothesis predicts that the post-translational modification of histones can bring about distinct chromatin states, and it therefore serves a key regulatory role in chromatin biology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The impact of one mark on another has been termed cross-talk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Some marks are mutually exclusive, while others act in concert. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>As multiple marks contributing to one outcome are generally brought about by complexes containing multiple catalytic and binding domains, it appears regulation of chromatin involves a web of writers and readers of histone modifications, chromatin remodeling activities and DNA methylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Here, we focus on the protein lysine methyltransferases G9a and GLP as examples of this extended cross-talk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>G9a and GLP can catalyze the formation of and bind to the same methyl mark via distinct domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We consider the impact of other histone modifications on G9a/GLP activity and the coordination of activities within G9a/GLP containing complexes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>We evaluate the potential impact of product binding on product specificity and on maintenance and propagation of the methyl mark. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Lastly, we examine the recruitment of other silencing factors by G9a/GLP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Regulated assembly of specific complexes around key marks may reinforce or alter the biological outcome associated with given histone modifications. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The histone code hypothesis recognizes that the post-translational modification of histones can directly impact chromatin structure or can be read by effector modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Certain modifications have been correlated with unique transcriptional outcomes and chromatin states. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Individually, the modifications of the histone code are bound with weak affinity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Binding modules with the same specificity are found in complexes with differing, and sometimes opposing, activities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>For example, G9a and GLP have been described as both co-repressors (1–11) and co-activators (1,12,13). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>This has led some to doubt the validity of the histone code hypothesis, as they question the ability of a single modification to affect a biological outcome (14–16). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Multivalent interactions have been proposed as the answer, where no single modification, but rather patterns of modifications and the network of interacting proteins that can read and write them are responsible for the regulation of chromatin (17,18). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>We adopt this extended view, and we focus on G9a/GLP as an example of this, because they feature the ability to bind their own product and to serve as an organizing hub for diverse activities. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The impact of one mark of the histone code on another is frequently observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>With the structural and biochemical characterization of more of the players in histone modification, the underlying mechanisms of cross-talk, and the interplay of histone cross-talk and other pathways, such as chromatin remodeling and DNA methylation and repair, are becoming clear (19–25). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Mechanistically, cross-talk occurs when one or more binding modules and catalytic domains reside in the same complex or polypeptide, allowing coordination of different activities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Cross-talk can occur prior to catalysis, in which case the recognition of one mark (or its absence) can serve to recruit an enzyme to its substrate in the generation or removal of a second mark. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>This is essential for targeting and coordination of activities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>We detail a second type of cross-talk, product binding, where binding by a reader module follows catalysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>G9a and GLP can bind their products via a domain distinct from the catalytic domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In other cases, product binding has proved essential to maintain marks after their establishment or to spread the modifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>As sequence- and structure-specific DNA-binding modules within the modifier complexes may also play a large role in contributing specificity, we also consider their role in mediating gene-specific silencing in G9a/GLP complexes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Product binding also allows for more complicated signaling on chromatin, where a complex, bound to its product, can act as a platform to integrate diverse signals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>G9a/GLP </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The highly similar euchromatic methyltransferases G9a-like protein (GLP, also known as EuHMT1) and G9a (also known as EuHMT2) form a heteromeric complex, and the loss of either substantially reduces mono- and dimethylation of H3K9, which is a marker of silent euchromatin (10,26–28). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>G9a has also been recognized for its ability to methylate histone H1.4 and other non-histone proteins, including itself (29–32). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>G9a and GLP bind their H3K9me1 and H3K9me2 products via ankyrin repeat domains (33), which contain a hydrophobic cage present in methyllysine binding modules of diverse folds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>This cage binds H3K9me1/2 with approximately equal affinity, but it is too narrow to accommodate H3K9me3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In G9a or GLP knockout cells, DNA methylation and HP1 binding to euchromatin are lost (10,34). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The associated loss of silencing causes embryonic lethality, and differentiation of ES cells in the absence of G9a leads to apoptosis (26). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>G9a is required for the restriction of cell fate in development, for the silencing of the homeobox gene Oct3/4, which is required for pluripotency (4), for NRSF/REST-mediated silencing of neuronal genes in non-neuronal lineages (35), for PRDI-BF1 (Blimp-1) silencing in B-cell differentiation (5) and for CDP/cut mediated silencing of genes involved in cell differentiation and proliferation (8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The role of G9a/GLP as a gatekeeper of differentiation has been demonstrated by knockdown and with a novel inhibitor, BIX-01294 (36–39). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>In the absence of the repressive H3K9me1/2 mark, genes normally expressed only in stem cells are induced, and cells are more readily reverted to pluripotent states. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The diverse functions of G9a/GLP appear to require different activities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The isolated catalytic domain targeted to DNA is sufficient for transcriptional silencing (9,40). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Conversely, DNA methylation appears to require the ankryin repeat domain, but not histone methyltransferase activity (34,41,42). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Lastly, methyltransferase activity has little or no effect on the transcriptional activation of nuclear receptor regulated genes, β-globin or rDNAs by G9a (1,12,13). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>We consider potential roles for G9a product binding (Figure 1), including competition with methyltransferase activity to restrict procession to trimethylated H3K9, blocking the back modification of the H3K9me1/2 marks by lysine demethylases, spreading of the methyl mark akin to the Su(var)3-9/HP1 system, and recruiting other proteins including histone H1, HP1, DNA methyltransferases and transcription factors. Figure 1.Domain organization of G9a and GLP. G9a and GLP consist of a N-terminal domain with automethylation site(s), the product-binding ankyrin repeats and the catalytic SET domain, which also mediates formation of heteromers (PDB codes 3B95 and 2RFI). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The influence of other post-translational modifications on G9a/GLP activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Unlike certain other methyltransferases, such as Set1 or Dot1 (43), G9a/GLP methylation is not dependent on pre-existing marks, but merely the absence of modifications to the target lysine or adjacent residues is sufficient for catalysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>This limited catalytic cross-talk in G9a/GLP relates to their recognition of a fairly short stretch (minimally H3T6-H3T11) of H3 for methylation (30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Acetylated H3K9 and phosphorylated H3S10 or H3T11 block methylation, while H3K4 acetylation or methylation merely reduces activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Additionally, arginine methylation at H3R8 blocks activity (30,44). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Product binding is blocked by phosphorylation of H3S10 (33). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Coordination with other activities </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>A few studies have probed the spatiotemporal relationships of modifications during transcriptional activation or silencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>One compelling study traced the silencing of the Dntt (deoxynucleotidyltransferase, terminal) promoter during differentiation of thymocytes and it clearly established a temporal sequence of events from active to silent chromatin (45). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>During the maturation of the thymocytes, the promoter was stripped of activating modifications by deacetylation of H3K9 and demethylation of H3K4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The modifications were first lost at the promoter and then spread outwards. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Conversely, silencing H3K9 methylation nucleated at the promoter and spread over 10 kb outward from the promoter over time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Transcription was strongly reduced with the loss of the activating modifications and fully quenched when dimethylated H3K9 (H3K9me2) reached ∼50% of its maximal value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Lastly, DNA CpG methylation increased as the cells terminally differentiated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Coincident with this process, the gene relocalized to a region of silent heterochromatin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, in a cell line with reversible Dntt silencing, modifications were nucleated at the promoter, but did not spread. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Notably, the study did not identify the H3K9 methyltransferases involved and we include it as a fine example of the coordination of silencing activities, but not of G9a/GLP function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The developmental silencing of the Oct3/4 promoter follows a similar course, with loss of activating modifications and gain of G9a/GLP-mediated H3K9 methylation, followed by association of HP1 and DNA methyltransferases (4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Similar coordination has been seen in other silencing complexes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Small heterodimer partner (SHP), known for its ability to silence transcription mediated by a number of nuclear-receptors, is able to interact with histone deacetylases (HDACs), a H3K9me2 methyltransferase (G9a) and a silencing SWI–SNF family complex (3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>It appears that HDAC activity precedes histone lysine methylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>H3K9me2, in turn, was required for recruitment of the silencing chromatin remodeling complex (3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Similarly, a RE1-silencing transcription factor (REST) complex containing an H3K4me3 demethylase (SMCX), HDACs and H3K9me2 methyltransferases (G9a) is targeted to neuron-restrictive silencing elements (a conserved sequence in the promoters of a subset of neural genes) (46). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>In this case, H3K4me3 demethylation appeared to coincide with histone deacetylation, which was followed by H3K9 methylation (46). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The next challenge is making clear the molecular mechanisms that underlie these patterns. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Interplay of product binding with degree of methylation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Constitutive heterochromatin is distinguished by a high concentration of H3K9me3, while euchromatin/facultative heterochromatin is primarily marked with H3K9me1/2 and limited regions of H3K9me3. In vitro, G9a rapidly generates both mono- and dimethyllysine, but it more slowly proceeds to trimethylation (47,48). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Although the G9a and GLP knockouts most noticeably reduce global H3K9me1 and H3K9me2, G9a may mediate some trimethylation in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Long residence at a target site may allow the formation of trimethyllysine, as G9a tethered to a synthetic mini-locus, as a Gal4 DNA-binding domain fusion generates H3K9me3 in vivo (49) and G9a trimethylates itself (29,30,32). In vivo, G9a-mediated H3K9me3 has been detected, typically in small regions near promoters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>For example, in the absence of G9a, H3K9me3 levels have been found to be reduced at the Oct3/4 promoter, at the promoters of paternally imprinted genes and at a host of other developmentally silenced genes (4,42,50). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>H3K9me3 reduction at G9a-silenced promoters (but not non-target promoters) is also observed when G9a is chemically inhibited, though the knockout of G9a or GLP had a slightly more potent effect in the same study (38). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Since G9a and GLP appear to bring about multiple levels of methylation, potentially based on the duration of their residency on a target, they must strike a balance between proceeding to trimethylation and restriction to lower methylation states. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Of particular interest is the distinction between the lower states of H3K9 methylation (me1 and me2), which the G9a and GLP ankyrin repeats can bind (33), and higher states (me2 and me3), which are preferred by HP1 (51). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>All three degrees of methylation bring about silencing, as even a monomethylating mutant G9a (F1205Y) transgene was able to silence target genes in G9a-null ES cells (47). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The ability to reverse a mark and reactivate transcription also relates to the degree of methylation, as some demethylases, such as JHDM2A and LSD1, can demethylate H3K9me1/2 but not H3K9me3 (52,53). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Other demethylases, such as those of the JMJD2 family that can act on trimethylysine, would be required for removal of the H3K9me3 mark (54–56). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>One untested hypothesis is that the G9a and GLP ankyrin repeats could compete with the non-processive catalytic reaction, quenching the reaction at the mono- and dimethyl state and protecting substrates from trimethylation by competition with the catalytic domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Such competition could come into play whether G9a/GLP themselves are responsible for catalyzing the H3K9me2 to H3K9me3 transition, or another enzyme (such as SETDB1) carries out this process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The ability to limit methylation will be variable, as some G9a substrates will make poor binding partners for the ankyrin repeats. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>In particular, for ankyrin repeat binding, H3K9 through H3G13 were observed in the crystal structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>A diglycine motif (H3G12 and H3G13) is required to allow for a sharp turn and mutation to alanine reduced binding (33). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>These features are largely dispensable for the methylation, where only H3T6-H3T11 are required for G9a/GLP SET domain activity (30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>H3R8—which is indispensable for methylation—and preceding residues do not appear in the ankyrin repeat structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Although the substrate requirements for methylation have been studied exhaustively, the current understanding of binding specificity of the ankyrin repeats comes from a single target. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>It would be interesting to determine whether the substrates that are not bound as products are more prone to conversion to trimethylation, either by G9a/GLP or another methyltransferase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Taken together, the histone and non-histone methyltransferase activity of G9a and GLP, potentially moderated by the product binding domains, along with the action of competitive demethylases, may allow a distinction between the ‘permanent’ silencing associated with imprinting or restriction of cell fate, where HP1 dependent chromatin compaction and DNA methylation are warranted, and more dynamic processes, such as cell-cycle dependent regulation, silencing in cell types with plastic fates, metabolic feedback (e.g. bile-acid metabolism) and cell signaling through nuclear receptors (2,3,6,57). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>G9a/GLP product binding and ‘gatekeeping’ </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>A second possibility is that G9a and GLP bind their products to protect the modification, competing with demethylases that might back-modify the mark (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>This ‘gatekeeper’ function has been suggested by studies showing GLP or G9a, among several other methyltransferases, restrict unliganded nuclear receptors from activating transcription (57). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Liganded nuclear receptors require a partner demethylase to promote transcription. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>This begs the question of whether it is the methyl mark or the physical presence of the methyltransferase and associated complex that serves as the gatekeeper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Treatment with estradiol decreased promoter occupancy of several methyltransferases and the knockdown of the methytransferase itself is sufficient to yield transcriptional activity in the absence of ligand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>This suggests active, promoter specific competition between methylases and demethylases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Sequestering methylation through product binding could provide a physical means of blocking removal of the mark. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>At the same time, the physical presence of the methyltransferase complex could block promoter access and aberrant transcription. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Additionally, since G9a/GLP heteromers could bind tails of neighboring nucleosomes, substantial local cross-linking could occur, contributing to compaction of local chromatin (Figure 3). Figure 2.Product protection. Product binding could protect the H3K9me1,2 from Histone Lysine Demethylases (HKDMs), or conversion to H3K9me3 by Histone Lysine Methyltransferases (HKMTs), including that of G9a/GLP. Figure 3.Compaction of chromatin. Polyvalent binding could compact chromatin by crosslinking nucleosomes bearing H3K9 methylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>One member of the dimer, and one H3 tail are shown for simplicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, G9a methylates H1.4, and facilitates its binding to chromatin (though the requirement of product binding has not been formally demonstrated). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Recruiting allies to reinforce silencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>H1.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>This role as a chromatin-compacting gatekeeper is reinforced by the ability of G9a to recruit other proteins, including histone H1.4, HP1 and C/EBP (CCAAT/Enhancer-binding protein), to chromatin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Though there are several H1 variants, they are generally silencing and contribute to higher order chromatin structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>H1 positioning serves to block nuclesome repositioning and sliding, and it occludes access of other proteins to DNA [reviewed in (58)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>H1 variants appear to have distinct, non-overlapping roles, and H1.4 participates in dynamic, gene specific silencing (59). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>G9a methylates H1.4 at lysine 26 (H1.4K26), suggesting a cross-talk where the presence of methylated H3K9 could recruit G9a to methylate H1.4K26, or vice versa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>G9a also appears to participate directly in recruiting H1.4 to chromatin (59). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>It will be interesting to determine if product binding is involved, as the residues flanking K26 appear ideal for ankyrin repeat binding (K26SAGG versus K9STGG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>G9a binding of H1.4K26me could facilitate its placement onto chromatin and reinforce the alteration of chromatin structure brought about by H1 (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The methylation of H1 serves as another mark to reinforce silencing, as methylated H1.4 is a binding platform for HP1 (59,60), for L3MBTL1, which participates in chromatin compaction (59) [reviewed in (61)] and for MSX1, a homeobox transcriptional repressor (62). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Completing the cycle, H1.4 lysine demethylases were also identified (59). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>HP1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>G9a and GLP are required for the binding of HP1 to euchromatin, as the knockout of either greatly diminishes euchromatic HP1 staining, and loss of G9a reduces HP1 occupancy at specific promoters (4,10,63). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Paradoxically, although the G9a catalytic domain is sufficient for silencing when targeted to a reporter gene, it is insufficient for HP1 recruitment (9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>It appears that G9a targets HP1 to chromatin by automethylating itself (Figure 4a), potentially at multiple sites (29,32). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The dominant automethylation site (found in GLP also) mimics the region around H3K9, even containing a phosphorylation site that blocks HP1 binding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Mutation of the target lysine eliminates HP1 binding and causes HP1 to delocalize from G9a containing loci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, both relevant studies found G9a automethylation sites to be di- and trimethylated (29,32). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Consistent with our proposal that ankyrin repeat binding to mono- and dimethylated products might regulate product specificity, the identified automethylation sites contain substitutions (KTMSK instead of KSTGG in H3) that should render binding to ankyrin repeats impossible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Again, degree of methylation is all-important, as HP1 has a preference for H3K9me2/3 over H3K9me1 (51). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The best in vivo demonstration of this specificity is provided by the overexpression of a demethylase (GASC1) that removes the H3K9me2/3 marks but cannot act on H3K9me1 (55). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The gain in H3K9me1 at the expense of H3K9me2/3 was insufficient to retain HP1 binding (55). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The requirement for direct interaction of G9a with HP1 is reminiscent of Suv39H1 mediated targeting of HP1, where not only H3K9 methylation, but also a direct interaction between Suv39H1 and HP1 is required for HP1 residence (9,64). Figure 4.Recuritment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>(a) G9a automethylation recruits HP1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>(b) DNA methyltransferases interact with G9a in a manner not dependent on catalytic activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>(c) G9a/GLP have been shown to bind or to methylate a number of targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>G9a methylation of C/EPBβ blocks transcriptional activation, and G9a methylation of the CYDL chromodomain blocks its ability to bind histone (red X’s). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Many other targets have been identified, some of which may also be bound as products. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>As HP1 itself has been implicated in the recruitment of other protein and DNA methyltransferases in the formation of not only silent heterochromatin but also euchromatin, this could prove an important gateway into other mutually reinforcing mechanisms of silencing (65). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Some studies have proposed a direct interaction between G9a and the DNA methyltransferases (see below). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>However, HP1 binding to automethylated G9a or H3K9me2/3 could serve to recruit DNMT3a and DNMT3b. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Indeed, HP1 knockdown has little effect on G9a occupancy at the TNFα promoter, but DNMT3a, DNMT3b and CpG methylation were lost in the absence of HP1 or G9a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>This suggests that G9a is the key organizer of silencing at that promoter and that recruitment of DNMTs requires HP1 as a bridge (63). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>DNA methyltransferases </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>There is a surprising lack of cross-talk involved in G9a-mediated DNA methylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>G9a and GLP are both required for normal levels of DNA methylation in facultative heterochromatin and interact with DNA methyltransferases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>An attractive model emerges, where G9a and GLP might establish H3K9 methylation, bind to it, and then attract DNA methyltransferases directly, or through HP1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>However, several studies have shown the catalytic activities of G9a and GLP to be dispensable for DNA methylation, and that G9a-mediated DNA and histone methylation are independent pathways, either of which can accomplish silencing (34,41,42). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>This implies that G9a and GLP play a more structural role in the context of DNA methylation, where their presence, but not activity, recruits DNA methyltransferases to target loci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Perhaps they bridge the DNA-binding partners of G9a (see above) and DNA methyltransferases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Indeed, G9a appears to interact directly with the de novo DNA methyltransferase DNMT3a and DNMT3b through its ankyrin repeat domain, even in the absence of the G9a catalytic SET domain (42) (Figure 4b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Whether this is physiological or perhaps an alternate pathway that suffices to bring about some methylation in the absence of a pathway that does more linearly couple histone and DNA methylation is unclear. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>DNA binding and other target proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>G9a also has been reported to inhibit the CCAAT/Enhancer-binding protein-β (C/EBP-β) (31). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>G9a interacts with and methylates C/EBP-β, blocking its ability to activate transcription. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Binding is not observed in the absence of a functional catalytic domain, which suggests product binding; however, this was not formally tested (31). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Many other targets for G9a methylation have been identified (29,30); all of which are known to play roles in processes involving chromatin (Figure 4c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>It is unclear how many of these substrates can also meet the requirement for product binding to the ankyrin repeats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>In general, lysine methylation exerts its effect through modules that bind the methyl marks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>As an exception to this rule, G9a methylation appears to block directly the CYDL chromodomain from binding H3K9me3, apparently by altering the chemical properties of a key lysine (30). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Spreading the methyl mark </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>G9a and GLP are responsible for broad regions of H3K9 methylation up to 4.9 Mb, in what have been termed ‘large organized chromatin K9 modifications’ (LOCKS), which can cover up to nearly 50% of the genome in some differentiated cell types (66). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The finding that there are few LOCKS in embryonic stem cells, and that they grow in number with differentiation is under dispute [see (67), rebuttal in (68)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>However, the existence of LOCKS, their apparent tissue specificity and the presence of G9a/GLP-mediated methylation within LOCKS is not (68). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>These broad patterns of methylation are at odds with the narrow targeting of G9a and GLP to primarily promoter regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>For example, G9a is found in complex with the CCAAT displacement protein, a transcription factor involved in differentiation and development (8), Blimp-1 (also known as PRDI-BF1), a DNA-binding protein involved in the terminal differentiation of B lymphocytes (5) and is linked to the CtBP co-repressor via an adaptor protein (11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Several DNA-binding zinc-finger proteins also recruit G9a (7,69). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Spreading the modification outward from these sites could bring about the methylation of large regions of chromatin adjacent to regions where G9a and GLP are targeted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>In spreading, the binding of product [via their ankyrin repeats (33)] could position G9a and GLP to methylate the next neighboring nucleosome, which then can serve as a binding site for enzyme (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The cyclic repetition of this process would allow the mark to propagate over great distances. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Although this model is attractive, G9a is also targeted to chromatin by non-coding RNAs, which form large nuclear sub-compartments to which genes are recruited during silencing (70–72). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Long non-coding RNAs are best recognized for silencing clusters of imprinted genes, but given the volume of non-coding RNAs detected, and their specific expression patterns in development and differentiation [reviewed in (73,74)] it would not be surprising if the formation of G9a-containing LOCKS is a RNA-mediated process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>These nuclear sub-structures may distinguish the large swaths of more permanent silencing associated with cell differentiation and imprinting from more localized and reversible domains of G9a- and GLP-mediated silencing. Figure 5.Spreading. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Like Su(var3-9)/HP1 and yeast Clr4 (SET and chromodomain), product binding could help propagate the methyl mark by posing the catalytic domain for attack on the next neighboring nucleosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Repetition of this process allows spreading of the mark from the site of nucleation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>CONCLUSIONS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The web of interactions detailed above will likely benefit from a systems approach like those applied to signaling networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Catalytic activity, product binding, RNA binding and partner binding will have to be analysed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Of particular interest is defining what non-histone targets of G9a/GLP can be bound as products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>It is unknown what governs the switch to co-activation by G9a—whether the presence of another mark like arginine methylation or recruiting a key transcription factor is important. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Similarly, it is unclear if DNA methylation follows lysine methylation and HP1 recruitment, or if the two are independent pathways bridged by G9a/GLP acting as a scaffold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Lastly, we ask whether the propagation of the methyl mark occurs by product-binding mediated spreading, a RNA-mediated process, or both. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>G9a and GLP provide a tractable system to test hypotheses, as point mutants perturbing catalytic activity and product binding are defined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>One unanswered question that could complicate these experiments is why, despite their apparent heteromeric nature, perturbation of one activity typically has a penetrating effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>In the case of complete knockouts, loss of one member of the complex causes the other to degrade (10), but in the case of more discreet deletions or point mutants, the answer remains enigmatic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Detailed analyses using mutations in both partners will likely be essential. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>FUNDING </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>R.E.C. is a fellow of the Jane Coffin Childs Memorial Fund for Medical Research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The work in the Cheng laboratory is currently supported by the US National Institutes of Health (GM068680-05, GM049245-16 and DK-082678-02). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Funding for open access charge: waived. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Conflict of interest statement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>None declared. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>1ChaturvediCPHoseyAMPaliiCPerez-IratxetaCNakataniYRanishJADilworthFJBrandMDual role for the methyltransferase G9a in the maintenance of beta-globin gene transcription in adult erythroid cellsProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>USA2009106183031830819822740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>2DavisCAHaberlandMArnoldMASutherlandLBMcDonaldOGRichardsonJAChildsGHarrisSOwensGKOlsonENPRISM/PRDM6, a transcriptional repressor that promotes the proliferative gene program in smooth muscle cellsMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Biol.2006262626263616537907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>3FangSMiaoJXiangLPonugotiBTreuterEKemperJKCoordinated recruitment of histone methyltransferase G9a and other chromatin-modifying enzymes in SHP-mediated regulation of hepatic bile acid metabolismMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Biol.2007271407142417145766 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>4FeldmanNGersonAFangJLiEZhangYShinkaiYCedarHBergmanYG9a-mediated irreversible epigenetic inactivation of Oct-3/4 during early embryogenesisNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Biol.2006818819416415856 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>5GyoryIWuJFejerGSetoEWrightKLPRDI-BF1 recruits the histone H3 methyltransferase G9a in transcriptional silencingNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Immunol.2004529930814985713 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>6KimJKEstevePOJacobsenSEPradhanSUHRF1 binds G9a and participates in p21 transcriptional regulation in mammalian cellsNucleic Acids Res.20093749350519056828 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>7NishidaMKatoMKatoYSasaiNUedaJTachibanaMShinkaiYYamaguchiMIdentification of ZNF200 as a novel binding partner of histone H3 methyltransferase G9aGenes Cells20071287788817584299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>8NishioHWalshMJCCAAT displacement protein/cut homolog recruits G9a histone lysine methyltransferase to repress transcriptionProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>USA2004101112571126215269344 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>9StewartMDLiJWongJRelationship between histone H3 lysine 9 methylation, transcription repression, and heterochromatin protein 1 recruitmentMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Biol.2005252525253815767660 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>10TachibanaMUedaJFukudaMTakedaNOhtaTIwanariHSakihamaTKodamaTHamakuboTShinkaiYHistone methyltransferases G9a and GLP form heteromeric complexes and are both crucial for methylation of euchromatin at H3-K9Genes Dev.20051981582615774718 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>11UedaJTachibanaMIkuraTShinkaiYZinc finger protein Wiz links G9a/GLP histone methyltransferases to the co-repressor molecule CtBPJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Chem.2006281201202012816702210 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>12LeeDYNorthropJPKuoMHStallcupMRHistone H3 lysine 9 methyltransferase G9a is a transcriptional coactivator for nuclear receptorsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Chem.20062818476848516461774 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>13YuanXFengWImhofAGrummtIZhouYActivation of RNA polymerase I transcription by cockayne syndrome group B protein and histone methyltransferase G9aMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Cell20072758559517707230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>14BeckerPBGene regulation: a finger on the markNature2006442313216823438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>15HenikoffSHistone modifications: combinatorial complexity or cumulative simplicity?Proc Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>USA20051025308530915811936 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>16PtashneMOn the use of the word ‘epigenetic’Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Biol.200717R233R23617407749 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>17RuthenburgAJLiHPatelDJAllisCDMultivalent engagement of chromatin modifications by linked binding modulesNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Biol.2007898399418037899 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>18SchreiberSLBernsteinBESignaling network model of chromatinCell200211177177812526804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>19HungTBindaOChampagneKSKuoAJJohnsonKChangHYSimonMDKutateladzeTGGozaniOING4 mediates crosstalk between histone H3 K4 trimethylation and H3 acetylation to attenuate cellular transformationMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Cell.20093324825619187765 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>20LeeJSShuklaASchneiderJSwansonSKWashburnMPFlorensLBhaumikSRShilatifardAHistone crosstalk between H2B monoubiquitination and H3 methylation mediated by COMPASSCell20071311084109618083099 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>21SuganumaTWorkmanJLCrosstalk among Histone ModificationsCell200813560460719013272 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>22CedarHBergmanYLinking DNA methylation and histone modification: patterns and paradigmsNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Genet.20091029530419308066 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>23FischleWTalk is cheap—cross-talk in establishment, maintenance, and readout of chromatin modificationsGenes Dev.2008223375338219141469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>24van AttikumHGasserSMCrosstalk between histone modifications during the DNA damage responseTrends Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Biol.20091920721719342239 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>25YangXJSetoELysine acetylation: codified crosstalk with other posttranslational modificationsMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Cell20083144946118722172 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>26TachibanaMSugimotoKNozakiMUedaJOhtaTOhkiMFukudaMTakedaNNiidaHKatoHG9a histone methyltransferase plays a dominant role in euchromatic histone H3 lysine 9 methylation and is essential for early embryogenesisGenes Dev.2002161779179112130538 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>27PetersAHKubicekSMechtlerKO’SullivanRJDerijckAAPerez-BurgosLKohlmaierAOpravilSTachibanaMShinkaiYPartitioning and plasticity of repressive histone methylation states in mammalian chromatinMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Cell2003121577158914690609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>28RiceJCBriggsSDUeberheideBBarberCMShabanowitzJHuntDFShinkaiYAllisCDHistone methyltransferases direct different degrees of methylation to define distinct chromatin domainsMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Cell2003121591159814690610 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>29ChinHGEstevePOPradhanMBennerJPatnaikDCareyMFPradhanSAutomethylation of G9a and its implication in wider substrate specificity and HP1 bindingNucleic Acids Res.2007357313732317962312 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>30RathertPDhayalanAMurakamiMZhangXTamasRJurkowskaRKomatsuYShinkaiYChengXJeltschAProtein lysine methyltransferase G9a acts on non-histone targetsNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Chem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Biol.2008434434618438403 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>31PlessOKowenz-LeutzEKnoblichMLausenJBeyermannMWalshMJLeutzAG9a-mediated lysine methylation alters the function of CCAAT/enhancer-binding protein-betaJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Chem.2008283263572636318647749 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>32SampathSCMarazziIYapKLSampathSCKrutchinskyANMecklenbraukerIVialeARudenskyEZhouMMChaitBTMethylation of a histone mimic within the histone methyltransferase G9a regulates protein complex assemblyMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Cell20072759660817707231 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>33CollinsRENorthropJPHortonJRLeeDYZhangXStallcupMRChengXThe ankyrin repeats of G9a and GLP histone methyltransferases are mono- and dimethyllysine binding modulesNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Struct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Biol.20081524525018264113 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>34TachibanaMMatsumuraYFukudaMKimuraHShinkaiYG9a/GLP complexes independently mediate H3K9 and DNA methylation to silence transcriptionEMBO J.2008272681269018818694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>35RoopraAQaziRSchoenikeBDaleyTJMorrisonJFLocalized domains of G9a-mediated histone methylation are required for silencing of neuronal genesMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Cell20041472773815200951 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>36MaDKChiangCHPonnusamyKMingGLSongHG9a and Jhdm2a regulate embryonic stem cell fusion-induced reprogramming of adult neural stem cellsStem Cells2008262131214118535151 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>37ChangYZhangXHortonJRUpadhyayAKSpannhoffALiuJSnyderJPBedfordMTChengXStructural basis for G9a-like protein lysine methyltransferase inhibition by BIX-01294Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Struct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Biol.20091631231719219047 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>38KubicekSO’SullivanRJAugustEMHickeyERZhangQTeodoroMLReaSMechtlerKKowalskiJAHomonCAReversal of H3K9me2 by a small-molecule inhibitor for the G9a histone methyltransferaseMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Cell20072547348117289593 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>39ShiYDespontsCDoJTHahmHSScholerHRDingSInduction of pluripotent stem cells from mouse embryonic fibroblasts by Oct4 and Klf4 with small-molecule compoundsCell Stem Cell2008356857418983970 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>40SnowdenAWGregoryPDCaseCCPaboCOGene-specific targeting of H3K9 methylation is sufficient for initiating repression in vivoCurr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Biol.2002122159216612498693 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>41DongKBMaksakovaIAMohnFLeungDAppanahRLeeSYangHWLamLLMagerDLSchubelerDDNA methylation in ES cells requires the lysine methyltransferase G9a but not its catalytic activityEMBO J.2008272691270118818693 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>42Epsztejn-LitmanSFeldmanNAbu-RemailehMShufaroYGersonAUedaJDeplusRFuksFShinkaiYCedarHDe novo DNA methylation promoted by G9a prevents reprogramming of embryonically silenced genesNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Struct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Biol.2008151176118318953337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>43ShahbazianMDZhangKGrunsteinMHistone H2B ubiquitylation controls processive methylation but not monomethylation by Dot1 and Set1Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Cell20051927127716039595 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>44ChinHGPradhanMEstevePOPatnaikDEvansT.C.JrPradhanSSequence specificity and role of proximal amino acids of the histone H3 tail on catalysis of murine G9A lysine 9 histone H3 methyltransferaseBiochemistry200544129981300616185068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>45SuRCBrownKESaaberSFisherAGMerkenschlagerMSmaleSTDynamic assembly of silent chromatin during thymocyte maturationNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Genet.20043650250615098035 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>46TahilianiMMeiPFangRLeonorTRutenbergMShimizuFLiJRaoAShiYThe histone H3K4 demethylase SMCX links REST target genes to X-linked mental retardationNature200744760160517468742 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>47CollinsRETachibanaMTamaruHSmithKMJiaDZhangXSelkerEUShinkaiYChengXIn vitro and in vivo analyses of a Phe/Tyr switch controlling product specificity of histone lysine methyltransferasesJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Chem.20052805563557015590646 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>48TrojerPZhangJYonezawaMSchmidtAZhengHJenuweinTReinbergDDynamic Histone H1 Isotype 4 Methylation and Demethylation by Histone Lysine Methyltransferase G9a/KMT1C and the Jumonji Domain-containing JMJD2/KDM4 ProteinsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Chem.20092848395840519144645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>49OsipovichOMilleyRMeadeATachibanaMShinkaiYKrangelMSOltzEMTargeted inhibition of V(D)J recombination by a histone methyltransferaseNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Immunol.2004530931614985714 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>50WagschalASutherlandHGWoodfineKHenckelAChebliKSchulzROakeyRJBickmoreWAFeilRG9a histone methyltransferase contributes to imprinting in the mouse placentaMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Biol.2008281104111318039842 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>51HughesRMWigginsKRKhorasanizadehSWatersMLRecognition of trimethyllysine by a chromodomain is not driven by the hydrophobic effectProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>USA2007104111841118817581885 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>52MetzgerEWissmannMYinNMullerJMSchneiderRPetersAHGuntherTBuettnerRSchuleRLSD1 demethylates repressive histone marks to promote androgen-receptor-dependent transcriptionNature200543743643916079795 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>53YamaneKToumazouCTsukadaYErdjument-BromageHTempstPWongJZhangYJHDM2A, a JmjC-containing H3K9 demethylase, facilitates transcription activation by androgen receptorCell200612548349516603237 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>54ChenZZangJWhetstineJHongXDavrazouFKutateladzeTGSimpsonMMaoQPanCHDaiSStructural insights into histone demethylation by JMJD2 family membersCell200612569170216677698 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>55CloosPAChristensenJAggerKMaiolicaARappsilberJAntalTHansenKHHelinKThe putative oncogene GASC1 demethylates tri- and dimethylated lysine 9 on histone H3Nature200644230731116732293 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>56WhetstineJRNottkeALanFHuarteMSmolikovSChenZSpoonerELiEZhangGColaiacovoMReversal of histone lysine trimethylation by the JMJD2 family of histone demethylasesCell200612546748116603238 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>57Garcia-BassetsIKwonYSTeleseFPrefontaineGGHuttKRChengCSJuBGOhgiKAWangJEscoubet-LozachLHistone methylation-dependent mechanisms impose ligand dependency for gene activation by nuclear receptorsCell200712850551817289570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>58HappelNDoeneckeDHistone H1 and its isoforms: contribution to chromatin structure and functionGene200943111219059319 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>59SanchoMDianiEBeatoMJordanADepletion of human histone H1 variants uncovers specific roles in gene expression and cell growthPLoS Genet.20084e100022718927631 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>60DaujatSZeisslerUWaldmannTHappelNSchneiderRHP1 binds specifically to Lys26-methylated histone H1.4, whereas simultaneous Ser27 phosphorylation blocks HP1 bindingJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Chem.2005280380903809516127177 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B61"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>61TrojerPReinbergDBeyond histone methyl-lysine binding: how malignant brain tumor (MBT) protein L3MBTL1 impacts chromatin structureCell Cycle2008757858518256536 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B62"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>62LeeHHabasRAbate-ShenCMSX1 cooperates with histone H1b for inhibition of transcription and myogenesisScience20043041675167815192231 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B63"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>63El GazzarMYozaBKChenXHuJHawkinsGAMcCallCEG9a and HP1 couple histone and DNA methylation to TNFalpha transcription silencing during endotoxin toleranceJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Chem.2008283321983220818809684 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B64"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>64EskelandREberharterAImhofAHP1 binding to chromatin methylated at H3K9 is enhanced by auxiliary factorsMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Biol.20072745346517101786 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B65"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>65KwonSHWorkmanJLThe heterochromatin protein 1 (HP1) family: put away a bias toward HP1Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Cells20082621722718664736 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B66"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>66WenBWuHShinkaiYIrizarryRAFeinbergAPLarge histone H3 lysine 9 dimethylated chromatin blocks distinguish differentiated from embryonic stem cellsNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Genet.20094124625019151716 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B67"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>67FilionGJvan SteenselBReassessing the abundance of H3K9me2 chromatin domains in embryonic stem cellsNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Genet.201042420037608 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B68"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>68WenBWuHShinkaiYIrizarryRFeinbergAReply to “Reassessing the abundance of H3K9me2 chromatin domains in embryonic stem cells”Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Genet.20104256 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B69"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>69VassenLFiolkaKMoroyTGfi1b alters histone methylation at target gene promoters and sites of gamma-satellite containing heterochromatinEMBO J.2006252409241916688220 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B70"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>70NaganoTMitchellJASanzLAPaulerFMFerguson-SmithACFeilRFraserPThe Air noncoding RNA epigenetically silences transcription by targeting G9a to chromatinScience20083221717172018988810 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B71"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>71RedrupLBrancoMRPerdeauxERKruegerCLewisASantosFNaganoTCobbBSFraserPReikWThe long noncoding RNA Kcnq1ot1 organises a lineage-specific nuclear domain for epigenetic gene silencingDevelopment200913652553019144718 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B72"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>72PandeyRRMondalTMohammadFEnrothSRedrupLKomorowskiJNaganoTMancini-DinardoDKanduriCKcnq1ot1 antisense noncoding RNA mediates lineage-specific transcriptional silencing through chromatin-level regulationMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Cell20083223224618951091 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B73"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>73AmaralPPDingerMEMercerTRMattickJSThe eukaryotic genome as an RNA machineScience20083191787178918369136 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B74"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>74MattickJSAmaralPPDingerMEMercerTRMehlerMFRNA regulation of epigenetic processesBioessays200931515919154003 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
