<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3125170</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21738642</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-05225</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021362</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Virology</subject><subj-group><subject>Viral Disease Diagnosis</subject><subject>Viral Evolution</subject><subject>Viral Persistence and Latency</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Gastrointestinal Infections</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Bocavirus Episome in Infected Human Tissue Contains Non-Identical Termini </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Genome of Human Bocavirus Episome</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kapoor</surname><given-names>Amit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hornig</surname><given-names>Mady</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Asokan</surname><given-names>Aravind</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Brent</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Henriquez</surname><given-names>Jose A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lipkin</surname><given-names>W. Ian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Center for Infection and Immunity, Columbia University, New York, New York, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Gene Therapy Center, The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, North Carolina, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Vartanian</surname><given-names>Jean-Pierre</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Institut Pasteur, France</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>ak3117@columbia.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: AK WIL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: AK JAH MH BW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: AK JAH AA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AK JAH AA MH BW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: AK MH WIL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e21362</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>3</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Kapoor et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title/><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Human bocaviruses (HBoV) are highly prevalent human infections whose pathogenic potential remains unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Recent identification of the first non-human primate bocavirus [1] in captive gorillas raised the possibility of the persistent nature of bocavirus infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>To characterize bocavirus infection in humans, we tested intestinal biopsies from 22 children with gastrointestinal disease for the presence of HBoV DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Four HBoV-positive tissue samples were analyzed to determine whether viral DNA was present in the linear genomic, the episomal closed circular or the host genome-integrated form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Whereas one tissue sample positive for HBoV3 contained the episomal form (HBoV3-E1), none had the genome-integrated form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The complete genome sequence of HBoV3-E1 contains 5319 nucleotides of which 513 represent the non-coding terminal sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The secondary structure of HBoV3-E1 termini suggests several conserved and variable features among human and animal bocaviruses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Our observation that HBoV genome exists as head-to-tail monomer in infected tissue either reflects the likely evolution of alternative replication mechanism in primate bocaviruses or a mechanism of viral persistence in their host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Moreover, we identified the HBoV genomic terminal sequences that will be helpful in developing reverse genetic systems for these widely prevalent parvoviruses. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Significance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>HBoV have been found in healthy human controls as well as individuals with respiratory or gastrointestinal disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Our findings suggest that HBoV DNA can exist as episomes in infected human tissues and therefore can likely establish persistent infection in the host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Previous efforts to grow HBoV in cell culture and to develop reverse genetic systems have been unsuccessful. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Complete genomic sequence of the HBoV3 episome and its genomic termini will improve our understanding of HBoV replication mechanism and its pathogenesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Parvoviruses are small, non-enveloped icosahedral viruses with single-stranded linear DNA genomes that frequently infect animals through the fecal-oral route [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>They are members of the Parvoviridae family, which comprises two sub-families, Densovirinae and Parvovirinae that infect non-vertebrate and vertebrate hosts, respectively [2], [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses (ICTV) has further classified the sub-family Parvovirinae into five genera: Dependovirus, Bocavirus, Erythrovirus, Parvovirus and Amdovirus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Bocaviruses are unique among parvoviruses because they contain a third ORF between the non-structural and structural coding regions [4], [5], [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The genus Bocavirus includes the bovine parvoviruses (BPV), minute virus of canines (MVC) [2], porcine bocaviruses [7], gorilla bocavirus [1] and 4 species of human bocaviruses (HBoV 1–4) [4], [8], [9], [10], [11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Parvoviruses are unique as they have a linear single-stranded DNA genome with hairpin sequences at each end. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The length of the DNA genome is between 4500 and 5500 nucleotides [2], [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Depending on their replication requirements, parvoviruses (PV) can be autonomous PV or dependoviruses; the latter includes adeno-associated viruses (AAV) and requires presence of a helper virus for successful replication [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Bocaviruses are considered autonomous parvoviruses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The non-coding or non-translated regions on the genomic termini contain palindromic sequences, commonly known as inverted terminal repeats (ITR), that play a vital role in viral replication [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Since their discovery using nucleic acid amplification-based techniques [4], [8], [9], [11], the terminal regions of all primate bocavirus species remain unsequenced, limiting the scope of studies on viral replication and the development of reverse genetic systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Here we report the complete genome of the HBoV episome found in infected human intestinal tissue and the secondary structure of its termini. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>HBoV1 infection, widely considered acute, has been linked with mild to severe lower respiratory tract infections in children, frequently in association with other viral infections [8], [13], [14], [15], [16], [17], [18], [19], [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>HBoV1 has also been detected at low frequency in stool samples, although its association with enteric disease is weaker than with respiratory disease [9], [21], [22], [23], [24], [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>HBoV2 was first identified in stool samples of Pakistani children [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Lower frequencies of HBoV2 were detected in the stools of Scottish adults and children [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>HBoV3 and HBoV2 were recently found in stool samples from Australian children with diarrhea [9], and HBoV4 was first identified in stool samples of children from Nigeria and Tunisia [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Whether any of the four HBoV species causes human disease is still undetermined [3], [27], [28]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>During a survey of divergent bocaviruses in animals, the first distinct species of non-human primate bocavirus, GBoV1, was identified in stool samples of gorillas from a captive colony [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis suggests that GBoV1 is most genetically related to HBoV1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>GBoV1 and its related variant were also detected in stool samples of wild animals in Cameroon, confirming their non-human primate origin and worldwide distribution [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The presence of GBoV1 in stool samples of animals living in captivity for several years suggests that bocavirus infection may be persistent in these animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In humans, HBoV infection is predominantly acute; therefore, most studies done to determine the association between HBoV and disease compared the prevalence of viral DNA in samples from symptomatic patients and healthy controls [9], [14], [17], [21], [22], [23], [30], [31], [32], [33], [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Here we report the first detection of episomal HBoV3 in human intestinal tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>These results raise the possibility that bocaviruses, like other well-characterized parvoviruses, may cause persistent infection of their hosts [12], [35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Samples and source </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Patient biopsies were collected as part of a study to assess the frequency of measles virus transcripts in ilea of children with autistic disorder and gastrointestinal symptoms (AUT-GI) and children with gastrointestinal symptoms without any apparent neurologic disorder (CON-GI) [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The Institutional Review Boards (IRB) of Columbia University Medical Center (CUMC) and Partners specifically reviewed and approved the design of the previous study under which these samples were obtained after written consent of parents and guardians, in addition to child assent, as appropriate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>After the conclusion of the previous study, all residual samples were de-identified and stored, and thereafter were deemed exempt from additional review by the IRB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>All procedures employed in the current study were approved by the CUMC IRB under a human subjects protocol designed for the investigation of properly de-identified samples, wherein the need for any additional consent has been specifically waived. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>All samples were analyzed anonymously. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Sample processing and pan-bocavirus PCR assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>DNA was extracted from ileal biopsy material from 22 patients (15 AUT-GI and 7 CON-GI patients) with TRIzol (Invitrogen), using the manufacturer's protocols for sequential extraction of RNA and DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>DNA concentration and integrity were determined using a Nanodrop ND-1000 Spectrophotometer (Nanodrop Technologies) and a Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Samples were stored at −80°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>PCR primers panBOV-F1 (5′-TAATGCAYCARGAYTGGGTIGANCC -3′) and panBOV-R1 (5′- GTACAGTCRTAYTCRTTRAARCACCA-3′) were used for the first round of hemi-nested PCR; primers panBOV-F2 (5′- GCAYCARGAYTGGGTIGANCCWGC – 3′) and panBOV-R1 (same as first round) were used for the second round of semi-nested PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>For the first round of nested PCR, 5 µl of each specimen's DNA were mixed with 5.2 µl 10× polymerase reaction buffer (Qiagen), 3 µl of MgCl2, 1.25 µl each dNTP (10 mM), 50 pmol each of forward (both panBOV-F1) and reverse primer (panBOV-R1), 0.65 µl HotStart Taq DNA polymerase (Qiagen) and 32 µl nuclease free water, in a total reaction volume of 50 µl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The PCR reaction was performed using the following protocol: initial denaturation at 95°C for 7 min, followed by 6 cycles at 95°C for 40 sec, 60°C for 45 sec and 68°C for 30 sec, followed by 35 cycles at 95°C for 30 sec, 57°C for 30 sec and 68°C for 30 sec, and a final extension at 72°C for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>During the first round of PCR, the first 6 cycles were done at a high annealing temperature to increase stringency, and the remaining cycles were performed at a lower temperature to facilitate primer hybridization by tolerating some nucleotide mismatches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>We added 0.5 µl of the PCR product from the first round to the reaction mixture for the second round of PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>We used the same cycling conditions for the second round, with an annealing temperature of 64°C for the first 6 cycles and 58°C for the remaining 35 cycles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Following electrophoresis, products were imaged on a 2% agarose gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>PCR products showing positive bands of approximately 290 bp, corresponding to the highly conserved amplified NS gene fragment, were purified using a PCR purification kit (Qiagen) and then directly sequenced from both ends. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Complete genome sequencing and inverse PCRs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The complete HBoV2 and HBOV3 genomes found in clinical samples were acquired using the primer walking approach as previously described [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>In brief, each PCR extension step used one primer specific for the novel virus sequence and another degenerate primer to hybridize all known bocavirus sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>After the complete genome was assembled, each base was sequenced in triplicate to confirm our results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>To detect the presence of the extra-chromosomal circular episomal form of HBoV (HBoV-EPI), we used a nested inverse PCR assay with outward primers against known genomic termini. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>We used the following inverse PCR primer sequences (5′ to 3′): TATGCTTATAAGTTCCTCTCCAATGGAC for Bo2-Inv-F1; GAAAAGGGTGACTGTAATCCCGAGC for Bo3-Inv-F1; TCTAATTACAGGAGCAGAAAAGGCC for Bo2-Inv-R1; GATTGGCTGACATACGTCACTTCC for Bo3-Inv-R1; GTTCCTCTCCAATGGACAAG for Bo2-Inv-F2; GGGTGACTGTAATCCCGAGCTCA for Bo3-Inv-F2; CAGGAGCAGAAAAGGCCATA for Bo2-Inv-R2; and CTGACATACGTCACTTCCTGGGC for Bo3-Inv-R2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>All first round primers were designed to be exonuclease-resistant by phosphorothioation of the first three 5′ end bases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The first round PCR mix contained Bo3-Inv-F1 or Bo2-Inv-F1 and Bo3-Inv-R1 or Bo2-Inv-R1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>During the second round, we used either Bo3-Inv-F2 or Bo2-Inv-F2 and Bo3-Inv-R2 or Bo2-Inv-R2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>For the first round of nested PCR, 5 µl of DNA extracted from tissue samples were used in first round of PCR using reaction conditions for Hot Start DNA polymerase (as described above). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The PCR reaction was performed using the following protocol: initial denaturation at 95°C for 7 min, followed by 5 cycles at 95°C for 40 s, 61°C for 40 s, and 72°C for 1 min, followed by 35 cycles at 95°C for 30 s, 58°C for 40 s, and 72°C for 1.15 min, and a final extension at 72°C for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>We added 0.5 µl of PCR product from the first round to the reaction mixture for the second round of PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Second round primers were used under identical cycling conditions, with annealing temperatures of 64°C and 57°C for the first 6 cycles and 60°C and 54°C for the remaining 35 cycles for HBoV3 and HBov2, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Following electrophoresis, products were imaged on a 1.5% agarose gel, isolated, and sequenced from both ends. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The complete HBoV3-Episome (HBoV3-E1) genome was submitted to Genbank under accession number JN086998. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>A detailed protocol of the techniques used to detect the HBoV host chromosome-integrated form (HBoV-INT) can be found in our recent publication on the discovery of mammalian endogenous parvoviruses [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Briefly, to detect the genome-integrated form, we used the same nested PCR assays described above, except that the template for the first round of inverse PCR used restriction enzyme digested- and re-circularized host genomic DNA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Sequence and DNA secondary structure analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>To determine the sequence relationship of HBoV3-E1 and HBoV3-IB1 with other known HBoV species, at least one representative virus, including the one with the best-characterized genome, was used to generate the nucleotide sequence alignments of the entire coding region (NS, NP and VP gene). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>We used the following Genbank sequences in the analysis: EU262978, FJ858259, AB481085, EF450727, AB481077, FJ560720 for HBoV1; FJ170279, EU082213, GQ200737, GU048664, GU048662, EU082214, GU048663, FJ170280, FJ170278 for HBoV2; EU918736, HM132056, FJ948861, GU048665, FJ973562, GQ867667, GQ867666, FJ973563 for HBoV3; and FJ973561 for HBoV4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The model test implemented in the phylogenetic program MEGA 5 [38] showed that the nucleotide substitution pattern among variable sites of different HBoV sequences can be best analyzed using a General Time Reversible (GTR) model with a discrete Gamma distribution (+G) of 5 rate categories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>We constructed a maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree and then performed bootstrap re-sampling to demonstrate robustness of phylogenetic groupings [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Modeling of the secondary structure of the non-coding DNA sequence region (NCR) between the VP and NS genes in HBoV3-E1 and MVC (FJ214110) was done using a standard minimum energy folding algorithm for single-stranded nucleic acids implemented in the “mfold” web server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mfold.rna.albany.edu/?q=mfold/DNA-Folding-Form">http://mfold.rna.albany.edu/?q=mfold/DNA-Folding-Form</ext-link>) [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>For better comparison with the HBoV3-E1 NCR, the secondary structure of the complete MVC NCR was determined after circularizing the linear MVC genome in 5′ to 3′ orientation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Comparative secondary structure analysis of the right-hand termini of different HBoV species was done using HBoV3-E1 and the most complete genomic terminal sequences available in Genbank for HBoV1 (GQ925675) and HBoV2 (GQ200737) [40]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Presence of HBoV DNA in human tissue samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>We examined the presence of HBoV DNA in intestinal biopsy samples using a sensitive nested PCR assay (1–10 copies) that targets conserved sequences in HBoV capsid genes and can amplify all known primate bocavirus species [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Of the 22 samples tested, 4 tested positive for HBoV DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Sequence analysis confirmed that 3 samples were positive for HBoV3, and 1 was positive for HBoV2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>These results were confirmed using PCR targeting other regions of the viral genome (NS and NP) [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The complete genome of the HBoV2 variant found in one child's biopsy tissues showed &gt;97% nucleotide identity to HBoV2 viruses recently identified in China and Thailand (Genbank accession no. GU048662-3 and GU301644, respectively) (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the HBoV3 found in these tissues showed &lt;1–2% nucleotide divergence from published HBoV3 genomes found in Australia, Nigeria and Thailand (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Sequence comparison of HBoV3 viruses found in other children also showed &lt;1% nucleotide divergence over the entire genomic coding region (NS, NP and VP gene). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The HBoV sequences reported in this study showed a high sequence similarity to already-published HBoV sequences published by us [4] and others [10], [31], [41]; thus, only minimal phylogenetic analysis was done to confirm the genetic relatedness among these viruses (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0021362-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021362.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Comparative phylogenetic analysis of HBoV3-E1 and HBoV2-IB1 (filled rectangles). </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide alignments were generated using the complete coding sequence of the NS, NP and VP genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Names of sequences used for analysis are shown as Genbank accession numbers followed by the names of HBoV species and strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The tree was constructed with the maximum likelihood method using a GTR+G substitution model [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Bootstrap replicates (&gt;70%) are shown above the branches and distances (&gt;0.02) are shown below the braches. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0021362.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>We used the same nested inverse PCR assays to detect the HBoV-INT and HBoV-EPI forms (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Non-manipulated nucleic acids extracted from HBoV DNA positive biopsies were used to detect the HBOV-EPI form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Inverse PCR assays of digested and re-circularized nucleic acids were used to detect the HBoV-INT form [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Although none of the 4 HBoV DNA-positive samples contained the HBoV-INT form, one sample was positive for the HBoV-EPI form (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>To confirm these results, inverse PCR assays were repeated on the original DNA sample, and the amplification product was sequenced multiple times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The sequences at the ends of the amplification product showed 100% nucleotide identity to the termini of linear HBoV3 and HBoV1 genomes available in Genbank (Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Sequencing and alignment of the inverse PCR product confirmed the amplification of the junction region sequence located between the 5′ and 3′ termini (head-to-tail orientation) and the presence of the HBoV3-EPI form in human tissue (Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0021362-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021362.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Schematic representation of the HBoV3 episome, results of inverse PCR and sequence alignment of HBoV genomic termini. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>(A) Describes the genomic organization of the HBoV3 episome and location/orientation of PCR primers used for screening samples and inverse PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>(B) Shows results of inverse PCR assay for three samples (B-1 to B-3) that were positive for HBoV3 screening PCR with molecular weight (MW) marker and negative (Neg) reagent PCR control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>(C) Shows alignment of previously known genomic termini of HBoV3 and HBoV1 linear genomes with the non-coding region of HBoV3 episome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Unique sequence identified in this study is shown as connecting the 3′ and 5′ termini (nucleotide with no background and “-” represent sequence that remained elusive in previous studies). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0021362.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Genomic characterization of HBoV3 episome </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Because we detected the HBoV-EPI form in only 1 sample, we re-extended and re-sequenced the complete HBoV3-E1 genome using the inverse PCR fragment as a starting point for genomic analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Every base of the complete HBoV3-E1 genome was sequenced at least 3 times (Genbank accession no. JN086998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The PCR product chromatograms were consistent with infection by a single HBoV lineage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>However, mixed HBoV infection cannot be ruled out as population sequencing only allows detection of a minority of variants comprising &gt;10% of the total sequences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The complete HBoV3-E1 circular genome contains 5319 nt and codes for 3 large ORFs flanked by a 513 nucleotide long NCR representing both termini (Fig. 2A and 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>ORF1 encodes nonstructural (NS) protein; ORF2 encodes overlapping VP1/VP2 capsid proteins; and ORF3 encodes NP1 [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Helicase and ATPase, conserved motifs associated with rolling circle replication, are present within ORF1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Unlike animal bocaviruses, the HBoV3-E1 NS gene also exhibited conserved RNA splicing signals essential to generate shorter and longer NS protein in all HBoV species [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>To confirm the recombinant origin of HBoV3-E1, we performed a sliding window analysis of sequence homology between the coding region of HBoV3-E1 and members of the other 3 HBoV species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>We found that whereas the HBoV3-E1 NS1 and NP1 genes were more closely related to HBoV1 than to HBoV2 and HBoV4, the HBoV3-E1 VP genes were more similar to the HBoV2 and HBoV4 VP1/VP2 gene (data not shown) [4], [9], [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0021362-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021362.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Secondary structure prediction and sequences for the non-coding terminal region of HBoV3-E1 (top) and MVC (bottom). </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The 3 major bocavirus genes are shown in shaded boxes as NS, NP and VP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The NS gene protein initiation codon and VP genes stop codon are underlined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The 2 stable and long palindromic sequences are shown as hairpin 1 and 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Cluster of DNA stems and loops immediately upstream of the N-terminus of the NS gene are shown as 5′ terminal structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Based on the Genbank data, the start and end of the HBoV and MVC linear genomes are shown with arrows. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0021362.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>As the HBoV3-E1 genome is covalently linked (head-to-tail) and the complete ITR sequences of linear HBoV genomes are not known, we were not able to definitively locate the start or end of the genome (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>However, sequence alignment of the complete HBoV-E1 NCR with HBoV linear genomic termini unmasked over 50 previously unsequenced nt in the HBoV termini (Fig. 2C) that is predicted to encode a small 49 aa long protein with very weak domain homology to bacteriophage head-to-tail connecting protein [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>This family of proteins is found in bacteria and viruses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The head-to-tail connector, a dodecamer of gp10, is embedded within a unique five-fold vertex of the head. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The connector serves as the site of assembly of the transient DNA packaging motor that translocates the dsDNA genome to a precursor head shell, or prohead [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Additional studies in other HBoV species will be necessary to test the role of this novel protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Sequence and structure of HBoV3-E1 termini </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Confidence in the predicted secondary structure of DNA or RNA requires comparative modeling of multiple, diverse yet significantly related sequences [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>As such sequences are unavailable for comparison in HBoV species, we relied on experimentally-confirmed MVC ITR structures [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The secondary structure of the 513 nt long HBoV3-E1 NCR sequence between the VP termination and the NS initiation codon contained 3 distinct DNA structures, namely, a hairpin-1, hairpin-2 and a 5′ cluster. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Although the MVC and HBoV termini showed no sequence similarity, they shared 3 structurally similar regions in the NCR (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>We were unable to locate the terminal nt of the HBoV3-E1 genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The alignment generated with sequences reported for linear genomes suggests that the terminal bases may be within the hairpin-2 region (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>We observed that the hairpin-1 region located in the HBoV3-E1 3′ (RHS) terminus showed remarkable structural similarity to rabbit ear-like structures formed by the termini of several parvoviruses [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>To confirm the presence of the DNA stem loop, we used the 3′ terminal partial ITR sequence available for all HBoV species for folding and comparative analysis (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, despite their sequence diversity, the sequences of all 3 HBoV species folded into almost identical secondary structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Moreover, HBoV species 1 and 2 are highly genetically diverse and show &lt;80% protein identity, and even lower nt identity, in their protein coding regions (NS, NP and VP gene) [4], [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Comparative sequence analysis of the complete 513 nt long HBoV3-E1 NCR showed high sequence identity (&gt;90%) with the partial terminal sequences available for HBoV1, HBoV2 and HBoV3, but not with either of the complete terminal sequences of animal bocaviruses (MVC and BPV). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The conserved role of ITR structures in replication of HBoV may require maintenance of a high degree of sequence identity among these genetically diverse viruses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Sequence alignment also confirmed that HBoV termini are non-identical and form imperfect palindromes, characteristics that are more similar to parvoviruses than to animal bocaviruses [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0021362-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021362.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Secondary structure prediction of the sequences immediately downstream of the structural gene of different HBoV species (upper-HBoV1, middle-HBoV2 and lower-HBoV3-E1). </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The stems and arms are numbered for comparison, and the termination codon of the VP gene is marked by a solid line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The rabbit-ear structure (structure 3 and 4) present in all 3 HBoV species is comparable to similar conserved structures of left-hand side termini reported for animal bocaviruses (MVC and BPV) [44]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0021362.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>GBoV1 is genetically most related to HBoV1 and was first identified in feces of captive animals living in isolation for several years [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Later, GBoV1 was also found in fecal samples of wild primates from Cameroon, confirming GBoV1 as an authentic non-human primate bocavirus [1], [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>These findings inspired us to explore the nature of primate bocavirus infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Because longitudinal fecal samples from these animals were not available for study, we used human intestinal biopsy samples to characterize the different genomic forms of HBoV. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Our results show that, like adeno-associated viruses [45], HBoV can become persistently established in host cells by forming the extra-chromosomal closed circular (episomal) form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>However, unlike AAV, we did not find evidence of HBoV DNA integration into the host genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The approach we used to determine HBoV integration into human genome is more sensitive than other adapter ligation-based approaches [35], [46], as the primers during 2 rounds of PCR selectively amplify only circular DNA containing viral termini. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Previously, we used a similar approach to successfully characterize an endogenous rat parvovirus that exists as a single viral copy per cellular genome [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>However, we cannot rule out the possibility that HBoV integrates in a rare minority of infected cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Moreover, because we tested only a few human intestinal tissue samples, a larger sample set should be studied to confirm or refute the existence of the HBoV host chromosome integrated form. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Despite the discovery of different HBoV species, the genomic sequences of their termini remain elusive, limiting the development of a successful cell culture replication system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The information yielded by sequencing the HBoV terminal region and characterizing the HBoV3 episome will be helpful in studying its replication and pathogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The closed circular form of HBoV may be rapidly and clonally amplified using highly efficient strand displacement DNA polymerases to generate large quantities of infective episomes [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately we didn't have sufficient sample or DNA left to perform these experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>During replication, most parvoviruses generate replicative intermediates that contain multiple, covalently-linked linear genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Notably, these concatamers show head-to-head or tail-to-tail (adjoining of same termini) linear genomic orientations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>We sequenced the inverse PCR product multiple times and repeated the assay to confirm the identification of the head-to-tail circularized HBoV genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Genomic characterization of HBoV3-E1 resulted in identification of more than 50 previously unsequenced nt in primate bocaviruses [8], [9], [11], [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>However, it is possible that the linear form of the HBoV genome contains more sequences that maintain terminal stability during replication, that are otherwise not important during replication of a circular template. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The AAV episomal junction region lacks some sequences present in linear viral genomes [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>During the review of our manuscript, a new study [48] reported identification of head-to-tail oriented circular DNA form for another HBoV species (HBoV1) during its infection in cell culture and clinical samples further confirming the existence of HBoV episome in infected cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Parvoviruses are ubiquitous and are proposed to contribute to a broad spectrum of diseases in animals, including enteritis, panleukopenia, hepatitis, erythrocyte aplasia, immune complex-mediated vasculitis and cerebellar ataxia [3], [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Most studies done to determine the association of HBoV with disease have shown that a high percentage of samples from healthy subjects are also positive for HBoV DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>However, these studies typically report presence or absence rather than quantitative data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Given our evidence that HBoV sequences may persist, future work of HBoV epidemiology should place more emphasis on the quantity, rather than mere presence, of viral genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Moreover, previous reports of high prevalence of HBoV in association with infection with other viruses (mixed infections) may reflect reactivation of latent bocavirus episomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Although we could not determine what population or percentage of intestinal cells was infected with HBoV in our samples, our results show that, during natural HBoV infection, some linear viral genomes can circularize and exist as extra-chromosomal episomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Our observation that HBoV genome exist as head-to-tail monomer in infected tissue either reflects the likely evolution of alternative replication mechanism in primate bocaviruses or a mechanism of viral persistence in their host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>We also report the complete HBoV episomal genome and the secondary structures of its termini. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>This novel sequence information will increase our understanding of how these recently discovered parvoviruses replicate and cause infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Funding: This work was supported by National Institutes of Health grant awards AI090196, AI079231, AI57158, AI070411, and EY017404. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0021362-Kapoor1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>1 KapoorAMehtaNEsperFPoljsak-PrijateljMQuanPL 2010 Identification and characterization of a new bocavirus species in gorillas. PLoS One 5 e11948 20668709 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Claude1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>2 ClaudeMFauquetMAMManiloffJDesselbergerUBallLA 2004 Virus Taxonomy: The Eighth Report of the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses Academic Press  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Brown1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>3 BrownKE 2010 The expanding range of parvoviruses which infect humans. Rev Med Virol 20 231 244 20586082 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Kapoor2"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>4 KapoorASimmondsPSlikasELiLBodhidattaL 2010 Human bocaviruses are highly diverse, dispersed, recombination prone, and prevalent in enteric infections. J Infect Dis 201 1633 1643 20415538 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Manteufel1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>5 ManteufelJTruyenU 2008 Animal bocaviruses: a brief review. Intervirology 51 328 334 19023216 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Qiu1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>6 QiuJChengFJohnsonFBPintelD 2007 The transcription profile of the bocavirus bovine parvovirus is unlike those of previously characterized parvoviruses. J Virol 81 12080 12085 17715221 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Cheng1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>7 ChengWXLiJSHuangCPYaoDPLiuN 2010 Identification and nearly full-length genome characterization of novel porcine bocaviruses. PLoS One 5 e13583 21049037 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Allander1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>8 AllanderTTammiMTErikssonMBjerknerATiveljung-LindellA 2005 Cloning of a human parvovirus by molecular screening of respiratory tract samples. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 102 12891 12896 16118271 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Arthur1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>9 ArthurJLHigginsGDDavidsonGPGivneyRCRatcliffRM 2009 A novel bocavirus associated with acute gastroenteritis in Australian children. PLoS Pathog 5 e1000391 19381259 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Chieochansin1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>10 ChieochansinTChutinimitkulSPayungpornSHiranrasTSamransamruajkitR 2007 Complete coding sequences and phylogenetic analysis of Human Bocavirus (HBoV). Virus Res 129 54 57 17532505 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Kapoor3"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>11 KapoorASlikasESimmondsPChieochansinTNaeemA 2009 A newly identified bocavirus species in human stool. J Infect Dis 199 196 200 19072716 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Berns1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>12 BernsKI 1990 Parvovirus replication. Microbiol Rev 54 316 329 2215424 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Allander2"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>13 AllanderT 2008 Human bocavirus. J Clin Virol 41 29 33 18055252 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Allander3"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>14 AllanderTJarttiTGuptaSNiestersHGLehtinenP 2007 Human bocavirus and acute wheezing in children. Clin Infect Dis 44 904 910 17342639 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Bastien1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>15 BastienNChuiNRobinsonJLLeeBEDustK 2007 Detection of human bocavirus in Canadian children in a 1-year study. J Clin Microbiol 45 610 613 17122013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-CatalanoPons1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>16 Catalano-PonsCBueMLaudeHCattanFMoulinF 2007 Human bocavirus infection in hospitalized children during winter. Pediatr Infect Dis J 26 959 960 17901806 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Chung1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>17 ChungJYHanTHKimCKKimSW 2006 Bocavirus infection in hospitalized children, South Korea. Emerg Infect Dis 12 1254 1256 16965708 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Fry1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>18 FryAMLuXChittaganpitchMPeretTFischerJ 2007 Human bocavirus: a novel parvovirus epidemiologically associated with pneumonia requiring hospitalization in Thailand. J Infect Dis 195 1038 1045 17330795 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Gagliardi1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>19 GagliardiTBIwamotoMAPaulaFEProenca-ModenaJLSaranzoAM 2009 Human bocavirus respiratory infections in children. Epidemiol Infect 1 5  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Lau1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>20 LauSKYipCCQueTLLeeRAAu-YeungRK 2007 Clinical and molecular epidemiology of human bocavirus in respiratory and fecal samples from children in Hong Kong. J Infect Dis 196 986 993 17763318 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Albuquerque1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>21 AlbuquerqueMCRochaLNBenatiFJSoaresCCMaranhaoAG 2007 Human bocavirus infection in children with gastroenteritis, Brazil. Emerg Infect Dis 13 1756 1758 18217564 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Anderson1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>22 AndersonLJ 2007 Human bocavirus: a new viral pathogen. Clin Infect Dis 44 911 912 17342640 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Campe1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>23 CampeHHartbergerCSingA 2008 Role of Human Bocavirus infections in outbreaks of gastroenteritis. J Clin Virol 43 340 342 18835213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Lindner1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>24 LindnerJModrowS 2008 Human bocavirus–a novel parvovirus to infect humans. Intervirology 51 116 122 18536522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Ziegler1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>25 ZieglerSTillmannRLMullerASimonASchildgenV 2008 No gastroenteric Bocavirus in high risk patients stool samples. J Clin Virol 43 349 350 18755626 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Kapoor4"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>26 KapoorASimmondsPSlikasELiLBodhidattaL Human bocaviruses are highly diverse, dispersed, recombination prone, and prevalent in enteric infections. J Infect Dis 201 1633 1643  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Mackay1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>27 MackayIM 2007 Human bocavirus: multisystem detection raises questions about infection. J Infect Dis 196 968 970 17763314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Simmonds1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>28 SimmondsP 2008 Steps towards serological diagnosis of human bocavirus infections. Clin Infect Dis 46 547 549 18199041 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Sharp1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>29 SharpCPLeBretonMKantolaKNanaADiffo JleD 2010 Widespread infection with homologues of human parvoviruses B19, PARV4, and human bocavirus of chimpanzees and gorillas in the wild. J Virol 84 10289 10296 20668071 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Cheng2"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>30 ChengWXJinYDuanZJXuZQQiHM 2008 Human bocavirus in children hospitalized for acute gastroenteritis: a case-control study. Clin Infect Dis 47 161 167 18532891 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Chieochansin2"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>31 ChieochansinTSamransamruajkitRChutinimitkulSPayungpornSHiranrasT 2008 Human bocavirus (HBoV) in Thailand: clinical manifestations in a hospitalized pediatric patient and molecular virus characterization. J Infect 56 137 142 18164764 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Dina1"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>32 DinaJVabretAGouarinSPetitjeanJLecoqJ 2009 Detection of human bocavirus in hospitalised children. J Paediatr Child Health  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Xu1"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>33 XuZQChengWXLiBWLiJLanB 2011 Development of a real-time PCR assay for detecting and quantifying human bocavirus 2. J Clin Microbiol  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Yu1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>34 YuJMLiDDXuZQChengWXZhangQ 2008 Human bocavirus infection in children hospitalized with acute gastroenteritis in China. J Clin Virol 42 280 285 18499516 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Schnepp1"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>35 SchneppBCJensenRLChenCLJohnsonPRClarkKR 2005 Characterization of adeno-associated virus genomes isolated from human tissues. J Virol 79 14793 14803 16282479 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Hornig1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>36 HornigMBrieseTBuieTBaumanMLLauwersG 2008 Lack of association between measles virus vaccine and autism with enteropathy: a case-control study. PLoS One 3 e3140 18769550 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Kapoor5"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>37 KapoorASimmondsPLipkinWI 2010 Discovery and characterization of mammalian endogenous parvoviruses. J Virol 84 12628 12635 20943964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Tamura1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>38 TamuraKPDPetersonNStecherGNeiMKumarS 2011 MEGA5: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis using Maximum Likelihood, Evolutionary Distance, and Maximum Parsimony Methods. Molecular Biology and Evolution (submitted)  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Zuker1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>39 ZukerM 2003 Mfold web server for nucleic acid folding and hybridization prediction. Nucleic Acids Res 31 3406 3415 12824337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Chen1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>40 ChenAYChengFLouSLuoYLiuZ 2010 Characterization of the gene expression profile of human bocavirus. Virology 403 145 154 20457462 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Chieochansin3"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>41 ChieochansinTThongmeeCVimolketLTheamboonlersAPoovorawanY 2008 Human bocavirus infection in children with acute gastroenteritis and healthy controls. Jpn J Infect Dis 61 479 481 19050360 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-MarchlerBauer1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>42 Marchler-BauerALuSAndersonJBChitsazFDerbyshireMK 2011 CDD: a Conserved Domain Database for the functional annotation of proteins. Nucleic Acids Res 39 D225 229 21109532 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Mears1"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>43 MearsJACannoneJJStaggSMGutellRRAgrawalRK 2002 Modeling a minimal ribosome based on comparative sequence analysis. J Mol Biol 321 215 234 12144780 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Sun1"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>44 SunYChenAYChengFGuanWJohnsonFB 2009 Molecular characterization of infectious clones of the minute virus of canines reveals unique features of bocaviruses. J Virol 83 3956 3967 19211770 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Chen2"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>45 ChenCLJensenRLSchneppBCConnellMJShellR 2005 Molecular characterization of adeno-associated viruses infecting children. J Virol 79 14781 14792 16282478 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Luft1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>46 LuftFKlaesRNeesMDurstMHeilmannV 2001 Detection of integrated papillomavirus sequences by ligation-mediated PCR (DIPS-PCR) and molecular characterization in cervical cancer cells. Int J Cancer 92 9 17 11279600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Schnepp2"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>47 SchneppBCJensenRLClarkKRJohnsonPR 2009 Infectious molecular clones of adeno-associated virus isolated directly from human tissues. J Virol 83 1456 1464 19019948 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0021362-Lusebrink1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>48 LusebrinkJSchildgenVTillmannRLWittlebenFBohmerA 2011 Detection of Head-to-Tail DNA Sequences of Human Bocavirus in Clinical Samples. PLoS One 6 e19457 21573237 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
