<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPGSJ//DTD full length article DTD version 7.0 XML//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName ajarticle_v7_x.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 7.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName naturesa2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Br. J. Cancer</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3494444</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">bjc2012403</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/bjc.2012.403</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22976800</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Mismatch repair deficiency: a temozolomide resistance factor in medulloblastoma cell lines that is uncommon in primary medulloblastoma tumours </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running">Mismatch repair deficiency in medulloblastoma</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>von Bueren</surname><given-names>A O</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bacolod</surname><given-names>M D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hagel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Heinimann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fedier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kordes</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pietsch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grotzer</surname><given-names>M A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>H S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kool</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11">11</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rutkowski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Pediatric Hematology and Oncology, University Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf</institution>, Martinistr. 52, Hamburg D-20246, <country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Neuro-Oncology Program, University Children's Hospital Zurich</institution>, Zurich, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Institute of Molecular Life Sciences, University of Zurich</institution>, Zurich, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution>Preston Robert Tisch Brain Tumor Center, Duke University Medical Center</institution>, Durham, NC, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution>Institute of Neuropathology, University Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf</institution>, Hamburg, <country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution>Research Group Human Genetics, Department of Biomedicine and Division of Medical Genetics UKBB, University of Basel</institution>, Basel, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><institution>Department of Gynecology, University Hospital Zurich</institution>, Zurich, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="aff8"><label>8</label><institution>Department of Neuropathology, University of Bonn</institution>, Bonn, <country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff9"><label>9</label><institution>Department of Oncogenomics, Academic Medical Center</institution>, Amsterdam, <country>The Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="aff10"><label>10</label><institution>Institute of Molecular Cancer Research, University of Zurich</institution>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="aff11"><label>11</label><institution>Division of Pediatric Neurooncology, German Cancer Research Center</institution>, Heidelberg, <country>Germany</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label>E-mail: <email>a.von-bueren@uke.de</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>09</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>09</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>107</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1399</fpage><lpage>1408</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>06</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>13</day><month>08</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>08</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 Cancer Research UK</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cancer Research UK</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"><license-p>From twelve months after its original publication, this work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Tumours are responsive to temozolomide (TMZ) if they are deficient in O6-methylguanine-DNA methyltransferase (MGMT), and mismatch repair (MMR) proficient. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Methods: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The effect of TMZ on medulloblastoma (MB) cell killing was analysed with clonogenic survival assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Expression of DNA repair genes and enzymes was investigated using microarrays, western blot, and immunohistochemistry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>DNA sequencing and promoter methylation analysis were employed to investigate the cause of loss of the expression of MMR gene MLH1. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Results: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Temozolomide exhibited potent cytotoxic activity in D425Med (MGMT deficient, MLH1 proficient; IC50=1.7 μℳ), moderate activity against D341Med (MGMT proficient, MLH1 deficient), and DAOY MB cells (MGMT proficient, MLH1 proficient). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>MGMT inhibitor O6-benzylguanine sensitised DAOY, but not D341Med cells to TMZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Of 12 MB cell lines, D341Med, D283Med, and 1580WÜ cells exhibited MMR deficiency due to MLH1 promoter hypermethylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>DNA sequencing of these cells provided no evidence for somatic genetic alterations in MLH1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Expression analyses of MMR and MGMT in MB revealed that all patient specimens (n=74; expression array, n=61; immunostaining, n=13) are most likely MMR proficient, whereas some tumours had low MGMT expression levels (according to expression array) or were totally MGMT deficient (3 out of 13 according to immunohistochemistry). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Conclusion: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>A subset of MB may respond to TMZ as some patient specimens are MGMT deficient, and tumours appear to be MMR proficient. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>medulloblastoma</kwd><kwd>temozolomide</kwd><kwd>drug resistance</kwd><kwd>mismatch repair</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Medulloblastoma (MB) is the most common malignant paediatric brain tumour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Standard treatment includes surgery, chemotherapy, and irradiation (for older children and adolescents). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The anti-cancer drug that has shown promise in the treatment of recurrent paediatric brain tumours is the methylating agent temozolomide (TMZ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Already a part of standard treatment of glioblastomas (Stupp et al, 2005), this orally administered drug causes only mild and tolerable side-effects (Broniscer et al, 2007; Nicholson et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In an ongoing clinical trial for recurrent paediatric brain tumours (Phase II), the efficacy of TMZ (alone) is being tested against that of intravenous carboplatin/etoposide (HIT-REZ 2005; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT00749723">http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT00749723</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Another clinical trial compares the effectiveness of the well-tested combination of TMZ and irinotecan hydrochloride with or without bevacizumab (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01217437">http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01217437</ext-link>) in recurrent MB. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>TMZ spontaneously hydrolyses to MTIC (3-methyl-(triazen-1-yl)imidazole-4 carboxamide), which then degrades into the DNA-reactive methyldiazonium cation that forms methyl adducts at O-6 (G), N-7 (G), N-1 (A), and N-3 (A) positions (Marchesi et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The O6-methylguanine (O6-meG)/cytosine (O6-meG:C) pair can result into the O6-meG:T mismatch in the progeny DNA after a first round of replication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The mismatch repair (MMR) system, a protein complex including MSH2, MSH6, MLH1, and PMS2 proteins attempts to repair the O6-meG:T mismatch by removing a patch of the newly synthesised strand containing thymine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>However, if O6-meG remains in the template strand, thymine could still be misincorporated opposite O6-meG and a futile cycle of repair by the MMR system takes place during this S phase of the cell cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>This process triggers collapsed replication fork and subsequent DNA double-strand break that then leads to G2/M arrest (Drablos et al, 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Another DNA repair protein that modulates TMZ activity is MGMT (O6-methylguanine-DNA methyltransferase), which can directly excise the methyl lesion at the O6 position of guanine (Pegg, 1990; Gerson, 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In theory, a defective MMR and/or presence of expression of MGMT can lead to the tumour's tolerance to TMZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Previous studies demonstrated that increased expression (Dunn et al, 2009; Karayan-Tapon et al, 2010) or reduced promoter methylation (Dunn et al, 2009; Karayan-Tapon et al, 2010) (which also increases expression level) of MGMT correlated with lower overall survival of adult glioblastoma (GBM) patients whose treatment regimen included TMZ. Cahill et al (2007) reported that among radiotherapy/TMZ-treated GBM patients, a subset of recurrent tumours had lost the expression of the MMR protein MSH6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>As clinical studies involving the use of TMZ in paediatric MB have started only fairly recently, the association between MGMT/MMR status and clinical response and outcome among TMZ-treated MB patients are yet to be reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In this study, we aimed to investigate the impact of MGMT/MMR status on the response of MB cell lines to TMZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>We then proceeded to analyse the expression of MMR and MGMT genes and proteins by expression array (61 MB and 12 MB cell lines) and immunostaining (13 MB) to examine the potential clinical relevance of the MMR system and MGMT in MB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The underlying cause for MMR deficiency in MB cells was further explored by sequencing and methylation analysis of the MLH1 gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Material and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Cell lines and culture conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>We used the MB cell lines DAOY (from a 4-year-old male) (Jacobsen et al, 1985), D341Med (from a 3.5-year-old male) (Friedman et al, 1988), D425Med (from a 5-year-old male) (Bigner et al, 1990), D556Med (from a 7-year-old female) (Aldosari et al, 2002), D283Med (from ascitic fluid of a 6-year-old child with metastatic MB) (Friedman et al, 1985), MHH-MED-1 (from the cerebrospinal fluid of a 10-year-old male) (Pietsch et al, 1994), MHH-MED-3 (from a 3-year-old female) (Pietsch et al, 1994), MHH-MED-4 (from a 4-year-old male) (Pietsch et al, 1994), and UW228-2 (from a 9-year-old female) (Keles et al, 1995). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Cell lines were cultured as previously described (Hartmann et al, 2005; Faoro et al, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Three cell lines (1580WÜ, 5-year-old female; MEB-MED-8S, 1-year-old male; and MEB-MED-8A, 1-year-old male) were established by one of the authors (TP) and were used as described previously (Hartmann et al, 2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Tumour samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Two MB series were analysed: (a) 61 primary MB samples whose expression array data (Affymetrix HG U133 Plus 2.0 arrays, Santa Barbara, CA, USA) (Kool et al, 2008, 2012) were reanalysed for the present study, and (b) 13 archival MB tissue samples from patients diagnosed at the University Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf, Germany. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>All these archival tissue samples were reviewed by an experienced neuropathologist (CH) and the diagnosis of MB was confirmed in all. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Written informed consent was obtained from all patients and/or from the parents of all patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>All cases were made anonymous before the investigation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Drugs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Temozolomide (Schering-Plough; Kenilworth, NJ, USA) and O6-benzylguanine (O6-BG) (Sigma Aldrich, Basel, Switzerland) were used as described elsewhere (Faoro et al, 2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Western blot analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>MB cells were incubated with lysis buffer (50 mℳ Tris HCl, pH 7.8, 0.15 ℳ NaCl, 1% NP-40, Roche (Basel, Switzerland) complete mini EDTA-free protease-inhibitor cocktail) on ice for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Lysis was checked under the microscope and the supernatant was isolated after centrifugation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Eighty microgram of protein extracts were mixed with an equal volume of 2 × SDS loading buffer (20% glycerol, 4% SDS, 0.2 ℳ DTT, 0.01% bromophenol blue, 0.125 ℳ Tris HCl, pH 6.8), electrophoresed in 12% Tris-Glycine SDS polyacrylamide gel, and transferred onto Biotrace PVDF membranes (Pall Co., Ann Arbor, MI, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The subsequent steps for western blotting were performed using the WesternBreeze Chemiluminescent Western Blot Immunodetection kit (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA), with the alkaline phosphatase-conjugated anti-mouse secondary antibody and CDP-Star Chemiluminescent substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Mouse monoclonal antibodies used were specific for MLH1 (Oncogene, Cambridge, MA, USA), MSH2 (Oncogene), MSH6 (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA), PMS2 (Oncogene), and βIII tubulin (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The expression of MGMT and β-actin were analysed by western blot analysis as described previously (Faoro et al, 2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Clonogenic survival assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>To assess clonogenic survival, the number of seeded cells was adjusted to obtain around 100 colonies per cell culture dish for a given treatment (von Bueren et al, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Where required, the specific MGMT inhibitor O6-BG at a concentration of 25 μℳ was added to the cell cultures 2 h before the addition of various concentrations of TMZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The cultures were then maintained at 37°C in a humidified atmosphere containing 5% CO2, and allowed to grow for 9 (DAOY), 14 (D341Med), or 12 (D425Med) days, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>This was followed by the fixation of the cells in methanol/acetic acid (75% : 25%) and the staining with Giemsa dye. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Colonies with more than 50 cells were counted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Clonogenic assays were repeated three times as independent experiments using triplicate cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The relative colony formation (percentage of clonogenic survival) was plotted against the drug concentrations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>MGMT and MLH1 sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA was extracted from DAOY, D341Med, D283Med, and 1580WÜ cells using standard procedures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The DNA fragments encompassing four exons and adjacent intronic sequences of MGMT (OMIM 156569) gene were PCR amplified and directly sequenced using BigDye Terminator v1.1 Cycle Sequencing Kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA) and the ABI PRISM 3100 genetic analyser. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>For DAOY, D341Med, D283Med, and 1580WÜ, the genomic DNA regions covering 19 exons of MLH1 (OMIM 120436; GenBank accession number NM_0000249) were also PCR amplified and sequenced as described recently (Buerki et al, 2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>MLH1 promoter hypermethylation analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The promoter methylation status of MLH1 in DAOY, D341Med, D283Med, and 1580WÜ cells was evaluated using the SALSA ME011-B1 MS-MLPA (methylation-specific, multiplex-ligation-dependent probe amplification) MMR Probemix Kit (MRC Holland, Amsterdam, The Netherlands) (Buerki et al, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The kit included five MLH1-specific probes: MLH1 1 (237 bp; −659 bp distance to ATG start); MLH1 2 (265 bp; −383 bp distance to ATG start); MLH1 3 (189 bp; −246 bp distance to ATG start); MLH1 4 (166 bp; −13  bp distance to ATG start); and MLH1 5 (292 bp; +208 bp distance to ATG start) (Nygren et al, 2005; Gylling et al, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>All reactions were carried out according to the manufacturer's protocol and fragment analysis was performed on an ABI PRISM 310 Genetic analyser (Buerki et al, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Analyses were performed using three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Gene expression by microarray analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The gene expression data of MB tumours (n=61), which are available from NCBI's Gene Expression Omnibus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>; accession number GSE10327) and published by Kool et al (2012), were reanalysed, whereas those of the 12 MB cell lines (D341Med, D425Med, D283Med, DAOY, MHH-MED-1, D556Med, 1580WÜ, MHH-MED-3, MEB-MED-8S, MHH-MED-4, MEB-MED-8A, and UW228-2) were newly generated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>In both series, Affymetrix HG U133 Plus 2.0 arrays (Affymetrix) were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Data analysis was performed using the R2 microarray analysis and visualisation platform (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://r2.amc.nl">http://r2.amc.nl</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemistry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Thirteen additional MB specimens were examined immunohistochemically for MMR and MGMT protein expression using standard immunohistochemical techniques (Truninger et al, 2005; Menigatti et al, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>In brief, tumours were fixed in buffered formalin and embedded in paraffin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Four micrometre thick sections were mounted on glass slides coated with organosilane (DakoCytomation, Hamburg, Germany), deparaffinised, and rehydrated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Antigen retrieval was accomplished by heating the sections in a pressure cooker at 120°C for 2 min in 10 mℳ citrate-buffered solution (pH 6.0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>DAKO (Hamburg, Germany) peroxidase blocking reagent and goat serum were sequentially used to suppress non-specific staining due to endogenous peroxidase activity and unspecific binding of antibodies, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Incubations with primary monoclonal antibodies were performed as follows: anti-MSH2: 24 h at 4°C with Ab NA27 (Calbiochem, Darmstadt, Germany), 1 : 50; anti-MSH6: 24 h at 4°C with Ab 610919 (BD Biosciences), 1 : 65; anti-MLH1: 24 h at 4°C with Ab 551091 (BD Biosciences), 1 : 200; anti-PMS2: 24 h at 4°C with Ab 556415 (BD Biosciences), 1 : 85; and anti-MGMT: 24 h at 4°C with Ab MS-470-P1 (NeoMarker, Kalamazoo, MI, USA), 1 : 170. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>After washing, anti-mouse secondary antibodies conjugated to peroxidase labelled polymer (DAKO EnVision+ kit) were applied for 30 min at RT, and the peroxidase activity was developed by incubation with 3,3′diaminobenzidine chromogen solution (DAKO). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The sections were then counterstained with hematoxylin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Immunoreactivity of the tissue was verified by labelling with antibodies against the Ki-67 antigen (anti-Ki-67: 24 h at 4°C with Ab M 7240, DAKO, 1 : 125). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Slides were evaluated qualitatively for nuclear staining of tumour cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Whenever possible, data points are reported as mean±standard deviation (s.d.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>(GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA, USA) software was used to calculate IC50 values and their 95% confidence intervals, and to statistically compare the fitted midpoints (log IC50) of the two curves (von Bueren et al, 2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Temozolomide sensitivity depends on both the MMR status and on its MGMT expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>We investigated the effect of TMZ on the clonogenic survival with and without O6-BG pretreatment in DAOY, D425Med, and D341Med cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Results from clonogenic survival assay (CFA) indicated that D425Med cells were highly sensitive to TMZ (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The TMZ IC50 values and their 95% confidence intervals for D425Med (IC50: 1.705 μℳ), DAOY (IC50: 383.8 μℳ), and D341Med cells (IC50: 178.2 μℳ) are shown in Figure 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>We have previously shown that the MGMT gene in D425Med cells is epigenetically silenced (Faoro et al, 2011), explaining the cell line's sensitivity to TMZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, DAOY and D341Med cells expressed MGMT (Faoro et al, 2011), consistent with their tolerance to TMZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Upon addition of the MGMT inhibitor O6-BG, the depletion of MGMT protein expression was evident for both DAOY and D341Med cells (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>However, as indicated in Figure 1, O6-BG addition was able to potentiate the cytotoxic activity of TMZ in DAOY (TMZ IC50 value of 151.9 μℳ, significantly lower than the basal IC50 of 383.8 μℳ; P&lt;0.001), the most TMZ-resistant MB cell line analysed in our study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>In contrast, no significant increased cytotoxic activity of TMZ was evident in D425Med and D341Med cells upon O6-BG addition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>This observation was expected for the MGMT-deficient D425Med cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>For the MGMT-proficient D341Med cells, these results were quite surprising. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>We first considered the possibility that the D341Med cells used in these experiments carried a mutated yet immuno-detectable MGMT protein, that is, a mutant protein resistant to inhibition by O6-BG, such as those variants previously reported in BCNU/O6-BG-resistant MB sublines (Bacolod et al, 2002, 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Sequencing did not reveal any evidence for somatic genetic alterations in MGMT, when assessing D341Med, DAOY and D425Med cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>However, when we analysed the MMR status by western blot (Figure 2), losses of MLH1 and PMS2 expression were found in D341Med cells, while all the MMR proteins investigated were normally expressed in DAOY. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>MB tumours are MMR proficient, some MB cells are MMR deficient, and the majority of MB tumours and MB cells are MGMT proficient </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The loss of MMR function in one of three MB cell lines, prompted us to investigate the frequency of MMR deficiency in MB tumours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>We analysed the expression levels of the four MMR genes among 61 primary MB tumours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The clinical, histological, and molecular subgroup (WNT, SHH, group 3 (GRP3) and group 4) characteristics of the 61 patients are described elsewhere (Kool et al, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Included as reference were the expression data of nine normal cerebellum (CB; without information about age) samples which were assessed also by Affymetrix HG U133 Plus 2.0 array by Roth et al (2006), and data were available from NCBI's Gene Expression Omnibus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>; accession number GSE3526). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 3 the expression levels of MLH1, MSH2, and MSH6 across 61 tumour samples (and all four molecular subtypes) were higher compared with the MMR gene expression assessed in the CB samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The expression of PMS2 in primary MB tissues was within the range of the reference CB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these data suggest that MMR defects associated with loss of expression of MMR genes are absent or rare in MB tumours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>We then examined the expression level of MMR genes among 12 established MB cell lines; including the three cell lines used in the CFAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Expression array analysis (Figure 4) indicated that of the 12 cell lines, 3 had undetectable expression of the MMR gene MLH1: D341Med, D283Med, and 1580WÜ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>This confirmed what we found in D341Med cells by western blot: loss of the MLH1 protein expression (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>In D341Med cells, the non-detection of the PMS2 protein (even though the mRNA is expressed) can be explained by its degradation in the absence of the heterodimeric partner MLH1 (Figure 4) (Yao et al, 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Expression array analysis also showed that MGMT expression is detectable in all of the 61 MB tumours with transcription levels equal to or higher compared to those of CB samples (Figure 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Microarray analysis of the 12 MB cells revealed that only 2 cell lines (D425Med and Meb-Med-8a) did not express MGMT mRNA (Figure 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, tissue blocks of the 61 MB tumours used in the microarray study were not available for the analysis of the MMR protein expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we tested an additional 13 MB tumours (Table 1) by immunohistochemistry and found that all of them were positive for the presence of MSH2, MSH6, MLH1, and PMS2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>A representative example is shown in Figure 6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Apparently, three of the 13 tumours (23%) showed complete loss of MGMT protein expression (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Mechanism of MLH1 silencing in D341Med, D283Med, and 1580WÜ cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>We then asked whether the lack of expression of MLH1 in D341Med, D283Med, and 1580WÜ cell lines can be explained by hypermethylation of the gene's promoter region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Using SALSA ME011-B1 MMR assay, we were able to demonstrate that all three cell lines exhibited extensive CpG island methylation in at least four of five MLH1 promoter regions that were investigated (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>This methylation pattern appeared to be sufficient for silencing of the MLH1 expression (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>In contrast, DAOY (which is positive for MLH1 expression) was methylated in only one CpG site (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>DNA sequencing also indicated that none of the aforementioned cell lines (including DAOY) were mutated in MLH1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The two important molecular predictors of TMZ efficacy are MGMT expression and MMR status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Using MB cell line models, we were able to demonstrate that TMZ is most effective when the MB cells have a functioning MMR, in addition to low level of MGMT expression (whose correlation to TMZ sensitivity in MB has been previously demonstrated through in vitro viability assays (Daniel et al, 2010; Faoro et al, 2011) and xenograft studies (Daniel et al, 2010)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>For cells with defective MMR, MGMT depletion (e.g., by O6-BG) will not potentiate TMZ activity, as we have shown in this study, and has been reported previously using colon cancer cell lines (Liu et al, 1996). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Thus far, there is limited information available regarding the prevalence and clinical relevance of MMR deficiency among MB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>A recent report by Viana-Pereira et al (2009) indicated that 4 out of 36 (11%) MB tumours had microsatellite instability (the resulting phenotype of defective MMR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>However, an earlier report found that MLH1, MSH2, and PMS2 (MSH6 was not probed) were expressed in all of 22 MB analysed by western blotting (Lee et al, 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we demonstrated that all of the 74 MB tumours (61 analysed by expression profiling and by immunostaining) seem to be MMR proficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>In addition, MMR deficiency has been described in only a small fraction of malignant glioma in the paediatric age group (Vladimirova et al, 2008; Pollack et al, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, very rare cases of MMR deficiency originating from biallelic germline mutations of a MMR gene have been reported (Poley et al, 2007; Scott et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Taken collectively, these studies point to the low prevalence of MMR deficiency in MB tumours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the transcript levels of MMR genes MLH1, MSH2, and MSH6 were clearly higher in MB tumours when compared with CB samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The transcript levels of PMS2 in MB tumours (expression levels were slightly higher when compared with CB tissues) need to be interpreted with caution as the probe seems to detect PMS2 and PMS2CL (the probe sets 209805_at and 221206_at can detect both PMS2 and PMS2CL mRNAs; noted in affymetrix.com). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>This current study also showed that, in contrast to the primary MB tumours, 3 out of 12 MB cell lines had defective MMR system due to promoter hypermethylation of the MLH1 gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>As we have not been able to obtain primary tumour specimens from which the cell lines were established, we can not conclude whether this epigenetic event occurred in the primary tumours or during the establishment and propagation of the corresponding cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>There are possible explanations for the observation that 3 out of 12 MB cell lines are, due to MLH1 promoter hypermethylation are MMR deficient, while primary MB tumours are MMR proficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>First, the cancer cell lines may have been selected from a sub-population of cancer cells specifically adapted to growth in tissue culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Some cells from the primary tumour may have possessed MLH1 promoter hypermethylation, thus MMR-deficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Although the great majority of the tumour cells were MMR proficient, those MMR-deficient cells might have been selected during the establishment of the tumour cell line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Another possible explanation is that at least part of the methylations might have been acquired in vitro during cell propagation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>In line with our observation regarding MB tumours and cell lines is the fact that colorectal cancer cell lines display higher rates of methylations (Suter et al, 2003) when compared with primary colorectal cancers (Lengauer et al, 1998) (e.g., MLH1 promoter methylation was detected in 30% of colorectal cancer cell lines (Suter et al, 2003)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Thus, it seems that MB tumours are, like the great majority of cancers rarely MMR deficient (Lengauer et al, 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Some MB cell lines are MMR deficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="?"><plain>So how does MMR deficiency confer an advantage on cells in vitro? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In MMR-deficient cells, mutations in oncogenes and tumour suppressor accumulate more easily, thus resulting in clonal expansion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>These these cells might be more conducive to transformation into culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>This inconsistency between tumours and cell lines highlight the limitations when using cancer cell lines as a model to study MB or other cancers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Differences between primary tumours and cancer cell lines have been reported for gene copy numbers, as several cancer-related genes show higher amplification and deletion frequencies in cell lines than tumours of their respective histology as demonstrated in MB for several genes including c-MYC gene amplification (Grotzer et al, 2001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The expression of MGMT (detected at the mRNA level, the protein level, activity, or indirectly as promoter methylation) is detectable in many MB (Hongeng et al, 1997; Bobola et al, 2001; Rood et al, 2004; Faoro et al, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>An important issue is whether data from microarray analysis (which detects mRNA expression) and those results from immunohistochemical analysis (which detects protein expression) can be interpreted similarly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>According to our gene expression analysis, MGMT expression seems to be present in primary MB, and expression values of ∼20% of the tumours are rather low (similar MGMT mRNA expression levels as CB samples). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>We would in general expect higher MGMT transcript levels – similar transcript levels as observed for MMR genes MLH1, MSH2, and MSH6 – in MGMT-proficient tumours when compared with CB samples. Silber et al (1993) showed a generally higher MGMT expression in brain tumours compared to adjacent normal brain tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Whether in those tumours with low MGMT mRNA expression the protein might be detectable in tumour cells by immunohistochemistry is questionable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Moreover, we need to consider that we can not exclude the possibility that the low MGMT expression assessed at the transcript level by microarray analysis could be the result from the contamination with tumour stroma cells or non-tumour cells expressing MGMT mRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Of note, a snap-frozen MB tumour sample was included in the microarray study when ⩾70% of the sample contained tumour cells (Kool et al, 2008, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The fact that 2 out of 12 MB cell lines were MGMT deficient is providing further evidence that a small proportion of MB tumours might be MGMT deficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>In addition, there is marked intratumoral heterogenicity for MGMT immunoreactivity in the brain tumours including MB (Rood et al, 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Ideally, we would have analysed the two different cohorts by both techniques (microarray analysis and immunohistochemistry) and this is a limitation of our study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>As we do not have the tissue blocks of the primary MB used in the microarray study, and as we have very limited amounts of tissues from the tumours analysed by immunohistochemistry, we were unable to assess MGMT/MMR proteins and mRNA expression in the two patient cohorts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Although one would expect concordance when comparing MGMT promoter methylation status, MGMT mRNA expression, and MGMT protein expression, discrepancies have been reported in several tumour entities including MB (Rood et al, 2004) and these results highlight the limitations of the methods used to date to assess MGMT protein/mRNA expression and promoter methylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Given the low frequency of MMR deficiency in MB tumours (likely no one in our series (n=74)), MGMT expression level seems to be a more relevant factor mediating tolerance to TMZ in MB and could therefore have a role as predictive/prognostic factor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Studies of GBM patients suggest that the level of MGMT expression is a predictor of TMZ response and outcome (i.e., higher MGMT expression correlated to poorer overall survival rate) (Dunn et al, 2009; Karayan-Tapon et al, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>However, recent reports investigating a limited number of paediatric brain tumour patients (including MB) (Sardi et al, 2009; Faoro et al, 2011) point to the weakness of such an association (Sardi et al, 2009; Faoro et al, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Several explanations are possible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>First, multimodal therapy of MB patients includes not only alkylating agents but also other cytotoxic drugs and radiotherapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Second, most of the reported MGMT expression levels on MB were performed in primary tumours before any chemotherapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>It is possible that MGMT expression is further upregulated during the course of treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>This has been demonstrated in vitro, where continuous exposure of O6-BG alkylating drugs such as BCNU led to further upregulation of MGMT (and BCNU resistance) in MB cell lines (Bacolod et al, 2002, 2004). Zhang et al (2010) applied a similar approach to a glioma cell line (U373VR) (continuous exposure to TMZ) and also detected MGMT upregulation in the resulting TMZ-resistant line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Third, just like MGMT upregulation, MMR deficiency may arise during the course of TMZ treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>In the aforementioned study by Zhang et al (2010), a glioma sub-line which acquired TMZ resistance also showed decreased expression of MSH6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Moreover, recent studies indicate that MMR gene abnormalities can be acquired in malignant glioma with initially intact MMR as a somatic mutation (MSH6) after treatment with alkylating agents (Pollack et al, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Finally, another resistance mechanism may be involved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>For instance, a third DNA repair mechanism, base excision repair (BER), has been shown to contribute to TMZ resistance in cancer cells (Marchesi et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The rational for this finding is that TMZ also causes other DNA damages, such as N7-meG and the highly cytotoxic N3-meA, which are repaired by BER. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The depletion of MGMT by adding O6-BG before TMZ therapy proved to be effective in potentiating the anti-cancer toxicity against MB in preclinical studies (Friedman et al, 1995; Bobola et al, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>In a clinical trial investigating a combination of TMZ/O6-BG in paediatric patients with recurrent brain tumours (including MB) (Broniscer et al, 2007) showed modest anti-tumour activity of the drug combination (Broniscer et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The use of O6-BG, however, bears the risk of serious complications since O6-BG can also potentiate TMZ in killing normal bone marrow cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Owing to hematopoietic toxicity and lack of efficacy, the combination of O6-BG/BCNU was not further tested in clinical trials of paediatric CNS tumours (Adams et al, 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Moreover, O6-BG can elevate the mutagenicity of TMZ, as it inhibits the very protein (MGMT) that repairs its mutagenic adduct (O6-meG) (Cai et al, 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, continuous exposure of MB cells to O6-BG and BCNU may result in the development of BCNU-resistant cells that have mutated MGMT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The mutant MGMT, it turned out, was inhibited by O6-BG much less effectively (Bacolod et al, 2002, 2004). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>In summary, certain molecular factors such as MGMT and MMR expressions/activities may influence the efficacy of TMZ in MB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Our data demonstrate that a subset of MB may successfully respond to TMZ as some MB tumours are MGMT deficient, and MB tumours fortunately appear to be MMR proficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>However, as MMR deficiency is evident in 3 out of 12 MB cell lines (in all cases due to transcriptional silencing of MLH1 gene), we may speculate that this defect can arise during/after treatment of MB patients, a hypothesis that needs to be tested by investigating recurrent MB for these DNA repair proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Thus, it would be preferable to evaluate MGMT and MMR in tumour tissues obtained from surgery of the relapse before treatment with TMZ. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>We would like to thank Dr Bert Vogelstein, Dr Josef Jiricny, and Dr Stefan M Pfister for helpful comments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>We thank Dr Darell D Bigner for kindly providing D283Med cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>We are grateful to Dr Udo zur Stadt and Guido Looft for some assistance in sequencing experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Temozolomide was a generous gift of Schering-Plough (Kenilworth, NJ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>We acknowledge the following sources of funding: The Swiss Research Foundation Child and Cancer (AOVB, MAG), German Children's Cancer Foundation/Deutsche Kinderkrebsstiftung (AOVB, SR, TP), Krebsliga Zürich (GM), Krebsliga beider Basel (KH), Oncosuisse (KH), German Research Foundation (TP) and Fördergemeinschaft Kinderkrebszentrum Hamburg e. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>(AOVB, SR). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>This work is published under the standard license to publish agreement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>After 12 months the work will become freely available and the license terms will switch to a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>AdamsDMZhouTBergSLBernsteinMNevilleKBlaneySM2008Phase 1 trial of O6-benzylguanine and BCNU in children with CNS tumors: a Children's Oncology Group studyPediatr Blood Cancer50(354955317941066 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib2"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>AldosariNWiltshireRNDutraASchrockEMcLendonREFriedmanHSBignerDDBignerSH2002Comprehensive molecular cytogenetic investigation of chromosomal abnormalities in human medulloblastoma cell lines and xenograftNeuro-Oncol4(2758511916498 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib3"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>BacolodMDJohnsonSPAli-OsmanFModrichPBullockNSColvinOMBignerDDFriedmanHS2002Mechanisms of resistance to 1,3-bis(2-chloroethyl)-1-nitrosourea in human medulloblastoma and rhabdomyosarcomaMol Cancer Ther1(972773612479369 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib4"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>BacolodMDJohnsonSPPeggAEDolanMEMoschelRCBullockNSFangQColvinOMModrichPBignerDDFriedmanHS2004Brain tumor cell lines resistant to O6-benzylguanine/1,3-bis(2-chloroethyl)-1-nitrosourea chemotherapy have O6-alkylguanine-DNA alkyltransferase mutationsMol Cancer Ther3(91127113515367707 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib5"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>BignerSHFriedmanHSVogelsteinBOakesWJBignerDD1990Amplification of the c-myc gene in human medulloblastoma cell lines and xenograftsCancer Res50234723502180567 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib6"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>BobolaMSBergerMSEllenbogenRGRobertsTSGeyerJRSilberJR2001O6-Methylguanine-DNA methyltransferase in pediatric primary brain tumors: relation to patient and tumor characteristicsClin Cancer Res7(361361911297257 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib7"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>BobolaMSSilberJREllenbogenRGGeyerJRBlankAGoffRD2005O6-methylguanine-DNA methyltransferase, O6-benzylguanine, and resistance to clinical alkylators in pediatric primary brain tumor cell linesClin Cancer Res11(72747275515814657 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib8"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>BroniscerAGururanganSMacDonaldTJGoldmanSPackerRJStewartCFWallaceDDanksMKFriedmanHSPoussaintTYKunLEBoyettJMGajjarA2007Phase I trial of single-dose temozolomide and continuous administration of o6-benzylguanine in children with brain tumors: a pediatric brain tumor consortium reportClin Cancer Res13(22 Part 16712671818006772 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib9"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>BuerkiNGautierLKovacMMarraGBuserMMuellerHHeinimannK2012Evidence for breast cancer as an integral part of lynch syndromeGenes Chromosomes Cancer51(1839122034109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib10"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>CahillDPLevineKKBetenskyRACoddPJRomanyCAReavieLBBatchelorTTFutrealPAStrattonMRCurryWTIafrateAJLouisDN2007Loss of the mismatch repair protein MSH6 in human glioblastomas is associated with tumor progression during temozolomide treatmentClin Cancer Res13(72038204517404084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib11"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>CaiYWuMHXu-WelliverMPeggAELudemanSMDolanME2000Effect of O6-benzylguanine on alkylating agent-induced toxicity and mutagenicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>In Chinese hamster ovary cells expressing wild-type and mutant O6-alkylguanine-DNA alkyltransferasesCancer Res60(195464546911034089 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib12"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>DanielRARozanskaALMulliganEADrewYThomasHDCastelbuonoDJHostomskyZPlummerERTweddleDABoddyAVCliffordSCCurtinNJ2010Central nervous system penetration and enhancement of temozolomide activity in childhood medulloblastoma models by poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase inhibitor AG-014699Br J Cancer1031588159620978505 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib13"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>DrablosFFeyziEAasPAVaagboCBKavliBBratlieMSPena-DiazJOtterleiMSlupphaugGKrokanHE2004Alkylation damage in DNA and RNA – repair mechanisms and medical significanceDNA Repair (Amst)3(111389140715380096 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib14"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>DunnJBaborieAAlamFJoyceKMoxhamMSibsonRCrooksDHusbandDShenoyABrodbeltAWongHLiloglouTHaylockBWalkerC2009Extent of MGMT promoter methylation correlates with outcome in glioblastomas given temozolomide and radiotherapyBr J Cancer101(112413119536096 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib15"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>FaoroDvon BuerenAOShalabyTSciuscioDHurlimannMLArnoldLGerberNUHaybaeckJMittelbronnMRutkowskiSHegiMGrotzerMA2011Expression of O6-methylguanine-DNA methyltransferase in childhood medulloblastomaJ Neurooncol103(1596920820873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib16"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>FriedmanHSBurgerPCBignerSHTrojanowskiJQBrodeurGMHeXMWikstrandCJKurtzbergJBerensMEHalperinECBignerDD1988Phenotypic and genotypic analysis of a human medulloblastoma cell line and transplantable xenograft (D341 Med) demonstrating amplification of c-mycAm J Pathol1304724843279793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib17"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>FriedmanHSBurgerPCBignerSHTrojanowskiJQWikstrandCJHalperinECBignerDD1985Establishment and characterization of the human medulloblastoma cell line and transplantable xenograft D283 MedJ Neuropathol Exp Neurol445926054056828 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib18"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>FriedmanHSDolanMEPeggAEMarcelliSKeirSCatinoJJBignerDDScholdSC1995Activity of temozolomide in the treatment of central nervous system tumor xenograftsCancer Res55(13285328577796412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib19"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>GersonSL2002Clinical relevance of MGMT in the treatment of cancerJ Clin Oncol20(92388239911981013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib20"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>GrotzerMAHogartyMDJanssAJLiuXZhaoHEggertASuttonLNRorkeLBBrodeurGMPhillipsPC2001MYC messenger RNA expression predicts survival outcome in childhood primitive neuroectodermal tumor/medulloblastomaClin Cancer Res7(82425243311489822 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib21"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>GyllingARidanpaaMVierimaaOAittomakiKAvelaKKaariainenHLaivuoriHPoyhonenMSallinenSLWallgren-PetterssonCJarvinenHJMecklinJPPeltomakiP2009Large genomic rearrangements and germline epimutations in Lynch syndromeInt J Cancer124(102333234019173287 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib22"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>HartmannWKochABruneHWahaASchullerUDaniIDenkhausDLangmannWBodeUWiestlerODSchillingKPietschT2005Insulin-like growth factor II is involved in the proliferation control of medulloblastoma and its cerebellar precursor cellsAm J Pathol166(41153116215793295 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib23"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>HongengSBrentTPSanfordRALiHKunLEHeidemanRL1997O6-Methylguanine-DNA methyltransferase protein levels in pediatric brain tumorsClin Cancer Res3(12 Part 1245924639815647 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib24"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>JacobsenPFJenkynDJPapadimitriouJM1985Establishment of a human medulloblastoma cell line and its heterotransplantation into nude miceJ Neuropathol Exp Neurol444724852993532 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib25"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Karayan-TaponLQuillienVGuilhotJWagerMFromontGSaikaliSEtcheverryAHamlatALoussouarnDCampionLCamponeMValletteFMGratas-Rabbia-ReC2010Prognostic value of O6-methylguanine-DNA methyltransferase status in glioblastoma patients, assessed by five different methodsJ Neurooncol97(331132219841865 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib26"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>KelesGEBergerMSSrinivasanJKolstoeDDBobolaMSSilberJR1995Establishment and characterization of four human medulloblastoma-derived cell linesOncol Res74935038866661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib27"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>KoolMKorshunovARemkeMJonesDTSchlansteinMNorthcottPAChoYJKosterJSchouten-van MeeterenAvan VuurdenDCliffordSCPietschTvon BuerenAORutkowskiSMcCabeMCollinsVPBacklundMLHaberlerCBourdeautFDelattreODozFEllisonDWGilbertsonRJPomeroySLTaylorMDLichterPPfisterSM2012Molecular subgroups of medulloblastoma: an international meta-analysis of transcriptome, genetic aberrations, and clinical data of WNT, SHH, Group 3, and Group 4 medulloblastomasActa Neuropathol123(447348422358457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib28"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>KoolMKosterJBuntJHasseltNELakemanAvan SluisPTroostDMeeterenNSCaronHNCloosJMrsicAYlstraBGrajkowskaWHartmannWPietschTEllisonDCliffordSCVersteegR2008Integrated genomics identifies five medulloblastoma subtypes with distinct genetic profiles, pathway signatures and clinicopathological featuresPLoS One3(8e308818769486 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib29"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>LeeSEJohnsonSPHaleLPLiJBullockNFuchsHFriedmanAMcLendonRBignerDDModrichPFriedmanHS1998Analysis of DNA mismatch repair proteins in human medulloblastomaClin Cancer Res4141514199626457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib30"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>LengauerCKinzlerKWVogelsteinB1998Genetic instabilities in human cancersNature396(67126436499872311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib31"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>LiuLMarkowitzSGersonSL1996Mismatch repair mutations override alkyltransferase in conferring resistance to temozolomide but not to 1,3-bis(2-chloroethyl)nitrosoureaCancer Res56(23537553798968088 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib32"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>MarchesiFTurrizianiMTortorelliGAvvisatiGTorinoFDe VecchisL2007Triazene compounds: mechanism of action and related DNA repair systemsPharmacol Res56(427528717897837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib33"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>MenigattiMTruningerKGebbersJOMarbetUMarraGScharP2009Normal colorectal mucosa exhibits sex- and segment-specific susceptibility to DNA methylation at the hMLH1 and MGMT promotersOncogene28(689990919060925 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib34"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>NicholsonHSKretschmarCSKrailoMBernsteinMKadotaRFortDFriedmanHHarrisMBTedeschi-BlokNMazewskiCSatoJReamanGH2007Phase 2 study of temozolomide in children and adolescents with recurrent central nervous system tumors: a report from the Children's Oncology GroupCancer110(71542155017705175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib35"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>NygrenAOAmezianeNDuarteHMVijzelaarRNWaisfiszQHessCJSchoutenJPErramiA2005Methylation-specific MLPA (MS-MLPA): simultaneous detection of CpG methylation and copy number changes of up to 40 sequencesNucleic Acids Res33(14e12816106041 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib36"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>PeggAE1990Mammalian O6-alkylguanine-DNA alkyltransferase: regulation and importance in response to alkylating carcinogenic and therapeutic agentsCancer Res50(19611961292205376 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib37"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>PietschTScharmannTFonatschCSchmidtDOecklerRFreihoffDAlbrechtSWiestlerADZeltzerPRiehmH1994Characterization of five new cell lines derived from human primitive neuroectodermal tumors of the central nervous systemCancer Res54327832878205550 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib38"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>PoleyJWWagnerAHoogmansMMMenkoFHTopsCKrosJMReddingiusREMeijers-HeijboerHKuipersEJDinjensWN2007Biallelic germline mutations of mismatch-repair genes: a possible cause for multiple pediatric malignanciesCancer109(112349235617440981 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib39"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>PollackIFHamiltonRLSobolRWNikiforovaMNNikiforovYELyons-WeilerMALaFramboiseWABurgerPCBratDJRosenblumMKGillesFHYatesAJZhouTCohenKJFinlayJLJakackiRI2010Mismatch repair deficiency is an uncommon mechanism of alkylator resistance in pediatric malignant gliomas: a report from the Children's Oncology GroupPediatr Blood Cancer55(61066107120589656 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib40"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>RoodBRZhangHCogenPH2004Intercellular heterogeneity of expression of the MGMT DNA repair gene in pediatric medulloblastomaNeuro-Oncol6(320020715279712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib41"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>RothRBHeveziPLeeJWillhiteDLechnerSMFosterACZlotnikA2006Gene expression analyses reveal molecular relationships among 20 regions of the human CNSNeurogenetics7(2678016572319 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib42"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>SardiICeticaVMassiminoMBuccolieroAMGiuntiLGenitoriLAricoM2009Promoter methylation and expression analysis of MGMT in advanced pediatric brain tumorsOncol Rep22(477377919724855 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib43"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>ScottRHMansourSPritchard-JonesKKumarDMacSweeneyFRahmanN2007Medulloblastoma, acute myelocytic leukemia and colonic carcinomas in a child with biallelic MSH6 mutationsNat Clin Pract Oncol4(213013417259933 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib44"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>SilberJRMuellerBAEwersTGBergerMS1993Comparison of O6-methylguanine-DNA methyltransferase activity in brain tumors and adjacent normal brainCancer Res53(14341634208324751 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib45"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>StuppRMasonWPvan den BentMJWellerMFisherBTaphoornMJBelangerKBrandesAAMarosiCBogdahnUCurschmannJJanzerRCLudwinSKGorliaTAllgeierALacombeDCairncrossJGEisenhauerEMirimanoffRO2005Radiotherapy plus concomitant and adjuvant temozolomide for glioblastomaN Engl J Med352(1098799615758009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib46"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>SuterCMNorrieMKuSLCheongKFTomlinsonIWardRL2003CpG island methylation is a common finding in colorectal cancer cell linesBr J Cancer88(341341912569385 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib47"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>TaylorMDNorthcottPAKorshunovARemkeMChoYJCliffordSCEberhartCGParsonsDWRutkowskiSGajjarAEllisonDWLichterPGilbertsonRJPomeroySLKoolMPfisterSM2012Molecular subgroups of medulloblastoma: the current consensusActa Neuropathol123(446547222134537 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib48"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>TruningerKMenigattiMLuzJRussellAHaiderRGebbersJOBannwartFYurtseverHNeuweilerJRiehleHMCattaruzzaMSHeinimannKScharPJiricnyJMarraG2005Immunohistochemical analysis reveals high frequency of PMS2 defects in colorectal cancerGastroenterology128(51160117115887099 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib49"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Viana-PereiraMAlmeidaISousaSMahler-AraujoBSerucaRPimentelJReisRM2009Analysis of microsatellite instability in medulloblastomaNeuro Oncol11(545846719179424 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib50"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>VladimirovaVDenkhausDSoerensenNWagnerSWolffJEPietschT2008Low level of microsatellite instability in paediatric malignant astrocytomasNeuropathol Appl Neurobiol34(554755418053027 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib51"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>von BuerenAOOehlerCShalabyTvon HoffKPruschyMSeifertBGerberNUWarmuth-MetzMStearnsDEberhartCGKortmannRDRutkowskiSGrotzerMA2011c-MYC expression sensitizes medulloblastoma cells to radio- and chemotherapy and has no impact on response in medulloblastoma patientsBMC Cancer117421324178 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib52"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>von BuerenAOShalabyTOehler-JanneCArnoldLStearnsDEberhartCGArcaroAPruschyMGrotzerMA2009RNA interference-mediated c-MYC inhibition prevents cell growth and decreases sensitivity to radio- and chemotherapy in childhood medulloblastoma cellsBMC Cancer91019134217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib53"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>YaoXBuermeyerABNarayananLTranDBakerSMProllaTAGlazerPMLiskayRMArnheimN1999Different mutator phenotypes in Mlh1- versus Pms2-deficient miceProc Natl Acad Sci USA96(126850685510359802 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib54"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>ZhangJStevensMFLaughtonCAMadhusudanSBradshawTD2010Acquired resistance to temozolomide in glioma cell lines: molecular mechanisms and potential translational applicationsOncology78(210311420357518 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Effect of temozolomide alone (straight lines) or temozolomide with a 2-h pretreatment with O6-BG (O6-benzylguanine; dashed lines) on the clonogenic survival of the medulloblastoma cell lines DAOY (A), D341Med (B), and D425Med (C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Single cells were seeded into culture dishes and treated with the denoted concentrations of temozolomide in absence or presence of O6-BG and then allowed to further grow for 9 (DAOY), 14 (D341Med), or 12 (D425Med) days, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Data are presented as the mean±standard deviation (s.d.) of three independent experiments performed in triplicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>The IC50 values and their 95% confidence intervals were calculated from the regression curve and are indicated for each data set for temozolomide alone and temozolomide with a 2-h pretreatment with O6-BG for DAOY, D341Med, and D425Med cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Differences between the two curves are represented by P-values (P&lt;0.001, P&lt;0.01, P&lt;0.05; NS, not significant). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bjc2012403f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Analysis of protein expression of mismatch repair polypeptides MSH6, MSH2, PMS2, and MLH1 in D341Med, and DAOY cells by western blotting (βIII Tubulin expression used as loading control). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Positive controls were protein extracts from HeLa cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Representative blot (two independent experiments) is shown. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bjc2012403f2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>The expression levels (Affymetrix HG U133 Plus 2.0 arrays) of the mismatch repair genes MLH1, MSH2, MSH6, and PMS2 in 61 medulloblastoma (Kool et al, 2012) grouped into the four molecular subtypes (Taylor et al, 2012) of medulloblastoma (WNT, SHH, Group 3 (GRP3) and Group 4 (GRP4)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Also included are the gene expression levels of mismatch repair genes for nine normal cerebellum (CB) samples published previously (Roth et al, 2006). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bjc2012403f3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>The expression levels (Affymetrix HG U133 Plus 2.0 arrays) of mismatch repair genes MLH1, MSH2, MSH6, and PMS2 in 12 medulloblastoma cell lines. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bjc2012403f4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>(A) The expression levels (Affymetrix HG U133 Plus 2.0 arrays) of MGMT in 61 medulloblastoma (Kool et al, 2012) grouped into the four molecular subtypes (Taylor et al, 2012) of medulloblastoma (WNT, SHH, Group 3 (GRP3), and Group 4 (GRP4)) compared with nine samples of normal cerebellum (CB), (B) MGMT expression levels of 12 medulloblastoma cell lines. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bjc2012403f5"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemistry of MMR proteins, MGMT, and Ki-67 antigen in 13 medulloblastoma tissues samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Demonstration of nuclear expression of MLH1 (upper left), MSH2 (middle), MSH6 (upper right), PMS2 (lower left), MGMT (middle), and Ki-67 antigen (lower right) in a medulloblastoma from a 10-year-old girl (chromogen diaminobenzidine, scale bar applies to all pictures). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bjc2012403f6"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Disease characteristics of 13 medulloblastoma patients analysed for expression of mismatch repair polypeptides MLH1, MSH2, MSH6, and PMS2 by immunohistochemistry</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="("/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Sex </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain> Male </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>8 (61.5%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain> Female </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>5 (38.5%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Age (years) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain> Median age at diagnosis (range) of 12 patients </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>10.7 (2.9–64.8) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain> NA (n=1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Histology </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain> Classic MB </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>11 (84.6%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain> Desmoplastic MB </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>2 (15.4%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain> Large cell/anaplastic MB </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>0 (0%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain> NA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>0 (0%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Extent of metastasis </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain> M0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>8 (61.5%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain> M1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>0 (0%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain> ⩾M2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>4 (30.8%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain> NA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>1 (7.7%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t1-fn1"><p>Abbreviations: MB=medulloblastoma; M1=presence of tumour cells in the cerebrospinal fluid at time of diagnosis; ⩾M2=metastatic disease (macroscopic) at initial presentation on MRI of the brain (M2), spine (M3), or extraneuronal metastases (M4); NA=not available.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>
<italic>MLH1</italic> promoter methylation of DAOY (included as control), and MB cell lines (D283Med, 1580WÜ, and D341Med) with absence of <italic>MLH1</italic> expression as determined by gene expression profiling</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="5" align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>MLH1 promoter methylation status (% of methylated probe) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Cell line </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>MLH1 probe 07187-L07710 A-region </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>MLH1 probe 06221-L01747 B-region </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>MLH1 probe 06222-L07712 C-region </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>MLH1 probe 01686-L15580 D-region </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>MLH1 probe 02258-L01745 Intron 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Number of methylated probes </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Interpretation </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>DAOY </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>69 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>1 Out of 5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Not methylated </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>D283Med </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>97 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>100 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>84 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>95 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>97 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>5 Out of 5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Methylated </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>1580WÜ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>100 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>100 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>100 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>55 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>4 Out of 5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Methylated </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>D341Med </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>100 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>100 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>100 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>100 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>84 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>5 Out of 5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Methylated </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t2-fn1"><p>Abbreviation: MB=medulloblastoma.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
