<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Toxins (Basel)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Toxins (Basel)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">toxins</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Toxins</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2072-6651</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3528259</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23242318</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins4121500</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">toxins-04-01500</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>In Vitro Antiplasmodial Activity of Phospholipases A2 and a Phospholipase Homologue Isolated from the Venom of the Snake Bothrops asper </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Castillo</surname><given-names>Juan Carlos Quintana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-toxins-04-01500">1</xref><xref rid="c1-toxins-04-01500" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>Leidy Johana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-toxins-04-01500">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>Cesar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-toxins-04-01500">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gutiérrez</surname><given-names>José María</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-toxins-04-01500">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pérez</surname><given-names>Juan Carlos Alarcón</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-toxins-04-01500">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-toxins-04-01500"><label>1 </label>Center for the Study of Biological Systems, Cooperative University of Colombia, Medellín 050012, Colombia</aff><aff id="af2-toxins-04-01500"><label>2 </label>Ophidism/Escorpionism Program, University of Antioquia, Medellín 050012, Colombia; E-Mails: <email>johana2104@gmail.com</email> (L.J.V.); <email>juan.alarcon@siu.udea.edu.co</email> (J.C.A.P.)</aff><aff id="af3-toxins-04-01500"><label>3 </label>Malaria Group, School of Medicine, University of Antioquia, Medellín 050012, Colombia; E-Mail: <email>cesar.segura@siu.udea.edu.co</email></aff><aff id="af4-toxins-04-01500"><label>4 </label>Clodomiro Picado Institute, School of Microbiology, University of Costa Rica, San José 1000, Costa Rica; E-Mail: <email>jose.gutierrez@ucr.ac.cr</email></aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-toxins-04-01500"><label>*</label> Author to whom correspondence should be addressed; E-Mail: <email>juan.quintanac@ucc.edu.co</email>; Tel.: +57-4-219-6536; Fax: +57-4-263-1914.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1500</fpage><lpage>1516</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>02</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>23</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2012 by the authors; licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This article is an open-access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The antimicrobial and antiparasite activity of phospholipase A2 (PLA2) from snakes and bees has been extensively explored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>We studied the antiplasmodial effect of the whole venom of the snake Bothrops asper and of two fractions purified by ion-exchange chromatography: one containing catalytically-active phospholipases A2 (PLA2) (fraction V) and another containing a PLA2 homologue devoid of enzymatic activity (fraction VI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The antiplasmodial effect was assessed on in vitro cultures of Plasmodium falciparum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The whole venom of B. asper, as well as its fractions V and VI, were active against the parasite at 0.13 ± 0.01 µg/mL, 1.42 ± 0.56 µg/mL and 22.89 ± 1.22 µg/mL, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Differences in the cytotoxic activity on peripheral blood mononuclear cells between the whole venom and fractions V and VI were observed, fraction V showing higher toxicity than total venom and fraction VI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Regarding toxicity in mice, the whole venom showed the highest lethal effect in comparison to fractions V and VI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that B. asper PLA2 and its homologue have antiplasmodial potential. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>snake venom</kwd><kwd><italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Bothrops asper</italic></kwd><kwd>phospholipase A<sub>2</sub></kwd><kwd>enzymatic activity</kwd><kwd>phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> homologue</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Malaria is responsible for approximately 1.5 million deaths every year in the world. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Over 85% of them occur in Africa, with Plasmodium falciparum as the leading species involved in mortality [1,2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The 2010 WHO report confirmed almost 1 million deaths during the previous year [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Malaria is caused by parasites of the genus Plasmodium and is a public health problem in tropical and sub-tropical regions of the world. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The most widely used treatment of the clinical syndrome includes artemisinin-based combined therapies [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>High rates of antimalarial treatment failure have led to the investigation of possible therapeutic alternatives, among which toxins and poisons of animal and plant extracts are included [4,5,6,7,8,9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The viperid snake species Bothrops asper is widely distributed throughout America, from southern Mexico to northern Ecuador [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Its venom is a complex mixture of peptides, enzymes and toxins, including metalloproteases (41%–44%), phospholipases A2 (PLA2) (29%–45%), serine proteases (4%–18%), L-amino acid oxidases (5%–59%), disintegrins (1%–2%) C-type lectin-like proteins (0.5%) and cysteine-rich secretory proteins (CRISP) (0.1%) [11], which are responsible for the toxicity of the venom and result in the complex pathophysiology provoked by these envenomations, characterized by coagulopathy, hemorrhage, blistering, edema, nephrotoxicity, shock and myotoxicity [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The PLA2 (E.C 3.1.1.4) superfamily includes enzymes that hydrolyze phospholipids, specifically the sn-2 ester bond, to produce fatty acids and lysophospholipids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Secreted PLA2s (sPLA2) share several characteristics: low molecular mass (13–18 kDa), numerous disulfide bonds, histidyl and aspartyl catalytic residues and a highly conserved calcium (Ca2+) binding region [13,14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>PLA2s from snake venom exhibit a variety of pharmacological/toxicological activities, such as myotoxicity, neurotoxicity, anticoagulant activity, edema-forming activity, cardiotoxicity, antibacterial activity, antiparasite effect and anti-aggregation activity on platelets, among others [15,16,17,18,19,20,21,22,23,24,25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Based on the already described antimicrobial and anti-parasitic activity of PLA2 [17,25,26,27,28] from snake venoms, the antimalarial potential of the venom of B. asper and PLA2s from this venom were explored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Two PLA2s from the whole venom were purified and characterized, and their in vitro antiplasmodial activity against P. falciparum was investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Cytotoxicity on peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) and acute toxicity in mice were also evaluated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Results indicate that catalytically-active and inactive PLA2s isolated from B. asper venom are cytotoxic against P. falciparum and, thus have the potential as antimalarials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Isolation of Phospholipase A2 Fractions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Six fractions obtained by fractionating B. asper venom on ion exchange chromatography on CM-Sephadex C-25 were evaluated for PLA2 activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>It was found that fraction V was the only positive fraction for PLA2 activity (see Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>However, fraction VI, corresponding to a PLA2 homologue devoid of enzymatic activity (see Section 3.2), was also analyzed for antiplasmodial activity to determine the possibility of catalytically-independent actions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Fractions V and VI were subjected to further separation by RP-HPLC on a C18 column. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>This separation revealed that fraction V had four subfractions (see Figure 1B,C), only one of which (V-4) showed PLA2 activity, whereas fraction VI showed only one peak. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>These two fractions were used to assess antiplasmodial activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="toxins-04-01500-f001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>(A) Chromatographic elution profile on CM Sephadex C-25 at 280 nm from the venom of B. asper; fractions V and VI (shaded) were further characterized; (B) Elution profile on RP-HPLC on a C18 column of fraction V; (C) Elution profile on RP-HPLC on a C18 column of fraction VI; (D) SDS-PAGE (12%) separation of venom and fractions: MW, molecular weight markers; lane 1, crude venom; lane 2, fraction V under non-reducing conditions; lane 3, fraction V under reducing conditions; lane 4, fraction VI under non-reducing conditions; lane 5, fraction VI under reducing conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="toxins-04-01500-g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Indirect Hemolytic Activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Fraction V had a minimal indirect hemolytic dose of 1.35 µg, while fraction VI showed no such activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The PLA2 isolated by HPLC from fraction V showed a minimum indirect hemolytic dose of 0.82 µg, while the peak obtained by HPLC separation of fraction VI lacked activity (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The hemolysis test with different substrates (egg yolk, plasma or human serum) yielded similar results in all assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>When indirect hemolytic activity was determined in solution, 100% hemolysis was observed using concentrations of 25 µg/mL for whole venom and 12.5 µg/mL for fraction V, whereas fraction VI lacked PLA2 activity in all tests (see Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="toxins-04-01500-f002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Indirect hemolytic activity in solution of venom and fractions V and VI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Analysis on erythrocyte suspensions containing (A) egg yolk; (B) inactivated human plasma and (C) inactivated human serum. *p ≤ 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="toxins-04-01500-g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Antiplasmodial Activity of the Venom, Fractions and Purified PLA2s </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Both venom and fractions V and VI exhibit antiplasmodial activity on the FCB1 strain of P. falciparum, with fraction V being more active than fraction VI (see Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the venom was more active than the two fractions evaluated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Guillaume et al. showed that removal of phospholipids from cultures of P. falciparum reduced the antiplasmodial activity of PLA2 [27], confirming the crucial role of PLA2 enzymatic activity to control the growth of parasites in this test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Our data demonstrate the antimalarial efficacy of fraction with PLA2 activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>However, a PLA2 homologue devoid of enzymatic activity also resulted in restriction of P. falciparum multiplication, confirming a catalytically-independent antiplasmodial activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>This effect could be due to the perturbing action exerted by the PLA2 homologue in the plasma membrane, thus resulting in an increase in permeability [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>It has been shown that the C-terminal region of these PLA2 homologues is responsible for this catalytically-independent membrane perturbation, as demonstrated in bacteria [16,30,31], being, therefore, a different mechanism from the one described for other PLA2s [26,27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="toxins-04-01500-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">toxins-04-01500-t001_Table 1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Antimalarial activity, cytotoxic activity on peripheral blood mononuclear cells and acute toxicity of B. asper venom and isolated PLA2s. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>ND: not determined. £ No deaths were recorded at this dose. € p ≤ 0.05 when compared with the other treatments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Compound </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Antimalarial activity IC50 (µg/mL) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>LD50 (µg/kg) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Cytotoxicity CC50 (µg/mL) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>B. asper venom </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>0.13 ± 0.01 € </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>3566 (2561 to 3693) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>38.46 ± 0.95 Ω </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Fraction V </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>1.42 ± 0.56 € </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>£ &gt; 15000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>26.98 ± 0.51 Ω </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Fraction VI </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>22.89 ± 1.22 € </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>£ &gt; 15000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>67.43 ± 1.03 Ω </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>CQ * </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>323.35 ± 6.97 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>ND </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>ND </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>* CQ: chloroquine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>These results are expressed in nM concentration; CC50: Dose that induces 50% cytotoxicity in peripheral blood mononuclear cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Results are expressed as mean ± S.E.M.; Ω p ≤ 0.05 when compared with the other treatments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The changes observed in the intraerythrocytic development of Plasmodium indicate that structural changes occur, as well as modifications in membrane functions in parasitized red blood cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>In addition, increments and changes in the permeability of the membrane have been described, together with the appearance of new parasite-derived proteins and changes in the composition of membrane lipids [32,33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The observed increased permeability could also be responsible for the PLA2 activity on the parasite, as demonstrated by Moll et al., who noted that in the absence of serum in the culture in vitro, PLA2 lysed parasitized cells [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>This increase in membrane permeability could also enhance the antimalarial activity of the PLA2 homologue observed in our experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>SDS-PAGE </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Electrophoresis showed that proteins of fractions V and VI (lanes 2 and 4, respectively) had molecular weights ranging from 25 kDa and 14 kDa, when fractions were separated in non-reducing conditions, thus evidencing the presence of monomers and dimers, whereas only bands of around 14 kDa were observed (lanes 3 and 5 in Figure 1D, respectively) when these fractions were subjected to reducing conditions, thus corresponding to PLA2 monomers (Figure 1D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>2.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Mass Spectrometry and Identification of the Protein </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>We determined the molecular mass of each of the fractions obtained by RP-HPLC: Fraction V (fractions V-1, V-2, V-3 and V-4) and VI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Mass spectrometric analysis showed that V-1 was of 13786.9 Da, V-2 was of 13950.1 Da, V-3 was of 13972.4 Da, V-4 was of 13974.6 Da and VI was of 13725 Da. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The tandem mass MS/MS analysis indicated that the PLA2s isolated corresponding to the fractions V-1, V-2, V-3 and VI were K49 PLA2 homologs, and V-4 was D49 PLA2 (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="toxins-04-01500-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">toxins-04-01500-t002_Table 2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Protein identification results for B. asper-PLA2 by ESI MS/MS peptide sequence obtained from mass tandem MS/MS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Fraction </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>MH+ (monoisotopic mass ) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>z </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>MS/MS-derived sequence </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Data base ID </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Species </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Score </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Reference </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr style="border-top:solid thin"><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Spectrum mill </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Mascot </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>P V-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>1944.87 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>3+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>NPVTSYGAYGCNCGVLGR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Q9PVE3.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>B. asper M1-3-3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>17.76 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>52 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>[35] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>1394.64 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>TIVCGENNSCLK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>AAF66702.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>B. moojeni Myotoxin II precursor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>14.21 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>87 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>[36] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>460.74 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>MILQETGK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Q9PRT7.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>B. asper Myotoxin IV </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>37 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>[37] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>434.05 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>CCYVHK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>AAF66702.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>B. moojeni Myotoxin II precursor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>[36] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>P V-2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>1944.87 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>3+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>NPVTSYGAYGCNCGVLGR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Q9PVE3.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>B. asper M1-3-3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>12.65 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>68 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>[35] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>1394,57 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>TIVCGENNSCLK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>1CLP_B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>B. asper Myotoxin II </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>53 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>[38] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>1637.76 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>3+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>DKTIVCGENNSCLK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>AAF66702.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>B. moojeni Myotoxin II precursor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>12.23 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>24 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>[36] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>952.78 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>ELCECDK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>AAF66702.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>B. moojeni Myotoxin II precursor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>27 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>[36] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>996.80 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>1+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>ENLDTYNK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>AAF66702.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>B. moojeni Myotoxin II precursor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>12.69 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>31 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>[36] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>802.36 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>AVAICLR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Q9PRT7.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>B. asper Myotoxin IV </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>36 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>[37] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>P V-3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>1944.87 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>3+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>NPVTSYGAYGCNCGVLGR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Q9PVE3.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>B. asper M1-3-3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>10.85 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>43 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>[35] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>1394.64 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>TIVCGENNSCLK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>AAF66702.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>B. moojeni Myotoxin II precursor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>57 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>[36] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>1637.74 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>3+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>DKTIVCGENNSCLK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>AAF66702.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>B. moojeni Myotoxin II precursor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>17.52 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>31 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>[36] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>952.78 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>ELCECDK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>AAF66702.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>B. moojeni Myotoxin II precursor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>27 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>[36] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>802.36 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>AVAICLR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Q9PRT7.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>B. asper Myotoxin IV </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>32 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>[37] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>1533.66 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>SYGAYGCNCGVLGR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>AAF66703.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>B. neuwiedi pauloensis PLA2 homolog </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>17.32 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>63 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>[39] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>P V-4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>2064.41 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>DATDRCCFVHDCCYGK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>P20474.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>B. asper Myotoxin III </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>9.51 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>30 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>[35] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>1728.75 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>EICECDKAAAVCFR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>1GMZ_A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>B. pirajai Piratoxin III </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>8.61 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>[40] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>1506.59 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>SGVIICCEGTPCEK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>P20474.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>B. asper Myotoxin III </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>64 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>[35] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>862.56 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>MILEETK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>P20474.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>B. asper Myotoxin III </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>35 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>[35] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>794.57 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>AAAVCFR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>P86974.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>B. leucurus blD-PLA2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>26 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>[41] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>1273.31 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>YMAYPDLLCK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>P20474.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>B. asper Myotoxin III </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>42 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>[35] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>675.45 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>YSYSR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>P20474.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>B. asper Myotoxin III </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>23 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>[35] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>P VI </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>1329.72 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>MILQETGKNPAK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Q9IAT9.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>B. neuwiedi pauloensis BnSP-7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>11.63 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>42 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>[39] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>1533.66 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>SYGAYGCNCGVLGR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>AAF66703.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>B. neuwiedi pauloensis PLA2 homolog </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>17.92 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>52 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>[39] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>790.04 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>1+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>LTGCNPK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>P86453.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>B. alternatus BaTx </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>[42] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>1637.56 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>DKTIVCGENNSCLK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>AAF66702.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>B. moojeni Myotoxin II precursor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>21 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>[36] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>1394.57 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>2+ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>TIVCGENNSCLK </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>1CLP_B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>B. asper Myotoxin II </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>77 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>[38] </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="toxins-04-01500-f003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Multiple sequence alignment of Fraction P V-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>The boxes represent conserved amino acids. B. asper M1-3-3 Swiss Protein ID: Q9PVE3.1, GenBank ID: AAF14241.1|AF109911, Myotoxin B. asper PDB ID: 1CLP_A, Myotoxin-II B. asper Swiss Protein ID: P24605.3, Bothropstoxin-Ia B. jararacussu GenBank ID: CAA55334.2, BnSP-7 B. neuwiedi Q9IAT9.2, Piratoxin-II Bothrops pirajai P82287.1, Piratoxin-I B. pirajai Swiss Protein ID: 58399.2, Myotoxin-I B. atrox Swiss Protein ID: P82287.1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="toxins-04-01500-g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="toxins-04-01500-f004" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Multiple sequence alignment of Fraction P V-2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>The boxes represent conserved amino acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Myotoxin- IV B. asper Swiss Protein ID: P0C616, M1-3-3 B. asper Swiss Protein ID: SP|Q9PVE3.1, GenBank ID: AAF14241.1|AF109911, Piratoxin-Ii B. pirajai PDB ID: 2QLL_A, Bothropstoxin-Ia B. jararacussu GenBank ID: CAA55334.2, BnSP-7 B. neuwiedi Swiss Protein ID: Q9IAT9.2, Piratoxin-II B. pirajai Swiss Protein ID: P82287.1, BnIV B. neuwiedi PDB ID: 3MLM_A, Piratoxin-I B. pirajai Swiss Protein ID: 58399.2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="toxins-04-01500-g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the identified peptides were subjected to BLAST analysis to determine their identity with other phospholipases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>The results confirmed the high identity of these peptides with PLA2s from the venoms of B. asper, B. neuwiedi, B. jararacussu, B. pirajai and Cerrophidion godmani, among others (see Figure 3, Figure 4, Figure 5, Figure 6, Figure 7). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="toxins-04-01500-f005" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Multiple sequence alignment of Fraction P V-3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>The boxes represent conserved amino acid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>M1-3-3 B. asper Swiss Protein ID: Q9PVE3.1, Myotoxin-II B. asper Swiss Protein ID: P24605.3, piratoxin-II B. pirajai Swiss Protein ID: P82287, Piratoxin-I B. pirajai Swiss Protein ID: 58399.2, Bothropstoxin-Ia B. jararacussu GenBank ID: CAA55334.2, BnSP-7 B. neuwiedi Swiss Protein ID: Q9IAT9.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>BOJU-I B. jararacussu Swiss Protein ID: Q90249.3, Myotoxin-II B. moojeni GenBank ID: AAF66702.1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="toxins-04-01500-g005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="toxins-04-01500-f006" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Multiple sequence alignment of Fraction P V-4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>The boxes represent conserved amino acid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Myotoxin-III B. asper Swiss Protein ID: P20474.2, BthTx-II B. jararacussu Swiss Protein ID: P45881.1, PLA2 S. miliarius GenBank ID: ABY77926.1, N6 PLA2 C. godmani GenBank ID: AAR14161.1, N6 PLA2 B. schlegelii GenBank ID: AAR14162.1, PLA-N T. flavoviridis GenBank ID: BAC56893, PA2B_AGKAG D. acutus Swiss Protein ID: Q1ZY03, Variant ammodytoxin-B V. aspis GenBank ID: CAE47279.1, PLA2 S. c. tergeminus Accession number GenBank ID: ABY77930.1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="toxins-04-01500-g006"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="toxins-04-01500-f007" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Multiple sequence alignment of Fraction P VI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>The boxes represent conserved amino acid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Myotoxin-II B. asper Swiss Protein ID: P24605.1, Piratoxin-I B. pirajai Swiss Protein ID: P58399.2, Piratoxin-II B. pirajai Swiss Protein ID: P82287.3, BthTx-Ia B. jararacussu GenBank ID: CAA55334, BnSP-7 B. neuwiedi Swiss Protein ID: Q9IAT9.2, myotoxin-II B. moojeni PDB ID: 1XXS_2, MjTx-I B. moojeni Swiss Protein ID: P82114.1, BaTx B. alternatus Swiss Protein ID: P86453.1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="toxins-04-01500-g007"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>The results of the alignments show that the PLA2s and PLA2 homologues purified from the venom of B. asper from Colombia are similar to other PLA2s and PLA2 homologues present in other Bothrops snakes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>In addition, the PLA2 D49 shows homology with other PLA2s from Bothrops, being higher with those of B. asper from Costa Rica (see Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>2.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Cytotoxic Activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Analysis of the cytotoxic effect of the whole venom and the different fractions tested showed that fraction V was more cytotoxic than whole venom or fraction VI on PBMC cells (see Figure 8). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="toxins-04-01500-f008" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Cytotoxic activity of B. asper venom and isolated fractions on human peripheral blood mononuclear cells.VT venom, Fraction V, fraction VI. * p ≤ 0.05 compared to different doses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="toxins-04-01500-g008"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>The cytotoxic activity of venoms and PLA2s is a problem in using these in future biomedical applications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>However, our results show that the PLA2 isolated exerts an antimalarial effect at a lower dose than that required to induce cytotoxicity in PBMC and indirect hemolysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Other authors have shown that cytotoxic activity is dependent on serum in suspensions of tumor cells and red blood cells [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>In some experiments, we cultured cells with fetal bovine serum 2% (FBS) and inactivated serum or plasma, and in these conditions, the cytotoxic dose was still higher than the antimalarial dose (results not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>2.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Acute Toxicity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>The LD50 of the whole venom of B. asper was 3566 µg/kg (2561 to 3693), whereas no lethality was observed in mice injected with fractions V and VI at doses as high as 15,000 µg/kg (see Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>The envenoming of B. asper induces local and systemic symptoms, such as edema, pain and bleeding, among others, due to the effect of different toxins in the venom, such as PLA2, serine proteinases and metalloproteases, among others [19,44,45,46,47,48,49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>The low toxicity of fraction V and of the PLA2 homologue isolated from fraction VI compared with the venom indicates their low overall toxicity in mice and reinforces the concept that these fractions are good lead compounds in the search for antimalarial activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>This is in agreement with reports on the use of snake venom PLA2s to inhibit microorganisms, such as bacteria and fungi, as well as parasites including Giardia duodenalis, Trypanosoma cruzi, Leishmania spp and P. falciparum [17,30,31,50,51,52]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Venom and Reagents </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>The venom was obtained by manual milking of 40 adult specimens from different regions of Colombia held in captivity at the Serpentarium of the University of Antioquia (Medellín, Colombia). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Once extracted and pooled, the venoms were centrifuged (3000 rpm, 15 min), and the resulting supernatants were lyophilized and stored at −20 °C until use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Acetonitrile (CH3CN) and trifluoroacetic acid (CF3COOH) HPLC grade were purchased from Fisher Scientific (Loughborough, UK). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Histopaque®-1077, RPMI-1640 medium culture, Thiazolyl Blue Tretrazolium Bromide (MTT) and dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) were purchased from Sigma (Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Water for HPLC was deionized to a degree of purity of 17 Ω. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3dot2-toxins-04-01500"><title><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Venom Fractionation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>PLA2s were purified from 50 mg of whole venom of B. asper dissolved in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), pH 7.2, and passed through a CM-Sephadex C25 ion exchange column (1.8 × 120 cm) at the flow rate 1.0 mL/min on a low-pressure chromatography system (Econo-System, BioRad, Hercules, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>The resulting fractions were analyzed for their PLA2 activity and then PLA2 positive fractions submitted to a reverse phase HPLC (RP-HPLC) (Shimadzu, Model Prominence, Shimadzu Corporation, Kyoto, Japan) in a C18 column (pore 5 µm, 250 mm × 4.6 mm mark RESTEK Bellefonte, PA, USA) using a linear gradient (0%–100%) acetonitrile (v/v) in 0.1% (v/v) trifluoroacetic acid at a flow rate 1.0 mL/min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Finally, fractions were lyophilized and stored at −20 °C until use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Electrophoresis and Molecular Mass Determination </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Protein homogeneity of the obtained fractions were determined by electrophoresis under reducing and non-reducing conditions in SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) 15% [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Protein molecular weight was estimated according to a molecular weight markers range of 97.4 to 14.4 kDa (BioRad, Philadelphia, PA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>The gels were stained with Coomassie Brilliant Blue G-250. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>The molecular masses of PLA2 fractions were confirmed by direct-infusion mass spectrometry in an IonTrap (series 6310, Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>3.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Protein Iidentification by HPLC-nESI-MS/MS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>The PLA2s and PLA2 homologues isolated from B. asper venom (fractions V and VI see results, Figure 1B,C) were digested in solution with trypsin (0.1 ng) at 30 °C (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA) overnight, according to the manufacturer’s instructions, and injected onto a nano LC-ESI-MS/MS system (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA) using a nano column C18 (Agilent Zorbax 300SB-C18, 150 × 0.075mm, 3.5 μm) coupled to a mass spectrometer IonTrap MSD series 6300 (Model 6310, Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA) [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>MS/MS mass spectra were obtained in positive mode, dynamic range 200–1200 Da; Electrospray at 2 kV and 230 °C dry temperature, trap drive 200 ms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Charged state deconvolution of the MS/MS spectra were determined using the ChemStation G2070-91126 (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>3.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Search Database </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Deconvoluted profile spectra were used to search online the MASCOT [55] and Spectrum Mill (Agilent Technology, Santa Clara, CA, USA) in the NCBInr database for protein identification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>The parameters of the search included digestion with trypsin and Carbamidomethyilation modified (C) as fixed modification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>The minimum score for the intensity of each fraction was 50%, monoisotopic mass, mass tolerance of 2.5 Da and a way to search for identity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>3.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>BLAST Search of the Identified Peptides </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>The identified peptides were subjected to a BLAST search [56] to determine the homology with other PLA2 family proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>This homology was performed in BLASTP, the search parameters being non-redundant protein sequence (nr) and a snake organism. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>3.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Acute Toxicity of the Venom and Fractions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>The Median Lethal Dose (LD50) was determined by the Spearman-Karber method (World Health Organization, 1981) using groups of four mice (Swiss-Webster mice strain) injected intraperitoneally (IP) with varying doses of either fractions or whole B. asper venom, previously dissolved in 0.5 mL PBS, pH 7.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Fatalities were recorded within 48 h, and the results were expressed as the average of three repetitions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>3.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Cytotoxic Activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) were separated by centrifugation of citrated human blood (400g, 30 min) with Histopaque®-1077 (Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, USA), washed with PBS and transferred to 96 well plates at a concentration of 3 × 105 cells/well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Cells were cultured with different concentrations of fractions (37 °C, 5% CO2) for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>After this time, 40 µL of MTT was added and incubated for 3 h (same conditions as described). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>The reaction was halted by adding 130 µL of dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) and readings were performed in a microplate reader at 420 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>The 50% cytotoxic dose was calculated by linear regression [57]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>3.9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Indirect Hemolysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>This was evaluated following the method that uses agarose gel-erythrocyte-egg yolk [58,59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>We estimated the minimum indirect hemolytic dose (MIHD), defined as the dose of venom producing a hemolytic halo of 20 mm in diameter after 20 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>In addition, indirect hemolytic activity was assessed on red blood cells in suspension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>For this, different doses of either the whole venom or fractions V and VI were incubated with fresh human red blood cells for 30 min at 37 °C in the presence of 250 µL of inactivated human serum, inactivated human plasma, egg yolk or PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Afterwards, samples were centrifuged, and the percentage of lysis was determined by recording the absorbance at 540 nm as an index of released hemoglobin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>As a control of 100% hemolysis, 2%Triton X-100 was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>The results were expressed as percentage of lysis, and the venom or toxin concentration producing 100% hemolysis was determined. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>3.10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Cultivation of Plasmodium falciparum </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Based on the procedure described by Trager and Jensen [60], parasites were grown at 37 °C in A+ human erythrocytes to a hematocrit of 2% and 3%–6% parasitemia under an atmosphere of 3% CO2, 6% O2 and 91% N2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>3.11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Determination of Percentage of Growth Inhibition of P. falciparum by B. asper PLA2 Fractions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Increasing concentrations of PLA2 fractions V and VI in complete medium were plated in 96-well plates (100 µL/well) and incubated with asynchronous P. falciparum FCB1 (1.5% parasitemia, 4% hematocrit, 100 µL/well). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Parasites were incubated as previously described [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>After 24 h, 0.5 mCi of 3H-hypoxanthine was added to the culture, and parasites were cultured for further 24 h at the same conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Finally, the plates were freeze-thawed, and parasites were harvested onto filter paper, added to liquid scintillation cocktail and the incorporation of 3H-hypoxanthine determined in a Microbeta counter 1450 (Wallac, Perkin Elmer, Waltham, MA, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>The percentage of growth inhibition was calculated based on 100% uptake of the 3H-hypoxanthine of controls (parasites in culture medium, incomplete RPMI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Growth inhibition was calculated based on 100% uptake of the 3H-hypoxanthine control in parasites in the absence of PLA2s or PLA2 homologues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>The IC50 values correspond to the venom or toxin concentration required to kill 50% of the parasites within 48 h, and was determined from dose-response curves according to Desjardins et al. [58]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>3.12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>The results are presented as mean ± S.E.M of three replicates, and experimental differences between means were determined by analysis of variance followed by Dunnett’s test for intragroup comparisons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>Significance was set up at p &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>Our observations suggest that PLA2s and PLA2 homologues present in the venom of Bothrops asper represent promising lead compounds in the search for novel antimalarial agents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>Further studies should be performed on the identification of the molecular determinants of this activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>The authors thank Carlos Augusto Uribe, for his excellent assistance in the mass spectrometer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the Departamento Administrativo de Ciencia, Tecnología e Innovación (COLCIENCIAS) project number 111540820526, Universidad de Antioquia (Estrategia para la Sostenibilidad de los Grupos 2013–2014) and Universidad Cooperativa de Colombia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>This study was performed as partial requirement for the PhD degree of Juan Carlos Quintana Castillo at Universidad de Antioquia. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><notes><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>1. World Health Organization World Malaria Report 2008 Available online:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://malaria.who.int/wmr2008/malaria2008.pdf">http://malaria.who.int/wmr2008/malaria2008.pdf</ext-link> (accessed on 10 August 2012)  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>2. BremanJ.G.AlilioM.S.MillsA. Conquering the intolerable burden of malaria: What’s new, what’s needed: A summary Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>Trop. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Hyg. 2004 71 1 15 15331814 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>3. World Health Organization World Malaria Report 2010 Available online:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/malaria/publications/atoz/artemisinin_resistance_containment_2011.pdf">http://www.who.int/malaria/publications/atoz/artemisinin_resistance_containment_2011.pdf</ext-link> (accessed on 13 March 2011)  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>4. Abdel-SattarE.MaesL.SalamaM.M. In vitro activities of plant extracts from Saudi Arabia against malaria, leishmaniasis, sleeping sickness and Chagas disease Phytother. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Res. 2010 24 1322 1328 10.1002/ptr.3108 20127723 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>5. AyukoT.A.NjauR.N.CorneliusW.LeahN.NdiegeI.O. In vitro antiplasmodial activity and toxicity assessment of plant extracts used in traditional malaria therapy in the Lake Victoria Region Mem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>Inst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>Oswaldo Cruz. 2009 104 689 694 10.1590/S0074-02762009000500004 19820826 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>6. GaoB.XuJ.Rodriguez MdelC.Lanz-MendozaH.Hernandez-RivasR.DuW.ZhuS. Characterization of two linear cationic antimalarial peptides in the scorpion Mesobuthus eupeus Biochimie 2010 92 350 359 10.1016/j.biochi.2010.01.011 20097251 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>7. KarunamoorthiK.IlangoK.MuruganK. Laboratory evaluation of traditionally used plant-based insect repellent against the malaria vector Anopheles arabiensis Patton (Diptera: Culicidae) Parasitol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>Res. 2010 106 1217 1223 10.1007/s00436-010-1797-y 20195634 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>8. MilhousW.K.WeinaP.J. Plant science. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>The botanical solution for malaria Science 2010 327 279 280 10.1126/science.1184780 20075238 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>9. MullerG.C.BeierJ.C.TraoreS.F.ToureM.B.TraoreM.M.BahS.DoumbiaS.SchleinY. Successful field trial of attractive toxic sugar bait (ATSB) plant-spraying methods against malaria vectors in the Anopheles gambiae complex in Mali, West Africa Malar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>J. 2010 9 210 10.1186/1475-2875-9-210 20663142 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>10. CampbellJ.LamarW. The Venomous Reptiles of the Western Hemisphere Cornell University Press Chichester, Scotland, UK 2004  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>11. Alape-GironA.SanzL.EscolanoJ.Flores-DiazM.MadrigalM.SasaM.CalveteJ.J. Snake venomics of the lancehead pitviper Bothrops asper: Geographic, individual, and ontogenetic variations J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>Proteome Res. 2008 7 3556 3571 10.1021/pr800332p 18557640 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>12. AnguloY.LomonteB. Biochemistry and toxicology of toxins purified from the venom of the snake Bothrops asper Toxicon 2009 54 949 957 10.1016/j.toxicon.2008.12.014 19111755 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>13. SixD.A.DennisE.A. The expanding superfamily of phospholipase A(2) enzymes: Classification and characterization Biochim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>Acta 2000 1488 1 19 10.1016/S1388-1981(00)00105-0 11080672 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>14. TalvinenK.A.NevalainenT.J. Cloning of a novel phospholipase A2 from the cnidarian Adamsia carciniopados Comp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>Physiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>B 2002 132 571 578 10.1016/S1096-4959(02)00073-8 12091102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>15. Andriao-EscarsoS.H.SoaresA.M.RodriguesV.M.AnguloY.DiazC.LomonteB.GutierrezJ.M.GiglioJ.R. Myotoxic phospholipases A(2) in bothrops snake venoms: Effect of chemical modifications on the enzymatic and pharmacological properties of bothropstoxins from Bothrops jararacussu Biochimie 2000 82 755 763 10.1016/S0300-9084(00)01150-0 11018293 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>16. BarbosaP.S.MartinsA.M.HavtA.ToyamaD.O.EvangelistaJ.S.FerreiraD.P.JoazeiroP.P.BeriamL.O.ToyamaM.H.FontelesM.C. Renal and antibacterial effects induced by myotoxin I and II isolated from Bothrops jararacussu venom Toxicon 2005 46 376 386 10.1016/j.toxicon.2005.04.024 16115661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>17. Costa TorresA.F.DantasR.T.ToyamaM.H.Diz FilhoE.ZaraF.J.Rodrigues de QueirozM.G.Pinto NogueiraN.A.Rosa de OliveiraM.de Oliveira ToyamaD.MonteiroH.S. Antibacterial and antiparasitic effects of Bothrops marajoensis venom and its fractions: Phospholipase A2 and L-amino acid oxidase Toxicon 2010 55 795 804 10.1016/j.toxicon.2009.11.013 19944711 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>18. EvangelistaI.L.MartinsA.M.NascimentoN.R.HavtA.EvangelistaJ.S.de NoroesT.B.ToyamaM.H.Diz-FilhoE.B.toyama DdeO.FontelesM.C. Renal and cardiovascular effects of Bothrops marajoensis venom and phospholipase A2 Toxicon 2010 55 1061 1070 10.1016/j.toxicon.2009.12.004 20036276 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>19. GutierrezJ.M.LomonteB. Phospholipase A2 myotoxins from Bothrops snake venoms Toxicon 1995 33 1405 1424 10.1016/0041-0101(95)00085-Z 8744981 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>20. HarrisJ.B.GrubbB.D.MaltinC.A.DixonR. The neurotoxicity of the venom phospholipases A(2), notexin and taipoxin Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>Neurol. 2000 161 517 526 10.1006/exnr.1999.7275 10686073 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>21. KiniR.M. Excitement ahead: Structure, function and mechanism of snake venom phospholipase A2 enzymes Toxicon 2003 42 827 840 10.1016/j.toxicon.2003.11.002 15019485 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>22. KiniR.M.EvansH.J. Structure-function relationships of phospholipases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>The anticoagulant region of phospholipases A2  J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>Chem. 1987 262 14402 14407 3117784 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>23. LanducciE.C.de CastroR.C.ToyamaM.GiglioJ.R.MarangoniS.de NucciG. AntunesE. Inflammatory oedema induced by the lys-49 phospholipase A(2) homologue piratoxin-i in the rat and rabbit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>Effect of polyanions and p-bromophenacyl bromid Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>Pharmacol. 2000 59 1289 1294 10736429 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>24. MurakamiM.T.ArrudaE.Z.MeloP.A.MartinezA.B.Calil-EliasS.TomazM.A.LomonteB.GutierrezJ.M.ArniR.K. Inhibition of myotoxic activity of Bothrops asper myotoxin II by the anti-trypanosomal drug suramin J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2005 350 416 426 10.1016/j.jmb.2005.04.072 15961104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>25. QuintanaJ.C.ChaconA.M.VargasL.SeguraC.GutierrezJ.M.AlarconJ.C. Antiplasmodial effect of the venom of Crotalus durissus cumanensis, crotoxin complex and Crotoxin B Acta Trop. 2012 124 126 132 10.1016/j.actatropica.2012.07.003 22884508 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>26. DeregnaucourtC.SchrevelJ. Bee venom phospholipase A2 induces stage-specific growth arrest of the intraerythrocytic Plasmodium falciparum via modifications of human serum components J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>Chem. 2000 275 39973 39980 10.1074/jbc.M006712200 10988294 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>27. GuillaumeC.DeregnaucourtC.ClaveyV.SchrevelJ. Anti-Plasmodium properties of group IA, IB, IIA and III secreted phospholipases A2 are serum-dependent Toxicon 2004 43 311 318 10.1016/j.toxicon.2004.01.006 15033330 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>28. PasseroL.F.LaurentiM.D.TomokaneT.Y.CorbettC.E.ToyamaM.H. The effect of phospholipase A2 from Crotalus durissus collilineatus on Leishmania (Leishmania) amazonensis infection Parasitol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>Res. 2008 102 1025 1033 10.1007/s00436-007-0871-6 18180953 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>29. LomonteB.RangelJ. Snake venom Lys49 myotoxins: From phospholipases A(2) to non-enzymatic membrane disruptors Toxicon 2012 60 520 530 10.1016/j.toxicon.2012.02.007 22781132 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>30. NuñezV.ArceV.GutierrezJ.M.LomonteB. Structural and functional characterization of myotoxin I, a Lys49 phospholipase A2 homologue from the venom of the snake Bothrops atrox Toxicon 2004 44 91 101 10.1016/j.toxicon.2004.04.013 15225567 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>31. SantamariaC.LariosS.QuirosS.Pizarro-CerdaJ.GorvelJ.P.LomonteB.MorenoE. Bactericidal and antiendotoxic properties of short cationic peptides derived from a snake venom Lys49 phospholipase A2 Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 2005 49 1340 1345 10.1128/AAC.49.4.1340-1345.2005 15793109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>32. HillD.A.DesaiS.A. Malaria parasite mutants with altered erythrocyte permeability: A new drug resistance mechanism and important molecular tool Future Microbiol. 2010 5 81 97 10.2217/fmb.09.109 20020831 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>33. VialH.J.AncelinM.L. Malarial lipids Malaria: Parasite Biology, Pathogenesis, and Protection ShermanI.W. ASM Press Washington, DC, USA 1998 159 175  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>34. MollG.N.VialH.J.van der WieleF.C.AncelinM.L.RoelofsenB.SlotboomA.J.de HaasG.H.van DeenenL.L.Op den KampJ.A. Selective elimination of malaria infected erythrocytes by a modified phospholipase A2 in vitro Biochim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>Acta 1990 1024 189 192 10.1016/0005-2736(90)90224-C 2337614 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>35. LizanoS.LambeauG.LazdunskiM. Cloning and cDNA sequence analysis of Lys(49) and Asp(49) basic phospholipase A(2) myotoxin isoforms from Bothrops asper Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>Cell Biol. 2001 33 127 132 10.1016/S1357-2725(00)00073-X 11240369 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>36. SoaresA.M.RodriguesV.M.Homsi-BrandeburgoM.I.ToyamaM.H.LombardiF.R.ArniR.K.GiglioJ.R. A rapid procedure for the isolation of the Lys-49 myotoxin II from Bothrops moojeni (caissaca) venom: Biochemical characterization, crystallization, myotoxic and edematogenic activity Toxicon 1998 36 503 514 10.1016/S0041-0101(97)00133-5 9637370 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>37. DiazC.LomonteB.ZamudioF.GutierrezJ.M. Purification and characterization of myotoxin IV, a phospholipase A2 variant, from Bothrops asper snake venom Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>Toxins 1995 3 26 31 10.1002/nt.2620030107 7749580 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>38. ArniR.K.WardR.J.GutierrezJ.M.TulinskyA. Structure of a calcium-independent phospholipase-like myotoxic protein from Bothrops asper venom Acta Crystallogr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>D 1995 51 311 317 10.1107/S0907444994011455 15299297 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>39. RodriguesV.M.SoaresA.M.MancinA.C.FontesM.R.Homsi-BrandeburgoM.I.GiglioJ.R. Geographic variations in the composition of myotoxins from Bothrops neuwiedi snake venoms: Biochemical characterization and biological activity Comp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>Physiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>A 1998 121 215 222 10.1016/S1095-6433(98)10136-8  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>40. RigdenD.J.HwaL.W.MarangoniS.ToyamaM.H.PolikarpovI. The structure of the D49 phospholipase A2 piratoxin III from Bothrops pirajai reveals unprecedented structural displacement of the calcium-binding loop: Possiblerelationship to cooperative substrate binding Acta Crystallogr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>D 2003 59 255 262 10.1107/S0907444902021467 12554936 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>41. HiguchiD.A.BarbosaC.M.BincolettoC.ChagasJ.R.MagalhaesA.RichardsonM.SanchezE.F.PesqueroJ.B.AraujoR.C.PesqueroJ.L. Purification and partial characterization of two phospholipases A2 from Bothrops leucurus (white-tailed-jararaca) snake venom Biochimie 2007 89 319 328 10.1016/j.biochi.2006.10.010 17110015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>42. Ponce-SotoL.A.LomonteB.GutierrezJ.M.Rodrigues-SimioniL.NovelloJ.C.MarangoniS. Structural and functional properties of BaTX, a new Lys49 phospholipase A2 homologue isolated from the venom of the snake Bothrops alternatus Biochim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>Acta 2007 1770 585 593 10.1016/j.bbagen.2006.11.015 17270350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>43. VadasP. Group II phospholipases A2 are indirectly cytolytic in the presence of exogenous phospholipid Biochim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>Acta 1997 1346 193 197 10.1016/S0005-2760(97)00029-5 9219902 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>44. OteroR.NunezV.OsorioR.G.GutierrezJ.M.GiraldoC.A.PosadaL.E. Ability of six Latin American antivenoms to neutralize the venom of mapana equis (Bothrops atrox) from Antioquia and Choco (Colombia) Toxicon 1995 33 809 815 10.1016/0041-0101(95)00009-B 7676472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>45. Otero-PatinoR. Epidemiological, clinical and therapeutic aspects of Bothrops asper bites Toxicon 2009 54 998 1011 10.1016/j.toxicon.2009.07.001 19591857 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>46. Otero-PatinoR.CardosoJ.L.HigashiH.G.NunezV.DiazA.ToroM.F.GarciaM.E.SierraA.GarciaL.F.MorenoA.M. A randomized, blinded, comparative trial of one pepsin-digested and two whole IgG antivenoms for Bothrops snake bites in Uraba, Colombia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>The Regional Group on Antivenom Therapy Research (REGATHER) Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>Trop. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>Hyg. 1998 58 183 189 9580075 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>47. GutierrezJ.M.OwnbyC.L.OdellG.V. Pathogenesis of myonecrosis induced by crude venom and a myotoxin of Bothrops asper Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>Pathol. 1984 40 367 379 10.1016/0014-4800(84)90054-6 6539250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>48. GutierrezJ.M.OwnbyC.L.OdellG.V. Isolation of a myotoxin from Bothrops asper venom: Partial characterization and action on skeletal muscle Toxicon 1984 22 115 128 10.1016/0041-0101(84)90144-2 6426093 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>49. TrebienH.A.CalixtoJ.B. Pharmacological evaluation of rat paw oedema induced by Bothrops jararaca venom Agents Actions 1989 26 292 300 10.1007/BF01967293 2660497 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>50. ChoiS.J.ParentR.GuillaumeC.DeregnaucourtC.DelarbreC.OjciusD.M.MontagneJ.J.CelerierM.L.PhelipotA.AmicheM. Isolation and characterization of Psalmopeotoxin I and II: Two novel antimalarial peptides from the venom of the tarantula Psalmopoeus cambridgei FEBS Lett. 2004 572 109 117 10.1016/j.febslet.2004.07.019 15304333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>51. ShinoharaL.de FreitasS.F.da SilvaR.J.GuimaraesS. In vitro effects of Crotalus durissus terrificus and Bothrops jararaca venoms on Giardia duodenalis trophozoites Parasitol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>Res. 2006 98 339 344 10.1007/s00436-005-0037-3 16378220 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>52. AdadeC.M.ConsB.L.MeloP.A.Souto-PadronT. Effect of Crotalus viridis viridis snake venom on the ultrastructure and intracellular survival of Trypanosoma cruzi Parasitology 2011 138 46 58 10.1017/S0031182010000958 20663246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>53. LaemmliU.K. Cleavage of structural proteins during the assembly of the head of bacteriophage T4 Nature 1970 227 680 685 10.1038/227680a0 5432063 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>54. ShevchenkoA.WilmM.VormO.MannM. Mass spectrometric sequencing of proteins silver-stained polyacrylamide gels Anal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>Chem. 1996 68 850 858 10.1021/ac950914h 8779443 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>55. Matrix Science Mascot MS/MS Ion Search Available online:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.matrixscience.com/cgi/search_form.pl?FORMVER=2&amp;SEARCH=MIS">http://www.matrixscience.com/cgi/search_form.pl?FORMVER=2&amp;SEARCH=MIS</ext-link> (accessed on 12 May 2012)  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>56. NCBI Standard Protein Blast Available online:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi?PAGE=Proteins">http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi?PAGE=Proteins</ext-link> (accessed on 15 May 2012)  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>57. LomonteB.GutierrezJ.M.RomeroM.NunezJ.TarkowskiA.HansonL.A. An MTT-based method for the in vivo quantification of myotoxic activity of snake venoms and its neutralization by antibodies J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain>Immunol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="550" pm="."><plain>Methods 1993 161 231 237 10.1016/0022-1759(93)90299-M 8505552 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="551" pm="."><plain>58. HabermannE.HardtK.L. A sensitive and specific plate test for the quantitation of phospholipases Anal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="552" pm="."><plain>Biochem. 1972 50 163 173 4342994 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="553" pm="."><plain>59. GutierrezJ.M.ChavesF.RojasE.ElizondoJ.AvilaC.CerdasL. Production of monovalent anti-Bothrops asper antivenom: Development of immune response in horses and neutralizing ability Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="554" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="555" pm="."><plain>Trop. 1988 36 511 517 3078800 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60-toxins-04-01500"><text><SENT sid="556" pm="."><plain>60. TragerW.JensonJ.B. Cultivation of malarial parasites Nature 1978 273 621 622 10.1038/273621a0 351412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
