<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3235092</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22174750</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-14508</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027833</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Agriculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Aquaculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Oyster Farming</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy and Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Endocrine System</subject><subj-group><subject>Endocrine Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Endocrine Subsystems</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Reproductive System</subject><subj-group><subject>Reproductive Physiology</subject><subject>Sexual Reproduction</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Integrative Physiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzymes</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzyme Regulation</subject><subject>Enzyme Structure</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Nucleic acids</subject><subj-group><subject>DNA</subject><subj-group><subject>Complementary DNA</subject><subject>DNA amplification</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Protein Structure</subject><subject>Recombinant Proteins</subject><subject>Transmembrane Proteins</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Immunochemistry</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Comparative Genomics</subject><subject>Functional Genomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Sequence Analysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genome Databases</subject><subj-group><subject>Sequence Databases</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Comparative Genomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Marine Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Proteomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>A Crucial Role in Fertility for the Oyster Angiotensin-Converting Enzyme Orthologue CgACE </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Oyster ACE Is Crucial for Fertility</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Riviere</surname><given-names>Guillaume</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fellous</surname><given-names>Alexandre</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>Alban</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bernay</surname><given-names>Benoit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Favrel</surname><given-names>Pascal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>UMR M100 Physiologie et Ecophysiologie des Mollusques Marins, Université de Caen Basse-Normandie - IFREMER, Caen, France</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Plateau de post-genomique ‘Proteogene’, IFR 146 ICORE, Caen, France</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Promponas</surname><given-names>Vasilis J.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Cyprus, Cyprus</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>guillaume.riviere@unicaen.fr</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: GR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: BB A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Fellous A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Franco GR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: PF BB A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Fellous A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Franco GR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: PF GR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>12</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e27833</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Riviere et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) is a highly conserved metallopeptidase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In mammals, the somatic isoform governs blood pressure whereas the germinal isoform (tACE) is required for fertility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>In Ecdysozoans, ACE-like enzymes are implicated in reproduction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Despite ACE orthologues being present from bacteria to humans, their function(s) remain(s) unknown in distant organisms such as Lophotrochozoans. In silico analysis of an oyster (Crassostrea gigas) EST library suggested the presence of an ACE orthologue in molluscs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Primer walking and 5′-RACE revealed that the 1.9 kb cDNA encodes CgACE, a 632 amino acid protein displaying a conserved single active site and a putative C-terminal transmembrane anchor, thus resembling human tACE, as supported by molecular modelling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>FRET activity assays and Maldi-TOF spectrometry indicated that CgACE is a functional dipeptidyl-carboxypeptidase which is active on Angiotensin I and sensitive to ACE inhibitors and chloride ion concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Immunocytochemistry revealed that, as its human counterpart, recombinant CgACE is synthesised as a transmembrane enzyme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>RT-qPCR, in-situ hybridization and immunohistochemistry shed light on a tissue, and development stage, specific expression pattern for CgACE, which is increased in the gonad during spermatogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The use of ACE inhibitors in vivo indicates that the dipeptidase activity of CgACE is crucial for the oyster fertilization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Our study demonstrates that a transmembrane active ACE is present in the oyster Crassostrea gigas, and for the first time ascribes a functional role for ACE in Lophotrochozoans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Its biological function in reproduction is conserved from molluscs to humans, a finding of particular evolutionary interest especially since oysters represent the most important aquaculture resource worldwide. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE, dipeptidyl-peptidase A, kininase II, E.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>3.4.15.1, DCP1) belongs to the M2-metalloprotease family and acts as a zinc-dependent dipeptidyl carboxypeptidase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In mammals, two isoforms are transcribed from two alternate promoters within the ace-1 gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The somatic isoform (sACE) is a crucial regulator of blood pressure especially since it generates the vasopressor angiotensin II (Ang II) from angiotensin I (Ang I). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the testicular (germinal) ACE (tACE) is required for fertility (reviews in [1], [2]) The ace-1gene originates from the duplication of an ancestral gene possessing a unique active site-coding region [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Consequently, sACE possesses two domains (the N-domain and C-domain, respectively) displaying the highly conserved gluzincin motif HExxH-23(24)-E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>However, tACE possesses only one domain, corresponding to the C-terminal part of sACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The N- and C- domains have distinct enzymatic specificities with respect to substrates, inhibitors [4] and chloride ion dependence [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Crystal structures of both the human N domain [6] and tACE [7], [8] have shown their active site to be a narrow catalytic channel connecting two large cavities within helical ellipsoids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Human ACE enzymes possess a C-terminal transmembrane domain and are membrane-anchored isoforms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, ACE can be released from the cell surface by a post-translational shedding [9]–[12], which can influence the biological role of ACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>An ACE homologue, ACE2, has also been characterized in humans [13], [14] and in mice [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>A great diversity of catalytically active ACE-related enzymes has been found outside Vertebrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In Ecdysozoans, ACE orthologues have been cloned in insects and crustaceans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, only single active site proteins, that are synthesised as soluble [16]–[18] as well as transmembrane [19] proteins, were described. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In the fruit fly Drosophila melanogaster, two homologous enzymes, AnCE [20] and Race [16] show about 40% amino-acid sequence identities with vertebrate ACEs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>They also share similar enzymatic properties [21], yet their precise biochemical behaviour displays slight differences which are explained by structure/activity comparisons [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Moreover, active ACE orthologues in arthropods hydrolyse a broad range of substrates, and play a key role in reproduction [23]–[25], and development [26]–[28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the ecdysozoan worm C. elegans possesses an ACE orthologue, ACN-1, with a role in development despite lacking an ACE-like proteolytic activity [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>More distant in the evolution, a lophotrochozoan ACE protein was characterized in the leech which is related to the N-domain mammalian ACE [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>However, its biological role is unknown despite molecular data suggesting a function in digestion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>ACE is extremely conserved during animal evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Indeed, a functional soluble ACE orthologue is already present in the prokaryote Xanthomonnas axonopodis pv citri which is expressed in the bacterial periplasmic space [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, to our knowledge, all the attempts to address biological functions of ACE outside of Vertebrates and Ecdysozoa have been unsuccessful. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Thus, these roles remain unknown despite such issues being fundamental in the understanding of both ACE evolution and physiology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The pacific oyster Crassostrea gigas is a bivalve mollusc belonging to the Lophotrochozoa, a distant evolutionary group which remains extremely poorly described with respect to Ecdysozoa despite being its sister clade among protostomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, C. gigas is the most important aquaculture resource worldwide (FAO, 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is emerging as a model species, leading to the generation of a great amount of genomic expression data [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, a partial cDNA sequence displaying similarity with ACE was identified within an EST library from gonads and early development stages of C. gigas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>In order to gain more insight into ACE evolution and to investigate its putative activity and biological function in lophotrochozoans, we report the cloning and functional characterization of CgACE, the oyster ACE orthologue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The cDNA of CgACE was cloned and recombinant CgACE expressed in CHO cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>FRET assays and Maldi-TOF spectrometry were used to characterize CgACE activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>A homology-based model of CgACE was generated, and expression levels and localizations of the CgACE mRNA and protein were examined. C. gigas fecundations were also carried out in the presence of ACE inhibitors to address a putative biological function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, this study shows the first evidence of a biological role of ACE outside of vertebrates and ecdysozoa. CgACE is also the first molluscan ACE-like enzyme ever characterised. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Adult two-year old Crassostrea gigas specimens were purchased from an oyster farm (Blainville, Manche, France). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Embryos, Larvae and spat were obtained at the IFREMER experimental hatchery (Argenton, France) [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Reproductive stage and sex were histologically determined as follows: stage 0 (sexual resting stage), male and female stage I (gonial multiplication stage), stage II (gametes maturation) and stage III (sexual maturity) [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>5′-RACE PCR and primer walking </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>In silico analysis within the ‘Gigasdatabase’ oyster Crassostrea gigas EST database [32] revealed that three sequences produce significant homologies with the Angiotensin-converting enzyme (GenBank Accession numbers: CU989003, CU992640 and FP010921). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>These sequences were used to design oligonucleotides which were used downstream in 5′-RACE and primer walking strategies for the characterisation of the whole sequence of the ACE orthologue in C. gigas, named CgACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Five prime rapid amplification of cDNA ends (5′-RACE) was performed on spat cDNA (Generacer kit, Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Primer walking was conducted using the cDNA library plasmid as template, as previously described [30] (primers sequences and reaction conditions available upon request). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The whole protein sequence of the CgACE protein (Genbank accession number JN382542) was submitted to multiple sequence alignment with the ClustalW2 algorithm [35] (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk">www.ebi.ac.uk</ext-link>) using the Gonnet matrix (parameters: gap open: 10; gap extension: 0,2; gap distance: 5; no end gap penalty; no iteration; numiter: 1; clustering method: neighbour-joining). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The alignment file was used to generate a tree file with the neighbour-joining method using the Quicktree program v1.1 [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Based on this tree file, an unrooted tree diagram was plotted with the PHYLIP 3.67 Drawtree software [37] (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mobyle.pasteur.fr">http://mobyle.pasteur.fr</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Molecular characterisation and expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The full-length CgACE cDNA was amplified by PCR (primers: CgACEflS5 5′- CAC CTT AAC AAA CCA GAG AAG AGA AAG TCG AGG TG – 3′ and CgACEflAS1 5′- TAA ACA TGC CCG TTC CCA ATT TAT CCC TGC T -3′), subcloned into the pcDNA3.1 vector (Invitrogen) and sequenced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The obtained pCgACE plasmid was then co-transfected with pRL4-TK or pAcGFP (Promega) (9∶1) in CHO-K1 cells (ATCC n° CCL-61) using lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Cells were incubated for 24 to 48 h then assayed for ACE expression and activity (see below). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>For negative and positive controls, cells were respectively transfected using the empty vector (pcDNA3.1, mock), or a plasmid encoding the human wild-type sACE (pHswtACE, kindly provided by Annie Michaud, INSERM U883, College de France) in the same conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Renilla luciferase or GFP measurements were used to compensate for transfection efficiencies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>RT-qPCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Total mRNA was isolated from dissected organs (4 pools of 6 animals), spat after shell was removed, larvae or embryos as previously described [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Briefly, samples were extracted using Tri-Reagent (Sigma), then RNA were purified using affinity chromatography (Nucleospin RNA II kit, Macherey-Nagel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>After digestion of genomic DNA with 1 U RQ1 DNAse (Promega) for 30 minutes to prevent genomic DNA contamination, 250 ng of total RNA were reverse-transcribed using 200 U of M-MLV RT (Promega) and 100 ng random hexamers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Resulting cDNAs were diluted and the equivalent amount of 5 ng of starting RNA was assayed for CgACE expression using actin (Genbank accession number: AF026063) and elongation-factor alpha (Genbank accession number: BAD15289) transcripts as reference genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>SYBR-green quantitative PCR was realised on an iCycler iQ© apparatus (Bio-Rad). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Absolute Blue SYBRgreen Supermix (ThermoScientific) was used in 40 cycles (95°C/15 s, 60°C/15 s) reactions with the following primers: CgACE-F1 (5′-CAAGTGGAGATGGAGGGTGT-3′) and CgACE-R1 (5′-AACAGGAGGAGGTCACTTCCTT-3′); QaActin: (5′-CGTTGCCAATGGTGATG-3′) and QsActin (5′-GCCCTGGACTTCGAACAA-3′); or Qs-Cg-EF (5′-ACCACCCTGGTGAGATCAAG-3′) and Qa-Cg-EF (5′-ACGACGATCGCATTTCTCTT-3′) as sense and antisense primers respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Accurate amplification of the target amplicon was checked by performing a melting curve and an end-point agarose gel electrophoresis followed by ethidium bromide staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>A parallel amplification of reference genes was carried out to normalize the expression data of CgACE transcript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The relative level of CgACE expression was calculated for one copy of the reference gene by using the following formula: N = 2(Ct Ref gene−Ct CgACE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Water was used instead of cDNA as a negative control for amplification, and DNAse-untreated cDNA was used to check for absence of genomic DNA contamination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>All samples were analysed in triplicate to establish the mRNA expression profile of CgACE. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Protein extraction and fractionation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Tissues or cell pellets were homogenized in ACE homogenization buffer (50 mmol.L−1 HEPES, 150 mmol.L−1 NaCl, 25 µmol.L−1 ZnSO4, 1 mmol.L−1 PMSF, 0,5% v/v CHAPS, pH = 6.5) and centrifuged (10000 g for 20 min. at 4°C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Cell culture media were harvested and concentrated when required on YM-100 and YM-10 centricon columns (Millipore). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Supernatants containing total proteins and media were aliquoted and stored at −80°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Cell proteins were fractionated as previously described [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Briefly, transfected cells (75 cm2 flasks) were scraped in homogenisation buffer (HB; 20 mmol.L−1 Tris–HCl pH = 7.2, 1 mmol.L−1 EDTA, 250 mmol.L−1 sucrose, 0,1 mmol.L−1 PMSF, 2 mmol.L−1 benzamidine), then centrifuged (1000 g, 5 min, 4°C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Supernatant was discarded and pellet was homogenised in 400 µL HB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The suspension was then ultracentrifuged at 100000 g for 1 h at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was harvested (soluble fraction of cell proteins) and the pellet was washed with 1 ml HB, then resuspended in 400 µL HB (membrane fraction of cell proteins). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Protein concentrations were determined using the Bradford method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>For clarity, these protein extracts are termed in this study ‘recombinant CgACE’ and ‘recombinant HswtACE’. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Immunological detection of CgACE </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>All immunological detections were performed using the sheep HKCE antiserum (kindly provided by Annie Michaud, INSERM U883, Collège de France, [31]) (dilutions: 1/5000 for immunocytochemistry, western blot and slot-blot; 1/1200 for immunohistochemistry). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Anti-sheep IgG coupled to FITC (1/100, immunocytochemistry and slot-blot), alkaline phosphatase (1/300 immunohistochemistry) or horseradish peroxydase (1/200, western blot) were used as secondary antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Western and slot-blots were carried out on 20 to 50 µg proteins, as previously described [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Slot-blot membranes were analysed for fluorescence signal using a ProXpress scanner (Perkin Elmer). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>For immunocytochemistry, CHO-K1 cells were cultured on coverslips then transfected (see above). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Cells were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for 10 minutes at 4°C then rinsed twice with ice-cold PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>All incubations were performed at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Coverslips were mounted using DAPI containing mounting media and slides were observed under a confocal microscope (Olympus). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>For immunohistochemistry, oyster gonad samples (male and female stages I, II and III) were embedded in paraffin and serial 5 µm-sections deposited on poly-L-lysin slides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>After paraffin removal and rehydration, slides were treated with hydrogen peroxide (0,3%) and saponin (0,05%) for antigen unmasking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The primary antibody was incubated overnight at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The secondary antibody was added for 1 hour at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Controls were realised on the same slides but omitting either the primary or the secondary antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Slides were histologically counter-stained using light green. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>ACE activity assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Protein samples from total and/or fractionated extractions were assayed for ACE activity as follows: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s2h1"><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>FRET activity assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>CgACE hydrolysis of the human somatic ACE fluorogenic substrate Abz-FRK(Dnp)P-OH (Bachem) was determined in standard conditions as described previously [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Briefly, protein samples were incubated in activity buffer (140 mmol.L−1 NaCl, 5 mmol.L−1 KCl, 0,1 mmol.L−1 CaCl2, 0,63 mmol.L−1 MgSO4, 1 mmol.L−1 NaH2PO4, 6,1 mmol.L−1 glucose, 10 µmol.L−1 ZnSO4), in the presence or absence of ACE inhibitors (1.10−6 mol.L−1 Captopril (Sigma), Lisinopril or Fosinoprilat (kindly provided by Annie Michaud, INSERM U883, College de France)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>FRK substrate (1.10−5 mol.L−1) was added and reactions were incubated for 1 to 2 hours at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Negative and positive controls were realised using pcDNA3.1- or pHswtACE-transfected cells extracts, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2h2"><title><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Influence of chloride ion concentration on HHL hydrolysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>A fluorescent assay was used to determine whether CgACE activity on the substrate hippuryl-histidyl-leucine (HHL) was sensitive to chloride ions concentration, using the procedure described previously [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Briefly, serum-free CgACE-transfected-cell culture medium were concentrated and desalted by diafiltration on cellulose columns (Millipore) and 7,5 µL of desalted concentrate were incubated in the presence of 5,7 mmol.L−1 HHL in potassium phosphate buffer containing increasing NaCl concentrations (from 0 to 1 mol.L−1) for 30 minutes at 37° C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Reactions were stopped by the addition of NaOH (final concentration: 0,25 mol.L−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The presence of HL product at the end of the reaction was measured by the addition of α-phtaldialdehyde. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Fluorescence development was stopped after 10 minutes by hydrochloride (final concentration: 0,3 mol.L−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Fluorescence was measured at excitation 360 nm and emission 485 nm (Berthold Mithras 940 LE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Activity negative controls and fluorescence blanks were realized for each NaCl concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Specificity of the reaction was controlled by pre-incubations in the presence of ACE inhibitors (captopril, lisinopril and fosinoprilat at 1.10−6 mol.L−1 each for 15 minutes at room temperature), and by parallel assays using 7,5 and 5 µL of concentrated pcDNA3.1- or pHswtACE-transfected cell culture medium, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2h3"><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Mass spectrometry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>CgACE was assayed for angiotensin I hydrolysis as described above, except that human angiotensin I (Sigma) was used instead of FRK as a substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The presence of angiotensin II at the end of the reaction was assayed using maldi/TOF-TOF mass spectrometry (MS) (AB Sciex 5800 proteomics analyzer, TOF/TOF ion optics and OptiBeam™ on-axis laser irradiation, 1000 Hz repetition rate). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The system was calibrated immediately before analysis with a mixture of des-Arg-Bradykinin, Angiotensin I, Glu1-Fibrinopeptide B, ACTH (18–39), ACTH (7–38) (mass precision better than 5 ppm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Reaction solutions were mixed with CHCA matrix/50% ACN, 0.1% TFA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>MS and MS/MS spectra were acquired in the positive reflector mode by summarizing 1000 single spectra (5×200, laser intensity 3000) in the mass range from 600 to 2000 Da and both m/z 1297 (Angiotensin I) and m/z 1046.7 (Angiotensin II), respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s2i"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Molecular modelling of CgACE </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>A model of CgACE was generated using testis ACE (ProteinDataBank pdb code 1O8A) as a template as previously described [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The CgACE sequence was submitted to the Esypred3D server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fundp.ac.be/sciences/biologie/urbm/bioinfo/esypred/">http://www.fundp.ac.be/sciences/biologie/urbm/bioinfo/esypred/</ext-link>) and alignments were obtained by combining, weighting and screening the results of several multiple alignment programs following the procedure described in [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Model comparisons were realized using the program DeepView [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Figures were generated with Pymol [45]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>In situ hybridization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>A 856 pb fragment corresponding to the 3′-end of the CgACE cDNA, was amplified by PCR, subcloned into the pCRII vector (Invitrogen) and sequenced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The obtained plasmid was then linearized using NotI or EcoRI in separate reactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The linearized product was resolved on agarose-gel electrophoresis stained with ethidium bromide and purified by affinity chromatography (Wizard SV gel purification, Promega). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>These products were used to generate sense and antisense CgACE digoxygenin-labelled riboprobes using SP6 and T7 RNA polymerases, respectively, and digoxygenin-dUTP (SP6/T7 RNA labelling kit, Roche). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Paraffin-embedded tissues were cut (3 µm thick) and mounted on superfrost slides (VWR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Slides were deparaffined, rehydrated and hybridized overnight at 56°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>After extensive wash, digoxygenin-labelled hybridized probes were detected using an anti-digoxygenin alkaline-phosphatase antibody (Roche) and NBT-BCIP substrate (Sigma). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2k"><title><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Fecundation assays in the presence of ACE inhibitors </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Broodstock Crassostrea gigas specimens were purchased from an oyster farm in Guernsey (Guernsey, GB) or obtained in the IFREMER experimental hatchery (Argenton, France). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Gonads were scarified and gametes were filtered on a 100 µm mesh for the removal of large debris. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>For females, oocytes (oo) were harvested as the remaining fraction on a 30 µm mesh; for males, spermatozoa (spz) were harvested as the passing fraction on a 30 µm mesh. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Spermatozoa were pre-incubated in filtered-sterile (0,22 µM) seawater (FSW) alone or in the presence of 10−8 to 10−3 mol.L−1 ACE inhibitors for 10 minutes at 25°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Fertilizations were triggered by the addition of oocytes and were carried out in oxygenated FSW at 25°C (500 oo.L−1; ca. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>100 spz/oo). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Fertilization rates were determined as the number of at least two cell embryos within the total egg number after 2 hours. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2l"><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>All the results are given as the mean +/− s.e.m. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>(standard error to the mean) of at least triplicate experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The results were analysed for statistical significance using two tailed Student's t test, one-way or two-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni's post-hoc test. p&lt;0.05 was considered significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Data were analysed using the Graphpad Prism software version 5.0. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Molecular characterisation of CgACE </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The cloning strategies allowed the characterization of a ∼2 kb cDNA exhibiting an in-frame 5′ stop codon, a 1896 base pairs coding sequence and a conserved polyadenylation signal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The aforementioned Crassostrea gigas Angiotensin-I converting enzyme cDNA sequence, named CgACE, was deposited in the Genbank database with the accession number JN382542. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>After signal peptide cleavage (A19/R20), the mature CgACE is predicted to be a 613 residues protein bearing a single conserved gluzincin motif HHEMGH(24)E starting at position 369, and a putative C-terminal transmembrane anchor (A506 to Y524) (Figure 1A and Supplementary Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Western blot of CgACE displays a single band slightly higher than 75 kDa, in line with the theoretical prediction of 74 kDa when considering putative post-translational modifications such as glycosylation (T136, T350, S425) (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Reminiscent of its human sACE counterpart, recombinant CgACE protein (Figure 1D) and ACE activity (see below) (Figure 1E) were detected not only within membrane protein fraction, but also within the soluble fraction and in the culture medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, recombinant CgACE and HswtACE exhibit a similar cell distribution (Figure 1F) when expressed in CHO-K1 cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0027833-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027833.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Molecular characterization of CgACE. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>A: schematic representation of the CgACE protein primary sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>B: unrooted tree diagram showing the evolutionary relationship between human (tACE, Ndom, ACE2), fly (AnCE, ACEr), C. elegans (ACN-1), leech (TtACE), leishmania (LdDCP), bacteria (XcACE) and oyster (CgACE) ACE orthologues (see Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>C: western blot; MW, molecular weight marker; Cg, recombinant CgACE; Hs, recombinant human wild-type sACE, pcDNA3.1, protein extract from mock-transfected cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>D: Slot blot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The subcellular origin of proteins analysed (Med, culture medium; Sol, soluble fraction of cell proteins; Mb, membrane fraction of cell proteins) is indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>E: ACE activity in cell fractions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The rate of FRK fluorigenic substrate hydrolysis by recombinant CgACE and HswtACE and the origin of protein extracts are indicated. **: p&lt;0.01, ***: p&lt;0.001, two way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni's post hoc test, vs pcDNA3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>F: immunocytochemistry of cells transfected with pcDNA3.1 (left), pCgACE (middle) or pHswtACE (right). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Blue signal indicates nucleus (DAPI) and green signal indicates ACE detection (FITC) (see methods). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027833.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic position </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>CgACE exhibits significant similarity with other functional ACEs throughout the animal kingdom, but little if any with the inactive Caenorhabditis ACN-1 orthologue (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Concerning evolutionary position, CgACE clusters between the drosophila (AnCE and ACEr) and the bacterial orthologues, despite showing a greater similarity with the human and leech enzymes (Figure 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>This result is obtained regardless of the score matrix used for sequence alignments (Gonnet or BLOSUM, respectively, data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0027833-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027833.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Similarity between ACE-like proteins throughout the animal kingdom. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0027833-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0027833.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>tACE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Ndom </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>ACE2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>AnCE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>ACEr </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>ACN-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>TtACE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>XcACE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>LdDCP </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>tACE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Ndom </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>51 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>ACE2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>39 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>39 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>AnCE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>43 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>39 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>35 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>ACEr </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>38 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>36 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>34 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>49 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>ACN-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>TtACE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>45 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>45 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>38 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>39 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>36 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>XcACE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>34 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>36 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>33 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>30 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>30 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>33 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>LdDCP </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Cg ACE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>41 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>38 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>34 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>34 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>35 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>38 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>33 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>The homology is given as a score representing the percentage of identity between proteins as given by the Gonnet matrix (see methods); tACE, human tACE (GI: 23238214); Ndom, human sACE N-domain (GI: 113045 residues 1–612); ACE2, human ACE2 (GI: 42543475); AnCE, Drosophila melanogaster ACE (GI: 10728771); ACEr, Drosophila melanogaster ACE-related (GI: 17137262); ACN-1, Caenorhabditis elegans non-peptidase ACE (GI: 71985293); TtACE, leech Theromyzon tessulatum ACE (GI: 45272589); XcACE, Xanthomonas axonopodis pv.citri ACE (GI: 21241971); LdDCP, Leishmania donovani dicarboxypeptidase (GI: 56130986); CgACE: Crassostrea gigas ACE (Genbank accession number: JN382542). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Biochemical characterisation of CgACE </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Maldi-TOF mass spectrometry indicates that CgACE cleaves a C-terminal dipeptide from angiotensin I and therefore generates angiotensin II (Figure 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the MS/MS data obtained from synthetic AngII on the one hand, and from the 1046 m/z peptide resulting from AngI hydrolysis by CgACE on the other hand, indicates that both peptides present the same sequence (DRVYIHPF) (Supplementary Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>In addition, CgACE is able to hydrolyse a specific ACE substrate, i.e. Abz-FRK(Dnp)P-OH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>In line with what was observed for AngI hydrolysis, this activity is significantly reduced in the presence of specific ACE inhibitors such as captopril, lisinopril and fosinoprilat (figure 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, in the reaction conditions used herein, these inhibitors are less potent for CgACE than for the human ACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Indeed, micromolar concentrations decrease CgACE activity by ca. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>40 to 50% instead of 90 to 95% in human tACE (Figure 2B). CgACE is also able to hydrolyze the HHL substrate. CgACE activity on HHL is sensitive to chloride ion concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the enzyme displays maximum activity for concentrations around 0,05 mol.L−1 and exhibits only little activity (ca. ∼15% of maximum activity) for concentrations above 0,5 mol.L−1 (Figure 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>In this regard, CgACE exhibits similar characteristics to the N-domain of human sACE when compared to the C-domain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0027833-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027833.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Biochemical characterization of CgACE. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>A: MS spectra of human Angiotensin I hydrolysates after incubation with protein extracts from pcDNA3.1-transfected cells (top) and recombinant CgACE (bottom). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Peptide and peak masses (m/z), relative intensity (left Y axis) and signal intensity (right Y axis) are indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>The 550–1500 and 1000–1100 m/z ranges are represented using different magnifications for clarity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>AngI: angiotensin I, AngII: angiotensin II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>The peptide sequence of angiotensin I is given, the arrowhead indicates the cleavage site leading to angiotensin II formation. B: Influence of 10−6 mol.L−1 ACE inhibitors on FRK hydrolysis by protein extracts from cells transfected with the vector backbone (pcDNA3.1), pCgACE or pHswtACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>The inhibitors used and their concentrations are indicated. **: p&lt;0.01, ***: p&lt;0.001, one way ANOVA followed by Dunnett's post hoc test, vs no inhibitor. C: influence of chloride ion concentration on HHL hydrolysis by CgACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>The p value for one way ANOVA of chloride concentration influence on CgACE activity is given. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027833.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Homology model of CgACE </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>As the crystal structures of the human ACE [6], [7], ACE2 [46] and Drosophila AnCE [47] all display the same fold, a structural model was generated to understand the interactions of residues in the active site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>The pair-wise alignment of human tACE and oyster CgACE sequences revealed a 41% sequence identity that allowed us to confidently model the overall fold of CgACE based on the tACE structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>The homology modeling indicates that CgACE would closely resemble the human tACE in terms of overall conformation (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>The primary structure of CgACE includes all the residues implied in zinc (H369, H373 and E397), lisinopril (H339, A340, E370, K501, H503, Y510 and Y513) and captopril (Q226, K501, Y510, H339, H503 and Y513) binding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the structural model indicates that the catalytic channel of CgACE would be narrower than the human tACE active site (Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0027833-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027833.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Molecular modelling of CgACE. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Comparison between the CgACE model (left) and the human tACE structure (right). A: Ribbon representation of the overall conformation of the mature proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>The active site is indicated (black asterisk). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Spectrum colours indicate the position within the protein sequence from the N-terminal (blue) to the C-terminal (red) ends. B: Comparison of the active site between CgACE and tACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>ACE is represented as a surface with the positive charge indicated in blue and the negative in red. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Lisinopril (in yellow) is shown to orientate the active site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Magnified views of the catalytic channel region are represented (top view with lysyl binding pocket down, upper panel; front view from the lysyl binding pocket, bottom panel). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027833.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>In vivo Expression and activity of CgACE </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>The CgACE transcript shows little if any expression within adult tissues, except in the digestive tract (labial palps, digestive gland) and the gills. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Similar expression levels are detected within the development stages of the oyster. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>In contrast, RT-qPCR reveals that the CgACE messenger RNA displays a dramatic increase in the gonadal area along with the spermatogenesis and spermiogenesis, but no significant change during female gametogenesis (Figure 4A). In situ hybridization indicates that the CgACE mRNA is highly expressed in the germinal compartment of the gonad; i.e. mostly spermatogonia, spermatocytes I and spermatocytes II (Figure 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>No specific signal could be detected within female gonads (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Consistently, a great specific ACE activity was found in sperm protein extracts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, little specific ACE activity could be detected within stripped oocyte protein extracts (Figure 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The CgACE protein was present within the gonadic tubules of male oysters (Figure 5B), while no specific signal could be detected within the female gonadal area (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0027833-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027833.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>mRNA expression of CgACE. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>A: Relative CgACE mRNA expression levels in adult tissues (upper left panel), development stages (upper right) and gametogenesis (bottom). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>The expression level and reference genes are indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>The bottom diagram represents the sexual maturation. ***: p&lt;0.001, two-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni's post hoc test. B: CgACE in situ hybridization in adult oysters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>S, sense riboprobe; AS, antisense riboprobe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>The magnification (100×, 400×) and the sexual maturation stage (I, II and III) are indicated; g.t., gonadic tubule; r.t. , reserve tissue ; d.l., digestive lumen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Arrowheads indicate typical signal localization. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027833.g004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0027833-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027833.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>ACE activity in gametes and protein expression in gonads of C. gigas. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>A: FRK fluorigenic substrate hydrolysis by protein extracts from oyster gametes in the absence (no inhibitor) or the presence of 5.10−5 mol.L−1 captopril. B: Immunohistochemistry of CgACE in adult oysters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>The corresponding control slides (top pictures, no primary antibody) are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>The sexual maturation stage (I, II and III) is indicated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027833.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3f"><title><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Biological function of CgACE </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>All the inhibitors induced a dose-dependent decrease in the fecundation rate (p&lt;0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>The IC50 values are ca. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>5.10−6, 5.10−5 and 5.10−3 mol.L−1 for lisinopril, fosinoprilat and captopril, respectively, indicating that the enzymatic activity of CgACE is crucial for fertility in C. gigas (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0027833-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027833.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Influence of ACE inhibitors on C. gigas fecundation. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Dose-response fertilization assays in the presence of ACE inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>The fecundation efficiency is given as the percentage of segmented eggs relative to controls two hours after oocytes and sperm were mixed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>The inhibitors (captopril, lisinorpil and fosinoprilat) and concentrations used (x axis) are indicated. ***: p&lt;0.0001, two-way ANOVA, effect of concentration for each inhibitor. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027833.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>This study presents the characterization of a functional angiotensin-converting enzyme orthologue in the oyster Crassostrea gigas, termed CgACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>This work describes the cloning, expression, structural modelling, function and biological characterization of the enzyme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, CgACE is not only the first ACE orthologue characterized in molluscs, but also the first to be given a biological function outside Vertebrates and Ecdysozoans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>The oyster enzyme characterization may help to answer numerous questions that remain unclear, such as functional issues along with ACE evolution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>The oyster ACE orthologue, CgACE, resembles the human germinal isoform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>As revealed by western blotting, the molecular weight of the mature protein is consistent with the in silico predictions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Futhermore, it also correlates the actual size of single active site ACE-like enzymes found from Insects up to Mammals. CgACE bears a unique active site and retains all the residues supporting both the catalytic activity and the interactions with inhibitors such as captopril and lisinopril (see results). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>These observations are in line with the finding that CgACE exhibits an ACE-like activity which is sensitive to ACE inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, recombinant CgACE hydrolyses synthetic Angiotensin I and FRK peptides far less efficiently than the recombinant HswtACE, even when taking the number of active sites into account. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>However, the homology modelling clearly indicates that CgACE displays a wider catalytic channel than the human tACE, suggesting more permissive biochemical behaviour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Such a conformation of the active site, where substrates/inhibitors would ‘loosely’ fit, also probably explains why the classical ACE inhibitors seem less potent on recombinant oyster ACE than on human ACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Indeed, despite captopril, lisinopril and fosinoprilat efficiently prevent CgACE activity on FRK peptide at low concentrations (i.e. 10−5 mol.L−1), such an inhibition is less potent than for the human recombinant protein extract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Similarly, in the presence of 10−6 mol.L−1 captopril, angiotensin II was detected by mass spectrometry after angiotensin I hydrolysis by recombinant CgACE, but not by recombinant HswtACE (data not shown), indicating that the inhibition of CgACE is somehow incomplete. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, and because three different peptides are in vitro substrates for CgACE, it is not excluded that the enzyme may hydrolyse a wide range of substrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, one should keep in mind that the biochemical data herein originates from unpurified recombinant oyster ACE expressed in mammalian cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Such methodology was widely demonstrated to be robust enough to assess the protease activity of recombinant ACE-like enzymes [4], [30], [31], [48], but may not adequately reflect the precise and specific biochemistry features of the native CgACE, which were not investigated further. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Such an explanation might also hold true for the N- or C-domain specificity of inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Indeed, both captopril and lisinopril are able to inhibit CgACE activity on the FRK substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>The ‘N-domain-like’ influence of chloride ion concentration on HHL hydrolysis suggests that CgACE may resemble the N-domain of mammalian sACE, and this despite showing a higher similarity with tACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>This finding is in line with what was observed for TtACE in the leech, also belonging to Lophotrochozoans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>In contrast with the chloride concentration influence, phylogenetic analyses do not indicate that the oyster and leech ACE ortholgues are closely related to one another. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Indeed, drosophila ACEs intercalate between them, and CgACE appears close to the bacterial XcACE, whereas TtACE clusters with vertebrate isoforms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Because both leeches and oysters belong to the Lophotrochozoa, such an observation might reflect complex evolutionary relationships between annelids and molluscs, and may also involve the specific parasitic trait of leeches, as discussed elsewhere [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Besides, the finding of a unique catalytic region within CgACE, and more generally within all lophotrochozoan ACE-like enzymes described to date [30], seems consistent with the late occurrence of genome duplication during the course of animal evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Indeed, this duplication occurred far after the Protostomes-Deuterostomes divergence and is widely admitted to explain the presence of two active site ACE-coding sequences in vertebrate genomes, such as the human ace-1 gene [3]. In silico hydrophobicity predictions indicate the presence of a transmembrane domain in the carboxy-terminal region of the mature oyster ACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, membrane fractions of cells expressing CgACE exhibit ACE activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>In addition, though such information should be carefully interpreted, cells expressing the transmembrane human wild-type somatic ACE, and cells expressing CgACE, display similar ACE immunoreactivity suggesting similar recombinant protein localizations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Altogether, these results indicate that, very surprisingly, CgACE possesses a C-terminal transmembrane anchor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, CgACE is the first transmembrane ACE-like enzyme ever characterized outside of vertebrates and ecdysozoans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Besides, ACE activity is also found in the soluble fractions and culture media of transfected cells as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Moreover, CgACE and tACE display high similarity within the stalk region lying upstream from the transmembrane domain (see Supplementary Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Consequently the oyster enzyme, like its human counterpart, putatively undergoes post-translational shedding that would release soluble recombinant CgACE from the CHO cells membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>However, because the presence of an ACE-secretase in oysters is not demonstrated, the biological significance of such phenomenon remains elusive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the oyster ACE displays a C-terminal transmembrane anchor, indicating that the appearance of this feature within ACE could lye before the Bilaterians division, and thus be more ancient than what was previously hypothesized [31]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Oysters are seawater organisms that lack a closed circulatory system and therefore do not display blood pressure regulation issues like Mammals do. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Regardless of this point, the presence of ACE in oysters is consistent with the presence of ACE orthologues throughout the animal kingdom [30], [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>However, the biological function(s) of such orthologues has never been addressed outside Vertebrates and Ecdysozoans, despite being of interest for the understanding of the evolution of enzyme/substrates systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>The absence of a model species with highly developed molecular and functional tools in Lophotrochozoans, and the great diversity of organisms within this group are certainly participating in such a poor understanding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>However, RT-qPCR and in situ hybridization experiments reveal that, within somatic tissues, the highest CgACE expression levels are observed in the oyster's digestive tract, i.e. labial palps, gills and digestive gland. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>This expression pattern likely reflects a digestive and unspecialized role of the enzyme, like already speculated for ACE orthologues in all the other metazoan organisms in which ACE expression was examined [31], [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Consistently, the greatest amounts of CgACE mRNA during oyster development are observed just before the metamorphosis when the animals undergo morpho-physiological changes implicating a degradation of many cell proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>However, very interestingly, the main site of CgACE mRNA and protein synthesis appears to be the germinal compartment within the gonadal area, but only in male oysters. CgACE mRNA levels dramatically increase in the male germinal tract along with spermatogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>These mRNAs are likely synthesized in the germinal cells because spermatogonia, spermatocytes I and spermatocytes II display strong labelling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>In contrast, spermatids and mature spermatozoids exhibit little if any signal, in line with their low and selective transcriptional activity (for review see [50], [51]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Because the number of germinal cells increases during sexual maturation, the increasing amounts of CgACE transcripts likely originate in the growing number of germinal cells expressing stable levels of CgACE mRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, because the whole gonadal area was assayed in RT-qPCR, an increase in the individual CgACE transcription within each germinal cell cannot be excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Besides, the transfer of mature transmembrane enzymes has, to the best of our awareness, never been demonstrated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the ‘Sertoli-like’ intra-tubular somatic cells are unlikely to synthesize CgACE, though (i) in situ results cannot strictly rule out such expression, and (ii) a feeder role is presumed for those cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Immunolocalisation strongly correlates with this mRNA expression pattern, since the CgACE protein seems to be present within the gonadic tubules from early (stage I) to late stages (spermatozoids) of male gametogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a strong specific ACE activity is found in oyster sperm protein extracts, indicating that the mature enzyme accumulates into spermatozoids, but not into the surrounding fluid, in contrast with what was observed in the crayfish [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, non negligible levels of ACE activity were also found in oocyte protein extracts, whereas both oocytes and the female gonadal area hardly transcribe CgACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Such activity could come from solubilised digestive ACE which would then accumulate in the developing ovary and help generate peptides for vitellogenesis, mimicking the situation already observed in the mosquito [25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>A finding of interest lies in the assessment of the biological function of CgACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Since ACE inhibitors are active on CgACE, they were used as functional tools in oyster fecundation assays, resulting in a dramatic and dose-dependent decrease in the fertilization rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Most of this effect should be attributed to the inhibition of sperm ACE activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the very little ACE activity within mature oocytes is unlikely to be significant in this context. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Because captopril, lisinopril and fosinoprilat are efficient on both recombinant CgACE and oyster sperm extracts, our results indicate that the peptidase activity of CgACE is crucial for fertilization in oysters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Even though high inhibitor concentrations could not totally prevent eggs fertilization (∼10 to 20% of the oocytes still undergo cleavage whatever the concentrations used), their effect is highly potent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Captopril displays a higher IC50 but its effect is harder to make clear because of the presence of thiol groups which could (i) compromise the molecular stability in sea water and (ii) become toxic for embryo cleavage at high concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, because human ACE inhibitors do not completely block CgACE activity in all the reaction conditions we assayed, one could argue that a fully potent specific CgACE inhibitor could completely block oyster fecundation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Besides, the presence of another oyster ACE-like orthologue cannot be excluded, which would be little if at all sensitive to the inhibitors we used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Such concerns could be addressed when the oyster genome becomes available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, or in addition, other proteases than CgACE, that were not investigated, could also exist and exhibit similar functions, such as mouse ACR and PRSS21 serine protease orthologues [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>The latter explanation seems more straightforward because such a basic and required process as the fecundation ability is likely to be rescued by compensatory mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, expressed sequence tags presenting strong similarities with these two proteins exist within oyster libraries (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, IC50 values for lisinopril and captopril show evidence of the critical importance of CgACE, in a similar fashion to that of the human germinal ACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of the protease activity strongly suggests that CgACE would be expressed at the spermatozoid surface, and could degrade proteins of the chorionic membrane in order to help the male pronucleus penetrate the oocyte cytoplasm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, caution should be taken regarding this interpretation, because seawater chloride concentrations (c.a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>0,5 mol.L−1) are not optimal for recombinant CgACE activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>This may reflect the high physiological tolerance to freshwater of C. gigas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Otherwise, CgACE could exert additional physiological roles within the oyster extracellular compartment which we did not examine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Characterization of endogenous CgACE substrate(s) would clearly be of great help. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>However, many additional experiments are required in order to gain insights into these very interesting issues that lie beyond the focus of the present study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Taken together, our results show that oysters express a functional ACE orthologue bearing a unique active site, CgACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, CgACE displays a transmembrane anchor, accumulates in spermatozoids, and is critical for fecundation through its peptidase activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>To date, CgACE is the only ACE orthologue to be assigned a biological function outside Vertebrates and Ecdysozoans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>These findings not only help a better understanding of enzyme evolution, but also bring insights into the reproduction of the most important aquaculture resource worldwide. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0027833.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Multiple sequence alignment between  Cg ACE and other ACE-like proteins widespread the animal kingdom. The alignement was generated using the BLOSUM62 matrix; tACE, human tACE (GI: 23238214); Ndom, human sACE N-domain (GI: 113045 residues 1–612); ACE2, human ACE2 (GI: 42543475); AnCE, Drosophila melanogaster ACE (GI: 10728771); ACEr, Drosophila melanogaster ACE-related (GI: 17137262); ACN-1, Caenorhabditis elegans non-peptidase ACE (GI: 71985293); TtACE, leech Theromyzon tessulatum ACE (GI: 45272589); XcACE, Xanthomonas axonopodis pv.citri ACE (GI: 21241971); LdDCP, Leishmania donovani dicarboxypeptidase (GI: 56130986); CgACE: Crassostrea gigas ACE (Genbank accession number: JN382542). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>The similar (grey) and identical (black) residues between 80% of the sequences are shaded; the signal peptide cleavage site (↑), the gluzincin residues (A) and the putative transmembrane anchor (*) of CgACE are indicated below the alignment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>(DOC) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0027833.s001.doc"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0027833.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>MS/MS spectra of synthetic angiotensin II (A) and of the 1046 m/z peptide from hydrolysates of angiotensin I by  Cg ACE (B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>(DOC) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0027833.s002.doc"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>The authors are grateful to Dr Christophe Lelong (Caen, France) for scientific comments and Alan Semple (Dublin, Ireland) for critical reading of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Funding: This work was supported by grants from the French National Research Agency (ANR -08-GENM-041 “Gametogenes”), the European 7th Framework Program (FP7 ref 245119 “REPROSEED”) and the Regional Council of Basse-Normandie (France) (fifth research regional program and a doctoral grant to AF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0027833-Corvol1"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>1 CorvolPEyriesM 2004 Peptidyl dipeptidase A: angiotensin I converting enzyme. RawlingsMDWoessnerFJ Handbook of proteolytic enzymes London Academic Press 332 346  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Turner1"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>2 TurnerAJHooperNM 2002 The angiotensin-converting enzyme gene family: genomics and pharmacology. Trends Pharmacol Sci 23 177 183 11931993 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Hubert1"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>3 HubertCHouotAMCorvolPSoubrierF 1991 Structure of the angiotensin I-converting enzyme gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Two alternate promoters correspond to evolutionary steps of a duplicated gene. J Biol Chem 266 15377 15383 1651327 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Dive1"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>4 DiveVCottonJYiotakisAMichaudAVassiliouS 1999 RXP 407, a phosphinic peptide, is a potent inhibitor of angiotensin I converting enzyme able to differentiate between its two active sites. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 96 4330 4335 10200262 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Jaspard1"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>5 JaspardEWeiLAlhenc-GelasF 1993 Differences in the properties and enzymatic specificities of the two active sites of angiotensin I-converting enzyme (kininase II). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Studies with bradykinin and other natural peptides. J Biol Chem 268 9496 9503 7683654 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Corradi1"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>6 CorradiHRSchwagerSLNchindaATSturrockEDAcharyaKR 2006 Crystal structure of the N domain of human somatic angiotensin I-converting enzyme provides a structural basis for domain-specific inhibitor design. J Mol Biol 357 964 974 16476442 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Natesh1"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>7 NateshRSchwagerSLSturrockEDAcharyaKR 2003 Crystal structure of the human angiotensin-converting enzyme-lisinopril complex. Nature 421 551 554 12540854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Natesh2"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>8 NateshRSchwagerSLEvansHRSturrockEDAcharyaKR 2004 Structural details on the binding of antihypertensive drugs captopril and enalaprilat to human testicular angiotensin I-converting enzyme. Biochemistry 43 8718 8724 15236580 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Eyries1"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>9 EyriesMMichaudADeinumJAgrapartMChomilierJ 2001 Increased shedding of angiotensin-converting enzyme by a mutation identified in the stalk region. J Biol Chem 276 5525 5532 11076943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Oppong1"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>10 OppongSYHooperNM 1993 Characterization of a secretase activity which releases angiotensin-converting enzyme from the membrane. Biochem J 292 Pt 2 597 603 8389141 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Parkin1"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>11 ParkinETTrewAChristieGFallerAMayerR 2002 Structure-activity relationship of hydroxamate-based inhibitors on the secretases that cleave the amyloid precursor protein, angiotensin converting enzyme, CD23, and pro-tumor necrosis factor-alpha. Biochemistry 41 4972 4981 11939793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Parvathy1"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>12 ParvathySOppongSYKarranEHBuckleDRTurnerAJ 1997 Angiotensin-converting enzyme secretase is inhibited by zinc metalloprotease inhibitors and requires its substrate to be inserted in a lipid bilayer. Biochem J 327 Pt 1 37 43 9355732 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Donoghue1"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>13 DonoghueMHsiehFBaronasEGodboutKGosselinM 2000 A novel angiotensin-converting enzyme-related carboxypeptidase (ACE2) converts angiotensin I to angiotensin 1–9. Circ Res 87 E1 E9 10969042 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Tipnis1"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>14 TipnisSRHooperNMHydeRKarranEChristieG 2000 A human homolog of angiotensin-converting enzyme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Cloning and functional expression as a captopril-insensitive carboxypeptidase. J Biol Chem 275 33238 33243 10924499 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Komatsu1"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>15 KomatsuTSuzukiYImaiJSuganoSHidaM 2002 Molecular cloning, mRNA expression and chromosomal localization of mouse angiotensin-converting enzyme-related carboxypeptidase (mACE2). DNA Seq 13 217 220 12487024 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Tatei1"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>16 TateiKCaiHIpYTLevineM 1995 Race: a Drosophila homologue of the angiotensin converting enzyme. Mech Dev 51 157 168 7547464 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Taylor1"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>17 TaylorCACoatesDShirrasAD 1996 The Acer gene of Drosophila codes for an angiotensin-converting enzyme homologue. Gene 181 191 197 8973330 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Wijffels1"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>18 WijffelsGFitzgeraldCGoughJRidingGElvinC 1996 Cloning and characterisation of angiotensin-converting enzyme from the dipteran species, Haematobia irritans exigua, and its expression in the maturing male reproductive system. Eur J Biochem 237 414 423 8647080 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Simunic1"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>19 SimunicJSoyezDKamechN 2009 Characterization of a membrane-bound angiotensin-converting enzyme isoform in crayfish testis and evidence for its release into the seminal fluid. FEBS J 276 4727 4738 19656189 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Cornell1"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>20 CornellMJWilliamsTALamangoNSCoatesDCorvolP 1995 Cloning and expression of an evolutionary conserved single-domain angiotensin converting enzyme from Drosophila melanogaster. J Biol Chem 270 13613 13619 7775412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Coates1"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>21 CoatesDIsaacRECottonJSiviterRWilliamsTA 2000 Functional conservation of the active sites of human and Drosophila angiotensin I-converting enzyme. Biochemistry 39 8963 8969 10913309 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Bingham1"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>22 BinghamRJDiveVPhillipsSEVShirrasADIsaacRE 2006 Structural diversity of angiotensin-converting enzyme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Insights from structure-activity comparisons of two Drosophila enzymes. FEBS Journal 273 362 373 16403023 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Hurst1"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>23 HurstDRylettCMIsaacREShirrasAD 2003 The drosophila angiotensin-converting enzyme homologue Ance is required for spermiogenesis. Dev Biol 254 238 247 12591244 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Zhu1"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>24 ZhuWVandingenenAHuybrechtsRBaggermanGDe LoofA 2001 In vitro degradation of the Neb-Trypsin modulating oostatic factor (Neb-TMOF) in gut luminal content and hemolymph of the grey fleshfly, Neobellieria bullata. Insect Biochem Mol Biol 31 87 95 11102838 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Ekbote1"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>25 EkboteUCoatesDIsaacRE 1999 A mosquito (Anopheles stephensi) angiotensin I-converting enzyme (ACE) is induced by a blood meal and accumulates in the developing ovary. FEBS Lett 455 219 222 10437776 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Crackower1"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>26 CrackowerMASaraoROuditGYYagilCKozieradzkiI 2002 Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 is an essential regulator of heart function. Nature 417 822 828 12075344 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Quan1"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>27 QuanGXMitaKOkanoKShimadaTUgajinN 2001 Isolation and expression of the ecdysteroid-inducible angiotensin-converting enzyme-related gene in wing discs of Bombyx mori. Insect Biochem Mol Biol 31 97 103 11102839 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Donoghue2"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>28 DonoghueMHsiehFBaronasEGodboutKGosselinM 2000 A novel angiotensin-converting enzyme-related carboxypeptidase (ACE2) converts angiotensin I to angiotensin 1–9. Circ Res 87 E1 E9 10969042 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Brooks1"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>29 BrooksDRApplefordPJMurrayLIsaacRE 2003 An essential role in moulting and morphogenesis of Caenorhabditis elegans for ACN-1: a novel member of the angiotensin-converting enzyme family that lacks a metallopeptidase active site. J Biol Chem  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Riviere1"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>30 RiviereGMichaudADeloffreLVandenbulckeFLevoyeA 2004 Characterization of the first non-insect invertebrate functional angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE): leech TtACE resembles the N-domain of mammalian ACE. Biochem J 382 565 573 15175004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Riviere2"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>31 RiviereGMichaudACorradiHRSturrockEDRaviAK 2007 Characterization of the first angiotensin-converting like enzyme in bacteria: Ancestor ACE is already active. Gene 399 81 90 17597310 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Fleury1"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>32 FleuryEHuvetALelongCde LorgerilJBouloV 2009 Generation and analysis of a 29,745 unique Expressed Sequence Tags from the Pacific oyster (Crassostrea gigas) assembled into a publicly accessible database: the GigasDatabase. BMC Genomics 10 341 19640306 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Fabioux1"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>33 FabiouxCPouvreauSLe RouxFHuvetA 2004 The oyster vasa-like gene: a specific marker of the germline in Crassostrea gigas. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 315 897 904 14985097 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Rodet1"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>34 RodetFLelongCDubosMPCostilKFavrelP 2005 Molecular cloning of a molluscan gonadotropin-releasing hormone receptor orthologue specifically expressed in the gonad. Biochim Biophys Acta 1730 187 195 16150500 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Thompson1"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>35 ThompsonJDHigginsDGGibsonTJ 1994 CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, positions-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice. Nucleic Acid Research 22 4673 4680  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Howe1"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>36 HoweKBatemanADurbinR 2002 Quicktree: building huge Neighbour-Joining trees or protein sequences. Bioinformatics 18 1546 1547 12424131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Felsenstein1"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>37 FelsensteinJ 1989 PHYLIP – Phylogeny Inference Package (version 3.2). Cladistics 5 164 166  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-LeQuere1"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>38 Le QuereHHerpinAHuvetALelongCFavrelP 2009 Structural and functional characterizations of an Activin type II receptor orthologue from the pacific oyster Crassostrea gigas. Gene 436 101 107 19393178 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Lobban1"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>39 LobbanMShakurYBeattieJHouslayMD 1994 Identification of two splice variant forms of type-IVB cyclic AMP phosphodiesterase, DPD (rPDE-IVB1) and PDE-4 (rPDE-IVB2) in brain: selective localization in membrane and cytosolic compartments and differential expression in various brain regions. Biochem J 304 Pt 2 399 406 7998974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Franco1"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>40 FrancoAJouauxAMathieuMSourdainePLelongC 2010 Proliferating cell nuclear antigen in gonad and associated storage tissue of the Pacific oyster Crassostrea gigas: seasonal immunodetection and expression in laser microdissected tissues. Cell Tissue Res 340 201 210 20151153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Carmona1"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>41 CarmonaAKSchwagerSLJulianoMAJulianoLSturrockED 2006 A continuous fluorescence resonance energy transfer angiotensin I-converting enzyme assay. Nat Protocols 1 1971 1976 17487185 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Schwager1"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>42 SchwagerSLCarmonaRSturrockED 2006 A high-troughput fluorimetric assay for angiotensin I-converting enzyme. Nat Protocols 1 1961 1964 17487183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Lambert1"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>43 LambertCLeonardNDe BolleXDepiereuxE 2002 ESyPred3D: Prediction of proteins 3D structures. Bioinformatics 18 1250 1256 12217917 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Guex1"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>44 GuexNPeitschMC 1997 SWISS-MODEL and the Swiss-PdbViewer: an environment for comparative protein modeling. Electrophoresis 18 2714 2723 9504803 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-DeLano1"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>45 DeLanoWL 2002 The PyMOL Molecular Graphics System  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Towler1"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>46 TowlerPStakerBPrasadSGMenonSTangJ 2004 ACE2 X-ray structures reveal a large hinge-bending motion important for inhibitor binding and catalysis. J Biol Chem 279 17996 18007 14754895 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Kim1"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>47 KimHMShinDRYooOJLeeHLeeJO 2003 Crystal structure of Drosophila angiotensin I-converting enzyme bound to captopril and lisinopril. FEBS Lett 538 65 70 12633854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Houard1"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>48 HouardXWilliamsTAMichaudADaniPIsaacRE 1998 The Drosophila melanogaster-related angiotensin-I-converting enzymes Acer and Ance–distinct enzymic characteristics and alternative expression during pupal development. Eur J Biochem 257 599 606 9839949 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Riviere3"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>49 RiviereGMichaudABretonCVanCampGLaborieC 2005 Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) and ACE activities display tissue-specific sensitivity to undernutrition-programmed hypertension in the adult rat. Hypertension 46 1169 1174 16203874 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Kierszenbaum1"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>50 KierszenbaumALTresLL 1978 RNA transcription and chromatin structure during meiotic and postmeiotic stages of spermatogenesis. Fed Proc 37 2512 2516 357185 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Erickson1"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>51 EricksonRP 1990 Post-meiotic gene expression. Trends Genet 6 264 269 1978427 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0027833-Kawano1"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>52 KawanoNKangWYamashitaMKogaYYamazakiT 2010 Mice lacking two sperm serine proteases, ACR and PRSS21, are subfertile, but the mutant sperm are infertile in vitro. Biol Reprod 83 359 369 20484738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
