<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gbe</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">gbe</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Genome Biology and Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1759-6653</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4684697</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26446539</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evv186</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">evv186</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Genome Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Whole Genome Sequencing of the Asian Arowana (Scleropages formosus) Provides Insights into the Evolution of Ray-Finned Fishes </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>Christopher M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv186-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv186-AFF2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="evv186-FN1"><sup>†</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Mun Hua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv186-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv186-AFF2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="evv186-FN1"><sup>†</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Croft</surname><given-names>Larry J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv186-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv186-AFF2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv186-AFF3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>Michael P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv186-AFF4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>Han Ming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv186-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evv186-AFF2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="evv186-COR1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="evv186-AFF1"><sup>1</sup>School of Science, Monash University Malaysia, Petaling Jaya, Selangor, Malaysia</aff><aff id="evv186-AFF2"><sup>2</sup>Monash University Malaysia Genomics Facility, Monash University Malaysia, Petaling Jaya, Selangor, Malaysia</aff><aff id="evv186-AFF3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Malaysian Genomics Resource Centre Berhad, Boulevard Signature Office</institution>, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</aff><aff id="evv186-AFF4"><sup>4</sup>Museum and Art Gallery of the Northern Territory, Darwin, NT, Australia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="evv186-COR1">*Corresponding author: E-mail: <email>gan.han.ming@monash.edu</email>.</corresp><fn id="evv186-FN1"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>†These authors contributed equally to this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="evv186-FN2"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Associate editor: Jay Storz </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="evv186-FN3"><p><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Data deposition: This project has been deposited at DNA Data Bank of Japan/EMBL/GenBank under the accession JARO00000000. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>10</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>06</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2885</fpage><lpage>2895</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2015. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" license-type="creative-commons"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The Asian arowana (Scleropages formosus) is of commercial importance, conservation concern, and is a representative of one of the oldest lineages of ray-finned fish, the Osteoglossomorpha. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>To add to genomic knowledge of this species and the evolution of teleosts, the genome of a Malaysian specimen of arowana was sequenced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>A draft genome is presented consisting of 42,110 scaffolds with a total size of 708 Mb (2.85% gaps) representing 93.95% of core eukaryotic genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Using a k-mer-based method, a genome size of 900 Mb was also estimated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>We present an update on the phylogenomics of fishes based on a total of 27 species (23 fish species and 4 tetrapods) using 177 orthologous proteins (71,360 amino acid sites), which supports established relationships except that arowana is placed as the sister lineage to all teleost clades (Bayesian posterior probability 1.00, bootstrap replicate 93%), that evolved after the teleost genome duplication event rather than the eels (Elopomorpha). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Evolutionary rates are highly heterogeneous across the tree with fishes represented by both slowly and rapidly evolving lineages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>A total of 94 putative pigment genes were identified, providing the impetus for development of molecular markers associated with the spectacular colored phenotypes found within this species. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>genome</kwd><kwd>fish</kwd><kwd>phylogenomics</kwd><kwd>evolutionary rate</kwd><kwd>pigmentation genes</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro"><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>More than half of all vertebrate species are fishes, with the Class Osteichthyes (bony fish) being the most diverse class within the Subphylum Vertebrata. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>(Santini et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>2009; Near et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>2012; Betancur-R et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Fish have a long evolutionary history extending over 500 Myr into the Cambrian, with the evolution of the jawless fishes, which are currently represented by the lampreys (Agnatha). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Jawed fishes (Gnathostoma) evolved some 450 Ma and are divided among three lineages: the cartilaginous fishes (Chondrichthyes), the bony fishes (Osteichthyes), and the lobe-finned fishes (Sarcopterygii). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>With the availability of more molecular genetic and genomic data, there has been increasing interest in understanding the diversification of the major fish groups and the molecular evolutionary dynamics of fish lineages, their timing, and evolution of specific genes (Inoue et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>2003; Takezaki et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>2004; Shan and Gras 2011; Near et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>2012; Zou et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>2012; Amemiya et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>2013; Betancur-R et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>2013; Broughton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>2013; Opazo et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>2013; Dornburg et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>2014; Venkatesh et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Of the 3 lineages in which fish are found, the bony fishes are by far the most diverse with nearly 30,000 recognized species and there has been much interest in understanding the drivers of their evolutionary success. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Significant attention has been given to the impact of what is generally known as the fish- or teleost-specific genome duplication event (TGD) (Robinson-Rechavi et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>2001; Hoegg et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>2004; Hurley et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Chromosomal duplications may provide opportunities for evolutionary experimentation, as paralogous genes are exapted to new functions, thereby facilitating rapid morphological, physiological, and behavioral diversification (Taylor et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>2001; Hoegg et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>2004; Meyer and Van de Peer 2005; Santini et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>2009; Opazo et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The Asian arowana (Scleropages formosus: Osteoglossidae) is of fundamental interest to fish phylogenetics as it belongs to one of the oldest teleost groups, the Osteoglossomorpha. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>This lineage comprises the mooneyes, knifefish, elephantfish, freshwater butterflyfish, and bonytongues, and is one of the three ancient extant lineages that diverged immediately after the TGD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The other two are the Elopomorpha comprising eels, tarpons and bonefish, and the Clupeocephala, which embraces the majority of teleost diversity including the species-rich Ostariophysi (e.g., catfish, carps and minnows, tetras) and Percomorphaceae (e.g., wrasse, cichlids, gobies, flatfish) (Betancur-R et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>2013; Broughton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>2013; Betancur-R, Naylor, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>2014; Betancur-R, Wiley, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>There has been on-going disagreement on which one is the sister group to all other teleosts (Patterson and Rosen 1977; Nelson 1994; Arratia 1997; Patterson 1998; Zou et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Historically, the Osteoglossomorph was considered to have diverged first (Patterson and Rosen 1977; Lauder and Liem 1983; Nelson 1994; Inoue et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>2003; Brinkmann et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>2004); however, comprehensive morphological studies, including both fossil and extant teleosts, and recent molecular-based studies supported the Elopomorpha as the sister lineage to all other bony fishes (Arratia 1997, 1999, 2000; Li and Wilson 1999; Diogo 2007; Santini et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>2009; Near et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>2012; Betancur-R et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>2013; Broughton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The arowana, sometimes also referred to as dragon fish, is also noteworthy as it is one of the most expensive fish in the world due to the occurrence of several bright color morphs that makes it highly sought after as an ornamental species (Dawes et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>1999; Yue et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Potentially relevant in this context is that teleost fishes are thought to have a greater range of pigment synthesis genes and pathways than any other vertebrate group (Braasch et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>However, the basis of color variation has seen little research in arowana with the exception of studies by Mohd-Shamsudin et al. (2011) and Mu et al. (2012) who found no consistent patterns of divergence between color variants and mitochondrial markers. Scleropages formosus is also of significant conservation concern in the wild. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The species is listed by the International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN) as endangered (Kottelat 2013) and by the Convention on International Trades in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora as “highly endangered” (Yue et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>2006). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>In this study, we present the whole genome sequences for S. formosus obtained from a captive Malaysian specimen, as a representative of the local wild form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>We then place this species within a phylogenetic framework including sequences from all available fish with sequenced genomes making this the most complete phylogenomic analysis of fish so far conducted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>We also carry out analysis of the rate of molecular evolution within and between fish lineages and identify a range of genes associated with pigmentation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Genome Sequencing, Assembly, and Annotation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>A total of 297,227,578 paired-end and 290,438,918 mate-pair reads (2 × 100 bp) were generated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Preprocessing resulted in 291,628,300 paired-end and 288,008,898 mate-pair reads, and these were subsequently assembled to generate a draft genome that consists of 42,110 scaffolds with a total size of 708 Mb and 2.85% gaps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The longest scaffold is 616,488 bp long and the N50 scaffold length is 58,849 bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>We also carried out a k-mer-based approach using read data and estimated the arowana genome size at approximately 900 Mb, a number in accord with the size of 1.05 Gb reported by Shen et al. (2014) estimated through flow cytometric comparative fluorescence with chicken cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Based on these estimates, sequencing depth estimations ranging from 57 to 66 × coverage were inferred. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Features predicted from the assembly include 24,274 protein-coding genes, 609 transfer RNAs (tRNAs), and 29 ribosomal RNAs (100% 5S rRNA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Based on sequence similarity (e-value threshold of 1 × 10−10, hit coverage cut-off of 70%), 71% of the predicted genes shared sequence similarity to another protein in the nonredundant (NR) database on National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>For protein-coding genes, 95.8% have Annotation Edit Distance (Eilbeck et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>2009) scores of less than 0.5 and 85.5% contain at least one Pfam domain, an indication of a well-annotated genome (Campbell et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The gene space in this assembly appears fairly complete with 93.95% of core eukaryotic genes represented. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>This is further supported by the mapping of 78.92% of transcriptomic reads sequenced from a different arowana sample from Shen et al. (2014) to our assembled genome, with 64.32% of unmapped reads belonging to 18S and 28S ribosomal genes and 7.60% to mitochondrial genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>These genes are usually present in high copy numbers and may not have been assembled in our de novo assembly due to exceedingly high read coverage and short read lengths (Nagarajan and Pop 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>This finding is also consistent with the lack of specific rRNAs (18S, 28S) predicted from the assembly. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Phylogenomics and Evolutionary Rates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Our sample of arowana shows a 100% identity to the most common mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase subunit 1 (COI) haplotype (accession number: HM156394) found among Malaysian specimens by Mohd-Shamsudin et al. (2011) and is 99.87% similar to the complete COI gene (accession number: DQ023143) from a fish obtained from a commercial farm in Singapore (Yue et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Tree-based ortholog inference resulted in a set of orthologous proteins belonging to 177 gene families (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv186/-/DC1">supplementary material S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv186/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) shared across all 23 fishes and 4 tetrapod species (table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Concatenation of each aligned ortholog generated a final supermatrix comprising of a total of 71,360 amino acid sites per species with only 7.07% gaps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The aligned supermatrix and the best-fit partitioning scheme generated by PartitionFinder can be found in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv186/-/DC1">supplementary materials S2</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv186/-/DC1">S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv186/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Rooted with the Chondrichthyes, both Bayesian (BI) and maximum-likelihood (ML) inferred phylogenomic trees display a topology largely consistent with recent studies with either more limited taxon sampling (Zou et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>2012; Amemiya et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>2013) or smaller gene sampling (Broughton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>2013; Glasauer and Neuhauss 2014; Braasch et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>2015) with respect to evolutionary relationships and taxonomic classification (fig. 1). Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>1.—Phylogenetic relationships among fish species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic tree was inferred from a supermatrix containing the alignment of sequences from 27 species (177 orthologous proteins, 71,360 aligned amino acid positions, 7.07% gaps) and was rooted with the Chondrichthyes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Black circles indicate maximum nodal support with bootstrap values of 100% and Bayesian posterior probabilities of 1.00. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The yellow and green circles represent 93% and 98% bootstrap support values, respectively, both with maximal Bayesian posterior probability values of 1.00. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Branch length information is included and the rate of molecular evolution (number of amino acid substitutions per site) for each fish lineage is placed beside each taxa label. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>These values were calculated from the split of all ray-finned fish from lobe-finned fish and tetrapod lineages (node indicated with the orange star). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>A (T) is placed next to the species for which transcriptome data were utilized. Table 1List of Species Included in the Phylogenetic AnalysesOrganismsourceScientific NameClassOrderReferenceRay-finned fish    Asian arowana*Scleropages formosusActinopterygiiOsteoglossiformesThis study    European eelZAnguilla anguillaActinopterygiiAnguilliformesHenkel et al. (2012)    MedakaEOryzias latipesActinopterygiiBeloniformesKasahara et al. (2007)    Blind cave fishEAstyanax mexicanusActinopterygiiCharaciformesMcGaugh et al. (2014)    Common carpCCyprinus carpioActinopterygiiCypriniformesXu et al. (2014)    ZebrafishEDanio rerioActinopterygiiCypriniformesHowe et al. (2013)    Amazon mollyEPoecilia formosaActinopterygiiCyprinodontiformesUnpublished    Southern platyfishEXiphophorus maculatusActinopterygiiCyprinodontiformesSchartl et al. (2013)    Northern pikeVEsox luciusActinopterygiiEsociformesRondeau et al. (2014)    Atlantic codEGadus morhuaActinopterygiiGadiformesStar et al. (2011)    Three-spined sticklebackEGasterosteus aculeatusActinopterygiiGasterosteiformesJones et al. (2012)    Electric eelFElectrophorus electricusActinopterygiiGymnotiformesGallant et al. (2014)    Spotted garELepisosteus oculatusActinopterygiiLepisosteiformesUnpublished    Nile tilapiaEOreochromis niloticusActinopterygiiPerciformesBrawand et al. (2014)    Atlantic salmonSASalmo salarActinopterygiiSalmoniformesDavidson et al. (2010)    Rainbow troutGOncorhynchus mykissActinopterygiiSalmoniformesBerthelot et al. (2014)    Japanese pufferETakifugu rubripesActinopterygiiTetraodontiformesAparicio et al. (2002)    Green spotted pufferETetraodon nigroviridisActinopterygiiTetraodontiformesJaillon et al. (2004)Lobe-finned fish    African coelacanthELatimeria chalumnaeSarcopterygiiCoelacanthiformesAmemiya et al. (2013)    aLungfishSRProtopterus annectensSarcopterygiiLepidosireniformesAmemiya et al. (2013)Cartilaginous fish    Elephant sharkACallorhinchus miliiChondrichthyesChimaeriformesVenkatesh et al. (2014)    bSmall-spotted catsharkSKScyliorhinus caniculaChondrichthyesCarchariniformesWyffels et al. (2014)    bLittle skateSKLeucoraja erinaceaChondrichthyesRajiformesWang et al. (2012)Tetrapods    Western clawed frogEXenopus tropicalisAmphibiaAnuraFuchs et al. (2006)    ChickenEGallus gallusAvesGalliformesHillier et al. (2004)    HumanEHomo sapiensMammaliaPrimatesVenter et al. (2001)    LizardEAnolis carolinensisReptiliaSquamataAlföldi et al. (2011)Note.—Codes for source: A*STAR (A), CarpBase (C), Ensembl (E), efish genomics (F), Genoscope (G), SalmonDB (SA), SkateBase (SK), SRA (SR), UVic (V), ZF Genomics (Z), this study (*).aRaw transcriptome reads were used.bAssembled transcripts were used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The rapid and divergent evolution of certain ray-finned fish groups is apparent in the tree from the relatively long branch lengths. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Substantial evolutionary rate heterogeneity is observed within and among fish lineages by the comparison of amino acid substitutions per site calculated from branch lengths (fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, based on Tajima’s relative rate test (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv186/-/DC1">supplementary material S4</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv186/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), the Asian arowana was reported to have a significantly different evolutionary rate in comparison with other ray-finned fish lineages with P values ranging from 0 to 0.00048 (European eel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Using a Bonferroni corrected critical P value of 0.00098 (equivalent to α = 0.05 for a single test) results in the rejection of null hypothesis of equal rates of evolution between the arowana lineages and all other fish species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>A major difference in our estimated phylogenetic relationships to other recent studies is the placement of the arowana sample as the sister lineage to all other teleost lineages, which conflicts with morphology-based studies and more recent molecular perspectives which posit that Elopomorpha is the sister group to all other teleost lineages (Arratia 1997, 1999; Li and Wilson 1999; Diogo 2007; Broughton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>2013; Glasauer and Neuhauss 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>However, our result is consistent with other studies that have the Osteoglossomorpha as the sister lineage to all other teleosts (Patterson and Rosen 1977; Lauder and Liem 1983; Nelson 1994; Inoue et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>2003; Brinkmann et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>We look forward to more comprehensive genomic resources becoming available with greater taxon sampling for teleost fishes to allow more rigorous testing of these alternate hypotheses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Our results support the findings of Amemiya et al. (2013) who found that the lungfish and not the coelacanth to be the closest relative to the tetrapods, which has also been a subject to much disputation (Brinkmann et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>2004; Takezaki et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>2004; Shan and Gras 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>However, although we also found that the coelacanth proteins evolve at a slower rate relative to those of the tetrapods, from figure 1 it can be seen that the substitution rate in the coelacanth lineage is more than half of that for the tetrapod lineage, which is substantially faster than that observed by Amemiya et al. (2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>This discrepancy is most likely a result of the use of different protein data sets, taxon sampling, and outgroups in the two studies and provides a caveat for generalizing results from a single study even when utilizing information from a large number of genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Putative Pigmentation Genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>A total of 94 different pigmentation genes were identified from our genome sequences (table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Only the best hit for each pigmentation gene was retained in the table and these are grouped into various functional categories related to melanophore development, components of melanosomes, melanosome construction, melanosome transport, regulation of melanogenesis, systemic effects, xanthophore development, pteridine synthesis, iridophore development, and other functions as shown by Braasch et al. (2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>This result indicates that a wide range of pigmentation genes have been retained across the teleosts and will provide a valuable resource for the study of the genetic and developmental basis for the spectacular color phenotypes of the Asian arowana. Table 2Putative Arowana Pigmentation GenesGeneAccession (Homo sapiens)Locus ID (arowana)PIDe-valueAccession (annotation)SpeciesMelanophore development    adam17NP_003174.3Z043_11571668.980.00XP_010733184.1Larimichthys crocea    adamts20NP_079279.3Z043_10647571.360.00XP_008274326.1Stegastes partitus    creb1NP_004370.1Z043_12298795.370.00XP_005167757.1Danio rerio    ece1NP_001106819.1Z043_11262880.030.00CDQ77702.1Oncorhynchus mykiss    EdnrbNP_001116131.1Z043_10507681.500.00XP_007254865.1Astyanax mexicanus    EgfrNP_958439.1Z043_114891————    fgfr2NP_000132.3Z043_10486684.500.00KKF10433.1La. crocea    frem2NP_997244.4Z043_10138270.220.00XP_012683949.1Clupea harengus    fzd4NP_036325.2Z043_10875589.760.00XP_012693402.1Cl. harengus    gna11NP_002058.2Z043_10631096.020.00XP_010750457.1La. crocea    gnaqNP_002063.2Z043_11408186.570.00XP_010735114.1La. crocea    gpc3NP_001158091.1Z043_10123552.033 × 10−175XP_006639062.1Lepisosteus oculatus    gpr161NP_722561.1Z043_11675073.060.00XP_007227875.1As. mexicanus    hdac1NP_004955.2Z043_10821096.710.00XP_006631299.1Le. oculatus    ikbkgNP_003630.1Z043_10576164.162 × 10−170XP_010903123.1Esox lucius    itgb1NP_596867.1Z043_11674971.960.00NP_001030143.1D. rerio    KitNP_001087241.1Z043_11885471.890.00XP_008297546.1St. partitus    lef1NP_057353.1Z043_100731————    lmx1aNP_001167540.1Z043_10887191.039 × 10−180XP_008417499.1Poecilia reticulata    mbtps1NP_003782.1Z043_10439186.310.00XP_009291810.1D. rerio    mcoln3NP_060768.8Z043_11021369.960.00XP_006634884.1Le. oculatus    mitfNP_937801.1Z043_10535783.910.00XP_006630679.1Le. oculatus    pax3NP_039230.1Z043_107599————    rab32NP_006825.1Z043_10428178.476 × 10−118XP_012671987.1Cl. harengus    scarb2NP_005497.1Z043_10539778.220.00NP_001117983.1O. mykiss    sfxn1NP_073591.2Z043_12111989.100.00XP_010895582.1E. lucius    snai2NP_003059.1Z043_11723185.885 × 10−164XP_003759837.1Sarcophilus harrisii    sox10NP_008872.1Z043_10624277.780.00XP_008294581.1St. partitus    sox18NP_060889.1Z043_10746961.333 × 10−161XP_001337702.1D. rerio    sox9NP_000337.1Z043_11891779.080.00XP_006635207.1Le. oculatus    tfap2aNP_001027451.1Z043_11993386.120.00XP_006634534.1Le. oculatus    trpm1NP_001238949.1Z043_11166671.060.00XP_006629107.1Le. oculatus    trpm7NP_060142.3Z043_10044182.160.00XP_006628750.1Le. oculatus    wnt1NP_005421.1Z043_12012993.510.00XP_010873444.1E. lucius    wnt3aNP_149122.1Z043_11818496.120.00XP_008312650.1Cynoglossus semilaevis    zic2NP_009060.2Z043_10177988.540.00XP_006638968.1Le. oculatusComponents of melanosomes    dctNP_001913.2Z043_10852673.90.00XP_008326759.1Cy. semilaevis    rab32NP_006825.1Z043_11653667.761 × 10−88XP_003224067.2Anolis carolinensis    rab38NP_071732.1Z043_12211290.051 × 10−126AAI50366.1D. rerio    slc24a4NP_705934.1Z043_11425181.840.00XP_005803162.1Xiphophorus maculatus    slc24a5NP_995322.1Z043_10339682.060.00XP_005814818.1X. maculatus    tyrp1NP_000541.1Z043_10795674.520.00XP_005743086.1Pundamilia nyerereiMelanosome construction    ap3d1NP_003929.4Z043_12076273.210.00XP_011472829.1Oryzias latipes    fig4NP_055660.1Z043_10311586.550.00XP_006626354.1Le. oculatus    gpr143NP_000264.2Z043_10217578.420.00XP_012680526.1Cl. harengus    hps3NP_115759.2Z043_10037070.790.00XP_012680760.1Cl. harengus    lystNP_001288294.1Z043_10075769.990.00XP_008300589.1St. partitus    nsfNP_006169.2Z043_10844793.610.00XP_005164054.1D. rerio    pldnNP_036520.1Z043_10941478.424 × 10−73XP_008274283.1St. partitus    rabggtaNP_004572.3Z043_121567————    txndc5NP_110437.2Z043_11662677.020.00CDQ77189.1O. mykiss    vps11NP_068375.3Z043_12108190.410.00XP_010863485.1E. lucius    vps18NP_065908.1Z043_11126785.090.00XP_010892538.1E. lucius    vps33aNP_075067.2Z043_11654294.660.00CDQ76904.1O. mykiss    vps39NP_056104.2Z043_11704789.050.00XP_010749485.1La. croceaMelanosome transport    mlphNP_077006.1Z043_10168762.900.00XP_005168768.1D. rerio    myo5aNP_000250.3Z043_10244886.240.00XP_006628770.1Le. oculatus    myo7aNP_001120652.1Z043_10093178.910.00AAI63570.1D. rerio    rab27aNP_899059.1Z043_11197387.892 × 10−148XP_006628775.1Le. oculatusRegulation of melanogenesis    creb1NP_004370.1Z043_12298795.370.00XP_005167757.1D. rerio    drd2NP_000786.1Z043_11298083.670.00XP_006642348.1Le. oculatus    mc1rNP_002377.4Z043_12163676.154 × 10−167AGC50885.1Cyprinus carpio    mgrn1NP_001135763.2Z043_11124985.270.00XP_006637253.1Le. oculatus    pomcNP_001030333.1Z043_10334051.727 × 10−66AAO17793.1Anguilla japonicaSystemic effects    atp6ap1NP_001174.2Z043_10810266.240.00XP_012682891.1Cl. harengus    atp6ap2NP_005756.2Z043_10088275.140.00XP_012675204.1Cl. harengus    atp6v0cNP_001185498.1Z043_12512295.363 × 10−90XP_008434615.1P. reticulata    atp6v0d1NP_004682.2Z043_12193394.480.00NP_955914.1D. rerio    atp6v1e1NP_001687.1Z043_10454992.092 × 10−143XP_007579195.1Poecilia formosa    atp6v1fNP_004222.2Z043_100808100.004 × 10−81XP_006633325.1Le. oculatus    atp6v1hNP_998784.1Z043_11348390.610.00XP_007260238.1As. mexicanus    atp7bNP_000044.2Z043_12208854.410.00XP_010017200.1Nestor notabilis    rps19NP_001013.1Z043_11893991.677 × 10−95XP_008329573.1Cy. semilaevis    rps20NP_001014.1Z043_107890100.004 × 10−80NP_001117836.1O. mykissXanthophore development    atp6v1e1NP_001687.1Z043_10454992.092 × 10−143XP_007579195.1P. formosa    atp6v1hNP_998784.1Z043_11348390.610.00XP_007260238.1As. mexicanus    csf1rNP_001275634.1Z043_11885471.890.00XP_008297546.1St. partitus    ednrbNP_001116131.1Z043_10507681.500.00XP_007254865.1As. mexicanus    ghrNP_001229389.1Z043_10116057.240.00BAD20706.1An. japonica    pax3NP_039230.1Z043_107599————    sox10NP_008872.1Z043_10624277.780.00XP_008294581.1St. partitusPteridine synthesis    gchiNP_001019195.1Z043_11044981.941 × 10−125XP_007231033.1As. mexicanus    mycbp2NP_055872.4Z043_10447391.140.00XP_007251746.1As. mexicanus    paicsNP_001072992.1Z043_12186887.940.00XP_010870568.1E. lucius    pcbd1NP_000272.1Z043_10584295.051 × 10−66XP_012672435.1Cl. harengus    PtsNP_000308.1Z043_10301581.212 × 10−84XP_012670027.1Cl. harengus    qdprNP_000311.2Z043_10996286.835 × 10−129XP_006137052.1Pelodiscus sinensis    SprNP_003115.1Z043_11428863.646 × 10−126NP_001133746.1Salmo salar    xdhNP_000370.2Z043_11538469.120.00XP_006636840.1Le. oculatusIridophore development    atp6v1hNP_998784.1Z043_11348390.610.00XP_007260238.1As. mexicanus    dacNP_001077.2Z043_12329273.280.00ACN11084.1Sa. salar    ednrbNP_001116131.1Z043_10507681.500.00XP_007254865.1As. mexicanus    LtkNP_002335.2Z043_11842468.810.00XP_010877407.1E. lucius    sox10NP_008872.1Z043_10624277.780.00XP_008294581.1St. partitus    sox9NP_000337.1Z043_11891779.080.00XP_006635207.1Le. oculatus    trim33NP_056990.3Z043_11560966.930.00NP_001002871.2D. rerio    vps18NP_065908.1Z043_11126785.090.00XP_010892538.1E. lucius    vps39NP_056104.2Z043_11704789.050.00XP_010749485.1La. croceaUncategorized function    abhd11NP_683711.1Z043_11726279.649 × 10−155XP_010893523.1E. lucius    ebna1bp2NP_006815.2Z043_12330077.787 × 10−146XP_006634973.1Le. oculatus    gfpt1NP_002047.2Z043_10157495.160.00XP_006625541.1Le. oculatus    gja5NP_859054.1Z043_10734371.020.00XP_008273833.1St. partitus    irf4NP_002451.2Z043_10275975.710.00XP_006634623.1Le. oculatus    kcnj13NP_002233.2Z043_11919471.767 × 10−173XP_010768290.1Notothenia coriiceps    pabpc1NP_002559.2Z043_10957296.200.00XP_007230879.1As. mexicanus    skiv2l2NP_056175.3Z043_11215491.680.00XP_006627067.1Le. oculatus    tpcn2NP_620714.2Z043_11504162.500.00CDQ78014.1O. mykiss </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Sample Collection and DNA Extraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>A tail fin sample of S. formosus from a specimen was donated by the Malaysian Freshwater Fisheries Research Centre (FRI Glami Lemi). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>DNA was extracted using Qiagen Blood and Tissue DNA extraction kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Then, 1 µg of the purified DNA was sheared (500 bp setting) using Covaris S220 (Covaris, Woburn, MA) and prepped with Illumina TruSeq DNA Sample Preparation Kit (Illumina, San Diego, CA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Additionally, a 3-kb insert mate-pair library was generated using the Illumina Mate Pair Library Prep Kit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Both libraries were quantified using KAPA library quantification kit (KAPA Biosystems, Capetown, South Africa) and sequenced on the Illumina HiSeq 2000 using the 2 × 101 bp paired-end read setting (Illumina) located at the Malaysian Genomics Resource Centre. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Genome Size Estimation based on k-mer Frequency in Sequence Reads </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Genome size of S. formosus was approximated from k-mer frequency distributions in raw genomic reads as was done by Li et al. (2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Frequencies of distinct 15-, 17-, 19-, and 21-mers occurring in genomic reads from the paired-end library were counted using JELLYFISH (Marçais and Kingsford 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The real sequencing depth (N) was estimated from the peak of each frequency distribution (M), read length (L), and k-mer length (K) correlated according to the following formula: M = N × (L − K + 1)/L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Genome size was then approximated from the division of total genomic bases by the real sequencing depth. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Assembly and Annotation of the Scleropages formosus Genome </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Raw reads were error corrected and preprocessed by removing low-quality reads (average Phred quality ≤20) and reads containing more than 10% ambiguous nucleotides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The resulting set of reads longer than 30 bp were assembled and scaffolded using the MSR-CA genome assembler (now renamed MaSuRCA, with default settings) (Zimin et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Further scaffolding was carried out with reads from the mate-pair library using Scaffolder (Barton MD and Barton HA 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The final draft assembly consists of scaffolds longer than 200 bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Finally, the CEGMA program (Parra et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>2007) was used to assess the completeness of the assembly by detecting the presence of 248 highly conserved proteins within the draft genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>To compare our draft assembly with other arowana resources, transcriptomic reads generated using 454 pyrosequencing from the Asian arowana transcriptome (Shen et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>2014) were aligned to the draft genome using GMAP (Wu and Watanabe 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Unmapped transcriptomic reads were further characterized by a BLASTN (Altschul et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>1990) search against the NT database on NCBI. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Arowana transcriptome reads were downloaded (SRA: SRR941557, SRR941783, SRR941785), preprocessed with QTrim (default settings) (Shrestha et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>2014), and assembled de novo using IDBA-tran (–max_isoforms 10 –maxk 80) (Peng et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>To predict protein-coding genes, MAKER (Cantarel et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>2008) was run on the arowana genome using the assembled arowana transcriptome and Ensembl proteins from zebrafish (Danio rerio), Nile tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus), medaka (Oryzias latipes), and Japanese puffer (Takifugu rubripes) as evidence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Repetitive regions were masked with all organisms in RepBase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>MAKER was run iteratively to train the SNAP (Korf 2004) gene predictor in a bootstrap fashion to improve the predictor’s performance, and final MAKER predictions were made using the trained SNAP as well as Augustus trained with the zebrafish species model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Functional annotation of the predicted sequences was performed with a BLASTP (Altschul et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>1990) search (e-value threshold of 1 × 10−10) against vertebrate proteins in NCBI’s NR database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>A 70% blast hit coverage cut-off (based on subject length) was also applied to obtain confident annotations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Unannotated protein sequences were then searched against all sequences in NCBI’s NR database with the same e-value and hit coverage cut-offs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Gene ontologies, protein domains, and families were identified with InterProScan (Jones et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>tRNA genes in the assembly were detected by MAKER using tRNAscan (Lowe and Eddy 1997), while RNAmmer (Lagesen et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>2007) was used to predict rRNA sequences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Orthology Inference </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Data selection for phylogenomic analyses is controversial and centers on issues of data quality and quantity and on benefits of taxon sampling versus high data coverage that minimizes alignment gaps (Laurin-Lemay et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>2012; Amemiya et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>2013; Betancur-R et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>2013; Misof et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>2013; Salichos and Rokas 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>We take a conservative approach that minimizes gaps in the supermatrix and use several ways to carefully distinguish orthologs from paralogs to assemble a high quality phylogenomic data set, ensuring the estimation of a robust and accurate tree, including the placement of the deeper lineages in the tree. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>First, because conserved genes make for the best phylogenomic markers (Betancur-R et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>2013), Hidden Markov Model (HMM) profiles from the TreeFam database (Schreiber et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>2014) of gene families conserved across 104 other animal species were used to identify these conserved protein sequences in the arowana genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>For all species, protein sequences longer than 100 amino acids were scanned for sequence homology to gene families in the TreeFam database (version 9) (Schreiber et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>2014) using hmmsearch (Eddy 2011) (e-value threshold of 1 × 10−10) and gene families having sequence homology to at least one protein in all 27 species were retained for subsequent orthology inference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Orthology inference from these protein clusters was conducted with scripts from the pipeline recently described by Yang and Smith (2014), which employs a tree-based approach to first identify paralogs, prune spurious branches, and finally identify orthologs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Briefly, protein sequences in each gene family were aligned and trimmed with the fasta_to_tree.py script. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>In addition, clusters containing paralogs were limited during orthology inference by implementing a tree-based approach on individual sequence clusters, along with additional pruning steps, to separate paralogs and orthologs (Yang and Smith 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Due to computational limitations, we modified the pipeline to use IQ-TREE (Nguyen et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>2015) to build smaller gene trees (less than 1,000 sequences) and FastTreeMP (Price et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>2010) for larger gene trees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>For each tree, tips longer than 0.5 (=absolute tip cut-off) or longer than 0.2 and ten times longer than its nearby tips (=relative tip cut-off) were trimmed with trim_tips.py. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Monophyletic tips belonging to the same taxon were masked with mask_tips_by_taxonID_genomes.py. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Internal branches longer than 0.3, which may be separating orthologous groups, were cut with cut_long_internal_branches.py and only trees containing sequences from all 27 species were retained, thus reducing the amount of missing data and lowering the potential for nonphylogenetic signals (Borowiec et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Protein sequence alignment, alignment trimming, and gene tree building were repeated for remaining sequences for each tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Orthology inference was then carried out on the newly inferred trees with paralogy pruning by maximum inclusion using the prune_paralogy_MI.py script (relative tip cut-off 0.2, absolute tip cut-off 0.5, minimum taxa 27), which iteratively extracts the subtree containing the most taxa without taxon duplication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Protein sequences in each cluster were aligned with mafft_wrapper.py, each alignment was trimmed with pep_gblocks_wrapper.py, and all alignments were finally concatenated into a supermatrix. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Orthology calls in teleosts, and specifically for Osteoglossomorphs and Elopomorphs, are not as simple and are complicated by divergent evolution in genes as a result of multiple rounds of genome duplication prior to teleost diversification (Braasch et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Although we have taken several strict measures to identify orthologs and exclude paralogs, it is important to note that it is extremely challenging to ensure that all identified protein sequences in each cluster are truly orthologous. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis was done based on amino acid alignments for a total of 27 species (table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>For organisms lacking available proteome data sets, namely the lungfish, little skate, and small-spotted catshark, protein sequences were obtained from their respective transcriptomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>For the lungfish specifically, raw Illumina RNA-seq reads (SRA: SRR505721–SRR505726) were assembled with the Trinity assembler (Grabherr et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>All transcriptomes were translated with Transdecoder (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://transdecoder.sourceforge.net/">http://transdecoder.sourceforge.net/</ext-link>, last accessed April 14, 2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Each ortholog is treated as a separate data block and used as input to PartitionFinder (branchlengths = linked, model_selection = AICc, search = rcluster) (Lanfear et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>2014) to estimate the best-fit partitioning schemes and models of protein evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Based on these results, ML analysis was conducted with RAxML (Stamatakis 2014) under the recommended partitions and substitution models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>A total of 100 trees were generated using distinct random seeds and the tree with the best likelihood value was chosen as the final tree topology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Nodal support was represented by bootstrap replicates with the autoMRE convergence criterion (Pattengale et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>A Bayesian inference using the same supermatrix partitioned into each ortholog was also carried out using ExaBayes (Aberer et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Four independent chains were run for 2 million generations and sampled every 500 generations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>With 25% of initial samples discarded as burn-in, runs were considered to have converged when the average standard deviation of split frequencies is less than 1%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Both ML and BI phylogenetic trees were rooted using the Chondrichthyes as the outgroup and visualized with MEGA6 (Tamura et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Rate of Molecular Evolution </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>To compare evolutionary rates of the Asian arowana versus other ray-finned fish lineages, the rate of molecular evolution for each fish lineage was calculated by adding branch lengths from the end of each terminal branch to the node where the split between ray-finned fish and lobe-finned fish (and tetrapods) occurred (fig. 1, orange star). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>In addition, the Tajima’s relative rate test (Tajima 1993) was implemented, as done by Amemiya et al. (2013) to test for equal rates between lineages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Using MEGA6 (Tamura et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>2013), Tajima’s relative rate tests (with missing positions and gaps eliminated) were conducted for comparisons between the Asian arowana and other ray-finned fishes, with a member of the Chondricthyes set as outgroup. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Identification of Putative Pigmentation Genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Predicted protein sequences for arowana were screened for putative pigmentation genes using a list curated by Braasch et al. (2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Using their homologs in humans (table 2), arowana proteins were searched against pigment genes using BLASTP (Altschul et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>1990) with an e-value threshold of 1 × 10−40 and subsequently filtered with a hit coverage cut-off of 70%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The best hit for each pigment gene was chosen as a candidate to test for the presence of conserved domains by using the Batch CD-Search tool (Marchler-Bauer and Bryant 2004) to search against the Conserved Domain Database (Marchler-Bauer et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evv186/-/DC1">Supplementary materials S1–S4</ext-link> are available at Genome Biology and Evolution online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gbe.oxfordjournals.org/">http://www.gbe.oxfordjournals.org/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_7_10_2885__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="supp_evv186_Supp1_TF9_list.txt"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="supp_evv186_Supp2_alignment.phy"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="supp_evv186_Supp3_partitions.txt"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="supp_evv186_Supp4_tajimarr.xlsx"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Funding for this study was provided by the Monash University Malaysia Tropical Medicine and Biology Multidisciplinary Platform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>We are also grateful to the staff of the Malaysian Freshwater Fisheries Research Centre (FRI Glami Lemi), Jelebu, and Puviarasi Meganathan, Monash University Malaysia, for their assistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>We particularly thank Broad Institute for their permission to use the spotted gar genomic resources in this work and also acknowledge Wesley Warren and The Genome Institute, Washington University School of Medicine, for the availability of the Amazon molly genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>Literature Cited</title><ref id="evv186-B1"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>AbererAJKobertKStamatakisA 2014 ExaBayes: massively parallel bayesian tree inference for the whole-genome era. Mol Biol Evol. 31:2553–2556.25135941 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B2"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>AlföldiJ 2011 The genome of the green anole lizard and a comparative analysis with birds and mammals. Nature 477:587–591.21881562 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B3"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>AltschulSFGishWMillerWMyersEWLipmanDJ 1990 Basic local alignment search tool. J Mol Biol. 215:403–410.2231712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B4"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>AmemiyaCT 2013 The African coelacanth genome provides insights into tetrapod evolution. Nature 496:311–316.23598338 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B5"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>AparicioS 2002 Whole-genome shotgun assembly and analysis of the genome of Fugu rubripes. Science 297:1301–1310.12142439 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B6"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>ArratiaG 1997 Basal teleosts and teleostean phylogeny. Palaeo Ichthyologica 7:1–168. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B7"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>ArratiaG 1999 The monophyly of Teleostei and stem-group teleosts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Consensus and disagreements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>In: ArratiaGSchultzeHP, editors. Mesozoic fishes 2—systematics and the fossil record. Munich (Germany): Friedrich Pfeil p. 265–334. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B8"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>ArratiaG 2000 Phylogenetic relationships of Teleostei. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Past and present. Estud Oceanol. 19:19–51. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B9"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>BartonMDBartonHA 2012 Scaffolder—software for manual genome scaffolding. Source Code Biol Med. 7:4.22640820 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B10"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>BerthelotC 2014 The rainbow trout genome provides novel insights into evolution after whole-genome duplication in vertebrates. Nat Commun. 5:3657.24755649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B11"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Betancur-RRNaylorGJOrtíG 2014 Conserved genes, sampling error, and phylogenomic inference. Syst Biol. 63:257–262.24293251 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B12"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Bentancur-RRWileyE 2014 Phylogenetic classification of bony fishes—version 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.deepfin.org/Classification_v3.htm">http://www.deepfin.org/Classification_v3.htm</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B13"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Betancur-RR 2013 The tree of life and a new classification of bony fishes. PLoS Curr: Tree of Life. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B14"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>BorowiecMLLeeEKChiuJCPlachetzkiDC 2015 Dissecting phylogenetic signal and accounting for bias in whole-genome data sets: a case study of the Metazoa. bioRxiv Advance Access published January 16, 2015; doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/013946">http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/013946</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B15"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>BraaschIBrunetFVolffJNSchartlM 2009 Pigmentation pathway evolution after whole-genome duplication in fish. Genome Biol Evol. 1:479–493.20333216 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B16"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>BraaschI 2015 A new model army: emerging fish models to study the genomics of vertebrate Evo-Devo. J Exp Zool B Mol Dev Evol. 324:316–341.25111899 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B17"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>BrawandD 2014 The genomic substrate for adaptive radiation in African cichlid fish. Nature 513:375–381.25186727 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B18"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>BrinkmannHVenkateshBBrennerSMeyerA 2004 Nuclear protein-coding genes support lungfish and not the coelacanth as the closest living relatives of land vertebrates. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 101:4900–4905.15037746 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B19"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>BroughtonREBetancur-RRLiCArratiaGOrtíG 2013 Multi-locus phylogenetic analysis reveals the pattern and tempo of bony fish evolution. PLoS Curr. 5. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B20"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>CampbellMSHoltCMooreBYandellM 2014 Genome annotation and curation using MAKER and MAKER-P. Curr Protoc Bioinformatics. 48:4.11.1–4.11.39. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B21"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>CantarelBL 2008 MAKER: an easy-to-use annotation pipeline designed for emerging model organism genomes. Genome Res. 18:188–196.18025269 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B22"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>DavidsonWS 2010 Sequencing the genome of the Atlantic salmon (Salmo salar). Genome Biol. 11:403.20887641 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B23"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>DawesJALimLCCheongL 1999 The dragon fish. England: Kingdom Books. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B24"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>DiogoR. 2007 The origin of higher clades: osteology, myology, phylogeny and evolution of bony fishes and the rise of tetrapods. Science Pub Incorporated. New Hamsphire: Enfield. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B25"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>DornburgATownsendJPFriedmanMNearTJ 2014 Phylogenetic informativeness reconciles ray-finned fish molecular divergence times. BMC Evol Biol. 14:169.25103329 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B26"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>EddySR 2011 Accelerated profile HMM searches. PLoS Comput Biol. 7:e1002195.22039361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B27"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>EilbeckKMooreBHoltCYandellM 2009 Quantitative measures for the management and comparison of annotated genomes. BMC Bioinformatics 10:67.19236712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B28"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>FuchsCBurmesterTHankelnT 2006 The amphibian globin gene repertoire as revealed by the Xenopus genome. Cytogenet Genome Res. 112:296–306.16484786 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B29"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>GallantJR 2014 Genomic basis for the convergent evolution of electric organs. Science 344:1522–1525.24970089 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B30"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>GlasauerSMKNeuhaussSCF 2014 Whole-genome duplication in teleost fishes and its evolutionary consequences. Mol Genet Genomics. 289:1045–1060.25092473 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B31"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>GrabherrMG 2011 Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome. Nat Biotech. 29:644–652. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B32"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>HenkelCV 2012 Primitive duplicate Hox clusters in the European eel’s genome. PLoS One 7:e32231.22384188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B33"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>HillierLW 2004 Sequence and comparative analysis of the chicken genome provide unique perspectives on vertebrate evolution. Nature 432:695–716.15592404 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B34"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>HoeggSBrinkmannHTaylorJSMeyerA 2004 Phylogenetic timing of the fish-specific genome duplication correlates with the diversification of Teleost fish. J Mol Evol 59:190–203.15486693 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B35"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>HoweK 2013 The zebrafish reference genome sequence and its relationship to the human genome. Nature 496:498–503.23594743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B36"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>HurleyIHaleMEPrinceVE 2005 Duplication events and the evolution of segmental identity. Evol Dev. 7:556–567.16336409 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B37"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>InoueJGMiyaMTsukamotoKNishidaM 2003 Basal actinopterygian relationships: a mitogenomic perspective on the phylogeny of the “ancient fish”. Mol Phylogenet Evol. 26:110–120.12470943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B38"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>JaillonO 2004 Genome duplication in the teleost fish Tetraodon nigroviridis reveals the early vertebrate proto-karyotype. Nature 431:946–957.15496914 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B39"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>JonesFC 2012 The genomic basis of adaptive evolution in threespine sticklebacks. Nature 484:55–61.22481358 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B40"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>JonesP 2014 InterProScan 5: genome-scale protein function classification. Bioinformatics 30:1236–1240.24451626 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B41"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>KasaharaM 2007 The medaka draft genome and insights into vertebrate genome evolution. Nature 447:714–719.17554307 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B42"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>KorfI 2004 Gene finding in novel genomes. BMC Bioinformatics 5:59.15144565 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B43"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>KottelatM. 2013 Scleropages formosus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species, Version 2014.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2305/IUCN.UK.2011-1.RLTS.T20034A9137739.en">http://dx.doi.org/10.2305/IUCN.UK.2011-1.RLTS.T20034A9137739.en</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B44"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>LagesenK 2007 RNAmmer: consistent and rapid annotation of ribosomal RNA genes. Nucleic Acids Res. 35:3100–3108.17452365 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B45"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>LanfearRCalcottBKainerDMayerCStamatakisA 2014 Selecting optimal partitioning schemes for phylogenomic datasets. BMC Evol Biol. 14:82.24742000 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B46"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>LauderGVLiemKF 1983 The evolution and interrelationships of the actinopterygian fishes. Bull Mus Comp Zool. 150:95–197. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B47"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Laurin-LemaySBrinkmannHPhilippeH 2012 Origin of land plants revisited in the light of sequence contamination and missing data. Curr Biol. 22:R593–R594.22877776 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B48"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>LiGQWilsonMVH 1999 Early divergence of Hiodontiformes sensu stricto in East Asia and phylogeny of some Late Mesozoic teleosts from China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>In: ArratiaGSchultzeHP, editors. Mesozoic fishes 2: systematics and fossil record. Munich (Germany): Dr F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Pfiel p. 369–384. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B49"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>LiR 2010 The sequence and de novo assembly of the giant panda genome. Nature 463:311–317.20010809 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B50"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>LoweTMEddySR 1997 tRNAscan-SE: a program for improved detection of transfer RNA genes in genomic sequence. Nucleic Acids Res. 25:955–964.9023104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B51"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>MarçaisGKingsfordC 2011 A fast, lock-free approach for efficient parallel counting of occurrences of k-mers. Bioinformatics 27:764–770.21217122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B52"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Marchler-BauerABryantSH 2004 CD-Search: protein domain annotations on the fly. Nucleic Acids Res. 32:W327–W331.15215404 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B53"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Marchler-BauerA 2014 CDD: NCBI’s conserved domain database. Nucleic Acids Res. 43:222–226. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B54"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>McGaughSE 2014 The cavefish genome reveals candidate genes for eye loss. Nat Commun. 5:5307.25329095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B55"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>MeyerAVan de PeerY 2005 From 2R to 3R: evidence for a fish-specific genome duplication (FSGD). Bioessays 27:937–945.16108068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B56"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>MisofB 2013 Selecting informative subsets of sparse supermatrices increases the chance to find correct trees. BMC Bioinformatics 14:348.24299043 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B57"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Mohd-ShamsudinMI 2011 Molecular characterization of relatedness among colour variants of Asian Arowana (Scleropages formosus). Gene 490:47–53.21945689 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B58"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>MuXD 2012 Mitochondrial DNA as effective molecular markers for the genetic variation and phylogeny of the family Osteoglossidae. Gene 511:320–325.23036711 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B59"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>NagarajanNPopN 2013 Sequence assembly demystified. Nat Rev Genet. 14:157–167.23358380 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B60"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>NearTJ 2012 Resolution of ray-finned fish phylogeny and timing of diversification. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 109:13698–13703.22869754 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B61"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>NelsonJS 1994 Fish of the world. New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B62"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>NguyenLTSchmidtHAvon HaeselerAMinhBQ 2015 IQ-TREE: a fast and effective stochastic algorithm for estimating maximum-likelihood phylogenies. Mol Biol Evol. 32:268–274.25371430 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B63"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>OpazoJCButtsGTNeryMFStorzJFHoffmannFG 2013 Whole-genome duplication and the functional diversification of teleost fish hemoglobins. Mol Biol Evol. 30:140–153.22949522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B64"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>ParraGBradnamKKorfI 2007 CEGMA: a pipeline to accurately annotate core genes in eukaryotic genomes. Bioinformatics 23:1061–1067.17332020 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B65"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>PattengaleNDAlipourMBininda-EmondsORPMoretBMEStamatakisA 2009 How many bootstrap replicates are necessary? In: BatzoglouS, editor. Research in computational molecular biology. Berlin Heidelberg: Springer p. 184–200. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B66"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>PattersonC. 1998 Comments on basal teleosts and teleostean phylogeny, by Gloria Arratia. Copeia 1107–1109. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B67"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>PattersonCRosenDE 1977 Review of ichthyodectiform and other Mesozoic teleost fishes, and the theory and practice of classifying fossils. Bull Am Mus Nat Hist. 158:81–172. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B68"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>PengY 2013 IDBA-tran: a more robust de novo de Bruijn graph assembler for transcriptomes with uneven expression levels. Bioinformatics 29:i326–i334.23813001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B69"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>PriceMNDehalPSArkinAP 2010 FastTree 2—approximately maximum-likelihood trees for large alignments. PLoS One 5:e9490.20224823 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B70"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Robinson-RechaviM 2001 Euteleost fish genomes are characterized by expansion of gene families. Genome Res. 11:781–788.11337474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B71"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>RondeauEB 2014 The genome and linkage map of the northern pike (Esox lucius): conserved synteny revealed between the salmonid sister group and the Neoteleostei. PLoS One 9:e102089.25069045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B72"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>SalichosLRokasA 2013 Inferring ancient divergences requires genes with strong phylogenetic signals. Nature 497:327–331.23657258 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B73"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="?"><plain>SantiniFHarmonLCarnevaleGAlfaroM 2009 Did genome duplication drive the origin of teleosts? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>A comparative study of diversification in ray-finned fishes. BMC Evol Biol. 9:194.19664233 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B74"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>SchartlM 2013 The genome of the platyfish, Xiphophorus maculatus, provides insights into evolutionary adaptation and several complex traits. Nat Genet. 45:567–572.23542700 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B75"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>SchreiberFPatricioMMuffatoMPignatelliMBatemanA 2014 TreeFam v9: a new website, more species and orthology-on-the-fly. Nucleic Acids Res. 42:D922–D925.24194607 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B76"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>ShanYGrasR 2011 43 genes support the lungfish-coelacanth grouping related to the closest living relative of tetrapods with the Bayesian method under the coalescence model. BMC Res Notes. 4:49.21385375 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B77"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>ShenXY 2014 The first transcriptome and genetic linkage map for Asian arowana. Mol Ecol Resour. 14:622–635.24354690 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B78"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>ShresthaR 2014 QTrim: a novel tool for the quality trimming of sequence reads generated using the Roche/454 sequencing platform. BMC Bioinformatics 15:33.24479419 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B79"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>StamatakisA 2014 RAxML version 8: a tool for phylogenetic analysis and post-analysis of large phylogenies. Bioinformatics 30:1312–1313.24451623 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B80"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>StarB 2011 The genome sequence of Atlantic cod reveals a unique immune system. Nature 477:207–210.21832995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B81"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>TajimaF 1993 Simple methods for testing the molecular evolutionary clock hypothesis. Genetics 135:599–607.8244016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B82"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>TakezakiN 2004 The phylogenetic relationship of tetrapod, coelacanth, and lungfish revealed by the sequences of forty-four nuclear genes. Mol Biol Evol. 21:1512–1524.15128875 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B83"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>TamuraKStecherGPetersonDFilipskiAKumarS 2013 MEGA6: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0. Mol Biol Evol. 30:2725–2729.24132122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B84"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>TaylorJSVan de PeerYBraaschIMeyerA 2001 Comparative genomics provides evidence for an ancient genome duplication event in fish. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci. 356:1661–1679.11604130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B85"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>VenkateshB 2014 Elephant shark genome provides unique insights into gnathostome evolution. Nature 505:174–179.24402279 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B86"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>VenterJC 2001 The sequence of the human genome. Science 291:1304–1351.11181995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B87"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>WangQ 2012 Community annotation and bioinformatics workforce development in concert—Little Skate Genome Annotation Workshops and Jamborees. Database (Oxford) 2012:bar064.22434832 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B88"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>WuTDWatanabeCK 2005 GMAP: a genomic mapping and alignment program for mRNA and EST sequences. Bioinformatics 21:1859–1875.15728110 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B89"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>WyffelsJ 2014 SkateBase, an elasmobranch genome project and collection of molecular resources for chondrichthyan fishes. F1000Res. 3:191.25309735 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B90"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>XuP 2014 Genome sequence and genetic diversity of the common carp, Cyprinus carpio. Nat Genet. 46:1212–1219.25240282 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B91"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>YangYSmithSA 2014 Orthology inference in nonmodel organisms using transcriptomes and low-coverage genomes: improving accuracy and matrix occupancy for phylogenomics. Mol Biol Evol. 31:3081–3092.25158799 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B92"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>YueGLiewWOrbanL 2006 The complete mitochondrial genome of a basal teleost, the Asian arowana (Scleropages formosus, Osteoglossidae). BMC Genomics 7:242.16989663 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B93"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>ZiminAV 2013 The MaSuRCA genome assembler. Bioinformatics 29:2669–2677.23990416 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evv186-B94"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>ZouMGuoBTaoWArratiaGHeS 2012 Integrating multi-origin expression data improves the resolution of deep phylogeny of ray-finned fish (Actinopterygii). Sci Rep. 2:66522993690 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
