<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?subarticle report12702?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">F1000Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">F1000Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">F1000Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>F1000Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2046-1402</issn><publisher><publisher-name>F1000Research</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4776736</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/f1000research.7195.2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Note</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Articles</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell Growth &amp; Division</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Control of Gene Expression</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Effect of the synthesis of rice non-symbiotic hemoglobins 1 and 2 in the recombinant Escherichia coli TB1 growth </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><fn-group content-type="pub-status"><fn><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>[version 2; referees: 2 approved] </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Álvarez-Salgado</surname><given-names>Emma</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arredondo-Peter</surname><given-names>Raúl</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="a1">
<label>1</label>Laboratorio de Biofísica y Biología Molecular, Centro de Investigación en Dinámica Celular, Instituto de Investigación en Ciencias Básicas y Aplicadas, Universidad Autónoma del Estado de Morelos, Cuernavaca, Morelos, 62210, Mexico</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email xlink:href="mailto:ra@uaem.mx">ra@uaem.mx</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>EAS and RAP conceived the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>EAS executed the experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>RAP prepared the first draft of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>EAS and RAP revised the draft manuscript and have agreed to the final content. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Competing interests: No competing interests were disclosed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>1053</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2016 Álvarez-Salgado E and Arredondo-Peter R</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Licence, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="f1000research-4-8834.pdf"/><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Non-symbiotic hemoglobins (nsHbs) are widely distributed in land plants, including rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>These proteins are classified into type 1 (nsHbs-1) and type 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The O 2-affinity of nsHbs-1 is very high mostly because of an extremely low O 2-dissociation rate constant resulting in that nsHbs-1 apparently do not release O 2 after oxygenation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Thus, it is possible that the in vivo function of nsHbs-1 is other than O 2-transport. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Based on the properties of multiple Hbs it was proposed that nsHbs-1 could play diverse roles in rice organs, however the in vivo activity of rice nsHbs-1 has been poorly analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>An in vivo analysis for rice nsHbs-1 is essential to elucidate the biological function(s) of these proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Rice Hb1 and Hb2 are nsHbs-1 that have been generated in recombinant Es cherichia coli TB1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The rice Hb1 and Hb2 amino acid sequence, tertiary structure and rate and equilibrium constants for the reaction of O 2 are highly similar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Thus, it is possible that rice Hb1 and Hb2 function similarly in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>As an initial approach to test this hypothesis we analyzed the effect of the synthesis of rice Hb1 and Hb2 in the recombinant E. coli TB1 growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Effect of the synthesis of the O 2-carrying soybean leghemoglobin a, cowpea leghemoglobin II and Vitreoscilla Hb in the recombinant E. coli TB1 growth was also analyzed as an O 2-carrier control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Our results showed that synthesis of rice Hb1, rice Hb2, soybean Lb a, cowpea LbII and Vitreoscilla Hb inhibits the recombinant E. coli TB1 growth and that growth inhibition was stronger when recombinant E. coli TB1 synthesized rice Hb2 than when synthesized rice Hb1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>These results suggested that rice Hb1 and Hb2 could function differently in vivo. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Function</kwd><kwd>heterologous expression</kwd><kwd>in vivo</kwd><kwd>Oryza</kwd><kwd>oxygen</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>SEP-PROMEP</funding-source><award-id>UAEMor-PTC-01-01/PTC23</award-id></award-group><award-group id="fund-2"><funding-source>Consejo Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnología</funding-source><award-id>25229N</award-id><award-id>42873Q</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>This work was partially financed by SEP-PROMEP (grant number UAEMor-PTC-01-01/PTC23) and Consejo Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnología (CoNaCyT grant numbers 25229N and 42873Q), México, to RA-P.</funding-statement><funding-statement><italic>I confirm that the funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</italic></funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="version-changes"><sec sec-type="version-changes"><label>Revised</label><title>Amendments from Version 1</title><p>We incorporated some of the references suggested by Dr. Matilla into the revised version of the article and indicated in the legend to Figure 1 that molecular sizes and molecular masses correspond to the Hb cDNAs and proteins analyzed in this work.</p></sec></notes></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro"><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Non-symbiotic hemoglobins (nsHbs) are O 2-binding proteins widely distributed in land plants, including rice 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The nsHbs are classified into type 1 and type 2 (nsHbs-1 and nsHbs-2, respectively) based on sequence similarity and O 2-affinity 2, 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The O 2-affinity of nsHbs-1 is very high mostly because of an extremely low O 2-dissociation ( k off) rate constant 3– 5 resulting in that nsHbs-1 apparently do not release O 2 after oxygenation 6, 7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the O 2-affinity of nsHbs-2 is moderate mostly because of a moderate to high k off rate constant for O 2, thus apparently nsHbs-2 easily release O 2 after oxygenation 2, 3, 6, 7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Hence, it is possible that the in vivo function of nsHbs-1 is other than O 2-transport and that nsHbs-2 function in vivo as O 2-carriers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Five copies ( hb1 to 5) of the nshb gene have been detected in the rice genome, which are differentially expressed in embryonic and vegetative organs from plants growing under normal and stress conditions 8– 11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Based on the available information on the properties of rice nsHbs and data from the analysis of other plant and non-plant Hbs, it was proposed that rice nsHbs could exhibit a variety of functions in vivo, including O 2-transport, O 2-sensing, NO-scavenging and redox-signaling 6, 12, 13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>However, the in vivo activity of rice nsHbs has been poorly analyzed 12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>An in vivo analysis for rice nsHbs is essential to elucidate the biological function(s) of these proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>An approach to analyze the in vivo activity of nsHbs is generating knock out rice for individual nshb genes, however this is complicated because of the existence of five copies of nshb in the rice genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>An alternative approach to analyze the in vivo activity of rice nsHbs is examining individual rice nsHbs in a heterologous system, such as recombinant Escherichia coli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Rice Hb1 4 and Hb2 14 are nsHbs-1 that have been generated in recombinant E. coli TB1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The rice Hb1 and Hb2 amino acid sequence 4, tertiary structure 15 and rate and equilibrium constants for the reaction of O 2 4, 14 are highly similar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Thus, it is possible that rice Hb1 and Hb2 function similarly in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>As an initial approach to test this hypothesis we analyzed the effect of the synthesis of rice Hb1 and Hb2 in the recombinant E. coli TB1 growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Our results showed that synthesis of rice Hb1 and Hb2 inhibited the recombinant E. coli TB1 growth and that growth inhibition was stronger when recombinant E. coli TB1 synthesized rice Hb2 than when synthesized rice Hb1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Untransformed (wild-type) and transformed (recombinant) E. coli TB1 (Invitrogen, CA, USA) containing the constitutive pEMBL18 +::Hb1 4, pEMBL18 +::Hb2 14, pEMBL18 +::Lb a 16, pEMBL18 +::LbII 17 and pUC18::VHb 18 plasmids were grown in LB broth (Sigma-Aldrich, MO, USA) at 37°C with shaking at 200 rpm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Plasmids pEMBL18 +::Lb a, pEMBL18 +::LbII and pUC18::VHb were included as an O 2-carrier control since they code for the synthesis of the O 2-carrying soybean leghemoglobin a (Lb a), cowpea leghemoglobin II (LbII) 17, 19, 20 and Vitreoscilla Hb (VHb) 21, 22, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The existence of the VHb insert into the pUC18::VHb plasmid was verified by PCR (30 cycles at 55°C/30s for annealing, 72°C/30s for extension and 95°C/30s for denaturation) using specific oligonucleotides (VitHb/ATG: 5´-ATG TTA GAC CAG CAA ACC ATT-3´ and VitHb/TAA: 5´-TTA TTC AAC CGC TTG AGC GTA-3´) designed from the vhb sequence deposited in the Genbank database under the accession number X13516. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The existence of the Hb1, Hb2, Lb a and LbII inserts into the pEMBL18 +::Hb1, pEMBL18 +::Hb2, pEMBL18 +::Lb a and pEMBL18 +::LbII plasmids, respectively, was verified by EcoRI- and NcoI (Invitrogen, CA, USA) -double digestion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Inserts were detected by electrophoresis in a 1.4% agarose gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The existence of recombinant Hbs in cell soluble extracts was verified by SDS-PAGE in a 12.5% polyacrylamide gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Evaluation of the effect of the Hb synthesis in the recombinant E. coli TB1 growth was performed in 50 ml cultures inoculated with ≈5 × 10 8 colony forming units from a 20 ml overnight culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Wild-type E. coli TB1 was included as control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>All assays were performed in triplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Cell growth was quantitated by spectrophotometry using λ = 650 nm for an 8.5 h period. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Results and discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Electrophoretic analysis of the PCR reaction and EcoRI- and NcoI-double digestions showed that plasmids isolated from recombinant E. coli TB1 contained inserts corresponding to the rice Hb1 4, rice Hb2 4, soybean Lb a 16, cowpea LbII 17 and Vitreoscilla Hb 18 cDNAs ( Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Likewise, analysis by SDS-PAGE showed that rice Hb1, rice Hb2, soybean Lb a, cowpea LbII and Vitreoscilla Hb existed in the soluble extracts of recombinant E. coli TB1 ( Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>This evidence indicated that rice Hb1, rice Hb2, soybean Lb a, cowpea LbII and Vitreoscilla Hb were synthesized by recombinant E. coli TB1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1. </label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>(A) Detection of Vitreoscilla Hb PCR fragment and soybean Lb a, cowpea LbII, rice Hb1 and rice Hb2 cDNAs from recombinant E. coli TB1 by agarose gel electrophoresis. PCR fragment and cDNA sizes are within the 435 to 507 base pairs range, which corresponds to the molecular sizes of the Hb cDNAs analyzed here. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Molecular size markers are indicated in base pairs. (B) Detection of Vitreoscilla Hb, soybean Lb a, cowpea LbII, rice Hb1 and rice Hb2 proteins (arrow heads) from recombinant E. coli TB1 soluble extracts by SDS-PAGE. A 20 to 50 μg aliquot of total soluble proteins was loaded onto each lane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Recombinant Hb masses are within the 14 to 18.4 KD range, which corresponds to the molecular masses of the Hbs analyzed here. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Mass markers are indicated in kD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="f1000research-4-8834-g0000"/></fig><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Figure 2 shows that synthesis of rice Hb1, rice Hb2, soybean Lb a, cowpea LbII and Vitreoscilla Hb inhibited the recombinant E. coli TB1 growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>This was unexpected for soybean Lb a, cowpea LbII and Vitreoscilla Hb because these proteins would promote cell growth due to their O 2-transport activity 17, 19– 22. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>However, under the conditions tested in this work apparently soybean Lb a, cowpea LbII and Vitreoscilla Hb affected some aspects of the recombinant E. coli TB1 metabolism, possibly owed to the constitutive expression of these proteins into the host cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Synthesis of rice Hb1 inhibited the recombinant E. coli TB1 growth similarly (∼37%) to the synthesis of soybean Lb a, cowpea LbII and Vitreoscilla Hb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>This observation suggests that rice Hb1 could function in vivo similarly to O 2-carrying Hbs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Likewise, synthesis of rice Hb2 also inhibited the recombinant E. coli TB1 growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>However, growth inhibition was stronger (∼61%) when recombinant E. coli TB1 synthesized rice Hb2 than when synthesized rice Hb1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>This observation suggests that rice Hb2 could function in vivo by scavenging O 2, possibly owing to its extremely low k off rate constant for O 2 14. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="f2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2. </label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Growth of wild-type (TB1) and recombinant (VHb, Lb a, LbII, Hb1 and Hb2) E. coli. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Values (mean ± SD) correspond to three replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>See the Methods section for experimental details. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="f1000research-4-8834-g0001"/></fig></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Results presented in this work suggest that in spite of the high similarity between rice Hb1 and Hb2 these proteins could function differently in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>In order to elucidate the apparent metabolic effects generated by the synthesis of rice Hb1 and Hb2, future work might focus on the physiological and biochemical characterization of recombinant E. coli TB1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>This may include measuring cell respiratory rates and identifying cell proteins and metabolites using oximetry and proteomic and metabolomic approaches, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Results from these analyses could provide valuable information to understand the in vivo function of rice nsHbs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Authors wish to express their gratitude to Dr. Dale A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Webster (Illinois Institute of Technology, USA) for kindly providing the pUC18::VHb plasmid. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="ref-1"><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>1 Garrocho-VillegasVGopalasubramaniamSKArredondo-PeterR: Plant hemoglobins: what we know six decades after their discovery. Gene. 2007;398(1–2):78–85. 10.1016/j.gene.2007.01.035 <?supplied-pmid 17540516?>17540516 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-2"><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>2 SmaggheBJHoyJAPercifieldR: Review: correlations between oxygen affinity and sequence classifications of plant hemoglobins. Biopolymers. 2009;91(12):1083–1096. 10.1002/bip.21256 <?supplied-pmid 19441024?>19441024 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-3"><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>3 TrevaskisBWattsRAAnderssonCR: Two hemoglobin genes in Arabidopsis thaliana: the evolutionary origins of leghemoglobins. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1997;94(22):12230–12234. 10.1073/pnas.94.22.12230 <?supplied-pmid 9342391?>9342391 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-4"><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>4 Arredondo-PeterRHargroveMSSarathG: Rice hemoglobins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Gene cloning, analysis, and O 2-binding kinetics of a recombinant protein synthesized in Escherichia coli. Plant Physiol. 1997;115(3):1259–1266. 10.1104/pp.115.3.1259 <?supplied-pmid 9390447?>9390447 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-5"><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>5 DuffSMWittenbergJBHillRD: Expression, purification, and properties of recombinant barley ( Hordeum sp.) hemoglobin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Optical spectra and reactions with gaseous ligands. J Biol Chem. 1997;272(27):16746–16752. 10.1074/jbc.272.27.16746 <?supplied-pmid 9201978?>9201978 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-6"><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>6 Arredondo-PeterRHargroveMSMoranJF: Plant hemoglobins. Plant Physiol. 1998;118(4):1121–1125. 10.1104/pp.118.4.1121 <?supplied-pmid 9847086?>9847086 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-7"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>7 HoyJAHargroveMS: The structure and function of plant hemoglobins. Plant Physiol Biochem. 2008;46(3):371–379. 10.1016/j.plaphy.2007.12.016 <?supplied-pmid 18321722?>18321722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-8"><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>8 Garrocho-VillegasVBustos-RiveraGGoughJ: Expression and in silico structural analysis of a rice ( Oryza sativa) hemoglobin 5. Plant Physiol Biochem. 2008;46(10):855–859. 10.1016/j.plaphy.2008.05.004 <?supplied-pmid 18586507?>18586507 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-9"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>9 Lira-RuanVRossEJHSarathG: Mapping and analysis of a hemoglobin gene family from rice ( Oryza sativa). Plant Physiol Biochem. 2002;40(3):199–202. 10.1016/S0981-9428(02)01365-7  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-10"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>10 Lira-RuanVRuiz-KubliMArredondo-PeterR: Expression of non-symbiotic hemoglobin 1 and 2 genes in rice ( Oryza sativa) embryonic organs. Commun Integr Biol. 2011;4(4):457–458. <?supplied-pmid 21966570?>21966570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-11"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>11 Lira-RuanVSarathGKlucasRV: Synthesis of hemoglobins in rice ( Oryza sativa var. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Jackson) plants growing in normal and stress conditions. Plant Sci. 2001;161(2):279–287. 10.1016/S0168-9452(01)00411-3 <?supplied-pmid 11448759?>11448759 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-12"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>12 Arredondo-PeterRMoranJFSarathG: Rice ( Oryza) hemoglobins [version 2; referees: 2 approved]. F1000Res. 2014;3:253. 10.12688/f1000research.5530.2 <?supplied-pmid 25653837?>25653837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-13"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>13 VigeolasHHühnDGeigenbergerP: Nonsymbiotic hemoglobin-2 leads to an elevated energy state and to a combined increase in polyunsaturated fatty acids and total oil content when overexpressed in developing seeds of transgenic Arabidopsis plants. Plant Physiol. 2011;155(3):1435–1444. 10.1104/pp.110.166462 <?supplied-pmid 21205621?>21205621 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-14"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>14 SmaggheBJSarathGRossE: Slow ligand binding kinetics dominate ferrous hexacoordinate hemoglobin reactivities and reveal differences between plants and other species. Biochemistry. 2006;45(2):561–570. 10.1021/bi051902l <?supplied-pmid 16401085?>16401085 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-15"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>15 GopalasubramaniamSKGarrocho-VillegasVRiveraGB: Use of in silico (computer) methods to predict and analyze the tertiary structure of plant hemoglobins. Methods Enzymol. 2008;436:393–410. 10.1016/S0076-6879(08)36022-4 <?supplied-pmid 18237645?>18237645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-16"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>16 HargroveMSBarryJKBruckerEA: Characterization of recombinant soybean leghemoglobin a and apolar distal histidine mutants. J Mol Biol. 1997;266(5):1032–1042. 10.1006/jmbi.1996.0833 <?supplied-pmid 9086279?>9086279 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-17"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>17 Arredondo-PeterRMoranJFSarathG: Molecular cloning of the cowpea leghemoglobin II gene and expression of its cDNA in Escherichia coli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Purification and characterization of the recombinant protein. Plant Physiol. 1997;114(2):493–500. 10.1104/pp.114.2.493 <?supplied-pmid 9193085 ?>9193085 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-18"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>18 WakabayashiSMatsubaraHWebsterDA: Primary sequence of a dimeric bacterial haemoglobin from Vitreoscilla. Nature. 1986;322(6078):481–483. 10.1038/322481a0 <?supplied-pmid 3736670 ?>3736670 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-19"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>19 ApplebyCA: The origin and functions of haemoglobin in plants. Sci Progress. 1992;76(3/4):365–398. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/43421309?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents">Reference Source</ext-link>  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-20"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>20 ApplebyCABradburyJHMorrisRJ: Leghemoglobin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Kinetic, nuclear magnetic resonance, and optical studies of pH dependence of oxygen and carbon monoxide binding. J Biol Chem. 1983;258(4):2254–2259. <?supplied-pmid 6822555?>6822555 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-21"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>21 ChiPYWebsterDAStarkBC:  Vitreoscilla hemoglobin aids respiration under hypoxic conditions in its native host. Microbiol Res. 2009;164(3):267–275. 10.1016/j.micres.2006.11.018 <?supplied-pmid 17403602?>17403602 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-22"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>22 DikshitRPDikshitKLLiuYX: The bacterial hemoglobin from Vitreoscilla can support the aerobic growth of Escherichia coli lacking terminal oxidases. Arch Biochem Biophys. 1992;293(2):241–245. 10.1016/0003-9861(92)90391-9 <?supplied-pmid 1311160?>1311160 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><sub-article id="report12702" article-type="peer-review"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5256/f1000research.8834.r12702</article-id><title-group><article-title>Referee response for version 2</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Matilla</surname><given-names>Angel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="r12702a1">1</xref><role>Referee</role></contrib><aff id="r12702a1">
<label>1</label>Department of Plant Physiology, Faculty of Pharmacy, University of Santiago de Compostela, Santiago de Compostela, Spain</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Competing interests: </bold>No competing interests were disclosed.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><related-article id="d35e2016" related-article-type="peer-reviewed-article" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.12688/f1000research.7195.2">Version 2</related-article><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>recommendation</meta-name><meta-value>approve</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The authors have sufficiently addressed my concerns. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>I have read this submission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>I believe that I have an appropriate level of expertise to confirm that it is of an acceptable scientific standard. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></body></sub-article><sub-article id="report12624" article-type="peer-review"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5256/f1000research.7751.r12624</article-id><title-group><article-title>Referee response for version 1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Matilla</surname><given-names>Angel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="r12624a1">1</xref><role>Referee</role></contrib><aff id="r12624a1">
<label>1</label>Department of Plant Physiology, Faculty of Pharmacy, University of Santiago de Compostela, Santiago de Compostela, Spain</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Competing interests: </bold>No competing interests were disclosed.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><related-article id="d35e2065" related-article-type="peer-reviewed-article" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.12688/f1000research.7195.1">Version 1</related-article><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>recommendation</meta-name><meta-value>approve-with-reservations</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The work by Álvarez-Salgado and Arredondo-Peter (2015) was carefully evaluated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Broadly, this research is worthy of achieving an approval in F1000Research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>However, before it achieves this status, is necessary to carry out some minor modifications. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Thus, the first paragraph of the Introduction, referred to the different affinity of nsHbs1 and nsHb2 for O 2, needs to include some recent references (eg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Hoy and Hargrove, 2008; Smagghe et al, 2009; Thiel et al., 2011; among others). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Likewise, in the second paragraph of the Introduction (ie. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Based on the available information…. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>NO scavenging and redox-signaling) the following latest references must also be added (ie. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Siddiqui et al., 2010; Vigeolas et al., 2010, among others). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>With respect to Res &amp; Discuss, (i) the first paragraph should include some reference to show that the bands referred by the authors (Fig. 1A) specifically belong to rice (Hb1, Hb2), soybean (LBA), cowpea (LbII) and Vitreoscilla (Hb) cDNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>This fact is key in this work. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Likewise, bands corresponding to VHb and Lba (Fig. 1B) are confusing to the reader; (ii) I would eliminate from Fig. 2 the results of LBA, LbII and HBv growth (include as data not shown) because the main importance of this work are the results concerning nb1 and nbII; (iii) "... these proteins would promote cell growth due to their O 2-transport activity"; this conclusion is based in old results and is very risky; this growth promotion should also be referred to higher plants?; please discuss; and (iv) I repeat, some actual references must be also included into discussion. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>I have read this submission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>I believe that I have an appropriate level of expertise to confirm that it is of an acceptable scientific standard, however I have significant reservations, as outlined above. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></body></sub-article><sub-article id="report11632" article-type="peer-review"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5256/f1000research.7751.r11632</article-id><title-group><article-title>Referee response for version 1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="r11632a1">1</xref><role>Referee</role></contrib><aff id="r11632a1">
<label>1</label>Department of Plant Science, University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, MB, Canada</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Competing interests: </bold>No competing interests were disclosed.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><related-article id="d35e2124" related-article-type="peer-reviewed-article" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.12688/f1000research.7195.1">Version 1</related-article><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>recommendation</meta-name><meta-value>approve</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>This is an interesting approach to possibly differentiating between the functions of this group of proteins.  A fundamental question that arises out of this work is why do hemoglobin proteins inhibit E. coli growth? The growth differences between the rice Pgb1.1-transformed line and the rice Pgb1.2 line is particularly interesting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>I would be cautious, however, in attempting to interpret the results with respect to the proteins possibly behaving as oxygen carriers/transporters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="?"><plain>My concerns are based on the following: Why would a unicellular organism without mitochondria require an oxygen carrier since oxidative phosphorylation occurs on the plasma membrane?If plant phytoglobins have an oxygen carrier function would you not expect the two class 1 phytoglobins to have the same effect since they both have similar oxygen binding characteristics?Why would you anticipate that Pgb1.2 might participate more in NO scavenging than Pgb1.1 in E. coli if they both have similar configurations in the heme pocket? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Is it not the class 2 Pgbs that are suggested to possibly being less amenable to NO scavenging?Is it possible that the expression of the class 2 protein is interfering with some function of the native flavohemoglobin in E. coli?Although E. coli does not have a true nucleus, is it possible that the protein is specifically interfering with transcriptional/translation functions in the chromosome, e.g., the N-end rule pathway as one possibility?My other comment concerns the terminology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The individuals who work in this area agreed to forego the use of the term "nonsymbiotic hemoglobins" at an international meeting in 2014, replacing it with "phytoglobin", since the original designation does not appropriately describe the protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>I would hope that the authors consider modifying the manuscript to ensure that the name change becomes recognized in the literature. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>I have read this submission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>I believe that I have an appropriate level of expertise to confirm that it is of an acceptable scientific standard. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></body><sub-article id="comment1752" article-type="response"><front-stub><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arredondo-Peter</surname><given-names>Raul</given-names></name><aff>Universidad Autonoma del Estado de Morelos, Mexico</aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Competing interests: </bold>No competing interests were disclosed.No competing interests were disclosed.No competing interests were disclosed.No competing interests were disclosed.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></pub-date></front-stub><body><p><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>We thank Dr. Robert Hill for evaluating this article and providing constructive comments and suggestions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>We agree with Dr. Hill´s comments corresponding to questions 1 to 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Undoubtedly they should also be considered in future research focused to elucidate the physiological effects of the synthesis of rice non-symbiotic hemoglobins 1 and 2 in recombinant E. coli TB1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Regarding the terminology, we decided to not change the term “non-symbiotic hemoglobins 1 and 2” by “phytoglobins 1.1 and 1.2” (which was accepted in the 2014 XVIII Oxygen-Binding and Sensing Proteins meeting) because details for the accepted nomenclature have not been published. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Thus, the accepted nomenclature is not yet widely available to individuals working/interested in the plant hemoglobins field. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Hence, replacing the term non-symbiotic hemoglobins 1 and 2 (which has been used for many years in the literature) by the novel term phytoglobins 1.1 and 1.2 could result as confusing to readers of this article. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></body></sub-article></sub-article></article>
