<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Mol Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Mol Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijms</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1422-0067</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4346909</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25658800</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms16023493</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ijms-16-03493</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Transcriptome Profiling and Identification of Transcription Factors in Ramie (Boehmeria nivea L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Gaud) in Response to PEG Treatment, Using Illumina Paired-End Sequencing Technology </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>Xia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-ijms-16-03493">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Jie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-ijms-16-03493">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Jingyu</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Yiwen</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Lunjin</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Bo</given-names></name><xref rid="c1-ijms-16-03493" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Lijun</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Dingxiang</given-names></name><xref rid="c1-ijms-16-03493" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Rouached</surname><given-names>Hatem</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-ijms-16-03493">Key Laboratory of Crop Ecophysiology and Farming Systems in the Middle Reaches of the Yangtze River, Ministry of Agriculture; College of Plant Science and Technology, Huazhong Agricultural University, Wuhan 430070, China; E-Mails: <email>anxia111@126.com</email> (X.A.); <email>lqlcj@126.com</email> (J.C.); <email>13164612991@163.com</email> (J.Z.); <email>lywen2009@126.com</email> (Y.L.); <email>dailunjin@gmail.com</email> (L.D.); <email>liulijun@mail.hzau.edu.cn</email> (L.L.)</aff><author-notes><fn id="fn1-ijms-16-03493"><label>†</label><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>These authors contributed equally to this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><corresp id="c1-ijms-16-03493"><label>*</label>Authors to whom correspondence should be addressed; E-Mails: <email>pdxiang@mail.hzau.edu.cn</email> (D.P.); <email>wangbo@mail.hzau.edu.cn</email> (B.W.); Tel./Fax: +86-27-8728-7136 (D.P.).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>04</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>3493</fpage><lpage>3511</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 by the authors; licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license><license-p>This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Ramie (Boehmeria nivea L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Gaud), commonly known as China grass, is a perennial bast fiber plant of the Urticaceae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>In China, ramie farming, industry, and trade provide income for about five million people. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Drought stress severely affects ramie stem growth and causes a dramatic decrease in ramie fiber production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>There is a need to enhance ramie’s tolerance to drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>However, the drought stress regulatory mechanism in ramie remains unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Water stress imposed by polyethylene glycol (PEG) is a common and convenient method to evaluate plant drought tolerance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In this study, transcriptome analysis of cDNA collections from ramie subjected to PEG treatment was conducted using Illumina paired-end sequencing, which generated 170 million raw sequence reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Between leaves and roots subjected to 24 (L2 and R2) and 72 (L3 and R3) h of PEG treatment, 16,798 genes were differentially expressed (9281 in leaves and 8627 in roots). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Among these, 25 transcription factors (TFs) from the AP2 (3), MYB (6), NAC (9), zinc finger (5), and bZIP (2) families were considered to be associated with drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The identified TFs could be used to further investigate drought adaptation in ramie. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>ramie</kwd><kwd>PEG</kwd><kwd>paired-end sequencing</kwd><kwd>transcription factor</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Abiotic stresses, such as drought and high salt, are becoming increasingly common because of global climate change, and severely inhibit plant growth and development [1,2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Among all the abiotic stresses, drought has probably the most significant effect on plant distribution, growth, and productivity in natural and agricultural systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Studies on the molecular responses to drought are vital, and will ultimately lead to enhanced stress tolerance in crops [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>However, the responses and adaptations of plants subjected to drought conditions are complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>During the process of domestication, plants have developed numerous physiological and biochemical strategies to cope with adverse conditions [1,4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>For example, when the leaf-to-air vapor pressure or relative humidity changes, a plant’s leaves close their stomata to reduce water loss through transpiration; when suffering from progressive water loss, the leaves begin to curl to protect the photosynthetic machinery [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, the water content of cells is maintained by synthesizing and accumulating various small molecule compounds, such as soluble sugars [6] and proline [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the production of reactive oxygen species (ROS), which are caused by severe drought stress [8], could have detrimental effects on plant growth and development [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>To cope with oxidative damage, several enzymes are activated in plant cells, including superoxide dismutase (SOD), catalase (CAT), ascorbate peroxidase (APX), glutathione reductase (GR), and non-enzymatic antioxidants, such as ascorbic acid and glutathione [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Studies on the molecular mechanisms of plant responses to these stresses and damages are increasing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Recently, analyses of a large number of transcriptome sequence data sets have revealed many new stress-responsive genes in Arabidopsis [10] and rice [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>However, there have been few reports on ramie [12,13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Ramie is an important natural fiber crop, widely planted in China, India, and other Southeast Asian and Pacific Rim countries [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>It is the second major fiber crop after cotton in China and plays an important role in Chinese economy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Ramie fibers possess high tensile strength, antibacterial properties, and good moisture absorption characteristics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In China, ramie is mainly planted by the Yangtze River and can be harvested three times per year. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>However, the per capita arable land area is shrinking as urbanization and industrialization accelerate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is a good practice to plant ramie on sloping land so that more land can be used to grow grain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>However, ramie yields have shown dramatic decreases recently because of reduced rainfall in the summer or autumn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Thus, drought tolerance research in ramie (especially research into breeding drought-resistant varieties) has become particularly important. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>However, to date, only a few reports have focused on ramie physiological traits [12,13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>In a previous study, research into the ramie universal transcriptome has identified 24 genes that could be transcription factors (TFs), but only 12 of them have been shown to be authentically involved in drought stress responses [13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>In this study, hydroponic ramie seedlings, propagated from stem cuttings of cultivar Huazhu No. 5 and transplanted into half-strength Hoagland’s solution, were generated and subjected to simulated drought stress (PEG treatments). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Four physiological traits were observed (the relative water content, RWC; the peroxidase activity, POD; the malondialdehyde content, MDA; and the proline content) from the leaves of the seedlings to distinguish the stress severity and for collecting samples for transcriptome sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>A total of 16,798 (9281 in leaves and 8627 in roots, respectively) unigenes were differentially expressed in the transcriptome data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Among these, 25 TFs from the AP2 (3), MYB (6), NAC (9), zinc finger (5), and bZIP (2) families were considered to be associated with drought stress because of their expression patterns (coincided with the propensities of the observed physiological traits) in leaves or roots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>This study increased our understanding of the molecular responses to drought in ramie, which will improve drought resistance breeding in ramie. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Physiological Responses of Ramie to Drought Stress </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Leaves harvested at 0, 12, 24, 48, and 72 h after being treated with 15% PEG6000 (w/v) were prepared for measuring the four physiological traits (the RWC, the POD activity, the MDA content, and the proline content). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>RWC seemed to decline consistently (Figure 1a), most significantly after 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The highest RWC was at 0 h and the lowest RWC was at 72 h under drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The critical time-points were observed as 0, 24, and 72 h after drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The POD activity first increased but then decreased (Figure 1b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The highest POD activity was at 24 h and the lowest POD activity was at 0 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The POD activity increased most significantly after 12 h and declined most significantly after 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The POD activity remained stable after 72 h under drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The critical time-point was 24 h after drought stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-16-03493-f001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Four physiological traits of leaves from ramie seedlings under drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>(a) the RWC of leaves; (b) the POD activity; (c) the MDA content; (d) the proline content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The leaves were harvested at 0, 12, 24, 48, and 72 h after treatment with 15% (w/v) PEG6000. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The error bars mean standard error. a, b, c, d, and e indicated significant differences (p &lt; 0.05) among different time-points. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-03493-g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>By contrast, the MDA and proline content increased throughout the entire drought stress periods (Figure 1c,d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The highest MDA and proline contents were at 72 h and the lowest were at 0 h under drought stress, the critical time-points were determined as 0 and 72 h after drought stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Based on the critical time-points of the change of the RWC, the POD activity, the MDA content, and the proline content under drought stress, we chose three time-points (0, 24, and 72 h after PEG treatment), to investigate the transcriptome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Illumina Paired-End Sequencing, Reads Assembly, and Annotation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Illumina paired-end sequencing technology yields 2 × 300 bp independent reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>After stringent quality checking and data cleaning, approximately 33,976,322,460 bp (30G) of high-quality data (94.02% of the raw data) were generated under the Q20 standard. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The sequence data generated in this study have been deposited at the NCBI in the Short Read Archive database under accession SRP041143. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Assembly of the high-quality sequencing reads yielded 138,381 unigenes, with an average length of 730.6 bp and a range from 201 to 20,860 bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The lengths distribution of the assembled contigs is shown in Figure 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The lengths distribution of the unigenes is given in Figure 3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>To provide putative annotations for the assembled unigenes, Blastp similarity searches were performed against the non-redundant protein (Nr) and the Swiss-Prot protein databases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The paired-end reads were realigned to contigs and the contigs in one transcript were assembled by Trinity and were defined as unigenes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The unigene sequences were compared to the non-redundant (nr) protein database with a cut-off E-value of 1 × 10−5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>As a result, 47,565 (Supplementary file 1) unigenes (34%) were annotated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>All sequences of the unigene are shown in Supplementary file 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-16-03493-f002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Length distribution of assembled contigs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-03493-g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-16-03493-f003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Length distribution of assembled unigenes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-03493-g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Functional Classification and Metabolic Pathway Assignment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>To provide putative functional classifications for the transcriptome assembly, all the assembled unigenes were evaluated using Blastp similarity searches against the Gene Ontology (GO) database, which classified 22,058 (Supplementary file 3) matched unigenes into the three functional categories (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>In molecular function, those that matched unique sequences were clustered into 25 subcategories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The largest subcategory in the molecular function class was “catalytic activity” (11,849; 21.54%) and the second was “binding” (11,620; 21.12%) (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>For the cellular component category, the sequences were divided into 11 subcategories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The most represented cellular components were “cell” (18,176; 30.58%) and “intracellular” (16,053; 27.01%) (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>For the biological process category, the sequences were classified into 21 subcategories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The most represented biological processes were “cellular process” (16,499; 27.67%) and “macromolecule metabolism” (10,676; 17.90%) (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) [14] database can be used to analyze the gene products of metabolic processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>A total of 6502 (Supplementary file 4) assembled sequences were observed to be associated with 2755 predicted KEGG metabolic pathways, and were grouped into five KEGG biochemical pathways: Genetic information processing, organismal systems, cellular processes, environmental information processing and metabolism (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The metabolic pathways were well represented by carbohydrate metabolism, amino acid metabolism, energy metabolism, lipid metabolism, nucleotide metabolism, metabolism of cofactors and vitamins, and the biodegradation and metabolism of xenobiotics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Those pathways related to genetic information processing included genes involved in translation, transcription, replication and repair, and folding, sorting and degradation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Pathways related to cellular processes and environmental information processing were also well represented by unigenes from ramie. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>These results represented a valuable resource for investigating metabolic pathways in ramie. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-16-03493-f004" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Histogram of Gene Ontology (GO) classifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>(A) Molecular function (green); (B) Cellular component (red); (C) Biological process (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The histogram indicates the number of unigenes that have GO annotations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-03493-g004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-16-03493-f005" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>KEGG classification of assembled unigenes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>A total of 6502 assembled sequences were associated with 2755 predicted KEGG metabolic pathways and were assigned to five KEGG biochemical pathways: (A) cellular processes; (B) environmental information processing; (C) genetic information processing; (D) metabolism; and (E) organismal systems. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-03493-g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Analysis of Differential Gene Expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Gene expression was calculated according to the reads per kilo base of transcript per million reads mapped (RPKM) method [15], using the MA-plot-based method with Random Sampling (MARS) model from the DEGseq [16] program package. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>16,798 (Supplementary file 5) genes (12.14% of all genes) were identified as differentially expressed genes (DEGs) in roots and leaves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>These amounted to 9842 genes (accounting for 7.11% of all genes) in the leaves of ramie and 9748 genes (accounting for 7.04%) in the roots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The numbers of unigenes that had differential expression patterns are shown in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Seven altered pathways were significantly enriched (corrected p-value ≤ 0.05), with genes involved in amino acid metabolism, carbohydrate metabolism, lipid metabolism, signal transduction, translation, energy metabolism, and folding, sorting, and degradation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>These seven altered pathways were the most significantly enriched in the ramie leaves (Supplementary file 6); the Y-axis denotes the numbers of unigenes that were annotated to the enrichment between the two sample combinations in each KEGG pathway). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>For roots, the altered pathways contained xenobiotic biodegradation and metabolism genes, in addition to the seven altered pathways previously mentioned (Supplementary file 6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="ijms-16-03493-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">ijms-16-03493-t001_Table 1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Numbers of unigenes that had differential expression patterns during drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The comparisons were conducted from posterior samples to anterior ones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>For example, the first row indicates that there were 2631 down-regulated unigenes and 1450 were up-regulated unigenes in sample L2 compared with sample L1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Sample </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Up-Regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Down-Regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>L1–L2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>1450 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>2631 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>L2–L3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>2281 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>3120 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>R1–R2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>3872 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>1913 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>R2–R3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>2090 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>4590 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>2.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Identification of Drought-Responsive TFs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Given that TFs appear to have a major effect on drought-responsive genes, one of the objectives of this study was to identify drought-inducible TFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Among the differentially expressed unigenes, those with expression patterns that coincided with the patterns of the physiological traits (as displayed in Figure 1) were considered important. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Generally, more unigenes were generated as “all-up” (unigenes up-regulated in L2 compared with L1, and simultaneously up-regulated in L3 compared with L2) or “all-down” patterns than “up-down” (unigenes were up-regulated in L2 compared with L1, while down-regulated in L3 compared with L2) and “down-up” patterns in leaves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>While more TFs showed up-down or down-up patterns than all-up and all-down patterns in roots (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, unigenes from the five main TF families (AP2, MYB, NAC, zinc finger, and bZIP) that shared all-up or all-down patterns in leaves and up-down or down-up patterns in roots were considered to have consistent physiological trait trends and were selected for further quantification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Altogether, 25 genes were found to encode known or putative TFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Of the 25 TFs selected, three belonged to the AP2, six to the MYB, nine to the NAC, five to the zinc finger, and two to the bZIP families (Supplementary file 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>To further evaluate the role of these TFs, we analyzed their expression levels using quantitative real-time reverse transcription PCR (qRT-PCR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 6, these TFs were all-up-regulated, all-down-regulated, up–down-regulated, or down–up-regulated by drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, when the transcriptome sequencing was performed, only one cDNA library was constructed for each sample; therefore, the effectiveness of the transcriptome data was validated (due to lack of duplication when preparing the transcriptome sequencing). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Specifically, 11 unigenes (comp41385, C2; comp79146, E1; comp77912, I1; comp75203, K2; comp80737, M2; comp86676, N1; comp84340, O2; comp83977, T1; comp56037, U2; comp83361, V2 and comp58004, Y1 in Figure 6) from the 25 TFs were randomly chosen, and their expression profiles in leaves or roots (where they were picked out originally, as listed in Supplementary file 7) were tested (Supplementary file 8) using similarly treated plant samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The results showed that they had the same expression trends (Supplementary file 9) with the qRT-PCR output from the residual RNA (Figure 6), and simultaneously correlated with the transcriptome data (Supplementary file 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>These data validated our transcriptome result. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-16-03493-f006" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Expression analysis of 25 transcription factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Specifically, comp79664, comp77101 and comp41385 (A, B and C, respectively) were from the AP2 TF family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Comp56509, comp79146, comp80892, comp72628, comp73235, comp77912, comp78350, comp75203 and comp80372 (D, E, F, G, H, I, J, K and L, respectively) were from the NAC TF family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Comp80737, comp86676, comp84340, comp51469, comp54867 and comp33749 (M, N, O, P, Q and R, respectively) were from the MYB TF family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Comp95985, comp83977, comp56037, comp83361 and comp52860 (S, T, U, V and W, respectively) were from the zinc finger TF family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Comp28477 and comp58004 (X and Y, respectively) were from the bZIP TF family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>All of them were chosen for qRT-PCR quantification, using GAPDH as an internal control (Supplementary file 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The line charts A1–Y1 were carried out in leaves, while A2–Y2 were carried out in roots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Each line chart (A1–Y2) was formed from the order of samples subjected to minor, moderate, and severe drought stress (X-axis) for their quantitative results (Y-axis) in three biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The significance analyses were performed for each unigene among three samples using the ANOVA method of Sigmaplot software with a cut-off p-value of 0.05. * indicate that the corresponding unigenes shared regular expression patterns from leaves (all-up or all-down) or roots (up–down or down–up) where they were picked out (Supplementary file 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The error bars indicate the standard error. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-03493-g006"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="ijms-16-03493-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">ijms-16-03493-t002_Table 2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Numbers of unigenes with different expression patterns in leaves and roots during drought stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Samples </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>All-up </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>All-down </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Up–down </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Down–up </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Leaves </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>379 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>637 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>348 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>98 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Roots </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>57 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>3048 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>675 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Characterization of the Ramie Transcriptome </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The Illumina sequencing method, with the largest output and lowest reagent cost, has been widely used for deep sequencing of model and non-model organisms [12,17,18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>In the previous studies, the Illumina paired-end sequencing platform was used for high-throughput sequencing of the ramie transcriptome [12,13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>There were some evident advantages to this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>First, after stringent quality checking and data cleaning, approximately 33,976,322,460 bp (30G) of high-quality data (94.02% of the raw data) were generated under the Q20 standard, which was more than previous studies in ramie [12,13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Second, based on the high-quality reads, the sequencing assembly yielded 138,381 (Supplementary file 1) unigenes, which were more than that created by other transcriptome sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Third, 16,798 (Supplementary file 5) genes (12.14% of all genes) were identified as DEGs in roots or leaves, which comprised 9842 genes (accounting for 7.11% of all genes) in the leaves and 9748 genes (accounting for 7.04%) in the roots of ramie. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The number of DEGs was higher than that found in previous studies [12,13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Finally, the six samples, specifically the leaves (L1–L3) and roots (R1–R3) under increasing drought stress, were determined by the physiological traits (RWC etc., as displayed in Figure 1) and phenotypes (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Thus, understanding on molecular regulation of ramie under drought stress was specifically ascertained by the results conducted from the ramie seedlings submitted to mild (L2 and R2) and severe (L3 and R3) drought stress compared with the control (L1 and R1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The transcriptome sequence generated in this study will be valuable for further ramie research on drought stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Physiological Traits Changed under PEG Treatment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The PEG-simulated drought approach has many advantages: The water potential (ψW) can be controlled precisely and a large number of treatments can be performed quickly [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>In this study, 15% (w/v) PEG6000 was used to induce drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Many abiotic stresses trigger the production of ROS, which disrupt normal metabolism by oxidative damage of membrane lipids, proteins, and nucleic acids [20,21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>SOD and POD (among other so-called scavengers) are able to eliminate these harmful molecules [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>In this study, more unigenes were generated as all-up or all-down patterns than up–down and down–up patterns in leaves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>However, more up–down or down–up patterns than all-up and all-down patterns were observed for the root genes (Table 2), which coincided with the trends of the physiological traits (RWC, MDA, and proline content shared all-up or all-down trends, while POD activity was decreased after increasing, as indicated in Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The Five Main Families of TFs Responding to Drought Stress in Ramie </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Proteins that are characterized as being involved in the protection of plant cells from dehydration stress damage include molecule chaperons, osmotic adjustment proteins [23], ion channels [24], transporters [25] and antioxidation or detoxification proteins [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Transcriptome analyses using microarray technology, together with conventional approaches, have revealed that dozens of TFs are involved in the plant response to drought stress [27,28,29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The expressions of these stress-related functional proteins are largely regulated by specific TFs [30,31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>More than 30 families of TFs have been predicted to be associated with drought stress from Arabidopsis [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Members of the NAC, AP2, MYB, bZIP, and zinc-finger families have been shown to have roles in the regulation of plant defense and stress responses [23,24,25,26,27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Unigenes that shared all-up or all-down patterns in leaves and up-down or down-up patterns in roots were chosen for further quantitative analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Specifically, 25 TFs from the AP2 (3), MYB (6), NAC (9), zinc finger (5) and bZIP (2) families were putatively identified as directly associated with drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Further expression analysis of these genes (Figure 6) and validation of randomly chosen unigenes (Supplementary file 9) by qRT-PCR confirmed their involvement in ramie’s response to drought stress and were consistent with the transcriptome data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>NAM (no apical meristem), ATAF1-2, and CUC2 (cup-shaped cotyledon) [32] constitute one of the largest TF families (NAC), and this family is plant-specific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>NAC proteins play vital roles in many plant developmental processes [33] and also in biotic and abiotic stress tolerance [34,35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The involvement of NAC TFs in the regulation of drought responses was first reported in Arabidopsis [35]; and NAC TFs have subsequently been shown to improve drought tolerance in rice [36] and cotton [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>NAC TFs (encoding comp79664, comp77101, and comp41385) showed up–down or down–up expression patterns only in roots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Overexpression of the rice NAC gene SNAC1 improved drought and salt tolerance by enhancing root development [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>The proline content was enhanced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The MDA content was decreased in the transgenic cotton seedlings under drought and salt treatments compared with the wild-type [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>In this study, the up–down or down–up expression of three genes (comp79664, comp77101, and comp41385) might be related with the increase of MDA and proline contents throughout the entire drought stress periods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>In a previous report, 18 NAC domain factors were identified from expression profiling of stress-treated rice [37]. OsNAC10 and SNAC1/OsNAC9 were believed to have similar stress response functions because of their sequence similarity [37]. OsNAC10-overexpression in rice resulted in enlarged roots, and enhanced drought tolerance and grain yield under field drought conditions [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>These results suggested the NAC TFs might confer drought resistance through altered root architecture. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The MYB TFs were previously reported to be regulatory genes in drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>They altered the expression levels of some drought stress-responsive genes and affected several physiological traits to overcome adverse conditions [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>For example, AtMYB2 plays a role in ABA-dependent drought stress responses [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The expression of AtMYB41 is up-regulated when under drought, ABA or salt stress [40,41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>In a previous study, AtMYB60 (an R2R3-MYB gene of Arabidopsis) was shown to be involved in the regulation of stomatal movements [42]. AtMYB60 is a transcriptional modulator of physiological responses in guard cells, and its expression is negatively modulated during drought [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The water loss rate was lower in detached leaves from transgenic Arabidopsis compared with the WT leaves [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Overexpression of AtMYB44 enhanced stomatal closure to confer abiotic stress tolerance in transgenic Arabidopsis [44]. Arabidopsis, AtMYB88 and AtMYB124 are also involved in the regulation of stoma aperture development [45,46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>In this study, a MYB TF (encoding comp80737) was up-regulated, while comp86676, comp84340, and comp51469 were down-regulated in leaves under drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Comp54867 was first up-regulated and then down-regulated, whereas comp33749 was first down-regulated and then up-regulated in ramie roots under drought stress (Supplementary file 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>MYB TFs have different expression patterns in the leaves and roots of ramie. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>One MYB gene (TaMYBsdu1) was markedly up-regulated in the leaf and root of wheat under long-term drought stress [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>These data suggested that MYB TFs might have different expression patterns in different crops. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The MYB TFs might play an important role in the regulation of stomatal movements and improving water retention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>This hypothesis will require further experimental testing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The zinc finger TFs were previously reported to be positive regulators of plant tolerance to drought stress [48,49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The transgenic lines that showed DgZFP3-overexpression (a drought stress-responsive Cys2/His2-type zinc finger protein gene) in tobacco plants did not accumulate as much H2O2 under drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>They accumulated more proline and showed greater POD and superoxide dismutase activities than in the WT plants under both the control and drought stress conditions [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>DST (drought and salt tolerance) is a zinc finger transcription factor that negatively regulates stomatal closure via direct modulation of genes related to H2O2 homeostasis [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>In this study, two zinc finger TFs (comp95985 and comp83977) were down-regulated in leaves under progressive drought stress (Supplementary file 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>They may be positive regulators in the increased accumulation of proline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Otherwise, two of them (comp83361 and comp52860) were first up-regulated and then down-regulated, whereas one (comp56037) was first down-regulated and then up-regulated in ramie roots under progressive drought stress (Supplementary file 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>We propose that the zinc finger TFs may play a key role in the increased accumulation of proline (Figure 1d) and in the improved peroxidase (POD) (Figure 1b) activities, which would enhance ramie tolerance to drought stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>bZIP TFs were previously reported to be negative regulators of the drought stress response in rice [52] and tobacco [53], probably by deploying a better ROS-scavenging system to be an integral part of the defense against drought in the transgenic plants expressing PtrABF (a bZIP transcription factor) [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Our results (Figure 6X1,Y1) were consistent with previously reported results [52,53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>We inferred that the bZIP TFs might play an important role in reducing the accumulation of ROS and increasing the activities and expression levels of antioxidant enzymes (POD, Figure 1b) during drought stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The AP2/ERF family is a large family of plant-specific transcription factors that share a well-conserved DNA-binding domain [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>This transcription factor family includes DRE-binding proteins (DREBs), which activate the expression of abiotic stress-responsive genes via specific binding of the dehydration-responsive element/C-repeat (DRE/CRT) cis-acting element in their promoters [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Transgenic alfalfa plants overexpressing WXP1 (a putative Medicago truncatula AP2 domain-containing TF gene) showed improved drought tolerance compared with the wild-type [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Transgenic Arabidopsis plants indicated an AP2/EREBF TF (AtERF7) reduced the sensitivity of guard cells to ABA and increased transpirational water loss [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>In this study, two AP2 TFs (comp79664 and comp77101) were first up-regulated and then down-regulated, whereas comp41385 was first down-regulated and then up-regulated in roots under progressive drought stress (Supplementary file 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>We hypothesize that the AP2 TFs might have important roles in ABA responses during drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>However, more evidence is needed to support this conclusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>The putative drought stress-related TFs that were identified in this study will further increase our understanding of gene expression, transcriptional regulation, and signal transduction during plant responses to drought. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Our data will also help future investigations into drought adaptation in ramie. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>We have also developed an efficient regeneration and transformation protocol for ramie via Agrobacterium-mediated genetic transformation [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, ongoing research in our laboratory using genetic engineering and several functional or regulatory genes has demonstrated activation or repression of both specific and broad pathways related to drought tolerance in ramie. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Material and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>4.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Plant Materials Preparation, RNA Extraction, and cDNA Library Construction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>In this study, the elite ramie variety, “Huazhu No. 5”, was used as the plant material and was obtained from the Ramie Germplasm Resources Garden, located at Huazhong Agricultural University, Wuhan, China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Two weeks after planting, the “Huazhu No. 5” seedlings were propagated from stem cuttings, which were transplanted into half-strength Hoagland’s solution for 20 days [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The period of seedling was when the plant height reached about 10 cm [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Physiological traits (the RWC, POD, the MDA, and the proline content) of ramie leaves at 0, 12, 24, 48, and 72 h after being subjected to drought stress (15% PEG6000) were measured to evaluate the severity of the stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Every experiment was repeated at least three times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>All stress experiments were conducted in a greenhouse at 28 ± 2 °C/23 ± 2 °C (day/night) with a relative humidity of 50%–70% under a 16/8-h (light/dark) photoperiod and a photon flux density of 350 µmol·m−2·s−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Based on the changing trends of these parameters, we chose three time points, which were 0, 24, and 72 h after being treated with PEG, to investigate the transcriptome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was isolated from leaves and roots harvested at 0 (L1 and R1), 24 (L2 and R2), and 72 (L3 and R3) h, using an RNAprep Pure Plant Kit (Tiangen Biotech, Beijing, China) with three replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>The RNA integrity and quality were confirmed by gel electrophoresis and using a NanoDrop 2000 spectrophotometer (Thermo, Waltham, MA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Twenty micrograms of RNA were separately pooled from the six samples for cDNA library preparation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>The residual RNA was used for qRT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>After digestion by DNase I (Takara, Japan) at 37 °C for 30 min, poly(A) RNA was isolated from 30 μg of total RNA using Dynabeads® Oligo (dT) 25 (Life, Lake Success, NY, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>The volume of purified mRNA was adjusted to 100 μL before adding 100 μL Binding Buffer, incubating at 65 °C for 2 min and immediately cooling on ice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Pre-rinsed magnetic beads (100 μL) were then added and the samples were then mixed well for 5 min at RT, and placed in the magnetic shelf (Life, Lake Success, NY, USA) for 1–2 min; the supernatant was then discarded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>The magnetic beads were washed twice using 200 μL of Washing Buffer B, resuspended by 15 μL of Tris-HCl (10 mM, pre-cooled), and then heated at 75–80 °C for 2 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>The supernatant containing the purified mRNA was then generated using the magnetic shelf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>The cDNA library was constructed from 100 ng of mRNA using NEBNext® UltraTM RNA Library Prep Kit from Illumina (NEB, Ipswich, MA, USA), following the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>The ligated cDNAs, ranging from 200 to 500 bp, were subjected to PCR amplification for 12–15 rounds using the Universal PCR Primer and the Index (X) Primer under the following procedures: 98 °C for 15 s, 65 °C for 30 s, and 72 °C for 30 s. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Finally, the library was subjected to high-throughput sequencing after purification using an isometric volume of AMPure XP Beads (Agencourt, Webster, TX, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>4.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Sequence Assembly, Annotation, and GO Terms/KEGG Pathways Construction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Transcriptome sequencing was performed for six equally pooled cDNA libraries, which were separately conducted from leaves (L1–L3) and roots (R1–R3) subjected to progressive drought stresses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Sequencing was performed on an Illumina HiSeq2500 genome analyzer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The raw reads were cleaned using FASTX-Toolkit (http://hannonlab.cshl.edu/fastx_toolkit/) to remove the adaptor sequences, empty reads and low-quality sequences (reads with unknown “N” sequences or those that were less than 20 bp long). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>The clean reads were assembled into non-redundant transcripts using Trinity [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The resulting sequences were used for Blastp searches and annotation against the Nr protein, the GO, the KEGG and the Swiss-Prot databases using an E-value cut-off of 1 × 10−5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>The predicted protein coding sequences were annotated to the non-redundant protein databases in GenBank, Swiss-Prot, and TrEMBL using Blastp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>GO mapping was carried out by GoPipe [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>The KEGG pathway annotations were performed using Blast against the KEGG [14] databases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>4.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Differential Expression Redundancy and Enrichment Analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>After assembly and annotation, the universal reads from the six separately pooled samples (L1–L3, and R1–R3) were mapped to unigenes to calculate the RPKM value [15] for each assembled unigene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>The differences in expression redundancy among the three samples from the leaves (L1–L3) or the roots (R1–R3) were determined using the RPKM value [15] for each unigene using the MARS model from the DEGseq program package [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>The p value threshold was &lt;0.001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>The differentially expressed genes were used for GO terms/KEGG pathway enrichment analyses using the hyper geometric test to measure significantly enriched terms:(1)P=1−∑i=0m−1(Mi)(N−Mn−i)(Nn) where N is the number of genes with GO/KEGG annotations and n represents the number of differentially expressed genes in N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>The variables, M and m, represent the total number of genes and the number of differentially expressed genes, respectively, in each GO/KEGG term. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>The threshold used to determine significant enrichment of the gene sets was corrected to a p value ≤0.05 and a false discovery rate (FDR) &lt;0.01. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>4.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Real-Time Quantitative RT-PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>The residual RNA from transcriptome sequencing was used for qRT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>The RNA was reverse transcribed into cDNA using the GoScript Reverse Transcription System (Promega, Fitchburg, WI, USA), following the manufacturer’s protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>QRT-PCR was performed in a 20-μL reaction vessel containing 10 μL iTaq Universal SYBR Green supermix (Bio-RAD; Hercules, CA, USA), 10 pmoL of forward and reverse gene-specific primers, and 1 μL cDNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Forward and reverse primers (Supplementary file 8) were designed for each gene of interest using Primer 3 online software version 4.0.0 [60] and adjusted by oligo software version 7.56 [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Additionally, primers specific to GAPDH were designed to serve as an endogenous control to normalize the data for differences in input RNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>PCR amplification was performed in an IQ5 (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA), according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Following a denaturation step at 95 °C for 5 min, the amplification step comprised 40 cycles at 95 °C for 15 s and 60 °C for 30 s. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>A melting curve was constructed to determine the specificity of each PCR primer by maintaining the reaction at 95 °C for 1 min, cooling the sample to 55 °C for 1 min and finally heating to 95 °C at a rate of 0.5 °C per 6 s. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>The reactions were carried out in triplicate to ensure reproducibility. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>4.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Estimations of the RWC, the MDA, the Proline Content, and POD </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>The RWC was calculated according to the following method [48]:  RWC (%) = (FW − DW)/(TW − DW) × 100 (2) FW, fresh leaf weights; TW, turgid leaf weights; DW, dry leaf weights. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>The MDA levels (a measure of lipid peroxidation) were assessed as previously described [7] by measuring the amount of thiobarbituric acid reactive substances present in the samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>MDA content (μmoL·L−1) was calculated using the formula:  C (μmoL·L−1) = 6.45 × [(OD532 − OD600)] − 0.56 × OD450(3) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>The extraction and colorimetric determination of proline from leaves were carried out according to a previously described method [39]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>POD was determined using the guaiacol oxidation method as previously described [48]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>In this study, we used Illumina paired-end sequencing technology to characterize the transcriptome of ramie under progressive drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>After stringent quality checking and data cleaning, approximately 33,976,322,460 bp (30G) of high-quality data (94.02% of raw data) were generated from 170 million raw sequence reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Differential gene expression analysis revealed 9281 putative genes in leaves and 8627 in roots that might be associated with drought tolerance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Among these, 25 TFs shared consistent expression patterns with physiological traits associated with drought stress, and thus they were picked out and validated by qRT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>This study represents a fully characterized transcriptome, and provides a valuable resource for genetic and genomic studies in ramie plants, especially under drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Our work is useful for breeding drought-resistant ramie varieties. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>This study was supported by the National Natural Science Funds (31171594) and the Supporting Program for Science and Technology Research of China (2010BAD02B01). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app id="app1-ijms-16-03493"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><p>Supplementary materials can be found at <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/16/02/3493/s1">http://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/16/02/3493/s1</uri>.</p></app></app-group></SecTag><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Sample preparation, production of results, and drafting the manuscript: Xia An, Jingyu Zhang, and Yiwen Liao. Conceived and designed the experiments: Xia An and Bo Wang. Contributed reagents and materials: Lijun Liu and Dingxiang Peng. Carried out the qRT-PCR experiment: Xia An and Lunjin Dai. RNA extraction and bioinformatics analysis: Jie Chen. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>1. ShinozakiK.Yamaguchi-ShinozakiK. Molecular responses to dehydration and low temperature: Differences and cross-talk between two stress signaling pathways Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Opin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Plant Biol. 2000 3 217 223 10.1016/S1369-5266(00)80068-0 <?supplied-pmid 10837265?>10837265 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>2. NakashimaK.TakasakiH.MizoiJ.ShinozakiK.Yamaguchi-ShinozakiK. NAC transcription factors in plant abiotic stress responses Biochim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Acta 2012 1819 97 103 10.1016/j.bbagrm.2011.10.005 <?supplied-pmid 22037288?>22037288 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>3. LiY.C.MengF.R.ZhangC.Y.ZhangN.SunM.S.RenJ.P.NiuH.B.WangX.YinJ. Comparative analysis of water stress-responsive transcriptomes in drought-susceptible and -tolerant wheat (triticum aestivum L.) J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Plant Biol. 2012 55 349 360 10.1007/s12374-011-0032-4  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>4. PastoriG.M.FoyerC.H. Common components, networks, and pathways of cross-tolerance to stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>The central role of “redox” and abscisic acid-mediated controls Plant Physiol. 2002 129 460 468 12068093 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>5. DongY.P.FanG.Q.ZhaoZ.L.DengM.J. Transcriptome expression profiling in response to drought stress in paulownia australis Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Sci. 2014 15 4583 4607 10.3390/ijms15034583 <?supplied-pmid 24642880?>24642880 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>6. LiM.R.LiY.LiH.Q.WuG.J. Overexpression of AtNHX5 improves tolerance to both salt and drought stress in Broussonetia papyrifera (L.) Vent Tree Physiol. 2011 31 349 357 10.1093/treephys/tpr003 21512100 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>7. LiuG.Z.LiX.L.JinS.X.LiuX.Y.ZhuL.F.NieY.C.ZhangX.L. Overexpression of rice NAC Gene SNAC1 improves drought and salt tolerance by enhancing root development and reducing transpiration rate in transgenic cotton PLoS One 2014 9 e86895 10.1371/journal.pone.0086895 <?supplied-pmid 24489802?>24489802 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>8. MittlerR. Abiotic stress, the field environment and stress combination Trends Plant Sci. 2006 11 15 19 10.1016/j.tplants.2005.11.002 <?supplied-pmid 16359910?>16359910 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>9. DengB.L.JinX.H.YangY.LinZ.W.ZhangY.L. The regulatory role of riboflavin in the drought tolerance of tobacco plants depends on ROS production Plant Growth Regul. 2014 72 269 277 10.1007/s10725-013-9858-8  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>10. UranoK.MaruyamaK.OgataY.MorishitaY.TakedaM.SakuraiN.SuzukiH.SaitoK.ShibataD.KobayashiM. Characterization of the ABA-regulated global responses to dehydration in Arabidopsis by metabolomics Plant J. 2009 57 1065 1078 19036030 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>11. RabbaniM.A.MaruyamaK.AbeH.KhanM.A.KatsuraK.ItoY.YoshiwaraK.SekiM.ShinozakiK.Yamaguchi-ShinozakiK. Monitoring expression profiles of rice genes under cold, drought, and high-salinity stresses and abscisic acid application using cDNA microarray and RNA get-blot analyses Plant Physiol. 2003 133 1755 1767 10.1104/pp.103.025742 <?supplied-pmid 14645724?>14645724 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>12. LiuT.M.ZhuS.Y.TangQ.M.ChenP.YuY.T.TangS.W. De novo assembly and characterization of transcriptome using Illumina paired-end sequencing and identification of CesA gene in ramie (Boehmeria nivea L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Gaud) BMC Genomics 2013 14 10.1186/1471-2164-14-125  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>13. LiuT.M.ZhuS.Y.TangQ.M.YuY.T.TangS.W. Identification of drought stress-responsive transcription factors in ramie (Boehmeria nivea L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Gaud) BMC Plant Biol. 2013 13 10.1186/1471-2229-13-130  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>14. KanehisaM.GotoS.FurumichiM.TanabeM.HirakawaM. KEGG for representation and analysis of molecular networks involving diseases and drugs Nucleic Acids Res. 2010 38 355 360 10.1093/nar/gkp896  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>15. MortazaviA.WilliamsB.A.MccueK.SchaefferL.WoldB. Mapping and quantifying mammalian transcriptomes by RNA-Seq Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Methods 2008 5 621 628 10.1038/nmeth.1226 <?supplied-pmid 18516045?>18516045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>16. WangL.K.FengZ.X.WangX.WangX.W.ZhangX.G. DEGseq: An R package for identifying differentially expressed genes from RNA-seq data Bioinformatics 2010 26 136 138 10.1093/bioinformatics/btp612 <?supplied-pmid 19855105?>19855105 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>17. YangY.XuM.LuoQ.F.WangJ.LiH.G. De novo transcriptome analysis of Liriodendron chinense petals and leaves by Illumina sequencing Gene 2014 534 155 162 10.1016/j.gene.2013.10.073 <?supplied-pmid 24239772?>24239772 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>18. JinS.B.FuH.T.ZhouQ.SunS.M.JiangS.F.XiongY.W.GongY.S.QiaoH.ZhangW.Y. Transcriptome analysis of androgenic gland for discovery of novel genes from the oriental river prawn, Macrobrachium nipponense, using Illumina Hiseq 2000 PLoS One 2013 8 e76840 10.1371/journal.pone.0076840 <?supplied-pmid 24204682?>24204682 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>19. VersluesP.E.AgarwalM.Katiyar-AgarwalS.ZhuJ.ZhuJ.K. Methods and concepts in quantifying resistance to drought, salt and freezing, abiotic stresses that affect plant water status Plant J. 2006 45 523 539 10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02593.x <?supplied-pmid 16441347?>16441347 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>20. AshrafM. Biotechnological approach of improving plant salt tolerance using antioxidants as markers Biotechnol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Adv. 2009 27 84 93 10.1016/j.biotechadv.2008.09.003 <?supplied-pmid 18950697?>18950697 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>21. FoyerC.H.ShigeokaS. Understanding oxidative stress and antioxidant functions to enhance photosynthesis Plant Physiol. 2011 155 93 100 10.1104/pp.110.166181 <?supplied-pmid 21045124?>21045124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>22. ChenS.M.CuiX.L.ChenY.GuC.S.MiaoH.B.GaoH.S.ChenF.D.LiuZ.L.GuanZ.Y.FangW.M. CgDREBa transgenic chrysanthemum confers drought and salinity tolerance Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Bot. 2011 74 255 260 10.1016/j.envexpbot.2011.06.007  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>23. TamuraT.HaraK.YamaguchiY.KoizumiN.SanoH. Osmotic stress tolerance of transgenic tobacco expressing a gene encoding a membrane-located receptor-like protein from tobacco plants Plant Physiol. 2003 131 454 462 10.1104/pp.102.011007 <?supplied-pmid 12586870?>12586870 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>24. WardJ.M.SchroederJ.I. Calcium-activated K+ channels and calcium-induced calcium release by slow vacuolar ion channels in guard cell vacuoles implicated in the control of stomatal closure Plant Cell 1994 6 669 683 <?supplied-pmid 12244253?>12244253 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>25. KleinM.GeislerM.SuhS.J.KolukisaogluH.U.AzevedoL.PlazaS.CurtisM.D.RichterA.WederB.SchulzB. Disruption of AtMRP4, a guard cell plasma membrane ABCC-type ABC transporter, leads to deregulation of stomatal opening and increased drought susceptibility Plant J. 2004 39 219 236 15225287 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>26. BartelsD. Targeting detoxification pathways: An efficient approach to obtain plants with multiple stress tolerance? Trends Plant Sci. 2001 6 284 286 10.1016/S1360-1385(01)01983-5 <?supplied-pmid 11435150?>11435150 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>27. Yamaguchi-ShinozakiK.ShinozakiK. Transcriptional regulatory networks in cellular responses and tolerance to dehydration and cold stresses Annu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Plant Biol. 2006 57 781 803 10.1146/annurev.arplant.57.032905.105444 <?supplied-pmid 16669782?>16669782 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>28. NakashimaK.ItoY.Yamaguchi-ShinozakiK. Transcriptional regulatory networks in response to abiotic stresses in Arabidopsis and grasses Plant Physiol. 2009 149 88 95 10.1104/pp.108.129791 <?supplied-pmid 19126699?>19126699 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>29. FujitaY.FujitaM.ShinozakiK.Yamaguchi-ShinozakiK. ABA-mediated transcriptional regulation in response to osmotic stress in plants J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Plant Res. 2011 124 509 525 10.1007/s10265-011-0412-3 <?supplied-pmid 21416314?>21416314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>30. ZhuJ.K. Salt and drought stress signal transduction in plants Annu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Plant Biol. 2002 53 247 273 10.1146/annurev.arplant.53.091401.143329 <?supplied-pmid 12221975?>12221975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>31. SinghK.B.FoleyR.C.Onate-SanchezL. Transcription factors in plant defense and stress responses Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Opin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Plant Biol. 2002 5 430 436 10.1016/S1369-5266(02)00289-3 <?supplied-pmid 12183182?>12183182 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>32. AidaM.IshidaT.FukakiH.FujisawaH.TasakaM. Genes involved in organ separation in Arabidopsis: An analysis of the cup-shaped cotyledon mutant Plant Cell 1997 9 841 857 10.1105/tpc.9.6.841 <?supplied-pmid 9212461?>9212461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>33. OlsenA.N.ErnstH.A.Lo LeggioL.SkriverK. NAC transcription factors: Structurally distinct, functionally diverse Trends Plant Sci. 2005 10 79 87 10.1016/j.tplants.2004.12.010 <?supplied-pmid 15708345?>15708345 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>34. BuQ.Y.JiangH.L.LiC.B.ZhaiQ.Z.ZhangJ.Y.WuX.Q.SunJ.Q.XieQ.LiC.Y. Role of the Arabidopsis thaliana NAC transcription factors ANAC019 and ANAC055 in regulating jasmonic acid-signaled defense responses Cell Res. 2008 18 756 767 10.1038/cr.2008.53 <?supplied-pmid 18427573?>18427573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>35. TranL.S.P.NakashimaK.SakumaY.SimpsonS.D.FujitaY.MaruyamaK.FujitaM.SekiM.ShinozakiK.Yamaguchi-ShinozakiK. Isolation and functional analysis of Arabidopsis stress-inducible NAC transcription factors that bind to a drought-responsive cis-element in the early responsive to dehydration stress 1 promoter Plant Cell 2004 16 2481 2498 10.1105/tpc.104.022699 <?supplied-pmid 15319476?>15319476 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>36. HuH.H.DaiM.Q.YaoJ.L.XiaoB.Z.LiX.H.ZhangQ.F.XiongL.Z. Overexpressing a NAM, ATAF, and CUC (NAC) transcription factor enhances drought resistance and salt tolerance in rice Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>USA 2006 103 12987 12992 10.1073/pnas.0604882103 <?supplied-pmid 16924117?>16924117 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>37. JeongJ.S.KimY.S.BaekK.H.JungH.HaS.H.Do ChoiY.KimM.ReuzeauC.KimJ.K. Root-specific expression of OsNAC10 improves drought tolerance and grain yield in rice under field drought conditions Plant Physiol. 2010 153 185 197 10.1104/pp.110.154773 <?supplied-pmid 20335401?>20335401 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>38. ZhangL.C.ZhaoG.Y.XiaC.JiaJ.Z.LiuX.KongX.Y. A wheat R2R3-MYB gene, TaMYB30-B, improves drought stress tolerance in transgenic Arabidopsis J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Bot. 2012 63 5873 5885 10.1093/jxb/ers237 <?supplied-pmid 23048128?>23048128 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>39. AbeH.UraoT.ItoT.SekiM.ShinozakiK.Yamaguchi-ShinozakiK. Arabidopsis AtMYC2 (bHLH) and AtMYB2 (MYB) function as transcriptional activators in abscisic acid signaling Plant Cell 2003 15 63 78 10.1105/tpc.006130 <?supplied-pmid 12509522?>12509522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>40. CominelliE.SalaT.CalviD.GusmaroliG.TonelliC. Over-expression of the Arabidopsis AtMYB41 gene alters cell expansion and leaf surface permeability Plant J. 2008 53 53 64 10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03310.x <?supplied-pmid 17971045?>17971045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>41. LippoldF.SanchezD.H.MusialakM.SchlerethA.ScheibleW.R.HinchaD.K.UdvardiM.K. AtMyb41 regulates transcriptional and metabolic responses to osmotic stress in Arabidopsis Plant Physiol. 2009 149 1761 1772 10.1104/pp.108.134874 <?supplied-pmid 19211694?>19211694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>42. CominelliE.GalbiatiM.VavasseurA.ContiL.SalaT.VuylstekeM.LeonhardtN.DellaportaS.L.TonelliC. A guard-cell-specific MYB transcription factor regulates stomatal movements and plant drought tolerance Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2005 15 1196 1200 10.1016/j.cub.2005.05.048 <?supplied-pmid 16005291?>16005291 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>43. SuL.T.LiJ.W.LiuD.Q.ZhaiY.ZhangH.J.LiX.W.ZhangQ.L.WangY.WangQ.Y. A novel MYB transcription factor, GmMYBJ1, from soybean confers drought and cold tolerance in Arabidopsis thaliana Gene 2014 538 46 55 10.1016/j.gene.2014.01.024 <?supplied-pmid 24440241?>24440241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>44. JungC.SeoJ.S.HanS.W.KooY.J.KimC.H.SongS.I.NahmB.H.ChoiY.D.CheongJ.J. Overexpression of AtMYB44 enhances stomatal closure to confer abiotic stress tolerance in transgenic Arabidopsis Plant Physiol. 2008 146 623 635 10.1104/pp.107.110981 <?supplied-pmid 18162593?>18162593 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>45. LaiL.B.NadeauJ.A.LucasJ.LeeE.K.NakagawaT.ZhaoL.GeislerM.SackF.D. The Arabidopsis R2R3 MYB proteins FOUR LIPS and MYB88 restrict divisions late in the stomatal cell lineage Plant Cell 2005 17 2754 2767 10.1105/tpc.105.034116 <?supplied-pmid 16155180?>16155180 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>46. XieZ.LeeE.LucasJ.R.MorohashiK.LiD.MurrayJ.A.SackF.D.GrotewoldE. Regulation of cell proliferation in the stomatal lineage by the Arabidopsis MYB FOUR LIPS via direct targeting of core cell cycle genes Plant Cell 2010 22 2306 2321 10.1105/tpc.110.074609 <?supplied-pmid 20675570?>20675570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>47. RahaieM.XueG.P.NaghaviM.R.AlizadehH.SchenkP.M. A MYB gene from wheat (Triticum aestivum L.) is up-regulated during salt and drought stresses and differentially regulated between salt-tolerant and sensitive genotypes Plant Cell Rep. 2010 29 835 844 20490502 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>48. LuoX.BaiX.ZhuD.LiY.JiW.CaiH.WuJ.LiuB.H.ZhuY.M. GsZFP1, a new Cys2/His2-type zinc-finger protein, is a positive regulator of plant tolerance to cold and drought stress Planta 2012 235 1141 1155 10.1007/s00425-011-1563-0 <?supplied-pmid 22160567?>22160567 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>49. Ben SaadR.ZouariN.Ben RamdhanW.AzazaJ.MeynardD.GuiderdoniE.HassairiA. Improved drought and salt stress tolerance in transgenic tobacco overexpressing a novel A20/AN1 zinc-finger “AlSAP” gene isolated from the halophyte grass Aeluropus littoralis Plant Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2010 72 171 190 10.1007/s11103-009-9560-4 <?supplied-pmid 19838809?>19838809 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>50. LiuQ.L.XuK.D.ZhongM.PanY.Z.JiangB.B.LiuG.L.JiaY.ZhangH.Q. Overexpression of a novel chrysanthemum Cys2/His2-type zinc finger protein gene DgZFP3 confers drought tolerance in tobacco Biotechnol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Lett. 2013 35 1953 1959 10.1007/s10529-013-1289-0 <?supplied-pmid 23881327?>23881327 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>51. HuangX.Y.ChaoD.Y.GaoJ.P.ZhuM.Z.ShiM.LinH.X. A previously unknown zinc finger protein, DST, regulates drought and salt tolerance in rice via stomatal aperture control Genes Dev. 2009 23 1805 1817 10.1101/gad.1812409 <?supplied-pmid 19651988?>19651988 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>52. LiuC.T.WuY.B.WangX.P. bZIP transcription factor OsbZIP52/RISBZ5: A potential negative regulator of cold and drought stress response in rice Planta 2012 235 1157 1169 10.1007/s00425-011-1564-z <?supplied-pmid 22189955?>22189955 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>53. HuangX.S.LiuJ.H.ChenX.J. Overexpression of PtrABF gene, a bZIP transcription factor isolated from Poncirus trifoliata, enhances dehydration and drought tolerance in tobacco via scavenging ROS and modulating expression of stress-responsive genes BMC Plant Biol. 2010 10 10.1186/1471-2229-10-230 <?supplied-pmid 21083930?>21083930 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>54. MizoiJ.ShinozakiK.Yamaguchi-ShinozakiK. AP2/ERF family transcription factors in plant abiotic stress responses Biochim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Acta 2012 1819 86 96 10.1016/j.bbagrm.2011.08.004 <?supplied-pmid 21867785?>21867785 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>55. ZhangJ.Y.BroecklingC.D.BlancaflorE.B.SledgeM.K.SumnerL.W.WangZ.Y. Overexpression of WXP1, a putative Medicago truncatula AP2 domain-containing transcription factor gene, increases cuticular wax accumulation and enhances drought tolerance in transgenic alfalfa (Medicago sativa) Plant J. 2005 42 689 707 10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02405.x <?supplied-pmid 15918883?>15918883 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>56. SongC.P.AgarwalM.OhtaM.GuoY.HalfterU.WangP.ZhuJ.K. Role of an Arabidopsis AP2/EREBP-type transcriptional repressor in abscisic acid and drought stress responses Plant Cell 2005 17 2384 2396 10.1105/tpc.105.033043 <?supplied-pmid 15994908?>15994908 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>57. AnX.WangB.LiuL.J.JiangH.ChenJ.YeS.T.ChenL.Y.GuoP.A.HuangX.PengD.X. Agrobacterium-mediated genetic transformation and regeneration of transgenic plants using leaf midribs as explants in ramie (Boehmeria nivea (L.) Gaud) Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Rep. 2014 41 3257 3269 10.1007/s11033-014-3188-4 <?supplied-pmid 24488319?>24488319 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>58. GrabherrM.G.HaasB.J.YassourM.LevinJ.Z.ThompsonD.A.AmitI.AdiconisX.FanL.RaychowdhuryR.ZengQ.D. Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol. 2011 29 644 652 21572440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>59. ChenZ.Z.XueC.H.ZhuS.ZhouF.F.LingX.F.B.LiuG.P.ChenL.B. GoPipe: Streamlined Gene Ontology annotation for batch anonymous sequences with statistics Prog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Biophys. 2005 32 187 190  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>60. UntergasserA.CutcutacheI.KoressaarT.YeJ.FairclothB.C.RemmM.RozenS.G. Primer3-new capabilities and interfaces Nucleic Acids Res. 2012 40 e115 10.1093/nar/gks596 <?supplied-pmid 22730293?>22730293 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B61-ijms-16-03493"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>61. RychlikW. OLIGO 7 primer analysis software Methods Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2007 402 35 60 <?supplied-pmid 17951789?>17951789 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
