<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4503668</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-10762</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0132184</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Tandem Duplications and the Limits of Natural Selection in Drosophila yakuba and Drosophila simulans </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Mutation Limited Evolution for Tandem Duplications</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>Rebekah L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cridland</surname><given-names>Julie M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>Ling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Tina T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Andolfatto</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>Kevin R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of California, Berkeley, California, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of California, Davis, Davis, California, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff003">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of California, Irvine, Irvine, California, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff004">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology and the Lewis Sigler Institute for Integrative Genomics, Princeton University, Princeton, New Jersey, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>Arnar</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Iceland, ICELAND</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: RLR JMC PA KRT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: LS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: RLR JMC TTH PA KRT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: RLR JMC PA KRT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: RLR KRT PA JMC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>bekah@berkeley.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>e0132184</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 Rogers et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Rogers et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0132184.pdf"/><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Tandem duplications are an essential source of genetic novelty, and their variation in natural populations is expected to influence adaptive walks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Here, we describe evolutionary impacts of recently-derived, segregating tandem duplications in Drosophila yakuba and Drosophila simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>We observe an excess of duplicated genes involved in defense against pathogens, insecticide resistance, chorion development, cuticular peptides, and lipases or endopeptidases associated with the accessory glands across both species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The observed agreement is greater than expectations on chance alone, suggesting large amounts of convergence across functional categories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>We document evidence of widespread selection on the D. simulans X, suggesting adaptation through duplication is common on the X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Despite the evidence for positive selection, duplicates display an excess of low frequency variants consistent with largely detrimental impacts, limiting the variation that can effectively facilitate adaptation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Standing variation for tandem duplications spans less than 25% of the genome in D. yakuba and D. simulans, indicating that evolution will be strictly limited by mutation, even in organisms with large population sizes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Effective whole gene duplication rates are low at 1.17 × 10−9 per gene per generation in D. yakuba and 6.03 × 10−10 per gene per generation in D. simulans, suggesting long wait times for new mutations on the order of thousands of years for the establishment of sweeps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Hence, in cases where adaptation depends on individual tandem duplications, evolution will be severely limited by mutation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>We observe low levels of parallel recruitment of the same duplicated gene in different species, suggesting that the span of standing variation will define evolutionary outcomes in spite of convergence across gene ontologies consistent with rapidly evolving phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>RLR is supported by NIH Ruth Kirschstein National Research Service Award F32-GM099377 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nih.gov/">http://www.nih.gov/</ext-link>). Research funds were provided by NIH grant R01-GM085183 to KRT and R01-GM083228 to PA. All sequencing was performed at the UC Irvine High Throughput Genomics facility, which is supported by the National Cancer Institute of the National Institutes of Health under Award Number P30CA062203. The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institutes of Health. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="1"/><page-count count="28"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All data files are available via <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molpopgen.org/Data">http://molpopgen.org/Data</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.github.com/ThorntonLab/DrosophilaPopGenData-Rogers2014">http://www.github.com/ThorntonLab/DrosophilaPopGenData-Rogers2014</ext-link>. Aligned bam files were deposited in the National Institutes of Health Short Read Archive under accession numbers SRP040290 and SRP029453. Sequenced stocks were deposited in the University of California, San Diego (UCSD) stock center with stock numbers 14021-0261.38- 14021-0261.51 and 14021-0251.293 - 14021-0251.311.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All data files are available via <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molpopgen.org/Data">http://molpopgen.org/Data</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.github.com/ThorntonLab/DrosophilaPopGenData-Rogers2014">http://www.github.com/ThorntonLab/DrosophilaPopGenData-Rogers2014</ext-link>. Aligned bam files were deposited in the National Institutes of Health Short Read Archive under accession numbers SRP040290 and SRP029453. Sequenced stocks were deposited in the University of California, San Diego (UCSD) stock center with stock numbers 14021-0261.38- 14021-0261.51 and 14021-0251.293 - 14021-0251.311.</p></notes></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Tandem duplications are an essential source of genetic novelty that is useful for the development of novel traits [1–3] and their prevalence in populations is therefore expected to influence the arc of evolutionary trajectories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The observed landscape of tandem duplications in Drosophila spans only a few percent of the genome [4–7], and it is unclear to what extent duplications among new mutations or standing variation can provide a sufficient source of adaptive genetic variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Tandem duplications produce a variety of novel gene structures including chimeric genes, recruited non-coding sequence, dual promoter genes, and whole gene duplications [4, 8, 9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Surveys based on single sequenced reference genomes have suggested that whole gene duplications may form at low rates in comparison with SNPs, with even lower mutation rates for complex variants such as chimeric genes [4, 8, 10, 11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Yet, these alternative genetic structures are known forces of evolutionary innovation [12–16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Whole gene duplications often develop novel functions or specialize in ancestral functions [1], and chimeric genes are more likely still to produce novel molecular effects and play a role in adaptive evolution [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Although these variants contribute substantially to the evolution of genome content [8, 10, 17], their lower rates of formation may render evolution of tandem duplications more likely to be limited by mutation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>If population-level mutation rates are sufficiently large, new mutations will accumulate quickly and adaptation is expected to proceed rapidly [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>However, if population-level mutation rates are low, then there will be long waiting times until the next new mutation and evolutionary trajectories are likely to stall at suboptimal solutions during the mutational lag [18–20]. Drosophila have large population sizes in comparison to other multicellular eukaryotes with N e ≈ 105−106 [21–23] and absolute numbers of individuals sufficient to provide large numbers of SNPs at many sites every generation [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>However, the ability of SNPs to traverse adaptive landscapes is often limited [25] and, the prevalence of other types of mutations beyond SNPs has not been systematically surveyed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Alternative genetic constructs such as chimeric genes can readily traverse mutational landscapes to obtain structures that cannot be readily reached via point mutations [26, 27] whereas whole gene duplications often free sequences from functional constraints to allow for the development of new gene functions [1, 2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>If the supply of tandem duplications is limited by mutation, we expect to see suboptimal outcomes in adaptive walks, limited ability to adapt to changing environments, and low rates of evolution through parallel recruitment of the same genetic solutions in different species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The Drosophila offer an excellent model system for population genomics, allowing for a whole genome survey of the genetic landscape of standing variation across species in natural populations and determination of genetic convergence across taxa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>There are multiple sequenced reference genomes for Drosophila, and genomes are small and compact, making whole genome population surveys using next generation sequencing readily tractable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Here, we focus on D. yakuba and D. simulans, which are separated by 12 MY of divergence [28], offering distantly related groups which are not expected to share polymorphic variation due to ancestry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Thus, we can measure the limits of standing variation and the incidence of parallel duplication across species, which should be broadly applicable to multicellular eukaryotic evolution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Convergent evolution is regarded as the ultimate signal of natural selection: if the same solution is favored for a given environment then selection should result in similar phenotypes [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>There are many known cases of convergent phenotypic evolution, but the understanding of convergence at the genetic level is limited to a small number of case studies across diverse clades [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>These case studies have revealed convergent evolution through different genetic solutions in vertebrates [31–33], and arthropods [34–37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Parallel evolution through similar genetic solutions, however, appears to be more common at mutational hotspots where high mutation rates at targeted sites produce mutations at a steady rate [38–40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Beyond these results from natural populations, convergence has often been observed in experimental evolution and is considered a signal of selection favoring alleles [38, 40–43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>However, most studies of laboratory evolution take advantage of microbes or viruses with large population sizes roughly 109−1010 such that every mutation is likely to be sampled every generation [38, 40] or from small populations that share a common pool of standing variation [41, 44] and may therefore be qualitatively different outcomes in comparison to natural evolution in multicellular eukaryotes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Indeed, known examples of evolution through parallel recruitment of the same genetic solutions in natural populations often occur through a common ancestral genetic pool [45] or through introgression [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>In D. melanogaster, parallel selection on standing variation results in high levels of convergence at the genetic level due to shared pools of ancestral variation [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that given the same mutational spectrum with which to work, convergent evolution will be common. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>However, whether similar genetic solutions can arise independently and result in sweeps on similar variants without shared ancestry is largely unknown. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Identifying factors that influence convergent evolution across distantly related taxa that do not share population level variation due to ancestry is essential to understanding the ways mutation limits evolution, the role of standing variation in evolutionary trajectories, and the genetic architecture of adaptation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Here, we survey standing variation for tandem duplications in Drosophila yakuba and Drosophila simulans and the role that this standing variation plays in adaptive evolution in natural populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>We identify signals of reduced diversity surrounding tandem duplications, and an overabundance of high frequency variants on the D. simulans X chromosome, pointing to a role for adaptation through gene duplication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>We observe high levels of convergence at the level of gene ontology but limited shared variation across species at specific genes, pointing to limited rates of convergent evolution at the level of single genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>We show that the span of tandem duplications in populations is limited to a small fraction of the genome and that low mutation rates will lead to long waiting times for sweeps on new mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>These results imply that evolution by tandem duplication will be limited by mutation and that parallel recruitment of gene duplicates across species is likely to be exceedingly rare even in the face of strong selection on similar phenotypes in different species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="sec002"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>We previously identified hundreds to thousands of segregating duplications in natural populations of D. yakuba and D. simulans, including large numbers of gene duplications [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>We assess the numbers and types of gene duplications, differences in duplication rates across species and explore the limits of the landscape of standing variation for tandem duplications present in each species to determine the extent to which these variants can serve as a source of genetic novelty. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Recently derived, segregating tandem duplications were previously detected using paired-end read mapping and coverage changes in D. yakuba and D. simulans in samples of 20 isofemale lines derived from natural populations of each species [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Using divergently oriented paired-end reads, we identified 1415 segregating tandem duplications in D. yakuba, in comparison to 975 in D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Strains have been sequenced to high coverage of 50–150X and duplicate identification methods have a 96% validation rate using PacBio long molecule sequencing, and a low false negative rate less than 1% based on comparisons across strains [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Thus, this dataset represents a high quality portrait of variation for population genomics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Here, we describe signals of selection acting on these tandem duplications, the limits of standing variation for tandem duplicates, and their role in adaptive evolution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec003"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Widespread selection on the D. simulans X chromosome </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>If tandem duplications are common targets for adaptation and selective sweeps, we should observe a shift in the site frequency spectrum (SFS) toward high frequency variants relative to neutral markers [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>We compare the SFS for duplications with the SFS for SNPs from 8–30 bp of short introns used as a putatively neutral proxy to determine whether duplicates are subject to selection (Figure A in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The SFS for duplications is significantly different from that of intronic SNPs on the D. simulans autosomes using a Wilcoxon rank sum test (W = 268, P = 2.981 × 10−6) and D. yakuba autosomes (W = 212, P = 3.507 × 10−6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>In D. yakuba the SFS for duplicates on the X is significantly different from that of SNPs (W = 211, P = 4.781 × 10−4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Duplicates show an excess of singleton variants on the autosomes in both species (Figure A in S1 File), suggesting deleterious impacts on average. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>We find a significant difference between the SFS of duplicates on the X chromosome and the autosomes in D. yakuba (W = 172, P = 0.0128) but not in D. simulans (W = 183.5, P = 0.1848) (Fig 1, Tables A-B in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0132184.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0132184.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>SFS for tandem duplications in D. yakuba and D. simulans, corrected for ascertainment bias. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Site frequency spectra on the autosomes (black) and on the X (grey) in D. yakuba. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>SFS on the autosomes (black) and on the X (grey) in D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>SFS for X-linked intronic SNPs (black) and duplicates (white) in D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The excess of high frequency variants on the X in D. simulans suggests widespread selection for tandem duplicates on the D. simulans X. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0132184.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>We have calculated average heterozygosity per site (θ π) [49], Wattersons’s θ (Sa per site) [50], and Tajima’s D [51] for the four major autosomal arms and the X chromosome in D. yakuba and D. simulans using 5 kb windows with a 500 bp slide correcting for the number of sites with coverage sufficient to confidently identify SNPs (Figures B-K in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>We compare θ π in windows immediately surrounding tandem duplications and for windows surrounding putatively neutral SNPs from 8–30 bp of short introns to search for signals of reduced diversity consistent with selection acting on tandem duplications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>These tandem duplications are polymorphic and represent putative sweeps in progress and such comparisons to within-genome controls of neutral SNPs offer greater power than alternative tests of selection [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>A significant excess of diversity surrounding duplicates is seen on chromosome 2 in D. yakuba (W = 31594, P = 2.517 × 10−4), a putative product of alternative evolutionary dynamics driven by segregating inversions on 2L [53, 54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>We find a reduction in θ π per site surrounding newly arisen tandem duplications on D. yakuba chromosome 3, which is not known to contain inversions (single tailed Wilcoxon rank sum test, W = 170168 P = 0.00665, see Table C in S1 File, Fig 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0132184.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0132184.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Diversity (θ π) as a function of distance from new mutations in D. yakuba for putatively neutral intronic SNPs (black) and for tandem duplications (red) by chromosome with lowess smoothing. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Duplicates show a reduction in diversity approaching duplications on chromosome 3L, whereas neutral SNPs show no reduction in diversity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Plots exclude centromeric regions and the 4th chromosome which have atypical nucleotide diversity. D. yakuba chromosome 2 displays an atypical pattern of increased diversity and was handled separately from chromosome 3 due to segregating inversions in populations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0132184.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>In D. simulans autosomes we observe a significant reduction in diversity for 5 kb windows immediately surrounding tandem duplications (single tailed Wilcoxon rank sum test, W = 627683.5 P = 2.267 × 10−7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Chromosome 3L in D. simulans contains a region encompassing multiple duplications with signals of a broad selective sweep encompassing multiple loci located at roughly 8.5 Mb that is excluded from these tests of selection (Figure I in S1 File) but results remain significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The D. simulans X shows signals of reduced diversity surrounding tandem duplications (single tailed Wilcoxon rank sum test, W = 13450.5, P = 0.01819); see Table C in S1 File) (Fig 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>We observe an excess of tandem duplications at a sample frequency of 20 out of 20 sample strains (with no indication of duplication or misassembly in the resequenced reference) on the X chromosome of D. simulans in comparison to neutral SNPs (P &lt; 10−6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>We observe no duplicates at a sample frequency of 20 out of 20 in D. yakuba on the X or autosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Furthermore comparisons of the SFS for neutral SNPs and duplications segregating in populations show an excess of highest frequency duplicates ≥ 16 out of 17 on the D. simulans X (χ 2 = 21.8334, df = 1, P = 2.974 × 10−6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The excess of high frequency duplicates on the D. simulans X chromosome is indicative of selection favoring large numbers of tandem duplicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>These results imply that adaptation through duplication is common on the D. simulans X. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0132184.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0132184.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide diversity, θ π as a function of distance from new mutations in D. simulans for putatively neutral intronic SNPs (black) and for tandem duplications (red) by chromosome with lowess smoothing. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Duplicates show a reduction in mean diversity approaching duplications on the D. simulans autosomes and X chromosome, whereas neutral SNPs show no reduction in diversity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Plots exclude centromeric regions and the 4th chromosome which have atypical nucleotide diversity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Chromosome 3L is strongly affected by a cluster of duplications at roughly 8.5Mb, which is excluded from the plot, but the effect is still significant without this region. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0132184.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>It is possible that tandem duplications whose breakpoints lie within gene sequences may have different phenotypic impacts from tandem duplications that capture whole genes and do not interrupt or otherwise modify gene sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>We compare θ π for windows centered around tandem duplications that capture solely intergenic sequence with those that capture whole genes and do not create chimeric constructs with those that create chimeric genes or recruit non-coding sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>In D. simulans, tandem gene duplications that do not create chimeric genes have reduced diversity (W = 17880, P = 0.0123) in comparison to mutations that capture intergenic mutations (Fig 4C–4D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Such results are consistent with selection driving an excess of whole gene duplications in D. simulans [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>However, tandem duplications whose breakpoints lie within gene sequences thereby forming chimeric genes do not show similar overabundance (W = 5020, P = 0.5755). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Relationships in D. yakuba are not significant for chimeric gene mutations (W = 2656, P = 0.8226) or whole gene duplications that do not create chimeric genes (W = 6387, P = 0.8847). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Based on a binomial test, we observe a marginally significant overrepresentation of tandem duplications that capture gene sequences vs. solely non-coding sequences in D. yakuba (P = 0.0291) and highly significant for D. simulans (P = 9.044 × 10−5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0132184.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0132184.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Histogram of nucleotide diversity, θ π, (A) For Intergenic mutations (yellow) and duplications that capture gene sequences but do not create chimeric constructs (blue) in D. yakuba. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>(B) For Intergenic mutations (yellow) and duplications that create chimeric genes (red) in D. yakuba. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>(C) For Intergenic mutations (yellow) and duplications that capture gene sequences but do not create chimeric constructs (blue) in D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>(D) For Intergenic mutations (yellow) and duplications that create chimeric genes (red) in D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0132184.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Populations of both D. yakuba and D. simulans show negatively skewed Tajima’s D for neutral SNPs, suggesting recent population expansion in both species (Figures B-K in S1 File), and similar results have been identified in D. melanogaster [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>While demography and neutral evolutionary forces can result in shifts of diversity and site frequency spectra, these forces should affect sequences across individual chromosome arms and act similarly on intronic SNPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Hence, demography is unlikely to explain the observed differences between duplicates and intronic SNPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Further, gene conversion might putatively alter the SFS, while divergence of paralogs would artificially increase observed diversity for regions immediately surrounding tandem duplications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>These forces would artificially skew statistics away from selection, leading to underreporting of the adaptive impacts of chimeric genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Thus, we would expect many of the high frequency variants reported here to be strong candidates for ongoing selective sweeps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>We further observe large numbers of singleton variants among tandem duplicates in comparison with intronic SNPs in D. yakuba and D. simulans autosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Copy number variants are subject to purifying selection in D. melanogaster [5, 56], and we observe large numbers of singleton variants in excess of neutral expectations, indicating negative selection preventing variants from rising to higher frequency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Hence, while some variants are likely to offer a means of adaptive change, many are likely to ultimately be lost from the pool of standing variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>We suggest that tandem duplications are likely to confer phenotypic impacts that are on average large enough to surpass the threshold of nearly neutral effects in Drosophila. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Limits of standing variation in natural populations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>We observe hundreds of segregating tandem duplicates in D. yakuba and D. simulans, spanning 2.6% of assayable the genome (i.e X and 4 major autosomal arms) in D. yakuba and 1.8% of the assayable genome in D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>If evolutionary trajectories depend on tandem duplications to effect beneficial phenotypic changes, then these trajectories may be constrained if the population does not contain the desired variants as standing variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>We estimate the number of variants present in the entire population based on the observed sample variation in order to determine the extent to which selection will be limited by mutation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>We estimate that the population contains at most 6800 segregating tandem duplications in D. yakuba and 4,500 in D. simulans (Tables E-F in S1 File), corresponding to 13.4% of major chromosome arms in D. yakuba and 9.7% of major chromosome arms in D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Estimates using rarefaction estimators free from assumptions of neutrality [57] are comparable (Table E in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Thus, the standing variation for tandem duplications will be insufficient to offer tandem duplications for every potential mutation for the majority of the genome (≈ 85%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>If a tandem duplication is required for adaptation, evolutionary trajectories must then by definition rely on new mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Tajima’s D is negative in both D. yakuba and D. simulans suggesting recent population expansion and greater census size than effective population size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Even under expectations of large population sizes of 108 after population expansion, we estimate that there are at most 8550 duplications segregating in the population at large for D. yakuba and 5700 for D. simulans (Table E in S1 File), still far from expectations required to span the entire genome (Table F in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>We calculate population level mutation rates θ π (4N e μ) of 0.00277 per gene per generation for whole gene duplications, 0.00082 for recruited non-coding sequence and 0.00088 for chimeras in D. yakuba. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Population level mutation rates in D. simulans are slightly higher for most types of mutations with 0.00291 per gene per generation for whole gene duplications, 0.00117 for recruited non-coding sequence but a lower population level mutation rate of 0.00041 for chimeras. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>In comparison, we calculate θ π for putatively neutral intronic SNPs of 0.0138 for D. yakuba and 0.0280 for D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>We use these estimates of θ to calculate the likelihood of adaptation from alleles among the standing variation rather than new mutation for a population (P sgv) [18] assuming variants with a large selection coefficient of 1% under an additive genetic model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>With such low levels of θ π the likelihood of adaptation from a tandem duplication among the standing variation is 2.2% in D. yakuba and 2.6% in D. simulans (Table 1), a strikingly low likelihood that standing variation offers a sufficient substrate for adaptation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Even with a massive selective coefficient of s = 0.20 [24], the likelihood of adaptation from standing variation rather than new mutation is 3.1% for duplicates in D. yakuba and 3.4% in D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Chimeras are even more extreme with less than a 1% chance of fixation from standing variation (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>In comparison, intronic SNPs have a likelihood of adaptation from standing variation of 12.1% in D. yakuba and 24.6% in D. simulans given s = 0.01, and 15.7% in D. yakuba and 30.1% in D. simulans, given extreme selection coefficients of s = 0.20 (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Thus, the limits of standing variation are expected to be far more severe for complex gene structures than for SNPs and will not offer sufficient standing variation to provide for adaptation via tandem duplication for any randomly selected gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone.0132184.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0132184.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Mutation limited evolution in D. yakuba and D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0132184.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0132184.t001"/><table frame="box" rules="all" border="0"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/></colgroup><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Species </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Intron SNPs </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Whole Gene </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Recruit* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Chimera** </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" align="left" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>D. yakuba </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>μ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>5.8 × 10−9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>1.17 × 10−9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>3.46 × 10−10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>3.70 × 10−10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>θ π </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>0.0138 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>0.00277 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>0.00082 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>0.00088 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>P sgv, s = 0.01 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>12.1% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>2.23% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>0.67% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>0.71% </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>P sgv, s = 0.20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>15.7% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>3.05% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>0.91% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>0.97% </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>T e, s = 0.01 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>7270 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>36,000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>122,000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>114,000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>T e, s = 0.20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>364 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>1,800 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>6,087 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>5,704 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Species </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Intron SNPs </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Whole Gene </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Recruit </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Chimera </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" align="left" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>D. simulans </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>μ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>5.8 × 10−9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>6.03 × 10−10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>2.42 × 10−10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>8.52 × 10−11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>θ π </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>0.0280 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>0.00291 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>0.00117 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>0.00041 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>P sgv, s = 0.01 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>24.6% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>2.56% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>1.04% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>0.37% </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>P sgv, s = 0.20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>30.1% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>3.41% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>1.38% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>0.49% </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>T e, s = 0.01 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>3580 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>34,400 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>85,700 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>243,000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>T e, s = 0.20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>179 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>1,720 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>4,290 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>12,100 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>* Tandem duplications that recruit non-coding sequence to form new genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="t001fn002"><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>** Chimeric genes formed through tandem duplication. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="t001fn003"><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>P sgv from Hermisson and Pennings (2005) estimates the likelihood of adaptation from standing genetic variation under an additive model assuming neutral variation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="t001fn004"><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>T e (Gillespie 1991 and Maynard Smith 1971) estimates the average time until establishment of a selective sweep from a new mutation in generations given that a site is under strong selection with beneficial mutation rate equal to θ π. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Estimates provide a lower bound on T e. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Drosophila have large effective population sizes and should offer large absolute numbers of tandem duplications in comparison to many other multicellular eukaryotes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>However, the dynamics of standing variation may be drastically different for organisms with varying effective population sizes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>We estimate time to loss given loss (sometimes called the sojourn time) [58], population mutation rates, and maximum nearly-neutral selection coefficients [59] for organisms with different population sizes in order to determine the extent to which dynamics observed in Drosophila might be applicable to other organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>For organisms with very low N e, we expect to observe fewer mutations due to lower population level mutation rates, but a greater tolerance for extreme variation as more variants are subject to nearly neutral dynamics though sojourn times are largely unaffected (Table I in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Under such a scheme, evolution will still be severely limited by mutation with only small numbers of mutations appearing in the population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Given small N e, however, an extreme variant needed for adaptation to extreme environmental change is more likely to be tolerated among the standing variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Thus, there may be higher variance in adaptive outcomes for organisms with small N e due to the limits of mutation and in extremely rare cases organisms with small N e might be able to adapt to sudden and drastic shifts in selective pressures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Long waiting times for new mutations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>We calculate the per generation effective mutation rate μ per gene for whole gene duplications, considering duplicates that capture 90% or more of gene sequences, in agreement with previous methods [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>We estimate a whole gene duplication rate of 1.17 × 10−9 per gene per generation for D. yakuba and 6.03 × 10−10 per gene per generation for D. simulans (Fig 5, Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>These estimates are in general agreement with surveys of duplicates in the D. melanogaster reference genome of 3.68 × 10−10 per gene per generation [8, 10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>The rate of recruited non-coding sequence is 3.46 × 10−10 in D. yakuba and 2.42 × 10−10 in D. simulans and the rate of chimeric gene formation is equally low with 3.7 × 10−10 in D. yakuba and 8.52 × 10−11 in D. simulans (Fig 5, Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>We observe more tandem duplications in D. yakuba in spite of its lower N e, yielding a duplication rate per gene in D. yakuba two-fold higher than that of D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>New mutations are often unable to spread through populations as low frequency variants can be lost through stochastic drift especially if recessive [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the time to a sweep on a new mutation is expected to be substantially longer than the time until new mutations appear in populations [19, 20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0132184.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0132184.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Genomewide population mutation rates for all duplications (θ), population sizes (N e), and per gene mutation rates (μ) for gene structures produced by whole gene duplication, recruitment of non-coding sequence, and chimeric genes by species. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Low mutation rates and mutation limited evolution leads to low levels of parallel recruitment of tandem duplications. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0132184.g005"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Given these estimates of θ π for each class of mutations, we estimate T e, the time to establishment of a deterministic sweep from new mutations in a population such that variants overcome the forces of drift [19, 20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>We assume that beneficial mutations appear at strongly selected sites at a rate equivalent to the genome-wide effective mutation rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>In reality not all mutations are beneficial and the true rate of adaptive substitution is likely to be less common than those discussed here. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>These estimates therefore represent a lower bound on the time to adaptation through new mutation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>With a modest selection coefficient of s = 0.01 similar to that previously observed for duplicates and chimeras [12], in D. yakuba T e would be 7270 generations (600 years at 12 generations per year) for SNPs, 36,000 generations (3000 years) for whole gene duplications, and over 100,000 generations (≥ 9500 years) for chimeric genes (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>For D. simulans, these numbers point to a greater disparity between SNPs and duplicates with T e of 3580 generations (300 years) for SNPs, 34,400 generations (2800 years) for whole gene duplications, and 243,000 generations (20,000 years) for chimeric genes (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>These estimates of effective mutation rates for whole gene duplications and complex gene structures point to long waiting times for new mutations and a disparity in the response of duplicates and SNPs in the face of strong selective pressures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Although the differences in effective mutation rates appear to be modest, they can result in additional thousands of years in the waiting time for selective sweeps to establish with new mutations, resulting in limited ability to adapt to shifting selective pressures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Under more extreme selection coefficients, given the assumption that the beneficial mutation rate matches the mutation rate per site, waiting times may be shorter, allowing for adaptation at SNPs in hundreds of generations (decades) and thousands of generations (centuries) for gene duplications (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Under expanded census sizes 100X larger than N e with extreme selection coefficients, waiting times for new mutations may potentially approach the range of full availability of mutations (Table H in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>However, such extreme dynamics are unlikely to reflect the range of selection coefficients or the rate of adaptation genomewide [61, 62] and are well outside selection coefficients previously estimated for duplicate and chimeric genes of ≈ 1% [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Thus, we would not expect such estimates based on selection coefficients of 20% to be broadly applicable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Parallel evolution for tandem duplications </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>We find 56 genes are partially or wholly duplicated both in D. yakuba and in D. simulans, 11% of duplicated genes in D. simulans (56478) and less than the number of genes duplicated multiple times in D. simulans alone, suggesting that there is little concurrence in the standing variation of the two species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>That 56 genes would be shared across the two species is greater than expected given the limits of available standing variation of 478 duplicated genes in D. simulans and 875 in D. yakuba based on uniform chance (P = 2.812 × 10−8, binomial test) pointing to mutational or selective pressures on similar genes (SI Text). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Fewer annotated gene models are available for D. simulans w501 reference [63] leading to smaller absolute numbers of genes even though proportions are similar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, a comparison to duplicate genes in D. melanogaster[64] shows only 5 genes that exist among the segregating variation of tandem duplications in all three species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>The mutations described here have been polarized with respect to ancestry, and are segregating meaning that they are expected to have formed very recently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>As such, shared variants are the product of independent mutation in the two species, not shared ancestry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>We find that 13.4% of the genome is present but unsampled in D. yakuba and 9.7% in D. simulans, indicating that the likelihood of shared, unsampled variation is low. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Such unsampled alleles will be at low frequency and are unlikely to be able to establish selective sweeps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Hence, the portion of variation available for selective sweeps that is shared across species will be low, resulting in a rarity of evolution through parallel recruitment of tandem duplicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Some genes within the genome are captured by as many as 6 independent tandem duplications in D. yakuba and 32 independent tandem duplications in D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>There are 10 genes in D. yakuba and 12 genes in D. simulans that are captured by more than three independent tandem duplications, and these have been excluded from mutation estimates (Table G in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Some of these variants are chorion proteins known to experience somatic duplications in follicle cells [65], and certain of these hotspots may therefore represent cases of somatic mutation rather than inherited variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>These “hotspots” within the genome may have duplication rates high enough that evolution will not be subject to the same limitations with respect to standing variation and sweeps on new mutations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Rapid Evolution </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Biases in the rates at which tandem duplications form in different genomic regions or a greater propensity for selection to favor duplications in specific functional classes can result in a bias in gene ontology categories among duplicated genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>We previously used DAVID gene ontology analysis software to identify overrepresented functions among duplicate genes in D. yakuba and D. simulans [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Here, we compare the agreement in gene ontology categories in D. yakuba and D. simulans with expectations based on random sampling to determine whether such convergence at the level of functional categories is significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Notably, among randomly selected subsets of genes for D. yakuba and D. simulans there is no agreement in functional categories at an EASE cutoff of 1.0 for any biochemical function or domain, and no functional category was significant at an EASE cutoff of 1.5, a stark contrast with what is observed for duplications (see S2 File). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Among genes captured by tandem duplications, immune response and toxin metabolism, chitin cuticle formation and chemosensation are overrepresented in both species (Fig 6A, Table D in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Such overrepresentation is not identified in randomly selected subsets of genes for D. yakuba and D. simulans, suggesting a greater level of convergence than is expected based on chance alone (Table D in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>To determine whether selection is favoring these functional classes, we identified duplications outside centromeric regions that lie in windows at or below the 5% tail of θ π, consistent with selection reducing diversity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Among these genes in regions with reduced diversity we identify genes in both D. yakuba and D. simulans with functions in chorion or oogenesis, mating behavior, immune response and defense against bacteria, olfactory response, chitin metabolism, xenobiotics and toxin metabolism, and sperm development (Supplementary Information). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>The presence of genes with these functional categories is consistent with a portion of the overrepresentation in gene ontologies across all duplicates being driven at least in part by selection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0132184.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0132184.g006</object-id><label>Fig 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>A) Gene ontology classes overrepresented by species among singly duplicated genes or among multiply duplicated genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>B) Number of genes duplicated by species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Most variants are species specific, with small numbers of parallel duplication of orthologs across species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0132184.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec008"><title><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>We have described the prevalence of tandem duplications in natural populations of D. yakuba and D. simulans, their frequencies in the population, and the genes that they affect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>We find that tandem duplications show a bias towards gene ontologies associated with rapid evolutionary processes and that they commonly affect the X chromosome in D. simulans in comparison to the autosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>In spite of their strong role in adaptation, we find low rates of parallel recruitment of tandem duplications across species due to low formation rates and mutation limited evolution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec009"><title><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Widespread positive selection on the X chromosome in D. simulans </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>We observe an excess of high frequency tandem duplications on the D. simulans X chromosomes in comparison to neutral intronic SNPs as well as signs of reduced diversity surrounding tandem duplications on the D. simulans X, consistent with widespread selection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Background selection [66] and hitchhiking [67] are not expected to act differently on duplications in comparison to SNPs and cannot explain the patterns observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Yet, we observe significant differences between the SFS of duplicates and putatively neutral SNPs, pointing to a role for adaptation through tandem duplication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>We also observe reduced nucleotide diversity surrounding tandem duplications on the D. simulans X, consistent with selection favoring duplicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Hence, the overabundance of high-frequency tandem duplications on the X is likely to be driven by selection and these represent strong candidate loci for ongoing selective sweeps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Based on the newly assembled D. simulans reference, X vs. autosome divergence indicates faster evolution on the X chromosome at non-synonymous sites, long introns, and UTRs [63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>This pattern is distinct from observations at synonymous sites as well as general patterns of differential evolution on the autosomes [63], further evidence of more frequent selective sweeps on the X chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Roughly 25% of tandem duplications in each species are flanked by repetitive sequence and there is an overabundance of tandem duplicates associated with repetitive sequence on the D. simulans X [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>It is possible that such repeats contribute to the formation of these mutations, thereby influencing the evolution of the D. simulans X. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>The X chromosome is thought to evolve rapidly due to sexual conflict, intragenomic conflict, and sexual selection [68] and thus multiple selective forces may facilitate the spread of duplicates on the X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>The X chromosome in D. simulans houses an excess of duplicates in comparison to all autosomes, as well as a strong association with repetitive sequence and tandem duplications on the X [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the X chromosome appears to be subject to particularly rapid evolution of duplicate content in D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Previous work has identified signals of adaptation through duplication on the D. melanogaster X chromosome [69, 70], suggesting parallel evolution through duplication in these species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>However, we do not observe similar patterns in D. yakuba, suggesting that the X may either be evolving under different selective pressures in the two different clades or that selective pressures on the D. yakuba X chromosome are of lesser magnitude. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Stronger sexual selection, greater selection for X-chromosome related traits, sympatric associations with competitor species with reinforcement for mating aversion, or a greater instance of driving X chromosomes might potentially drive these species differences in X-chromosome evolution, and elucidating the nature of selection on these sex chromosomes may help explain the adaptive (or selfish) role of tandem duplication on the X. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Mutation limited evolution </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>While both D. simulans and D. yakuba house a rich diversity of duplicated sequences, only a few percent of the genome will be covered by tandem duplications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>With lower mutation rates for duplications [8, 10, 71], there may be long waiting times to achieve any single new mutation, and the landscape of standing variation will shape evolutionary outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>As such, any evolutionary path that is dependent upon tandem duplications of any specific genomic sequence will be severely limited by the small likelihood that the necessary mutation is among the standing variation. Drosophila represent organisms with large effective population sizes (Fig 5) [22, 72] and are expected to host large numbers of duplications as standing variation in comparison to other multicellular eukaryotes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>We have shown that the number of tandem duplications segregating in the population is substantially smaller than the number of mutations needed to guarantee a duplicate of any desired genomic region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>However, when population level mutation rates are small, standing variation is unlikely to offer a sufficient substrate for selective sweeps and systems will be stuck waiting for new mutations that are slow to materialize [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>We observe population level mutation rates θ per gene for tandem duplications on the order of 0.00277 in D. yakuba and 0.00291 in D. simulans (Table 1, Fig 5) resulting in low probabilities that standing variation offers the major source of adaptation and long waiting times to sweeps on new mutations on the order of hundreds to thousands of years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>While retrogenes might provide additional sources of duplicated sequences, their rates of formation are exceptionally limited [8, 10] and they are therefore not expected to contribute more substantially than tandem duplications to genomic variation and will not suffice to overcome these limitations of low mutation rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Thus, we conclude that outside of a small number of mutational hotspots evolution through duplication is mutation limited even in Drosophila which have large N e, and that these limits are expected to be even more severe for many other multicellular eukaryotes, especially vertebrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>In some rare cases, organisms with small N e may harbor more extreme variation under nearly neutral dynamics, but the absolute number of such mutations will be very limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Thus, cases of adaptation from standing variation of extreme variants in organisms with small N e are possible, but rare. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>The majority of tandem duplications identified in D. yakuba and D. simulans appear to be at extremely low frequency, with an excess of singleton variants in comparison to neutral intronic SNPs, suggesting that large numbers of tandem duplications are detrimental, consistent with previous work in other species [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>It has previously been argued that the accumulation of duplications is the product of small N e and inability of selection to purge nearly neutral alleles from the population [17, 59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>However, we show that duplicates are less likely to be neutral in comparison to putatively neutral intronic SNPs suggesting that they often have phenotypic effects larger than the limit near-neutrality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>We have shown that both positive and negative selection will affect the fixation or loss of duplications and that simplified nearly neutral theories are unlikely to explain the patterns observed across species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Rather, selection is expected to play an appreciable role in the evolution of tandem duplications and their contribution to genome content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Previous work has shown different patterns for young and old duplicate genes, with many young duplicates and chimeras forming in tandem but more duplicates and chimeras preserved over long periods that are where paralogs are dispersed from one another [8, 10, 73] even though variants found in tandem show signals of selection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Two factors are likely to explain this disparity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>First, genome shuffling and syntenic breaks are common over time [74, 75]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Second, it is likely that forces leading to adaptation are likely to be distinct from forces that lead to gene preservation as preservation requires that genes remain essential over long periods of time, especially if selective pressures on non-essential genes are transient [10, 12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Likelihood of parallel recruitment of tandem duplications across species </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Convergent evolution is often interpreted of a signal of adaptation in experimental evolution and in natural populations [29, 30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Here, we show that for tandem duplications, parallel recruitment of genes for duplication and diversification independent from shared ancestry will be very rare in spite of convergence in functional categories represented. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Thus, the reliance on genetic convergence to establish natural selection in natural populations will underreport selected alleles and result in significant underestimation of the number and types of alleles that are selected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Though convergence is common in experimental evolution of both prokaryotic systems and multicellular eukaryotes with shared ancestry [30], these results suggest that these systems are unlikely to reflect the frequency of convergent evolution in natural populations of independently evolving species of multicellular eukaryotes that have little shared standing variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>We observe an excess of variants with gene ontologies consistent with similar rapid evolutionary processes both in D. yakuba and in D. simulans (Fig 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>However, few genes (∼ 11%) are duplicated in both species and only a handful have been identified in D. simulans, D. yakuba, and D. melanogaster (Fig 6B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Moreover, none of the high frequency variants in the in D. yakuba and D. simulans capture orthologous sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Hence, in spite of parallel selective pressures on rapidly evolving phenotypes, there is little parallel recruitment of the same genetic solutions with respect to duplication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Given the limited genomic span of standing variation in the population (Table F in S1 File), and low rates of new mutation (Fig 5, Table 1), as well as the low frequency of a large fraction of variants, parallel fixation of tandem duplications in the same genes will be extremely rare even among genera with large effective population sizes facing similar selective pressures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Convergence depends on the waiting time of new mutations to enter populations and establish selective sweeps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>We show that the average waiting time for a new mutation given a selection coefficient of s = 0.01 is hundreds of years for SNPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Here, we find that tandem duplications display signals of reduced heterozygosity in the surrounding regions as well as an association with gene ontologies indicative of rapidly evolving phenotypes, and an overrepresentation of shared tandem duplicates across species for specific genes given the limits of standing variation, consistent with widespread adaptation through tandem duplication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>However, the average waiting time for a deterministic sweep to establish in a population will be thousands of years for tandem duplications and tens of thousands of years for chimeric genes given a modest selection coefficient of s = 0.01. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Such strongly selected sites are expected to be rare throughout the genome and beneficial mutations are likely to appear less often than the actual mutation rate [61, 62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Thus, these waiting times given strong selection provide a lower bound to the waiting time for a selected sweep. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>We therefore expect that mutation will severely limit evolution through whole gene duplication and chimera formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>To the extent that adaptation depends on tandem duplications, the ability of organisms to adapt to changing environments will be hindered by a lack of variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Thus, even when a given tandem duplication is needed for adaptation, we expect that the limits of mutation will lead to low levels of convergence and scarcity of shared genetic solutions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec012"><title><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Duplicate genes and rapidly evolving phenotypes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Both D. simulans and D. yakuba have an overabundance of genes with ontology classifications involved in immune function, chemosensory processing or response, and drug and toxin metabolism that is significantly greater than expectations based on random chance (Table D in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>These phenotypes are strongly associated with rapid evolution due to host-parasite interactions, predator-prey coevolution, and sexual conflict [76–79]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Previous work has observed similar bias toward rapid amino acid substitutions in olfactory genes, and chitin cuticle genes in D. melanogaster and D. simulans [80], selection for gene family evolution in and selection for toxin resistance is common in D. melanogaster [78, 81] suggesting that associated phenotypes may be under widespread selection in multiple species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Host pathogen systems as well as arms races in pesticide and toxin resistance operate under Red Queen dynamics in which conflicts between organisms result in repeated selective sweeps [82]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Organisms that lack the genetic means to adapt to rapidly changing systems will be at a distinct disadvantage in the face of selective events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the overrepresentation of tandem duplications in cytochromes and drug or toxin metabolism genes confirms rapid evolution in copy number seen in comparison of reference genomes [75] as well as recent studies of insecticide resistance and viral resistance in natural populations [3, 81, 83]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Large amounts of divergence driven by selection among non-synonymous sites and UTRs in D. simulans [84] and high rates of adaptive substitutions [80, 85] point to widespread selective pressures acting in D. simulans, and it is likely that these same pressures influence the current diversity and frequency of copy number variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>If rapidly evolving systems rely heavily on complex mutations or if selection coefficients are modest, profiles of standing variation will place strong limits on outcomes in response to selection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Shifting selective pressures such as those found in rapidly evolving systems or gross ecological change require a pool of genetic variation to facilitate adaptation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>We observe standing variation and mutational profiles that will limit evolutionary trajectories and would expect these limits to be even more severe for rapidly evolving phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Repeated sweeps are expected to purge genetic and phenotypic diversity, and recovering such diversity after sweeps can take thousands of generations [86]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Thus, during rapid evolution, selection will potentially purge diversity that is needed for subsequent steps in the adaptive walk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Hence, although tandem duplications are key players in rapid evolution, their limited rates of formation combined with low frequencies due to commonly detrimental impacts will hinder evolutionary outcomes or force alternative adaptive trajectories precisely when variation is urgently needed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Hence, we do not observe convergence across individual loci in spite of substantial convergence across functional categories. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec013"><title><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec014"><title><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Tandem duplications </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Tandem duplications were identified using paired-end Illumina sequencing of genomic DNA for 20 strains of D. yakuba and 20 strains of D. simulans as well as the reference genome of each species as described in Rogers et al. (2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>The dataset describes derived, segregating tandem duplications that span 25 kb or less. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>These sequences exclude ancestral duplications as well as putative duplications in the resequenced reference genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>The resulting list of variants describes segregating variation for newly formed tandem duplicates across the full genome in these two species of non-model Drosophila. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>All data files are available via <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molpopgen.org/Data">http://molpopgen.org/Data</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.github.com/ThorntonLab/DrosophilaPopGenData-Rogers2014">http://www.github.com/ThorntonLab/DrosophilaPopGenData-Rogers2014</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Aligned bam files were deposited in the National Institutes of Health Short Read Archive under accession numbers SRP040290 and SRP029453. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Sequenced stocks were deposited in the University of California, San Diego (UCSD) stock center with stock numbers 14021-0261.38- 14021-0261.51 and 14021-0251.293–14021-0251.311. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec015"><title><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Identifying duplicated coding sequence </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Tandem duplications were previously identified using a combination of paired-end read mapping and coverage changes in 20 isofemale lines of D. yakuba and 20 isofemale lines in D. simulans generated via 9–12 generations of sibling mating from wild-caught flies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>We sequenced 10 isofemale lines of D. yakuba from Nairobi, Kenya, and 10 isofemale lines from Nguti, Cameroon as well as 10 isofemale lines of D. simulans from Nairobi, Kenya and 10 isofemale lines from Madagascar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Duplications were identified through divergently oriented reads and coverage changes in comparison to reference genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>We identify 1415 tandem duplications in D. yakuba and 975 tandem duplications segregating in D. simulans that span 845 different gene sequences in D. yakuba and 478 different gene sequences in D. simulans [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Gene duplications were defined as any divergent read calls whose maximum span across all lines overlaps with the annotated CDS coordinates. D. yakuba CDS annotations were based on flybase release D. yakuba r.1.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Gene annotations for the recent reassembly of the D. simulans reference were produced by aligning all D. melanogaster CDS sequences to the D. simulans reference in a tblastx (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genomics.princeton.edu/AndolfattoLab/w501_genome.html">http://genomics.princeton.edu/AndolfattoLab/w501_genome.html</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Percent coverage of the CDS was defined based on the portion of the corresponding genomic sequence from start to stop that was covered by the maximum span of divergent read calls across all strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Using the representation of gene sequences in D. yakuba of 84516082 we use a binomial test to calculate the likelihood of 56 shared variants among the 47810786 genes duplicated in D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec016"><title><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Estimated number of segregating tandem duplications </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>We compared the estimated total number of duplications expected in a population to estimates of diversity based on our sample of 20 strains, correcting S for a 3.9% false positive rate (Table E in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Under a standard coalescent model [50, 87, 88]:  E[Spopulation]=Ssampleasample*apopulation Where a in a sample of size n (in this case n = 20): asample=∑i=1n−11i  apopulation=∑i=12Ne1i When 2N e is large: θ∑i=12Ne1i≈θ(ln(2Ne)+0.57722) Hence: E[Spopulation]=Ssamplea20*(ln(2Ne)+0.57722) We can use similar methods to estimate the variance in the number of segregating sites in the population. Var[Spopulation]=θ∑i=12Ne1i+θ2∑i=02Ne1i2 When 2N e is large: ∑i=12Ne1i2≈π26.  Var[Spopulation]=θ(ln(2Ne)+0.57722)+θ2π26  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, we can use rarefaction estimators, which are free of population genetic assumptions to estimate the total number of duplications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Using the Chao estimator [57] for Stotal=Sobs+S122S2, where S 1 and S 2 are the number of variants at a frequency of 1 and 2 resepectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>The estimated variance is then S2[(S14S2)4+(S1S2)3+(S12S2)2]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec017"><title><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Gene Ontology </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Overrepresented functional categories were identified using DAVID gene ontology software with an EASE threshold of 1.0. as previously described [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>We observe several functional categories indicative of rapid evolution that are shared between the two species (Table D in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>In order to determine whether such agreement at the level of functional category is greater than expected by chance, we selected a random subset of 845 genes for D. yakuba and 478 genes from D. simulans, and performed ontology analysis for a comparison. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec018"><title><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Proportion of the genome represented by segregating duplicates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>To determine the number of duplications necessary to span the full range of the genome, we simulated chromosomes with a length determined by the number of base pairs with non-zero coverage in our reference strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>We then simulated random draws from the distribution of duplication lengths for each chromosome, placing duplication start sites at random and recorded the number of duplications necessary to cover 10%, 25%, 50%, and 90% of sequence length for each chromosome in each trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Simulations were repeated for 1000 trials for each chromosome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>These simulations do not account for mutational biases that might result in clustering of duplications in particular regions while other regions remain static, nor do they require that new duplications reach an appreciable frequency so that they are immune to stochastic loss through genetic drift. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>They do not require that duplications capture sufficient sequence to have functional impacts or require that breakpoints not disrupt known functional elements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, simulating individual chromosomes separately decreases the likelihood of resampling particular sites thereby lowering the estimated number of duplications needed to cover the entire genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Hence, these estimates put a highly conservative lower bound on the minimum number of mutations necessary to capture the full genomic sequence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>To estimate the expected proportion of the genome spanned by all duplicates in the population, we resampled 6700 duplicates from the observed size distribution of D. yakuba with replacement and 4000 duplicates from the observed size distribution of D. simulans, placing duplications at random positions across the chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>We performed 100 replicates of sampling and report the mean across all replicates for each species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>In D. simulans we observe one case with 19 independent whole gene duplications of a single ORF [4], suggesting up to 1000-fold variation in mutation rates over the genome average. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Estimates of population level variation and genome wide effective mutation rates ignore mutation rate variation where some regions may be highly prone to duplications whereas others remain static, which would reduce the likelihood of unobserved tandem duplications outside of mutational hotspots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Hence, these estimates represent a lower bound on the number of duplications necessary to span the entire genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec019"><title><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Effective mutation rates and waiting times for duplicates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>We estimate average heterozygosity (θ π) and effective mutation rates (μ) per gene for D. yakuba and D. simulans for gene duplications that capture at least 90% of gene sequence (in agreement with previous estimates [10]), for genes that recruit non-coding sequence, and for chimeric genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Heterozygosity estimates used to calculate effective mutation rates were corrected for ascertainment bias (see SI Text) and excluded genes that were captured by 4 or more independent mutations, a signal of hotspots and mutation rate heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>Heterozygosity per gene is estimated given 16,082 gene sequences in D. yakuba and 10,786 coding sequences in D. simulans (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Like all estimates of mutation rates, these will exclude lethal varinats or variants that produce sterility or early-life pathogenic effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>However, they should accurately reflect the amount of variation that can be observed among standing variation, including even moderately deleterious mutations that are destined for eventual loss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Given estimates of θ π, we estimate the probability of adaptation from standing variation under an additive genetic model for neutral variants, P sgv = 1 − e −θπ*ln(1+2Nes) [18] and the time to establishment (T e) of a deterministic sweep from new mutations, such that new mutants escape the stochastic forces of drift, Te=1θπs [19, 20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>These estimates are provided for two strong selection coefficients of s = 0.01 similar to what is observed in Drosophila for chimeric and duplicate genes [12] and s = 0.20 modeling abnormally strong selection on a single locus consistent with Karasov et al. [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Estimates assume that a given site of interest is under strong selection and that the beneficial mutation rate is equal to the mutation rate per site per generation providing an upper limit on the ability of new mutations to facilitate adaptation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>In reality, strongly selected sites will be rare throughout the genome [61, 62] and these waiting times given strong selection will not accurately reflect the expected number of selective sweeps throughout the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>We additionally estimate the time to loss given loss for alleles in the population according to 2ln(N e) [58], the nearly neutral selection coefficient s&gt;14Ne [59] as well as population level mutation rates θ for alternative effective population sizes to determine the broader applicability of these results to other organisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec020"><title><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Intronic SNPs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>In order to produce a neutral proxy for sequence change in each species, we identified SNPs for short introns 100 bp or less, focusing on sites 8–30 which are generally subject to little constraint [89–91]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Reads containing indels were re-aligned using GATK [92]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>SNPs were identified across strains using samtools v1.18 mpileup [93] disabling probabilistic realignment (-B) and outputting genotype likelihoods in BCF format (-g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>The resulting BCF used to create a VCF using bcftools, calling bases using Bayesian inference (-c) calling genotypes per sample (-g) with a scaled mutation rate of 1% (-t.01) under a haploid model (ploidy = 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>SNPs were required to have minimum Illumina coverage depth of 20 reads, maximum coverage of 250 reads, MQ ≥ 20, and GQ ≥ 30 and invar GQ ≥ 40. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>We excluded SNPs identified in the reference, which are indicative of either assembly errors or residual heterozygosity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>We performed hierarchical cluster analysis in R using all SNPs by chromosome to evaluate population structure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>The ancestral state for each SNP was established through comparison with the nearest sequenced reference genome as an outgroup, D. erecta for D. yakuba sequences and D. melanogaster for D. simulans sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Orthologs between each species and its outgroup were identified using reciprocal best hit criteria in a BLASTn at an E-value cutoff of 10−5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Full gene sequences for each ortholog were then aligned using clustalw, keeping only genes which aligned with 85% or greater nucleotide identity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Divergence between the two species, Div x, y, was defined based on alignments of intronic sites from bases 8–30 between each species and the outgroup reference genome, excluding gapped sequences, for aligned orthologs with 85% or nucleotide identity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>The ancestral state was defined based on the corresponding sequence in the outgroup genome (D. melanogaster for D. simulans and D. erecta for D. yakuba). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>We excluded sites where the outgroup reference was in disagreement with both the D. yakuba reference and D. yakuba SNPs, as well as triallelic SNPs, sites with reference sequence of ‘N’, or SNPs identified in the VCF for the reference, suggesting inaccuracies in reference assembly or residual heterozygosity in the reference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>These resulted in a total of 7158 intronic SNPs in D. yakuba and 5504 intronic SNPs in D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>The resulting unfolded SFS was then corrected for the probability of independent mutations in both reference genomes leading to incorrect inference of the ancestral state. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Parallel mutations occurring independently at nucleotide sites in different species can obscure evolutionary relationships and artificially skew SFS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>We corrected SFS for SNPs prior to performing comparisons for tests of selection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Given net divergence D net = Div x, y − π x, the probability of identical independent mutations occurring in the outgroup reference genome is reflected by either the probability of an independent transition (ts) at the site of a transition mutation, or by 1/2 the probability of a transversion (tv) at the site of a transversion polymorphism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Thus, k=[(κ2+κ)2+12(22+κ)2]Dnet(1) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Empirically, in Drosophila κ=tstv=2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Thus, k=38Dnet. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>The unfolded SFS for intronic sites was corrected for the likelihood of independent mutations in the reference, k. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>The probability of independent mutations occurring in both genomes is equal to the probability of either two independent transitions or two independent transversions occurring in both genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>We calculated π x as the average heterozygosity per intronic site. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Given a likelihood of independent identical mutations of k=38Dnet. Si,obs=E[Si]-E[Si](k)+E[Sn-i](k)(2) Sn-i,obs=E[Sn-i]-E[Sn-i](k)+E[S-i](k)(3) Substituting Eq 3 into Eq 2, we obtain E[Si]=Si,obs(1-k)-Sn-i,obs(k)1-2k(4) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec021"><title><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Correcting Duplicates for Ascertainment Bias </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Tandem duplications, unlike SNPs, cannot be identified using paired-end reads in individual strains except through comparison to the reference genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Moreover, variants that are segregating at high frequency in populations are substantially more likely to be present in the reference, and therefore are substantially less likely to be identified in sample strains [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>We corrected site frequency spectra according to the model developed previously [5]. xi=yinn-i∑i=1n-2yinn-i(5) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Here, x i is the true proportion of alleles at frequency i in the population, and y i is the observed proportion of alleles at frequency i in a sample of n strains (here 21). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>The correction for ascertainment bias lowers estimates of the proportion found a low frequencies and increases estimates of the proportion at high frequency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>For estimates of population site frequency spectra, we removed all variants with divergently oriented reads in the reference strain, as these would not be identified in an accurately annotated reference. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec022"><title><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Residual heterozygosity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Some isofemale lines contained regions of residual heterozygosity in spite of over 10 generations of inbreeding in the lab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>To detect regions of residual heterozygosity, we called SNPs as above under a diploid model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>Segments with residual heterozygosity were detected using an HMM (“HMM”;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/HMM/">http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/HMM/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>Prior probabilities on states were set as: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>π=[0.5.0.5] </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>Transition probabilities were set to: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>T=[1-10-1010-1010-101-10-10] </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>and emission probabilities set to: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>E=[θϵ1-θ1-ϵ] </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list><p><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>Where ε = 0.001 and θ = 0.01. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>The most likely path was calculated using the Viterbi algorithm, and heterozygous segments 10kb or larger were retained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>Heterozygous blocks within 100kb of one another in a sample strain were clustered together as a single segment to define the span of residual heterozygosity within inbred lines. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec023"><title><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>Differences in Site Frequency Spectra </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>If different classes of duplications have different selective impacts, we should observe clear differences in site frequency spectra, with more positively selected duplications showing fewer singleton alleles and more high frequency variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>Site frequency spectra are not normally distributed, nor can they be normalized through standard transformations, and thus require non-parametric tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>We used a two-sided Wilcoxon rank sum test to determine whether site frequency spectra were significantly different. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>For each comparison, we excluded tandem duplications that are present in the reference genomes as well as putative ancestral duplications, as these are likely to display biases with respect to size, propensity to capture coding sequences, and association with repetitive content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>We compared site frequency spectra of the following groups within each species: duplications on the X and on the autosomes and all pairwise combinations of SNPs and duplicates on the X and autosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>We also performed Kolmogorov-Smirnov test for comparison. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>In D. simulans, we used a χ 2 test to determine whether high frequency alleles are overrepresented among duplications on the X relative to intronic SNPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>Data for the χ 2 test was binned using a cutoff to compare the proportion of variants as at a sample frequency of ≥1617. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Tandem duplicates that lie in regions with residually heterozygous segments extending 1kb upstream or downstream were excluded from the SFS, resulting in unequal sample sizes for different variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>Samples with fewer than 15 strains remaining were excluded from the SFS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>The SFS for intronic SNPs and for duplicates was then scaled to a sample of size 17 in D. simulans and 15 in D. yakuba according to Nielsen et al. [48]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec024"><title><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>Segregating Inversions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>In order to check for population substructure, we aligned all SNPs in intronic sequences from 8–30 bp as a neutral proxy [89–91] and performed hierarchical clustering in R using hclust. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>These SNPs were intended solely to differentiate strains and were not polarized with respect to the ancestral state or otherwise filtered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>We observe little evidence for population structure in D. simulans (Figure L in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>However, we identify structure on chromosome 2 in D. yakuba (Figure M in S1 File), consistent with known polymorphic inversions prohibiting recombination on chromosome 2 [53, 54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>Strains do not strictly cluster with respect to geography but rather are reticulated amongst other groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>Moreover, among duplicates we do not observe an excess of moderate frequency alleles as one would expect under population substructure given our sampling scheme (Figure A in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>Thus, these strains constitute a single admixed population. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>Some strains retained residual heterozygosity even after 9 generations of inbreeding, with greater residual heterozygosity in D. yakuba than in D. simulans, consistent with inversions segregating in D. yakuba. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>These regions of residual heterozygosity can result in incorrect estimates of SFS by artificially increasing chances of observing variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>Site frequency spectra were calculated across all strais by correcting sample frequencies for ascertainment bias, excluding regions of residual heterozygosity and then projecting frequencies onto a sample size of 15 in D. yakuba and 17 in D. simulans according to [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>As a neutral comparison we calculated SFS for intronic SNPs (as above) and projected the SFS down to a sample size of 15 in D. yakuba and 17 in D. simulans (Figure A in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec025"><title><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>Likelihood of shared variation through ancestry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>The likelihood of shared variation through shared ancestry can be obtained through a coalescent approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>The probability that an allele does not coalesce in the time period from the present back to the speciation event that separated D. yakuba and D. simulans is (1−12Ne)t. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>This can be approximated using e−t2Ne. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>We estimate θ pi for putatively neutral 8–30 bp from short introns using libsequence [94], ignoring sites that are heterozygous and sites with missing data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>For neutral intronic SNPs, θ pi = 0.0138 in D. yakuba and θ pi = 0.0280 in D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>Using the mutation rate of 5.8 × 10−9 [95], we find N e = (0.0138)/(4 × 5.8 × 10−9) = 5.93 × 105 in D. yakuba and N e = (0.0280)/(4 × 5.8 × 10−9) = 1.21 × 106 in D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>Using t = 12MY [28] and 12 generations per year, and N e = 1.2 × 106 from D. simulans, we obtain a probability of shared ancestry for an allele of 9 × 10−27, vanishingly small. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>We have polarized all mutations against the putative ancestral state using outgroup reference genomes, focusing solely on derived mutations [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the expectation of shared variation for any two alleles through shared ancestry for D. yakuba and D. simulans is expected to be low. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>Even large samples are not expected to harbor shared variation over such timescales [96]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>Thus, we expect shared variants described here to result from independent mutations, not from long standing neutral polymorphism. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec026"><title><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>Diversity surrounding SNPs and duplications </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>We estimate θ π, θ W, and Tajima’s D for all SNPs in the D. yakuba and D. simulans genomes, removing sites with missing or ambiguous data as well as heterozygous sites using libsequence [94]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>We calculate θ π, θ W, and Tajima’s D3 for 5 kb windows moving in a 500 bp slide across the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>For each window, we divide estimates by the number of sites per window with a minimum Illumina coverage depth of 20 reads, maximum coverage of 250 reads, MQ ≥ 20, consistent with the threshold used to identify SNPs, in order to estimate θ π and θ W per site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>We compare θ π per site for regions surrounding derived, segregating tandem duplications with regions surrounding derived, segregating, putatively neutral intronic SNPs from 8–30 bp of short introns, excluding windows with less than 4000 bp out 5000 bp that could be assayed for SNPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>We exclude second SNPs in a single 5 kb window, and exclude SNPs and duplicates that are found in the centromeric regions, which have unusually low diversity (Figures B-K in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>We scaled diversity estimates by chromosome mean and standard deviation to produce a unit normal distribution and allow data to be combined across chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>We then compared diversity at the 5000 bp window immediately surrounding SNPs to diversity for the window immediately surrounding duplications and the X chromosome using a single tailed Wilcoxon rank sum test (Table C in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>Chromosome 2 in D. yakuba houses multiple segregating inversions [53, 54], which can cause atypical evolutionary dynamics and abnormal signals of diversity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>Thus, we assayed data for chromosomes 2, 3 and X separately in D. yakuba. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>For D. simulans, data was combined across all autosomes, and the X chromosome in D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>We plotted lowess smoothed regressions of diversity using a smoothing factor of 110 from 50 kb upstream to 50kb downstream of a mutant (Figs 2–3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>Tests of nucleotide diversity and plots of diversity surrounding duplicates and SNPs exclude a cluster of multiple duplications from 8.45 Mb-8.55 Mb which has abnormally low diversity (Figure I in S1 File). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec027"><title><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0132184.s001"><label>S1 File</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0132184.s001.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0132184.s002"><label>S2 File</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>Contains Supplementary Text A-J. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>Text A: chromosome names vs number identifiers for D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>Text B: DAVID gene ontology results for D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>Text C: list of duplicated genes by chromosome for D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>Text D: DAVID gene ontology results for D. yakuba. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>Text E: list of duplicated genes by chromosome for D. yakuba. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>Text F: chromosome names vs number identifiers for D. yakuba. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>Text G: list of fly stocks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>Text H: Readme file. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>Text I: List of duplications for D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>Text J: List of duplications for D. yakuba. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>(ZIP) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0132184.s002.zip"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to thank Nigel F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>Delaney, Tim Bassinger, Elizabeth G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>King, Anthony D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>Long, and Alexis S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>Harrison, and Trevor Bedford for helpful discussions as well as the anonymous reviewers whose comments substantially improved the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>RLR, JMC, KRT, and PA performed analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>LS generated Illumina sequencing libraries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>TTH provided gene annotations for D. simulans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>RLR, JMC, PA and KRT designed experiments and analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0132184.ref001"><text><SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>1 ConantGC, WolfeKH. Turning a hobby into a job: how duplicated genes find new functions. Nat Rev Genet. 2008 12;9(12):938–950. 10.1038/nrg2482 <?supplied-pmid 19015656?>19015656 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref002"><text><SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>2 OhnoS. Evolution by gene duplication. London: George Alien &amp; Unwin Ltd Berlin, Heidelberg and New York: Springer-Verlag; 1970. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref003"><text><SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>3 MagwireMM, BayerF, WebsterCL, CaoC, JigginsFM. Successive increases in the resistance of Drosophila to viral infection through a transposon insertion followed by a Duplication. PLoS Genet. 2011 10;7(10):e1002337 10.1371/journal.pgen.1002337 <?supplied-pmid 22028673?>22028673 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref004"><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>4 RogersRL, CridlandJM, ShaoL, HuTT, AndolfattoP, ThorntonKR. Landscape of Standing Variation for Tandem Duplications in Drosophila yakuba and Drosophila simulans. Mol Biol Evol. 2014 7;31(7):1750–1766. 10.1093/molbev/msu124 <?supplied-pmid 24710518?>24710518 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref005"><text><SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>5 EmersonJJ, Cardoso-MoreiraM, BorevitzJO, LongM. Natural selection shapes genome-wide patterns of copy-number polymorphism in Drosophila melanogaster . Science. 2008 6;320(5883):1629–1631. 10.1126/science.1158078 <?supplied-pmid 18535209?>18535209 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref006"><text><SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>6 Cardoso-MoreiraM, EmersonJJ, ClarkAG, LongM.  Drosophila duplication hotspots are associated with late-replicating regions of the genome. PLoS Genet. 2011 11;7(11):e1002340 10.1371/journal.pgen.1002340 <?supplied-pmid 22072977?>22072977 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref007"><text><SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>7 DopmanEB, HartlDL. A portrait of copy-number polymorphism in Drosophila melanogaster . Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2007 12;104(50):19920–19925. 10.1073/pnas.0709888104 <?supplied-pmid 18056801?>18056801 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref008"><text><SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>8 ZhouQ, ZhangG, ZhangY, XuS, ZhaoR, ZhanZ, et al On the origin of new genes in Drosophila . Genome Research. 2008 9;18(9):1446–1455. 10.1101/gr.076588.108 <?supplied-pmid 18550802?>18550802 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref009"><text><SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>9 KatjuV, LynchM. On the formation of novel genes by duplication in the Caenorhabditis elegans genome. Molecular Biology and Evolution. 2006 5;23(5):1056–1067. 10.1093/molbev/msj114 <?supplied-pmid 16500928?>16500928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref010"><text><SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>10 RogersRL, BedfordT, HartlDL. Formation and longevity of chimeric and duplicate genes in Drosophila melanogaster . Genetics. 2009 1;181(1):313–322. 10.1534/genetics.108.091538 <?supplied-pmid 19015547?>19015547 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref011"><text><SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>11 HahnMW, HanMV, HanSG. Gene Family Evolution across 12 Drosophila Genomes. PLoS Genetics. 2007 11 9;3(11):e197 10.1371/journal.pgen.0030197 <?supplied-pmid 17997610?>17997610 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref012"><text><SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>12 RogersRL, HartlDL. Chimeric genes as a source of rapid evolution in Drosophila melanogaster . Mol Biol Evol. 2012 2;29(2):517–529. 10.1093/molbev/msr184 <?supplied-pmid 21771717?>21771717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref013"><text><SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>13 JonesCD, BegunDJ. Parallel evolution of chimeric fusion genes. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA. 2005 8 9;102(32):11373–11378. 10.1073/pnas.0503528102  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref014"><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>14 ShihHJ, JonesCD. Patterns of amino acid evolution in the Drosophila ananassae chimeric gene, siren, parallel those of other Adh-derived chimeras. Genetics. 2008 10;180(2):1261–1263. 10.1534/genetics.108.090068 <?supplied-pmid 18780749?>18780749 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref015"><text><SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>15 LongM, LangleyCH. Natural selection and the origin of jingwei, a chimeric processed functional gene in Drosophila . Science. 1993 4 2;260(5104):91–95. 10.1126/science.7682012 <?supplied-pmid 7682012?>7682012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref016"><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>16 ZhangJ, DeanAM, BrunetF, LongM. Evolving protein functional diversity in new genes of Drosophila . Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA. 2004 11 16; 101(46):16246–16250. 10.1073/pnas.0407066101  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref017"><text><SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>17 LynchM, ConeryJS. The evolutionary fate and consequences of duplicate genes. Science. 2000 11;290(5494):1151–1155. 10.1126/science.290.5494.1151 <?supplied-pmid 11073452?>11073452 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref018"><text><SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>18 HermissonJ, PenningsPS. Soft sweeps: molecular population genetics of adaptation from standing genetic variation. Genetics. 2005 4;169(4):2335–2352. 10.1534/genetics.104.036947 <?supplied-pmid 15716498?>15716498 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref019"><text><SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>19 Maynard SmithJ. What use is sex? Journal of theoretical biology. 1971;30(2):319–335. 10.1016/0022-5193(71)90058-0 5548029 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref020"><text><SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>20 GillespieJH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>In: The Causes of Molecular Evolution. Oxford University Press; 1991 p. 232. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref021"><text><SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>21 KreitmanM. Nucleotide polymorphism at the alcohol dehydrogenase locus of Drosophila melanogaster. Nature. 1983;304(5925):412–417. 10.1038/304412a0 <?supplied-pmid 6410283?>6410283 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref022"><text><SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>22 BachtrogD, ThorntonK, ClarkA, AndolfattoP. Extensive introgression of mitochondrial DNA relative to nuclear genes in the Drosophila yakuba species group. Evolution. 2006 2;60(2):292–302. 10.1111/j.0014-3820.2006.tb01107.x <?supplied-pmid 16610321?>16610321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref023"><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>23 AndolfattoP, WongKM, BachtrogD. Effective population size and the efficacy of selection on the X chromosomes of two closely related Drosophila species. Genome Biol Evol. 2011;3:114–128. 10.1093/gbe/evq086 <?supplied-pmid 21173424?>21173424 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref024"><text><SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>24 KarasovT, MesserPW, PetrovDA. Evidence that adaptation in Drosophila is not limited by mutation at single sites. PLoS Genet. 2010 6;6(6):e1000924 10.1371/journal.pgen.1000924 <?supplied-pmid 20585551?>20585551 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref025"><text><SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>25 CarneiroM, HartlDL. Colloquium papers: Adaptive landscapes and protein evolution. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA. 2010 1 26;107 Suppl 1:1747–1751. 10.1073/pnas.0906192106  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref026"><text><SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>26 CuiY, WongWH, Bornberg-BauerE, ChanHS. Recombinatoric exploration of novel folded structures: a heteropolymer-based model of protein evolutionary landscapes. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA. 2002 1 22;99(2):809–814. 10.1073/pnas.022240299  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref027"><text><SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>27 GiverL, ArnoldFH. Combinatorial protein design by in vitro recombination. Current Opinion in Chemical Biology. 1998 6;2(3):335–338. 10.1016/S1367-5931(98)80006-9 <?supplied-pmid 9691067?>9691067 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref028"><text><SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>28 TamuraK, SubramanianS, KumarS. Temporal patterns of fruit fly (Drosophila) evolution revealed by mutation clocks. Mol Biol Evol. 2004 1;21(1):36–44. 10.1093/molbev/msg236 <?supplied-pmid 12949132?>12949132 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref029"><text><SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>29 GouldSJ, LewontinRC. The spandrels of San Marco and the Panglossian paradigm: a critique of the adaptationist programme. Proc R Soc Lond, B, Biol Sci. 1979 9;205(1161):581–598. 10.1098/rspb.1979.0086 <?supplied-pmid 42062?>42062 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref030"><text><SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>30 SternDL. The genetic causes of convergent evolution. Nat Rev Genet. 2013 11;14(11):751–764. 10.1038/nrg3483 <?supplied-pmid 24105273?>24105273 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref031"><text><SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>31 ChenL, DeVriesAL, ChengCH. Convergent evolution of antifreeze glycoproteins in Antarctic notothenioid fish and Arctic cod. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 1997 4;94(8):3817–3822. 10.1073/pnas.94.8.3817 <?supplied-pmid 9108061?>9108061 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref032"><text><SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>32 ShapiroMD, SummersBR, BalabhadraS, AldenhovenJT, MillerAL, CunninghamCB, et al The genetic architecture of skeletal convergence and sex determination in ninespine sticklebacks. Curr Biol. 2009 7;19(13):1140–1145. 10.1016/j.cub.2009.05.029 <?supplied-pmid 19500990?>19500990 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref033"><text><SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>33 BrodieED. Convergent evolution: pick your poison carefully. Curr Biol. 2010 2;20(4):R152–154. 10.1016/j.cub.2009.12.029 <?supplied-pmid 20178758?>20178758 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref034"><text><SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain>34 KhadjehS, TuretzekN, PechmannM, SchwagerEE, WimmerEA, DamenWG, et al Divergent role of the Hox gene Antennapedia in spiders is responsible for the convergent evolution of abdominal limb repression. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2012 3;109(13):4921–4926. 10.1073/pnas.1116421109 <?supplied-pmid 22421434?>22421434 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref035"><text><SENT sid="550" pm="."><plain>35 WittkoppPJ, WilliamsBL, SelegueJE, CarrollSB. Drosophila pigmentation evolution: divergent genotypes underlying convergent phenotypes. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2003 2;100(4):1808–1813. 10.1073/pnas.0336368100 <?supplied-pmid 12574518?>12574518 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref036"><text><SENT sid="551" pm="."><plain>36 TanakaK, BarminaO, KoppA. Distinct developmental mechanisms underlie the evolutionary diversification of Drosophila sex combs. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2009 3;106(12):4764–4769. 10.1073/pnas.0807875106 <?supplied-pmid 19255422?>19255422 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref037"><text><SENT sid="552" pm="."><plain>37 ZhenY, AardemaML, MedinaEM, SchumerM, AndolfattoP. Parallel molecular evolution in an herbivore community. Science. 2012 9;337(6102):1634–1637. 10.1126/science.1226630 <?supplied-pmid 23019645?>23019645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref038"><text><SENT sid="553" pm="."><plain>38 RiehleMM, BennettAF, LongAD. Genetic architecture of thermal adaptation in Escherichia coli. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2001 1;98(2):525–530. 10.1073/pnas.98.2.525 <?supplied-pmid 11149947?>11149947 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref039"><text><SENT sid="554" pm="."><plain>39 ChanYF, MarksME, JonesFC, VillarrealG, ShapiroMD, BradySD, et al Adaptive evolution of pelvic reduction in sticklebacks by recurrent deletion of a Pitx1 enhancer. Science. 2010 1;327(5963):302–305. 10.1126/science.1182213 <?supplied-pmid 20007865?>20007865 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref040"><text><SENT sid="555" pm="."><plain>40 MoxonE, LenskiR, RaineyP. Adaptive evolution of highly mutable loci in pathogenic bacteria. Perspectives in Biology and Medicine. 1998;42(1):154–155. 10.1353/pbm.1998.0062 <?supplied-pmid 10766604?>10766604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref041"><text><SENT sid="556" pm="."><plain>41 BurkeMK, DunhamJP, ShahrestaniP, ThorntonKR, RoseMR, LongAD. Genome-wide analysis of a long-term evolution experiment with Drosophila. Nature. 2010 9;467(7315):587–590. 10.1038/nature09352 <?supplied-pmid 20844486?>20844486 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref042"><text><SENT sid="557" pm="."><plain>42 WoodsR, SchneiderD, WinkworthCL, RileyMA, LenskiRE. Tests of parallel molecular evolution in a long-term experiment with Escherichia coli. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. 2006;103(24):9107–9112. 10.1073/pnas.0602917103  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref043"><text><SENT sid="558" pm="."><plain>43 TenaillonO, Rodriguez-VerdugoA, GautRL, McDonaldP, BennettAF, LongAD, et al The molecular diversity of adaptive convergence. Science. 2012 1;335(6067):457–461. 10.1126/science.1212986 <?supplied-pmid 22282810?>22282810 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref044"><text><SENT sid="559" pm="."><plain>44 Orozco-terWengelP, KapunM, NolteV, KoflerR, FlattT, SchloettererC. Adaptation of Drosophila to a novel laboratory environment reveals temporally heterogeneous trajectories of selected alleles. Molecular ecology. 2012;21(20):4931–4941. 10.1111/j.1365-294X.2012.05673.x <?supplied-pmid 22726122?>22726122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref045"><text><SENT sid="560" pm="."><plain>45 ColosimoPF, HosemannKE, BalabhadraS, VillarrealG, DicksonM, GrimwoodJ, et al Widespread parallel evolution in sticklebacks by repeated fixation of Ectodysplasin alleles. Science. 2005 3;307(5717):1928–1933. 10.1126/science.1107239 <?supplied-pmid 15790847?>15790847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref046"><text><SENT sid="561" pm="."><plain>46 MartinA, PapaR, NadeauNJ, HillRI, CountermanBA, HalderG, et al Diversification of complex butterfly wing patterns by repeated regulatory evolution of a Wnt ligand. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2012 7;109(31):12632–12637. 10.1073/pnas.1204800109 <?supplied-pmid 22802635?>22802635 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref047"><text><SENT sid="562" pm="."><plain>47 ReinhardtJA, KolaczkowskiB, JonesCD, BegunDJ, KernAD. Parallel geographic variation in Drosophila melanogaster. Genetics. 2014 5;197(1):361–373. 10.1534/genetics.114.161463 <?supplied-pmid 24610860?>24610860 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref048"><text><SENT sid="563" pm="."><plain>48 NielsenR, BustamanteC, ClarkAG, GlanowskiS, SacktonTB, HubiszMJ, et al A scan for positively selected genes in the genomes of humans and chimpanzees. PLoS Biol. 2005 6;3(6):e170 10.1371/journal.pbio.0030170 <?supplied-pmid 15869325?>15869325 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref049"><text><SENT sid="564" pm="."><plain>49 TajimaF. Evolutionary relationship of DNA sequences in finite populations. Genetics. 1983 10;105(2):437–460. <?supplied-pmid 6628982?>6628982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref050"><text><SENT sid="565" pm="."><plain>50 WattersonGA. On the number of segregating sites in genetical models without recombination. Theor Popul Biol. 1975 4;7(2):256–276. 10.1016/0040-5809(75)90020-9 <?supplied-pmid 1145509?>1145509 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref051"><text><SENT sid="566" pm="."><plain>51 TajimaF. Statistical method for testing the neutral mutation hypothesis by DNA polymorphism. Genetics. 1989 11;123(3):585–595. <?supplied-pmid 2513255?>2513255 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref052"><text><SENT sid="567" pm="."><plain>52 CoopG, RalphP. Patterns of neutral diversity under general models of selective sweeps. Genetics. 2012 9;192(1):205–224. 10.1534/genetics.112.141861 <?supplied-pmid 22714413?>22714413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref053"><text><SENT sid="568" pm="."><plain>53 LemeunierF, AshburnerMA. Relationships within the melanogaster species subgroup of the genus Drosophila (Sophophora). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="569" pm="."><plain>II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="570" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic relationships between six species based upon polytene chromosome banding sequences. Proc R Soc Lond, B, Biol Sci. 1976 5;193(1112):275–294. 10.1098/rspb.1976.0046 <?supplied-pmid 6967?>6967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref054"><text><SENT sid="571" pm="."><plain>54 LlopartA, LachaiseD, CoyneJA. Multilocus analysis of introgression between two sympatric sister species of Drosophila: Drosophila yakuba and D. santomea. Genetics. 2005 9;171(1):197–210. 10.1534/genetics.104.033597 <?supplied-pmid 15965264?>15965264 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref055"><text><SENT sid="572" pm="."><plain>55 MackayTF, RichardsS, StoneEA, BarbadillaA, AyrolesJF, ZhuD, et al The Drosophila melanogaster Genetic Reference Panel. Nature. 2012 2;482(7384):173–178. 10.1038/nature10811 <?supplied-pmid 22318601?>22318601 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref056"><text><SENT sid="573" pm="."><plain>56 CridlandJM, ThorntonKR. Validation of rearrangement break points identified by paired-end sequencing in natural populations of Drosophila melanogaster . Genome Biol Evol. 2010;2:83–101. 10.1093/gbe/evq001 <?supplied-pmid 20333226?>20333226 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref057"><text><SENT sid="574" pm="."><plain>57 ChaoA. Nonparametric estimation of the number of classes in a population. Scandinavian Journal of statistics. 1984;p. 265–270. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref058"><text><SENT sid="575" pm="."><plain>58 HartlDL, ClarkAG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="576" pm="."><plain>In: Principles of population genetics. Sunderland, Mass.: Sinauer Associates; 2007 p. 652 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/catdir/toc/ecip074/2006036153.html">http://www.loc.gov/catdir/toc/ecip074/2006036153.html</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref059"><text><SENT sid="577" pm="."><plain>59 LynchM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="578" pm="."><plain>In: The Origins of Genome Architecture. Sunderland, Mass.: Sinauer Associates; 2007 p. 494 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/catdir/toc/ecip077/2007000012.html">http://www.loc.gov/catdir/toc/ecip077/2007000012.html</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref060"><text><SENT sid="579" pm="."><plain>60 HaldaneJBS. A mathematical theory of natural and artificial selection V: Selection and Mutation. Proceedings of the Cambridge Philosophical Society. 1927;23:838–844. 10.1017/S0305004100011750  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref061"><text><SENT sid="580" pm="."><plain>61 JensenJD, ThorntonKR, AndolfattoP. An approximate bayesian estimator suggests strong, recurrent selective sweeps in Drosophila. PLoS Genet. 2008;4(9):e1000198 10.1371/journal.pgen.1000198 <?supplied-pmid 18802463?>18802463 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref062"><text><SENT sid="581" pm="."><plain>62 AndolfattoP. Hitchhiking effects of recurrent beneficial amino acid substitutions in the Drosophila melanogaster genome. Genome Res. 2007 12;17(12):1755–1762. 10.1101/gr.6691007 <?supplied-pmid 17989248?>17989248 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref063"><text><SENT sid="582" pm="."><plain>63 HuTT, EisenMB, ThorntonKR, AndolfattoP. A second-generation assembly of the Drosophila simulans genome provides new insights into patterns of lineage-specific divergence. Genome Res. 2013 1;23(1):89–98. 10.1101/gr.141689.112 <?supplied-pmid 22936249?>22936249 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref064"><text><SENT sid="583" pm="."><plain>64 ZichnerT, GarfieldDA, RauschT, StutzAM, CannavoE, BraunM, et al Impact of genomic structural variation in Drosophila melanogaster based on population-scale sequencing. Genome Res. 2013 3;23(3):568–579. 10.1101/gr.142646.112 <?supplied-pmid 23222910?>23222910 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref065"><text><SENT sid="584" pm="."><plain>65 ClaycombJM, Orr-WeaverTL. Developmental gene amplification: insights into DNA replication and gene expression. Trends Genet. 2005 3;21(3):149–162. 10.1016/j.tig.2005.01.009 <?supplied-pmid 15734574?>15734574 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref066"><text><SENT sid="585" pm="."><plain>66 CharlesworthB, MorganMT, CharlesworthD. The effect of deleterious mutations on neutral molecular variation. Genetics. 1993 8;134(4):1289–1303. <?supplied-pmid 8375663?>8375663 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref067"><text><SENT sid="586" pm="."><plain>67 SmithJM, HaighJ. The hitch-hiking effect of a favourable gene. Genet Res. 1974 12;89(5–6):391–403. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref068"><text><SENT sid="587" pm="."><plain>68 PresgravesDC. Sex chromosomes and speciation in Drosophila . Trends Genet. 2008 7;24(7):336–343. 10.1016/j.tig.2008.04.007 <?supplied-pmid 18514967?>18514967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref069"><text><SENT sid="588" pm="."><plain>69 ThorntonK, LongM. Rapid divergence of gene duplicates on the Drosophila melanogaster X chromosome. Mol Biol Evol. 2002 6;19(6):918–925. 10.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a004149 <?supplied-pmid 12032248?>12032248 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref070"><text><SENT sid="589" pm="."><plain>70 ThorntonK, LongM. Excess of amino acid substitutions relative to polymorphism between X-linked duplications in Drosophila melanogaster. Mol Biol Evol. 2005 2;22(2):273–284. 10.1093/molbev/msi015 <?supplied-pmid 15483321?>15483321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref071"><text><SENT sid="590" pm="."><plain>71 LynchM, ConeryJS. The evolutionary demography of duplicate genes. Journal of Structural and Functional Genomics. 2003;3(1–4):35–44. 10.1023/A:1022696612931 <?supplied-pmid 12836683?>12836683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref072"><text><SENT sid="591" pm="."><plain>72 Eyre-WalkerA, KeightleyPD, SmithNG, GaffneyD. Quantifying the slightly deleterious mutation model of molecular evolution. Mol Biol Evol. 2002 12;19(12):2142–2149. 10.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a004039 <?supplied-pmid 12446806?>12446806 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref073"><text><SENT sid="592" pm="."><plain>73 ZhangYE, VibranovskiMD, KrinskyBH, LongM. Age-dependent chromosomal distribution of male-biased genes in Drosophila. Genome Res. 2010 11;20(11):1526–1533. 10.1101/gr.107334.110 <?supplied-pmid 20798392?>20798392 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref074"><text><SENT sid="593" pm="."><plain>74 BhutkarA, SchaefferSW, RussoSM, XuM, SmithTF, GelbartWM. Chromosomal rearrangement inferred from comparisons of 12 Drosophila genomes. Genetics. 2008 7;179(3):1657–1680. 10.1534/genetics.107.086108 <?supplied-pmid 18622036?>18622036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref075"><text><SENT sid="594" pm="."><plain>75 Drosophila Twelve Genomes Consortium. Evolution of genes and genomes on the Drosophila phylogeny. Nature. 2007 11 8;450(7167):203–218. 10.1038/nature06341 <?supplied-pmid 17994087?>17994087 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref076"><text><SENT sid="595" pm="."><plain>76 LazarroBP, ClarkAG. Rapid evolution of innate immune response genes In: R S SinghJX, KulathinalRJ, editors. Rapidly Evolving Genes and Genetic Systems. Oxford: Oxford University Press; 2012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref077"><text><SENT sid="596" pm="."><plain>77 BeckermanAP, de RoijJ, DennisSR, LittleTJ. A shared mechanism of defense against predators and parasites: chitin regulation and its implications for life-history theory. Ecol Evol. 2013 12;3(15):5119–5126. 10.1002/ece3.766 <?supplied-pmid 24455141?>24455141 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref078"><text><SENT sid="597" pm="."><plain>78 Ffrench-ConstantRH, DabornPJ, Le GoffG. The genetics and genomics of insecticide resistance. Trends Genet. 2004 3;20(3):163–170. 10.1016/j.tig.2004.01.003 <?supplied-pmid 15036810?>15036810 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref079"><text><SENT sid="598" pm="."><plain>79 PanhuisTM, ClarkNL, SwansonWJ. Rapid evolution of reproductive proteins in abalone and Drosophila. Philos Trans R Soc Lond, B, Biol Sci. 2006 2;361(1466):261–268. 10.1098/rstb.2005.1793 <?supplied-pmid 16612885?>16612885 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref080"><text><SENT sid="599" pm="."><plain>80 BegunDJ, HollowayAK, StevensK, HillierLW, PohYP, HahnMW, et al Population genomics: whole-genome analysis of polymorphism and divergence in Drosophila simulans. PLoS Biol. 2007 11;5(11):e310 10.1371/journal.pbio.0050310 <?supplied-pmid 17988176?>17988176 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref081"><text><SENT sid="600" pm="."><plain>81 SchmidtJM, GoodRT, AppletonB, SherrardJ, RaymantGC, BogwitzMR, et al Copy number variation and transposable elements feature in recent, ongoing adaptation at the Cyp6g1 locus. PLoS Genet. 2010 6;6(6):e1000998 10.1371/journal.pgen.1000998 <?supplied-pmid 20585622?>20585622 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref082"><text><SENT sid="601" pm="."><plain>82 Van ValenL. A new evolutionary law. Evolutionary theory. 1973;1:1–30. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref083"><text><SENT sid="602" pm="."><plain>83 BassC, FieldLM. Gene amplification and insecticide resistance. Pest Manag Sci. 2011 8;67(8):886–890. 10.1002/ps.2189 <?supplied-pmid 21538802?>21538802 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref084"><text><SENT sid="603" pm="."><plain>84 HaddrillPR, BachtrogD, AndolfattoP. Positive and negative selection on noncoding DNA in Drosophila simulans. Mol Biol Evol. 2008 9;25(9):1825–1834. 10.1093/molbev/msn125 <?supplied-pmid 18515263?>18515263 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref085"><text><SENT sid="604" pm="."><plain>85 AndolfattoP, WongKM, BachtrogD. Effective population size and the efficacy of selection on the X chromosomes of two closely related Drosophila species. Genome Biol Evol. 2011;3:114–128. 10.1093/gbe/evq086 <?supplied-pmid 21173424?>21173424 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref086"><text><SENT sid="605" pm="."><plain>86 KaplanNL, HudsonRR, LangleyCH. The “hitchhiking effect” revisited. Genetics. 1989 12;123(4):887–899. <?supplied-pmid 2612899?>2612899 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref087"><text><SENT sid="606" pm="."><plain>87 WakeleyJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="607" pm="."><plain>In: Coalescent Theory: An Introduction. Roberts &amp; Company Publishers; 2009 p. 97. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref088"><text><SENT sid="608" pm="."><plain>88 EwensWJ. A note on the sampling theory for infinite alleles and infinite sites models. Theor Popul Biol. 1974 10;6(2):143–148. 10.1016/0040-5809(74)90020-3 <?supplied-pmid 4445971?>4445971 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref089"><text><SENT sid="609" pm="."><plain>89 HalliganDL, KeightleyPD. Ubiquitous selective constraints in the Drosophila genome revealed by a genome-wide interspecies comparison. Genome Res. 2006 7;16(7):875–884. 10.1101/gr.5022906 <?supplied-pmid 16751341?>16751341 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref090"><text><SENT sid="610" pm="."><plain>90 ParschJ, NovozhilovS, Saminadin-PeterSS, WongKM, AndolfattoP. On the utility of short intron sequences as a reference for the detection of positive and negative selection in Drosophila. Mol Biol Evol. 2010 6;27(6):1226–1234. 10.1093/molbev/msq046 <?supplied-pmid 20150340?>20150340 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref091"><text><SENT sid="611" pm="."><plain>91 ClementeF, VoglC. Unconstrained evolution in short introns?—an analysis of genome-wide polymorphism and divergence data from Drosophila. J Evol Biol. 2012 10;25(10):1975–1990. 10.1111/j.1420-9101.2012.02580.x <?supplied-pmid 22901008?>22901008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref092"><text><SENT sid="612" pm="."><plain>92 McKennaA, HannaM, BanksE, SivachenkoA, CibulskisK, KernytskyA, et al The Genome Analysis Toolkit: a MapReduce framework for analyzing next-generation DNA sequencing data. Genome Res. 2010 9;20(9):1297–1303. 10.1101/gr.107524.110 <?supplied-pmid 20644199?>20644199 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref093"><text><SENT sid="613" pm="."><plain>93 LiH, HandsakerB, WysokerA, FennellT, RuanJ, HomerN, et al The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools. Bioinformatics. 2009 8;25(16):2078–2079. 10.1093/bioinformatics/btp352 <?supplied-pmid 19505943?>19505943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref094"><text><SENT sid="614" pm="."><plain>94 ThorntonK. libsequence: a C++ class library for evolutionary genetic analysis. Bioinformatics. 2003;19:2325–2327. 10.1093/bioinformatics/btg316 <?supplied-pmid 14630667?>14630667 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref095"><text><SENT sid="615" pm="."><plain>95 Haag-LiautardC, DorrisM, MasideX, MacaskillS, HalliganDL, HouleD, et al Direct estimation of per nucleotide and genomic deleterious mutation rates in Drosophila . Nature. 2007 1 4;445(7123):82–85. 10.1038/nature05388 <?supplied-pmid 17203060?>17203060 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0132184.ref096"><text><SENT sid="616" pm="."><plain>96 RosenbergNA. The shapes of neutral gene genealogies in two species: probabilities of monophyly, paraphyly, and polyphyly in a coalescent model. Evolution. 2003 7;57(7):1465–1477. 10.1554/03-012 <?supplied-pmid 12940352?>12940352 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
