<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4226036</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25034814</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">7065</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-604</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The mitochondrial and chloroplast genomes of the haptophyte Chrysochromulina tobin contain unique repeat structures and gene profiles </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hovde</surname><given-names>Blake T</given-names></name><address><email>hovdebt@uw.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff231"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Starkenburg</surname><given-names>Shawn R</given-names></name><address><email>shawns@lanl.gov</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff232"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hunsperger</surname><given-names>Heather M</given-names></name><address><email>hheather@uw.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff233"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>Laina D</given-names></name><address><email>mercel@uw.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff234"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Deodato</surname><given-names>Chloe R</given-names></name><address><email>chloed@uw.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff233"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>Ramesh K</given-names></name><address><email>rjha@lanl.gov</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff232"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chertkov</surname><given-names>Olga</given-names></name><address><email>ochrtkv@lanl.gov</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff232"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Monnat</surname><given-names>Raymond J</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><address><email>monnat@uw.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff231"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff235"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Cattolico</surname><given-names>Rose Ann</given-names></name><address><email>racat@uw.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff233"/></contrib><aff id="Aff231"><label/>Department of Genome Sciences, University of Washington, Seattle, WA USA </aff><aff id="Aff232"><label/>Los Alamos National Laboratory, Bioscience Division, Los Alamos, NM USA </aff><aff id="Aff233"><label/>Department of Biology, University of Washington, Seattle, WA USA </aff><aff id="Aff234"><label/>Department of Statistics, University of Washington, Seattle, WA USA </aff><aff id="Aff235"><label/>Department of Pathology, University of Washington, Seattle, WA USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>604</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Hovde et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. 2014</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This article is published under license to BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Haptophytes are widely and abundantly distributed in both marine and freshwater ecosystems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Few genomic analyses of representatives within this taxon have been reported, despite their early evolutionary origins and their prominent role in global carbon fixation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The complete mitochondrial and chloroplast genome sequences of the haptophyte Chrysochromulina tobin (Prymnesiales) provide insight into the architecture and gene content of haptophyte organellar genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The mitochondrial genome (~34 kb) encodes 21 protein coding genes and contains a complex, 9 kb tandem repeat region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Similar to other haptophytes and rhodophytes, but not cryptophytes or stramenopiles, the mitochondrial genome has lost the nad7, nad9 and nad11 genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The ~105 kb chloroplast genome encodes 112 protein coding genes, including ycf39 which has strong structural homology to NADP-binding nitrate transcriptional regulators; a divergent ‘CheY-like’ two-component response regulator (ycf55) and Tic/Toc (ycf60 and ycf80) membrane transporters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Notably, a zinc finger domain has been identified in the rpl36 ribosomal protein gene of all chloroplasts sequenced to date with the exception of haptophytes and cryptophytes - algae that have gained (via lateral gene transfer) an alternative rpl36 lacking the zinc finger motif. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The two C. tobin chloroplast ribosomal RNA operon spacer regions differ in tRNA content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Additionally, each ribosomal operon contains multiple single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) - a pattern observed in rhodophytes and cryptophytes, but few stramenopiles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Analysis of small (&lt;200 bp) chloroplast encoded tandem and inverted repeats in C. tobin and 78 other algal chloroplast genomes show that repeat type, size and location are correlated with gene identity and taxonomic clade. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The Chrysochromulina tobin organellar genomes provide new insight into organellar function and evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>These are the first organellar genomes to be determined for the prymnesiales, a taxon that is present in both oceanic and freshwater systems and represents major primary photosynthetic producers and contributors to global ecosystem stability. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/1471-2164-15-604) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Haptophytes</kwd><kwd>Chloroplast genome</kwd><kwd>Mitochondrial genome</kwd><kwd>Repeat structure</kwd><kwd>Repeat function</kwd><kwd><italic>Chrysochromulina</italic></kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2014</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Globally, primary producers fix ~100 gigatons of carbon each year [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>This production is equally distributed between terrestrial and aquatic ecosystems [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Haptophytes are globally abundant and important photosynthetic microalgae found in both marine and freshwater environments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Recent estimates indicate that haptophytes alone may represent “…30-50% of total photosynthetic standing stock in the world’s oceans” [2], where they play a key role in carbon fixation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Some haptophyte species are photosynthetic as well as mixotrophic, thus can live in dysphotic zones where light levels are too low to support photosynthesis [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>This metabolic versatility may contribute to fitness, and help explain haptophyte prevalence within global algal populations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Haptophyte evolutionary history remains enigmatic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Based on fossil records and 18S rDNA phylogenetic analyses [4, 5], it is estimated that these algae are an ancient lineage, arising over 1.2 billion years ago. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Phylogenomic analyses of the plastids of haptophytes, stramenopiles, dinoflagellates (alveolates) and cryptophytes show that the plastids of these four groups, collectively termed “CASH” [6], form a monophyletic grouping descendent from red algal plastids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>However, the relationships among CASH plastids remains controversial, as differing topologies are recovered in phylogenetic analyses of chloroplast genes using various methods and loci [7–14] (see Green [15] for review). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Aside from the plastid lineage controversy, the haptophyte host lineage may be affiliated with the stramenopile-alveolate-rhizaria (SAR) group [11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Despite their important ecological roles and interesting evolutionary history, there has been little genomic characterization of diverse haptophyte species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Two classes define Haptophytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The monophyletic Pavlovophyceae display minimal diversity, being described by 4 orders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the polyphyletic and globally abundant Prymnesiophyceae encompass 6 orders, of which the B2 clade seems most dominant in marine and fresh water ecosystems [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Of this vast assemblage of haptophytes, the organellar genomes of only one representative of the Pavlovophyceae, (Pavlova lutheri: Pavlovales), and three of the Prymnesiophyceae (Emiliania huxleyi: Isochrysidales; Phaeocystis antarctica and Phaeocystis globosa: Phaeocystales) have been sequenced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The large and complex Prymnesiales that encompass the B1 to B5 clades [17, 18], lack a sequenced representative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>This omission is surprising given reports demonstrating that &gt;55% of all haptophyte sequences in a Mediterranean location belong to this taxonomic assemblage [16, 19], and that members of this clade can dominate fresh water ecosystems [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>We reasoned that determining the genomic sequence of a B2 representative in the Prymnesiales would provide new information on haptophyte evolutionary origins and ecosystem roles. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The B2 clade prymnesiophyte chosen for sequencing, Chrysochromulina tobin, is a newly defined algal species (Deodato, Barlow, Hovde et al. in prep). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>This small (4 μm) unicellular alga is naturally wall-less, being delineated solely by a plasma membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>It lacks scales or additional extracellular structures. Chrysochromulina tobin lives in fresh to brackish water and is mixotrophic [21], using a long haptonema to hunt bacterial prey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Bacteria-containing cultures exhibit improved growth and produce more fatty acid than those maintained axenically (Deodato, Barlow, Hovde et al. in prep). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, C. tobin can be grown on completely defined artificial medium, and cell division is synchronized by light/dark photoperiods. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Here we report the sequencing and annotation of the complete Chrysochromulina tobin mitochondrial and chloroplast genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>These genomes were analyzed using available data from rhodophytes (red algae), chlorophytes (green algae) as well as haptophytes and other members of the CASH complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Data reported here show the mitochondrial genome to contain a large and complex repeat comprising 28% of the mitochondrial sequence, and to have lost several nad genes (nad7, 9 and 11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The C. tobin chloroplast genome contains a novel intergenic ribosomal spacer region, and multiple SNPs between rDNA copies within the inverted ribosomal repeat regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Analyses of chloroplast tandem and inverted repeats demonstrate gene-specific associations, regardless of algal species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Features of several genes provide new insight into aspects of chloroplast genome evolution including lateral gene transfer, gene retention, novel functional rolls and putative regulatory structures localized within intergenic regions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Results and discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial and chloroplast genome sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Purified total genomic DNA was used to prepare libraries for both the 454 pyrosequencing and Illumina platforms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>A total of 4.7 million reads and 79 million reads were generated on the 454 and Illumina platforms respectively, and then assembled using Newbler [22] and Velvet [23] (see Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The resulting draft assembly included 3,472 contigs with an average length of ~17 kb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>A single contig of 25,263 bp represented 74% of the mitochondrial genome, but no other assembled contigs contained remaining known mitochondrial sequence, likely due to the presence of a large repeat structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>This repeat structure required PCR amplification and sequencing to resolve the final circular draft. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The chloroplast genome was contained in two assembled contigs that totaled 101,192 bp in length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Due to the ribosomal inverted repeat, PCR followed by Sanger sequencing of the amplified products was used to join the two sequences and form a complete, circular mapping chloroplast assembly. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial gene content </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The Chrysochromulina tobin mitochondrial genome [GenBank:KJ201908] is 34,288 bp in size, has a GC content of 31.4%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The genome encodes 48 genes, including 25 tRNAs, 21 protein coding genes and a split ribosomal operon comprising the 16S and 23S rRNA genes (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The mitochondrial 21 protein coding gene complement includes a single novel open reading frame (orf457) that encodes a 457 amino acid protein that lacks strong homology to any other protein within the NCBI database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>As in other sequenced haptophytes, NCBI translation table 4 [24] was used, where UGA codes tryptophan rather than a termination codon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the genomic content among all published haptophyte genomes (E. huxleyi[25, 26]: [GenBank:AY342361, JN022704]; P. antarctica[27]: [GenBank:JN131834, JN131835]; P. globosa[27]: [GenBank:KC967226]; P. lutheri: [GenBank:HQ908424]) indicate that 14 energy and metabolism genes are conserved in all examined taxa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>All haptophyte genomes also contain an identical complement of five ribosomal proteins (rps3, rps8, rps12, rps14, and rpl16) except for P. antarctica and P. globosa which are missing the rps8 or the rps8 and rps14 genes respectively (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Most notably, nad7, nad9 and nad11 are consistently missing from all haptophyte and rhodophyte mitochondrial genomes sequenced to date. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, these three genes are present in all cryptophyte and stramenopile mitochondrial genomes.Figure 1 Chrysochromulina tobin mitochondrial genome map. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>(A) All genes are transcribed in the same direction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>A split ribosomal operon is present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The large repeat region of 9495 bp represents a significant portion (~28%) of the genome. (B) Detailed representation of the complex repeat region found in the mitochondrial genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Three large tandem repeat regions are flanked by two sections containing small tandem repeats designated A, B and C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>These repeat subunits also make up the regions separating the large tandem repeats from each other. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Blocks A, B and C have strong, but rarely perfect, sequence identity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Comparison of haptophyte mitochondrial genomes </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Chrysochromulina tobin UWC 291 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Phaeocystis antarctica (Partial) CCMP 1374 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Phaeocystis globosa (Partial) Pg-G(A) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Emiliania huxleyi CCMP 1516 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Emiliania huxleyi CCMP 373 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Pavlova lutheri CCMP 1325 (Partial) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Genome Size (bp) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>34288 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>27547 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>24477 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>28660 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>29013 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>34086 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain> GC % </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>31.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>29.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>30.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>28.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>28.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>37.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Protein-coding genes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>21 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>19 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>22 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain> Respiratory coding proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>14 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>14 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain> Ribosomal proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain> Unique gene content </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>ORF457 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>dam </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>dam </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>ORF636(dam), ORF105 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain> Missing genes found in other haptophytes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>rps8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>rps8, rps14 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>atp8 (partial only) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>atp8 (partial only) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>RNA-coding genes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain> tRNAs </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>26 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>24 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain> rRNA content </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>1 (split operon) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>1 (split operon) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>1 (split operon) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>1 (intact operon) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>1 (intact operon) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>1 (split operon) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Repeat elements </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain> Tandem repeats </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>27 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>27 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain> Inverted repeats </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain> Large repeat regions </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Note: No introns were found within any of the listed genomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>With respect to mitochondrial gene synteny among haptophyte taxa, many structural rearrangements have occurred. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The results of Mauve [28] gene cluster analysis showed very poor gene cluster conservation (Additional file 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The extensive nature of shuffled gene order is further evidenced by the fact that the ribosomal operon is split in all haptophyte genomes (C. tobin, P. antarctica, P. globosa, and P. lutheri) except E. huxleyi. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial repeats </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The Chrysochromulina tobin mitochondrial genome contains a large repeat region measuring 9.3 kb in length (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>This region features three large tandem repeats, each ~1.5 kb in length that are flanked by two regions consisting of additional small tandem repeats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>These small tandem repeat regions are composed of three subunits, arbitrarily classified A, B and C, based on sequence homology (though all sequences within each subunit class are not 100% identical). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Repeat unit A is comprised of 290 bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Unit B consists of 156 bp, of which ~84 bp exhibit significant sequence identity to unit A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Unit C is 85 bp in length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Although the flanking repeat regions are not identical in size (regions 1 and 2 are 1896 bp and 1558 bp respectively), a consistent pattern of B-A-A-A-B is found within these two flanking domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The three large tandem repeats are separated from each other within the repeat region by spacers (consisting of a C-A-A pattern). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, this direct repeat arrangement is strikingly similar to the larger (35 kb) repeat structure found in the diatom Phaeodactylum tricornutum[29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The cryptophytes, Hemiselmis andersenii and Rhodomonas salina, and the chlorophytes Pedinomonas minor and Acutodesmus obliquus also contain large tandem repeat regions (&gt;4 kb) that differ from the minimal repeat embellishment seen in most mitochondrial genomes of other algae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Not surprisingly, the complexity of this repeat structure caused assembly challenges. The fact that P. antarctica, P. globosa, and P. lutheri mitochondrial genomes remain incomplete is likely due to the presence of one or more large repeat structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>For example, Smith et. al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>[27] reported unresolved repeats within two repeat regions in P. antarctica and P. globosa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, the use of short read, high throughput sequencing techniques do not easily facilitate solving these complex repeat structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The first E. huxleyi mitochondrial genome published in 2004 [25], the stramenopile, Heterosigma akashiwo[30], as well as the diatoms Phaeodactylum tricornutum and Thalassiosira pseudonana[29] utilized fosmid sequencing, that supported assembly and primer walking for the resolution of longer repeats. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Chloroplast gene content </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The Chrysochromulina tobin chloroplast genome [GenBank:KJ201907] is 104,518 bp in size and has a GC content of 36.3%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The genome encodes 145 genes (Figure 2) including 27 tRNA coding genes, 112 protein coding genes and an inverted repeat, with each repeat copy containing the 23S, 16S and 5S rRNA genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The tRNAs present in this genome represent all potential amino acid anticodons, including a start methionine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Within the chloroplast genome, codon usage is standard for plastid genomes, and protein alignments suggest that codon GTG (valine) may serve as the translation initiation codon for ycf55, rps3, psbE, ycf65 and psbC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Such alternative translational start codons have been reported to occur in algal chloroplast genomes of wide taxonomic divergence (e.g., Cyanidium caldarium, Odontella sinensis, Heterosigma akashiwo, and Emiliania huxleyi) [31–33] although not for the same genes established in C. tobin.Figure 2 Chrysochromulina tobin chloroplast genome map. Genes facing outside are transcribed in the counter-clockwise direction and genes facing inside are transcribed in a clockwise direction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Two copies of the ribosomal operon are inverted and the repeat region contains no other genes beyond the ribosomal subunits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The small single copy (SSC) and large single copy (LSC) regions are labeled. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Inverted and tandem repeats are also designated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The C. tobin chloroplast gene complement is similar to other sequenced haptophyte chloroplast genomes: (Table 2; E. huxleyi[26, 31]: [Genbank:AY741371, JN022705]; P. antarctica: [GenBank:NC_016703]; P. globosa[27]: [GenBank:NC_021637] and P. lutheri: [GenBank: NC_020371] [6]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Additionally, an “uncultured prymnesiophyte C19847” (derived from metagenomic data of oceanic samples collected from the North Atlantic [GenBank:HM565909] [34]) was included in this analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>All haptophyte genomes are relatively small in size when compared to other microalgal species (Additional file 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Gene content comparison shows E. huxleyi (113 protein-coding genes) contains dfr (a two component signaling protein) that is absent in C. tobin. Unlike C. tobin, P. antarctica and P. globosa chloroplast genomes (both having 108 genes) are missing ORF132 (unknown function), ycf20 (unknown function), thiG, and thiS (thiamine biosynthesis protein G and S respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>A conserved coding region (ORF154), found uniquely in C. tobin (154 amino acids) and E. huxleyi (132 amino acids), is located adjacent to psbV in both genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The amino acid identity of these two hypothetical genes is low, suggesting remnants of functional proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The chloroplast genome of the phylogenetically distant haptophyte, P. lutheri, is missing 7 genes, and contains an additional 9 genes that are not found in available haptophyte chloroplast genomes (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>While gene content is similar among all of the haptophytes analyzed, the freshwater C. tobin actually has the highest sequence identity to the marine uncultured prymnesiophyte C19847. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>This result is not too surprising given recent studies that document the occurrence of multiple, independent freshwater colonizations by haptophytes [20, 35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Our 18 s rDNA based phylogenetic analyses (Deodato, Barlow et al., in prep) show C. tobin to cluster with species isolated from fresh water lakes in France [20].Table 2 Comparison of haptophyte chloroplast genomes  Chrysochromulina tobin UWC 291 Phaeocystis antarctica CCMP 1374 Phaeocystis globosa Pg-G(A) Emiliania huxleyi CCMP373 Emiliania huxleyi CCMP1516 Pavlova lutheri CCMP 1325Uncultured Prymnesiophyte C19847 (Partial genome)Genome Size (bp)1045181056511074611053091052979528145567 GC %36.335.535.436.836.835.637.2 Protein-coding Genes 11210810811911311145 Unique gene contentORF154, ycf20, thiG, thiS ORF132, ycf20, dfr, thiG, thiS ORF140, ycf66,ORF208, ORF66, rpoZ, ORF84, RF489,ORF70, ORF69N/A Missing genes found in other haptophytes ycf55, ycf47, ycf80, ycf65, rpl34,ycf46, ycf35 N/A RNA-coding genes  tRNAs27272728302718 Ribosomal operons (23S, 16S, 5S)2 (inverted repeat)2 (inverted repeat)2 (inverted repeat)2 (inverted repeat)2 (inverted repeat)11 Repeat elements  Inverted repeats167101516611 Tandem repeats1621121Note: No introns were found within any of the listed genomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Co-linearity in gene placement among haptophyte chloroplast genomes was assessed (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Unlike in diatoms [36], gene clusters have been exchanged between the large and small single copy regions within these haptophyte chloroplast genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>When comparing E. huxleyi to C. tobin, and E. huxleyi to P. antarctica, 17 and 13 gene clusters were conserved, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>A highly conserved region of 20,610 bp encompassing ccs1 through atpA (18 genes) was identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>This region contains a single inversion in the C. tobin rps2 and rps4 coding region, and is more highly conserved between E. huxleyi and P. antarctica – expanding to a ~30,000 bp region that initiates with petL (cytochrome b6/f complex component) and ends with psbE (photosystem II protein). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Another large gene cluster conserved in all three species consists of ~15,000 bp that contains the commonly preserved 24 ribosomal protein gene operon and the dnaK heat shock protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>GRIMM [37] analysis was used to quantify the degree of gene rearrangement among the three completed haptophyte chloroplast genomes above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The most parsimonious result found 11 genome rearrangements occurring between E. huxleyi and P. antarctica, 10 rearrangements between P. antarctica and C. tobin, and 19 rearrangements between E. huxleyi and C. tobin. The scrambled placement of genes among these haptophytes yields no clear insight into relatedness.Figure 3 Gene map comparison of C. tobin, P. antarctica and E. huxleyi chloroplast genomes aligned using Mauve. Inside each block a sequence identity similarity profile is shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Individual genes and strandedness are shown below each genome block. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Red regions in the individual gene plots indicate the locations of the large ribosomal operon repeat regions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Chloroplast repeats </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Large inverted repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The Chrysochromulina tobin ribosomal repeat region is structurally unique when compared to those found in both land plants and all algal chloroplasts sequenced to date. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Eighty two percent (209/256) of all chloroplast genomes (including non-algal species) examined at the genus level contain a large inverted repeat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The conventional structure of this conserved operon includes the 16S ribosomal gene, an intergenic spacer region (ISR) that encodes the tRNA-isoleucine (anticodon GAU), and the tRNA-alanine (anticodon UGC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The ISR is followed by the 23S ribosomal subunit gene and the 5S ribosomal gene (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>In land plants and chlorophytic algae, and less often in rhodophytes and CASH members [33, 38], the repeat region expands to include additional genes that flank the ribosomal gene operon, making the inverted repeat in chlorophytes larger on average (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>The ribosomal inverted repeat structures in C. tobin have non-identical tRNA coding sequences within each ribosomal intergenic spacer region (detail shown in Additional file 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>This domain normally contains two identical tRNA coding regions in each inverted repeat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>However, C. tobin has only tRNA alanine in inverted repeat A, and tRNA isoleucine in inverted repeat B (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>This pattern is also likely present in the uncultured prymnesiophyte C19847. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Only a single operon was assembled for this organism, but that operon solely contained tRNA-Ile within the ISR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the C19847 ribosomal operon that is adjacent to the petB gene contains a tRNA-Ile, while the ribosomal operon adjacent to petB in C. tobin contains tRNA-Ala. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Intramolecular recombination within chloroplast genomes having an inverted repeat is well documented for several algae as well as in land plants [39–41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>This process generates genomic isomers that differ solely in the orientation of their single copy domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, using long PCR to bridge both C. tobin repeat regions, no evidence of such flip-flop recombination was found.Figure 4 Ribosomal operon repeats of C. tobin and other haptophyte chloroplast genomes. The “standard” chloroplast ribosomal operon contains tRNA-Ile and tRNA-Ala in the ribosomal intergenic spacer regions (ISR). Chrysochromulina tobin contains tRNA-Ala in operon A and tRNA-Ile in operon B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Multiple SNPs (black triangles) are present between the C. tobin large and small ribosomal subunits coding regions to each other. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>One copy of the ribosomal operon contains both tRNAs while the other operon lacks both tRNAs in P. antarctica and P. globosa plastid genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>A metagenomic sample, uncultured prymnesiophyte C19847 [28], contains a single tRNA-Ala; the second ribosomal copy was not assembled and is therefore unknown in structure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Inventory of algal inverted repeat sequences in chloroplast genomes </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Organism </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>SNPs or indels found in 23S ribosomal subunit </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>SNPs or indels found in 16S ribosomal subunit </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Inverted repeat length † </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Accession number </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Haptophytes </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Chrysochromulina tobin </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>4656 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>This work </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Emiliania huxleyi CCMP373 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>4674 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>NC_007288 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Emiliania huxleyi CCMP1516 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>4868 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>JN022705 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Phaeocystis antarctica </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>4674 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>JN117275 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Phaeocystis globosa </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>4611 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>NC_021637 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Pavlova lutheri </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>NC_020371 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Stramenopiles </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Apedinella radians </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>4732 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Unpublished* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Aureococcus anophagefferens </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>NC_012898 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Aureoumbra lagunensis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>NC_012903 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Botrydium cystosum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>4924 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Unpublished* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Ectocarpus siliculosus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>8616 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>NC_013498 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Fistulifera sp. JPCC DA0580 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>12031 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>NC_015403 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Fucus vesiculosus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>5242 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>NC_016735 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Heterosigma akashiwo </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>21665 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>NC_010772 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Nannochloropsis gaditana </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>5109 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>NC_020014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Nannochloropsis oculata </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>7541 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Unpublished* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Nannochloropsis salina </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>5131 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Unpublished* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Nereocystis luetkeana </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>5416 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Unpublished* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Odontella sinensis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>7725 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>NC_001713 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Pelagomonas calceolata </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Unpublished* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Phaeodactylum tricornutum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>6916 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>NC_008588 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Pinguiococcus pyrenoidosus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>5070 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Unpublished* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Saccharina japonica </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>5312 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>NC_018523 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Synedra acus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>6795 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>NC_016731 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Synura petersenii </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>22465 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Unpublished* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Thalassiosira oceanica CCMP1005 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>23698 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>NC_014808 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Thalassiosira pseudonana </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>18345 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>NC_008589 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Tribonema aequale </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>5749 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Unpublished* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Vaucheria litorea </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>4935 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>NC_011600 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Cryptophytes </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Cryptomonas paramecium </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>NC_013703 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Guillardia theta </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>4922 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>NC_000926 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Rhodomonas salina </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>4959 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>NC_009573 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Chlorophytes </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Acutodesmus obliquus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>12023 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>NC_008101 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Bryopsis hypnoides </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>NC_013359 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Chlamydomonas renhardii </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>22211 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>NC_005353 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>Chlorella variabilis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>NC_015359 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Chlorella vulgaris </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>NC_001865 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Coccomyxa subellipsoidea C-169 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>NC_015084 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Dunaliella salina </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>14409 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>NC_016732 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Floydiella terrestris </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>NC_014346 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Gonium pectorale </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>14750 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>NC_020438 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>Leptosira terrestris </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>NC_009681 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>Micromonas sp. RCC299 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>7307 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>NC_012575 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Monomastix sp. OKE-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>NC_012101 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>Nephroselmis olivacea </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>46137 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>NC_000927 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Oedogonium cardiacum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>35492 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>NC_011031 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>Oltmannsiellopsis viridis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>18510 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>NC_008099 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>Ostreococcus tauri </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>6825 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>NC_008289 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>Parachlorella kessleri </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>10913 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>NC_012978 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>Pedinomonas minor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>10639 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>NC_016733 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>Picochlorum sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>Unpublished* </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>Pleodorina starrii </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>16608 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>NC_021109 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>Pseudendoclonium akinetum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>6110 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>NC_008114 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>Pycnococcus provasolii </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>NC_012097 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>Pyramimonas parkeae </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>12865 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>NC_012099 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>Schizomeris leibleinii </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>NC_015645 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>Stigeoclonium helveticum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>NC_008372 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>Trebouxiophyceae sp. MX-AZ01 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>NC_018569 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>Rhodophytes </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>Calliarthron tuberculosum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>NC_021075 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>Chondrus crispus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>NC_020795 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>Cyanidioschyzon merolae strain 10D </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>NC_004799 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>Cyanidium caldarium </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>NC_001840 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>Gracilaria tenuistipitata var. liui </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>NC_006137 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>Grateloupia taiwanensis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>NC_021618 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>Porphyra purpurea </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>4827 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>NC_000925 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>Pyropia haitanensis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>4828 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>NC_021189 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>Pyropia yezoensis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>4827 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>NC_007932 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><text><SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>Euglenoids </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>Euglena gracilis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>6127 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>NC_001603 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>Euglena viridis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>NC_020460 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>Eutreptiella gymnastica </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>NC_017754 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>Monomorphina aenigmatica </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>NC_020018 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><text><SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain>Streptophytes </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="550" pm="."><plain>Chaetosphaeridium globosum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="551" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="552" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="553" pm="."><plain>12431 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="554" pm="."><plain>NC_004115 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="555" pm="."><plain>Chara vulgaris </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="556" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="557" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="558" pm="."><plain>10919 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="559" pm="."><plain>NC_008097 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="560" pm="."><plain>Chlorokybus atmophyticus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="561" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="562" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="563" pm="."><plain>7640 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="564" pm="."><plain>NC_008822 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="565" pm="."><plain>Mesostigma viride </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="566" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="567" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="568" pm="."><plain>6056 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="569" pm="."><plain>NC_002186 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="570" pm="."><plain>Staurastrum punctulatum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="571" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="572" pm="."><plain>NC_008116 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td><text><SENT sid="573" pm="."><plain>Zygnema circumcarinatum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><text><SENT sid="574" pm="."><plain>No Inverted Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center"><text><SENT sid="575" pm="."><plain>NC_008117 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="576" pm="."><plain>†Large repeats containing the ribosomal operon in chloroplast genomes were queried for size and sequence homology between the 16S and 23S ribosomal subunits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="577" pm="."><plain>The three organisms Cyanidioschyzon merolae (Rhodophyta), Bryopsis hypnoides (Chlorophyta) and Monomorphina aenigmatica (Chlorophyta) were omitted from the small repeat statistical analyses because of the presence of a greatly expanded tandem repeat structure or large (&gt;200 bp) repeat structures, which causes an over representation the repeat structure due to the counting nature of the analyses presented. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="578" pm="."><plain>*Cattolico RA, Jacobs M, Rocap G. unpublished genomic data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="579" pm="."><plain>Non-canonical ribosomal operon structure is rarely found (Additional file 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="580" pm="."><plain>Within haptophytes, E. huxleyi has a canonical ribosomal operon structure, but P. antarctica and P. globosa do not. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="581" pm="."><plain>In both P. antarctica and P. globosa, one copy of the ribosomal operon contains both tRNAs in the intergenic spacer region (conventional arrangement), while the second copy lacks both tRNAs in the intergenic spacer domain (non-conventional). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="582" pm="."><plain>As also seen in Figure 4, copies of the ribosomal gene sequences encoded within the C. tobin repeat, contain single nucleotide polymorphisms in the 16S (6 SNPs) and 23S (5 SNPs) ribosomal genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="583" pm="."><plain>Notably, every cryptophyte and rhodophyte chloroplast genome examined that encodes a repeat structure also shows the presence of SNPs between replicated ribosomal genes (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="584" pm="."><plain>In contrast, only one alga in the chlorophyte lineage, Ostreococcus tauri, contains a SNP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="585" pm="."><plain>Additionally, no land plant species queried show SNPs in either 16S or 23S genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="586" pm="."><plain>Though speculative, the presence of alternative operon structure for the ribosomal genes, combined with the elevated appearance of SNPs suggest that the well-recognized “copy correction” mechanism [42] may be more effective in some “green” algal lineages (chlorophytic algae and algae with chlorophytic algal symbionts), than in the “red” lineage of autotrophs (rhodophytes and CASH taxa). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="587" pm="."><plain>The route to repeat loss within an algal chloroplast genome may be augmented by the accumulation of SNPs and disintegration of operon integrity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="588" pm="."><plain>Small repeat function in chloroplast genomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="589" pm="."><plain>Chloroplast genomes are consistently embellished with small repeats that are either tandem or inverted in orientation. Chrysochromulina tobin is no exception having 16 inverted repeats with an average length of 25.4 +/− 5.2 bp in stem length with loop domains averaging 6.1 +/− 3.0 bp in size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="590" pm="."><plain>A single tandem repeat comprised of a duplicated 15 bp sequence also occurs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="591" pm="."><plain>Similar to observations made for other chloroplast genomes [43–46] and bacterial genomes [47–49], most C. tobin chloroplast repeats occur within the intergenic space, at the termini of genes located on opposite coding strands (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="592" pm="."><plain>The conservation of repeats within the chloroplast genomes of all algal taxa suggests a functional constraint for these structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="593" pm="."><plain>Insight into the contribution of repeats to chloroplast metabolic processes was accomplished by elegant studies with Chlamydomonas reinhardtii[50–52] that exploited the early ability to transform this organism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="594" pm="."><plain>Though these studies were predominantly focused on inverted repeats and confined to a limited gene set (e.g., atpB and rbcL), observations reveal a multifunctional role for repeat structures [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="595" pm="."><plain>Data show that the presence of a repeat at the terminus of a gene is necessary for proper mRNA processing by exo- and endonucleases [54], maintaining RNA stability [52, 55] and supporting protein translation [50]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="596" pm="."><plain>Given the established functional contribution of repeats, we asked whether specific genes or conserved chloroplast gene clusters [41] were targeted for repeat association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="597" pm="."><plain>Significant gene-repeat association was observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="598" pm="."><plain>For example, an inverted repeat is found at the terminus (rps10) of the ribosomal protein operon that encompasses 24 genes; inverted repeats are often present after the RuBisCO operon (rbcL/rbcS), as well as following the photosystem II gene pair (psbC/psbD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="599" pm="."><plain>Each of these targeted genes has no spatial relationship to one another with respect to in-chromosome placement; no concurrence exists among these genes in repeat type (tandem, inverted) and no similarity in sequence identity is seen in the repeat structures that are associated with the targeted gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="600" pm="."><plain>Despite these facts, selected gene-repeat associations (e.g., rbcL/rbcS) are conserved in chloroplast genomes as taxonomically disparate as C. tobin and E. huxleyi (Haptophyta), Ectocarpus siliculosus (Stramenopila: Phaeophyceae), Cyanidium caldarium (Rhodophyta) and Rhodomonas salina (Cryptophyta) - a list that is by no means exhaustive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="601" pm="."><plain>Single genes that are not associated with operons can also be targeted for repeat tagging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="602" pm="."><plain>A good example is clpC that encodes an ATPase-dependent protease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="603" pm="."><plain>This gene is found in different locations with many dissimilar up and downstream gene neighbors among CASH taxa. clpC is tagged with a repeat in all haptophytes except P. lutheri. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="604" pm="."><plain>A repeat is also found next to clpC in 19 of 44 (43.2%) CASH plastid genomes analyzed to date. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="605" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 5, even within haptophytes, the repeat is conserved only in gene association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="606" pm="."><plain>Neither the size, sequence, nor stem loop structure formed by these repeats is conserved.Figure 5 Conserved inverted repeats found adjacent to haptophyte clp C genes.  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="607" pm="."><plain>Given that repeats appear to have a functional significance, it was also of interest to determine whether a pattern in repeat acquisition exists among evolutionary diverse algae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="608" pm="."><plain>Repeat properties were queried across three groups of algae: rhodophytes (red algae), the ‘green’ algal lineage (green algae and those algae derived from the secondary endosymbiotic uptake of a chlorophyte [i.e. euglenids]) and the CASH grouping of algal species (derived from secondary or higher order endosymbioses of a rhodophytic plastid). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="609" pm="."><plain>Data clearly show that the number of repeats found in a chloroplast genome varies when different algal groups are compared. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="610" pm="."><plain>Rhodophytes appear to have few repeats (10 to 16 when excluding Cyanidioschyzon merolae, n = 79), and the CASH taxa have a moderate number (4 to 49 repeats [average = 25]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="611" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the green plastid lineage has on average 80 repeats per genome, though representatives have as many as 281 (Dunaliella salina) to 435 (Chara vulgaris) (Additional file 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="612" pm="."><plain>Repeat type is also group dependent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="613" pm="."><plain>CASH algae have a greater number of inverted repeats in their chloroplast genomes, whereas the green lineages have significantly more tandem repeats (Figure 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="614" pm="."><plain>Attempts to assess whether differences in chloroplast size and intergenic distance influenced the number and size of repeat structures show both parameters to be positively correlated with an increase in repeat number for green and CASH plastid lineages (Figure 6B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="615" pm="."><plain>However, there appears to be a limit on repeat size in the CASH plastid lineage, for even as genomes become larger and/or intergenic distances increase (Additional file 5), repeat size does not exceed ~65 bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="616" pm="."><plain>This result significantly contrasts with that seen in the green lineage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="617" pm="."><plain>A strong correlation exists between increased repeat size, and either an increased genome size or an increased intergenic distance (Additional file 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="618" pm="."><plain>The fact that repeat embellishment occurs in every algal chloroplast genome analyzed to date, that repeats often are conserved near specific genes, and repeats contribute to chloroplast gene expression, suggest that future research analyzing chloroplast intergenic regions is warranted.Figure 6 Small repeat analysis across algal groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="619" pm="."><plain>(A) Tandem and Inverted repeat complement across CASH, rhodophyte and “green” algal species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="620" pm="."><plain>The dotted line represents a 1:1 ratio of tandem and inverted repeat counts. (B) Linear association of repeat number versus genome size and average intergenic distance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="621" pm="."><plain>Chloroplast protein characterization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="622" pm="."><plain>Analysis of select genes can provide unique insight into chloroplast genome evolution and function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="623" pm="."><plain>In this context, several genes within the Chrysochromulina tobin chloroplast genome are described below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="624" pm="."><plain>Ribosomal protein RPL36 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="625" pm="."><plain>It is now known that some ribosomal proteins are multifunctional. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="626" pm="."><plain>Not only do these proteins serve as architectural components in the ribosome itself, but may also have additional extra-ribosomal functions that help maintain cellular homeostasis [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="627" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 7B, the ‘conventional’ (C+ motif) RPL36 protein encoded by chlorophytes and rhodophytes has a highly conserved zinc finger motif of the cysteine-cysteine-cysteine-histidine (CCCH) type (indicated by arrows). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="628" pm="."><plain>The haptophyte and cryptophyte RPL36 (C− motif) proteins lack the conserved zinc finger domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="629" pm="."><plain>In both haptophytes and cryptophytes the first cysteine is replaced by a serine, and the terminal histidine of the zinc finger motif is replaced by a leucine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="630" pm="."><plain>Therefore it is very unlikely that the haptophyte/cryptophyte RPL36 C− retains zinc finger protein function.Figure 7 Phylogenetic analysis of RPL36 proteins. Bayesian majority rule consensus tree of 85 RPL36 proteins from haptophytes, cryptophytes, a haptophyte plastid-containing dinoflagellate, stramenopiles, rhodophytes, Paulinella chromatophora, and select bacteria and cyanobacteria. Taxa are colored according to the legend. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="631" pm="."><plain>Bayesian posterior probabilities and Maximum Likelihood bootstrap support are shown at nodes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="632" pm="."><plain>Scale bar shows amino acid substitutions per site (A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="633" pm="."><plain>Logo plot consensus sequences for the C− and C+ RPL36 protein (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="634" pm="."><plain>The zinc finger residues are completely conserved in the C+ genotype, while 2 residues are absent from the C− clade. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="635" pm="."><plain>Although the zinc finger function was not recognized, earlier studies used the unique RPL36 C− sequence observed in haptophyte and cryptophyte chloroplast genomes to argue for a sister relationship between the plastids of these taxa [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="636" pm="."><plain>Sanchez-Puerta and Delwiche attempted to reconcile the presence of an rpl36 C− gene (likely derived from a bacterium via lateral gene transfer) in the cryptophyte and haptophyte plastids with the presence of the ancestral rpl36 C+ gene in stramenopiles by positing that, for a time, two chloroplast genomes co-existed in the haptophytes and cryptophytes, some genomes containing the rpl36 C+ gene and others with the C− gene [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="637" pm="."><plain>One or the other genome was then fixed in particular lineages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="638" pm="."><plain>This hypothesis predicts the discovery of an rpl36 C+ gene in the chloroplast genomes of some haptophytes or cryptophytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="639" pm="."><plain>To better test this hypothesis, we infer a new rpl36 phylogeny including five additional haptophyte genera (seven species), 24 additional stramenopiles, four additional rhodophytes, as well as a representative of the recently recognized algal lineage Paulinella. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="640" pm="."><plain>Mining NCBI as well as our publically available chloroplast genome database [38], a total of 462 non-redundant RPL36 amino acid sequences were recovered for phylogenetic analysis (Additional files 6, 7, 8 and 9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="641" pm="."><plain>In Figure 7, this large dataset is condensed and re-inferred to include sequences from a limited number of bacterial and cyanobacterial representatives; rhodophytic as well as CASH plastids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="642" pm="."><plain>We confirm the RPL36 C− identity of all haptophyte and cryptophyte algae to the exclusion of all other eukaryotic algal taxa sampled, including stramenopiles and rhodophytes [57], thus Sanchez-Puerta and Delwiche’s hypothesis was not confirmed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="643" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, even though our rpl36 phylogeny increases bacterial sampling beyond that used for prior analyses, results do not support a planctomycete-origin of the laterally transferred rpl36 as previously suggested [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="644" pm="."><plain>No bacterial clade is strongly supported as the donor of the C− gene (Additional files 6 and 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="645" pm="."><plain>Determination of the donor lineage is made difficult by the short length of the rpl36 protein (C− 49 amino acids, C+ 38 amino acids) and the ancient nature of the lateral gene transfer event. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="646" pm="."><plain>The duality in chloroplast encoded rpl36 genes poses questions concerning the contribution of each alternative protein type to the maintenance of cellular stasis in different algal lineages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="647" pm="."><plain>The functional contribution is most likely multifaceted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="648" pm="."><plain>Certainly, the RPL36 protein, whether of the C+ or C− type, contributes to ribosomal structure [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="649" pm="."><plain>However, bacteria that contain both paralogs of the RPL36 protein differentially express rpl36 C− and rpl36 C+ when subject to zinc stress [59, 60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="650" pm="."><plain>The rpl36 C− gene is up-regulated under limiting conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="651" pm="."><plain>Since the zinc finger domain of RPL36 not only binds zinc, but also bind other cationic species [61], one might speculate that in algal cells an increased covalent ion binding potential might provide a competitive advantage when living in ecosystems where particular cofactors are in short supply. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="652" pm="."><plain>The fact that haptophyte/cryptophyte RPL36 C− proteins have an extended 7 to 9 amino acid C terminus that is enriched with positively charged as well as hydrophobic moieties supports the possibility that this small molecule also has a regulatory function, similar to that established for other ribosomal zinc finger proteins [62–64]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="653" pm="."><plain>Two component signal transduction systems </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="654" pm="."><plain>Two-component regulatory systems are key mechanisms through which many organisms (bacteria, archaea, and eukaryotes) control responses to fluctuating environmental conditions [65, 66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="655" pm="."><plain>Numerous two component regulatory systems exist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="656" pm="."><plain>In its simplest form, when cued by an external stimulus, a phosphoryl group from a conserved histidine residue within a sensor kinase protein is transferred to an aspartic acid in the receiver domain of a response regulator protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="657" pm="."><plain>Phosphorylation of the response regulator protein activates an effector domain (usually through a conformation change) to propagate the intended regulatory effect. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="658" pm="."><plain>The Chrysochromulina tobin chloroplast genome encodes two response regulator proteins but is devoid of sensor kinase genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="659" pm="."><plain>The first response regulator protein, orf27, encodes a protein similar to the TRG1 response regulator described for the stramenopile Heterosigma akashiwo[41, 67] and is also found in other CASH species, rhodophytes, and cyanobacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="660" pm="."><plain>The second response regulator, ycf55, is likely a member of a new subclass of response regulators evolved from the cyanobacterial type “CheY-like” response regulator proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="661" pm="."><plain>Many of the cyanobacterial CheY-like homologs are comprised of approximately 550 amino acids and contain two domains; the aforementioned receiver domain and a conserved domain of unknown function (DUF3685), hypothesized to be the effector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="662" pm="."><plain>Intriguingly, the cheY-like homolog (ycf55) found in C. tobin is comprised of only 314 amino acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="663" pm="."><plain>Multi-sequence protein alignments of a variety of response regulators from cyanobacteria, algae, and Arabidopsis revealed that the C-terminus of the C. tobin ycf55 is most similar to the cyanobacterial type CheY-like proteins, as both contain the terminal DUF3685 domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="664" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the N-terminus of the C. tobin ycf55 is divergent from both cyanobacterial CheY-like response regulators and the plant type response regulators (i.e., ARR1-14), including loss of the canonical site of phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="665" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, sequences that resemble the C. tobin type of ycf55 are conserved in rhodophytes (Chondrus crispus, Calliarthron tuberculosum, Gracilaria tenuistipitata, Porphyra purpurea, and two Pyropias species), other haptophytes (except P. lutheri), and some cyanobacteria (classified as ‘RRI-other’ [68]) indicating that this protein still provides an important function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="666" pm="."><plain>Within this divergent subclass of ycf55 proteins an aspartic acid residue (D43) just upstream of the canonical position is conserved, suggesting that this residue could replace the canonical site of phosphorylation by an as yet unknown sensor kinase. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="667" pm="."><plain>Structural analysis of Ycf39 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="668" pm="."><plain>Ycf39 is conserved in many CASH and rhodophytic species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="669" pm="."><plain>To gain insight into Ycf39 identity and its potential functional role, a structural and comparative modeling approach was taken. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="670" pm="."><plain>The HHpred server [69] was used to identify structures in the Protein Data Bank (PDB) [70] that showed high sequence homology to Ycf39. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="671" pm="."><plain>The top 10 structures recovered (Additional file 10) had E-values ranging from 9E−39 to 2.5E−36. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="672" pm="."><plain>Amino acid sequence identity of Ycf39 to these structural hits ranged between 15-18%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="673" pm="."><plain>All structural hits show very similar fold identities, and fall under NmrA-like or NAD-binding domains by Pfam classification [71]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="674" pm="."><plain>Eight out of ten structural homologs are known to bind NADP/NAD (Additional file 10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="675" pm="."><plain>Using the ten structures as templates for Rosetta comparative modeling [72], a total of 20,400 trajectories were assessed and clustered based on backbone RMSD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="676" pm="."><plain>The top scoring comparative model of Ycf39 (Figure 8A) is based on the structural template 2JL1 a triphenylmethane reductase (Additional file 11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="677" pm="."><plain>The 2JL1 and Ycf39 sequence alignment is shown in Additional file 12.Figure 8 Insights into 3D structure of ycf39 and its NADP binding potential. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="678" pm="."><plain>(A) 3D model of ycf39 sequence based on comparative modeling using a crystal structure (PDB code 2JL1) as a template. (B) Amplified view of the cleft in ycf39 model and docked NADP molecule. (C) NADP binding residues compared between ycf39 and 2JL1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="679" pm="."><plain>The numbers (top) represent the amino acid position in the template structure, 2JL1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="680" pm="."><plain>The corresponding residues in ycf39 were found by multiple sequence alignment using HHpred server [74]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="681" pm="."><plain>To determine whether the proposed model of Ycf39 could bind an NADP molecule, a large number of NADP conformers (n = 885, see Methods) were randomly docked into the largest pocket in the Ycf39 3D model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="682" pm="."><plain>Of the resulting random docked protein-ligand conformations obtained (n = 7,000), the top binding energy conformation is presented in Figure 8B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="683" pm="."><plain>The model showed an equivalent positioning of NADP in the proposed pocket of the Ycf39 3D model as was observed in the template structure (PDB code 2JL1 and Additional file 11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="684" pm="."><plain>In both cases, the nicotinamide group is buried in the protein, while the adenine group is near the surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="685" pm="."><plain>Additionally, locating the NADP interacting amino acids on the template (2JL1) and finding corresponding amino acids in Ycf39 based on sequence alignment showed 38% sequence identity and another 24% similarity (Figure 8C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="686" pm="."><plain>These amino acids were in close proximity to the docked NADP in our Ycf39 model (Additional file 13). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="687" pm="."><plain>Taken together, the sequence similarity of the Ycf39 protein product with NmrA-like family proteins (Additional file 1), the presence of a dockable site for NADP in the predicted structure of Ycf39 (Figure 8A, B) and striking similarity of the NADP interacting motif with a known NADP binder (Figure 8C) suggests Ycf39 should be identified as an NmrA-like protein in C. tobin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="688" pm="."><plain>A strong homology (45% amino acid identity) of Ycf39 to an NmrA family protein identified in the endosymbiotic cyanobacteria Nostoc azollae has also been found [73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="689" pm="."><plain>Characterized NmrA proteins function in the transcriptional regulation of genes important to nitrogen metabolite repression [74, 75], thus allowing a cell to access a preferred nitrogen source [76]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="690" pm="."><plain>Functional studies will be required to determine if the protein product of ycf39 serves this metabolic roll. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="691" pm="."><plain>Membrane transporter/translocator proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="692" pm="."><plain>The majority of chloroplast proteins are encoded in the nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="693" pm="."><plain>For this reason, translocators located in the chloroplast envelope are needed to facilitate import of the cytosolically produced proteins into the plastid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="694" pm="."><plain>Chloroplasts of primary endosymbiotic origin require protein transport across two membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="695" pm="."><plain>This process is facilitated by two complexes, the TOC and TIC translocons, located in the outer and inner chloroplast envelopes respectively [77–79]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="696" pm="."><plain>In plastids of higher order endosymbiotic origin (such as Chrysochromulina tobin), protein transport is complicated by the presence of either three or four membranes surrounding the chloroplast [80, 81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="697" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, Tic and Toc components have previously been found in algae containing more than two membranes [82, 83]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="698" pm="."><plain>Here, we identify two potential Tic subunit genes (tic20 and tic22) encoded in the C. tobin chloroplast genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="699" pm="."><plain>Tic20 is a small membrane protein that is anchored by three helices in the membrane and has protrusions into the stroma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="700" pm="."><plain>A Tic20 homolog is likely encoded by the ycf60 gene, a gene found exclusively in rhodophyte, haptophyte and stramenopile chloroplast genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="701" pm="."><plain>Tic22, a second member of the inner membrane import complex, has poorly characterized function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="702" pm="."><plain>We have identified ycf80 as a Tic22 translocator protein homolog. ycf80 homologs are found exclusively in the chloroplast genomes of the haptophytes C. tobin, E. huxleyi, P. antarctica and the uncultured prymnesiophyte C19847, as well as rhodophytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="703" pm="."><plain>The continued sequestering of genes encoding these two translocator components of the innermost membrane of both primary and secondary plastids (the putative plasma membrane of the original symbiont) suggests that evolutionary footprints of original transporter components still remain in select taxa. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="704" pm="."><plain>BLAST homology searches for nuclear encoded translocator homologs gave mixed results when querying the draft nuclear genome of C. tobin (Hovde, et. al. in preparation). toc159 is the only nuclear encoded Toc gene found in C. tobin. toc34, toc75 and toc64 are absent or are diverged so identification was compromised. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="705" pm="."><plain>Nuclear genes with strong homology to tic110 and tic55 are found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="706" pm="."><plain>This observation is consistent with data for the rhodophyte C. merolae[84]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="707" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, tic40 is also found in C. tobin, but is absent in rhodophytic queries. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="708" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="709" pm="."><plain>The complete sequence of Chrysochromulina tobin mitochondrial and chloroplast genomes, representative of the ecologically important haptophyte prymnesiales B2 clade, have been determined and annotated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="710" pm="."><plain>Within the mitochondrial genome, a large repeat structure consisting of ~9 kb was found along with a novel 457 amino acid open reading frame of unknown function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="711" pm="."><plain>The large inverted repeats in the chloroplast genome contain a combination of novel of intergenic spacer region structures and SNP variants when rDNA-containing domains are compared, indicating the possible loss of a copy correction mechanism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="712" pm="."><plain>Notably, no recombined structural isomers of the C. tobin chloroplast genome were found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="713" pm="."><plain>Small repeats within intergenic regions of the chloroplast genome have taxon-specific evolutionary features. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="714" pm="."><plain>The embellishment of specific genes by repeats argues for a functional role in metabolism for these structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="715" pm="."><plain>Several genes found in C. tobin chloroplast that remain uncharacterized, yet conserved in other algal species were analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="716" pm="."><plain>They include: the ribosomal protein rpl36; a new two component signal transduction protein; the potential NmrA-like NADP-binding nitrogen regulator, and two chloroplast protein import genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="717" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="718" pm="."><plain>Culture maintenance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="719" pm="."><plain>Chrysochromulina strain CCMP291, acquired from The National Center for Marine Algae (NCMA) by the Cattolico laboratory in 2006, was designated as P3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="720" pm="."><plain>These cultures were maintained in 250 mL Erlenmeyer flasks containing 100 ml of RAC-1, a proprietary fresh water medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="721" pm="."><plain>Flasks were plugged with silicone sponge stoppers (Bellco Glass, Vineland, NJ) and capped with a sterilizer bag (Propper Manufacturing, Long Island City, NY). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="722" pm="."><plain>Large volume experimental cultures for genomic DNA harvesting were maintained in 1.0 L of RAC-1 medium contained in 2.8 L large-mouth Fernbach flasks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="723" pm="."><plain>These flasks were plugged with hand-rolled, #50 cheese cloth-covered cotton stoppers and covered with a #2 size Kraft bag (Paper Mart, Orange, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="724" pm="."><plain>All cultures were maintained at 20°C on a 12 hour light:12 hour dark photoperiod under 100 μEm−2 s−1 light intensity using full spectrum T12 fluorescent light bulbs (Philips Electronics, Stamford, CT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="725" pm="."><plain>No CO2 was provided and cultures were not agitated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="726" pm="."><plain>Bacterized cultures were treated in the following manner to minimize bacterial contamination: P3 cultures were subject to re-iterative cell sorting using flow cytometry. Chrysochromulina tobin cells were stained for identification using BODIPY 505/515 (4,4-difluoro-1,3,5,7-tetramethyl-4-bora-3a,4a-diaza-s-indacene; Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), a neutral lipid binding fluorophore. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="727" pm="."><plain>Approximately 10 stained cells were sorted into a single well of a 96 well plate containing 100 μl RAC-1 medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="728" pm="."><plain>Due to poor growth in the 96 well plate, well contents were transferred to 10 ml of RAC-1 medium in 50 ml plastic tissue culture flasks (Nunc, Roskilde, Denmark). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="729" pm="."><plain>This cell sorting process was carried out 4 times with the resulting culture being designated as P4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="730" pm="."><plain>Cells obtained from reiterative flow cytometric selection (P4) were then treated in RAC-1 medium that contained either streptomycin (resulting in culture P5.5) or hygromycin (P5.6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="731" pm="."><plain>Treatment with these two antibiotics were identical: cells were exposed to a final concentration of 400 μg/ml antibiotic for 18 hours before 5 mL of treated cultures were transferred to 100 mL of antibiotic free RAC-1 medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="732" pm="."><plain>Cultures P5.5 and P5.6 were periodically tested for bacterial contamination using liquid LB medium made with RAC-1 medium in replacement of water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="733" pm="."><plain>Sequencing data and a cultured isolate has shown that one bacterial contaminant is still present in the antibiotic treated cultures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="734" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA isolation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="735" pm="."><plain>Total genomic DNA was collected from each of the P5.5 and P5.6 cultures using the Qiagen Genomic-tip Maxi DNA extraction protocol (Germantown, MD) with the following changes to the standard protocol [41]: 1.5 × 108 cells were harvested by centrifugation (Beckman-Coulter JA-10 Rotor at 7000 rpm (5378 × g) for 20 minutes) and resuspended in lysis buffer (20 mM EDTA, pH 8.0; 10 mM Tris-base, pH 8.0; 1% Triton X; 500 mM Guanidine; 200 mM NaCl) with 1.0 hour incubation at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="736" pm="."><plain>RNase A was added to a final concentration of 200 μg/ml and incubated for 30 minutes at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="737" pm="."><plain>600 μl of Proteinase K (20 mg/ml) (Sigma-Aldrich) was then added to the tube and incubated at 50°C for 2.0 hours, mixing every 30 minutes by swirling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="738" pm="."><plain>The Qiagen DNA binding tip (Maxi size) was equilibrated using the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="739" pm="."><plain>DNA preparation was transferred into the tip and allowed to pass using gravity at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="740" pm="."><plain>The tip was washed twice using Qiagen buffer QC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="741" pm="."><plain>15 ml of Buffer QF (at 37°C) was added to the tip to elute the DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="742" pm="."><plain>DNA was precipitated by the addition of 10.5 ml of 100% room temperature isopropanol followed by centrifugation (12,000 rpm (11,220 × g) for 20 min, 4°C using a JA-20 rotor). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="743" pm="."><plain>The pellet was washed in 4 ml of 4°C 70% ethanol and centrifuged again using the same conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="744" pm="."><plain>The DNA pellet was air dried for 5 min and resuspended in warmed Qiagen buffer EB (50°C) and incubated at 50°C for 2.0 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="745" pm="."><plain>DNA solution was quantitated using a spectrophotometer and subsequently transferred to 1.7 ml Eppendorf tubes and stored at −80°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="746" pm="."><plain>Genome sequencing, assembly and annotation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="747" pm="."><plain>The Chrysochromulina tobin chloroplast and mitochondrial genomes were sequenced using a combination of Illumina [85] and 454 sequencing technologies [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="748" pm="."><plain>Two shotgun libraries (2 × 100 and 1 × 150 base pair) were prepared using standard TruSeq protocols and sequenced from bulk C. tobin genomic DNA on an Illumina HiSeq2000 sequencer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="749" pm="."><plain>Additional shotgun single-end and paired-end (10 kb insert) DNA libraries were prepared for sequencing on the 454 Titanium platform generating 1.2 million and 3.5 million reads, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="750" pm="."><plain>The 454 single-end data and the 454 paired end data (insert size 8180 +/− 1495 bp) were assembled together using Newbler, version 2.3 (release 091027_1459). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="751" pm="."><plain>The Illumina-generated sequences were assembled separately with VELVET, version 1.0.13 [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="752" pm="."><plain>The resulting consensus sequences from both the VELVET and Newbler assemblies were computationally shredded into 10 kb fragments and were re-assembled with reads from the 454 paired end library using parallelPhrap, version 1.080812 (High Performance Software, LLC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="753" pm="."><plain>Based on homologous BLAST [86] searches against other chloroplast and mitochondrial genomes, the mitochondrial genome was identified as a single contig of 25,263 bp with one gap and the chloroplast genome was comprised of two contigs that totaled a combined 101,192 bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="754" pm="."><plain>Most mis-assemblies in the contigs of the mitochondrial and chloroplast genomes were corrected using gapResolution (Cliff Han, unpublished script, Los Alamos National Laboratory) or Dupfinisher [87]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="755" pm="."><plain>However, due to the large ribosomal inverted repeat in the chloroplast, PCR amplification anchored by priming of unique regions flanking and within the repeat sections was used as sequence template to resolve the final circular representation of the chloroplast genome structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="756" pm="."><plain>Similarly, a large tandem repeat structure identified in the mitochondrial genome prevented automated closure of the remaining gap. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="757" pm="."><plain>De-convolution of this repeat was completed by PCR amplification and cloning of multiple products (see primer table Additional file 14) into the pGem T-easy vector (Promega, Madison, WI) followed by capillary sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="758" pm="."><plain>The presence of chloroplast genomes containing flip-flop recombined isoforms was queried using all combinations of single copy region primers (petB, ycf60, psa and rpl21 primers) (Additional file 14). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="759" pm="."><plain>Only the expected primer pairs, petB-ycf60 and psa-rpl21 pairs, produced PCR products. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="760" pm="."><plain>The final, fully assembled chloroplast and mitochondrial genomes were supported by &gt; 500× average coverage from the combined sequencing platforms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="761" pm="."><plain>Each assembled genome was verified by aligning the original Illumina reads to the final draft using the Burrow-Wheeler Alignment tool (BWA) [88]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="762" pm="."><plain>Continuous coverage without gaps or missing reads was verified using Tablet alignment [89] which identified &gt;10 single nucleotide mismatches (both SNPs and indels) in the chloroplast draft assembly, which were corrected in the final assembly. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="763" pm="."><plain>Annotation was accomplished by GLIMMER [90] for initial gene calling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="764" pm="."><plain>BLAST homology searches to CpBase, a curated chloroplast database housed by the University of Washington Department of Oceanography [38] were used for final gene identification and recovery of small or missing genes that were overlooked by automated annotation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="765" pm="."><plain>Manual examination of BLAST homology searches was performed for each protein coding gene to determine correct start codons and gene length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="766" pm="."><plain>An identical approach was used to assemble the mitochondrial genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title><text><SENT sid="767" pm="."><plain>Comparative genomic analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="768" pm="."><plain>For comparative analysis of gene, tRNA and repeat content, genome size and GC content, the chloroplast genome of C. tobin was assessed using CpBase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="769" pm="."><plain>Visualization of chloroplast and mitochondrial genome gene order comparison was completed using Mauve [28] and GRIMM analysis was performed respectively [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="770" pm="."><plain>Mauve analysis of the three haptophyte genomes was performed using default seed weight, iterative alignment, determine LCBs and sum of pairs LCB scoring settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="771" pm="."><plain>GRIMM was performed on the Mauve output using default GRIMM settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="772" pm="."><plain>Additionally, genome map images were constructed using GenomeVx [91]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="773" pm="."><plain>Small repeat analysis: Small (&lt;200 bp) inverted repeats were identified using Einverted from EMBOSS [92]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="774" pm="."><plain>Tandem repeats were identified using Tandem Repeats Finder [93]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="775" pm="."><plain>Small repeats located next to genes (clpC, psaB, rpoC, atpA, rps10, rbcS, and psbC) appearing to be conserved across chloroplast genomes in multiple species from manual inspection were quantified across all CASH taxa available in CpBase [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="776" pm="."><plain>To refine the repeat list for the gene/repeat association analysis, the presence of tandem or inverted repeats adjacent to genes or gene clusters was queried using the “Repeat Finder” tool in CpBase [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="777" pm="."><plain>Parameters used were: Search distance: 300 bp, End: “Both”, Boundary: “Both”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="778" pm="."><plain>Additionally, no other feature (tRNA or protein coding gene) separating the gene and inverted repeat was counted in this analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="779" pm="."><plain>Small inverted repeat physical structure was determined by inputting the sequence into M-fold [94–96] using default parameters and a loop size maximum of 30 bp. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="780" pm="."><plain>Large inverted repeat homology: The size of large inverted repeats which contain at least the ribosomal 16S-23S operon was determined by 2 sequence BLAST comparison of the two halves of a genome, each half containing one of the ribosomal repeats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="781" pm="."><plain>BLASTN homology using the default settings was used to determine the borders of the repeat regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="782" pm="."><plain>To determine the sequence homology between two copies of 16S or 23S, BLASTN was used with default parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="783" pm="."><plain>Each SNP and single nucleotide insertion or deletion was counted separately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="784" pm="."><plain>If only one copy of the ribosomal operon was present, no homology search was performed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="785" pm="."><plain>Small repeat statistical analysis: A Fisher’s Exact test was implemented to compare the proportion of chloroplast with more tandem repeats than inverted repeats in CASH taxa, rhodophytes, and the “green lineage”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="786" pm="."><plain>Linear regressions were used to test for an association between small repeats, genome size, and intergenic length with average repeat size as well as total small repeats with genome size and intergenic length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="787" pm="."><plain>This analysis was repeated on the green lineage, CASH algae, and rhodophytes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title><text><SENT sid="788" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis of rpl36 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="789" pm="."><plain>By mining CpBase as well as NCBI, a total of 462 non-redundant RPL36 amino acid sequences were recovered for phylogenetic analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="790" pm="."><plain>These sequences were aligned in MUSCLE [97] and any C-terminal extensions were trimmed to create a 41 amino acid alignment with two gaps in the RPL36 C− proteins such that functional motifs of the zinc finger domain (and their substituted amino acids in the C− proteins) were aligned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="791" pm="."><plain>Protein matrices available in the CIPRES Science Gateway [98] MrBayes 3.2.2 tool were evaluated for appropriateness using ProtTest 2.4 [99]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="792" pm="."><plain>The cpREV + I + Γ model of protein sequence evolution was found to best suit the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="793" pm="."><plain>Gene trees were inferred with RAxML 7.6.3 [100]with 1000 bootstraps, as well as with MrBayes v3.2.2 [101] with two runs each of four chains, 10 million generations, and 25% burn-in. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="794" pm="."><plain>Stationarity and convergence of the Bayesian analysis were assessed with Tracer v1.5 [102]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="795" pm="."><plain>To best represent the data, 85 select taxa were chosen for Figure 7 and the phylogeny re-inferred with the same parameters but only 5 million generations in the Bayesian analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title><text><SENT sid="796" pm="."><plain>Structural modeling of Ycf39 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="797" pm="."><plain>A structural model of Ycf39 was built using template structures found on HHpred server [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="798" pm="."><plain>Secondary structure prediction for Ycf39 sequence was made using PsiPred [103] (Additional file 15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="799" pm="."><plain>Robetta server [104] was used to generate the peptide fragments based on local homology of the ycf39 sequence with other sequences in a structural database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="800" pm="."><plain>Rosetta comparative modeling protocol [72] uses a secondary structure profile of the query sequence, customized three- and nine- amino acid long peptide fragments based on secondary structure prediction of the query sequence from the structural database, a multiple sequence alignment file and a structural template to build the tertiary models of the query sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="801" pm="."><plain>A total of 20440 comparative modeling trajectories were run and a few top scoring models visualized using PyMOL (The PyMOL Molecular Graphics System, Schrödinger, LLC). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="802" pm="."><plain>To dock NADP to the top-ranked predicted ycf39 structures, NADP atomic coordinates were taken from one of the HHpred search hits (PDB code 2JL1) that had a bound NADP molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="803" pm="."><plain>Protons were added to this NADP structure using Avogadro molecule editor software [105], while the phosphate groups were kept deprotonated and the nicotinamide group was kept planar to match the deprotonated form of the molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="804" pm="."><plain>The formal charge of the resulting NADP molecule was zero. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="805" pm="."><plain>A PubChem [106] search identified 13 rotatable bonds in NADP that were sampled in two states, ± 30° from the dihedral angles observed in the 2JL1 crystal structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="806" pm="."><plain>The resulting library of 885 NADP conformers (Additional file 16) had full atom intra-molecule repulsive energies as calculated by Rosetta [107] within 1% of the starting molecule structure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="807" pm="."><plain>Random docking of NADP conformers to structural models of ycf39 was performed in three steps using the RosettaLigand protocol [108, 109]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="808" pm="."><plain>NADP conformers were randomly placed in the largest cleft observed in ycf39 3D model, then rotated in 1000 random orientations to identify orientations with the best shape complementarity to the protein surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="809" pm="."><plain>Small perturbations in translation and rotation (0.1 Å, 3°) were introduced with side chain repacking and energy minimization, followed by a second round of small perturbations in NADP position, orientation and torsions prior to a final energy minimization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="810" pm="."><plain>A total of 7000 trajectories were run using the above strategy to identify the best ycf39 structural model with a bound NADP molecule and the lowest ligand binding energy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="811" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec23"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_7065_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="812" pm="."><plain>Additional file 1: Figure S1: Mauve analysis of conserved regions in the mitochondrial genomes of Emiliania huxleyi, Phaeosyctis antarctica, and Chrysochromulina tobin. (PDF 344 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_7065_MOESM2_ESM.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="813" pm="."><plain>Additional file 2: Table S1: Genome size, intergenic distance and repeats across algal species used in the statistical analysis section. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="814" pm="."><plain>(XLS 44 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_7065_MOESM3_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="815" pm="."><plain>Additional file 3: Figure S2: Detailed intergenic spacer region comparison of the two Chrysochromulina tobin ribosomal operon repeats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="816" pm="."><plain>(PDF 274 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_7065_MOESM4_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="817" pm="."><plain>Additional file 4: Table S2: Other chloroplast genomes containing non-canonical ribosomal intergenic spacer regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="818" pm="."><plain>(PDF 304 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_7065_MOESM5_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="819" pm="."><plain>Additional file 5: Figure S3: Additional repeat analysis of CASH and green algal lineages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="820" pm="."><plain>(PDF 312 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_7065_MOESM6_ESM.zip"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="821" pm="."><plain>Additional file 6: Bayesian RPL36 phylogenetic tree with complete dataset; open in FigTree. (ZIP 31 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_7065_MOESM7_ESM.zip"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="822" pm="."><plain>Additional file 7: RPL36 alignment with complete dataset; nexus formatted. (ZIP 17 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM8"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_7065_MOESM8_ESM.zip"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="823" pm="."><plain>Additional file 8: Bayesian RPL36 phylogenetic tree with reduced dataset (Figure  7 ); open in Mesquite. (ZIP 6 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM9"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_7065_MOESM9_ESM.zip"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="824" pm="."><plain>Additional file 9: RPL36 alignment with reduced dataset; nexus formatted. (ZIP 3 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM10"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_7065_MOESM10_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="825" pm="."><plain>Additional file 10: Table S4: Top protein data bank structural hits to the NmrA protein (Ycf39) in the C. tobin chloroplast genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="826" pm="."><plain>(PDF 304 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM11"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_7065_MOESM11_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="827" pm="."><plain>Additional file 11: Figure S4: Structural template (PDB code 2JL1) for comparative modeling of Ycf39 sequence and NADP in the binding pocket of protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="828" pm="."><plain>(PDF 312 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM12"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_7065_MOESM12_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="829" pm="."><plain>Additional file 12: Figure S5: Multiple sequence alignment of ycf39 and one of the templates (PDB code 2JL1) used for comparative modeling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="830" pm="."><plain>(PDF 477 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM13"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_7065_MOESM13_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="831" pm="."><plain>Additional file 13: Figure S6: NADP interacting residues in 2JL1 and Ycf39 models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="832" pm="."><plain>(PDF 570 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM14"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_7065_MOESM14_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="833" pm="."><plain>Additional file 14: Table S5: Primers used for organellar genome resolution of repeat structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="834" pm="."><plain>(PDF 291 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM15"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_7065_MOESM15_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="835" pm="."><plain>Additional file 15: Figure S7: Secondary structure prediction of Ycf39 sequence using Psipred. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="836" pm="."><plain>(PDF 243 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM16"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_7065_MOESM16_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="837" pm="."><plain>Additional file 16: Figure S8: Conformers of NADP molecule used for RosettaLigand Dock protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="838" pm="."><plain>(PDF 339 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ISR</term><def><p>Intergenic Spacer Region</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SNP</term><def><p>Single Nucleotide Polymorphism</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RMSD</term><def><p>Root Mean Square Deviation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NADP</term><def><p>Nicotinamide Adenine Dinucleotide Phosphate.</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="839" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="840" pm="."><plain>The authors have no competing interests to declare. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="841" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="842" pm="."><plain>BTH and RAC conceived the study; CRD prepared C. tobin DNA; BTH, OC, SRS and RJM sequenced and assembled, and BTH annotated the chloroplast and mitochondrial genomes; RAC, BTH, RKJ, HMH and SRS investigated the specific genes presented in this work; BTH, RAC and LDM analyzed repeats, BTH and RAC spearheaded manuscript generation with the assistance of all authors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="843" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="844" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to thank: The Sequencing Technologies Team at LANL for generating the raw DNA reads to complete the assembly of the chloroplast and mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="845" pm="."><plain>Cedar McKay and Gabrielle Rocap for support in using CpBase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="846" pm="."><plain>Hwan Su Yoon for rpl36 gene sequences of unpublished rhodophytic algae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="847" pm="."><plain>Alden Hackmann for figure generation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="848" pm="."><plain>Andrew Scharenberg for flow cytometer resources. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="849" pm="."><plain>Computational resource support from Charlie E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="850" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="851" pm="."><plain>Strauss. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="852" pm="."><plain>RAC dedicates this manuscript to RA Gray, ED Cattolico and RO Morgan. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="853" pm="."><plain>Funding </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="854" pm="."><plain>BTH was supported by Interdisciplinary Training in Genomic Sciences NHGRI T32 HG00035. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="855" pm="."><plain>HMH was supported by the NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program DGE-0718124 and DGE-1256082. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="856" pm="."><plain>RKJ was supported by DTRA grant CBCALL12-LS6-1-0622 and Los Alamos computing resource grant WSYN_BIO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="857" pm="."><plain>RJM Jr was supported by NIH Award 1RL1CA133831. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="858" pm="."><plain>RAC, CRD, and SRS were supported by the US Department of Energy under contract DE-EE0003046 to the National Alliance for Advanced Biofuels and Bioproducts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="859" pm="."><plain>RAC was also supported by Sea Grant NA07OAR-4170007. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="860" pm="."><plain>1.FieldCBBehrenfeldMJRandersonJTFalkowskiPPrimary production of the biosphere: integrating terrestrial and oceanic componentsScience199828123724010.1126/science.281.5374.237<?supplied-pmid 9657713?>9657713 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="861" pm="."><plain>2.LiuHProbertIUitzJClaustreHAris-BrosouSFradaMNotFde VargasCExtreme diversity in noncalcifying haptophytes explains a major pigment paradox in open oceansProc Natl Acad Sci2009106128031280810.1073/pnas.0905841106<?supplied-pmid 19622724?>19622724 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="862" pm="."><plain>3.RasJClaustreHUitzJSpatial variability of phytoplankton pigment distributions in the Subtropical South Pacific Ocean: comparison between in situ and predicted dataBiogeosciences2008535336910.5194/bg-5-353-2008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="863" pm="."><plain>4.KeelingPJBurgerGDurnfordDGLangBFLeeRWPearlmanRERogerAJGrayMWThe tree of eukaryotesTrends Ecol Evol20052067067610.1016/j.tree.2005.09.005<?supplied-pmid 16701456?>16701456 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="864" pm="."><plain>5.MedlinLKKooistraWHCFPotterDSaundersGWAndersenRABhattacharyaDDPhylogenetic relationships of the “golden algae” (haptophytes, heterokont chromophytes) and their plastidsOrig Algae Their Plast1997ViennaSpringer187219 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="865" pm="."><plain>6.BaurainDBrinkmannHPetersenJRodríguez-EzpeletaNStechmannADemoulinVRogerAJBurgerGLangBFPhilippeHPhylogenomic evidence for separate acquisition of plastids in cryptophytes, haptophytes, and stramenopilesMol Biol Evol2010271698170910.1093/molbev/msq059<?supplied-pmid 20194427?>20194427 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="866" pm="."><plain>7.BodyłADo plastid-related characters support the Chromalveolate Hypothesis?J Phycol20054171271910.1111/j.1529-8817.2005.00091.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="867" pm="."><plain>8.YoonHSHackettJDPintoGBhattacharyaDThe single, ancient origin of chromist plastidsProc Natl Acad Sci U S A200299155071551210.1073/pnas.242379899<?supplied-pmid 12438651?>12438651 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="868" pm="."><plain>9.BachvaroffTRSanchez PuertaMVDelwicheCFChlorophyll c-containing plastid relationships based on analyses of a multigene data set with all four chromalveolate lineagesMol Biol Evol2005221772178210.1093/molbev/msi172<?supplied-pmid 15917498?>15917498 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="869" pm="."><plain>10.HarperJTWaandersEKeelingPJOn the monophyly of chromalveolates using a six-protein phylogeny of eukaryotesInt J Syst Evol Microbiol200555Pt 148749610.1099/ijs.0.63216-0<?supplied-pmid 15653923?>15653923 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="870" pm="."><plain>11.BurkiFOkamotoNPombertJ-FKeelingPJThe evolutionary history of haptophytes and cryptophytes: phylogenomic evidence for separate originsProc Biol Sci20122792246225410.1098/rspb.2011.2301<?supplied-pmid 22298847?>22298847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="871" pm="."><plain>12.BurkiFShalchian-TabriziKPawlowskiJPhylogenomics reveals a new “megagroup” including most photosynthetic eukaryotesBiol Lett2008436636910.1098/rsbl.2008.0224<?supplied-pmid 18522922?>18522922 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="872" pm="."><plain>13.KimEGrahamLEEEF2 analysis challenges the monophyly of Archaeplastida and ChromalveolataPLoS One20083e262110.1371/journal.pone.0002621<?supplied-pmid 18612431?>18612431 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="873" pm="."><plain>14.Sanchez-PuertaMVDelwicheCFA hypothesis for plastid evolution in ChromalveolatesJ Phycol2008441097110710.1111/j.1529-8817.2008.00559.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="874" pm="."><plain>15.GreenBRAfter the primary endosymbiosis: an update on the chromalveolate hypothesis and the origins of algae with Chl cPhotosynth Res201110710311510.1007/s11120-010-9584-2<?supplied-pmid 20676772?>20676772 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="875" pm="."><plain>16.BittnerLGobetAAudicSRomacSEggeESSantiniSOgataHProbertIEdvardsenBde VargasCDiversity patterns of uncultured Haptophytes unravelled by pyrosequencing in Naples BayMol Ecol2013228710110.1111/mec.12108<?supplied-pmid 23163508?>23163508 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="876" pm="."><plain>17.EdvardsenBEikremWGreenJCAndersenRder Staay SYM-vMedlinLPhylogenetic reconstructions of the Haptophyta inferred from 18S ribosomal DNA sequences and available morphological dataPhycologia200039193510.2216/i0031-8884-39-1-19.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="877" pm="."><plain>18.MedlinLKSáezAGYoungJRA molecular clock for coccolithophores and implications for selectivity of phytoplankton extinctions across the K/T boundaryMar Micropaleontol200867698610.1016/j.marmicro.2007.08.007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="878" pm="."><plain>19.McDonaldSSarnoDScanlanDZingoneAGenetic diversity of eukaryotic ultraphytoplankton in the Gulf of Naples during an annual cycleAquat Microb Ecol200750758910.3354/ame01148 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="879" pm="."><plain>20.SimonMLópez-GarcíaPMoreiraDJardillierLNew haptophyte lineages and multiple independent colonizations of freshwater ecosystemsEnviron Microbiol Rep2013532233210.1111/1758-2229.12023<?supplied-pmid 23584973?>23584973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="880" pm="."><plain>21.BigelowNBarkerJRykenSPattersonJHardinWBarlowSDeodatoCCattolicoRAChrysochromulina sp.: a proposed lipid standard for the algal biofuel industry and its application to diverse taxa for screening lipid contentAlgal Res2013238539310.1016/j.algal.2013.07.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="881" pm="."><plain>22.MarguliesMEgholmMAltmanWEAttiyaSBaderJSBembenLABerkaJBravermanMSChenY-JChenZDewellSBDuLFierroJMGomesXVGoodwinBCHeWHelgesenSHoCHIrzykGPJandoSCAlenquerMLIJarvieTPJirageKBKimJ-BKnightJRLanzaJRLeamonJHLefkowitzSMLeiMLiJGenome sequencing in open microfabricated high density picoliter reactorsNature2005437376380<?supplied-pmid 16056220?>16056220 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="882" pm="."><plain>23.ZerbinoDRBirneyEVelvet: algorithms for de novo short read assembly using de Bruijn graphsGenome Res20081882182910.1101/gr.074492.107<?supplied-pmid 18349386?>18349386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="883" pm="."><plain>24.Elzanowski A, Ostell J: The genetic codes. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/Utils/wprintgc.cgi?mode=c">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/Utils/wprintgc.cgi?mode=c</ext-link>] </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="884" pm="."><plain>25.PuertaMVSBachvaroffTRDelwicheCFThe complete mitochondrial genome sequence of the haptophyte Emiliania huxleyi and its relation to heterokontsDNA Res20041111010.1093/dnares/11.1.115141941 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="885" pm="."><plain>26.SmithDRKeelingPJTwenty-fold difference in evolutionary rates between the mitochondrial and plastid genomes of species with secondary red plastidsJ Eukaryot Microbiol20125918118410.1111/j.1550-7408.2011.00601.x<?supplied-pmid 22236077?>22236077 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="886" pm="."><plain>27.SmithDRArrigoKRAlderkampA-CAllenAEMassive difference in synonymous substitution rates among mitochondrial, plastid, and nuclear genes of Phaeocystis algaeMol Phylogenet Evol201471364010.1016/j.ympev.2013.10.018<?supplied-pmid 24216019?>24216019 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="887" pm="."><plain>28.DarlingACEMauBBlattnerFRPernaNTMauve: multiple alignment of conserved genomic sequence with rearrangementsGenome Res2004141394140310.1101/gr.2289704<?supplied-pmid 15231754?>15231754 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="888" pm="."><plain>29.Oudot-Le SecqM-PGreenBRComplex repeat structures and novel features in the mitochondrial genomes of the diatoms Phaeodactylum tricornutum and Thalassiosira pseudonanaGene2011476202610.1016/j.gene.2011.02.001<?supplied-pmid 21320580?>21320580 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="889" pm="."><plain>30.KarolKJacobsMAZhouYSimsEGillettWCattolicoRAComparative analysis of complete mitochondrial genome sequences from two geographically distinct Heterosigma akashiwo (Raphidophyceae) strains2008New London, Connecticut, U.S.AProceedings of the Seventh International Chrysophyte Symposium Connecticut College261282 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="890" pm="."><plain>31.Sánchez PuertaMVBachvaroffTRDelwicheCFThe complete plastid genome sequence of the haptophyte Emiliania huxleyi: a comparison to other plastid genomesDNA Res Int J Rapid Publ Rep Genes Genomes200512151156 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="891" pm="."><plain>32.WangLMaoYKongFLiGMaFZhangBSunPBiGZhangFXueHCaoMComplete Sequence and analysis of plastid genomes of two economically important red algae: Pyropia haitanensis and Pyropia yezoensisPLoS One201385e6590210.1371/journal.pone.0065902<?supplied-pmid 23734264?>23734264 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="892" pm="."><plain>33.StarkenburgSRKwonKJJhaRKMcKayCJacobsMChertkovOTwarySRocapGCattolicoRAA pangenomic analysis of the Nannochloropsis organellar genomes reveals novel genetic variations in key metabolic genesBMC Genomics20141521210.1186/1471-2164-15-212<?supplied-pmid 24646409?>24646409 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="893" pm="."><plain>34.CuvelierMLAllenAEMonierAMcCrowJPMessiéMTringeSGWoykeTWelshRMIshoeyTLeeJ-HBinderBJDuPontCLLatasaMGuigandCBuckKRHiltonJThiagarajanMCalerEReadBLaskenRSChavezFPWordenAZTargeted metagenomics and ecology of globally important uncultured eukaryotic phytoplanktonProc Natl Acad Sci U S A2010107146791468410.1073/pnas.1001665107<?supplied-pmid 20668244?>20668244 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="894" pm="."><plain>35.Shalchian-TabriziKReier-RøbergKReeDKKlavenessDBråteJMarine-freshwater colonizations of haptophytes inferred from phylogeny of environmental 18S rDNA sequencesJ Eukaryot Microbiol20115831531810.1111/j.1550-7408.2011.00547.x<?supplied-pmid 21518078?>21518078 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="895" pm="."><plain>36.Oudot-Le SecqM-PGrimwoodJShapiroHArmbrustEVBowlerCGreenBRChloroplast genomes of the diatoms Phaeodactylum tricornutum and Thalassiosira pseudonana: comparison with other plastid genomes of the red lineageMol Genet Genomics MGG200727742743910.1007/s00438-006-0199-4<?supplied-pmid 17252281?>17252281 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="896" pm="."><plain>37.TeslerGGRIMM: genome rearrangements web serverBioinforma Oxf Engl20021849249310.1093/bioinformatics/18.3.492 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="897" pm="."><plain>38.Rocap G, McKay C: The Stramenopile Chloroplast Genomics Project. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="898" pm="."><plain>[<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rocaplab.ocean.washington.edu/tools/cpbase">http://rocaplab.ocean.washington.edu/tools/cpbase</ext-link>] </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="899" pm="."><plain>39.P almerJDThompsonWFChloroplast DNA rearrangements are more frequent when a large inverted repeat sequence is lostCell19822953755010.1016/0092-8674(82)90170-26288261 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="900" pm="."><plain>40.AldrichJCherneyBMerlinEWilliamsCMetsLRecombination within the inverted repeat sequences of the Chlamydomonas reinhardii chloroplast genome produces two orientation isomersCurr Genet1985923323810.1007/BF00420317<?supplied-pmid 24173558?>24173558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="901" pm="."><plain>41.CattolicoRAJacobsMAZhouYChangJDuplessisMLybrandTMcKayJOngHCSimsERocapGChloroplast genome sequencing analysis of Heterosigma akashiwo CCMP452 (West Atlantic) and NIES293 (West Pacific) strainsBMC Genomics2008921110.1186/1471-2164-9-211<?supplied-pmid 18462506?>18462506 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="902" pm="."><plain>42.NewmanSMBoyntonJEGillhamNWRandolph-AndersonBLJohnsonAMHarrisEHTransformation of chloroplast ribosomal rna genes in Chlamydomonas: molecular and genetic characterization of integration eventsGenetics1990126875888<?supplied-pmid 1981764?>1981764 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="903" pm="."><plain>43.HaberleRCFourcadeHMBooreJLJansenRKExtensive rearrangements in the chloroplast genome of Trachelium caeruleum are associated with repeats and tRNA genesJ Mol Evol20086635036110.1007/s00239-008-9086-4<?supplied-pmid 18330485?>18330485 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="904" pm="."><plain>44.CaiZGuisingerMKimH-GRuckEBlazierJCMcMurtryVKuehlJVBooreJJansenRKextensive reorganization of the plastid genome of Trifolium subterraneum (Fabaceae) is associated with numerous repeated sequences and novel DNA insertionsJ Mol Evol20086769670410.1007/s00239-008-9180-7<?supplied-pmid 19018585?>19018585 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="905" pm="."><plain>45.GuisingerMMKuehlJVBooreJLJansenRKExtreme reconfiguration of plastid genomes in the angiosperm family Geraniaceae: rearrangements, repeats, and codon usageMol Biol Evol20112858360010.1093/molbev/msq229<?supplied-pmid 20805190?>20805190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="906" pm="."><plain>46.WickeSSchneeweissGMde PamphilisCWMüllerKFQuandtDThe evolution of the plastid chromosome in land plants: gene content, gene order, gene functionPlant Mol Biol20117627329710.1007/s11103-011-9762-4<?supplied-pmid 21424877?>21424877 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="907" pm="."><plain>47.DelihasNImpact of Small Repeat Sequences on Bacterial Genome EvolutionGenome Biol Evol2011395997310.1093/gbe/evr077<?supplied-pmid 21803768?>21803768 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="908" pm="."><plain>48.EmmanuelDLadoukakisAE-WThe excess of small inverted repeats in prokaryotesJ Mol Evol20086729130010.1007/s00239-008-9151-z18696026 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="909" pm="."><plain>49.PetrilloMSilvestroGNoceraPPDBocciaAPaolellaGStem-loop structures in prokaryotic genomesBMC Genomics2006717010.1186/1471-2164-7-170<?supplied-pmid 16820051?>16820051 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="910" pm="."><plain>50.RottRLevyHDragerRGSternDBSchusterG3’-processed mRNA is preferentially translated in Chlamydomonas reinhardtii chloroplastsMol Cell Biol1998184605461110.1128/MCB.18.8.4605<?supplied-pmid 9671470?>9671470 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="911" pm="."><plain>51.DragerRGZeidlerMSimpsonCLSternDBA chloroplast transcript lacking the 3’ inverted repeat is degraded by 3’-5’ exoribonuclease activityRNA19962652663<?supplied-pmid 8756408?>8756408 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="912" pm="."><plain>52.LevyHKindleKLSternDBTarget and specificity of a nuclear gene product that participates in mRNA 3′-end formation in Chlamydomonas chloroplastsJ Biol Chem1999274359553596210.1074/jbc.274.50.35955<?supplied-pmid 10585484?>10585484 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="913" pm="."><plain>53.AdamsCCSternDBControl of mRNA stability in chloroplasts by 3’ inverted repeats: effects of stem and loop mutations on degradation of psbA mRNA in vitroNucleic Acids Res1990186003601010.1093/nar/18.20.6003<?supplied-pmid 2235482?>2235482 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="914" pm="."><plain>54.MondeRASchusterGSternDBProcessing and degradation of chloroplast mRNABiochimie20008257358210.1016/S0300-9084(00)00606-4<?supplied-pmid 10946108?>10946108 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="915" pm="."><plain>55.AdamsKLPalmerJDEvolution of mitochondrial gene content: gene loss and transfer to the nucleusMol Phylogenet Evol20032938039510.1016/S1055-7903(03)00194-5<?supplied-pmid 14615181?>14615181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="916" pm="."><plain>56.WarnerJRMcIntoshKBHow common are extraribosomal functions of ribosomal proteins?Mol Cell20093431110.1016/j.molcel.2009.03.006<?supplied-pmid 19362532?>19362532 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="917" pm="."><plain>57.RiceDWPalmerJDAn exceptional horizontal gene transfer in plastids: gene replacement by a distant bacterial paralog and evidence that haptophyte and cryptophyte plastids are sistersBMC Biol200643110.1186/1741-7007-4-31<?supplied-pmid 16956407?>16956407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="918" pm="."><plain>58.BanNNissenPHansenJMoorePBSteitzTAThe complete atomic structure of the large ribosomal subunit at 2.4 A resolutionScience200028990592010.1126/science.289.5481.905<?supplied-pmid 10937989?>10937989 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="919" pm="."><plain>59.PaninaEMMironovAAGelfandMSComparative genomics of bacterial zinc regulons: enhanced ion transport, pathogenesis, and rearrangement of ribosomal proteinsProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20031009912991710.1073/pnas.1733691100<?supplied-pmid 12904577?>12904577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="920" pm="."><plain>60.OwenGAPascoeBKallifidasDPagetMSBZinc-responsive regulation of alternative ribosomal protein genes in Streptomyces coelicolor involves zur and σRJ Bacteriol20071894078408610.1128/JB.01901-06<?supplied-pmid 17400736?>17400736 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="921" pm="."><plain>61.BoysenRIHearnMTThe metal binding properties of the CCCH motif of the 50S ribosomal protein L36 from Thermus thermophilusJ Pept Res Off J Am Pept Soc200157192810.1034/j.1399-3011.2001.00752.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="922" pm="."><plain>62.MatthewsJMSundeMZinc fingers–folds for many occasionsIUBMB Life20025435135510.1080/15216540216035<?supplied-pmid 12665246?>12665246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="923" pm="."><plain>63.ChenKRobertsELuthey-SchultenZHorizontal gene transfer of zinc and non-zinc forms of bacterial ribosomal protein S4BMC Evol Biol2009917910.1186/1471-2148-9-179<?supplied-pmid 19640295?>19640295 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="924" pm="."><plain>64.BurdachJO’ConnellMRMackayJPCrossleyMTwo-timing zinc finger transcription factors liaising with RNATrends Biochem Sci20123719920510.1016/j.tibs.2012.02.001<?supplied-pmid 22405571?>22405571 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="925" pm="."><plain>65.StockAMRobinsonVLGoudreauPNTwo-component signal transductionAnnu Rev Biochem20006918321510.1146/annurev.biochem.69.1.183<?supplied-pmid 10966457?>10966457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="926" pm="."><plain>66.MascherTHelmannJDUndenGStimulus perception in bacterial signal-transducing histidine KinasesMicrobiol Mol Biol Rev20067091093810.1128/MMBR.00020-06<?supplied-pmid 17158704?>17158704 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="927" pm="."><plain>67.JacobsMAConnellLCattolicoRAA conserved His-Asp signal response regulator-like gene in Heterosigma akashiwo chloroplastsPlant Mol Biol19994164565510.1023/A:1006394925182<?supplied-pmid 10645724?>10645724 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="928" pm="."><plain>68.AshbyMKDistribution, structure and diversity of “bacterial” genes encoding two-component proteins in the EuryarchaeotaArchaea Vanc BC20062113010.1155/2006/562404 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="929" pm="."><plain>69.SödingJBiegertALupasANThe HHpred interactive server for protein homology detection and structure predictionNucleic Acids Res200533Web Server issueW244W24810.1093/nar/gki408<?supplied-pmid 15980461?>15980461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="930" pm="."><plain>70.BermanHMWestbrookJFengZGillilandGBhatTNWeissigHShindyalovINBournePEThe protein data bankNucleic Acids Res20002823524210.1093/nar/28.1.235<?supplied-pmid 10592235?>10592235 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="931" pm="."><plain>71.PuntaMCoggillPCEberhardtRYMistryJTateJBoursnellCPangNForslundKCericGClementsJHegerAHolmLSonnhammerELLEddySRBatemanAFinnRDThe Pfam protein families databaseNucleic Acids Res201240D290D30110.1093/nar/gkr1065<?supplied-pmid 22127870?>22127870 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="932" pm="."><plain>72.RamanSVernonRThompsonJTykaMSadreyevRPeiJKimDKelloggEDiMaioFLangeOKinchLShefflerWKimB-HDasRGrishinNVBakerDStructure prediction for CASP8 with all-atom refinement using RosettaProteins200977Suppl 9899910.1002/prot.22540<?supplied-pmid 19701941?>19701941 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="933" pm="."><plain>73.RanLLarssonJVigil-StenmanTNylanderJAAIninbergsKZhengW-WLapidusALowrySHaselkornRBergmanBGenome erosion in a nitrogen-fixing vertically transmitted endosymbiotic multicellular cyanobacteriumPLoS One201057e1148610.1371/journal.pone.0011486<?supplied-pmid 20628610?>20628610 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="934" pm="."><plain>74.AndrianopoulosAKourambasSSharpJADavisMAHynesMJCharacterization of the Aspergillus nidulans nmrA gene involved in nitrogen metabolite repressionJ Bacteriol199818019731977<?supplied-pmid 9537404?>9537404 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="935" pm="."><plain>75.Dunn-ColemanNSTomsettABGarrettRHNitrogen metabolite repression of nitrate reductase in Neurospora crassa: effect of the gln-1a locusJ Bacteriol1979139697700<?supplied-pmid 37243?>37243 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="936" pm="."><plain>76.LambHKLeslieKDoddsALNutleyMCooperAJohnsonCThompsonPStammersDKHawkinsARThe negative transcriptional regulator nmrA discriminates between oxidized and reduced dinucleotidesJ Biol Chem2003278321073211410.1074/jbc.M304104200<?supplied-pmid 12764138?>12764138 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="937" pm="."><plain>77.JarvisPSollJToc, tic, and chloroplast protein importBiochim Biophys Acta2002159017718910.1016/S0167-4889(02)00176-3<?supplied-pmid 12180471?>12180471 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="938" pm="."><plain>78.HörmannFSollJBölterBThe chloroplast protein import machinery: a reviewMethods Mol Biol Clifton NJ200739017919310.1007/978-1-59745-466-7_12 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR79"><text><SENT sid="939" pm="."><plain>79.McFaddenGIPlastids and protein targetingJ Eukaryot Microbiol19994633934610.1111/j.1550-7408.1999.tb04613.x<?supplied-pmid 10461382?>10461382 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR80"><text><SENT sid="940" pm="."><plain>80.McFaddenGIPrimary and secondary endosymbiosis and the origin of plastidsJ Phycol20013795195910.1046/j.1529-8817.2001.01126.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR81"><text><SENT sid="941" pm="."><plain>81.ChaalBKGreenBRProtein import pathways in “complex” chloroplasts derived from secondary endosymbiosis involving a red algal ancestorPlant Mol Biol20055733334210.1007/s11103-004-7848-y<?supplied-pmid 15830125?>15830125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR82"><text><SENT sid="942" pm="."><plain>82.HirakawaYBurkiFKeelingPJGenome-based reconstruction of the protein import machinery in the secondary plastid of a chlorarachniophyte algaEukaryot Cell20121132433310.1128/EC.05264-11<?supplied-pmid 22267775?>22267775 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR83"><text><SENT sid="943" pm="."><plain>83.StorkSLauJMoogDMaierU-GThree old and one new: protein import into red algal-derived plastids surrounded by four membranesProtoplasma20132501013102310.1007/s00709-013-0498-7<?supplied-pmid 23612938?>23612938 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR84"><text><SENT sid="944" pm="."><plain>84.KalanonMMcFaddenGIThe chloroplast protein translocation complexes of Chlamydomonas reinhardtii: a bioinformatic comparison of toc and tic components in plants, green algae and red algaeGenetics20081799511210.1534/genetics.107.085704<?supplied-pmid 18493043?>18493043 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR85"><text><SENT sid="945" pm="."><plain>85.BennettSSolexa LtdPharmacogenomics2004543343810.1517/14622416.5.4.433<?supplied-pmid 15165179?>15165179 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR86"><text><SENT sid="946" pm="."><plain>86.ZhangZSchwartzSWagnerLMillerWA greedy algorithm for aligning DNA sequencesJ Comput Biol J Comput Mol Cell Biol2000720321410.1089/10665270050081478 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR87"><text><SENT sid="947" pm="."><plain>87.HanCSChainPFinishing Repetitive Regions Automatically with DupfinisherProceedings of the 2006 International Conference on Bioinformatics &amp; Computational Biology, BIOCOMP'062006Las Vegas, Nevada, USACSREA Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR88"><text><SENT sid="948" pm="."><plain>88.LiHDurbinRFast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transformBioinforma Oxf Engl2009251754176010.1093/bioinformatics/btp324 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR89"><text><SENT sid="949" pm="."><plain>89.MilneIStephenGBayerMCockPJAPritchardLCardleLShawPDMarshallDUsing Tablet for visual exploration of second-generation sequencing dataBrief Bioinform20131419320210.1093/bib/bbs012<?supplied-pmid 22445902?>22445902 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR90"><text><SENT sid="950" pm="."><plain>90.DelcherALHarmonDKasifSWhiteOSalzbergSLImproved microbial gene identification with GLIMMERNucleic Acids Res1999274636464110.1093/nar/27.23.4636<?supplied-pmid 10556321?>10556321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR91"><text><SENT sid="951" pm="."><plain>91.ConantGCWolfeKHGenomeVx: simple web-based creation of editable circular chromosome mapsBioinforma Oxf Engl20082486186210.1093/bioinformatics/btm598 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR92"><text><SENT sid="952" pm="."><plain>92.RicePLongdenIBleasbyAEMBOSS: the European molecular biology open software suiteTrends Genet TIG20001627627710.1016/S0168-9525(00)02024-2<?supplied-pmid 10827456?>10827456 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR93"><text><SENT sid="953" pm="."><plain>93.BensonGTandem repeats finder: a program to analyze DNA sequencesNucleic Acids Res19992757358010.1093/nar/27.2.573<?supplied-pmid 9862982?>9862982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR94"><text><SENT sid="954" pm="."><plain>94.ZukerMMfold web server for nucleic acid folding and hybridization predictionNucleic Acids Res2003313406341510.1093/nar/gkg595<?supplied-pmid 12824337?>12824337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR95"><text><SENT sid="955" pm="."><plain>95.ZukerMJacobsonABUsing reliability information to annotate RNA secondary structuresRNA1998466967910.1017/S1355838298980116<?supplied-pmid 9622126?>9622126 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR96"><text><SENT sid="956" pm="."><plain>96.WaughAGendronPAltmanRBrownJWCaseDGautheretDHarveySCLeontisNWestbrookJWesthofEZukerMMajorFRNAML: a standard syntax for exchanging RNA informationRNA N Y N2002870771710.1017/S1355838202028017 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR97"><text><SENT sid="957" pm="."><plain>97.EdgarRCMUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughputNucleic Acids Res2004321792179710.1093/nar/gkh340<?supplied-pmid 15034147?>15034147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR98"><text><SENT sid="958" pm="."><plain>98.Moret B, Warnow T: Cyberinfrastructure for Phylogenetic Research (CIPRES) Project. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="959" pm="."><plain>[<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phylo.org/">http://www.phylo.org/</ext-link>] </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR99"><text><SENT sid="960" pm="."><plain>99.AbascalFZardoyaRPosadaDProtTest: selection of best-fit models of protein evolutionBioinforma Oxf Engl2005212104210510.1093/bioinformatics/bti263 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR100"><text><SENT sid="961" pm="."><plain>100.StamatakisARAxML-VI-HPC: maximum likelihood-based phylogenetic analyses with thousands of taxa and mixed modelsBioinformatics2006222688269010.1093/bioinformatics/btl446<?supplied-pmid 16928733?>16928733 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR101"><text><SENT sid="962" pm="."><plain>101.RonquistFHuelsenbeckJPMrBayes 3: Bayesian phylogenetic inference under mixed modelsBioinformatics2003191572157410.1093/bioinformatics/btg180<?supplied-pmid 12912839?>12912839 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR102"><text><SENT sid="963" pm="."><plain>102.DrummondAJSuchardMAXieDRambautABayesian phylogenetics with BEAUti and the BEAST 1.7Mol Biol Evol2012291969197310.1093/molbev/mss075<?supplied-pmid 22367748?>22367748 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR103"><text><SENT sid="964" pm="."><plain>103.JonesDTProtein secondary structure prediction based on position-specific scoring matricesJ Mol Biol199929219520210.1006/jmbi.1999.3091<?supplied-pmid 10493868?>10493868 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR104"><text><SENT sid="965" pm="."><plain>104.KimDEChivianDBakerDProtein structure prediction and analysis using the Robetta serverNucleic Acids Res200432Web Server issueW526W53110.1093/nar/gkh468<?supplied-pmid 15215442?>15215442 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR105"><text><SENT sid="966" pm="."><plain>105.HanwellMDCurtisDELonieDCVandermeerschTZurekEHutchisonGRAvogadro: an advanced semantic chemical editor, visualization, and analysis platformJ Cheminformatics201241710.1186/1758-2946-4-17 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR106"><text><SENT sid="967" pm="."><plain>106.BoltonEEWangYThiessenPABryantSHWheelerRASpellmeyerDCChapter 12 PubChem: integrated platform of small molecules and biological activitiesAnnu Rep Comput Chem, Volume 42008Oxford, UKElsevier217241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR107"><text><SENT sid="968" pm="."><plain>107.RohlCAStraussCEMMisuraKMSBakerDProtein structure prediction using RosettaMethods Enzymol2004383669310.1016/S0076-6879(04)83004-0<?supplied-pmid 15063647?>15063647 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR108"><text><SENT sid="969" pm="."><plain>108.DavisIWBakerDRosettaLigand docking with full ligand and receptor flexibilityJ Mol Biol200938538139210.1016/j.jmb.2008.11.010<?supplied-pmid 19041878?>19041878 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR109"><text><SENT sid="970" pm="."><plain>109.MeilerJBakerDROSETTALIGAND: protein-small molecule docking with full side-chain flexibilityProteins20066553854810.1002/prot.21086<?supplied-pmid 16972285?>16972285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
