<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Microbiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-302X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5660696</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.01995</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>A Nanoscale Study of Carbon and Nitrogen Fluxes in Mats of Purple Sulfur Bacteria: Implications for Carbon Cycling at the Surface of Coastal Sediments </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hubas</surname><given-names>Cédric</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/138286/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Boeuf</surname><given-names>Dominique</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>†</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/353382/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jesus</surname><given-names>Bruno</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/469174/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thiney</surname><given-names>Najet</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bozec</surname><given-names>Yann</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jeanthon</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/190513/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle, UMR BOREA, MNHN-CNRS-UCN-UPMC-IRD-UA, Station de Biologie Marine de Concarneau</institution>, <addr-line>Concarneau</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>CNRS, Station Biologique de Roscoff, Adaptation et Diversité en Milieu Marin</institution>, <addr-line>Roscoff</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Sorbonne Universités, UPMC Univ Paris 06, UMR 7144, Station Biologique de Roscoff, Adaptation et Diversité en Milieu Marin</institution>, <addr-line>Roscoff</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>EA2160, Laboratoire Mer Molécules Santé, Université de Nantes</institution>, <addr-line>Nantes</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>BioISI – Biosystems &amp; Integrative Sciences Institute, Campo Grande University of Lisbon, Faculty of Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Lisbon</addr-line>, <country>Portugal</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup><institution>Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle, UMR BOREA, MNHN-CNRS-UCN-UPMC-IRD-UA, Bâtiment Arthropodes</institution>, <addr-line>Paris</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Edited by: Télesphore Sime-Ngando, Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (CNRS), France </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Reviewed by: Steven Singer, Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, United States; Trinity L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Hamilton, University of Minnesota Twin Cities, United States </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: <italic>Cédric Hubas, <email xlink:type="simple">cedric.hubas@mnhn.fr</email></italic></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>†Present address: Dominique Boeuf, Daniel K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Inouye Center for Microbial Oceanography Research and Education, University of Hawai’i at Mânoa, Honolulu, HI, United States </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn003"><p><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>This article was submitted to Aquatic Microbiology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Microbiology </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>1995</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2017 Hubas, Boeuf, Jesus, Thiney, Bozec and Jeanthon.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Hubas, Boeuf, Jesus, Thiney, Bozec and Jeanthon</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Mass blooms of purple sulfur bacteria growing seasonally on green stranded macroalgae have a major impact on the microbial composition and functionality of intertidal mats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>To explore the active anoxygenic phototrophic community in purple bacterial mats from the Roscoff Aber Bay (Brittany, France), we conducted a combined approach including molecular and high-resolution secondary ion mass spectrometry (NanoSIMS) analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>To investigate the dynamics of carbon and nitrogen assimilation activities, NanoSIMS was coupled with a stable isotope probing (SIP) experiment and a compound specific isotope analysis (CSIA) of fatty acid methyl ester (FAME). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Sediment samples were incubated with 13C- and/or 15N-labeled acetate, pyruvate, bicarbonate and ammonium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>NanoSIMS analysis of 13C - and 15N -incubated samples showed elevated incorporations of 13C - and 15N in the light and of 13C -acetate in the dark into dense populations of spherical cells that unambiguously dominated the mats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>These results confirmed CSIA data that ranked vaccenic acid, an unambiguous marker of purple sulfur bacteria, as the most strongly enriched in the light after 13C -acetate amendment and indicated that acetate uptake, the most active in the mat, was not light-dependent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Analysis of DNA- and cDNA-derived pufM gene sequences revealed that Thiohalocapsa-related clones dominated both libraries and were the most photosynthetically active members of the mat samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>This study provides novel insights into the contribution of purple sulfur bacteria to the carbon cycle during their seasonal developments at the sediment surface in the intertidal zone. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>microbial mats</kwd><kwd><italic>Chromatiaceae</italic></kwd><kwd>Thiohalocapsa</kwd><kwd>stable isotope probing (SIP)</kwd><kwd>NanoSIMS</kwd><kwd>compound specific isotope analysis (CSIA)</kwd><kwd>fatty acid methyl ester (FAME)</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><counts><fig-count count="7"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="3"/><ref-count count="65"/><page-count count="14"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Microbial mats are complex small-scale self-sustaining benthic ecosystems (Stal, 1985) often built by cyanobacteria whose primary production enrich the sediment with organic matter that becomes available to different functional groups of microorganisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>In such ecosystems, the surface sediment layer (a few millimeters thick) is a transition zone between oxic and anoxic conditions that favor the development of stratified and cohesive layers of diverse assemblages of oxygenic and anoxygenic phototrophic microorganisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Mass blooms of anoxygenic phototrophic bacteria, forming large colored mats, can occur at the sediment surface in the intertidal zone (Imhoff, 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>On the Orkney islands (Wieland et al., 2003) and Roscoff Aber Bay (Hubas et al., 2013), blooms dominated by purple sulfur bacteria typically occur on sandy sediments locally enriched in organic matter derived from the decomposition of macroalgal deposits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>In their habitats, such as enclosed lagoons, estuaries, and salt marshes, purple sulfur bacteria have to cope with occasionally occurring drastic changes of salinity, temperature, and light conditions (Caumette, 1993; Caumette et al., 1994; Imhoff, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>This situation occurs in Roscoff Aber Bay, a temperate intertidal bay, where muddy-sandy sediments are extensively covered by stranded Enteromorpha sp. and mats of purple sulfur bacteria during warm summer months (Hubas et al., 2006b, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In a preliminary study (Hubas et al., 2013), we reported that these mats were dominated by Chromatiaceae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>These purple sulfur gammaproteobacteria are all capable of photolithoautotrophic growth under anoxic conditions with sulfide and elemental sulfur as electron donors and are potentially mixotrophic and photoassimilate simple organic compounds, of which acetate and pyruvate are the most widely used (Imhoff, 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>We previously assessed the biochemical composition (fatty acids, photosynthetic pigments) of the microbial mats and their influence on ecosystem functions (sediment cohesiveness, CO2 fixation) at low tide in Roscoff Aber Bay and demonstrated that the proliferation of these purple sulfur bacteria have a major impact on the diversity and functionality of intertidal mats (Hubas et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Particularly, their massive growth resulted in a dramatic increase of both gross CO2 fixation as well as total mat respiration in comparison to diatom-dominated mats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>However, despite the increase of total CO2 fixation, purple sulfur bacterial mats presented a net CO2 degassing whereas diatom-dominated mats represented a net CO2 sink. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>We suggested that photosynthetic efficiency was probably hampered in these mats and that macroalgal-derived organic matter favored the photoheterotrophic lifestyle of purple sulfur bacteria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Nanoscale secondary ion mass spectrometry (NanoSIMS) is a powerful technique capable of imaging elemental distributions and measuring metabolic activities of a single-cell level in mixed populations, including within biofilms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Combining NanoSIMS with stable isotope enriched incubations has been used recently to study the cycling and flux of carbon, sulfur and nitrogen in phototrophic microbial mats from several environments (Fike et al., 2008; Burow et al., 2012; Woebken et al., 2012, 2015; Lee et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>To better understand the structure and the development of phototrophic purple sulfur bacteria assemblages at the surface of intertidal sediment and their influence on important ecosystem functions and services, we sampled undisturbed cores of these mats and performed a stable isotope probing (SIP) experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In this study, our aims were (1) to identify the dominant and active members of the mats, (2) to elucidate preferred carbon sources taken up by the mat members and (3) to estimate organic and inorganic carbon and nitrogen uptake rates at the sub-micrometric scale by combining compound specific isotope analysis (CSIA) of fatty acid methyl ester (FAME) and NanoSIMS analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Sampling Site </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Sediment cores and microbial mats were collected at mid day in August 2010 at low tide in the Roscoff Aber Bay (Brittany, France; 48°42′59.836 N, 3°59′51.611 W). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The bay is about 1 km long and 2 km wide, entirely situated above mid-tide level, and its annual benthic metabolism has been extensively studied in the past (Hubas and Davoult, 2006; Hubas et al., 2006b, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Particularly sheltered, the bay is dominated by sandy-muddy sediments, with local freshwater inputs from the river located at the landward end of the bay and with freshwater seepages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The bay is affected by the seasonal proliferation of green macroalgae that affect both the trophic ecology (Riera and Hubas, 2003) and C fluxes of the ecosystem (Hubas and Davoult, 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The selected mats were established at the surface of fine-sand intertidal sediments (mean particle size: 215 ± 43 μm, Hubas et al., 2006b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Oxic layers were absent or very thin (&lt;1 mm thick) below these mats. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Incubation Experiments with Stable Isotopes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Core incubations were first carried out to follow substrate incorporation in microbial fatty acids over time using specific isotope analysis of fatty acid methyl ester (CSIA-FAME). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Undisturbed microbial mats were isolated at mid day from surrounding sediment using sterile polycarbonate cut-off syringes (10 mm diameter) pushed down to about 3 cm depth (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Three cores used to determine baseline conditions (control) were immediately removed from the sediment; the first two millimeters were sampled and immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The remaining cores were used for 3 different triplicate incubations designated AceL, PyrL, CO3L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Incubation designations referred to the labeled substrate added and to the light condition: “Ace” for [1-13C] sodium acetate-1- (99 atom %), “Pyr” for [2-13C] sodium pyruvate (99 atom %) and “CO3” for 13C sodium bicarbonate (99 atom %), “L” for incubations at ambient light. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>A constant volume (1.9 ml) of the 13C labeled substrate solutions (final concentration of 500 μM, prepared with seawater freshly collected from the study site) was gently added on top of the mat cores and incubated in situ at ambient light (&gt;1000 μmol photons m-2 s-1) and temperature (22–23°C) for 2 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>At the end of the incubation period, cores were removed from the sediment, the first two millimeters sampled and immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>General aspect of various types of purple sulfur bacterial mats of the Roscoff Bay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Emersed (a,b) or immerged (c) biofilms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Adapted from Hubas et al. (2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-08-01995-g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Core incubations were also carried out to examine the assimilation of labeled substrates at single cell level by NanoSIMS analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Several underwater purple sulfur bacterial mats were sampled as described above, homogenized and brought back to laboratory shortly after collection under controlled conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Briefly, the homogenized microbial mats were used for 7 different triplicate incubations designated control, AceL, AceD, PyrL, PyrD, CO3L, and CO3D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Incubation designations were as above and “D” referred to incubations in the dark. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The 13C labeled substrate solutions were prepared as above and incubations were performed at ambient light (&gt;1000 μmol photons m-2 s-1) or in the dark at controlled temperature (19°C) for 5 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Cores samples were incubated with 13C-labeled bicarbonate, 13C-labeled acetate and 13C -labeled pyruvate In addition, to estimate nitrogen uptake, 15N-labeled ammonium chloride (98 atom %; final concentration of 100 μM) was added to all incubations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The final atomic ratios (bicarbonate: 28.1, acetate: 33.5, pyruvate: 86.9% atom percent 13C, ammonium: 74.5% atom percent 15N) were calculated taking into account the natural concentrations of the corresponding substrate previously measured in discrete seawater samples collected before mat collection (bicarbonate, ammonium) or concentration ranges (acetate, pyruvate) used in similar studies (Morono et al., 2011; Tourna et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>After incubation, purple sulfur bacterial mats were fixed with 2% paraformaldehyde for 1 h, filtered on gold-coated polycarbonate (GTTP type; pore size 0.22 μm, diameter 25 mm, Millipore), and washed with filter-sterilized seawater to remove labeled substrates in excess. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The filters were further stored at -20°C until processing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Fatty Acid Composition </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Fatty acids (FAs) were extracted following the method of Bligh and Dyer (Bligh and Dyer, 1959) slightly modified by Meziane et al. (2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Total lipids were extracted by sonication (35 kHz, 20 min) using a chloroform/methanol/water cocktail (2:1:1, v:v:v), concentrated under a constant N2 flow, and the residue hydrolyzed (90 min, 90°C) with NaOH:MeOH (1:2, v:v). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>An internal standard (tricosanoic acid: 23:0, 10 μg) was added to each sample before extraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Hydrolysis (i.e., saponification) aimed to release individual FAs from more complex molecules, such as triglycerides or phospholipids, by breaking the ester bonds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Individual FAs were then derivatized into fatty acids methyl esters (FAMEs) by the addition of one methyl (CH3) group (i.e., methylation procedure) so that they can be separated and quantified by gas chromatography. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Methylation was performed by incubating individual FAs with boron-trifluoride methanol (BF3-MeOH) at 90°C for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Sample were then dried under N2 flux and transferred to hexane for injection in a gas chromatograph (GC, Varian CP-3800 equipped with flame ionization detector - FID). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Most FAMEs were identified by comparing their retention times with those of known standards (SupelcoTM 37, PUFA-1 Marine Source, and Bacterial Mix; Supelco Inc., Bellefonte, PA, United States). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Unidentified FAMEs were further identified by GC coupled to a mass spectrometer (GC-MS, Varian GC450-220MS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>For both devices, FAMEs separation was performed using a Supelco OMEGAWAX 320 column (30 m × 0.32 mm i.d., 0.25 μm film thickness) with H2 as carrier gas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>After injection of 1 μl of sample at 60°C, the temperature was raised to 150°C at 40°C min-1, then to 240°C (held 14 min) at 3°C min-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>FAMEs were systematically corrected for the added methyl group and corresponding individual FAs are designated in this study as CX:Y-nZ, where X is the number of carbons, Y the number of double bonds and Z the position of the ultimate double bond from the terminal methyl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Cyclopropane FAMEs were detected and noted 9-10diMe C16 and 9-10diMe C18 for Methyl cis-9,10-methylene hexa- and octa-decanoate, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Compound Specific Isotope Analysis (CSIA) of Fatty Acid Methyl Ester (FAME) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>After GC and GC-MS analyses, isotope ratio gas-chromatograph-mass spectrometry (GC-IRMS) was used to measure the carbon stable isotope ratios (expressed in ‰) of individual fatty acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Measurements were performed at the UC Davis Stable Isotope Facility of the University of California (Davis, CA, United States). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>FAMEs dissolved in hexane are injected in splitless mode and separated on a Varian factorFOUR VF-5ms column (30 m × 0.25 mm ID, 0.25 micron film thickness). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Once separated, FAMEs are quantitatively converted to CO2 in an oxidation reactor at 950°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Following water removal through a nafion dryer, CO2 enters the IRMS. δ13values were corrected using working standards composed of several FAMEs calibrated against NIST standard reference materials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Stable carbon isotope ratios for individual fatty acids (FA) were calculated from FAME data by correcting for the one carbon atom in the methyl group that was added during the derivatization process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>This correction was made according to Gladyshev et al. (2012) by taking into account the isotope ratio of the derivatized methanol (BF3-methanol, -37.9 ‰ in our study), and the fractional carbon contribution of the free fatty acid to the ester. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>13</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>13</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>13</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>where δ13CFA is the isotopic composition of the free fatty acids, δ13CFAME is the isotopic composition of the fatty acid methyl ester, f is the fractional carbon contribution of the free fatty acid to the ester and δ13CCH3OH is the isotopic composition of the methanol derivatization reagent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>For instance, in the case of a C16 FA, f would be equal to 16/17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The isotopic composition of the methanol was determined by the same GC-IRMS system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Molecular Identification of the Mat-Forming Purple Bacteria Using 16S rRNA and pufM Genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Biomass from three microbial mats was collected close to where the cores were sampled using sterile plastic syringes and transferred in Eppendorf tubes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Samples were immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and further stored at -80°C until analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>For DNA extraction, cells were thawed and suspended in DNA lysis buffer (0.75 M sucrose, 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8) and processed using the procedure described by Marie et al. (2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was extracted using the RNeasy Mini kit (Qiagen) following the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Any trace of genomic DNA was removed using a Turbo DNA-free kit (Ambion). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>DNA removal in RNA samples was confirmed by control PCR amplifications without the reverse transcription step. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>No amplification was detected in these controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>ThermoScript RT-PCR system (Invitrogen) was used for the reverse transcription of mRNA from total RNA samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The cDNA synthesis was performed at 50°C using random primers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Small-subunit (16S) rRNA genes were amplified by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using universal reverse primer 1492R and Bacteria-specific forward primer 8F (Weisburg et al., 1991). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>PCR amplification of pufM genes was performed using the primers 557F and 750R designed by Achenbach et al. (2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Reaction mixture (25 μL) contained the following components: 5X buffer (10 μl), 2 mM MgCl2, 10 pmoles of each deoxyribonucleotide triphosphate (dATP, dCTP, dGTP, dTTP; Eurogentec), 10 pmoles of each oligonucleotide primer, 2.5 U of GoTaq Flexi DNA polymerase (Promega) and 50 to 100 ng of template DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Amplifications were carried out in a GeneAmp PCR system 9700 (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, United States) with the following parameters: 95°C for 5 min, followed by 35 cycles of 95°C for 30 s, annealing at 55°C, respectively, and extension at 72°C for 60 s and 30 s for 16S rRNA and pufM gene amplification, respectively, with a final extension step at 72°C for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Amplicons were cloned directly or after gel extraction using the TOPO4-TA cloning kit (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Clones were sequenced using an ABI 3130 POP7 sequencer (Applied Biosystems) at the Biogenouest Sequencing-Genotyping Platform (Roscoff site). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The sequences were trimmed to remove any vector and primer sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Chimeras were removed using Uchime (v4.2.40; Edgar et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Gene sequences were compared to sequences in public databases with BLASTn (Altschul et al., 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The 16S rRNA gene sequences were aligned the SILVA SSUref N99 references (v.128) using ARB aligner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The pufM DNA sequences were translated into amino acid sequences and aligned using the MAFFT E-INS-I algorithm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The resulting protein alignment was back-translated to nucleotide acid sequences using pal2nal (Suyama et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Conservative values of 97% and 94% nucleic acid sequence similarity for 16S rRNA and pufM sequences, respectively, were chosen for clustering sequences into Operational Taxonomic Units (OTUs) using MOTHUR (Schloss et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Representative sequences (defined as the sequence with the minimum distance to all other sequences in the OTU) were obtained using MOTHUR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>A pufM database and a consensus Bayesian tree were built as described in Boeuf et al. (2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Representative sequences of each OTU (245 pb) and short pufM environmental reference sequences were aligned as above and added to the backbone tree using the ADD_BY_PARSIMONY algorithm implemented in ARB software (Ludwig et al., 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Likewise, representative ssu sequences of each OTU (927 pb) were added to the SILVA reference tree using ARB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Non-informative taxa were removed from both final tree. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>NanoSIMS Image Acquisition </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Secondary ion images of 12C-, 13C-, 12C14N-, 12C15N-, and 32S- were recorded simultaneously for each individual cell using the Cameca NanoSIMS N50 at the Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle (Paris, France). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>All measurements were performed using the same analytical conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Firstly, a 30 × 30 μm image field was chosen and the filters were pre-sputtered during 4 min with a 18.8 pA Cs- primary ion beam that was stepped over the sample in a 256 × 256 pixel raster with a counting time of 1 ms per pixel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Then image acquisition was made by rescanning 25–30 times a 25 × 25 μm image field sputtered with a 0.5 pA Cs- beam in a 256 × 256 pixel raster with a counting time of 1 ms per pixel. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>NanoSIMS Data Processing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>NanoSIMS data were then processed using the proprietary WinImage Software (L’image, CAMECA SIMS Image Processing). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Purple sulfur bacteria were detected based on their typical coccoïd shape from the 12C14N- images and each bacterial cell was defined as a region of interest (ROIs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>ROIs data were exported as.csv files and processed using the R© statistical framework to calculate carbon and nitrogen stable isotope ratios as well as atom percent of 13C and 15N. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ini</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>measured</mml:mtext><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ini</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>final</mml:mtext><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>where ri is a dimensionless ratio for incubation experiment i, Rini is the initial isotopic ratio of the bacteria (based on the mean of natural isotopic composition of the control), Rmeasured.i is the measured isotopic ratio (NanoSIMS) of a given bacterial cell for incubation experiment i, Rfinal.i is the theoretical isotopic ratio of a given bacterial cell based on the isotopic composition of the substrate used during the incubation experiment. Rfinal.i was calculated by taking into account the isotopic ratio of the substrate at its final concentration in the sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>It is assumed that no isotopic fractionation would occur during substrate assimilation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>All isotopic ratios (R) are in atom %. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Substrate incorporation was calculated as follows: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>bac</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>where Fi is the quantity of substrate incorporated by a bacterial cell per hour (moles.cell-1. h-1), Ci is the final concentration of substrate i (in moles.L-1), Vbac (in L) is the mean cell volume (estimated to 2.4 μm3, mean diameter = 1.67 μm), ri is the dimensionless ratio for incubation experiment i (see Equation 2), t is the incubation time in h. Fi was then converted to carbon and nitrogen weight units (fg C.cell-1. h-1 and fg N.cell-1. h-1) assuming a molar mass of 12 and 14 g.mol-1 for carbon and nitrogen, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>All analyses and graphs were performed using the R© statistical framework. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Normality was checked to perform one sample t-tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>When normality and/or homogeneity of variance assumption were not met, Van der Waerden tests were performed, which convert the ranks of a non-parametric Kruskal–Wallis rank sum test into quantiles of the standard normal distribution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) was performed to compare the regression slopes between carbon and nitrogen isotopic ratios. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>This analysis was used to test the effect of a categorical factor (i.e., treatment) on a dependent variable (i.e., N isotopic ratio) while controlling for the effect of a continuous co-variable (i.e., C isotopic ratio). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide Accession Numbers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>16S rRNA gene and transcript sequences obtained in this study are deposited under GenBank accession numbers <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MF320555">MF320555</ext-link> to <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MF320732">MF320732</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Sequences of pufM genes and transcripts are deposited under GenBank accession numbers <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KX352089">KX352089</ext-link> to <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KX352145">KX352145</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KX358536">KX358536</ext-link> to <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KX358562">KX358562</ext-link>, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Fatty Acid Composition </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The mats were characterized by several bacterial markers such as branched FAs (i.e., iso and anteiso FAs), two cyclopropane FAs, as well as the vaccenic fatty acid (C18:1n-7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>C16:1n-7, C18:1n-7, C16:0 and C14:0 prevailed in the mats and their concentrations varied greatly between treatments (Figure 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>However, their proportions in the six treatments did not vary significantly from the control (one sample t-test, p &gt; 0.05) (Figure 2B), indicating that treatments did not affect FA composition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Fatty acid composition of the purple sulfur bacterial mats in terms of quantity (A) and percentages (B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-08-01995-g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Compound Specific Isotope Analysis (CSIA) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Sediment cores with dense purple sulfur bacterial mats were incubated at ambient light and temperature with 13C- and/or 15N-labeled acetate, pyruvate, bicarbonate and ammonium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Main cellular fatty acids of purple sulfur bacteria (Núñez-cardona, 2012) such as C18:1n-7, C16:1n-7 and C16:0 were detected by GC-IRMS and their isotopic compositions measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>According to Van der Waerden tests, fatty acids were systematically significantly enriched compared to the control (natural FA isotopic composition), when acetate and bicarbonate were used as growth substrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Vaccenic acid (C18:1n-7), an unambiguous marker of purple sulfur bacteria was the most strongly enriched after 13C-acetate amendment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Although they were also significant, 13C enrichments with 13C-bicarbonate or 13C-pyruvate were much lower. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>In contrast, palmitic acid C16:0 and palmitoleic acid C16:1n-7 were more 13C enriched with bicarbonate than with acetate and pyruvate (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Although algal fatty acids such as C18:2n-6, C18:3n-3 (macroalgae) and C20:5n-3 (microalgae) were significantly enriched by the selected substrates, they were more 13C enriched in the presence of bicarbonate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In addition to the bacterial markers identified by GC and GC-MS, several others were further identified by GC-IRMS such as another cyclopropane FA (cyC17:0), known to improve membrane fluidity of halophilic microorganims (Oren, 2002), and hydroxy fatty acids such as C16:0-OH (Wakeham et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Both FAs and C17:0 anteiso were significantly more enriched when 13C-bicarbonate and 13C-acetate were provided as substrate than in the control and 13C-pyruvate amendment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Isotopic ratio (δ13C notation) of the main fatty acids of purple sulfur bacterial mats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The upper (purple), middle (green) and lower (blue) panels corresponds to fatty acids which are considered representative of the purple sulfur bacteria, the macro- and microalgae, and bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Note that the C18:1n-7 is considered as an unambiguous marker of purple sulfur bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>AceL, PyrL and CO3L correspond to the different treatments (respectively 13C-acetate, 13C-pyruvate and 13C-bicarbonate) at ambient light. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-08-01995-g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Carbon and Ammonium Assimilation by Purple Bacterial Mats </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>To evaluate how microbial populations actively assimilate organic/inorganic carbon and ammonium in the mats, we followed assimilation of 13C-acetate, 13C-pyruvate, 13C-bicarbonate and 15N-ammonium in individual cells in light and dark conditions and measure their uptakes in short-term experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>NanoSIMS imaging revealed that the purple bacterial mats were formed by dense populations of coccoid cells aggregated in microcolonies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>This dominant mat morphotype was detected based on its typical coccoid shape from the naturally abundant 14N (12C14N-) images (Figure 4A) and defined as ROI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>A total of 1,204 bacterial cells were identified and encircled across all the treatments as shown in Figure 4B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>For each ROI, 15N/14N (inferred from the 12C15N-/12C14N- ratio) and 13C/12C (13C-/12C-) ratios were calculated and expressed in delta value (‰, Figures 4C,D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Examination of the NanoSIMS images and delta values indicated that purple spherical bacterial cells were not equally enriched in 15N and 13C relative to the non-amended cells (control). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Significant differences were observed between treatments (Figures 4C,D) and within treatments, especially under light. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Cells displayed a great heterogeneity in terms of C and N uptake at a very small spatial scale (Figure 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>They were substantially more enriched in both 13C and 15N under light that in the dark irrespective of the growth substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The highest delta values were obtained with pyruvate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>A significant correlation between C and N ratios in each treatment (except control) as well as linear relationships (Figure 5) indicated that C and N uptakes were linked. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>All linear regressions, except AceD, were significantly similar (ANCOVA: p = 9.489e-12 with all treatments, p = 0.1037 when removing AceD, the control treatment was removed from all analyses). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Assimilation rates were very variable and ranged from 0 to 0.002 fg C.bacterial cell-1. h-1 and from 0 to 0.0003 fg N.bacteria cell-1. h-1 (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Uptake of 13C and 15N in the incubations were significantly higher in the light for the three carbon sources while no elevated 13C- and/or 15N-uptake was detected in dark incubations, except in 13C-acetate amendments, indicating that acetate incorporation, the most active in the dominant mat morphotype, was not light-dependent. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>(A,B) Examples of NanoSIMS isotopic images of the purple sulfur bacteria mats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Purple sulfur bacteria were identified using the 12C14N-detector and each bacterial cell was defined as a region of interest (ROI: white circles). (C,D) Shows the carbon and nitrogen isotopic ratios (δ13C and δ15N notations) of the ROIs for the different treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Ace, Pyr and CO3 correspond to the different treatments (respectively 13C-acetate, 13C-pyruvate and 13C-bicarbonate), and “L” and “D” correspond to light and dark incubations, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The total number of ROIs is given below each boxplot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Significant differences between treatments have been tested using a Van der Waerden test and the results are shown above each boxplot (treatments with the same letter are not significantly different). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-08-01995-g004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Relationships between nitrogen and carbon ratios of the different ROIs according to the different treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Each point represents a ROI (i.e., purple sulfur bacterial cell). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Ace, Pyr and CO3 correspond to the different treatments (respectively 13C-acetate, 13C-pyruvate and 13C-bicarbonate), and “L” and “D” correspond to light and dark incubations, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>T0 corresponds to the control treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Regression lines were calculated and displayed on the graph for each treatment together with their confidence interval (gray surfaces). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-08-01995-g005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>FIGURE 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Assimilation rates of carbon and nitrogen at the single cell level according to the different treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Ace, Pyr and CO3 correspond to the different treatments (respectively 13C-acetate, 13C-pyruvate and 13C-bicarbonate), and “L” and “D” correspond to light and dark incubations, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Significant differences between treatments have been tested using a Van der Waerden test and the results are shown above each boxplot (treatments with the same letter are not significantly different). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-08-01995-g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Identification of the Main Phylotypes in the Purple Mats </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The above described NanoSIMS analysis identified typical coccoid shaped purple bacteria highly active under light in incorporating acetate into biomass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>To determine the bacterial community in the mats and identify which community members expressed the functional gene for anoxygenic photosynthesis, 16S rRNA and pufM clone libraries were constructed from DNA and cDNA recovered from two mat samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Coverage estimates ranging from 66.7 to 98.4% (mean 82%) and rarefaction curves (Supplementary Figure S1) indicated that a large part of the sample diversity was detected in the libraries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>In 16S rRNA clone libraries of two samples (178 clones), a substantial proportion of the sequences were related to the genera Thiohalocapsa (OTUs 8 and 22) and Marichromatium (OTUs 2 and related) within the Chromatiaceae family (Supplementary Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Both these genera, known to form dense purple layers in microbial mats, are morphologically distinct since Thiohalocapsa cells are spherical and cells of Marichromatium are straight to slightly curved rods (Caumette et al., 1991; Imhoff et al., 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The most abundant bacterial phylotype (OTU1, ∼48% of the total clones) in the libraries was, however, very closely related to a Pseudomonas strain isolated from a deep-sea sediment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The rest of the bacterial community was composed of minor OTUs that included sulfate-reducing bacteria (Desulfobacteraceae) and diverse members of the phylum Bacteroidetes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Most of the 203 total DNA- and cDNA-derived pufM sequences (95 and 108 clones, respectively) recovered from three mat samples were assigned to known genera of the Chromatiaceae (Figure 7 and Supplementary Table S1). Thiohalocapsa-related pufM sequences were numerically dominant in the DNA libraries (&gt;60% of the total sequences). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Sequencing of the pufM transcripts revealed that the majority (&gt;80%) of expressed pufM sequences recovered from cDNA of the samples also belonged to the Thiohalocapsa cluster, confirming the identity of the prevalent morphotype observed on NanoSIMS images. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>FIGURE 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic tree showing the relationships between pufM gene sequences of anaerobic anoxygenic phototrophic bacteria retrieved from the Roscoff Aber Bay mats (in bold) and relatives retrieved in GenBank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The tree is based on a Bayesian tree to which sequences obtained in this study (189 bp) were added by ARB_PARSIMONY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The scale bar represents dissimilarity between nucleotide positions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-08-01995-g007"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The few other pufM sequences recovered in this study were closely related to the alphaproteobacterial genera Roseobacter, Jannaschia, Roseovarius, Sulfitobacter, Loktanella and to Luminiphilus in the Gammaproteobacteria (Supplementary Figure S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>These bacteria correspond to aerobic anoxygenic phototrophs (AAP) which are known from previous studies to represent marine, halophilic and salt-dependent bacteria in the top oxic layer of sandy or muddy intertidal sediments (Shiba et al., 1979; Buchan et al., 2005; Ranchou-Peyruse et al., 2006; Spring et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>In this study, we used a combination of chemical, molecular and NanoSIMS analyses to investigate natural purple sulfur bacterial mats from the intertidal sediments of the Roscoff Aber Bay and estimate carbon and nitrogen fluxes at the submicrometric scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>We discovered that purple bacteria belonging to the Thiohalocapsa cluster represented almost the entire fraction of the expressed pufM genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>In addition, the coupled NanoSIMS/CSIA-FAME approach led us to conclude that members of the genus Thiohalocapsa were the most photosynthetically active bacteria in the studied mats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>As pointed out recently by Gao et al. (2016), NanoSIMS is a handy tool to investigate the functions and process of microorganisms especially in complex natural environments but yet requires further development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>We believe that validation of NanoSIMS fluxes by CSIA is a very promising combination in revealing substrate uptake at the single cell level. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Bacterial Community Composition of Purple Sulfur Mats </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic analysis showed that purple bacterial mats were dominated by very few species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Based on 16S rRNA gene library, the most abundant clone was closely related to a Pseudomonas strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Whilst this finding is not completely within the scope of the present study, it is interesting to note that this dominant sequence was found in several different samples, suggesting that the corresponding organism is favored by the modified chemical and physical gradients occurring at the sediment surface and/or takes advantage of the development of purple bacterial mats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Other dominant 16S rRNA clones were mainly affiliated with the family Chromatiaceae and most closely related to Thiohalocapsa and Marichromatium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Members of the genera Marichromatium and Thiohalocapsa are typical purple sulfur bacteria isolated from or detected in shallow coastal habitats such as the Roscoff Aber Bay where they are exposed to diel cycles of light intensity and temperature (Bolhuis and Stal, 2011; Caumette et al., 1991; Tank et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Overall, pufM sequences that we obtained mainly grouped within the Thiohalocapsa clade. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Several lines of evidence indicate that Thiohalocapsa-related bacteria were the main purple sulfur bacteria in the mats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>First, Tank et al. (2009) demonstrated an overall high consistency of tree topologies of pufM and 16S rRNA gene, allowing a phylogenetic classification of purple sulfur bacteria to the genus and in many cases to the species level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Second, Thiohalocapsa-related sequences were prominent in the DNA- and rRNA based pufM libraries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>And third, microcolonies viewed on NanoSIMS images were mainly composed by spherical cells typical of the Thiohalocapsa species described to date (Caumette et al., 1991; Imhoff et al., 1998; Anil Kumar et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Minor phylotypes of purple sulfur bacteria and aerobic anoxygenic phototrophic bacteria were detected in the mat samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide sequence similarities of these phylotypes showed different degrees of relatedness (from 84 to 96% similarity) to recognized species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The majority of them could be assigned to uncultured Chromatiaceae and to aerobic anoxygenic phototrophic alpha- and Gammaproteobacteria AAPs related to the genera Roseobacter clade and Luminiphilus, respectively (Labrenz et al., 1999; Wagner-Dobler et al., 2003; Van Trappen et al., 2004; Macian et al., 2005; Spring et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The coexistence of aerobic and anaerobic anoxygenic phototrophs has been reported in bacterial mats covering marine and saline sediments (Ranchou-Peyruse et al., 2006; Thiel et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>AAP bacteria have been shown to be abundant and active in marine oxygenated waters (Béjà et al., 2002; Koh et al., 2011; Boeuf et al., 2013) and it is not clear whether they are active in oxygen-limited or anoxic conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>In this study, only one pufM sequence from AAP bacteria (OTU10) was recovered in the cDNA-based libraries, suggesting that most of detected AAP bacteria were not able to grow photosynthetically under the low oxygen levels occurring at the mat surface. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Structure and Heterogeneity of the Thiohalocapsa Mats </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>NanoSIMS images allowed the detection of 1024 ROIs based on the typical coccoïd shape of Thiohalocapsa-like cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The most remarkable feature of the microbial mats was the relative homogeneity of morphotypes characterized by the presence of sulfur globules inside the cells (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>They result from the transient storage of sulfur during oxidation of sulfide (Caumette et al., 1991). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>As the likely result of the sample preparation procedure for NanoSIMS (i.e., high vacuum, ionization), the sulfur globules were visible as “holes” in the NanoSIMS images. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>This situation has already been observed in electron micrographs (Frigaard and Dahl, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>In that context, the naturally abundant 14N (12C14N-) images were very useful to detect Thiohalocapsa-like cells and define ROIs but, surprisingly, it was not possible to detect elemental sulfur using the 32S-detector neither within the globules (as sulfur was probably lost during sample preparation) nor in the rest of the cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Our data demonstrated that 13C enrichments can vary greatly between individual cells from the same species in the same bacterial mat although they are physically close to each other and even within cell clumps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>This finding was surprising given the relative homogeneity of the microbial mats in terms of structure, fatty acid composition and bacterial community composition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>This has also been observed in natural populations of other phototrophic microorganisms (Musat et al., 2008; Ploug et al., 2010). Musat et al. (2008) reported this situation in anaerobic phototrophic bacteria and hypothesized that the observed differences could be explained by the presence of physiologically distinct populations of phylogenetically identical or closely related organisms or by differences in gene expression among individual cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>In this study, 13C and 15N uptake rates were positively related which may indicate that the observed heterogeneity between individuals is likely explained by the presence of active and inactive cells, reflecting distinct physiological states or life “traits” (Musat et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>C Assimilation in Natural Purple Sulfur Mats </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>NanoSIMS analyses showed that the highest δ13C were obtained in the light in the presence of pyruvate, suggesting that pyruvate was the preferred photoassimilated carbon source for the Thiohalocapsa-dominated mats in our experimental conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>However, direct comparison of the δ13C and δ15N values between treatments must be taken cautiously in the light of the final atomic ratio of each substrate used during the incubation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the natural concentrations of acetate, pyruvate, bicarbonate and ammonium as well as their natural δ13C and δ15N must be known in order to properly estimate C &amp; N fluxes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>In our experiments, we used initial bicarbonate (1.3 mM; final isotopic ratio of 33.5 atom%) and ammonium levels (30.8 μM; final isotopic ratio of 86.9 atom%) corresponding to mean values measured in water covering biofilms and that are typical mean values recorded in August (Hubas et al., 2006a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Since we were unable to measure the initial concentrations of acetate and pyruvate before the incubation experiments, these values were taken from the literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Pyruvate is an important intermediate for microbial metabolism but it is involved exclusively in intracellular reactions (Sansone, 1986). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>As a consequence, its natural concentrations in pore waters is generally very low (Sansone, 1986; Sawyer and King, 1993; Heuer et al., 2006) thought it can be locally abundant if cell lysis is important or adsorbed onto extracellular polymeric substances through ketal links (Sutherland, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Acetate is generally more abundant than pyruvate in sediments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>While most studies agree that acetate concentrations are about 50 μM in the oxic zone of the sediment, they may increase significantly (up to 2 mM) when the environment becomes anoxic (Albert and Martens, 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>We therefore used concentration estimates for pyruvate (70 μM) and acetate (1000 μM) which correspond to final isotopic ratios of 33.5 and 86.9 atom%, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Using these final atomic ratios, our data showed that Thiohalocapsa-related bacteria preferentially assimilate acetate and bicarbonate in the light. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Their uptakes of acetate, bicarbonate and pyruvate under light conditions are in agreement with the substrate utilization of Thiohalocapsa species in culture under anaerobic conditions when sulfide is present (Caumette et al., 1991; Imhoff et al., 1998; Anil Kumar et al., 2009), suggesting that anoxic conditions prevailed in the mats during the incubation experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, no studies have compared the assimilation rates of carbon sources by Thiohalocapsa species either in culture or in the natural environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Here, additionally to their potential nutritional preferences under light, we also showed that acetate assimilation, although slower, was still efficient in the dark while uptakes of bicarbonate and pyruvate were minor in the same conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Chemoorganotrophic growth in micro-oxic conditions in the dark has been reported in T. halophila with pyruvate (Caumette et al., 1991) and in other Chromatiaceae with acetate and/or pyruvate (Imhoff, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>This suggests that micro-aerobic conditions also occur in Thiohalocapsa-dominated mats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The coexistence of micro-aerobic and anoxic zones at the micrometer scale in the investigated biofilms may also have contributed to the observed heterogeneity in the uptake of labelled substrates as revealed by NanoSIMS analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The ability of Thiohalocapsa-related bacteria to use acetate, one of the most important intermediates of anaerobic degradation of organic matter, during diurnal cycles of the light regime in oxic to anoxic conditions may likely explain their bloom formation in coastal microbial mats of Roscoff Aber Bay. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Using our single cell NanoSIMS fluxes (Figure 6), we extrapolated the bicarbonate fixation rates (mean CO3L fluxes – mean CO3D fluxes) to the whole community assuming a mean cell density of 7.5 × 1011 cells.g sediment-1 as evaluated using BChl a levels (Hubas et al., 2013), a BChl a content of 0.01991 mg Bchl a.mg C-1 (Overmann, 1997), and a cell carbon content of 20 fgC.cell-1 (Lee and Fuhrman, 1987). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>The result (1.95 ± 0.14 10-7 gC.g sediment-1.h-1) is close to the gross CO2 fixation rate (2.7 ± 0.1 10-7 gC.g sediment-1.h-1) of Thiohalocapsa-dominated mats measured using benthic chambers in a previous study (Hubas et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>In this calculation, we considered a mean carbon flux of 27.3 ± 0.9 mgC m-2 h-1, a chamber surface of 0.71 m2, a volume of 1 m2 of biofilm of 1000 cm3 (width and length = 100 cm, depth = 0.1cm) and a sediment density of 1 g.cm-3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Both these estimations are also in line with those (0.18 10-7 gC.g sediment-1.h-1) of purple sulfur bacterial mats from the Orkney islands (Wieland et al., 2003) assuming a O:C ratio of 1 during respiration and the same g to m2 conversion factor as above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>This confirms that single-cell fixation rates may be useful to estimate carbon fluxes at the biofilm scale. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>The combination of analytical chemistry as well as molecular ecology methods together with NanoSIMS imaging allowed the quantification of carbon and nitrogen fluxes at the submicrometric scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Here, we demonstrated that Thiohalocapsa-dominated mats in the Roscoff Aber Bay assimilated a substantial amount of dissolved bicarbonate although they probably favor a photoheterotrophic lifestyle for their growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>In the future, more precise quantitative C and N budgets for purple sulfur bacterial mats could be constructed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, taking into account their wide dispersion in intertidal sediments, as recently evidenced by spectral reflectance (Hubas et al., 2011), this study gives the way to the hitherto unsuspected importance of purple sulfur bacteria in the coastal carbon biogeochemical fluxes of coastal environments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Author Contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Project PI: CH; field work: CH, CJ, and BJ; laboratory measurements: DB (molecular), NT (fatty acids), YB (chemistry); NanoSIMS measurements and analysis: CH and CJ; statistical analysis: CH and DB (molecular); manuscript writing: CH and CJ; manuscript revision: CH, CJ, and BJ. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Conflict of Interest Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by French National Program EC2CO-MicroBien (project BIOPOURPRE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The authors want to thank Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>François Robert and Dr. Smaïl Mostefaoui (National Ion MicroProbe Facility at the Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris, France) for precious advices on C fluxes calculation and for help with NanoSIMS measurements, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>BJ acknowledges the Station Biologique (Roscoff, France) for hosting him in the frame of the EU FP7 Integrating Activities project ASSEMBLE. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2017.01995/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2017.01995/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Presentation_1.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2"><media xlink:href="Presentation_1.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM3"><media xlink:href="Presentation_1.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM4"><media xlink:href="Table_1.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>AchenbachL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>A.CareyJ.MadiganM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>T. (2001). Photosynthetic and phylogenetic primers for detection of anoxygenic phototrophs in natural environments. Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 67 2922–2926. 10.1128/AEM.67.7.2922-2926.2001 <?supplied-pmid 11425703?>11425703 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>AlbertD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>B.MartensC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>S. (1997). Determination of low-molecular-weight organic acid concentrations in seawater and pore-water samples via HPLC. Mar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Chem. 56 27–37. 10.1016/S0304-4203(96)00083-7 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>AltschulS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>F.MaddenT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>L.SchäfferA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>A.ZhangJ.ZhangZ.MillerW. (1997). Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs. Nucleic Acids Res. 25 3389–3402. 10.1093/nar/25.17.3389 <?supplied-pmid 9254694?>9254694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Anil KumarP.SrinivasT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>R.ThielV.TankM.SasikalaC.RamanaC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>V. (2009). Thiohalocapsa marina sp. nov., from an Indian marine aquaculture pond. Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 59 2333–2338. 10.1099/ijs.0.003053-0 <?supplied-pmid 19620368?>19620368 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>BéjàO.SuzukiM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>T.HeidelbergJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>F.NelsonW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>C.PrestonC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>M.HamadaT. (2002). Unsuspected diversity among marine aerobic anoxygenic phototrophs. Nature 415 630–633. 10.1038/415630a <?supplied-pmid 11832943?>11832943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>BlighE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>G.DyerW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>J. (1959). A rapid method of total lipid extraction and purification. Can. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Physiol. 37 911–917. 10.1139/o59-099 <?supplied-pmid 13671378?>13671378 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>BoeufD.CottrellM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>T.KirchmanD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>L.LebaronP.JeanthonC. (2013). Summer community structure of aerobic anoxygenic phototrophic bacteria in the western Arctic Ocean. FEMS Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Ecol. 85 417–432. 10.1111/1574-6941.12130 <?supplied-pmid 23560623?>23560623 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>BolhuisH.StalL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>J. (2011). Analysis of bacterial and archaeal diversity in coastal microbial mats using massive parallel 16S rRNA gene tag sequencing. ISME J. 5 1701–1712. 10.1038/ismej.2011.52 <?supplied-pmid 21544102?>21544102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>BuchanA.GonzalezJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>M.MoranM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>A. (2005). Overview of the marine roseobacter lineage. Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 71 5665–5677. 10.1128/AEM.71.10.5665-5677.2005 <?supplied-pmid 16204474?>16204474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>BurowL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>C.WoebkenD.BeboutB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>M.McMurdieP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>J.SingerS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>W.Pett-RidgeJ. (2012). Hydrogen production in photosynthetic microbial mats in the Elkhorn Slough estuary, Monterey Bay. ISME J. 6 863–874. 10.1038/ismej.2011.142 <?supplied-pmid 22011721?>22011721 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>CaumetteP. (1993). Ecology and physiology of phototrophic bacteria and sulfate-reducing bacteria in marine salterns. Experientia 49 473–481. 10.1007/BF01955148 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>CaumetteP.CohenY.MatheronR. (1991). Isolation and characterization of Desulfovibrio halophilus sp. nov., a Halophilic Sulfate-reducing Bacterium Isolated from Solar Lake (Sinai). Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 14 33–38. 10.1016/S0723-2020(11)80358-9 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>CaumetteP.MatheronR.RaymondN.RelaxansJ.-C. (1994). Microbial mats in the hypersaline ponds of Mediterranean salterns (Salins-de-Giraud, France). FEMS Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Ecol. 13 273–286. 10.1111/j.1574-6941.1994.tb00074.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>EdgarR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>C.HaasB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>J.ClementeJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>C.QuinceC.KnightR. (2011). UCHIME improves sensitivity and speed of chimera detection. Bioinformatics 27 2194–2200. 10.1093/bioinformatics/btr381 <?supplied-pmid 21700674?>21700674 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>FikeD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>A.GammonC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>L.ZiebisW.OrphanV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>J. (2008). Micron-scale mapping of sulfur cycling across the oxycline of a cyanobacterial mat: a paired nanoSIMS and CARD-FISH approach. ISME J. 2 749–759. 10.1038/ismej.2008.39 <?supplied-pmid 18528418?>18528418 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>FrigaardN.-U.DahlC. (2009). Sulfur metabolism in phototrophic sulfur bacteria. Adv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Microb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Physiol. 54 103–200. 10.1016/S0065-2911(08)00002-718929068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>GaoD.HuangX.TaoY. (2016). A critical review of NanoSIMS in analysis of microbial metabolic activities at single-cell level. Crit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol. 36 884–890. 10.3109/07388551.2015.1057550 <?supplied-pmid 26177334?>26177334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>GladyshevM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>I.SushchikN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>N.KalachovaG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>S.MakhutovaO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>N. (2012). Stable isotope composition of fatty acids in organisms of different trophic levels in the Yenisei River. PLOS ONE 7:e34059. 10.1371/journal.pone.0034059 <?supplied-pmid 22470513?>22470513 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>HeuerV.ElvertM.TilleS.KrummenM.MollarX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>P.HmeloL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>R. (2006). Online δ13C analysis of volatile fatty acids in sediment/porewater systems by liquid chromatography–isotope ratio mass spectrometry. Limnol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Oceanogr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Methods 4 346–357. 10.4319/lom.2006.4.346 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="?"><plain>HubasC.DavoultD. (2006). Does seasonal proliferation of Enteromorpha sp. affect the annual benthic metabolism of a small macrotidal estuary? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>(Roscoff Aber Bay, France). Estuar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Coast. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Shelf Sci. 70 287–296. 10.1016/j.ecss.2006.06.019 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>HubasC.DavoultD.CariouT.ArtigasL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>F. (2006a). Factors controlling benthic metabolism during low tide along a granulometric gradient in an intertidal bay (Roscoff Aber Bay, France). Mar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Ecol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Prog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Ser. 316 53–68. 10.3354/meps316053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B65"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>HubasC.JesusB.RuivoM.MezianeT.ThineyN.DavoultD. (2013). Proliferation of purple sulphur bacteria at the sediment surface affects intertidal mat diversity and functionality. PLOS ONE 8:e82329 10.1371/journal.pone.0082329 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>HubasC.LamyD.ArtigasL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>F.DavoultD. (2006b). Seasonal variability of intertidal bacterial metabolism and growth efficiency in an exposed sandy beach during low tide. Mar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Biol. 151 41–52. 10.1007/s00227-006-0446-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>HubasC.JesusB.PassarelliC.JeanthonC. (2011). Tools providing new insight into coastal anoxygenic purple bacterial mats: review and perspectives. Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 162 858–868. 10.1016/j.resmic.2011.03.010 <?supplied-pmid 21530653?>21530653 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>HubasC.JesusB.RuivoM.MezianeT.ThineyN.DavoultD. (2013). Proliferation of purple sulphur bacteria at the sediment surface affects intertidal mat diversity and functionality. PLOS ONE 8:e82329. 10.1371/journal.pone.0082329 <?supplied-pmid 24340018?>24340018 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>HubasC.LamyD.ArtigasL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>F.DavoultD. (2007). Seasonal variability of intertidal bacterial metabolism and growth efficiency in an exposed sandy beach during low tide. Mar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Biol. 151 41–52. 10.1007/s00227-006-0446-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>ImhoffJ.SülingJ.PetriR. (1998). Phylogenetic relationships among the Chromatiaceae, their taxonomic reclassification and description of the new genera Allochromatium, Halochromatium, Isochromatium, Marichromatium, Thiococcus, Thiohalocapsa and Thermochromatium. Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Bacteriol. 48 1129–1143. 10.1099/00207713-48-4-1129 <?supplied-pmid 9828415?>9828415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>ImhoffJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>F. (2001). True marine and halophilic anoxygenic phototrophic bacteria. Arch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 176 243–254. 10.1007/s002030100326 <?supplied-pmid 11685368?>11685368 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>ImhoffJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>F. (2006). “The chromatiaceae,” in The Prokaryotes eds DworkinM.FalkowS.RosenbergE.SchleiferK.-H.StackebrandtE. (New York, NY: Springer) 846–873. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>ImhoffJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>F. (2014). “The family chromatiaceae,” in The Prokaryotes eds RosenbergE.DeLongE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>F.LoryS.StackebrandtE.ThompsonF. (Berlin: Springer) 151–178. 10.1007/978-3-642-38922-1_295 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>KohE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Y.PhuaW.RyanK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>G. (2011). Aerobic anoxygenic phototrophic bacteria in Antarctic sea ice and seawater. Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Rep. 3 710–716. 10.1111/j.1758-2229.2011.00286.x <?supplied-pmid 23761361?>23761361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>LabrenzM.CollinsM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>D.LawsonP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>A.TindallB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>J.SchumannP.HirschP. (1999). Roseovarius tolerans gen. nov., sp. nov., a budding bacterium with variable bacteriochlorophyll a production from hypersaline Ekho Lake. Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Bacteriol. 49 137–147. 10.1099/00207713-49-1-137 <?supplied-pmid 10028255?>10028255 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>LeeJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>Z.BurowL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>C.WoebkenD.EverroadR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>C.KuboM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>D.SpormannA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>M. (2014). Fermentation couples Chloroflexi and sulfate-reducing bacteria to Cyanobacteria in hypersaline microbial mats. Front. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 5:61. 10.3389/fmicb.2014.00061 <?supplied-pmid 24616716?>24616716 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>LeeS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>H.FuhrmanL. (1987). Relationship between biovolume and biomass of naturally derived marine bacterioplankton. Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 53 1298–1303.16347362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>LudwigW.StrunkO.WestramR.RichterL.MeierH.Yadhukumar (2004). ARB: a software environment for sequence data. Nucleic Acids Res. 32 1363–1371. 10.1093/nar/gkh293 <?supplied-pmid 14985472?>14985472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>MacianM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>C.ArahalD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>R.GarayE.LudwigW.SchleiferK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>H.PujalteM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>J. (2005). Jannaschia rubra sp. nov., a red-pigmented bacterium isolated from sea water. Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 55 649–653. 10.1099/ijs.0.63412-0 <?supplied-pmid 15774638?>15774638 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>MarieD.ZhuF.BalaguéV.RasJ.VaulotD. (2006). Eukaryotic picoplankton communities of the Mediterranean Sea in summer assessed by molecular approaches (DGGE, TTGE, QPCR). FEMS Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Ecol. 55 403–415. 10.1111/j.1574-6941.2005.00058.x <?supplied-pmid 16466379?>16466379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>MezianeT.D’AgataF.LeeS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Y. (2006). Fate of mangrove organic matter along a subtropical estuary: small-scale exportation and contribution to the food of crab communities. Mar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Ecol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Prog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Ser. 312 15–27. 10.3354/meps312015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>MoronoY.TeradaT.NishizawaM.ItoM.HillionF.TakahataN. (2011). Carbon and nitrogen assimilation in deep subseafloor microbial cells. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>U.S.A. 108 18295–18300. 10.1073/pnas.1107763108 <?supplied-pmid 21987801?>21987801 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>MusatN.HalmH.WinterhollerB.HoppeP.PeduzziS.HillionF. (2008). A single-cell view on the ecophysiology of anaerobic phototrophic bacteria. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>U.S.A. 105 17861–17866. 10.1073/pnas.0809329105 <?supplied-pmid 19004766?>19004766 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>Núñez-cardonaM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>T. (2012). “Fatty acids analysis of photosynthetic sulfur bacteria by gas chromatography,” in Gas Chromatography - Biochemicals, Narcotics and Essential Oils eds SalihB.ÇelikbıçakÖ (Rijeka: InTech) 117–138. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>OrenA. (2002). “The cellular structure of halophilic microorganisms,” in Halophilic Microorganisms and their Environments SE - 4 Cellular Origin, Life in Extreme Habitats and Astrobiology ed. OrenA. (Dordrecht: Springer) 69–123. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>OvermannJ. (1997). “Mahoney lake: a case study of the ecological significance of phototrophic sulfur bacteria,” in Advances in Microbial Ecology Advances in Microbial Ecology ed. JonesJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>G. (Boston, MA: Springer) 251–288. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>PlougH.MusatN.AdamB.MoraruC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>L.LavikG.VagnerT. (2010). Carbon and nitrogen fluxes associated with the cyanobacterium Aphanizomenon sp. in the Baltic Sea. ISME J. 4 1215–1223. 10.1038/ismej.2010.53 <?supplied-pmid 20428225?>20428225 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>Ranchou-PeyruseA.HerbertR.CaumetteP.GuyoneaudR. (2006). Comparison of cultivation-dependent and molecular methods for studying the diversity of anoxygenic purple phototrophs in sediments of an eutrophic brackish lagoon. Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 8 1590–1599. 10.1111/j.1462-2920.2006.01050.x <?supplied-pmid 16913919?>16913919 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>RieraP.HubasC. (2003). Trophic ecology of nematodes from various microhabitats of the Roscoff Aber Bay (France): importance of stranded macroalgae evidenced through δ 13 C and δ 15 N. Mar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>Ecol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Prog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Ser. 260 151–159. 10.3354/meps260151 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>SansoneF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>J. (1986). Depth distribution of short-chain organic acid turnover in Cape Lookout Bight sediments. Geochim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Cosmochim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>Acta 50 99–105. 10.1016/0016-7037(86)90052-9 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>SawyerT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>E.KingG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>M. (1993). Glucose uptake and end product formation in an intertidal marine sediment. Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 59 120–128. <?supplied-pmid 16348837?>16348837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>SchlossP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>D.WestcottS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>L.RyabinT.HallJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>R.HartmannM.HollisterE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>B. (2009). Introducing mothur: open-source, platform-independent, community-supported software for describing and comparing microbial communities. Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 75 7537–7541. 10.1128/AEM.01541 <?supplied-pmid 19801464?>19801464 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>ShibaT.ShimiduU.TagaN. (1979). Distribution of aerobic bacteria which contain bacteriochlorophyll a. Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 32 211–217. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>SpringS.RiedelT.SpröerC.YanS.HarderJ.FuchsB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>M. (2013). Taxonomy and evolution of bacteriochlorophyll a-containing members of the OM60/NOR5 clade of marine gammaproteobacteria: description of Luminiphilus syltensis gen. nov., sp. nov., reclassification of Hailea rubra as Pseudohaliea rubra gen. nov., comb. nov., and emendation of Chromatocurvus halotolerans. BMC Microbiol. 13:118. 10.1186/1471-2180-13-118 <?supplied-pmid 23705883?>23705883 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>StalL. (1985). Structure and development of a benthic marine microbial mat. FEMS Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>Lett. 31 111–125. 10.1016/0378-1097(85)90007-2 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>SutherlandI. (2005). “Microbial exopolysaccharides,” in Polysaccharides Structural Diversity and Functional Versatility ed. DumitriuS. (New York City, NY: Marcel Dekker) 431–457. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>SuyamaM.TorrentsD.BorkP. (2006). PAL2NAL: robust conversion of protein sequence alignments into the corresponding codon alignments. Nucleic Acids Res. 34 W609–W612. 10.1093/nar/gkl315 <?supplied-pmid 16845082?>16845082 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>TankM.BlümelM.ImhoffJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>F. (2011). Communities of purple sulfur bacteria in a Baltic Sea coastal lagoon analyzed by pufLM gene libraries and the impact of temperature and NaCl concentration in experimental enrichment cultures. FEMS Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>Ecol. 78 428–438. 10.1111/j.1574-6941.2011.01175.x <?supplied-pmid 22066777?>22066777 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>TankM.ThielV.ImhoffJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>F. (2009). Phylogenetic relationship of phototrophic purple sulfur bacteria according to pufL and pufM genes. Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 12 175–185. <?supplied-pmid 19784924?>19784924 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>ThielV.TankM.NeulingerS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>C.GehrmannL.DoradorC.ImhoffJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>F. (2010). Unique communities of anoxygenic phototrophic bacteria in saline lakes of Salar de Atacama (Chile): evidence for a new phylogenetic lineage of phototrophic Gammaproteobacteria from pufLM gene analyses. FEMS Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>Ecol. 74 510–522. 10.1111/j.1574-6941.2010.00966.x <?supplied-pmid 20868378?>20868378 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57"><text><SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>TournaM.StieglmeierM.SpangA.KonnekeM.SchintlmeisterA.UrichT. (2011). Nitrososphaera viennensis, an ammonia oxidizing archaeon from soil. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>Sci. 108 8420–8425. 10.1073/pnas.1013488108 <?supplied-pmid 21525411?>21525411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>Van TrappenS.MergaertJ.SwingsJ. (2004). Loktanella salsilacus gen. nov., sp. nov., Loktanella fryxellensis sp. nov. and Loktanella vestfoldensis sp. nov., new members of the Rhodobacter group, isolated from microbial mats in Antarctic lakes. Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 54 1263–1269. 10.1099/ijs.0.03006-0 <?supplied-pmid 15280301?>15280301 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59"><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>Wagner-DoblerI.RheimsH.FelskeA.PukallR.TindallB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>J. (2003). Jannaschia helgolandensis gen. nov., sp. nov., a novel abundant member of the marine Roseobacter clade from the North Sea. Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 53 731–738. 10.1099/ijs.0.02377-0 <?supplied-pmid 12807194?>12807194 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>WakehamS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>G.PeaseT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>K.BennerR. (2003). Hydroxy fatty acids in marine dissolved organic matter as indicators of bacterial membrane material. Org. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>Geochem. 34 857–868. 10.1016/S0146-6380(02)00189-4 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B61"><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>WeisburgW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>G.BarnsS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>M.PelletierD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>A.LaneD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>J. (1991). 16S ribosomal DNA amplification for phylogenetic study. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>Bacteriol. 173 697–703. 10.1128/jb.173.2.697-703.19911987160 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B62"><text><SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>WielandA.KühlM.McGowanL.FourçansA.DuranR.CaumetteP. (2003). Microbial mats on the Orkney Islands revisited: microenvironment and microbial community composition. Microb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>Ecol. 46 371–390. 10.1007/s00248-002-0108-2 <?supplied-pmid 12904912?>12904912 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B63"><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>WoebkenD.BurowL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>C.BehnamF.MayaliX.SchintlmeisterA.FlemingE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>D. (2015). Revisiting N2 fixation in Guerrero Negro intertidal microbial mats with a functional single-cell approach. ISME J. 9 485–496. 10.1038/ismej.2014.144 <?supplied-pmid 25303712?>25303712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B64"><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>WoebkenD.BurowL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>C.Prufert-BeboutL.BeboutB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>M.HoehlerT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>M.Pett-RidgeJ. (2012). Identification of a novel cyanobacterial group as active diazotrophs in a coastal microbial mat using NanoSIMS analysis. ISME J. 6 1427–1439. 10.1038/ismej.2011.200 <?supplied-pmid 22237543?>22237543 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
