<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Middle East J Dig Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Middle East J Dig Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Middle East J Dig Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">MEJDD</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEJDD</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Middle East Journal of Digestive Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2008-5230</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2008-5249</issn><issn-l>2008-5230</issn-l><publisher><publisher-name>Iranian Association of Gastroerterology and Hepatology</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4208930</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The Characteristics of Rare Codon Clusters in the Genome and Proteins of Hepatitis C Virus; a Bioinformatics Look </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fattahi</surname><given-names>Mohammadreza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"><sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="COR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Malekpour</surname><given-names>Abdorrasoul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>Mojtaba</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A02">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Safarpour</surname><given-names>Alireza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Naseri</surname><given-names>Nasrin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A01"><sup>1</sup> Gastroenterohepatology Research Center, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz, Iran
</aff><aff id="A02"><sup>2</sup> Department of Biotechnology, Institute of Science and High Technology and Environmental Science, Graduate University of Advanced Technology, Kerman, Iran
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Mohammadreza Fattahi, MD Gastroenterohepatology Research Center, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, P.O. Box: 71935-1311, Shiraz, Iran Telefax: + 98 71 36474263 <email>Fattahim@sums.ac.ir</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 by Middle East Journal of Digestive Diseases</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license><license-p>
This work is published by Middle East Journal of Digestive Diseases as an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>). Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted, provided the original work is properly cited.
</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://mejdd.org">http://mejdd.org</self-uri><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>BACKGROUND </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Recent studies suggest that rare codon clusters are functionally important for protein activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Here, for the first time we analyzed and reported rare codon clusters in Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) genome and then identified the location of these rare codon clusters in the structure of HCV protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>This analysis was performed using the Sherlocc program that detects statistically relevant conserved rare codon clusters. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>By this program, we identified the rare codon cluster in three regions of HCV genome; NS2, NS3, and NS5A coding sequence of HCV genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>For further understanding of the role of these rare codon clusters, we studied the location of these rare codon clusters and critical residues in the structure of NS2, NS3 and NS5A proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>We identified some critical residues near or within rare codon clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>It should be mentioned that characteristics of these critical residues such as location and situation of side chains are important in assurance of the HCV life cycle. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>CONCLUSION </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The characteristics of these residues and their relative status showed that these rare codon clusters play an important role in proper folding of these proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Thus, it is likely that these rare codon clusters may have an important role in the function of HCV proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>This information is helpful in development of new avenues for vaccine and treatment protocols. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>HCV genome</kwd><kwd>NS2,NS3 and NS5A proteins</kwd><kwd>Rare codon cluster</kwd><kwd>Sherlocc program</kwd><kwd>Ribosomal pauses</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><counts><fig-count count="8"/><table-count count="3"/><ref-count count="57"/><page-count count="14"/></counts></article-meta><notes><p> Please cite this paper as:</p><p>FattahiMR, MalekpourAR, MortazaviM, SafarpourAR, Naseri N.The Characteristics of Rare Codon Clusters in the Genome and Proteins of Hepatitis C Virus; a Bioinformatics Look. Middle East J Dig Dis 2014;6:214-27.</p></notes></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="introduction" id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Coding nucleotide sequences carry an integral message containing several different types of information for the various molecular mechanisms‏.1 Recent studies also suggest that beyond the amino-acid sequence lies an additional layer of information, hidden within the codon sequence, able to mediate local kinetics of translation.2 Studies of these hidden information in codon sequences, can reveal the molecular evolution of organisms, and provide insights into the functional categories and histories of genes in a genome.2 Codon-usage analysis can also contribute to understanding the interaction between RNA viruses and the immune response of the hosts.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Although each codon is specific for only one amino acid (or one stop signal), the genetic code is described as degenerate, or redundant because a single amino acid may be coded by more than one codon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Such groups of codons coding for a single amino acid are known as synonymous codons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>For instance, six synonymous codons can produce the amino acid leucine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>By contrast, a non-degenerate code, like for the amino acids methionine and tryptophan, is one for one: each code is unique, producing one and only one output. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>In total, 18 of the 20 amino acids can be encoded by more than one codon and most of this degeneracy is found at the third position in a codon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Synonymous codons encoding for a particular amino acid are very well conserved over most species although a few small exceptions have been reported.3,4 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Codon usage bias refers to differences in the frequency of occurrence of synonymous codons in coding DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Different factors have been proposed to explain the preferential usage of a subset of synonymous codons, including biased mutation pressure,5 difference in mutational bias between the leading and lagging strands of DNA replication,6,7 and natural selection for optimizing translation process (translational selection).8 While some codons are preferentially used in highly expressed genes, some codons are almost absent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>These codons are referred to in the literature as rare, unflavored or low usage codons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Some reports indicate synonymous codons used with low frequency tend to have depleted concentration of tRNAs.9-11 Dereased tRNAs concentration, influence ribosomes to pause at rare codons until the rare activated tRNA brings the next amino acid to the growing polypeptide.12,13 It was observed that the distribution of rare triplets along mRNAs is definitely non-uniform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The observation that rare codons are not randomly distributed, but rather organized in large clusters14 across species support the existence of a selective evolutionary pressure.15 The clustering of rare or un-favored codons near the start codon was first identified by Ikemura16 in the highly expressed ribosomal protein genes rplK, rplJ, and rpsM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>This was attributed to some functional constraint, perhaps a signal for special regulation.17 Several studies focused on identifying rare codons in protein sequences and replacing them with frequent synonymous ones.18 The results of studies, based on the identity, density and location of the rare codons, were diverse: change in substrate specificity,18 decrease in protein solubility,19 activation of a gene designed to detect misfolded proteins 19 and a decrease of a protein’s specific activity.20 It has been proposed that translational pauses may have evolved to secure the independent functionally competent folding of some regions of polypeptide chains during their synthesis.21 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The hepatitis C virus (HCV) is a small, enveloped, single-stranded, positive-sense RNA virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>It is a member of the hepacivirus genus in the family Flaviviridae.22 It consists of a 9.6 kb RNA, which contains an open reading frame (ORF) encoding a polyprotein, flanked by un-translated regions (UTR) at both ends .23,24 The HCV genome encodes a polyprotein precursor of about 3000 amino acids.25 The polyprotein is cleaved by the cellular signal peptidase and virally encodes two proteases into at least 10 mature proteins; core, envelope glycoprotein 1 (E1), E2, p7, nonstructural protein 2 (NS2), NS3, NS4A, NS4B, NS5A, and NS5B.26,27 No prophylactic HCV vaccine is currently available and increasing efforts are, therefore, needed in the development of an effective vaccine against HCV. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Previously, two rare codons have been detected in the HCV.28 Because of an increasing amount of evidence suggesting that rare codon clusters are functionally important for protein activity,29 in the present study for the first time we studied the rare codon clusters and their locations in structures of HCV proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>For this, we identified the Pfam accession number of 10 mature HCV proteins; core, E1, E2, p7, NS2, NS3, NS4A, NS4B, NS5A, and NS5B by use of HCVpro database (HCV protein interaction database).30 Subsequently, these Pfams accession numbers were analyzed in Sherlocc program.2 Sherlocc program detects statistically relevant conserved rare codon clusters and produces an HTML output.2 Analyses of these sequences show that several sites of HCV genome (NS2, NS3, NS4B, NS5A, and NS5B) have a rare codon cluster. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, the structures of TrEMBL entries that are reported in the output of Sherlocc program were studied in PDB database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The results of these studied shows that PDB structures of HCV proteins are not complete just as TrEMBL entries reported in Sherlocc Program outputs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>For this reason, by submission of NS2, NS3, NS4B, NS5A, and NS5B sequences with these TrEMBL entries in Swiss Model Alignment interface protein modeling server,31 3D structure models were obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>3D structures of the HCV proteins and locations of rare codon clusters were visualized and studied using PyMOL software.32 The major influence of codon usage is on local translation rate, and large clusters will a greater effect on protein production than an equivalent number of randomly scattered rare codons.15,33,34 Reports of improved folding yield or protein activity due to translational pausing 35,36 infer that potential factors might lead to the enrichment of rare codon clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>These results imply the role of rare codon clusters in all aspects of protein expression: mRNA stability, folding, secretion, and interactions with partner proteins.15 The results of these studies show that one hidden layer of codon usage information lies in the rare codon clusters and we believe studying rare codon clusters and their locations in the structure of HCV mRNA and proteins may help in the development of new and effective drugs in the future. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2-1"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Detection of rare codon clusters </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The protein family accession number (Pfam) of 10 mature HCV proteins; core, E1, E2, p7, NS2, NS3, NS4A, NS4B, NS5A, and NS5B were identified using HCVpro database 30 and listed in table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The analysis and detection of the codon clusters of these Pfam IDs was done in Sherlocc program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>For this, Sherlocc retrieves the nucleotide sequence of every protein in each Pfam protein family alignments from the European Nucleotide Archive (ENA) database.37 Then, using the appropriate translation table the correspondence of the nucleotide sequence with the amino-acid sequence provided in the Pfam alignment is verified and the specie codon usage frequencies are retrieved using the Kazusa codon usage frequency online database.38 To detect rare codon clusters, a 7 codon-wide window, is centered at every position of the alignment, and averages all codon usage frequencies inside the 7 codon-wide windows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>This average calculated across all proteins of the alignment has subsequently the net effect of assuring that only positions that are rare across the majority of the members of the family are retained.2 From this, the threshold can be chosen and will allow us to discriminate positions of the alignment occupied by rare codons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>All codon usage frequency averages under this threshold are tagged as slow.2 Estimated locus’s of these rare codon clusters in HCV genomic RNA is shown in figure 1 and HTML output of Sherlocc program is shown in figure 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The rare codon clusters characteristics in HCV proteins are listed in table 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>
Table 1
</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The characteristic of PFAM ID and rare codon clusters in HCV. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="none"><tbody><tr style="border-width: 1px 0px 1pt 0px ; border-style:solid none solid none;border-color:#00adee"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>HCV protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>PFAM ID </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Number rare codon clusters </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>codon usage average threshold </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Core </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Pf0154, Pf01543 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>E1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>PF01539 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>E2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>PF01560 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>P7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Not detected </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>NS2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>PF01538 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>NS3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>PF02907 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>NS4A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>PF01006 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>NS4B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>PF01001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>NS5ANS5ANS5A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Pf01506,Pf08300,Pf08301 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>011 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>-1818 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr style="border-width: 0px 0px 1pt 0px ; border-style:none none solid none;border-color:#00adee"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>NS5B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>PF00998 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>
Fig. 1
</label><graphic xlink:href="MEJDD-6-214-g001"/><statement><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>A schematic diagram of the HCV genome, the 5' and 3' un-translated regions (UTR) shown with putative secondary structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The long open reading frame of HCV genomic marked as a long box, in which estimated loci of rare codon clusters labeled. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></statement></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>
Fig. 2
</label><graphic xlink:href="MEJDD-6-214-g002"/><statement><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Extract of an HTML output A (NS2-PF01538), B1, B2, B3 (NS3-PF02907), C1 (NS5A-PF08301) and C2 (NS5A-PF08300) generated by Sherlocc program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Each row represents a protein from the alignment and displays the amino acid, its corresponding codon and the corresponding codon usage frequency (bold). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>At the bottom (gray row), codon usage frequency averages calculated at each position by the first window are displayed in bold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Averages under the selected threshold are considered ‘slow’ and tagged in orange.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></statement></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>
Table 2
</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The output of Sherlocc program and rare codon clusters characteristics in HCV proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="none"><tbody><tr style="border-width: 1px 0px 1pt 0px ; border-style:solid none solid none;border-color:#00adee"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>HCV protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>PFAM ID </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Swiss-Prot or TrEMBlentries </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Organism </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Number proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Residue length of the alignment </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain> RCC* Position  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>RCC Usage Frequency Average </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>RCC Middle Point </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Fraction of the pfam occupied by rare codon clusters </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr style="border-width: 0px 0px 1pt 0px ; border-style:none none solid none;border-color:#00adee"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Core </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Pf0154 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Q69422 (POLG_GBVB) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Hepatitis GB virus B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>76 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>24 – 44 64 - 68 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>16.02817.354 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>3365 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>0.3421052632 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr style="border-width: 0px 0px 1pt 0px ; border-style:none none solid none;border-color:#00adee"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>NS2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>PF01538 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>A8DF36_9HEPC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Hepatitis C virus subtype 1b </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>203 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>36-45 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>17.983 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>40 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>0.0492610837 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr style="border-width: 0px 0px 1pt 0px ; border-style:none none solid none;border-color:#00adee"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>NS3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>PF02907 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Q9QIX6_9HEPC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Hepatitis C virus subtype 1b </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>150 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>7-1441-4577-81 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>17.30517.67916.938 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>104275 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>0.1200000000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr style="border-width: 0px 0px 1pt 0px ; border-style:none none solid none;border-color:#00adee"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>NS4B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>PF01001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Q69422(POLG_GBVB) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Hepatitis GB virus B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>199 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>59-63 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>17.318 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>60 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>0.0251256281 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>NS5A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Pf01506 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>- </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Pf08300 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Q1KL41-9HEPC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Hepatitis C virus subtype 6a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>64 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>47-53 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>16.873 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>49 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>0.1093750000 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr style="border-width: 0px 0px 1pt 0px ; border-style:none none solid none;border-color:#00adee"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Pf08301 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Q1KL34_9HEPC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Hepatitis C virus subtype 6a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>103 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>84-87 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>17.405 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>85 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>0.0388349515 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>NS5B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>PF00998 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Q69422 (POLG_GBVB) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Hepatitis GB virus B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>545 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>3-7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>17.930 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>0.1339449541 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>15-21 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>17.007 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>35-45 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>39 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>17.814 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>91-95 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>92 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>17.598 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>104-107 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>105 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>16.697 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>116-119 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>117 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>17.472 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>172-175 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>173 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>17.261 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>316-322 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>318 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>18.033 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>418-422 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>419 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>17.196 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>439-448 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>443 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>17.542 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr style="border-width: 0px 0px 1pt 0px ; border-style:none none solid none;border-color:#00adee"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>514-524 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>518 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>17.675 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>*RCC: Rare codon cluster. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Analysis of rare codon clusters in the structure of HCV proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>To investigate the position of rare codon clusters in the structure of HCV proteins, the structures of TrEMBL entries proteins that were reported in Sherlocc program were studied in PDB database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The results showed that PDB structures of HCV proteins and their sequences are not complete and are just as TrEMBL entries sequences reported in Sherlocc Program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>For this reason, by submission of TrEMBL entries sequences of NS2, NS3, NS4B, NS5A, and NS5B in Swiss Model Alignment interface protein modeling server,31 3D structure models were obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Modeled residue range, used templates, sequence identity and other detail information were listed in table 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>3D structures of the HCV proteins and locations of rare codon clusters were visualized and studied using PyMOL software 32 as shown in  figures 3,  4 and 5. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>
Table 3
</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The characteristics of HCV protein modeling </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="none"><tbody><tr style="border-width: 1px 0px 1pt 0px ; border-style:solid none solid none;border-color:#00adee"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>HCV Protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Modeled residue range </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Based on template </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Sequence Identity [%] </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>E value </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>QMEAN Z-Score </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>NS2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>27-59 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>2kwtA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>87.88 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>5.56e-10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>-3.59 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>NS3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>1 to 149 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>4a1xA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>96.64 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>5.69e-76 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>0.05 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr style="border-width: 0px 0px 1pt 0px ; border-style:none none solid none;border-color:#00adee"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>NS5A-Q1KL41-9HEPCNS5A-Q1KL34_9HEPC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>36 to 19836 to 198 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>1zh1B1zh1B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>77.376.69 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>2.38e-711.65e-71 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>-0.93-0.81 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>
Fig. 3
</label><graphic xlink:href="MEJDD-6-214-g003"/><statement><p><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Molecular model of the NS2 HCV [27-59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>The structure is in blue, except rare codon cluster that is in green. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></statement></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>
Fig. 4
</label><graphic xlink:href="MEJDD-6-214-g004"/><statement><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The ribbon diagram of NS3 protease domain and location of rare codon cluster residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The overall structure is in blue, except rare codon clusters B1 (V36-F43) in red, B2 (P70-M74) in yellow and B3 (L106- H110) in green. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Notice that PyMOL software could not show the region of rare codon cluster B2 and we used spdbv(45) software for studying this region. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></statement></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>
Fig. 5
</label><graphic xlink:href="MEJDD-6-214-g005"/><statement><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Part of N-terminal domain sequence from NS2 protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Location of rare codon clusters (highlighted in green) and some essential residues (red) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></statement></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3-1"><title><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Detection of rare codon clusters </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>With use of HCVpro database the Pfam accession numbers of 10 mature HCV proteins were identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Pfam is a comprehensive collection of protein domains and families represented as multiple sequence alignments and as profile hidden Markov models.39 After detecting Pfam IDs of HCV proteins, these Pfams were studied in the Sherlocc program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Results of these studies show that this program did not identify rare codon clusters in the envelope glycoproteins 1 (E1), E2, p7 and nonstructural protein NS4A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>By contrast the rare codon clusters were identified in the core, nonstructural protein NS2, NS3, NS4B, NS5A and NS5B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>The HCVpro database30 detected two Pfams for core protein and analyzing the Pf01543 ID in the Sherlocc program detected no rare codon cluster while the Pf0154ID showed two rare codon clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>For NS5A, the HCVpro database detected three Pfams (Pf01506, Pf08300 and Pf08301). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Studying these Pfams shows that Pf01506 ID has no rare codon cluster while the rare codon clusters were identified in the Pf08300 and Pf08301 IDs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>However in HCVpro database no Pfam was identified for P7 and therefore the Sherlocc program could not identify the rare codon cluster in this region of RNA sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>By analyzing the PF01539, PF01560, PF01006 and Pf01506 IDs in this program, rare codon clusters were not detected in these regions of RNA sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>However, Sherlocc program detects statistically relevant conserved rare codon clusters and more precise studies might be needed for proving these results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The Pfam ID, number of rare codon clusters and codon usage average threshold are listed in table 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>The Sherlocc program produces an HTML output that reports the TrEMBL entries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Studying these TrEMBL entries showed that some of the relevant conserved rare codon clusters do not cover the TrEMBL entries from HCV proteins and eventually we gave up these rare codon clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>According to this thread, we did not consider the results of Sherlocc program analysis for core, NS4B and NS5B Pfam IDs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>The Pfam ID, Swiss-Prot or TrEMBL entries, organism, rare codon clusters position usage and other detail information are listed in table 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>It is important that rare codon cluster position reported in this table be based on the first TrEMBL entries. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Analysis positions of rare codon clusters in HCV mRNA sequences </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>HCV has positive sense single-strand RNA genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>The genome composes a single open reading frame that is 9600 nucleotide bases long.25 This single open reading frame is translated to produce one protein product, which is then further processed to produce smaller active proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>As previously mentioned, we identified six rare codon clusters in HCV genomic RNA found in the NS2, NS3 and NS5A regions of RNA. Figure 1 shows estimated locus’s of these rare codon clusters in RNA genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Translation of mRNA is regulated by structural and non-structural RNA elements, and interactions with RNA-binding proteins.40 One of the significant features of viral genome translation is the identification of genetic elements, either RNA sequences or protein domains, which may modulate the viral genome translation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Previously, six HCV genome elements (GE) had been identified.41 One of these GE, GE4, encodes the 5’ end of the viral NS5A gene that includes the membrane anchor domain.41 The interesting point is that one rare codon cluster was found in this genome element (GE4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>However, the position of rare codon clusters and their structural patterns in RNA may be important in opening new research fields for extending the possible cures for many disorders or viral infections. Figure 2 show the HTML output from Sherlocc program that reports the TrEMBL entries and the characteristic of rare codon clusters. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Studying rare codon clusters in the structure of HCV proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Knowledge of 3D structure is a useful prerequisite for understanding the role and function of proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Studying the location and roles of rare codon clusters on the three-dimensional structure of proteins, is a cornerstone in many aspects of modern biology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>The possible roles for rare codon clusters are to produce multiple translational pauses during the synthesis of its catalytic domain,2 play a regulating role in folding catalytically important domains, and in protein structure and indirect folding.29,42 Further, many results support the existence of a widespread functional role for rare codon clusters across species.2 As mentioned, six rare codon clusters were identified in HCV genome found in NS2, NS3 and NS5A of HCV proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Specific studies shows PDB structures of HCV proteins are not complete and are just as TrEMBL entries sequences reported in Sherlocc program outputs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Protein-protein blast show the rough location of rare codon clusters in these sequences but for precise studying of the location and role of rare codon clusters, it is necessary to gain 3D models from these sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>To this end, by submitting sequences of NS2, NS3 and NS5A in Swiss Model alignment interface protein modeling server,31 3D models of these proteins were obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The modeled residue range, template and other detailed information are listed in table 3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>The Sherlocc program identified TrEMBL entryA8DF36_9HEPCfor NS2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Using the Swiss-Model, these TrEMBL entry sequence were used for obtaining the 3D model of this protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>NS2, derived from the cleavage of NS2/3, inserted into the ER membrane through its N-terminal hydrophobic domain suggested containing multiple transmembrane segments.43 The NS2 protein has 217 residue and rare codon clusters found from amino acids 37 to 46 and in polyproteins extending from amino acids 846-855. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>The overall structure of NS2 was not determined and therefore the Swiss Model could not model the whole sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>The structure of NS2 protein has been modeled previously and in this model amino acids from 27 to 49 formed trans-membrane α helix (TMH-2).43 Results of modeling show that this rare codon cluster is located in this trans-membrane α helix (TMH-2). Figure 3 shows the modeled NS2 and the position of rare codon clusters. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>For NS3 protein, Sherlocc program identified TrEMBL entries Q9QIX6_9HEPC.The NS3 protein has 631 residue and three rare codon clusters found in polyproteins extending from amino acids 1062-1069, 1096-1100 and 1132-1136. NS3 is a multifunctional protein and the N-terminal domain (residues 1027–1119) contains eight β strands rather than six, including one strand contributed by NS4A.44 This array of b strands gives rise to a b sheet that superimposes with most of the distorted barrel found in the N-terminus of chymotrypsin.45 Result of modeling showed that these three rare codon clusters lie between strands A1-B1, E1-F and A2-B2 in N-terminal domain of NS3. Figure 4 shows the modeled NS3 and the position of rare codon clusters. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>As mentioned, HCVpro database for NS5A detected three Pfams. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>For Pf01506 ID this database did not identify any rare codon cluster while for Pf08300 and Pf08301 IDs two rare codon clusters were identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>These rare codon clusters were found in different loci sequences of NS5A and Sherlocc program for NS5A revealed two TrEMBL entries; Q1KL41-9HEPC and Q1KL34_9HEPC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>The protein was predicted to be mainly hydrophilic and contain no transmembrane helices.46 A recent study using bioinformatics assisted modeling suggested a three-domain organization with domain I (a.a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>1-213) located in the N-terminal region, and Domain II (a.a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>250-342) and Domain III (a.a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>356-447) in the C-terminal region.47 Analysis of the 3D model showed that these two rare codon clusters lie in domain I located in the N-terminal of NS5A HCV. Figure 5 shows the position of these rare codon clusters in the structure of NS5A HCV proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>The preliminary goal of this study was to perform a survey of rare codon clusters in the HCV genome and then identify the location of these clusters in the structure of HCV protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Previous studies on the distribution of rare codons clusters were performed on a limited number of proteins or protein families.2 The Sherlocc program and the online Sherlocc Finder Interface are efficient tools that can be used to study the widespread translational pauses in protein families.2 Please note that clusters identified by Sherlocc were compared with cases foundin the literature.2 For example, in the Salmonella phage P22 tail spike protein in which rare codons were previously identified using the MinMax algorithm,15 Sherlocc also identified rare codon clusters in the Salmonella phage P22 tail-spike protein family (PF09251).2 Another case involved the chloramphenicol acetyl transferase (CAT) protein for which rare codon clusters were identified computationally in a multi-organism sequence alignment of this protein.42 The Sherlocc program also identified rare codon clusters in the CAT protein family (PF00302). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we used Sherlocc program to analyze rare codon clusters in HCV genome and the structure of HCV proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>The results were interesting and showed that HCV has five rare codon clusters and these rare codon clusters may play an essential role in ensuring proper folding of the protein chain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>The HCV structural proteins, core, E1, and E2, were located at the amino terminus and nonstructural proteins, NS3, NS4A, NS4B, NS5A, and NS5B, were located at the carboxyl terminus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>The deduced amino acid sequence of HCV nonstructural 2 shows that NS2 is a hydrophobic transmembrane protein, described to be involved in different functions.43,48 NS2 is a 217 amino acid long cysteine-protease composed of a hydrophobic N-terminal membrane binding domain (MBD) and C-terminal globular and cytosolic protease subdomain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Previously a model of NS2 proposed that this protein is a polytopictrans membrane protein containing 3 putative transmembrane segments.43 Many studies have been done on this protein indicating interesting results regarding the role of amino acids.43 These studies show that alanine substitutions with aromatic residue in TMS2 (Y39) reduced infectivity titers up to 1,000-fold whereas mutations introducing electrostatic repulsion in TMS2 (E45R) blocked virus production .43 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Also, for W35F and W35FNS3- Q221L, interaction of NS2 with other viral proteins reduced, but to different extents.43 Based on the model of the NS2, residues 25 and 39, which were found on TMS1 and TMS2, respectively, might be in contact.43 It assumed the ‘‘hole’’ created in TMS2 by the Y39A substitution was compensated by a bulky amino acid in the interacting TMS1 counterpart, thus ‘filling up’ the hole in the mutated TMS2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>A striking correlation was found between reduction of aromaticity as well as size of residues at these sites (W35 and W36) and decrease of virus production arguing the aromatic side chains of W35 and W36 involved in essential interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>These results show that these residues play critical roles in proper folding of this protein and disrupting this process severely affected the virus life cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>An important point deduced from our analysis was that some of these residues were involved in rare codon clusters of NS2 (figure 6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>
Fig. 6
</label><graphic xlink:href="MEJDD-6-214-g006"/><statement><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>The ribbon diagram of NS3 protease domain and location of rare codon cluster residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>The overall structure is in blue, except rare codon clusters B1 (V36-F43) in red, B2 (P70-M74) in yellow and B3 (L106-H110) in green. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Notice that PyMOL software could not show the region of rare codon cluster B2 and we used spdbv(45) software for studying this region. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></statement></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>As mentioned, mutation of these residues blocks or reduces virus production and this shows that the situation of side chains are important in maintaining the HCV life cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>NS2 has a rare codon cluster found in transmembrane (TMS2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>According to the characteristics of transmembrane proteins, translation and folding of TMS2 mRNA appear to be more important and may take more time for folding compared with other parts of NS2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>However, these conclusions should be confirmed with experimental evidence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>The 631-residue HCV NS3 protein is a dual-function protein, containing the trypsin/chymotrypsin-like serine protease in the N-terminal region and a helicase in the C-terminal region.49,50 Co-transfection studies showed the NS3 serine protease domain, in absence of its C-terminal helicase counterpart, is mediating cleavage of polyprotein substrates.51 The minimal sequences needed for a serine protease activity determined by these groups is the N-terminal 180 amino acids of the NS3 protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Deletion of up to 14 residues from the N terminus of the NS3 protein is tolerated, although a further deletion of the N-terminal 22 amino acids resulted in significantly poorer processing of HCV polyprotein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, deletions from C terminus of this minimal serine protease domain abolished proteolytic activity.52,53 Our study showed that NS3 protein has three rare codon clusters found in polyprotein extending from amino acids 1062-1069, 1096-1100 and 1132-1136 that lies between strands A1-B1, E1-F and A2-B2 in N-terminal domain of NS3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Full-length NS3 protein found from amino acids 1027 to 1658 of the polyprotein of the genotype 1b consensus sequence.54 Previously, in the protease domain of NS3, amino acid residues involved in substrate-binding pocket were identified.55 These residues are potentially able to interact with peptide substrates.55 Studies show that some of these residues are found in rare codon cluster locus (figure 7). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>
Fig. 7
</label><graphic xlink:href="MEJDD-6-214-g007"/><statement><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Part of N-terminal domain from NS3 protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Location of rare codon cluster (highlighted in blue) and some of the substrate binding site residues (red color) shown. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></statement></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Most NS3 protease inhibitors are competitive with the substrate and thus target the substrate binding site.55 The earliest inhibitors were based on product peptides.56 Many positions of NS3 protease have shown to contribute to resistance in cell culture and in the clinic.55 Many of the positions confer resistance to both macro-cyclic and linear inhibitors.55 Amino acid substitutions at positions that are not essential for substrate binding would lead to drug-resistant proteases and viruses that do not debilitate for function.56 Our study showed that some of residues that involved in substrate binding site and confer resistance inhibitors can be found in the first rare codon cluster and near position of other rare codon cluster. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>As we know, the binding site residues are critical in enzymes and proper position of these residues should be adjusted accurately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>These data show that positions of rare codon clusters may play a critical role in proper folding and action of protease domain of NS3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>HCV nonstructural protein 5A (NS5A) plays an essential role in viral genome replication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>The protein is predicted to be mainly hydrophilic and to contain no transmembrane helices.46 A recent study using bioinformatics-assisted modeling suggested a three-domain organization 47 with domain I (a.a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>1-213) found in the N-terminal region, and Domain II (a.a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>250-342) and Domain III (a.a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>356-447) in the C-terminal region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>The N-terminal 30 aa of NS5A predicted to form a conserved amphipathic alpha-helix.57 Afterwards, this structure has shown to be very essential for HCV RNA replication.45 Our study showed that NS5A protein has two rare codon clusters found in polyprotein extending from amino acids 2051-2061 and 2154-2157that lies in N-terminal domain (domain I) of NS5A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Full-length NS5A protein was found from amino acids 1978 to 24287 of the polyprotein of the genotype 6a consensus sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Previously, in the N-terminal domain of NS5A, the amino acid residues involved in activity were identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>The location of some of these residues and rare codon clusters is shown in figure 8. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>
Fig. 8
</label><graphic xlink:href="MEJDD-6-214-g008"/><statement><p><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Part of amino acid sequences that important for activity of HCV NS5A in N-terminal domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Location of rare codon cluster (highlighted in green) and some of the substrate binding site residues (red color) shown. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></statement></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>As shown in this figure some of the residues found in the first rare codon cluster and near other rare codon clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, an unconventional zinc-binding motif predicted to exist in the N-terminal domain, showing that NS5A is a zinc metalloprotein.47 The predicted zinc-binding motif involves four cysteine residues (C39, C57, C59, and C80), and includes a structural motif (CX17CXCX20C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>This motif appeared critical for the structural stability and functions of NS5A protein, since mutation of any single cysteine residue in the motif disrupted the ability of NS5A to coordinate zinc and eliminated RNA replication.47 As we know these residues are critical in enzymes and proper position of these residues should be adjusted accurately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>These data show that rare codon cluster may play a critical role in proper folding and action of protease activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>These data indicate that in HCV life cycle, rare codon clusters play an important role that must be investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>However, other rare codon clusters may exist that could not be identified by Sherlocc program and require further study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Since most rare codon clusters were found in NS3, it appears that these clusters may play a more significant role than other HCV proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>As explained in the introduction, ribosomal pauses caused by rare codons can basically regulate specific folding events but could also be involved in other mechanisms involving the nascent polypeptide chain such as protein targeting or co-translational molecular recognition events.2 However, we cannot strictly state whether such pauses are needed for folding or molecular recognition of HCV proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Based on the involvement of families with rare clusters with membrane insertion or recognizing large complexes, it is suggested that those rare codon clusters are important in HCV life cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Proteins synthesized in a nonlinear kinetic landscape and mRNA sequence seem to carry more information than those necessary to encode protein sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Information that can be used for regulating folding events as well as regulating co-translational molecular recognition events such as recognizing signal peptides, formation of complexes, or membrane insertion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>We believe that this study presents a new perspective in genome research of HCV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>In the future, this study can also provide new fields in drug design for the treatment of HCV. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Authors wish to thank the staff of Gastroenterohepatology Research Center, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences for their kindly help in conducting of this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec id="s6"><title><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>The authors declare no conflict of interest related to this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>1KyprJA Part Of Codon Bias In Genes Protects Protein Spatial Structures From Destabilization By Random Single Point MutationsBiochem Biophys Res Commun1986139109473767992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R2"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>2ChartierMGaudreaultFNajmanovichRLarge-Scale Analysis Of Conserved Rare Codon Clusters Suggests An Involvement In Co-Translational Molecular Recognition EventsBioinformatics20122814384522467916 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R3"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>3ShackeltonLaParrishCrHolmesEcEvolutionary Basis Of Codon Usage And Nucleotide Composition Bias In Vertebrate Dna VirusesJ Mol Evol2006625516316557338 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R4"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>4OsawaSJukesTWatanabeKMutoARecent Evidence For Evolution Of The Genetic CodeMicrobiol Rev199256229641579111 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R5"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>5SantosMaMouraGMasseySeTuiteMfDriving Change: The Evolution Of Alternative Genetic CodesTrends Genet2004209510214746991 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R6"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>6SueokaNOn The Genetic Basis Of Variation And Heterogeneity Of Dna Base CompositionProc Natl Acad Sci U S A1962485829213918161 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R7"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>7LobryJAsymmetric Substitution Patterns In The Two Dna Strands Of BacteriaMol Biol Evol19961366058676740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R8"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>8McleanMjWolfeKhDevineKmBase Composition Skews, Replication Orientation, And Gene Orientation In 12 Prokaryote GenomesJ Mol Evol19984769169847411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R9"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>9SharpPmBailesEGrocockRjPedenJfSockettReVariation In The Strength Of Selected Codon Usage Bias Among BacteriaNucleic Acids Res20053311415315728743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R10"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>10IkemuraTCodon Usage And Trna Content In Unicellular And Multicellular OrganismsMol Biol Evol1985213343916708 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R11"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>11PercudaniRPavesiAOttonelloSTransfer RNA gene redundancy and translational selection in Saccharomyces cerevisiaeJ Mol Biol1997268322309159473 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R12"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>12DuretLTrna Gene Number And Codon Usage In The CElegans Genome Are Co-Adapted For Optimal Translation Of Highly Expressed GenesTrends Genet200016287910858656 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R13"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>13SorensenMaKurlandCPedersenSCodon usage determines translation rate in Escherichia coliJ Mol Biol1989207365772474074 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R14"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>14VarenneSBucJLloubesRLazdunskiCTranslation Is A Non-Uniform Process: Effect Of Trna Availability On The Rate Of Elongation Of Nascent Polypeptide ChainsJ Mol Biol1984180549766084718 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R15"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>15Clarke TF4thClarkPLRare Codons ClusterPLoS One20083e341218923675 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R16"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>16IkemuraTCorrelation between the abundance of Escherichia coli transfer RNAs and the occurrence of the respective codons in its protein genesJ Mol Biol19811461216167728 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R17"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>17IkemuraTCorrelation between the abundance of Escherichia coli transfer RNAs and the occurrence of the respective codons in its protein genes: a proposal for a synonymous codon choice that is optimal for the Ecoli translational systemJ Mol Biol19811513894096175758 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R18"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>18Kimchi-SarfatyCOhJMKimIWSaunaZECalcagnoAMAmbudkarSVA "silent" polymorphism in the MDR1 gene changes substrate specificityScience2007315525817185560 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R19"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>19CortazzoPCerveñanskyCMarínMReissCEhrlichRDeanaASilent mutations affect in vivo protein folding in Escherichia coliBiochem Biophys Res Commun20022935374112054634 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R20"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>20KomarAaLesnikTReissCSynonymous Codon Substitutions Affect Ribosome Traffic And Protein Folding During In Vitro TranslationFEBS Lett19994623879110622731 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R21"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>21GuisezYRobbensJRemautEFiersWFolding of the MS2 coat protein in Escherichia coli is modulated by translational pauses resulting from mRNA secondary structure and codon usage: a hypothesisJ Theor Biol1993162243528412226 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R22"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>22AlterMJEpidemiology Of Hepatitis C In The WestSemin Liver Dis1995155147597444 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R23"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>23ChooQ-LKuoGWeinerAjOverbyLrBradleyDwHoughtonMIsolation Of A Cdna Clone Derived From A Blood-Borne Non-A, Non-B Viral Hepatitis GenomeScience1989244359622523562 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R24"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>24SuzukiTIshiiKAizakiHWakitaTHepatitis C Viral Life CycleAdv Drug Deliv Rev20075912001217825945 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R25"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>25KatoNHijikataMOotsuyamaYNakagawaMOhkoshiSSugimuraTMolecular Cloning Of The Human Hepatitis C Virus Genome From Japanese Patients With Non-A, Non-B HepatitisProc Natl Acad Sci U S A199087952482175903 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R26"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>26ShimotohnoKTanjiYHirowatariYKomodaYKatoNHijikataMProcessing Of The Hepatitis C Virus Precursor ProteinJ Hepatol19952287927602084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R27"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>27ReedKRiceCOverview Of Hepatitis C Virus Genome Structure, Polyprotein Processing, And Protein PropertiesCurr Top Microbiol Immunol2000242558410592656 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R28"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>28HuJSWangQQZhangJChenHTXuZWZhuLThe Characteristic Of Codon Usage Pattern And Its Evolution Of Hepatitis C VirusInfect Genet Evol201111209810221907310 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R29"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>29ThanarajTArgosPProtein Secondary Structural Types Are Differentially Coded On Messenger RnaProtein Sci199651973838897597 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R30"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>30KwofieSkSchaeferUSundararajanVsBajicVbChristoffelsAHCVpro: hepatitis C virus protein interaction databaseInfect Genet Evol2011111971721930248 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R31"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>31SchwedeTKoppJGuexNPeitschMcSWISS-MODEL: An automated protein homology-modeling serverNucleic Acids Res2003313381512824332 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R32"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>32 Delano Wl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>The Pymol Molecular Graphics System. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>2002.  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R33"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>33VarenneSBatyDVerheijHShireDLazdunskiCThe Maximum Rate Of Gene Expression Is Dependent In The Downstream Context Of Unfavourable CodonsBiochimie198971122192517483 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R34"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>34VarenneSLazdunskiCEffect Of Distribution Of Unfavourable Codons On The Maximum Rate Of Gene Expression By An Heterologous OrganismJ Theor Biol1986120991103528671 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R35"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>35TsaiCJSaunaZeKimchi-SarfatyCAmbudkarSvGottesmanMmNussinovRSynonymous Mutations And Ribosome Stalling Can Lead To Altered Folding Pathways And Distinct MinimaJ Mol Biol20083832819118722384 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R36"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>36BuchanJrStansfieldIHalting A Cellular Production Line: Responses To Ribosomal Pausing During TranslationBiol Cell2007994758717696878 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R37"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>37LeinonenRAkhtarRBirneyEBowerLCerdeno-TárragaAChengYThe European Nucleotide ArchiveNucleic Acids Res201139Database issueD283120972220 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R38"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>38NakamuraYGojoboriTIkemuraTCodon Usage Tabulated From International Dna Sequence Databases: Status For The Year 2000Nucleic Acids Res20002829210592250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R39"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>39SonnhammerElEddySrDurbinRPfam: A Comprehensive Database Of Protein Domain Families Based On Seed AlignmentsProteins199728405209223186 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R40"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>40RobertsLHolcikMRNA structure: new messages in translation, replication and diseaseWorkshop on the role of RNA structures in the translation of viral and cellular RNAsEMBO Rep2009104495319343048 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R41"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>41LoicJaffreloSandrineChabasSandrineReigadasAudePfliegerCzeslawWychowskiJulieRumiA functional selection of viral genetic elements in cultured cells to identify hepatitis C virus RNA translation inhibitorsNucleic Acids Res200836e9518614605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R42"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>42WidmannMClairoMDipponJPleissJAnalysis Of The Distribution Of Functionally Relevant Rare CodonsBMC Genomics2008920718457591 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R43"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>43JiraskoVMontserretRLeeJyGouttenoireJMoradpourDPeninFStructural And Functional Studies Of Nonstructural Protein 2 Of The Hepatitis C Virus Reveal Its Key Role As Organizer Of Virion AssemblyPLoS Pathog20106e100123321187906 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R44"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>44KimJMorgensternKLinCFoxTDwyerMLandroJCrystal Structure Of The Hepatitis C Virus Ns3 Protease Domain Complexed With A Synthetic Ns4a Cofactor PeptideCell199687343558861917 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R45"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>45GuexNPeitschMcSwiss‐Model And The Swiss‐Pdb Viewer: An Environment For Comparative Protein ModelingElectrophoresis1997182714239504803 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R46"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>46MacdonaldAHarrisMHepatitis C Virus Ns5a: Tales Of A Promiscuous ProteinJ Gen Virol200485248550215302943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R47"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>47TellinghuisenTlMarcotrigianoJGorbalenyaAeRiceCmThe Ns5a Protein Of Hepatitis C Virus Is A Zinc MetalloproteinJ Biol Chem2004279485768715339921 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R48"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>48TomeiLFaillaCSantoliniEDe FrancescoRLa MonicaNNs3 Is A Serine Protease Required For Processing Of Hepatitis C Virus PolyproteinJ Virol1993674017267685406 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R49"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>49GorbalenyaAeKooninEvHelicases: Amino Acid Sequence Comparisons And Structure-Function RelationshipsCurr Opin Struct Biol1993341929 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R50"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>50GorbalenyaAeKooninEvDonchenkoApBlinovVmTwo Related Superfamilies Of Putative Helicases Involved In Replication, Recombination, Repair And Expression Of Dna And Rna GenomesNucleic Acids Res1989174713302546125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R51"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>51LinCPragaiBmGrakouiAXuJRiceCmHepatitis C Virus Ns3 Serine Proteinase: Trans-Cleavage Requirements And Processing KineticsJ Virol1994688147577966606 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R52"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>52BartenschlagerRAhlborn-LaakeLMousJJacobsenHKinetic And Structural Analyses Of Hepatitis C Virus Polyprotein ProcessingJ Virol1994685045558035505 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R53"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>53FaillaCTomeiLDe FrancescoRAn Amino-Terminal Domain Of The Hepatitis C Virus Ns3 Protease Is Essential For Interaction With Ns4aJ Virol1995691769777853516 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R54"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>54LohmannVKörnerFKochJOHerianUTheilmannLBartenschlagerRReplication Of Subgenomic Hepatitis C Virus Rnas In A Hepatoma Cell LineScience1999285110310390360 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R55"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>55RaneyKdSharmaSdMoustafaImCameronCeHepatitis C Virus Non-Structural Protein 3 (Hcv Ns3): A Multifunctional Antiviral TargetJ Biol Chem2010285227253120457607 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R56"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>56IngallinellaPAltamuraSBianchiETalianiMIngenitoRCorteseRPotent Peptide Inhibitors Of Human Hepatitis C Virus Ns3 Protease Are Obtained By Optimizing The Cleavage ProductsBiochemistry1998378906149636032 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R57"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>57VolkerBElkeBRolandMBennoWJan AlbertHHubertEbAn Amino-Terminal Amphipathic Α-Helix Mediates Membrane Association Of The Hepatitis C Virus Nonstructural Protein 5AJ Biol Chem20022778130911744739 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
