<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Acta Cryst. D</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Biological Crystallography</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0907-4449</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1399-0047</issn><publisher><publisher-name>International Union of Crystallography</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4188009</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">mv5109</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S1399004714017313</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="coden">ABCRE6</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1399004714017313</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Papers</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Structure of archaerhodopsin-2 at 1.8 Å resolution </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title>Archaerhodopsin-2</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kouyama</surname><given-names>Tsutomu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="b">b</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>Ryudo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kanada</surname><given-names>Soun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>Taichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>Siu Kit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>Midori</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a">a</xref></contrib><aff id="a"><label>a</label>Department of Physics, Graduate School of Science, <institution>Nagoya University</institution>, Nagoya, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="b"><label>b</label><institution>RIKEN Harima Institute/SPring-8</institution>, 1-1-1 Kouto, Mikazuki, Sayo, Hyogo, <country>Japan</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor">Correspondence e-mail: <email>kouyama@bio.phys.nagoya-u.ac.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>01</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>70</volume><issue>Pt 10</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">d141000</issue-id><fpage>2692</fpage><lpage>2701</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Kouyama et al. 2014</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/uk/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Licence, which permits
unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original authors and source are cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S1399004714017313">A full version of this article is available from Crystallography Journals Online.</self-uri><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The same hexagonal array of archaerhodpsin-2 trimers as observed in the native membrane is reconstituted in a three-dimensional crystal prepared by the membrane fusion method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In this crystal, a pair of conserved glutamate residues in the proton-release pathway is maintained by a low-barrier hydrogen bond. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Archaerhodopsin-2 (aR2), the sole protein found in the claret membrane of Halorubrum sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Aus-2, functions as a light-driven proton pump. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>In this study, structural analysis of aR2 was performed using a novel three-dimensional crystal prepared by the successive fusion of claret membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The crystal is made up of stacked membranes, in each of which aR2 trimers are arranged on a hexagonal lattice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>This lattice structure resembles that found in the purple membrane of H. salinarum, except that lipid molecules trapped within the trimeric structure are not distributed with perfect threefold symmetry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, diffraction data at 1.8 Å resolution provide accurate structural information about functionally important residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>It is shown that two glutamates in the proton-release channel form a paired structure that is maintained by a low-barrier hydrogen bond. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Although the structure of the proton-release pathway is highly conserved among proton-pumping archaeal rhodopsins, aR2 possesses the following peculiar structural features: (i) the motional freedom of the tryptophan residue that makes contact with the C13 methyl group of retinal is restricted, affecting the formation/decay kinetics of the L state, and (ii) the N-terminal polypeptide folds into an Ω-loop, which may play a role in organizing the higher-order structure. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>archaerhodopsin-2</kwd><kwd>light-driven proton pump</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><label>1.</label><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Introduction   </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Since the light-driven proton pump bacteriorhodopsin was discovered in the cell membrane of Halobacterium salinarum (Oesterhelt &amp; Stoeckenius, 1971 ▶), a large number of proton-pumping rhodopsins have been found in diverse species, including archaea, eubacteria, fungi and algae (Ihara et al., 1999 ▶; Waschuk et al., 2005 ▶; Spudich et al., 2014 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>To date, nine proton-pumping rhodopsins [i.e. archaerhodopsin-1 and archaerhodopsin-2; (aR1 and aR2; Enami et al., 2006 ▶; Yoshimura &amp; Kouyama, 2008 ▶), acetabularia rhodopsin II (Wada et al., 2011 ▶), bacteriorhodopsin (bR; Essen et al., 1998 ▶; Pebay-Peyroula et al., 1997 ▶; Sato et al., 1999 ▶; Faham &amp; Bowie, 2002 ▶), cruxrhodopsin-3 (cR3; Chan et al., 2014 ▶), deltarhodopsin-3 (dR3; Zhang et al., 2013 ▶), proteorhodopsin (Gushchin et al., 2013 ▶; Ran et al., 2013 ▶) and xanthorhodopsin (Luecke et al., 2008 ▶)] have been crystallized and their structural data have enabled the discussion of a common structural motif that is relevant to the proton-pumping activity (Kouyama &amp; Murakami, 2010 ▶; Ernst et al., 2014 ▶). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the diffraction data from three-dimensional crystals of bR, aR2, cR3 and dR3 that were prepared by the membrane-fusion method have shown that at neutral pH two glutamates in the proton-release channel form a paired structure (Fig. 1 ▶ a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>On the basis of the pH dependence of the protein structure, it has been argued that the paired structure of Glu194 and Glu204 in bR is maintained by a low-barrier hydrogen bond (Okumura et al., 2005 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>This argument has been supported by a recent theoretical study (Phatak et al., 2008 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Since the paired structure of Glu194 and Glu204 in bR is broken during the proton-pumping cycle, it has been suggested that the Glu194/Glu204 pair functions as a proton-release complex (Takeda et al., 2004 ▶; Yamamoto et al., 2009 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, structural models of bR determined using different crystal forms have suggested that the conformation of the proton-release channel is sensitive to the crystallization procedure (Fig. 1 ▶ b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In an orthorhombic crystal (space group C2) that was prepared by the epitaxial growth method, the side chain of Glu194bR is directed towards Tyr83bR (Essen et al., 1998 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>In a P63 crystal that was prepared by embedding the membrane protein in a cubic phase of monooleic acid, the side chain of Glu194bR is hydrogen-bonded to Ser193bR OH (Luecke, 2000 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>This configuration is distinct from that found in the P622 crystal of bR at neutral pH, in which Glu194bR is hydrogen-bonded to the backbone amide NH of the same residue (Okumura et al., 2005 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Since the lipid component (for example, triglycolipid) observed in the P622 crystal is partially removed or missing in the other crystal forms (Belrhali et al., 1999 ▶), it is possible that the conformation of the functionally important region is influenced by the lipid–protein inter­actions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Their influence cannot be ignored in discussion of the structural changes that occur during the proton-pumping cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>For example, there is a significant difference among the reported structural models of the L state (Royant et al., 2001 ▶; Kouyama et al., 2004 ▶; Lanyi, 2005 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>For a better understanding of the proton-pumping mechanism, it is important to accumulate structural data on other proton-pumping rhodopsins using high-quality three-dimensional crystals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Archaerhodopsin-2 (aR2) is a light-driven proton pump that is found in the cell membrane of Halorubrum sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Aus-2 (Uegaki et al., 1991 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The sequence identity among members of the archaerhodopsin family is high (&gt;90%; Mukohata et al., 1991 ▶; Ihara et al., 1999 ▶), whereas the amino-acid sequences of all members of the aR family are distinct from those of proton-pumping rhodopsins with known structure (i.e. the sequence identities are less than 50%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In previous studies, aR2 was crystallized as three-dimensional crystals belonging to space groups C2221 (Enami et al., 2006 ▶), P321 and P63 (Yoshimura &amp; Kouyama, 2008 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In the P321 and P63 crystals aR2 assembles into a trimeric structure with bacterioruberin bound to the inter-subunit crevice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>This trimeric structure is destroyed in the C2221 crystal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the structures of aR2 in these crystal forms revealed that the conformation of the extracellular end of helix C is greatly altered upon removal of the lipid component interacting with helix C. It would be interesting to investigate how much the structures of the photoreaction intermediates are affected by the protein packing or the protein–lipid interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, the previously reported three-dimensional crystals of aR2 were merohedrally twinned, making it difficult to analyze the possible effects of light-induced structural changes in aR2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In this study, we have applied the membrane-fusion method to prepare a novel three-dimensional crystal of aR2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>This crystal is made up of membranous layers, in each of which the aR2 trimers are arranged on a hexagonal lattice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Compared with the previously reported crystal forms of aR2, the new crystal has several advantages: (i) it diffracts X-rays to a higher resolution, (ii) the problem of crystal twinning is avoided and (iii) the hexagonal array as seen in the native claret membrane is reconstituted in the crystal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Owing to these properties, the new crystal provided accurate structural information about functionally important residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>It is shown that two glutamates (Glu199 and Glu209) in the proton-release channel are separated by a very short distance (2.3 Å). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>This result suggests that their paired structure is maintained by a low-barrier hydrogen bond. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, flash-induced absorption changes in aR2 showed that the K state decayed directly to the M state; i.e. the L state was undetected in the photocycle of aR2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>On the basis of these newly obtained structural and absorption kinetics data for aR2, we discuss possible structural factors affecting the photoreaction kinetics and the higher-order structure of proton-pumping rhodopsin. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec2"><label>2.</label><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods   </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1.</label><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Preparation and crystallization of archaerhodopsin-2   </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Claret membrane containing archaerhodopsin-2 was isolated from Halorubrum sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Aus-2 and purified according to a previously described procedure (Enami et al., 2006 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>For the crystallization of aR2, a mixture consisting of claret membrane (∼3 mg ml−1), 5 mg ml−1 nonylglucoside, 1 M ammonium sulfate, 0.08 M sodium chloride, 0.04 M sodium azide and 0.04 M HEPES pH 7 was slowly concentrated by the sitting-drop vapour-diffusion method using 0.5 ml 2.2–2.8 M ammonium sulfate, ∼0.1 M sodium citrate pH 7 as a reservoir solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Incubation at 15°C for approximately one month yielded hexagonal rod crystals with typical dimensions of 50 × 50 × 200 µm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2.</label><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Measurement of absorption kinetics   </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Transient transmission data from aR2 in claret membranes were acquired using a frequency-doubled Nd-YAG laser as described previously (Hayakawa et al., 2008 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The absorption kinetics measured at various wavelengths were analyzed using the singular value decomposition method (Chizhov et al., 1996 ▶). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3.</label><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Data collection, scaling and refinement   </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>For X-ray diffraction measurements, a single crystal was picked up and soaked in a post-crystallization solution consisting of 2.2 M ammonium sulfate, 0.1 M HEPES pH 7, 30% trehalose for ∼10 min; subsequently, the crystal was flash-cooled in dim light with liquid propane at its melting temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>X-ray diffraction data were collected on beamline BL38B1 at SPring-8, where a crystal kept at 100 K was exposed to a monochromatic X-ray beam at a wavelength of 1.0 Å with an X-ray flux rate of ∼2 × 1012 photons mm−2 s−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Diffraction data were collected using an oscillation range of 1° and an X-ray flux of ∼1 × 1013 photons mm−2 per image. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Indexing and integration of diffraction spots were carried out using MOSFLM 6.1 (Steller et al., 1997 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The scaling of data was accomplished using SCALA in the CCP4 program suite (Winn et al., 2011 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Structural analysis was performed with CNS (Brünger et al., 1998 ▶), REFMAC5 (Murshudov et al., 2011 ▶) and XtalView (McRee, 1993 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The structure of aR2 in the P321 crystal (PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=2ei4">2ei4</ext-link>) was used as an initial model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>After rotational and translational searching with MOLREP (Vagin &amp; Teplyakov, 2010 ▶), water and lipid molecules were added on the basis of the 2F o − F c map and the structure was refined by several cycles of simulated-annealing and individual B-factor refinements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The final refinement of the protein structure using REFMAC5 resulted in an R cryst of 21.4% and an R free of 23.4% (Table 1 ▶). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="sec3"><label>3.</label><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Results   </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1.</label><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Crystal packing   </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>In the first approach to model building, the crystal was presumed to belong to space group C2, with unit-cell parameters a = 108.6, b = 62.7, c = 116.3 Å, α = 90, β = 108.1, γ = 90° (blue solid lines in Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>2 ▶ a and 2 ▶ b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>In this space group, the asymmetric unit contains three subunits of aR2 (i.e. one trimer). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The side view of the unit cell shows that the crystal is composed of membranous layers (Fig. 2 ▶ a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>In each membranous layer, aR2 trimers are arranged on a hexagonal lattice with a cell dimension of 62.7 Å (Fig. 2 ▶ b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>At first sight, it appeared that there was no structural difference among the three protein molecules in the asymmetric unit, each of which was folded into seven transmembrane helices (helices A–G), an Ω-loop in the N-terminal region (Asn5–Pro12) and a β-sheet at the BC loop. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>However, close investigation of the electron-density map showed that the lipid molecules trapped within the aR2 trimer were not distributed with perfect threefold symmetry (Fig. 3 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Specifically, a hydrocarbon chain (possibly squalene) is positioned at the centre of the trimer, breaking the threefold symmetry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Although its extracellular half with an extended conformation is surrounded by three diphytanyl chains, the cytoplasmic half is disordered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Disorder was also observed for other lipids filling the inter-trimer space and the side chains of arginine residues (Arg34 and Arg230) that can interact with negatively charged lipid head groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Strictly speaking, we need to postulate that the three subunits in each trimer adopt slightly different conformations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>However, the structural differences among these subunits would be difficult to analyze unless all of the trimers within a membranous layer have the same in-membrane orientation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>In the current model building in space group C2 only the trimeric structure that is averaged over three possible in-membrane orientations can be analyzed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>In the second approach to model building, the crystal used in this study was assumed to belong to space group H32, with unit-cell parameters a = b = 62.7, c = 331.5 Å, α = 90, β = 90, γ = 120° (red broken lines in Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>2 ▶ a, 2 ▶ b and 2 ▶ c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>In space group H32, one subunit of aR2 is contained in the asymmetric unit; i.e. the aR2 trimer is supposed to have perfect threefold symmetry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>It should be pointed out that the structural model constructed on the assumption of space group H32 is equivalent to the averaged structure of the three subunits that are contained in the asymmetric unit of space group C2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Indeed, there was no essential difference between the structural models constructed by the above two approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>In the following discussion, we describe the structural model built in space group H32, which provides more accurate structural information about the functionally important residues (Fig. 4 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Hereafter, the hexagonal crystal investigated in this study will be called the H32 crystal. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Since the membranous layers in the H32 crystal are piled up with alternate orientations, there are two types of intermembrane protein–protein contacts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>On the extracellular side, the BC loop interacts with the DE loop of one of the neighbouring proteins and the N-terminal region of another neighbouring protein (Fig. 2 ▶ d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>On the cytoplasmic side, the EF loop contacts the EF loop of the protein opposite (Fig. 2 ▶ e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The structure of the protein–protein contact region is slightly different from that observed in the P321 crystal, in which the aR trimers are piled up directly along the c axis (Yoshimura &amp; Kouyama, 2008 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>A more significant difference is that the B factors of the main-chain atoms in the extracellular halves of helices A, B, C and D are much lower in the H32 crystal than in the P321 crystal (Fig. 5 ▶ d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>It is suggested that the motional freedom of these regions is suppressed by the inter-membrane protein–protein contacts in the H32 crystal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, relatively higher B factors are observed for the main-chain atoms in the cytoplasmic halves of helices E and F. This result suggests that the intermembrane protein–protein interaction at the EF loop is weak. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>It is unlikely that this interaction is a major factor in determining the cell dimension of the hexagonal lattice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that in freshly prepared claret membrane the aR2 trimers are arranged in a hexagonal lattice with a cell dimension of 63.3 Å at room temperature (Yoshimura &amp; Kouyama, 2008 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>This cell dimension is nearly identical to that (62.7 Å) of the hexagonal lattice found in the H32 crystal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>(The small difference may be owing to shrinkage of the hexagonal lattice at the cryogenic temperature.) Thus, it appears possible that successive fusion of native claret membranes in the pre-crystallization solution yields flat sac-like structures that are then piled up in the crystal-growth phase. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>In many respects, the membranous structure found in the H32 crystal resembles the purple membrane of H. salinarum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Firstly, the centre-to-centre distance (62.7 Å) between neighbouring aR2 trimers is similar to the cell dimension (62.45 Å) of the hexagonal lattice in the purple membrane (Grigorieff et al., 1996 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Secondly, the in-membrane orientation of the aR2 trimer is identical to that of the bR trimer in the purple membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>This similarity can be explained by taking into account the outline of the trimeric structure on the extracellular side, which is approximated by a truncated triangle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Since there is no direct protein–protein interaction between neighbouring trimers in the same membrane (Fig. 3 ▶), it is rational to suppose that the lipid molecules filling the inter-trimer space play an important role in maintaining the two-dimensional hexagonal arrays of the aR2 or bR trimer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>It was observed, however, that most of the lipid molecules filling the inter-trimer space were apparently disordered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>One possible explanation for such disorder is that claret membrane contains a special lipid component that destroys the local threefold symmetry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Such a lipid distribution may be effective at creating a flexible lipid environment that may be necessary for the protein to undergo large structural changes during the proton-pumping cycle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2.</label><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Structure of the proton-release channel   </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The high-resolution diffraction data from the H32 crystal allowed us to accurately determine the conformations of two glutamates (Glu199 and Glu209) present in the proton-release channel (Fig. 2 ▶ g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>When the structural model was refined using REFMAC5, the distance between Glu199 OE2 and Glu209 OE1 was determined to be 2.3 Å (Fig. 5 ▶ b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>(A slightly longer distance was evaluated when the structure was refined by CNS with default parameters.) This short distance suggests that the paired structure of Glu199 and Glu209 is maintained by a low-barrier hydrogen bond. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Glu199 OE2 is directed towards the main-chain amide NH of the same residue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>This conformation of Glu199 is nearly identical to that observed in the P321 or P63 crystal (Fig. 1 ▶ a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>When the protein structure in the H32 crystal is compared with that found in the C2221 crystal, however, a significant difference is observed in the proton-release channel (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>5 ▶ a and 5 ▶ b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Namely, the extracellular end of helix C moves outwards when the lipid distribution around the protein is disturbed during the crystallization process of the C2221 crystal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>It appears that the proton-release channel takes on a closed conformation as long as the extracellular end of helix C interacts with the diphytanyl group of the native lipid that fills the central opening of the aR2 trimer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3.</label><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Structure of the retinal-binding pocket   </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The retinal chromophore bound to the ∊-amino group of Lys220aR2 in helix G adopts the all-trans configuration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Although most residues in the retinal-binding pocket are highly conserved in proton-pumping archaeal rhodopsins, Met145 in bR is replaced by phenylalanine (Phe150) in aR2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Owing to this replacement, the polyene chain of retinal adopts a less curved conformation in aR2 than in bR (Fig. 6 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>This difference can explain the large blue shift in the visible absorption band of retinal (λmax ≃ 550 nm in aR2 versus λmax ≃ 570 nm in bR). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Another effect of the Met145bR→Phe150aR2 replacement is seen as a noticeable shift in the indole ring of the tryptophan residue (Trp182bR, Trp187aR2) in contact with the C13 methyl group of retinal towards helix G. Previous structural analysis of the K and L states of bR have shown that the relaxation of retinal into a planar 13-cis configuration in the K-to-L transition is accompanied by a noticeable movement in the indole ring of Trp182bR towards Met145bR and a large rotation of the side chain of Leu93bR (Fig. 6 ▶, model shown in yellow; Matsui et al., 2002 ▶; Kouyama et al., 2004 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>It is noteworthy that in aR2 the motional freedom of the tryptophan residue (Trp187aR2) in contact with the C13 methyl of retinal is reduced by the Met145bR→Phe150aR2 replacement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Thus, it would be expected that the K-to-L transition is slowed down in aR2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>To examine this possibility, we measured the absorption kinetics of aR2 under various solvent conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Fig. 7 ▶ shows the flash-induced absorption changes in aR2 observed in an aqueous suspension of claret membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>At pH 6, the absorption kinetics data were fitted with four exponential components. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The difference spectrum associated with the P1 component exhibits a positive peak at 580 nm and a negative peak at 410 nm, suggesting that the K state decays directly into the M state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>This transition is followed by the M-to-N transition (the P2 component with a positive peak at 410 nm and a negative peak around 560 nm), the N-to-O transition (the P3 component with a positive peak at 520 nm and a negative peak at 640 nm) and the process of recovering the initial state (the P4 component with a positive peak at 640 nm and a negative peak at 560 nm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>At a higher pH (e.g. at pH 9) the decay rate of N became lower, making it difficult to separately describe the decay kinetics of the N and O states. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, the decay kinetics of the K and M states remained unaltered over a wide pH range (pH 5–9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Under the investigated solvent conditions, the photocycle of aR2 can be described by the scheme K→M→N→O→aR2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Compared with the photocycle of bR (K→L→M→N→O→bR; Lozier et al., 1992 ▶), the photoreaction of aR2 is peculiar in that the L state is not detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>It is noteworthy that the lifetime of the K state of aR2 (∼40 µs) is much longer than that observed in bR (∼1 µs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>It is probable that the L state is undetectable because the decay rate of L is much higher than the decay rate of K. Together with the crystallographic data, the absorption kinetics data suggest that the L state is destabilized when the structure in the cytoplasmic vicinity of retinal is made rigid. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4.</label><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Structure of the N-terminal polypeptide   </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Compared with other proton-pumping rhodopsins, the structure of aR2 is peculiar in that its N-terminal polypeptide (Phe4–Pro12) folds into an Ω-loop (Fig. 8 ▶ b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>This loop structure is maintained by hydrogen bonds between the side chain of Asp5 and the main-chain amide NH atoms of three residues (Asn8, Asp9 and Gly10; Fig. 8 ▶ b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The side chain of Arg11 (and Glu13 at the extracellular end of helix A) interacts with Tyr84, which is located at the cytoplasmic end of helix C. This interaction contributes to fixation of the Ω-loop. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The structure of the N-terminal polypeptide in the H32 crystal is nearly identical to that observed in the P321 or P63 crystals, in which the aR2 trimers are packed in different fashions (Yoshimura &amp; Kouyama, 2008 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>This suggests that the structure of the Ω-loop is strongly built, although the B factors of the main-chain atoms are high unless the wobbling motion of the Ω-loop is suppressed by protein–protein interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>It is noteworthy that the amino-acid sequence in the Ω-loop is highly conserved among members of the archaerhodopsin family (Mukohata et al., 1991 ▶; Ihara et al., 1999 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the N-terminal region of aR1 folds into the same Ω-loop as observed in aR2 (Enami et al., 2006 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Since this loop interacts with the extracellular end of helix C, it seems possible that this loop may play a role in stabilizing the native conformation of the proton-release channel. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>It has previously been proposed that the segregation of membrane proteins in biological membranes can be explained by a hydrophobic matching principle related to the difference in lipid bilayer hydrophobic thickness and protein hydrophobic length (Sabra &amp; Mouritsen, 1998 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>It is noteworthy that in the H32 crystal the side chains of hydrophobic residues (Phe4 and Leu6) in the N-terminal region of aR2 are directed towards a crystallographic threefold axis (Fig. 8 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>These residues contribute to a substantial increase in protein hydrophobic length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>This peculiar structural feature may confer aR2 with a high ability to assemble into a two-dimensional crystalline array. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Indeed, it was observed that aR2-containing claret membrane was reluctant to disassemble in the presence of 50 mM nonylglucoside at 30°C, whereas the purple membrane of H. salinarum was completely solubilized under the same condition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="sec4"><label>4.</label><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Discussion   </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>It is shown here that two glutamates (Glu199aR2 and Glu209aR2) in the proton-release channel form a paired structure that is maintained by a low-barrier hydrogen bond. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>This same conformation of the proton-release complex has been observed in the P622 crystal of bR, the P321 crystal of cruxrhodopsin-3 and the R32 crystal of deltarhodopsin-3, all of which were prepared by the membrane-fusion method (Okumura et al., 2005 ▶; Yoshimura &amp; Kouyama, 2008 ▶; Zhang et al., 2013 ▶; Chan et al., 2014 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that the P622 crystal of bR has an absorption peak at 568 nm in the neutral pH range (pH 4–9), whereas alkalization above pH 9.5 causes a noticeable blue shift of the visible absorption band (Okumura et al., 2005 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Diffraction data from the P622 crystal soaked at high pH levels have shown that the alkaline transition is accompanied by reorientation of the carboxyl group of Glu194bR towards Tyr83bR (Fig. 1 ▶ b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>It is interesting to note that the conformation of Glu194bR in the alkaline pink conformer is very similar to that observed in the C2 crystal of bR (Fig. 1 ▶ b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>This similarity suggests that the transition to the alkaline pink conformer occurs at a much lower pH in the C2 crystal than in the P622 crystal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>It is conceivable that the neutral purple form of bR is destabilized when the local pH at the membrane surface is substantially increased by the partial removal of negatively charged native lipids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>In fact, the lipid component (for example triglycolipid) observed in the P622 crystal is partially removed or missing in other crystal forms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that the neutral purple form is destabilized in bR-containing vesicles reconstituted with egg lethicin, in which the transition from the neutral purple form into an inactive red form with λmax at 480 nm takes place at pH 6.5 (Nasuda-Kouyama et al., 1990 ▶). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>With respect to the protein structure in the P63 crystal, Glu194 OE2 in the structural model solved at 1.55 Å resolution (PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=1c3w">1c3w</ext-link>) has an unusually large B factor (62 Å2; Luecke et al., 1999 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>(The B factor of Glu199 OE2 of aR2 in the H32 crystal is 31 Å2.) It is possible that the conformation of Glu194bR in the P63 crystal represents a mixed state between the neutral purple form and the alkaline pink form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>There is another caveat to the structural model of bR that was built using the P63 crystal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Although the model building was performed on the supposition that the lipid molecules filling the intra-trimer or inter-trimer space are distributed with threefold symmetry, this supposition may not be correct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>In fact, the lipid head groups are not included in any reported model of bR determined using the P63 crystal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>For example, three triglycolipids are shown to bind to the central opening of the bR trimer in the P622 crystal, whereas this lipid component is missing in the P63 crystal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Since a step of protein solubilization is included in the preparation procedure of the P63 crystal, it is likely that the lipid distribution around the protein is altered at a pre-crystallization stage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>If the Glu194/Glu204 paired structure is already broken in the unphotolyzed state, the energetic barrier to a light-induced structural change in the proton-release channel would be lowered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that the rising rate of the M state of bR is much higher in the P63 crystal than in native purple membrane or the P622 crystal (Royant et al., 2001 ▶; Yamamoto et al., 2009 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is not surprising to find that the L state generated in the P63 crystal is structurally different from that observed in the P622 crystal (Royant et al., 2000 ▶; Kouyama et al., 2004 ▶; Lanyi &amp; Schobert, 2003 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>For example, a large swing of the side chain of Arg82 towards Glu194 is seen in the former model, whereas this swing is not seen in the latter model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Instead, the K-to-L transition in the P622 crystal is accompanied by a large structural change in the cytoplasmic vicinity of retinal, including a noticeable movement of the indole ring of Trp182bR towards Met145bR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>This light-induced structural change is in line with the present observation that the L state is destabilized when the motional freedom of the tryptophan in contact with the C13 methyl group is reduced by the Met145bR→Phe150aR2 replacement (Fig. 6 ▶). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>PDB reference: <ext-link ext-link-type="pdb" xlink:href="3wqj">archaerhodopsin-2, 3wqj</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></p></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>We thank the staff of BL38B1 at SPring-8, Harima, Japan for technical assistance during data collection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by a grant-in-aid from the Ministry of Education, Science and Culture of Japan. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bb1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Belrhali, H., Nollert, P., Royant, A., Menzel, C., Rosenbusch, J. P., Landau, E. M. &amp; Pebay-Peyroula, E. (1999). Structure, 7, 909–917. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb2"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Brünger, A. T., Adams, P. D., Clore, G. M., DeLano, W. L., Gros, P., Grosse-Kunstleve, R. W., Jiang, J.-S., Kuszewski, J., Nilges, M., Pannu, N. S., Read, R. J., Rice, L. M., Simonson, T. &amp; Warren, G. L. (1998). Acta Cryst. D54, 905–921. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb3"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Chan, S. K., Kitajima, T., Fujii, R., Murakami, M., Ihara, K. &amp; Kouyama, T. (2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Submitted. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb4"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Chizhov, I., Chernavskii, D. S., Engelhard, M., Mueller, K. H., Zubov, B. V. &amp; Hess, B. (1996). Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>J. 71, 2329–2345. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb40"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Enami, N., Okumua, H. &amp; Kouyama, T. (2003). J. Photosci. 9, 320–322. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb6"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Enami, N., Yoshimura, K., Murakami, M., Okumura, H., Ihara, K. &amp; Kouyama, T. (2006). J. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Biol. 358, 675–685. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb7"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Ernst, O. P., Lodowski, D. T., Elstner, M., Hegemann, P., Brown, L. S. &amp; Kandori, H. (2014). Chem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Rev. 114, 126–163. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb8"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Essen, L.-O., Siegert, R., Lehmann, W. D. &amp; Oesterhelt, D. (1998). Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>USA, 95, 11673–11678. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb9"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Faham, S. &amp; Bowie, J. U. (2002). J. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Biol. 316, 1–6. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb10"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Grigorieff, N., Ceska, T. A., Downing, K. H., Baldwin, J. M. &amp; Henderson, R. (1996). J. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Biol. 259, 393–421. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb46"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Gushchin, I., Chervakov, P., Kuzmichev, P., Popov, A. N., Round, E., Borshchevskiy, V., Ishchenko, A., Petrovskaya, L., Chupin, V., Dolgikh, D. A., Arseniev, A. S., Kirpichnikov, M. &amp; Gordeliy, V. (2013). Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>USA, 110, 12631–12636. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb11"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Hayakawa, N., Kasahara, T., Hasegawa, D., Yoshimura, K., Murakami, M. &amp; Kouyama, T. (2008). J. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Biol. 384, 812–823. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb12"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Ihara, K., Umemura, T., Katagiri, I., Kitajima-Ihara, T., Sugiyama, Y., Kimura, Y. &amp; Mukohata, Y. (1999). J. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Biol., 285, 163–174. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb51"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Kouyama, T. &amp; Murakami, M. (2010). Photochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Photobiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Sci. 9, 1458–1465. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb13"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Kouyama, T., Nishikawa, T., Tokuhisa, T. &amp; Okumura, H. (2004). J. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Biol. 335, 531–546. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb54"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Lanyi, J. K. (2005). Biochim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Acta, 1757, 1012–1018. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb14"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Lanyi, J. K. &amp; Schobert, B. (2003). J. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Biol. 328, 439–450. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb15"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Lozier, R. H., Xie, A., Hofrichter, J. &amp; Clore, G. M. (1992). Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>USA, 89, 3610–3614. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb52"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Luecke, H. (2000). Biochim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Acta, 30, 133–156. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb16"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Luecke, H., Schobert, B., Richter, H. T., Cartailler, J.-P. &amp; Lanyi, J. K. (1999). J. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Biol. 291, 899–911. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb50"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Luecke, H., Schobert, B., Stagno, J., Imasheva, E. S., Wang, J. M., Balashov, S. P. &amp; Lanyi, J. K. (2008). Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>USA, 105, 16561–16565. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb17"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Matsui, Y., Sakai, K., Murakami, M., Shiro, Y., Adachi, S., Okumura, H. &amp; Kouyama, T. (2002). J. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Biol. 324, 469–481. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb18"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>McRee, D. E. (1993). Practical Protein Crystallography. San Diego: Academic Press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb19"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Mukohata, Y., Ihara, K., Uegaki, K., Miyashita, Y. &amp; Sugiyama, Y. (1991). Photochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Photobiol. 54, 1039–1045. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb20"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Murshudov, G. N., Skubák, P., Lebedev, A. A., Pannu, N. S., Steiner, R. A., Nicholls, R. A., Winn, M. D., Long, F. &amp; Vagin, A. A. (2011). Acta Cryst. D67, 355–367. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb21"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Nasuda-Kouyama, A., Fukuda, K., Iio, T. &amp; Kouyama, T. (1990). Biochemistry, 29, 6778–6788. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb23"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Oesterhelt, D. &amp; Stoeckenius, W. (1971). Nature New Biol. 233, 149–152. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb24"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Okumura, H., Murakami, M. &amp; Kouyama, T. (2005). J. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Biol. 351, 481–495. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb42"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Pebay-Peyroula, E., Rummel, G., Rosenbusch, J. P. &amp; Landau, E. M. (1997). Science, 277, 1676–1681. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb25"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Phatak, P., Ghosh, N., Yu, H., Cui, Q. &amp; Elstner, M. (2008). Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>USA, 105, 19672–19677. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb47"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Ran, T., Ozorowski, G., Gao, Y., Sineshchekov, O. A., Wang, W., Spudich, J. L. &amp; Luecke, H. (2013). Acta Cryst. D69, 1965–1980. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb26"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Royant, A., Edman, K., Ursby, T., Pebay-Peyroula, E., Landau, E. M. &amp; Neutze, R. (2000). Nature (London), 406, 645–648. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb27"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Royant, A., Edman, K., Ursby, T., Pebay-Peyroula, E., Landau, E. M. &amp; Neutze, R. (2001). Photochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Photobiol. 74, 794–804. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb28"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Sabra, M. C. &amp; Mouritsen, O. G. (1998). Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>J. 74, 745–752. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb43"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Sato, H., Takeda, K., Tani, K., Hino, T., Okada, T., Nakasako, M., Kamiya, N. &amp; Kouyama, T. (1999). Acta Cryst. D55, 1251–1256. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb29"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Spudich, J. L., Sineshchekov, O. A. &amp; Govorunova, E. G. (2014). Biochim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Acta, 1837, 546–552. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb30"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Steller, I., Bolotovsky, R. &amp; Rossmann, M. G. (1997). J. Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Cryst. 30, 1036–1040. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb32"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Takeda, K., Matsui, Y., Kamiya, N., Adachi, S., Okumura, H. &amp; Kouyama, T. (2004). J. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Biol. 341, 1023–1037. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb33"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Uegaki, K., Sugiyama, Y. &amp; Mukohata, Y. (1991). Arch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Biophys. 286, 107–110. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb34"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Vagin, A. &amp; Teplyakov, A. (2010). Acta Cryst. D66, 22–25. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb41"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Wada, T., Shimono, K., Kikukawa, T., Hato, M., Shinya, N., Kim, S. Y., Kimura-Someya, T., Shirouzu, M., Tamogami, J., Miyauchi, S., Jung, K.-H., Kamo, N. &amp; Yokoyama, S. (2011). J. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Biol. 411, 986–998. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb35"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Waschuk, S. A., Bezerra, A. G., Shi, L. &amp; Brown, L. S. (2005). Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>USA, 102, 6879–6883. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb55"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Winn, M. D. et al. (2011). Acta Cryst. D67, 235–242. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb36"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Yamamoto, M., Hayakawa, N., Murakami, M. &amp; Kouyama, T. (2009). J. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Biol. 393, 559–573. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb37"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Yoshimura, K. &amp; Kouyama, T. (2008). J. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Biol. 375, 1267–1281. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bb45"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Zhang, J., Mizuno, K., Murata, Y., Murakami, M., Ihara, K. &amp; Kouyama, T. (2013). Proteins, 81, 1585–1592. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>(a) The structure of the proton-release channel observed for the neutral purple form of bR in the P622 crystal (purple; PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=1iw6">1iw6</ext-link>; Matsui et al., 2002 ▶) is compared with those observed for aR2 in the P321 crystal (green; PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=2ei4">2ei4</ext-link>; Yoshimura &amp; Kouyama, 2008 ▶), cR3 in the P321 crystal (orange; PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=4jr8">4jr8</ext-link>; Chan et al., 2014 ▶) and dR3 in the R32 crystal (blue; PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=4fbz">4fbz</ext-link>; Zhang et al., 2013 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>(b) The structure of the proton-release channel observed for the neutral purple form of bR in the P622 crystal (purple) is compared with those observed for the alkaline pink form of bR in the P622 crystal (yellow; PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=1xok">1xok</ext-link>; Okumura et al., 2005 ▶), bR in the C2 crystal (PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=1brr">1brr</ext-link>; Essen et al., 1998 ▶) and bR in the P63 crystal (PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=1qhj">1qhj</ext-link>; Belrhali et al., 1999 ▶). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="d-70-02692-fig1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>(a, b, c) Protein packing in the hexagonal crystal of aR2 used in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>The protein arrangement is described by space group H32 (red broken lines) or C2 (solid blue lines). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>(d) Intermembrane protein–protein contacts on the cytoplasmic side. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>(e) Intermembrane protein–protein contacts on the cytoplasmic surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>(f, g) Distribution of water molecules (cyan spheres) in proton-uptake and proton-release channels. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="d-70-02692-fig2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>A 2F o − F c map contoured at 1.4σ (a) or 0.8σ (b, c) is superimposed on the structural model that was built in space group C2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Lipid molecules trapped in the central opening (the extracellular side) of the aR2 trimer are shown in green or brown. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="d-70-02692-fig3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>2F o − F c maps around the retinal chromophore (a) and the FG loop (b) contoured at 1.6σ are superimposed on the structural model that was built in space group H32. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="d-70-02692-fig4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>The structures of the extracellular half of helix C (a) and the proton-release channel (b) of aR2 in the H32 crystal (purple, yellow and cyan) are compared with those observed in the C2221 crystal (salmon; PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=1vgo">1vgo</ext-link>; Enami et al., 2006 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>(c) Structural differences between the H32 crystal and the P321 crystal (PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=2ei4">2ei4</ext-link>; blue; Yoshimura &amp; Kouyama, 2008 ▶) and between the H32 crystal and the C2221 crystal (orange). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>The deviation of the Cα atom is plotted against the residue number. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>(d) The B factors observed in the H32 crystal (magenta) and the P321 crystal (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>The B factor of the Cα atom is plotted against the residue number. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="d-70-02692-fig5"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>The structure of aR2 in the H32 crystal (green) is compared with those of the unphotolyzed state (salmon; PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=1iw6">1iw6</ext-link>; Matsui et al., 2002 ▶) and the L state (yellow; PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=1ucq">1ucq</ext-link>; Kouyama et al., 2004 ▶) of bR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="d-70-02692-fig6"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Flash-induced absorption changes in aR2 at pH 6 (a, b) and pH 9 (c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>(a) An aqueous suspension of claret membranes was excited with light pulses at 532 nm and absorption changes were recorded at various wavelengths. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>(b, c) The absorption kinetics in the time range from 0.003  to 90 ms were fitted with four components and the amplitude of each component was plotted against the wavelength of the light used for measurement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>The dashed line represents the absorption change observed ∼7 µs after the excitation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="d-70-02692-fig7"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>(a) Structural comparison of aR2 in the H32 crystal (green), bR in the P622 crystal (orange; PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=1iw6">1iw6</ext-link>; Matsui et al., 2002 ▶), cR3 in the P321 crystal (blue; PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=4jr8">4jr8</ext-link>; Chan et al., 2014 ▶) and dR3 in the R32 crystal (yellow; PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=4fbz">4fbz</ext-link>; Zhang et al., 2013 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>(b) The N-terminal region of aR2 in the H32 crystal (green) is compared with that of aR1 in the P43212 crystal (grey; PDB entry <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scripts.iucr.org/cgi-bin/cr.cgi?rm=pdb&amp;pdbId=1uaz">1uaz</ext-link>; Enami et al., 2003 ▶). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>(c) The outline of the inter-trimer space in the hexagonal lattice found in the H32 crystal of aR2, viewed from the extracellular side. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>The N-terminal region of aR2 is shown in magenta. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="d-70-02692-fig8"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="table1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Data-collection and final refinement statistics</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody valign="top"><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="3" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Data collection </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain> Space group </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>C2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>H32 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain> Resolution (Å) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>45.1–1.8 (1.85–1.80) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>45.1–1.8 (1.90–1.80) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="3" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain> Unit-cell parameters </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>   a (Å) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>108.6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>62.74 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>   b (Å) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>62.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>62.74 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>   c (Å) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>116.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>331.45 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>  α (°) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>90.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>90.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>  β (°) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>108.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>90.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>  γ (°) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>90.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>120.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain> No. of unique reflections </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>62577 (10063) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>21944 (3462) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain> Multiplicity </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>3.2 (3.2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>8.8 (9.0) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain> Data completeness (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>90.7 (100) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>91.3 (100) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>  R merge † (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>4.6 (45.1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>5.4 (50.0) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain> 〈I/σ(I)〉 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>17.3 (3.2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>28.5 (5.1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain> Mosaicity (°) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>0.50 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>0.48 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>Refinement </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain> Resolution limit (Å) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>15.0–1.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>15.0–1.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain> Protein residues </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>234 × 3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>1–234 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain> No. of lipids </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain> No. of waters </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>155 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>51 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>  R cryst ‡ (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>20.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>21.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>  R free (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>22.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>24.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="3" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain> R.m.s.d. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>  Bond lengths (Å) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>0.019 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>0.018 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>  Bond angles (°) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>1.95 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>2.03 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="3" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>  B factor (Å2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>  Protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>23.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>23.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>  Water </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>36.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>36.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>  Lipids </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>58.6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td style="" rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><text><SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>60.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1"><label>†</label><p>
<italic>R</italic>
<sub>merge</sub> = <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="d-70-02692-efi1.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="d-70-02692-efi2.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>, where <italic>I</italic>
<sub><italic>i</italic></sub>(<italic>hkl</italic>) is the intensity of an individual reflection and 〈<italic>I</italic>(<italic>hkl</italic>)〉 is the mean intensity obtained from multiple observations of symmetry-related reflections.</p></fn><fn id="tfn2"><label>‡</label><p>
<italic>R</italic>
<sub>cryst</sub> = <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="d-70-02692-efi3.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="d-70-02692-efi4.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif"/></inline-formula>. A randomly omitted 5% of the reflections were used for the calculation of <italic>R</italic>
<sub>free</sub>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
