<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4206407</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25337915</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-20335</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110341</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Organismal Evolution</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbial Evolution</subject><subj-group><subject>Viral Evolution</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbial Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Viral Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Viral Genome</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Medical Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbial Pathogens</subject><subj-group><subject>Viral Pathogens</subject><subj-group><subject>Reoviruses</subject><subj-group><subject>Rotavirus</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Virology</subject><subj-group><subject>Viral Classification</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular Biology Techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Genotyping</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Genetic Diversity of G3 Rotavirus Strains Circulating in Argentina during 1998–2012 Assessed by Full Genome Analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">G3 Rotavirus Circulating in Argentina</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Degiuseppe</surname><given-names>Juan Ignacio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>Gabriel Ignacio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">
<sup>¤</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stupka</surname><given-names>Juan Andrés</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Laboratorio de Gastroenteritis Virales, Instituto Nacional de Enfermedades Infecciosas, Administración Nacional de Laboratorios e Institutos de Salud (ANLIS) “Dr. Carlos G. Malbrán”, Buenos Aires, Argentina</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Instituto de Investigaciones en Ciencias de la Salud, Universidad Nacional de Asunción, Asunción, Paraguay</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Arthur</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Children's Medical Research Institute, Australia</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>jdegiuseppe@anlis.gov.ar</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: JID GIP JAS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: JID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: JID GIP JAS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JID JAS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: JID GIP JAS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="fn1" fn-type="current-aff"><label>¤</label><p><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Current address: Laboratory of Infectious Diseases, National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland, United States of America </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e110341</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Degiuseppe et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Degiuseppe et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Seasonal shifts in the predominant strains and the periodic emergence of new strains are epidemiological features of human rotaviruses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>After the sporadic detection in two samples in 1998, G3P[8] strains reemerged as the predominant rotavirus during 2008–2009 in Argentina. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Notably, in 2011 6.3% (37/587) of samples presented the G3P[6] genotypes, which coincided with the recent detection of G3P[6] and G2P[6] strains in South America and Europe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Analyses of the 11 gene segments of four G3P[8] and two G3P[6] strains revealed that G3P[8] strains detected a decade apart (1998 and 2009) presented minor differences, while the G3P[6] strains presented a complete different genomic constellation albeit showing a similar VP7 gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>This study provides insights in the dynamics and evolution of one of the genotypes with the wider range of hosts and inter-species transmission potential. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The authors have no funding or support to report.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="7"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper.</p></notes></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Group A rotaviruses are the leading cause of sporadic acute diarrhea in young children worldwide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>It is estimated that rotaviruses are associated with over 450,000 deaths in that age group, most of them in developing countries [1]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Rotavirus genome comprises 11 segments of double-stranded RNA (dsRNA), which are surrounded by a triple layered capsid protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The outermost proteins of the capsid (VP7 and VP4) are responsible for eliciting neutralizing antibodies, and therefore the major targets for vaccine development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Genetic and antigenic differences within the VP7 and VP4 have been used to classify rotavirus into G and P types, respectively [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Despite that multiple genotypes (27 G types and 37 P types) have been described [3]–[4], only few of them are predominant in humans (i.e. G1P[8], G2P[4], G3P[8], G4P[8], and G9P[8]) [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Seasonal changes in the predominant strain and the periodic emergence of uncommon strains (like G12 or G8), are hallmarks of rotavirus epidemiology [5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Rotaviruses evolve through multiple genetic mechanisms, such as accumulation of point mutations, reassortment, and intragenic recombination [6]–[10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The analysis of the 11 genome segments has shown to be a useful tool to assess the evolutionary relationships among different strains, track reassortment events, and understand the origins of uncommon rotavirus [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Based on genetic analyses, each genome segment has been classified into multiple genotypes, and large-genome analyses revealed the association of genotypes that are known as genome constellations [11]–[12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Our laboratory has been leading the National Rotavirus Strain Surveillance Network from Argentina, and rotavirus-positive samples from different geographical regions of the country have been characterized since 1996. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Overall, G1P[8] rotaviruses were the most frequently detected in Argentina, followed by G4P[8], G2P[4]-which showed a cyclic pattern of predominance every 7 years-, and G9P[8] -which emerged in 2006- [13]–[17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>G3P[8] is one of the most common rotavirus strains in humans worldwide; however, in Argentina were sporadically detected (2/1764, 0.11%) from 1997–2007 [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In 2008, an increased frequency of detection of G3P[8] strains was observed reaching up to 54.1% of the strains analyzed in 2009 [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, in 2011 the genotype G3P[6] was first detected in Argentina in 37 samples (6.3%) [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>This finding coincided with the recent detection of G3P[6] and G2P[6] strains in Brazil and Belgium [20]–[21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Two different rotavirus vaccines, Rotarix and RotaTeq, are being use for children immunization in different countries [22]–[23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>These vaccines have been licensed in 2006 in Argentina, but until now they were not included into the National Immunization Program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Thus, their use is restricted to the private health sector, and estimations have shown that only 10% of the live birth cohort received the vaccine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Efficacy of vaccines depends in multiple factors, such as malnutrition, presence of maternal antibodies and the circulating strains [24]–[25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Thus, robust surveillance systems and the understanding of rotavirus evolution will help us to evaluate the future vaccination programs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>To gain insights into the genomic characteristics and evolution of G3 strains detected in Argentina, we sequenced the 11 gene segments of four G3P[8] and two G3P[6] strains, which revealed that G3P[8] strains from a decade apart (1998 and 2009) presented minor differences, while the G3P[6] strain that emerged in 2011 presented a complete different genomic constellation, albeit showing a similar VP7 gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Sample collection and G and P typing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Rotavirus-positive samples were detected by ELISA or immunochromatography by Sentinel Units across the country, and sent to the Rotavirus National Reference Laboratory for further genotype characterization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>G and P typing was performed by reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) followed by nested-multiplex PCR with consensus and type-specific primers [26]–[28]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Complete genome characterization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>To analyze the diversity of G3 strains, nearly the full length (&gt;95%) of their genome was sequenced in six strains: 2 G3P[8] from 1998 (Arg1240 and Arg1759), 2 G3P[8] from 2009 (Arg6795 and Arg7338) and 2 G3P[6] from 2011 (Arg9448 and Arg9467). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The two G3P[8]-2009 and two G3P[6]-2011 strains were randomly selected from a much larger collection of G3P[8] (n = 720) and G3P[6] (n = 37) strains circulating during 2009–2011. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In over 50% of this collection, RNA migration in polyacrilamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>All the G3P[8] strains presented the same long electropherotype, and all the G3P[6] presented the same short electropherotype (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Thus, high similarity for strains bearing the same G and P association was assumed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Viral dsRNA was extracted using automated QIAcube protocols (Qiagen, CA, USA), and the 11 segments were amplified by RT-PCR using Qiagen One Step RT-PCR kit (Qiagen, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>PCR products were purified with a QIAQuick PCR purification kit (Qiagen, CA, USA) and the sequencing was performed using the dideoxynucleotide chain termination method with the BigDye Terminator v3.1 Cycle Sequencing kit (Applied Biosystems, CA, USA) on a 3500Dx Genetic Analyzer automated sequencer (Applied Biosystems, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Primers targeting the conserved 5′- and 3′-end regions as well as internal primers were used for RT-PCR and sequence reactions (primer sequences are available upon request). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>All gene contigs were assembled with a coverage of 2× or more. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The nucleotide sequences have been deposited in GenBank under accession numbers KJ583136-KJ583157 (Arg1240 and Arg1759), KJ583158-KJ583179 (Arg6795 and Arg7338) and KJ583180-KJ583201 (Arg9448 and Arg9467). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Sequence and phylogenetic analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The analyses were conducted on the G3 strains reported in this work, as well as different strains in which the eleven genes sequences were available in GenBank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The alignments were carried out using BioEdit v7.0.1 [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide and amino acid differences were calculated using p-distance model, and the phylogenetic trees were reconstructed for each of the 11 gene segments using the neighbor-joining method, Tamura-Nei (TN93) as substitution model and gamma-distributed rate variation among sites as implemented in MEGA version 6 [30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Genomic Constellation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Sequencing of two representative G3 strains from three different seasons (1998, 2009 and 2011) was conducted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Overall, G3 strains detected in the same season were nearly identical between them (&gt;99% at nucleotide level). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analyses of the four G3P[8] strains showed a Wa-like (I1-R1-C1-M1-A1-N1-T1-E1-H1) genome constellation, while G3P[6] strains presented a DS1-like (I2-R2-C2-M2-A2-N2-T2-E2-H2) backbone (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Analyses of the nucleotide identity among the G3 strains from the three seasons confirm the genetic differences among the G3P[8] and G3P[6] strains in all genes but VP7 (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0110341-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110341.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis and genotype assessment. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic trees of (a) viral proteins and (b) non-structural protein coding gene segments of relevant rotavirus strains used for comparison with the Argentinean G3P[8] and G3P[6] strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Trees were calculated with the neighbour-joining method, Tamura-Nei substitution model (TN93) and gamma-distributed rate variation among sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Bootstrap values were calculated using 1000 replicates (values &gt;70% are shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The Argentinean G3P[8] strains detected in 1998 are marked with an empty circle, the G3P[8] strains detected in 2008/9 with filled circle, the Argentinean G3P[6] strains with filled square, and an Argentinean G12P[8] strain with a diamond. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0110341.g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0110341-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110341.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Genetic differences among Argentinean G3 strains. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide identities among the G3 Argentinean strains belonging to the three studied seasons are shown in different bars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Cut-off values for genotype assignment are indicated for each gene with dash lines. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0110341.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Comparison of Argentinean G3 strains </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analyses of the VP7 gene clustered all Argentinean G3 strains within the major lineage of human G3 (lineage I), and all the VP7 genes showed 95.3% and 96.2% of similarity at nucleotide and amino acid level, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Examination of individual amino acid changes in the VP7 revealed that 11 changes were observed between G3P[8] strains and the G3P[6] strains, 3 of them located at antigenic sites (D100N, from antigenic region 7–1a and A146V and A221D, from antigenic region 7–2) (Fig. 3a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>With regards to the VP4 gene, the G3P[8] strains grouped in P[8]-3 lineage (most common lineage in humans), while the P[6] strains grouped in P[6]-1a lineage along with other human P[6] strains (Fig. 1a) [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>As expected, the VP4 gene segments of the P[8] and P[6] strains showed similarities around 70% at nucleotide level (Fig. 2), and more than 165 amino acid changes along the complete protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>When comparing the G3P[8] strains that were detected a decade apart (i.e. G3P[8]-1998 and G3P[8]-2009 strains), their VP7 showed just one amino acid change in a non antigenic site (Y235H), while their VP4 presented 15 amino acid changes, two of them (N113D and S114P) located in a protective antigenic site (8–3) (Fig. 3a, b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>When analyzing the remaining nine genes, despite presenting the same Wa-like constellation, G3P[8]-1998 and G3P[8]-2009 strains grouped in different clusters in 6 of them (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>It is noteworthy that for three gene segments (VP1, VP3, and NSP4), all the strains analyzed were grouped by temporal patterns (i.e. strains circulating before and after year 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The highest amino acid difference was observed in NSP1, with 80 amino acid changes (18.5%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>With the exception of the VP6 and NSP1, the phylogenetic trees revealed that the Argentinean G3P[8]-2009 strains were more closely related to the contemporary G3P[8] strains detected in USA, than the Argentinean G3P[8]-1998 (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0110341-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110341.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Differences in antigenic sites among the Argentinean G3 strains and the vaccine strains. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Amino acid residues in VP7 (a) and VP4 (b) antigenic sites are shown for the three different Argentinean strains and vaccine strains. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0110341.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Analyses of the Argentinean G3P[6]-2011 genes showed that despite presenting a typical Genotype 2 constellation, all of them clustered distantly from the prototype strain DS1 (G2P[4]); and more closely related to the G3P[6] and G2P[6] strains recently detected in Belgium and USA [19]–[20], respectively (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The VP7 from South American and European G3P[6] strains shared the same amino acid sequence, except for one residue (D100N) located in the antigenic region 7–1a (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Comparison between Argentinean and Belgian strains showed nearly identical amino acid sequences in the VP4 gene segment, with only two residues changes at position 460 and 581 (VP5 region). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Only the VP8* region of the VP4 was available for the Brazilian strains, and they presented the same amino acid sequence among them and the Argentinean and Belgian strains. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Comparison of Argentinean G3P[8] and G12P[8] strains circulating in the same season </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>During 2008–2009, G12P[8] and G3P[8] strains co-circulated at similar frequencies in Argentina [18]; however, in most of the cities where the survey was conducted one strain predominated over the other one (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>We previously shown that the G12P[8] strains presented a Wa-like (Genotype 1) genome constellation [18], and comparison with the G3P[8]-2009 strains showed that they grouped in the same genotype but different clusters in all the 11 genes but VP7 gene (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>With the exception of the G type specificity, amino acid comparison showed high degree of similarity (&gt;96.5%) between these two co-circulating strains (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0110341-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110341.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Rotavirus strain distribution in Argentina, 2009. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Surveillance for rotavirus strains was conducted in eight cities during 2008–2009 [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Frequency of detection for G12P[8], G3P[8] and other strains are shown in pie charts for each city. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0110341.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Comparison of Argentinean G3 strains with vaccine strains </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>When compared the G3 Argentinean strains and the VP7 and VP4 vaccine components, the Argentinean G3P[8] strains were more related (96.9% at amino acid level) to the G3 component (WI78-8) of the RotaTeq vaccine than the G3P[8] strains (94.8% at amino acid level). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Three residues from the antigenic region 7–1b were found to differed between the G3P[8] strains and WI78-8: A212T, K238N and D242N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Moreover, G3P[6] strains showed three additional changes at antigenic regions 7–1a (D100N) and 7–2 (A146V and A221D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Higher differences were seen when comparing Argentinean strains with Rotarix (a G1P[8] strain). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Twelve changes, four in each of the three VP7 antigenic regions, were observed for G3P[8] strains and thirteen changes were observed for the G3P[6] strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>When analyzing the VP4 gene, Argentinean G3P[8] strains were found to have six amino acid changes compared to Rotarix (all of them located at the VP8* region), and only four differences with RotaTeq (three at VP8* region and one at VP5* region). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, G3P[6] strains showed 14 amino acid changes with Rotarix (all of them at antigenic sites of VP8* region) and 16 residues changes with RotaTeq (15 of them at the antigenic sites of VP8* region and one at the VP5* region) (Fig. 3a, b). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>G3 rotaviruses are considered one of the most frequently detected strains worldwide [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>This genotype presents the broadest host range (infecting humans, pigs, horses, cows, rabbit, cats, dogs, among others) and, consequently, the highest number of P type associations (i.e. P[2], P[3], P[6], P[7], P[8], P[9], P[12], P[14], P[22], P[24]) described for any other rotavirus G type [31]–[34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Despite this extreme diversity, a single G and P combination (G3P[8]) is the most prevalent G3 infecting humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>G3P[8] strains have been described circulating at low rates during the 1990s worldwide, but its re-emergence has been widely documented in the last decade [35]–[40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Its increased frequency in most of the countries is supposed to be at expenses of the decrease of frequencies of G1P[8] and G9P[8] [18], [41]–[42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>In Latin America, G3P[8] has been barely detected (i.e. &lt;0.5%) [43]–[44] until recently, when &gt;39% of the rotavirus strains circulating in Argentina during 2008–2010 presented this G and P combination [18]–[19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>To gain insights into the characteristics that may lead to G3P[8] to prevail in Argentina since 2009, we compared the genomes of G3P[8] shown circulating a decade apart, and with the newly emergent G3P[6] strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>All G3 strains from this study presented very low heterogeneity in the VP7 protein and, despite of being detected 10 years apart, no significant amino acid changes at the VP7 and VP4 proteins were detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Multiple changes at different antigenic regions were described in the recently emergent G3P[8] strains in different countries of Asia [39]–[40], [45]–[46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>However, the low heterogeneity of VP7 and VP4 after 10 years rules out that major antigenic changes accounted for the re-emergence of G3P[8] strains in Argentina. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>When we examined the genomic differences among the Argentinean G3P[8]-1998 and G3P[8]-2009, minor differences can be detected for most of the genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The major differences were observed in NSP1 gene segment, which is the one implicated in viral antagonism of the interferon response from the host [47]–[48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Several studies had indicated this protein as the most variable among rotavirus strains (i.e. sequence identities below 40% among mammalian rotaviruses) [47], [49]–[50], and those differences are implicated in the ability of rotavirus to antagonize the innate immune responses of the host [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Thus, the differences presented by G3P[8] in the NSP1 may play a role in the better fitness of the 2009 strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Of note is that in some genes (VP1, VP3 and NSP4), there is a temporal clustering of the strains; where G3 strains circulating after 2000 cluster together regardless of the country of detection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Thus, there seems to be a turning point in the evolution of G3 that lead to the re-emergence after of the low prevalence in the human population during 1990s. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Besides of the VP7 gene, G3P[8]-2009 strains presented the same genomic backbone than the G12P[8] strains, which co-circulated in the same season in Argentina [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The fact that both (G3 and G12) strains presented the same genetic backbone and alternated the predominance in different cities during the same season [18], suggest that the strains might be competing for the same susceptible population and one excludes the other one in a given geographical location (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Although, it remains unclear how an emergent strain acquires advantages over others and predominate at a given time and space, possible explanations may reside at multilevel factors ranging from host susceptibility to environmental aspects. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>As G3 strains seem to be spreading more efficiently since 2000s, unusual associations are therefore more predisposed to be detected infecting human (i.e. G3P[4] and G3P[10]) [52]–[53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>In Argentina, novel G3P[6] strains were detected at considerable rates in 2011 (i.e. 6.3%), unlike the low prevalence described in a recent Latin American meta-analysis (i.e. 0.2%) [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>These strains presented, except for the VP7 gene segment, a genotype 2 constellation backbone (DS1-like) of human origin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Recently, G3P[6] strains were reported in Brazil and Belgium [20]–[21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Comparison between the Argentinean G3P[6] strains and these reported recently in other countries, showed high similarity and clustering in all 11 gene segments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, one amino acid difference at the VP7 antigenic region 7-1a was observed between South American and European strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>This finding reflects the efficiency and speed by which rotaviruses evolve for optimal regional spreading. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Although G3P[6] strains presented genotype 2 constellation, they were found to be more closely related to strains bearing P[6] genotype than to DS-1 prototype strain [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>This fact reinforces the evidence of a probable Asian/African origin with a rapid spread through the world, rather than being an intergenotypic reassortant originated from two independent gene-exchanging steps. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Argentinean G3P[8] strains showed fewer amino acid changes than G3P[6] strains with the RotaTeq G3 vaccine component. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>When compared the VP4 antigenic sites, P[8] strains were found to be more closely related to RotaTeq than Rotarix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The fact that G3P[8] strains are more similar to vaccine components than G3P[6] strains seems to represent a challenge to current vaccines for the latter strain because of the higher number of differences at antigenic sites, i.e. a P[6] component with a DS-1 like backbone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Because coverage of vaccine do not exceeds 10% of Argentinean live birth cohort, the emergence and variation of strains within our country seems to reflect a natural fluctuation of rotavirus; however, we cannot rule out that massive vaccination in neighboring countries could play a role in emergence of new strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Rotaviruses constantly show us unpredicted scenarios; therefore robust and continuous epidemiological surveillance must be conducted with the goal of understanding rotavirus dynamics and evolution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0110341-Tate1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>1 TateJ, BurtonAH, Boschi-PintoC, SteeleAD, DuqueJ, et al (2012) WHO-coordinated Global Rotavirus Surveillance Network (2012) 2008 estimate of worldwide rotavirus-associated mortality in children younger than 5 years before the introduction of universal rotavirus vaccination programmes: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet Infect Dis 12: 136–141.22030330 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Estes1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>2Estes MK, Kapikian AZ (2007) Rotaviruses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>In Fields Virology, edn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>5, Edited by Knipe DM, Howley PM, Griffin DE, Lamb RA, Martin MA, Roizman B, Straus SE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Kluwer Health/Lippincott, Williams and Wilkins, pp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>1917–1974. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Matthijnssens1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>3 MatthijnssensJ, CiarletM, McDonaldSM, AttouiH, BányaiK, et al (2011) Uniformity of rotavirus strain nomenclature proposed by the Rotavirus Classification Working Group (RCWG). Arch Virol 156: 1397–1413.21597953 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Trojnar1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>4 TrojnarE, SachsenröderJ, TwardziokS, ReetzJ, OttoPH, et al (2013) Identification of an avian group A rotavirus containing a novel VP4 gene with a close relationship to those of mammalian rotaviruses. J Gen Virol 94: 136–142.23052396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Santos1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>5 SantosN, HoshinoY (2005) Global distribution of rotavirus serotypes/genotypes and its implication for the development and implementation of an effective rotavirus vaccine. Rev Med Virol 15: 29–56.15484186 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Degiuseppe1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>6 DegiuseppeJI, BeltraminoJC, MillanA, StupkaJA, ParraGI (2013) Complete genome analyses of G4P[6] rotavirus detected in Argentinean children with diarrhea provides evidence of interspecies transmission from swine. Clin Microbiol Infect 19: E367–371.23586655 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Ghosh1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>7 GhoshS, ShintaniT, UrushibaraN, TaniguchiK, KobayashiN (2012) Whole-genomic analysis of a human G1P[9] rotavirus strain reveals intergenogroup-reassortment events. J Gen Virol 93: 1700–1705.22592265 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Maunula1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>8 MaunulaL, Von BonsdorffCH (2002) Frequent reassortments may explain the genetic heterogeneity of rotaviruses: analysis of Finnish rotavirus strains. J Virol 76: 11793–11800.12414921 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Parra1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>9 ParraGI, BokK, MartinezM, GomezJA (2004) Evidence of rotavirus intragenic recombination between two sublineages of the same genotype. J Gen Virol 85: 1713–1716.15166456 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Steyer1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>10 SteyerA, Poljsak-PrijateliM, Barlic-MaganjaD, MarinJ (2008) Human, porcine and bovine rotaviruses in Slovenia: evidence of interspecies transmission and genome reassortment. J Gen Virol 89: 1690–1698.18559940 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Matthijnssens2"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>11 MatthijnssensJ, CiarletM, HeimanE, ArijsI, DelbekeT, et al (2008) Full genome-based classification of rotaviruses reveals a common origin between human Wa-like and porcine rotavirus strains and human DS-1-like and bovine rotavirus strains. J Virol 82: 3204–3219.18216098 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Matthijnssens3"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>12 MatthijnssensJ, Van RanstM (2012) Genotype constellation and evolution of group A rotaviruses infecting humans. Curr Opin Virol 2: 426–433.22683209 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Bok1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>13 BokK, PalaciosG, SijvargerK, MatsonD, GomezJ (2001) Emergence of G9P[6] human rotaviruses in Argentina: phylogenetic relationships among G9 strains. J Clin Microbiol 39: 4020–4025.11682524 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Bok2"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>14 BokK, CastagnaroN, BorsaA, NatesS, EspulC, et al (2001) Surveillance for rotavirus in Argentina. J Med Virol 65: 190–198.11505463 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Castello1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>15 CastelloAA, ArgüellesMH, RotaRP, OlthoffA, JiangB, et al (2006) Molecular epidemiology of group A rotavirus diarrhea among children in Buenos Aires, Argentina, from 1999 to 2003 and emergence of the infrequent genotype G12. J Clin Microbiol 44: 2046–2050.16757596 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Stupka1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>16 StupkaJA, ParraGI, GómezJ, ArbizaJ (2007) Detection of human rotavirus G9P[8] strains circulating in Argentina: phylogenetic analysis of VP7 and NSP4 genes. J Med Virol 79: 838–842.17457923 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Stupka2"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>17 StupkaJA, CarvalhoP, AmarillaAA, MassanaM, ParraGI, et al (2009) Argentinean National Surveillance Network for Diarrheas (2009) National rotavirus surveillance in Argentina: high incidence of G9P[8] strains and detection of G4P[6] strains with porcine characteristics. Infect Genet Evol 9: 1225–1231.19631763 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Stupka3"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>18 StupkaJA, DegiuseppeJI, ParraGI, the Argentinean National Rotavirus Surveillance Network (2012) Increased frequency of rotavirus G3P[8] and G12P[8] in Argentina during 2008–2009: Whole-genome characterization of emerging G12P[8] strains. J ClinVirol 54: 162–167. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Degiuseppe2"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>19 DegiuseppeJI, GiovacchiniC, StupkaJA, the Argentinean National Rotavirus Surveillance Network (2013) Rotavirus epidemiology and surveillance in Argentina: 2009–2011. Arch Arg Pediatr 111: 148–154 [Article in spanish]  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Heylen1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>20 HeylenE, ZellerM, CiarletM, De CosterS, Van RanstM, et al (2013) Complete genetic characterization of human G2P[6] and G3P[6] rotavirus strains. Infect Genet Evol 13: 27–35.22982160 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-daSilvaSoares1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>21 da Silva SoaresL, de Fátima Dos Santos GuerraS, do Socorro Lima de OliveiraA, da Silva Dos SantosF, de Fátima Costa de MenezesEM, et al (2013) Diversity of rotavirus strains circulating in Northern Brazil after introduction of a rotavirus vaccine: High prevalence of G3P[6] genotype. J Med Virol 86: 1065–1072.24136444 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Linhares1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>22 LinharesAC, VelazquezFR, Perez-SchaelI, Saez-LlorensX, AbateH, et al (2008) Efficacy and safety of an oral live attenuated human rotavirus vaccine against rotavirus gastroenteritis during the first 2 years of life in Latin American infants: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase III study. Lancet 371: 1181–1189.18395579 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Ciarlet1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>23 CiarletM, SchödelF (2009) Development of a rotavirus vaccine: clinical safety, immunogenicity, and efficacy of the pentavalent rotavirus vaccine, RotaTeq. Vaccine 27 (Suppl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>6)G72–G81.20006144 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Matthijnssens4"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>24 MatthijnssensJ, BilckeJ, CiarletM, MartellaV, BanyaiK, et al (2009) Rotavirus disease and vaccination: impact on genotype diversity. Future Microbiol 4: 1303–1316.19995190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Patel1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>25 PatelMM, ParasharUD (2009) Assesing the effectiveness and public health impact of rotavirus vaccines after introduction in immunization program. J Infect Dis 200 (S1): S291–299. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Das1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>26 DasBK, GentschJR, CicirelloHG, WoodsPA, GuptaA, et al (1994) Characterization of rotavirus strains from newborns in New Delhi, India. J Clin Microbiol 32: 1820–1822.7929782 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Gentsch1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>27 GentschJR, GlassRI, WoodsP, GouveaV, GorzigliaM, et al (1992) Identification of group A rotavirus gene 4 types by polymerase chain reaction. J Clin Microbiol 30: 1365–1373.1320625 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Gouvea1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>28 GouveaV, GlassRI, WoodsP, TaniguchiK, ClarkHF, et al (1990) Polymerase chain reaction amplification and typing of rotavirus nucleic acid from stool specimens. J Clin Microbiol 28: 276–282.2155916 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Hall1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>29 HallT (1999) BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NT. Nucleic Acids SympSer 41: 95–98. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Tamura1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>30 TamuraK, StecherG, PetersonD, FilipskiA, KumarS (2013) MEGA6: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis version 6.0. Mol Biol Evol 30: 2725–2729.24132122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Gentsch2"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>31 GentschJR, LairdAR, BielfeltB, GriffinDD, BányaiK, et al (2005) Serotype diversity and reassortment between human and animal rotavirus strains: implications for rotavirus vaccine programs. J Infect Dis 192 (S1): S146–S159. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Lee1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>32 LeeJB, YounSJ, NakagomiT, ParkSY, KimTJ, et al (2003) Isolation, serologic and molecular characterization of the first G3 caprine rotavirus. Arch Virol 148: 643–657.12664291 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Martella1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>33 MartellaV, PratelliA, GrecoG, GentileM, FiorenteP, et al (2001) Nucleotide sequence variation of the VP7 gene of two G3-type rotaviruses isolated from dogs. Virus Res 74: 17–25.11226570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Martella2"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>34 MartellaV, CiarletM, CamardaA, PratelliA, TempestaM, et al (2003) Molecular characterization of the VP4, VP6, VP7, and NSP4 genes of lapine rotaviruses identified in Italy: emergence of a novel VP4 genotype. Virology 314: 358–370.14517088 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Cashman1"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>35 CashmanO, CollinsPJ, LennonG, CryanB, MartellaV, et al (2012) Molecular characterization of group A rotaviruses detected in children with gastroenteritis in Ireland in 2006–2009. Epidemiol Infect 140: 247–259.21396145 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-DeGrazia1"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>36 De GraziaS, MartellaV, ColombaC, CascioA, AristaS, et al (2009) Genetic characterization of G3 rotaviruses detected in Italian children in the years 1993–2005. J Med Virol 81: 2089–2095.19856472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-IturrizaGmara1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>37 Iturriza-GómaraM, DallmanT, BányaiK, BöttigerB, BuesaJ, et al (2011) Rotavirus genotypes co-circulating in Europe between 2006 and 2009 as determined by EuroRotaNet, a pan-European collaborative strain surveillance network. Epidemiol Infect 139: 895–909.20707941 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-MartnezLaso1"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>38 Martínez-LasoJ, RománA, RodriguezM, CerveraI, HeadJ, et al (2009) Diversity of the G3 genes of human rotaviruses in isolates from Spain from 2004 to 2006: cross-species transmission and inter-genotype recombination generates alleles. J Gen Virol 90: 935–943.19264637 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Thongprachum1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>39 ThongprachumA, Chan-itW, KharimP, OkitsuS, NishimuraS, et al (2013) Reemergence of new variant G3 rotavirus in Japanese pediatric patients, 2009–2011. Infect Genet Evol 13: 168–174.23123146 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Wang1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>40 WangY, KobayashiN, ZhouX, NagashimaS, ZhuZ, et al (2009) Phylogenetic analysis of rotaviruses with predominant G3 and emerging G9 genotypes from adults and children in Wuhan, China. J Med Virol 81: 382–389.19107964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Mitui1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>41 MituiMT, ChanPK, NelsonEA, LeungTF, NishizonoaA, et al (2011) Co-dominance of G1 and emerging G3 rotaviruses in Hong Kong: A three-year surveillance in three major hospitals. J Clin Virol 50: 325–333.21330195 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Phan1"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>42 PhanTG, TrinhQD, KhamrinP, KaneshiK, UedaY, et al (2007) Emergence of new variant rotavirus G3 among infants and children with acute gastroenteritis in Japan during 2003–2004. Clin Lab 53: 41–48.17323824 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Castello2"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>43 CastelloAA, ArvayML, GlassRI, GentschJ (2004) Rotavirus strain surveillance in Latin America. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>A review of the last nine years. Pediatr Infect Dis J 23: S168–S172.15502697 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Linhares2"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>44 LinharesAC, StupkaJA, CiapponiA, BardachAE, GlujovskyD, et al (2011) Burden and typing of rotavirus group A in Latin America and the Caribbean: systematic review and meta-analysis. Rev Med Virol 21: 89–109.21384462 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Dey1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>45 DeySK, ThongprachumA, IslamA, PhanGT, RahmanM, et al (2009) Molecular analysis of G3 rotavirus among infants and children in Dhaka City, Bangladesh after 1993. Infect Genet Evol 9: 983–986.19560559 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Trihn1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>46 TrihnQD, PhamNT, NguyenTA, PhanTG, KhramrinP, et al (2007) Amino acid substitutions in the VP7 protein of human rotavirus G3 isolated in China, Russia, Thailand, and Vietnam during 2001–2004. J Med Virol 79: 1611–1616.17705183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Arnold1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>47 ArnoldMM, PattonJT (2009) Rotavirus antagonism of the innate immune response. Viruses 1: 1035–1056.21994581 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Hu1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>48 HuL, CrawfordSE, HyserJM, EstesMK, PrasadBV (2012) Rotavirus non-structural proteins: structure and function. Curr OpinVirol 2: 380–388. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-McDonald1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>49 McDonaldSM, MatthijnssensJ, McAllenJK, HineE, OvertonL, et al (2009) Evolutionary dynamics of human rotaviruses: balancing reassortment with preferred genome constellations. PLoS Pathog 5: e1000634.19851457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-McDonald2"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>50 McDonaldSM, DavisK, McAllenJK, SpiroDJ, PattonJT (2011) Intra-genotypic diversity of archival G4P[8] human rotaviruses from Washington, DC. Infect Genet Evol 11: 1586–1594.21712102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Arnold2"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>51 ArnoldMM, BarroM, PattonJT (2013) Rotavirus NSP1 mediates degradation of interferon regulatory factors through targeting of the dimerization domain. J Virol 87: 9813–9821.23824805 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Mukherjee1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>52 MukherjeeA, MullickS, KobayashiN, Chawla-SarkarM (2012) The first identification of rare human group A rotavirus strain G3P[10] with severe infantile diarrhea in eastern India. Infect Genet Evol 12: 1933–1937.22981998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0110341-Tran1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>53 TranTN, NakagomiT, NakagomiO (2013) Evidence for genetic reassortment between human rotaviruses by full genome sequencing of G3P[4] and G2P[4] strains co-circulating in India. Trop Med Health 41: 13–20.23532829 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
