<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5471232</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3826</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-03826-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Improving the detection of pathways in genome-wide association studies by combined effects of SNPs from Linkage Disequilibrium blocks </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Huiying</given-names></name><address><email>huiying.zhao@qut.edu.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nyholt</surname><given-names>Dale R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Yuanhao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Jihua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6782-2813</contrib-id><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Yuedong</given-names></name><address><email>yuedong.yang@griffith.edu.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000089150953</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.1024.7</institution-id><institution>Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation, </institution><institution>Queensland University of Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>Brisbane, QLD Australia </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9870 9448</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.440709.e</institution-id><institution>Shandong Provincial Key Laboratory of Functional Macromolecular Biophysics, </institution><institution>Dezhou University, </institution></institution-wrap>Dezhou, Shandong China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0437 5432</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.1022.1</institution-id><institution>Institute for Glycomics, </institution><institution>Griffith University, Parkland Dr, </institution></institution-wrap>Southport, QLD Australia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>3512</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have successfully identified single variants associated with diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>To increase the power of GWAS, gene-based and pathway-based tests are commonly employed to detect more risk factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>However, the gene- and pathway-based association tests may be biased towards genes or pathways containing a large number of single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) with small P-values caused by high linkage disequilibrium (LD) correlations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>To address such bias, numerous pathway-based methods have been developed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Here we propose a novel method, DGAT-path, to divide all SNPs assigned to genes in each pathway into LD blocks, and to sum the chi-square statistics of LD blocks for assessing the significance of the pathway by permutation tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The method was proven robust with the type I error rate &gt;1.6 times lower than other methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, the method displays a higher power and is not biased by the pathway size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The applications to the GWAS summary statistics for schizophrenia and breast cancer indicate that the detected top pathways contain more genes close to associated SNPs than other methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>As a result, the method identified 17 and 12 significant pathways containing 20 and 21 novel associated genes, respectively for two diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The method is available online by <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sparks-lab.org/server/DGAT-path">http://sparks-lab.org/server/DGAT-path</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have successfully identified multiple single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) associated with many diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>However, most common risk variants can’t be detected for polygenic traits due to weak or moderate effect sizes to account for only a small fraction of the overall phenotypic variation1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Consequently, GWAS require enormous sample sizes to identify the majority of risk variants, which remains a considerable challenge for many traits. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Instead of increasing sample sizes, an alternative way is to detect genetic risk factors by aggregating variants over a gene2–4 or a cluster of genes5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>A natural way to define a cluster of genes is the biological pathway that includes a series of actions to produce certain products or changes in a cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>By integrating prior knowledge on genes, pathway analysis is becoming an effective approach to reveal underlying genetic structures of diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>For example, pathway analysis has been used to detect mechanisms of diseases using both gene expression6 and GWAS7, 8 data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Currently, the methods for pathway analysis on GWAS data are mainly divided into two classes according to the type of input data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The first class works with an input of raw genotype data, such as FPCA9 and GSEA-SNP10, 11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Their applications are limited because raw data is not always available (especially with the shift towards meta-analysis of GWAS summary statistics). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the other class requires only the association P-value for each GWAS SNP (i.e., GWAS summary statistics)12–14. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>With the relatively high speed and low data requirements, methods using GWAS summary statistics offer the greatest potential. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Usually, these methods assess pathway associations through gene associations that are often estimated from P-values of SNPs assigned to the genes via gene-based tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>For example, GSA-SNP represents each gene by the P-value of its k-th best SNP, and evaluates a pathway by calculating a summed Z-score on the P-values of its genes relative to the random chance13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>KGG14 selects the most significant genes according to gene association tests from GATES2, and uses the genes to assess the association of pathways through the hyper-geometric test15. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>One major issue with these approaches is their incomplete adjustment for linkage disequilibrium (LD) correlations between SNPs, where because of the non-random association of alleles at multiple loci due to LD, the statistical associations between alleles at different loci will be different from the expected independent alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the associations of pathways may bias genes containing a group of significant SNPs with strong LD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>To adjust for LD, many methods have been proposed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>For example, ALIGATOR16 preselects a list of significantly associated SNPs to avoid LD between SNPs, while it ignores other SNPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Genomicper17 considers the LD relationship within pathways by a special “circular genomic permutation” approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>These methods do not directly use the LD relationship of SNPs in estimating pathway association, and may not completely remove the influence of LD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>In contrast, another class of methods explicitly separates SNPs into LD blocks and employs LD blocks for assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>For example, ProxyGeneLD18 divides SNPs in a gene into LD blocks, and adjusts the lowest P-values by the number of LD blocks in the gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>This approach adjusts for LD between SNPs within a gene but ignores the LD between genes in the same pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>PARIS12 separates SNPs in a pathway into LD blocks and counts the number of associated blocks containing at least one significant SNP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The significance of the pathway is then measured by the chance to have a greater number of significant blocks through permutation testing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>However, the PARIS uses an arbitrary threshold to define significant SNPs and considers significant blocks equally. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Given that an extremely significant SNP should be interpreted differently from a marginally significant SNP, the consideration of all detailed P-values is preferable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In this study, we developed a new method, DGAT-path, to assess pathways based on detailed P-values of all LD blocks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>By selecting the most significant SNP (of the lowest P-value) for each LD block, the p-values are converted into chi-square statistics and summed over all blocks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The summed chi-square score is then compared to those by randomly sampling pathways (permutation), and the chance to have greater scores by the random represents the significance of the pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In this way, we avoid the arbitrary threshold used in PARIS, and could consider all LD blocks differently based on detailed P-values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The method, DGAT-path, was found to have lower type I error rate while consistently higher power than other methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Application to GWAS summary statistics for schizophrenia (SCZ) and breast cancer indicated that DGAT-path detected a higher percentage of associated genes according to the recent GWAS Catalog. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>GWAS dataset </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>In this study, we used meta-analysis summary statistics from genome-wide association studies (GWAS) on the schizophrenia (SCZ) and breast cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The SCZ summary statistics were downloaded from the Psychiatric Genomics Consortium (PGC) webpage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.med.unc.edu/pgc/downloads">http://www.med.unc.edu/pgc/downloads</ext-link>) on 2 June 2014, which includes 1,237,819 SNPs obtained from a schizophrenia GWAS of 9379 cases and 7736 controls19. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The breast cancer summary statistics were downloaded from the dbGAP with accession number “phs000147.v1.pl”, including 483,123 SNPs obtained from a breast cancer GWAS of 1142 controls and 1145 cases20. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Pathway dataset </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>A comprehensive pathway dataset was built by collecting the data from KEGG21, BioCarta22, Gene ontology23, REACTOME24, and PANTHER25 that were downloaded in July 2015. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>This led to a dataset including 5,764 pathways and 15,718 genes after removing any pathway containing too many (&gt;300) or too few (&lt;5) genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The pathways were evenly separated into four ranges by the number of involved genes: [5, 9], [10, 16], [17, 36] and [37, 300], where 10, 17, 37 are 25th, 50th, and 75th percentiles of all pathway sizes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Finally, the four ranges include 1747, 1457, 1382, and 1178 pathways, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Methods for comparison </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>We downloaded KGG from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://grass.cgs.hku.hk/limx/kgg/">http://grass.cgs.hku.hk/limx/kgg/</ext-link>, GSA-SNP from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/gsa-snp/">https://sourceforge.net/projects/gsa-snp/</ext-link>, MAGMA (MAGMA-pval-1k version) from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ctg.cncr.nl/software/magma">https://ctg.cncr.nl/software/magma</ext-link>, PARIS from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ritchielab.psu.edu/software/paris-download">https://ritchielab.psu.edu/software/paris-download</ext-link>, and Genomicper from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/genomicper/index.html">https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/genomicper/index.html</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>For all methods, the default parameters were utilized in the analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>We didn’t compare ALIGATOR because it is developed specifically for only the Gene Ontology pathways. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Pathway analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Briefly, as shown in Fig. 1, we first collect all SNPs within genes belonging to a pathway and divide them into blocks according to LD correlations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>By representing each LD block with the most significant SNP (of the lowest P-value) inside the block, a score is calculated by summing the chi-square statistics converted from the P-value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The significance of the pathway is defined as the chance to observe the summed chi-square score after randomly sampling pathways (permutation).Figure 1The workflow of DGAT-path to assess pathway associations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Gene sets were obtained from the UCSC genome browser RefSeq (hg19) [downloaded on Mar 20, 2014]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Overlapping isoforms of a gene were combined to form a single full-length version of the gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>For isoforms that didn’t overlap, the isoform containing the most significant SNP (i.e., of the lowest P-value) was kept. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>This led to 23,438 unique genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>We assigned SNPs to a gene if they mapped to between 15 kb 5′ to the 5′ transcription start site (TSS) and 15 kb 3′ to the 3′ transcription end site (TES). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The 15 kb gene boundary extension was chosen because 90% of SNPs affecting expression quantitative trait loci (eQTLs) were observed within this proximity26. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>We employed the package GEC27 to divide the SNPs into LD blocks so that the SNPs mapped to a pathway with LD correlations (r 2) higher than 0.1 were grouped in the same LD block. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The pairwise LD correlations were calculated by PLINK28 based on 1,000 Genomes Project genotype data (CEU). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The lowest nominal P-value of SNPs in each block was converted to upper-tail chi-square statistics with one degree of freedom, and summed up to provide the observed score (S obs) for each pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>To calculate a pathway’s significance that is not biased by pathway sizes, we assigned SNPs to pathways, and separated them into LD blocks using the same procedure, from which the same numbers of LD blocks were randomly sampled to calculate permuted scores (S perm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The probability of producing a permuted score larger than the observed pathway score was defined as the association P-value of the pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>A lower association P-value indicated a more significantly associated pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The random sampling was repeated for 1,000 to 1,000,000 times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>To speed up the calculations, the sampling will stop when a permuted P-value is &gt;0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>In order to directly assess the impact of ignoring LD correlations between pathways, we developed another pathway analysis method, named DGAT-path (gene) that only divided SNPs into LD blocks if the SNPs mapped to the same gene (rather than the same pathway). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>This method is similar to the KGG method except that DGAT-path (gene) uses a permutation test, whereas KGG uses the hyper-geometric test to assess pathway significance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Simulation studies for the type I error rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Simulated pathways were generated by randomly assigning genes to pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Through this way, biological relationships were broken between genes while the LD correlations between SNPs were kept. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Importantly, this approach needs only GWAS summary statistics, which is different from previous approaches that require original genotype and/or phenotype data to permute phenotype labels or perform genomic randomization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The process was repeated for 1,000 times to generate 1,000 copies of random pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>By testing each method on the dataset, the percentage of pathways with P-values below 0.05 was calculated as the type I error rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the type I error rates were separately calculated on pathways of four size ranges to measure the impact of the pathway size. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Power estimation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The power was defined as the proportion of pathways with association P-value below 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>For each tested pathway, we multiplied P-values of all SNPs by one factor so that there are a certain percentage of significant SNPs (P-value &lt; 0.05) for the pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>This is based on a hypothesis that pathways are equally significant if they have exactly the same percentage of significant SNPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Here, we tested four different percentages of significant SNPs at 30%, 50%, 70%, and 80%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>In order to measure the influence of pathway sizes, we have calculated power separately for pathways with different sizes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Simulation studies of type I error rate </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>As shown in Fig. 2(a), DGAT-path consistently has the lowest type I error rate to detect significant pathways in the random dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>By comparison, DGAT-path (gene) without considering the LD correlations between genes in pathways constantly increases the error rate by a factor of 50%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>KGG has similar performance to the DGAT-path (gene): KGG has a higher type I error rate at low nominal P-value, but lower rate from a nominal P-value of 0.08. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>These differences are likely caused by different implementation of KGG and DGAT-path (gene). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The MAGMA approach shows a slightly but consistently higher error rate than the DGAT-path (gene). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>GSA-SNP and Genomicper have similar type I error rates that are consistently higher than those of other methods, except for PARIS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>While, PARIS shows significantly higher type I error rates that are 1.9 to 4.6 times higher than GSA-SNP.Figure 2Comparisons of methods by (a) the type I error rate and (b) the power at different nominal P-values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>To inspect the impact of pathway size, we calculated type I error rates for four different ranges of pathway size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>As shown in Fig. 3(a), DGAT-path has a stable type I error rate around 3% for all sizes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>DGAT-path (gene) and KGG have similar type I error rates on average (~4.5%), while KGG shows a clear trend of increasing error rates with pathway sizes, which is likely due to an over-estimate of the significance of larger pathways, as large pathways tend to contain more SNPs (genes) in LD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>MAGMA has consistently higher type I error rates than DGAT-path (gene). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Genomicper and GSA-SNP have similar and higher type I error rates than previous methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>PARIS has significantly higher type I error rates than the other methods for all pathway sizes (Figure S1).Figure 3Comparisons of methods under different pathway sizes and percentages of significant SNPs by (a) the type I error rates and (b) the power at the nominal P-value of 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Power estimation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>As shown in Fig. 2(b), DGAT-path outperforms all other methods in power at all nominal P-values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>When compared with KGG, although our method is marginally better at a nominal P-value of 0.02, the differences enlarge with an increase in nominal P-value thresholds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>At a nominal P-value of 0.1, DGAT-path has 14% higher power than KGG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Similar to the type I error rate, DGAT-path (gene) has a higher power than KGG at low nominal P-values, while a lower power at a nominal P-value &gt; 0.08. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>PARIS has a stable power of around 0.6 for all four nominal P-values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The power of Genomicper increases from 0.2 to 0.56 when nominal P-values increase from 0.01 to 0.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>MAGMA has a stable power of around 0.35 that is mostly lower than those by Genomicper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>GSA-SNP has the lowest power. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Fig. 3(b) shows the power of four methods at different pathway sizes and percentages of significant SNPs (P-value &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>DGAT-path, DGAT-path (gene), and KGG methods show an increasing power with an increased percentage of significant SNPs or pathway size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>This is expected given that an increase in the number of significant SNPs will decrease the probability to detect the same effective pathways randomly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>In regard to the size of pathways, DGAT-path can clearly detect more pathways of small size than others, which is presumably due to the benefit of dividing pathways into LD blocks and permutation test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the DGAT-path (gene) and KGG methods appear to be upwardly biased by significant genes having highly correlated SNP associations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>This bias enlarges with an increase in the number of genes within a pathway, and small pathways tend to be downwardly biased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Although two gene-based methods, KGG and DGAT-path (gene), detect more large-sized pathways for SNPs enrichment of 30%, they have a 1.8 and 3 times increase in the type I error rate, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The other four methods have considerably lower power compared to DGAT-path in all cases, and rank as follows from highest to lowest power: PARIS, Genomicper, MAGMA, to GSA-SNP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Comparing methods by identification of gene associations reported by GWAS Catalog for the SCZ and breast cancer </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The methods cannot be assessed by directly comparing the detected pathways because there is no gold standard to determine truly associated pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Such comparison is further complicated given the potential impact of incomplete adjustment for LD correlation between genes mapping to the same pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Here, we compared all methods according to the percentage of included associated genes within top detected pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>A higher percentage of associated genes indicate that the method is more likely to select truly associated pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The associated genes were selected as genes closest to SNPs with at least genome-wide suggestive association (P &lt; 1 × 10−5) within the GWAS catalog database29, last updated in year 2016. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Because pathways contain varying numbers of genes, we show the percentage of associated genes versus the total number of genes involved in different pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>As shown in Fig. 4(a), the DGAT-path generally detected higher percentages of significant genes for SCZ compared to the other pathway methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>For the first two detected pathways, the percentages of DGAT-path are &gt;1.6 times higher than other methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The difference decreases with an increase in the number of included genes because only a limited number of genes have been detected by GWAS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Hence, we have limited the number of included pathways so that total number of included genes is less than 1000. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>KGG has all but the 2nd point below the curve of DGAT-path. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The sparse points of KGG in the beginning resulted from its bias to pathways of big sizes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Although KGG implicated a higher percentage compared to GSA-SNP for the number of genes below 500, the two methods produce very similar results for larger pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>MAGMA shows similar, but consistently lower percentages compared to DGAT-path. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Genomicper and PARIS generally have the lowest percentages of associated genes.Figure 4The percentages of genes overlapping with the associated genes from recent GWAS catalogs as a function of the total number of genes in different numbers of top pathways detected by methods on the datasets of (a) SCZ (b) breast cancer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>When applied to the breast cancer data, as shown in Fig. 4(b), DGAT-path performs the best, and has stable ~4% overlapping genes when the top associated pathways contain &gt;400 genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>KGG has close but consistently lower percentages than DGAT-path. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The other four methods appear to implicate similar percentages of genes in the GWAS catalog database, which are all lower than the percentages by DGAT-path and KGG. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Significant associations identified by DGAT-path for the SCZ and breast cancer </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>By considering multiple test burdens of ~5,000 pathways, the genome-wide threshold for pathway analysis was chosen as 1.1 × 10−5 (0.05/5,000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Under this threshold, 17 pathways were identified by our method as significantly associated with SCZ, detailed in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Among them, “voltage-gated calcium channel activity” is a well-known pathway associated with SCZ30, 31. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, “long-term depression” and “long-term potentiation” were identified significantly associated with SCZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Indeed, a recent investigation indicated the relationship between SCZ with these two pathways32. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Moreover, “postsynaptic density”, “ion channel binding pathway”, and “postsynaptic membrane pathway” have been found enriched with genes containing SCZ-related mutations33, 34. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The “Wnt signaling pathway” has been investigated to detect mutations on genes in SCZ and/or bipolar disorder patients35, 36, and the role of this pathway in SCZ has been examined to detect biomarkers37. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Additionally, 986 genes were included in the significant pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Among them, five genes were identified as significantly associated with SCZ by the original study38 and 20 novel genes were identified as significantly associated by the recent GWAS study with an expanded sample size39.Table 1Pathways identified by DGAT-path as significantly associated with SCZ and Breast cancer.Pathway IDPathway NameP-valueSCZGO:0007156Homophilic cell adhesion&lt;10−6 GO:0007628Adult walking behavior&lt;10−6 GO:0014069Postsynaptic density&lt;10−6 GO:0045211Postsynaptic membrane&lt;10−6 GO:0046415Urate metabolic process&lt;10−6 path:hsa04713Circadian entrainment&lt;10−6 path:hsa04724Glutamatergic synapse&lt;10−6 path:hsa04730Long-term depression&lt;10−6 GO:0005245Voltage-gated calcium channel activity1.9 × 10−6 P00019Endothelin signaling pathway1.9 × 10−6 REACT_18325Regulation of insulin secretion1.9 × 10−6 GO:0044325Ion channel binding3.0 × 10−6 path:hsa04270Vascular smooth muscle contraction6.9 × 10−6 GO:0007169Transmembrane receptor protein tyrosine kinase signaling pathway6.9 × 10−6 path:hsa04720Long-term potentiation6.9 × 10−6 P00057Wnt signaling pathway7.9 × 10−6 path:hsa04261Adrenergic signaling in cardiomyocytes8.9 × 10−6 Breast CancerGO:0002456T cell mediated immunity&lt;9.9. × 10−7 GO:0003964RNA-directed DNA polymerase activity&lt;9.9 × 10−7 GO:0005751Mitochondrial respiratory chain complex IV&lt;9.9 × 10−7 GO:0007506Gonadal mesoderm development&lt;9.9 × 10−7 GO:0019031Yiral envelope&lt;9.9 × 10−7 GO:0042287MHC protein binding&lt;9.9 × 10−7 GO:0042989Sequestering of actin monomers&lt;9.9 × 10−7 GO:0050658RNA transport&lt;9.9 × 10−7 GO:0070544Histone H3-K36 demethylation&lt;9.9 × 10−7 P00012Cadherin signaling pathway&lt;9.9 × 10−7 GO:0045211Postsynaptic membrane&lt;9.9 × 10−7 GO:0045296Cadherin binding4.0 × 10−6  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>For the breast cancer GWAS summary statistics, DGAT-path identified 12 pathways with P-value below the threshold (1.1 × 10−5) (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The most significant pathways, “T cell mediated immunity” and “Viral envelope”, have previously been proven to be associated with breast cancer40–42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The significant pathways involve 431 candidate genes, among which fourteen genes have been collected by the Cancer Gene Census Category (CGC, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cancer.sanger.ac.uk/census/">http://cancer.sanger.ac.uk/census/</ext-link>) as known breast cancer genes (CDH11, CTNNB1, DNM2, EGFR, ERBB2, ERBB3, GOPC, GRIN2A, HNRNPA2B1, NDRG1, PICALM, STRN, TCF3, and TCF7L2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Another seven genes (CDH13, CDH7, CTNNA2, ERBB4, GRIK1, PCDH15, and TCF7L2) were reported as associated with the breast cancer by recent GWA studies43–47. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec13" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>In this study, we developed a new method, DGAT-path to assess pathway association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Through dividing SNPs in a pathway into LD blocks, a score is calculated by summing chi-square statistics converted from P-values of the most significant SNPs in each LD block. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Because the summed chi-square statistics for each pathway are independent, they follow a chi-square distribution with 2n degrees of freedom under the null hypothesis (n is the number of LD blocks in a pathway). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Thus, the summation of the observed independent chi-square statistics reflects the combination of effects of SNPs and provides a valid measure of pathway association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>To adjust for pathway size in estimating pathway association, we perform permutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The method is different from PARIS because PARIS uses a fixed P-value threshold (usually 0.05) to determine significant LD blocks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Additionally, PARIS counts the number of significant LD blocks, thus it considers all significant LD blocks equally, and totally ignores less significant LD blocks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>This may explain why PARIS has significantly lower performance than DGAT-path. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>In addition, PARIS requires setting a parameter to define the significant LD blocks, which may cause low power and high type I error rate when the threshold is not optimized. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The results indicated that the DGAT-path is less affected by pathway sizes with a stable type I error rate ranging from 2.7% to 3.7%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the type I error rate of KGG significantly enlarged with an increase in pathway size, most likely because larger pathways have a higher probability to include more correlations between gene association signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>This explanation was supported by the fact that DGAT-path (gene) shows increased type I error rates with an increase in the pathway sizes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Hence, these results support the necessity to adjust for LD correlation among genes in pathway analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>GSA-SNP appears to appropriately adjust for such potential bias of large pathways via its normalized Z-score by pathway size approach (showing no obvious relationship between the type I error rate and pathway size); however, GSA-SNP did not implicate as many genes according to GWAS catalog data as DGAT-path. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>This is most likely because GSA-SNP employs the average P-values of a gene set, which increase at the same time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Lastly, although MAGMA produced a lower type I error rate, it detected fewer pathways (had lower power) compared to GSA-SNP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Given that MAGMA was mainly developed for analysis of GWAS raw data, it might not be well optimized for the analysis of GWAS summary statistics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>For the power estimations, the traditional nominal P-value cutoff of 0.05 was initially selected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>When a more stringent threshold was utilized to account for testing multiple pathways, i.e., a P-value cutoff of 8.7 × 10−6 (0.05/5764), the power of DGAT-path remained the highest among the tested methods, having an average power of 1.4 times higher than KGG and 4 times higher than MAGMA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>While GSA-SNP detected very few associated pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Genomicper was utilized here by permutation at the SNP level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Genomicper requires a threshold to define the significant SNPs in the permutation test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>In this study, we used 0.05 as the threshold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The low performance of Genomicper may result from non-optimized threshold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>More details are included in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The running times of four methods were tested for pathways of three sizes on an intel i5 CPU of 2.6 GHz, and their runtimes are comparable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>As shown in Table S2, GSA-SNP is the fastest and needs eight and fourteen seconds for pathway containing six and 280 genes, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>DGAT-path ranks the second, and requires 12 and 34 seconds, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>These two methods show an increase of running time with increase of pathway size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>By comparison, MAGMA and PARIS have a closely constant running time for three pathway sizes, requiring 50 and 40 seconds, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Since KGG used GUI, its runtimes are not listed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Genomicper (setting the number of permutations to 100,000) took 185, 197, and 2239 seconds for three investigated pathway sizes, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>DGAT-path requires a simple file including chromosome, SNP name, p-value, and location, and a web server has been provided. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>DGAT-path can be applied to any pre-defined pathway databases, and GWAS summary statistics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Publisher's note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>This work has been supported by the National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) Early Career Fellowship (APP1091816) to H.Z., and the National Natural Science Foundation of China (61671107) to J.W. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>H.Z. &amp; Y.D.Y. designed the experiments, H.Z., D.R.N., Y.H.Y., W.J. &amp; Y.D.Y. wrote the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>1.YangJCommon SNPs explain a large proportion of the heritability for human heightNat Genet20104256556910.1038/ng.608<?supplied-pmid 20562875?>20562875 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>2.LiMXGuiHSKwanJSShamPCGATES: a rapid and powerful gene-based association test using extended Simes procedureAm J Hum Genet20118828329310.1016/j.ajhg.2011.01.019<?supplied-pmid 21397060?>21397060 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>3.LiuJZA versatile gene-based test for genome-wide association studiesAm J Hum Genet20108713914510.1016/j.ajhg.2010.06.009<?supplied-pmid 20598278?>20598278 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>4.ZhaoHFanDNyholtDRYangYEnrichment of SNPs in Functional Categories Reveals Genes Affecting Complex TraitsHum Mutat20163782082610.1002/humu.23007<?supplied-pmid 27113629?>27113629 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>5.BackesCSystematic permutation testing in GWAS pathway analyses: identification of genetic networks in dilated cardiomyopathy and ulcerative colitisBMC Genomics20141562210.1186/1471-2164-15-622<?supplied-pmid 25052024?>25052024 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>6.RezolaAAdvances in network-based metabolic pathway analysis and gene expression data integrationBrief Bioinform20151626527910.1093/bib/bbu009<?supplied-pmid 24626528?>24626528 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>7.EleftherohorinouHPathway analysis of GWAS provides new insights into genetic susceptibility to 3 inflammatory diseasesPLoS One20094e806810.1371/journal.pone.0008068<?supplied-pmid 19956648?>19956648 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>8.LeeYHKimJHSongGGGenome-wide pathway analysis in neuroblastomaTumour Biol2014353471348510.1007/s13277-013-1459-7<?supplied-pmid 24293394?>24293394 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>9.LuoLGenome-wide gene and pathway analysisEur J Hum Genet2010181045105310.1038/ejhg.2010.62<?supplied-pmid 20442747?>20442747 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>10.HoldenMDengSWojnowskiLKulleBGSEA-SNP: applying gene set enrichment analysis to SNP data from genome-wide association studiesBioinformatics2008242784278510.1093/bioinformatics/btn516<?supplied-pmid 18854360?>18854360 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>11.WangKLiMBucanMPathway-based approaches for analysis of genomewide association studiesAm J Hum Genet2007811278128310.1086/522374<?supplied-pmid 17966091?>17966091 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>12.YaspanBLGenetic analysis of biological pathway data through genomic randomizationHum Genet201112956357110.1007/s00439-011-0956-2<?supplied-pmid 21279722?>21279722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>13.NamDKimJKimSYKimSGSA-SNP: a general approach for gene set analysis of polymorphismsNucleic Acids Res201038W74975410.1093/nar/gkq428<?supplied-pmid 20501604?>20501604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>14.GuiHLiMShamPCChernySSComparisons of seven algorithms for pathway analysis using the WTCCC Crohn’s Disease datasetBMC Res Notes2011438610.1186/1756-0500-4-386<?supplied-pmid 21981765?>21981765 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>15.LiMXKwanJSShamPCHYST: a hybrid set-based test for genome-wide association studies, with application to protein-protein interaction-based association analysisAm J Hum Genet20129147848810.1016/j.ajhg.2012.08.004<?supplied-pmid 22958900?>22958900 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>16.ZhongHYangXKaplanLMMolonyCSchadtEEIntegrating pathway analysis and genetics of gene expression for genome-wide association studiesAm J Hum Genet20108658159110.1016/j.ajhg.2010.02.020<?supplied-pmid 20346437?>20346437 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>17.CabreraCPUncovering networks from genome-wide association studies via circular genomic permutation2012G3210671075 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>18.HongMGPawitanYMagnussonPKPrinceJAStrategies and issues in the detection of pathway enrichment in genome-wide association studiesHum Genet200912628930110.1007/s00439-009-0676-z<?supplied-pmid 19408013?>19408013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>19.Cross-Disorder Group of the Psychiatric Genomics, C.Identification of risk loci with shared effects on five major psychiatric disorders: a genome-wide analysisLancet20133811371137910.1016/S0140-6736(12)62129-123453885 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>20.HunterDJA genome-wide association study identifies alleles in FGFR2 associated with risk of sporadic postmenopausal breast cancerNat Genet20073987087410.1038/ng2075<?supplied-pmid 17529973?>17529973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>21.KanehisaMGotoSKEGG: kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomesNucleic Acids Res200028273010.1093/nar/28.1.27<?supplied-pmid 10592173?>10592173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>22.BeanDMesyN: Network Building, Sharing and PublishingPloS one20149e10603510.1371/journal.pone.0106035<?supplied-pmid 25181461?>25181461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>23.AshburnerMGene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The Gene Ontology ConsortiumNat Genet200025252910.1038/75556<?supplied-pmid 10802651?>10802651 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>24.CroftDReactome: a database of reactions, pathways and biological processesNucleic Acids Res201139D69169710.1093/nar/gkq1018<?supplied-pmid 21067998?>21067998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>25.ThomasPDPANTHER: a library of protein families and subfamilies indexed by functionGenome research2003132129214110.1101/gr.772403<?supplied-pmid 12952881?>12952881 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>26.PickrellJKUnderstanding mechanisms underlying human gene expression variation with RNA sequencingNature201046476877210.1038/nature08872<?supplied-pmid 20220758?>20220758 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>27.LiMXYeungJMChernySSShamPCEvaluating the effective numbers of independent tests and significant p-value thresholds in commercial genotyping arrays and public imputation reference datasetsHum Genet201213174775610.1007/s00439-011-1118-2<?supplied-pmid 22143225?>22143225 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>28.PurcellSPLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analysesAm J Hum Genet20078155957510.1086/519795<?supplied-pmid 17701901?>17701901 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>29.WelterDThe NHGRI GWAS Catalog, a curated resource of SNP-trait associationsNucleic Acids Res201442D1001100610.1093/nar/gkt1229<?supplied-pmid 24316577?>24316577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>30.QuachTTHonnoratJKolattukudyPEKhannaRDucheminAMCRMPs: critical molecules for neurite morphogenesis and neuropsychiatric diseasesMolecular psychiatry2015201037104510.1038/mp.2015.77<?supplied-pmid 26077693?>26077693 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>31.HallJTrentSThomasKLO’DonovanMCOwenMJGenetic risk for schizophrenia: convergence on synaptic pathways involved in plasticityBiological psychiatry201577525810.1016/j.biopsych.2014.07.011<?supplied-pmid 25152434?>25152434 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>32.HasanAInvestigations of motor-cortex cortical plasticity following facilitatory and inhibitory transcranial theta-burst stimulation in schizophrenia: a proof-of-concept studyJournal of psychiatric research20156119620410.1016/j.jpsychires.2014.12.006<?supplied-pmid 25555304?>25555304 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>33.PersTHComprehensive analysis of schizophrenia-associated loci highlights ion channel pathways and biologically plausible candidate causal genesHuman molecular genetics2016251247125410.1093/hmg/ddw007<?supplied-pmid 26755824?>26755824 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>34.IbrahimHMIonotropic glutamate receptor binding and subunit mRNA expression in thalamic nuclei in schizophreniaThe American journal of psychiatry20001571811182310.1176/appi.ajp.157.11.1811<?supplied-pmid 11058479?>11058479 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>35.LevchenkoABeta-catenin in schizophrenia: Possibly deleterious novel mutationPsychiatry research201522884384810.1016/j.psychres.2015.05.014<?supplied-pmid 26027441?>26027441 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>36.PandeyGNRizaviHSTripathiMRenXRegion-specific dysregulation of glycogen synthase kinase-3beta and beta-catenin in the postmortem brains of subjects with bipolar disorder and schizophreniaBipolar disorders20151716017110.1111/bdi.12228<?supplied-pmid 25041379?>25041379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>37.BousmanCANegative Symptoms of Psychosis Correlate with Gene Expression of the Wnt/beta-Catenin Signaling Pathway in Peripheral BloodPsychiatry journal2013201385293010.1155/2013/852930<?supplied-pmid 24236287?>24236287 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>38.Schizophrenia Psychiatric Genome-Wide Association Study, C.Genome-wide association study identifies five new schizophrenia lociNat Genet20114396997610.1038/ng.94021926974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>39.Schizophrenia Working Group of the Psychiatric Genomics, C.Biological insights from 108 schizophrenia-associated genetic lociNature201451142142710.1038/nature1359525056061 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>40.MartinetOT cell activation with systemic agonistic antibody versus local 4-1BB ligand gene delivery combined with interleukin-12 eradicate liver metastases of breast cancerGene therapy2002978679210.1038/sj.gt.3301687<?supplied-pmid 12040460?>12040460 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>41.de RicqlesDOlomuckiAGosselinFLidereauRBreast cancer and T-cell-mediated immunity to proteins of the mouse mammary tumour virus (MMTV)European cytokine network19934153160<?supplied-pmid 8391340?>8391340 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>42.EndoMHuman immunodeficiency virus-induced apoptosis of human breast cancer cells via CXCR4 is mediated by the viral envelope protein but does not require CD4Current HIV research20086344210.2174/157016208783571991<?supplied-pmid 18288973?>18288973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>43.ChungSA genome-wide association study of chemotherapy-induced alopecia in breast cancer patientsBreast Cancer Res201315R8110.1186/bcr3475<?supplied-pmid 24025145?>24025145 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>44.HaryonoSJDatasenaIGSantosaWBMulyarahardjaRSariKA pilot genome-wide association study of breast cancer susceptibility loci in IndonesiaAsian Pacific journal of cancer prevention: APJCP2015162231223510.7314/APJCP.2015.16.6.2231<?supplied-pmid 25824743?>25824743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>45.KimHCA genome-wide association study identifies a breast cancer risk variant in ERBB4 at 2q34: results from the Seoul Breast Cancer StudyBreast cancer research: BCR201214R5610.1186/bcr3158<?supplied-pmid 22452962?>22452962 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>46.MurabitoJMA genome-wide association study of breast and prostate cancer in the NHLBI’s Framingham Heart StudyBMC Med Genet20078Suppl 1S610.1186/1471-2350-8-S1-S6<?supplied-pmid 17903305?>17903305 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>47.SongNPrediction of breast cancer survival using clinical and genetic markers by tumor subtypesPLoS One201510e012241310.1371/journal.pone.0122413<?supplied-pmid 25867717?>25867717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
