<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ImpactJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Oncotarget</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1949-2553</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Impact Journals LLC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5471064</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28515345</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">15893</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.15893</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Genetic factors associated with risk of metabolic syndrome and hepatocellular carcinoma </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Ranran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Heng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Yingdi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Kaipeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Pengfei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Xiaoyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Juan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><sup>1</sup> Nanjing Maternity and Child Health Care Institute, Nanjing Maternity and Child Health Care Hospital, Obstetrics and Gynecology Hospital Affiliated to Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, China</aff><aff id="A2"><sup>2</sup> State Key Laboratory of Reproductive Medicine, Nanjing Maternity and Child Health Care Hospital, Obstetrics and Gynecology Hospital Affiliated to Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, China</aff><aff id="A3"><sup>3</sup> Department of Pediatrics, Nanjing Maternity and Child Health Care Hospital, Obstetrics and Gynecology Hospital Affiliated to Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, China</aff><aff id="A4"><sup>4</sup> Department of Endocrinology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold><italic>Correspondence to:</italic></bold><italic>Juan Wen,</italic><email>wenj2010@gmail.com</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2"><italic>Xiaoyun Liu,</italic><email>drliuxiaoyun@126.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>35403</fpage><lpage>35411</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2017 Tang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link> (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Although the metabolic syndrome is a commonplace topic, its potential threats to public health is a problem that cannot be neglected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>As the living conditions improved significantly over the past few years, the morbidity of metabolic syndrome has also steadily risen, and the onset age is becoming younger. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC), is one of the most prevalent life-threatening human cancers worldwide, incidence of which is also on the rise, gradually occupied the top of the list associated with metabolic syndrome related complication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Despite the advanced improvement of HCC management, the lifestyle, environmental factors, obesity, hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection have been recognized as risk factors for the development of liver cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>In recent years, genetic studies, especially the genome-wide association studies (GWASs) were widely performed, a new era of the human genome research was created, which has significantly promoted the study of complex disease genetics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>These progresses have contributed to the discovery of abundant number of genomic loci convincingly linked with complex metabolic feature and HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>In this review, we briefly summarize the association between metabolic syndrome and HCC, focusing on the genetic factors contributed to metabolic syndrome and HCC. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>genetic factors</kwd><kwd>metabolic syndrome</kwd><kwd>obesity</kwd><kwd>HCC</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Metabolic syndrome is a multi-pathological manifestation of syndrome, comprising obesity, dyslipidemia, insulin resistance, and type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2MD), etc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>These diseases are in a close connection with increased risk of hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) occurrence and development (Figure 1) [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Based on the existing study, insulin resistance, along with its associated adipocyte cytokines, hyperglycemia, and hyperinsulinemia may lead to hypertension and abnormal lipid profile, both of which will accelerate the progress of HCC [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>With the wildly performing of genome-wide association studies (GWASs) and gene sequencing, substantial genetic component compositions were proposed [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>For fat and lean mass in different body regions, including whole body and trunk fat mass, the heritability have been estimated to about 65% [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>It is supposed that distinction in fat distribution and illustration of genetic factors predisposing to adiposity could contribute to a further exploration of the phenotypic diversity and eventually make a more accurate disease sub-classification possible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>In the past few decades, huge efforts have been made to explore the common genetic factors in metabolic syndrome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>However, it is a challenging task at last for the extensive heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the pattern which have found common genetic variations associated with various symptoms and diseases, had been broken by the emergence of GWASs [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, pinpointing genes implicated in metabolic syndrome could be helpful to discover the latent biological pathways, which could be exploited in the development of medical treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Here, we briefly summarize the relationship between metabolic syndrome and HCC, focusing on the genetic factors contributed to metabolic syndrome and HCC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Association between metabolic syndrome and hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Metabolic syndrome is in a close connection with an increased risk of HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In obese patients, adipocyte cytokines may lead to abnormal lipid profile, and the body mass index (BMI) more than 30 kg/m2 could increase HCC risk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2MD), its relative hyperinsulinemia and hyper-insulin-like growth factor 1 (IGF-1) production, or synergistic actions with other variables, such as viral hepatitis and alcohol, all may contribute to the development of HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In addition, insulin resistance impaired the ability of insulin to suppress glucose production, and directly accelerate hepatocarcinogenesis via promoting cellular proliferation, inhibiting apoptosis and stimulating hepatic neovascularization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Moreover, bout 27% of non-alcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH)-associated hepatic cirrhosis eventually progresses to HCC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-08-35403-g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec></SecTag><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>ASSOCIATION BETWEEN METABOLIC SYNDROME AND HCC </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2_1"><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Obesity and hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Over the past few decades, the prevalence of obesity has sharp increased [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Overweight and obesity have been identified as independent risk factors for various cancers including liver cancer, breast cancer, endometrial cancer, colorectal cancer and esophagus cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>There is also a possible association between obesity and gallbladder, pancreas, thyroid and hematologic malignancies [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>For HCC, research showed that the body mass index (BMI) more than 30 kg/m2 could increase HCC risk [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Besides, HCC mortality rates in male with high BMI are 5 times higher than men of normal weight [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Comprehensive analysis including 11 studies from Asia, Europe and United States evidenced that both obesity (RR = 1.89) and overweight (RR = 1.17) were closely associated with the development of HCC [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>SEER-Medicare data analysis showed that adjusted OR of obesity for HCC was 1.93 [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The Metabolic Syndrome and Cancer Project (Me-Can) examined 578700 subjects from Austria, Norway and Sweden, showed RR of obesity for the development of HCC was 1.39 [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Danish and Korean boffins obtained similar conclusions after analyzing large cohorts of overweight patients [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>In addition, in a large retrospective cohort including 342 patients who transplanted liver for HCC, BMI was identified as an independent predictor of capillaries invasion [13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2_2"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) and HCC </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>For developing chronic liver disease and HCC, T2DM act as an independent risk factor [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In different cohort studies, the morbidity of HCC among those with diabetes rose from 1.5 to 4 times [10, 15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>A recent meta-analysis of 21 cohort studies demonstrated that the summary RR of HCC with T2DM was 1.86 (95% CI: 1.49-2.31) for patients with chronic liver disease [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>T2DM combined with its relative hyperinsulinemia and hyper-insulin-like growth factor 1 (IGF-1) production may also accelerate the development of HCC [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Diabetes seems to increase the risk of liver cancer by cooperating with other variables, such as viral hepatitis and alcohol [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, coexistent with diabetes appears to make the HCC relapse rate rise after curative therapy [19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2_3"><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Insulin resistance and HCC </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Insulin resistance is characterized by reduced sensitivity to insulin and, as a result, impaired ability of insulin to reduce peripheral blood glucose concentration [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>It is well established that insulin resistance act as a primary dominator that connects all the sections of metabolic syndrome [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>To overcome insulin resistance and maintain normal metabolic functions, insulin secretion is increased, leading to a state of compensatory hyperinsulinemia [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Insulin resistance may directly accelerate hepatocarcinogenesis via promoting cellular proliferation, inhibiting apoptosis and stimulating hepatic neovascularization [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>However, a 10-year prospective study from Korea of 1,298,385 patients showed that the risk of tumor was influenced by fasting blood glucose concentrations rather than insulin resistance, which challenges the theory that insulin directly effects on promotion of cancers [24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2_4"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) and HCC </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>NAFLD is the clinical manifestation in liver of metabolic syndrome [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>In Western countries and Asia, NAFLD is considered as the most common cause of chronic liver disease [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The clinic pathological classification of NAFLD include from extensive isolated steatosis (a milder form of hepatic adipose infiltration) to nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (a more severe form of hepatic adipose infiltration). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The clinical progress of simple steatosis is relatively gentle, but there are about one third of non-alcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH) affected subjects can develop into liver cirrhosis [26], and about 27% of NASH-associated hepatic cirrhosis eventually progresses to HCC [27, 28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>In recent years, NASH has been considered as an important pathogenic factor of HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Thus, since the prevalence of obesity, diabetes and metabolic syndrome continues to rise, a large proportion of the population will have a risk of developing NASH and cirrhosis, and ultimately liver cancer [29, 30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>SUSCEPTIBILITY LOCI FOR METABOLIC SYNDROME AND HCC </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The advances in genome technology, human genome deep sequencing, and the establishment of human variation cataloging, which helped the human genome analysis to create a new era, have further promoted the complex disease genetics research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>It was not until 2007 that the genetic map of complex diseases, such as obesity and HCC, had been preliminarily studied by genetic linkage analysis and candidate gene association studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>But for the potential limitations of the design, their application was limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>However, since 2007, through genome-wide association studies, there is a rocket increase in our understandings of specific genetic risk factors for adiposity, insulin resistance, T2MD, NAFLD and HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>These advances contributed a lot of convincing genetic loci related to the complex metabolic symptom and HCC [31]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s3_1"><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Obesity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The inheritance of obesity has been paid large attention and the genetic research of obesity has been the focus of research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The heritability of obesity is now universally thought to be range from 40% to 70% [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>In general, as of 2016, GWASs have successfully identified about 400 different loci associated with adiposity phenotypes [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/gwas/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/gwas/</ext-link>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The discoveries are mainly derived from individual studies and meta-analysis based on BMI as an indicator of obesity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Through GWAS, Frayling et al. reported the first BMI gene locus with significant statistical significance, which is a byproduct of the study for FTO gene associated with T2MD by GWAS [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>In 2008, a meta-analysis of GWASs from 16,876 European individuals replicated the FTO finding and also found another strong signal 188 kb downstream of the MC4R locus [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>In 2009, a paper reported a meta-analysis of GWASs from GIANT consortium, which included more than 32,000 individuals with independent replication from &gt;59,000 individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>They replicated the MC4R and FTO loci and reported six novel loci: TMEM18, SH2B1, GNPDA2, KCTD15, NEGR1, and MTCH2 [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>In 2012, a meta-analysis of GWASs for BMI in East Asians was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>They replicated seven previously identified loci (FTO, SEC16B, MC4R, GIPR-QPCTL, ADCY3-DNAJC27, BDNF and MAP2K5) and identified three additional loci in or near the CDKAL1, GP2, and PCSK1 genes [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>In 2013, Monda et al. conducted a meta-analysis in African individuals and identified two new loci in GALNT10 and MIR148A-NFE2L3 [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Then, Pei et al. carried out a meta-analysis of seven GWASs for BMI-related traits from diverse ethnic populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>They confirmed three previously reported obesity susceptibility loci in FTO, MC4R and TMEM18; and identified two novel loci in CTSS and NLK associated with fat body mass [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Recently, another meta-analysis among Asians was conducted by Wen et al. and four loci near the KCNQ1, ITIH4, NT5C2 and ALDH2/MYL2 genes were identified [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>FTO is a common susceptibility gene for BMI in Asian, African and European populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>And it remains the most influential gene, imposing an allelic 0.39 kg/m2 increase in BMI [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Besides, in 2011, Heid et al. published a meta-analysis of 32 GWASs of Waist-hip ratio (WHR) adjusted for BMI with follow-up of 16 loci in an additional 29 studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>They identified 13 novel loci in or near RSPO3, NFE2L3, VEGFA, TBX15-WARS2, ITPR2-SSPN, GRB14, DNM3-PIGC, HOXC13, ADAMTS9, LY86, ZNRF3-KREMEN1, CPEB4, and NISCH-STAB1 and the known signal at LYPLAL1 unique to fat distribution independently of BMI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>In 2013, a GWAS of WHR in up to 27,350 African individuals was performed and rs6931262 at RREB1 was identified for WHR adjusted for BMI [40]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3_2"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>T2DM </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Having a sibling with T2DM will increases the risk of T2DM by two to three times [41], suggesting genetic factors play an important role in T2DM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>As of 2016, more than 200 genetic loci have been identified as T2DM risk loci [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/gwas/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/gwas/</ext-link>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>In 2006, the risk variant in TCF7L2 was discovered by a positional linkage strategy in Iceland population [42], which remains the most influential common T2DM variant (allelic OR = ~1.46) [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Then it was successfully validated by several other GWASs [44–46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Soon, multiple T2DM loci were discovered by independent GWASs, such as SLC16A11, CDKAL1, FTO, HHEX, IGF2BP2, KCNJ11, PPARG, SLC30A8 et al.[44, 45, 47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>DIAGRAM conducted the first meta-analysis on T2DM comprising 10,128 European individuals at the discovery stage and identified six novel loci including ADAMTS9, CDC123-CAMK1D, JAZF1, NOTCH2, TSPAN8-LGR5, and THADA [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The second meta-analysis by DIAGRAM had a sample size of 8130 cases and 38,987 controls of European descent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Notably 12 T2DM loci harboring genes that included BCL11A, CENTD2, CHCHD9, HMGA2, DUSP9, ZBED3, HNF1A, KLF14, PRC1, KCNQ1, TP53INP1, and ZFAND6 were identified [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The third effort made by DIAGRAM included 26,488 cases and 83,964 controls of diverse ethnic populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Eight novel loci were discovered: ANK1, ANKRD55, BCAR1, CILP2, KLHDC5, MC4R, TLE1 and ZMIZ1 [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>In addition, AGEN-T2DM conducted a meta-analysis including approximately 55,000 individuals in East Asian populations and identified eight novel T2DM loci in European populations: MAEA, FITM2-R3HDML-HNF4A, GCC1-PAX4, GLIS3, KCNK16, PEPD, PSMD6 and ZFAND3 [51]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Although T2DM and obesity are highly interrelated from both epidemiological and pathophysiological viewpoints, they have few genetic risk loci in common. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Of 200 loci associated with T2DM and 400 loci associated with standard measures of adiposity, merely 11 loci are shared (CDKAL1, FTO, GIPR, KCNQ1, LINGO2, LYPLAL1, MC4R, TMEM18, GRB14, RREB1 and ZNF608), which may do not include shared associations below the level of genome-wide statistical significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>However, for SNPs primarily associated with BMI, there seems to be a positive correlation between the effect size on BMI and the effect of the same SNP on T2DM [31]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3_3"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Insulin resistance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The T2DM physiologic characteristics are pancreatic β-cell dysfunction and insulin resistance in the peripheral tissues and liver [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, T2DM susceptibility loci seldom map directly to insulin resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Multiple independent studies showed that the insulin resistance susceptibility loci included APOC3, GCKR, IRS1, IGF1, PPARG and so on [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>By 2016, about 70 genetic loci have been identified as insulin resistance risk loci [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/gwas/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/gwas/</ext-link>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>In 2011, based on the HyperGen study, a GWAS including 1,040 African Americans explored the association between insulin resistance and genetic variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The results showed SNPs linked with homeostasis model assessment of insulin resistance (HOMA-IR) and fasting insulin near ATP10A (rs6576507 and rs8026527) and CACNA1D (rs1401492) [54]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Obesity is related with insulin resistance, and also a strong risk factor for T2DM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Thus, we can assume reasonably that some loci of obesity would also be insulin resistance loci, or possibly T2DM susceptibility loci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>However, there is little overlap among loci for these traits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that the etiologically distinct subsets may exist in these extreme phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3_4"><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>NAFLD </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>NAFLD appears family genetic predisposition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Compared with overweight children without NAFLD, fatty liver was found to be more common in children whose siblings and parents had NAFLD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>[55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>After adjusting age, race, sex, and BMI, the heritability of NAFLD was estimated to be 39%, suggesting close relationship between the development of NAFLD and genetic factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>To date, a number of potential genetic determinants based on GWASs have been proposed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The Dallas Heart Study firstly identified the nonsynonymous rs738409 (I148M) located in PNPLA3, which was the most important genetic variant associated with NAFLD [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>After adjustment for ethnicity, BMI, diabetes status and alcohol use, PNPLA3 rs738409 was significantly associated with hepatic fat content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The results were subsequently confirmed by many independent studies [57] and other GWASs [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>A meta-analysis in 2011 including 16 studies also proposed a strong association between PNPLA3 rs738409 and a more aggressive disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Homozygous GG will lead to 28% increase in serum ALT levels, 3.5-fold greater risk of NASH, and 3.3-fold higher risk of fibrosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>[59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The second GWAS about NAFLD was performed in 236 women with NAFLD and identified an association between SNP rs2645424 in FDFT1 (an enzyme with a role in cholesterol synthesis) and NAFLD activity score [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>In 2011, Speliotes et al. conducted the third NAFLD GWAS [58], and identified five SNPs associated with NAFLD in or near PNPLA3 (rs738408), NCAN (rs2228603), PPP1R3B (rs4240624), GCKR (rs780094) and LYPLAL1 (rs12137855). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>There was a strong linkage disequilibrium between PNPLA3 rs738408 and the previously identified rs738409 [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Another recently GWAS in adolescents with NAFLD identified SNPs relevant to two neuron-specific genes (SLC38A8 and LPPR4) and two liver-specific genes (LCP1and GC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>This study further confirmed the significant differential expression of GC and LCP1 in a NAFLD cohort [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Another GWAS was conducted in the Japanese population involving 392 NAFLD subjects and 934 controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>In addition to those polymorphisms in the PNPLA3 gene, the polymorphisms in SAMM50 and PARVB were also observed to be associated with the occurrence and progression of NAFLD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>[62]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3_5"><title><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>HCC </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>As we known, virus infection, obesity, diabetes mellitus, alcohol and aflatoxin B1 exposure are pivotal risk factors for inducing HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Genetic factors of the individual genome may also act a role in liver malignant tumor [63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>In recent years, a plethora of studies have confirmed that the host genetic factors play crucial roles in developing HBV-induced HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>One of the first GWASs included 355 HBV carriers with HCC and 360 asymptomatic HBV carriers (ASCs) in Chinese population, indicated rs17401966 in KIF1B was significantly associated with HBV-related HCC, and SNPs in UBE4B and PGD genes were also shown to be significant for HCC emergence among patients with HBV-positive [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>In recent years, a large number of studies have confirmed that the host genetic factors played a key role in the development of HBV-related liver cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The other two GWASs from Chinese also found some novel SNPs as risk factors for HBV-related HCC, including rs9272105 in HLA-DQA1/DRB1, rs455804 in GRIK1 [65], rs9275319 in HLA-DQ gene and rs7574865 in STAT4 gene [66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Two GWASs conducted in large Japanese cohorts concluded that variant rs2596542 in the promoter region of the MICA gene [67], and SNP rs1012068 in DEPDC5 gene [68] was significantly related to HCV-induced HCC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>ANCESTRY-SPECIFIC GENETIC SUSCEPTIBILITY LOCI </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Most of the GWASs have been completed in the European, and there are many studies are emerging in other races. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Studies of obesity have shown highly comparable effects of common variants across major ancestry groups, strongly supporting shared common BMI and obesity loci across populations, although ancestry-specific loci have also been shown, such as KLHL32 in Africans and KLF9 in Asians [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Moreover, of the 14 WHR-associated loci, only 7 were found to have a significant effect in women [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>For T2DM, studies have reported novel loci such as KCNQ1and C2CD4A in Japanese individuals [70] and a number of loci for T2DM in East Asians [51, 71]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The ancestry-specific genetic susceptibility loci also exist in NAFLD and related cancer, including HCC and pancreatic cancer, suggesting great heterogeneity between the genetic background of different races or populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>It also presented challenges for precise medicine and personalized medicine. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>OUTLOOK </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>We remain in infancy of the research for potential molecular basis in the HCC development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>More specifically, in patients with NASH, the genetic variants and mechanisms that drive the development of HCC remains largely mysterious. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Based on the current GWASs, we hope to find new genetic components related to metabolic syndrome and liver cancer progression, yet major efforts are still needed to gain biological knowledge from discoveries. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s5_1"><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Seeking the missing heritability </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The past 8 years of genetic discoveries brought about by the GWASs approach have meant a giant leap for genetic research of complex traits, with more than 288 genetic loci shown to associate with metabolic traits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Yet, the major part of the genetic predisposition to these phenotypes remains unaccounted since the proportion of variance explained by genetic risk variants discovered to date is limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Implicit in the initial design, GWASs-identified variants in metabolic syndrome and related cancer are common (minor allele frequency &gt;5% in the population). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>There has been much focus on this missing heritability [72]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The rare alleles with large effects are the primary drivers of common disease, which has received renewed attention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The focus is needed to change to study the individual and combined effect of low-frequency and rare variants in metabolic disease through the analysis of data from microarray-based genotyping and wide-genome sequencing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In addition, influences other than main effects of SNPs may explain parts of the susceptibility for metabolic disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Preliminary evidence supports the role of copy number variations and gene-environment interactions in obesity, T2DM and HCC, as solid findings have been reported [73, 74], and future large-scale studies may reveal gene-gene interactions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s5_2"><title><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Identifying causal variants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>GWASs contribute to find the common genetic variants between normal and pathological features, but the major challenge is how to recognize the precise targets of those associations among them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The studies for investigating gene function for the loci from GWASs are needed, including accurate mapping of GWASs signal(s) combined with genetic epidemiology and bioinformatics methods of the integration and optimization of putative functional SNPs, and in vitro and in vivo experimental verification for predicted molecular mechanism to identify the targeted genes [75]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s5_3"><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Risk prediction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>As discussed above, common genetic variants unanimously impose modest risk increments on metabolic syndrome and related cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, combining these variants does not enable prediction these disease/traits [76, 77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Future studies are needed to reveal further important genetic susceptibility elements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>In addition, systemic integration of complex date obtained from other “omics” such as transcriptomics, proteomics and metabolomics, and modeling research for composite effect on the integrate common metabolic phenotype, is projected to be a breakthrough in the research of genetic determinants of metabolic traits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Besides gaining biological knowledge and allowing the identification of at-risk individuals, hopes have been high that knowledge of genetic risk factors would lead to personalized treatment based on the genetic profile. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>With the developing of the polymorphism risk-scoring algorithm and gene sequencing, it is plausible for identification high-risk groups for prevention and healthcare, and early screening for potential biomarkers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>And the complex molecular mechanisms for the NASH, related cirrhosis and HCC need more retrospective and prospective studies to underpin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Since there is a strong association between NASH and HCC, the direction of the study about NAFLD/NASH treatment should focus on how to reduce the risk of cancer in these patients, provide long-term benefits and reduce socio-economic pressure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>With the continued popularity of obesity, the prevalence of diabetes mellitus and metabolic syndrome is increasing, so it is imperative to screen the high risk groups of HCC in patients with metabolic syndrome, and to provide the appropriate monitoring strategies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>GRANT SUPPORT </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>This work was supported in part by the National Key Basic Research Program of China (2013CB530604), the National Natural Science Foundation of China (81600685), the Natural Science Foundation of Jiangsu Province (BK20160141), the Medical Science and technology development Foundation of Nanjing Department of Health (YKK16201), and the Science and Technology Development Fund of the Nanjing Medical University (2015NJMUZD062). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>1ScaleraATarantinoGCould metabolic syndrome lead to hepatocarcinoma via non-alcoholic fatty liver disease?World J Gastroenterol2014209217922825071314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R2"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>2ElsayedEYMosalamNAMohamedNRResistin and Insulin Resistance: A Link Between Inflammation and HepatocarcinogenesisAsian Pac J Cancer Prev2015167139714226514502 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R3"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>3LockeAEKahaliBBerndtSIJusticeAEPersTHDayFRPowellCVedantamSBuchkovichMLYangJCroteau-ChonkaDCEskoTFallTGenetic studies of body mass index yield new insights for obesity biologyNature201551819720625673413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R4"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>4HsuFCLenchikLNicklasBJLohmanKRegisterTCMychaleckyjJLangefeldCDFreedmanBIBowdenDWCarrJJHeritability of body composition measured by DXA in the diabetes heart studyObes Res20051331231915800289 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R5"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>5SandholtCHGrarupNPedersenOHansenTGenome-wide association studies of human adiposity: Zooming in on synapsesMol Cell Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>2015;418 Pt290100 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R6"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>6YuJShenJSunTTZhangXWongNObesity, insulin resistance, NASH and hepatocellular carcinomaSemin Cancer Biol20132348349123876851 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R7"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>7CalleEERodriguezCWalker-ThurmondKThunMJOverweight, obesity, and mortality from cancer in a prospectively studied cohort of U.S. adultsN Engl J Med20033481625163812711737 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R8"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>8ChenCLYangHIYangWSLiuCJChenPJYouSLWangLYSunCALuSNChenDSChenCJMetabolic factors and risk of hepatocellular carcinoma by chronic hepatitis B/C infection: a follow-up study in TaiwanGastroenterology200813511112118505690 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R9"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>9LarssonSCWolkAOverweight, obesity and risk of liver cancer: a meta-analysis of cohort studiesBr J Cancer2007971005100817700568 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R10"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>10WelzelTMGraubardBIZeuzemSEl-SeragHBDavilaJAMcGlynnKAMetabolic syndrome increases the risk of primary liver cancer in the United States: a study in the SEER-Medicare databaseHepatology20115446347121538440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R11"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>11BorenaWStrohmaierSLukanovaABjorgeTLindkvistBHallmansGEdlingerMStocksTNagelGManjerJEngelandASelmerRHaggstromCMetabolic risk factors and primary liver cancer in a prospective study of 578,700 adultsInt J Cancer201213119320021805476 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R12"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>12OhSWYoonYSShinSAEffects of excess weight on cancer incidences depending on cancer sites and histologic findings among menKorea National Health Insurance Corporation Study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>J Clin Oncol2005234742475416034050 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R13"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>13SiegelABLimEAWangSBrubakerWRodriguezRDGoyalAJacobsonJSHershmanDLVernaECZaretskyJHalazunKDoveLBrownRS JRDiabetes, body mass index, and outcomes in hepatocellular carcinoma patients undergoing liver transplantationTransplantation20129453954322864187 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R14"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>14RosmorducOFartouxLHCC and NASH: how strong is the clinical demonstration?Clin Res Hepatol Gastroenterol20123620220822326764 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R15"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>15SetiawanVWHernandezBYLuSCStramDOWilkensLRLe MarchandLHendersonBEDiabetes and racial/ethnic differences in hepatocellular carcinoma risk: the multiethnic cohortJ Natl Cancer Inst2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R16"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>16ChenJHanYXuCXiaoTWangBEffect of type 2 diabetes mellitus on the risk for hepatocellular carcinoma in chronic liver diseases: a meta-analysis of cohort studiesEur J Cancer Prev201524899924809655 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R17"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>17SmedileABugianesiESteatosis and hepatocellular carcinoma riskEur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci2005929129316231592 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R18"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>18DonatoFGelattiULiminaRMFattovichGSouthern Europe as an example of interaction between various environmental factors: a systematic review of the epidemiologic evidenceOncogene2006253756377016799617 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R19"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>19TeohNCFanJGDiabetes mellitus and prognosis after curative therapy for hepatocellular carcinoma: alas, still grave for those who are hyperglycemicJ Gastroenterol Hepatol2008231633163419120856 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R20"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>20SiddiqueAKowdleyKVInsulin resistance and other metabolic risk factors in the pathogenesis of hepatocellular carcinomaClin Liver Dis201115281296viix21689613 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R21"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>21GagginiMMorelliMBuzzigoliEDeFronzoRABugianesiEGastaldelliANon-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) and its connection with insulin resistance, dyslipidemia, atherosclerosis and coronary heart diseaseNutrients201351544156023666091 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R22"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>22BugianesiEMcCulloughAJMarchesiniGInsulin resistance: a metabolic pathway to chronic liver diseaseHepatology200542987100016250043 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R23"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>23KajiKYoshijiHKitadeMIkenakaYNoguchiRYoshiiJYanaseKNamisakiTYamazakiMMoriyaKTsujimotoTKawarataniHAkahaneTImpact of insulin resistance on the progression of chronic liver diseasesInt J Mol Med20082280180819020779 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R24"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>24JeeSHOhrrHSullJWYunJEJiMSametJMFasting serum glucose level and cancer risk in Korean men and womenJAMA200529319420215644546 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R25"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>25WongVWNonalcoholic fatty liver disease in Asia: a story of growthJ Gastroenterol Hepatol2013281823 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R26"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>26SerfatyLLemoineMDefinition and natural history of metabolic steatosis: clinical aspects of NAFLD, NASH and cirrhosisDiabetes Metab20083463463719195623 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R27"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>27WongVWWongGLChoiPCChanAWLiMKChanHYChimAMYuJSungJJChanHLDisease progression of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease: a prospective study with paired liver biopsies at 3 yearsGut20105996997420581244 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R28"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>28StarleyBQCalcagnoCJHarrisonSANonalcoholic fatty liver disease and hepatocellular carcinoma: a weighty connectionHepatology2010511820183220432259 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R29"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>29FanJGFarrellGCEpidemiology of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease in ChinaJ Hepatol20095020421019014878 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R30"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>30ToffaninSFriedmanSLLlovetJMObesity, inflammatory signaling, and hepatocellular carcinoma-an enlarging linkCancer Cell20101711511720159605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R31"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>31GrarupNSandholtCHHansenTPedersenOGenetic susceptibility to type 2 diabetes and obesity: from genome-wide association studies to rare variants and beyondDiabetologia2014571528154124859358 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R32"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>32BarshGSFarooqiISO'RahillySGenetics of body-weight regulationNature200040464465110766251 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R33"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>33FraylingTMTimpsonNJWeedonMNZegginiEFreathyRMLindgrenCMPerryJRElliottKSLangoHRaynerNWShieldsBHarriesLWBarrettJCA common variant in the FTO gene is associated with body mass index and predisposes to childhood and adult obesityScience200731688989417434869 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R34"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>34LoosRJLindgrenCMLiSWheelerEZhaoJHProkopenkoIInouyeMFreathyRMAttwoodAPBeckmannJSBerndtSIProstateLCOvarian Cancer Screening TCommon variants near MC4R are associated with fat mass, weight and risk of obesityNat Genet20084076877518454148 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R35"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>35WillerCJSpeliotesEKLoosRJLiSLindgrenCMHeidIMBerndtSIElliottALJacksonAULaminaCLettreGLimNLyonHNSix new loci associated with body mass index highlight a neuronal influence on body weight regulationNat Genet200941253419079261 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R36"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>36WenWChoYSZhengWDorajooRKatoNQiLChenCHDelahantyRJOkadaYTabaraYGuDZhuDHaimanCAMeta-analysis identifies common variants associated with body mass index in east AsiansNat Genet20124430731122344219 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R37"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>37MondaKLChenGKTaylorKCPalmerCEdwardsTLLangeLANgMCAdeyemoAAAllisonMABielakLFChenGGraffMIrvinMRA meta-analysis identifies new loci associated with body mass index in individuals of African ancestryNat Genet20134569069623583978 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R38"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>38PeiYFZhangLLiuYLiJShenHLiuYZTianQHeHWuSRanSHanYHaiRLinYMeta-analysis of genome-wide association data identifies novel susceptibility loci for obesityHum Mol Genet20142382083024064335 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R39"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>39WenWZhengWOkadaYTakeuchiFTabaraYHwangJYDorajooRLiHTsaiFJYangXHeJWuYHeMMeta-analysis of genome-wide association studies in East Asian-ancestry populations identifies four new loci for body mass indexHum Mol Genet2014235492550424861553 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R40"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>40LiuCTMondaKLTaylorKCLangeLDemerathEWPalmasWWojczynskiMKEllisJCVitolinsMZLiuSPapanicolaouGJIrvinMRXueLGenome-wide association of body fat distribution in African ancestry populations suggests new lociPLoS Genet20139e100368123966867 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R41"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>41KobberlingJ[Predictive value of diagnostic procedures]Dtsch Med Wochenschr19821075915957067642 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R42"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>42GrantSFThorleifssonGReynisdottirIBenediktssonRManolescuASainzJHelgasonAStefanssonHEmilssonVHelgadottirAStyrkarsdottirUMagnussonKPWaltersGBVariant of transcription factor 7-like 2 (TCF7L2) gene confers risk of type 2 diabetesNat Genet20063832032316415884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R43"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>43CauchiSEl AchhabYChoquetHDinaCKremplerFWeitgasserRNejjariCPatschWChikriMMeyreDFroguelPTCF7L2 is reproducibly associated with type 2 diabetes in various ethnic groups: a global meta-analysisJ Mol Med (Berl)20078577778217476472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R44"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>44ConsortiumSTDWilliamsALJacobsSBMoreno-MaciasHHuerta-ChagoyaAChurchhouseCMarquez-LunaCGarcia-OrtizHGomez-VazquezMJBurttNPAguilar-SalinasCAGonzalez-VillalpandoCFlorezJCSequence variants in SLC16A11 are a common risk factor for type 2 diabetes in MexicoNature20145069710124390345 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R45"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>45SaxenaRSaleheenDBeenLFGaravitoMLBraunTBjonnesAYoungRHoWKRasheedAFrossardPSimXHassanaliNRadhaVGenome-wide association study identifies a novel locus contributing to type 2 diabetes susceptibility in Sikhs of Punjabi origin from IndiaDiabetes2013621746175523300278 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R46"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>46PerryJRVoightBFYengoLAminNDupuisJGanserMGrallertHNavarroPLiMQiLSteinthorsdottirVScottRAAlmgrenPStratifying type 2 diabetes cases by BMI identifies genetic risk variants in LAMA1 and enrichment for risk variants in lean compared to obese casesPLoS Genet20128e100274122693455 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R47"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>47HaraKFujitaHJohnsonTAYamauchiTYasudaKHorikoshiMPengCHuCMaRCImamuraMIwataMTsunodaTMorizonoTGenome-wide association study identifies three novel loci for type 2 diabetesHum Mol Genet20142323924623945395 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R48"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>48ZegginiEScottLJSaxenaRVoightBFMarchiniJLHuTde BakkerPIAbecasisGRAlmgrenPAndersenGArdlieKBostromKBBergmanRNMeta-analysis of genome-wide association data and large-scale replication identifies additional susceptibility loci for type 2 diabetesNat Genet20084063864518372903 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R49"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>49VoightBFScottLJSteinthorsdottirVMorrisAPDinaCWelchRPZegginiEHuthCAulchenkoYSThorleifssonGMcCullochLJFerreiraTGrallertHTwelve type 2 diabetes susceptibility loci identified through large-scale association analysisNat Genet20104257958920581827 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R50"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>50ReplicationDIGMeta-analysisCAsian Genetic Epidemiology Network Type 2 Diabetes C, South Asian Type 2 Diabetes C, Mexican American Type 2 Diabetes C, Type 2 Diabetes Genetic Exploration by Nex-generation sequencing in muylti-EthnicSamplesCMahajanAGoMJZhangWBelowJEGaultonKJFerreiraTHorikoshiMGenome-wide trans-ancestry meta-analysis provides insight into the genetic architecture of type 2 diabetes susceptibilityNat Genet20144623424424509480 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R51"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>51ChoYSChenCHHuCLongJOngRTSimXTakeuchiFWuYGoMJYamauchiTChangYCKwakSHMaRCMeta-analysis of genome-wide association studies identifies eight new loci for type 2 diabetes in east AsiansNat Genet201144677222158537 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R52"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>52WatanabeRMThe genetics of insulin resistance: Where's Waldo?Curr Diab Rep20101047648420820957 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R53"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>53PetersenKFDufourSHaririANelson-WilliamsCFooJNZhangXMDziuraJLiftonRPShulmanGIApolipoprotein C3 gene variants in nonalcoholic fatty liver diseaseN Engl J Med20103621082108920335584 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R54"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>54IrvinMRWineingerNERiceTKPajewskiNMKabagambeEKGuCCPankowJNorthKEWilkJBFreedmanBIFranceschiniNBroeckelUTiwariHKGenome-wide detection of allele specific copy number variation associated with insulin resistance in African Americans from the HyperGEN studyPLoS One20116e2405221901158 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R55"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>55SchwimmerJBCeledonMALavineJESalemRCampbellNSchorkNJShiehmortezaMYokooTChavezAMiddletonMSSirlinCBHeritability of nonalcoholic fatty liver diseaseGastroenterology20091361585159219208353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R56"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>56RomeoSKozlitinaJXingCPertsemlidisACoxDPennacchioLABoerwinkleECohenJCHobbsHHGenetic variation in PNPLA3 confers susceptibility to nonalcoholic fatty liver diseaseNat Genet2008401461146518820647 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R57"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>57RotmanYKohCZmudaJMKleinerDELiangTJNashCRNThe association of genetic variability in patatin-like phospholipase domain-containing protein 3 (PNPLA3) with histological severity of nonalcoholic fatty liver diseaseHepatology20105289490320684021 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R58"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>58SpeliotesEKYerges-ArmstrongLMWuJHernaezRKimLJPalmerCDGudnasonVEiriksdottirGGarciaMELaunerLJNallsMAClarkJMMitchellBDGenome-wide association analysis identifies variants associated with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease that have distinct effects on metabolic traitsPLoS Genet20117e100132421423719 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R59"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>59SookoianSPirolaCJMeta-analysis of the influence of I148M variant of patatin-like phospholipase domain containing 3 gene (PNPLA3) on the susceptibility and histological severity of nonalcoholic fatty liver diseaseHepatology2011531883189421381068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R60"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>60ChalasaniNGuoXLoombaRGoodarziMOHarituniansTKwonSCuiJTaylorKDWilsonLCummingsOWChenYDRotterJINonalcoholic Steatohepatitis Clinical Research N. Genome-wide association study identifies variants associated with histologic features of nonalcoholic Fatty liver diseaseGastroenterology2010139156715761576e1561156620708005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R61"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>61AdamsLAWhiteSWMarshJALyeSJConnorKLMagangaRAyonrindeOTOlynykJKMoriTABeilinLJPalmerLJHamdorfJMPennellCEAssociation between liver-specific gene polymorphisms and their expression levels with nonalcoholic fatty liver diseaseHepatology20135759060023213074 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R62"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>62KitamotoTKitamotoAYonedaMHyogoHOchiHNakamuraTTeranishiHMizusawaSUenoTChayamaKNakajimaANakaoKSekineAGenome-wide scan revealed that polymorphisms in the PNPLA3, SAMM50, and PARVB genes are associated with development and progression of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease in JapanHum Genet201313278379223535911 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R63"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>63HoshidaYFuchsBCTanabeKKGenomic risk of hepatitis C-related hepatocellular carcinomaJ Hepatol20125672973021963516 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R64"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>64ZhangHZhaiYHuZWuCQianJJiaWMaFHuangWYuLYueWWangZLiPZhangYGenome-wide association study identifies 1p36.22 as a new susceptibility locus for hepatocellular carcinoma in chronic hepatitis B virus carriersNat Genet20104275575820676096 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R65"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>65LiSQianJYangYZhaoWDaiJBeiJXFooJNMcLarenPJLiZYangJShenFLiuLYangJGWAS identifies novel susceptibility loci on 6p21.32 and 21q21.3 for hepatocellular carcinoma in chronic hepatitis B virus carriersPLoS Genet20128e100279122807686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R66"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>66JiangDKSunJCaoGLiuYLinDGaoYZRenWHLongXDZhangHMaXPWangZJiangWChenTYGenetic variants in STAT4 and HLA-DQ genes confer risk of hepatitis B virus-related hepatocellular carcinomaNat Genet201345727523242368 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R67"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>67KumarVKatoNUrabeYTakahashiAMuroyamaRHosonoNOtsukaMTateishiROmataMNakagawaHKoikeKKamataniNKuboMGenome-wide association study identifies a susceptibility locus for HCV-induced hepatocellular carcinomaNat Genet20114345545821499248 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R68"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>68MikiDOchiHHayesCNAbeHYoshimaTAikataHIkedaKKumadaHToyotaJMorizonoTTsunodaTKuboMNakamuraYVariation in the DEPDC5 locus is associated with progression to hepatocellular carcinoma in chronic hepatitis C virus carriersNat Genet20114379780021725309 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R69"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>69HeidIMJacksonAURandallJCWinklerTWQiLSteinthorsdottirVThorleifssonGZillikensMCSpeliotesEKMagiRWorkalemahuTWhiteCCBouatia-NajiNMeta-analysis identifies 13 new loci associated with waist-hip ratio and reveals sexual dimorphism in the genetic basis of fat distributionNat Genet20104294996020935629 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R70"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>70YamauchiTHaraKMaedaSYasudaKTakahashiAHorikoshiMNakamuraMFujitaHGrarupNCauchiSNgDPMaRCTsunodaTA genome-wide association study in the Japanese population identifies susceptibility loci for type 2 diabetes at UBE2E2 and C2CD4A-C2CD4BNat Genet20104286486820818381 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R71"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>71KoonerJSSaleheenDSimXSehmiJZhangWFrossardPBeenLFChiaKSDimasASHassanaliNJafarTJowettJBLiXGenome-wide association study in individuals of South Asian ancestry identifies six new type 2 diabetes susceptibility lociNat Genet20114398498921874001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R72"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>72MaherBPersonal genomes: The case of the missing heritabilityNature2008456182118987709 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R73"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>73WaltersRGJacquemontSValsesiaAde_SmithAJMartinetDAnderssonJFalchiMChenFAndrieuxJLobbensSDelobelBStutzmannFEl-Sayed MoustafaJSA new highly penetrant form of obesity due to deletions on chromosome 16p11.2Nature201046367167520130649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R74"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>74KilpelainenTOQiLBrageSSharpSJSonestedtEDemerathEAhmadTMoraSKaakinenMSandholtCHHolzapfelCAutenriethCSHypponenEPhysical activity attenuates the influence of FTO variants on obesity risk: a meta-analysis of 218,166 adults and 19,268 childrenPLoS Med20118e100111622069379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R75"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>75EdwardsSLBeesleyJFrenchJDDunningAMBeyond GWASs: illuminating the dark road from association to functionAm J Hum Genet20139377979724210251 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R76"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>76MeigsJBShraderPSullivanLMMcAteerJBFoxCSDupuisJManningAKFlorezJCWilsonPWD'Agostino RBSRCupplesLAGenotype score in addition to common risk factors for prediction of type 2 diabetesN Engl J Med20083592208221919020323 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R77"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>77SpeliotesEKWillerCJBerndtSIMondaKLThorleifssonGJacksonAULango AllenHLindgrenCMLuanJMagiRRandallJCVedantamSWinklerTWAssociation analyses of 249,796 individuals reveal 18 new loci associated with body mass indexNat Genet20104293794820935630 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
