<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosgen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2432036</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18584035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">08-PLGE-RA-0013R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000108</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subject>Biochemistry/Transcription and Translation</subject><subject>Cell Biology/Cell Signaling</subject><subject>Cell Biology/Gene Expression</subject><subject>Diabetes and Endocrinology</subject><subject>Diabetes and Endocrinology/Obesity</subject><subject>Diabetes and Endocrinology/Type 2 Diabetes</subject><subject>Molecular Biology</subject><subject>Pharmacology</subject><subject>Physiology</subject><subject>Physiology/Endocrinology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Metabolic Actions of Estrogen Receptor Beta (ER&#x003b2;) are Mediated by a Negative Cross-Talk with PPAR&#x003b3;</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Metabolic Action of ER&#x003b2;</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Foryst-Ludwig</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Clemenz</surname><given-names>Markus</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>Stephan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hartge</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sprang</surname><given-names>Christiane</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>Nikolaj</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Krikov</surname><given-names>Maxim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bhanot</surname><given-names>Sanjay</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>Rodrigo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Morani</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>Jan-&#x000c5;ke</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Unger</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kintscher</surname><given-names>Ulrich</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>&#x0002a;</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Center for Cardiovascular Research (CCR), Institute of Pharmacology, Charit&#x000e9;-Universit&#x000e4;tsmedizin Berlin, Berlin, Germany</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>ISIS Pharmaceuticals, Carlsbad, California, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Biosciences and Nutrition, Karolinska Institutet, NOVUM, Huddinge, Sweden</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Auwerx</surname><given-names>Johan</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Institut de G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;tique et de Biologie Mol&#x000e9;culaire et Cellulaire, CNRS/INSERM/Universit&#x000e9; Louis Pasteur, France</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>ulrich.kintscher@charite.de</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AF UK. Performed the experiments: AF MC SH MH CS NF MK RB AM. Analyzed the data: AF. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SB JG. Wrote the paper: AF JG TU UK.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e1000108</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>1</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Foryst-Ludwig et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Estrogen receptors (ER) are important regulators of metabolic diseases such as obesity and insulin resistance (IR). While ER&#x003b1; seems to have a protective role in such diseases, the function of ER&#x003b2; is not clear. To characterize the metabolic function of ER&#x003b2;, we investigated its molecular interaction with a master regulator of insulin signaling/glucose metabolism, the PPAR&#x003b3;, in vitro and in high-fat diet (HFD)-fed ER&#x003b2; -/- mice (&#x003b2;ERKO) mice. Our in vitro experiments showed that ER&#x003b2; inhibits ligand-mediated PPAR&#x003b3;-transcriptional activity. That resulted in a blockade of PPAR&#x003b3;-induced adipocytic gene expression and in decreased adipogenesis. Overexpression of nuclear coactivators such as SRC1 and TIF2 prevented the ER&#x003b2;-mediated inhibition of PPAR&#x003b3; activity. Consistent with the in vitro data, we observed increased PPAR&#x003b3; activity in gonadal fat from HFD-fed &#x003b2;ERKO mice. In consonance with enhanced PPAR&#x003b3; activation, HFD-fed &#x003b2;ERKO mice showed increased body weight gain and fat mass in the presence of improved insulin sensitivity. To directly demonstrate the role of PPAR&#x003b3; in HFD-fed &#x003b2;ERKO mice, PPAR&#x003b3; signaling was disrupted by PPAR&#x003b3; antisense oligonucleotide (ASO). Blockade of adipose PPAR&#x003b3; by ASO reversed the phenotype of &#x003b2;ERKO mice with an impairment of insulin sensitization and glucose tolerance. Finally, binding of SRC1 and TIF2 to the PPAR&#x003b3;-regulated adiponectin promoter was enhanced in gonadal fat from &#x003b2;ERKO mice indicating that the absence of ER&#x003b2; in adipose tissue results in exaggerated coactivator binding to a PPAR&#x003b3; target promoter. Collectively, our data provide the first evidence that ER&#x003b2;-deficiency protects against diet-induced IR and glucose intolerance which involves an augmented PPAR&#x003b3; signaling in adipose tissue. Moreover, our data suggest that the coactivators SRC1 and TIF2 are involved in this interaction. Impairment of insulin and glucose metabolism by ER&#x003b2; may have significant implications for our understanding of hormone receptor-dependent pathophysiology of metabolic diseases, and may be essential for the development of new ER&#x003b2;-selective agonists.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title><p>In the present study, we demonstrate for the first time a pro-diabetogenic function of the ER&#x003b2;. Our experiments indicate that ER&#x003b2; impairs insulin sensitivity and glucose tolerance in mice challenged with a high fat diet (HFD). Loss of ER&#x003b2;, studied in ER&#x003b2; -/- mice (&#x003b2;ERKO mice), results in increased body weight gain and fat deposition under HFD-treatment. Conversely, absence of ER&#x003b2; averted accumulation of triglycerides and preserved regular insulin signaling in liver and skeletal muscle. This observation was associated with improved whole-body insulin sensitivity and glucose tolerance. Increased adipose tissue mass in the presence of improved insulin sensitivity and glucose tolerance is usually observed under chronic stimulation of the nuclear hormone receptor PPAR&#x003b3;. In consonance, we show that activation of PPAR&#x003b3; was markedly induced in gonadal fat from &#x003b2;ERKO mice and blockade of adipose PPAR&#x003b3; signaling by antisense oligonucleotide injection reversed the metabolic phenotype. Moreover, our cell culture experiments indicate that ER&#x003b2; is a negative regulator of ligand-induced PPAR&#x003b3; activity in vitro. Finally, we identify SRC1 and TIF2 as key players in the ER&#x003b2;-PPAR&#x003b3; interaction. In summary, the present study demonstrates that ER&#x003b2; impairs insulin and glucose metabolism, which may, at least in part, result from a negative cross-talk with adipose PPAR&#x003b3;.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The estrogen receptors (ERs) are members of the nuclear hormone receptor family (NHR) which act as eukaryotic ligand-dependent transcription factors. ERs are involved in the regulation of embryonic development, homeostasis and reproduction. Two major estrogen receptors, alpha and beta (ER&#x003b1; and ER&#x003b2;), convey the physiological signaling of estrogens (17&#x003b2;-estradiol, E2) <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Nilsson1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Additionally, ERs are activated by specific synthetic ligands such as raloxifene, tamoxifen, the ER&#x003b2;-specific ligand diarylpropionitrile (DPN), and the ER&#x003b2;-specific agonist propylpyrazole-triol (PPT), which belong to the group of selective estrogen receptor modulators (SERMS) <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Smith1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pgen.1000108-McKenna1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>.</p><p>The prevalence of metabolic diseases such as obesity, insulin resistance and type 2 diabetes has increased dramatically during the recent ten years <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Haslam1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Gender differences in the pathophysiology of obesity and metabolic disorders are well established <xref rid="pgen.1000108-RegitzZagrosek1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pgen.1000108-Barros1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. However, the molecular mechanisms of sexual dimorphism in metabolic diseases are largely unknown. In addition, lack of ER activation has been implicated in postmenopausal impairment of glucose and lipid metabolism, resulting in visceral fat distribution, insulin resistance and increased cardiovascular risk after menopause <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Carr1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. In this context the investigation of ER-signaling and its role in metabolic disorders has gained increasing attention <xref rid="pgen.1000108-McKenna1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1000108-Barros1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>.</p><p>To identify the ER subtype involved in the regulation of metabolic disorders, studies have been carried out in ER-deficient mice. ER&#x003b1;-deficient (&#x003b1;ERKO) mice have profound insulin resistance and impaired glucose tolerance <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Cooke1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pgen.1000108-Bryzgalova1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. These studies indicate that ER&#x003b1; has a protective role in metabolic disorders by improving insulin sensitivity and glucose tolerance. The metabolic function of ER&#x003b2; is not clear. ER&#x003b2; knockout mice (&#x003b2;ERKO) have a similar body weight and equal fat distribution in comparison to wild type littermates. Additionally, &#x003b2;ERKO and wild-type (wt) mice exhibit similar insulin and lipid levels <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Ohlsson1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. However, previous studies in &#x003b2;ERKO mice were only carried out under low fat diet, which may have concealed a phenotype relevant for human obesity normally induced by high-energy/fat diet.</p><p>The peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma (PPAR&#x003b3;) belongs to the NHR family and is a major regulator of glucose and lipid metabolism by modulating energy homeostasis in adipose tissue, skeletal muscle and liver <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Semple1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pgen.1000108-Picard1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Glitazones or thiazolidinediones (TZDs) are high-affinity PPAR&#x003b3; agonists, and act as insulin sensitizers. TZDs induce adipogenesis and adipose tissue remodeling followed by an improvement of glucose tolerance <xref rid="pgen.1000108-YkiJarvinen1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. The role of PPAR&#x003b3; in the control of glucose homeostasis expands beyond its primary action in adipose tissue, and involves the regulation of adipocytokine production such as adiponectin, leptin, and resistin <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Matsuzawa1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pgen.1000108-Kadowaki1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Consistently, reduced PPAR&#x003b3; activity has important metabolic and cardiovascular pathophysiological consequences leading to insulin resistance, diabetes and end organ damage <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Semple1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>.</p><p>The molecular mechanisms underlying PPAR&#x003b3; function are similar to those of ER-signaling. In a basal state, PPAR&#x003b3;, similar to ERs, is bound to corepressor proteins such as nuclear receptor corepressor (NCoR) or silencing mediator of retinoic acid and thyroid hormone receptor (SMRT) <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Guan1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. After binding within the ligand binding domain (LBD), PPAR&#x003b3; ligands induce its heterodimerization with retinoid x receptor alpha (RXR&#x003b1;), and its subsequent interaction with co-activators like steroid receptor coactivators (SRCs) followed by binding to PPAR&#x003b3; response elements (PPREs) within target gene promoters <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Glass1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Importantly, PPAR&#x003b3; is sharing a similar pool of cofactors with ER&#x003b2; which provides a platform for mutual interactions between these two NHRs <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Glass1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1000108-Gronemeyer1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>.</p><p>To study the crosstalk between ER&#x003b2; and PPAR&#x003b3;, we investigated the regulation of PPAR&#x003b3;-mediated transcriptional activity by ER&#x003b2;. Our in-vitro experiments in 3T3-L1 preadipocytes showed that ER&#x003b2; inhibits ligand-mediated PPAR&#x003b3;-transcriptional activity. That resulted in the blockade of PPAR&#x003b3;-induced adipocytic gene expression and in decreased adipogenesis. Overexpression of nuclear coactivators such as steroid receptor coactivator 1 (SRC1) and transcriptional intermediary factor 2 (TIF2) prevented the ER&#x003b2;-mediated inhibition of PPAR&#x003b3; activity, whereas the presence of vitamin D receptor (VDR)-interacting protein 205 (DRIP205) or PPAR&#x003b3; coactivator-1alpha (PGC1&#x003b1;) had no effect indicating a role for distinct nuclear coactivators for ER&#x003b2;-PPAR&#x003b3; interaction in-vitro. High fat diet (HFD)-fed &#x003b2;ERKO mice showed increased body weight and fat mass. In contrast, triglyceride content in liver and muscle was decreased in &#x003b2;ERKO mice, which was associated with a marked improvement of hepatic and muscular insulin signaling. Compared to wt, &#x003b2;ERKO mice demonstrated improved systemic insulin sensitivity and glucose tolerance. In consonance with the metabolic phenotype and with the in-vitro data, &#x003b2;ERKO mice exhibited augmented PPAR&#x003b3; signaling in adipose tissue corresponding to increased food efficiency and significantly elevated RQ (respiratory quotient). Blockade of adipose PPAR&#x003b3; signaling in &#x003b2;ERKO mice by PPAR&#x003b3; antisense oligonucleotide injection resulted in a reversal of the &#x003b2;ERKO phenotype including body weight reduction and impairment of insulin sensitivity.</p><p>In summary, the present data demonstrate that ER&#x003b2; impairs insulin and glucose metabolism which may, at least in part, result from a negative cross-talk with adipose PPAR&#x003b3;.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>ER&#x003b2; Inhibits PPAR&#x003b3; Activity in a Ligand-Independent Manner</title><p>In order to demonstrate a molecular interaction between PPAR&#x003b3; and ER&#x003b2; in a metabolically relevant cell system, we first investigated ligand-dependent PPAR&#x003b3; activity in the presence of ER&#x003b2; in 3T3-L1 preadipocytes. Cells were treated with the PPAR&#x003b3;-agonist pioglitazone (10 &#x000b5;M), with or without additional E2 stimulation, and PPAR&#x003b3; activation was measured using pGal4-hPPAR&#x003b3;DEF/pG5TkGL3 luciferase assay <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Schupp1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Upon pioglitazone stimulation, 3T3-L1 preadipocytes showed pronounced PPAR&#x003b3; activation (bar 1&#x0002b;2, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). This activation was not affected by co-treatment with ligands for ER&#x003b2; such as E2 (bar 2 vs. 3, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g001">Figure 1A</xref>) or DPN (data not shown). Overexpression of ER&#x003b2; led to a marked inhibition of ligand-dependent PPAR&#x003b3; activity (bar 2 vs. 4&#x0002b;6&#x0002b;8, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g001">Figure 1A</xref>) which was also corroborated in a PPAR&#x003b3; response element (PPRE) luciferase assay ( <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1000108.s001">Figure S1</xref>). This inhibition was E2 (bar 4&#x0002b;6&#x0002b;8 vs. 5&#x0002b;7&#x0002b;9, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g001">Figure 1A</xref>) and DPN independent (data not shown). The inhibitory effect of ER&#x003b2; seemed to be isoform specific, since ER&#x003b1; overexpression resulted in no inhibition of PPAR&#x003b3; activity (bar 11, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g001">Figure 1A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1000108.s002">Figure S2</xref>). To further explore the regulation of PPAR&#x003b3; by ER&#x003b2;, we performed additional experiments coexpressing an activation function 1 domain (AF-1) deleted-ER&#x003b2; construct in 3T3-L1 cells. Overexpression of this truncated form of ER&#x003b2; which still contains a functional ligand binding domain (LBD) did not reduce PPAR&#x003b3; activity indicating that ER&#x003b2; AF-1 is necessary for regulation of PPAR&#x003b3; by ER&#x003b2; (bar 10, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). To assure adequate overexpression and function of ER&#x003b2; in our system, 3T3-L1 preadipocytes were transiently transfected with ER&#x003b2; followed by Western blot analysis and transactivation assays using ER response elements (ERE)-luciferase system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g001">Figure 1B, C</xref>). Both assays confirmed adequate expression and function of ER&#x003b2;.</p><fig id="pgen-1000108-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000108.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>ER&#x003b2; inhibits PPAR&#x003b3; activity in a ligand-independent manner.</title><p>A) 3T3-L1 preadipocytes were transfected with the indicated plasmids together with pGal4-hPPAR&#x003b3;DEF, pG5TkGL3 and renilla, followed by treatment with 10 &#x000b5;M pioglitazone, 100 nM E2, or in combination as indicated. # p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. pSG5&#x0002b;veh; &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. pSG5&#x0002b;Pio, ns: not significant vs. pSG5&#x0002b;Pio, ns<sub>a</sub>: not significant vs. ER&#x003b2;&#x0002b;Pio. B) 3T3-L1 preadipocytes were transfected with ER&#x003b2; (as indicated), and protein level of ER&#x003b2; was analysed by Western blot. C) 3T3-L1 preadipocytes were transfected with the indicated plasmids together with pERE-TkGL3, and cells were treated with 100 nM E2, as indicated. &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. pSG5&#x0002b;E2; ns: not significant vs. pSG5&#x0002b;veh.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.1000108.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>ER&#x003b2; Inhibits PPAR&#x003b3;-Dependent Adipocyte Differentiation and Target Gene Expression</title><p>While our data implicated a negative regulation of ligand-mediated PPAR&#x003b3; transcription by ER&#x003b2;, we next investigated the regulation of PPAR&#x003b3;-dependent gene expression during 3T3-L1 preadipocyte differentiation. The preadipocytes were transfected with indicated plasmids and differentiated for 3 days using standard differentiation medium <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Schupp1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. As the full differentiation procedure requires 7-10 days of treatment, the observed effect on fat droplet accumulation and expression pattern are typical for early phase of adipocyte differentiation. The 3T3-L1 cells transfected with ER&#x003b2; and differentiated for 3 days showed reduced adipogenesis visualized by fat droplet accumulation in comparison to control cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). Low levels of ER&#x003b2; could also be detected in untransfected 3T3-L1 cells and its expression was slightly elevated during differentiation (data not shown) underlining the physiological importance of our findings. Overexpression of the ER&#x003b1; isoform in these cells did not show any inhibitory effect on preadipocyte differentiation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). The adipocyte protein 2 (aP2) gene belongs to the classical PPAR&#x003b3;-regulated genes involved in the early phase of adipogenesis <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Tontonoz1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. The expression level of aP2 measured by real-time PCR was significantly elevated in the differentiated control cells (bar 2 vs. 1, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). Overexpression of ER&#x003b2;-but not ER&#x003b1;- in these cells led to a significant reduction of aP2 expression (bar 2 vs. 4 and 6, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g002">Figure 2B</xref>) indicating that endogenous PPAR&#x003b3; activation in 3T3-L1 cells was inhibited by ER&#x003b2;.</p><fig id="pgen-1000108-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000108.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>ER&#x003b2; inhibits PPAR&#x003b3;-dependent adipocyte differentiation and target gene expression.</title><p>A) 3T3-L1 preadipocytes were transfected with the indicated plasmids and cells were treated with differentiation mix (diff) for 3 days, as indicated. Representative phase-contrast images (20&#x000d7;magnifications) after Oil-Red-O staining are shown. B) 3T3-L1 preadipocytes were transfected with the indicated plasmids and cells were treated with differentiation mix (diff) for 3 days as indicated. mRNA expression of aP2 level is shown, as indicated. Real Time quantitative RT-PCR studies were carried out using total RNA. &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. control, # p&#x0003c;0,05 vs. control&#x0002b;diff; ns: not significant vs. control&#x0002b;diff. C) 3T3-L1 preadipocytes were transfected with the indicated plasmids and cells were treated with 10 &#x000b5;M pioglitazone for 3 days, as indicated. Representative phase-contrast images (40&#x000d7;magnifications) after Oil-Red-O staining are shown. D) mRNA expression of aP2 levels measured in transfected cells treated with 10 &#x000b5;M pioglitazone for 3 days, as indicated. Real Time quantitative RT-PCR studies were carried out using total RNA. &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. pSG5&#x0002b;veh, # p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. PPAR&#x003b3;/RXR&#x003b1;&#x0002b;Pio. Values represent means&#x000b1;SEM of at least three independent experiments performed in triplicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.1000108.g002"/></fig><p>Furthermore pioglitazone (10 &#x000b5;M) treatment of 3T3-L1 cells overexpressing PPAR&#x003b3;/RXR&#x003b1; showed increased adipogenesis, an effect that was markedly inhibited by coexpression of ER&#x003b2; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). aP2 expression level was also significantly reduced in cells co-expressing ER&#x003b2; together with PPAR&#x003b3;/RXR&#x003b1; (bar 2 vs. 3, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g002">Figure 2D</xref>). These data indicate that ER&#x003b2; inhibits PPAR&#x003b3;-transcriptional activity resulting in the blockade of PPAR&#x003b3;-induced adipocytic target gene expression and amelioration of adipogenesis.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>PPAR&#x003b3; Target Gene Expression and PPAR&#x003b3; Activity Are Increased in &#x003b2;ERKO Mice</title><p>To investigate ER&#x003b2;'s action on PPAR&#x003b3; in vivo, we studied PPAR&#x003b3; activity and PPAR&#x003b3; target genes in HFD-fed &#x003b2;ERKO and wt mice. &#x003b2;ERKO mice and their wt littermates were fed HFD containing 60&#x00025; calories from fat for 12 weeks followed by the analysis of PPAR&#x003b3;-dependent gene expression in gonadal fat tissue. Adipose mRNA expression of PPAR&#x003b3; target genes involved in triglycerides (TG) synthesis such as lipoprotein lipase (Lpl), phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase (PEPCK) and CD36 was significantly upregulated in &#x003b2;ERKO mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g003">Figure 3</xref> A&#x02013;C). Key mediators of insulin and glucose metabolism such as the retinol-binding protein 4 (RBP4) were also regulated in &#x003b2;ERKO mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g003">Figure 3D</xref>). Consistently with these findings, adiponectin mRNA expression and adiponectin serum levels were elevated in &#x003b2;ERKO mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g003">Figure 3E, F</xref>). No difference of PPAR&#x003b3; target gene regulation between &#x003b2;ERKO and wt mice was observed in liver (data not shown).</p><fig id="pgen-1000108-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000108.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>PPAR&#x003b3; target gene expression and PPAR&#x003b3; activity are increased in &#x003b2;ERKO mice.</title><p>A&#x02013;E) Analysis of Lpl, PEPCK, CD36, RBP4 and adiponectin mRNA expression levels in gonadal fat from HFD-fed wt and &#x003b2;ERKO mice. Real-time quantitative RT-PCR studies were carried out using total RNA prepared from gonadal fat isolated from HFD-fed wt and &#x003b2;ERKO mice (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;3 per group). For details, see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref> and supplemental data. &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. wt-control. F) Adiponectin levels measured in serum isolated from fasted wt and &#x003b2;ERKO mice (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;10 per group); &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. wt-control. Values represent means&#x000b1;SEM. G) Nuclear fractions isolated from gonadal fat from HFD-fed wt and &#x003b2;ERKO mice (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;3 and n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;4, respectively) were incubated with <sup>32</sup>P-labeled PPRE and analyzed by EMSA, as described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>. Real-time quantitative RT-PCR studies for PPAR&#x003b3; mRNA expression in gonadal fat were performed. Additionally 20 &#x000b5;g of the nuclear fraction used in EMSA assay were analyzed in Western Blot using PPAR&#x003b3;-specific antibody.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.1000108.g003"/></fig><p>Positive regulation of a series of adipose PPAR&#x003b3; target genes in &#x003b2;ERKO mice suggested a general induction of PPAR&#x003b3; transcription in &#x003b2;ERKO mice. To prove this, we performed EMSA assays in gonadal fat from &#x003b2;ERKO and wt mice after 12 weeks on HFD. Nuclear fractions isolated from adipose tissues from &#x003b2;ERKO mice showed an increased binding/activation of endogenous PPAR&#x003b3; in comparison to wt mice (line 4&#x02013;7 vs. 1&#x02013;3, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g003">Figure 3G</xref>) in the presence of similar PPAR&#x003b3; expression levels, as shown by real-time RT-PCR analysis and Western Blot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g003">Figure 3G</xref>). Increased adipose PPAR&#x003b3; target gene expression and PPAR&#x003b3;-DNA binding confirmed an augmented PPAR&#x003b3; signaling in adipose tissue from &#x003b2;ERKO mice.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>&#x003b2;ERKO Mice Exhibit Enhanced PPAR&#x003b3; Signaling under Pioglitazone Treatment</title><p>To exclude the possibility that the augmented expression of PPAR&#x003b3; target genes measured in HFD-fed &#x003b2;ERKO is the result of increased adipose tissue mass, we performed experiments using ex-vivo fat pads isolated from wt and &#x003b2;ERKO mice, treated for 24h with 10 &#x000b5;M pioglitazone or vehicle-control, followed by analysis of PPAR&#x003b3; target gene expression using real-time RT-PCR. In this system augmented ligand-induced PPAR&#x003b3; target gene expression mainly results from enhanced PPAR&#x003b3; transcriptional activity and not from increased fat mass. The expression level of PEPCK and Lpl was significantly increased in both wt and &#x003b2;ERKO fat pads under pioglitazone treatment (bar 1 vs. 2 and bar 3 vs. 4 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g004">Figure 4 A and B</xref>). However, pioglitazone-induced PPAR&#x003b3; target gene expression was markedly elevated in &#x003b2;ERKO mice compared to wt mice, indicating an augmented PPAR&#x003b3; signaling in the absence of ER&#x003b2; (bar 2 vs. 4, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g004">Figure 4 A and B</xref>).</p><fig id="pgen-1000108-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000108.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>&#x003b2;ERKO mice exhibit enhanced PPAR&#x003b3; signaling under pioglitazone treatment.</title><p>A&#x0002b;B) Explanted gonadal fat pads isolated from wt- and &#x003b2;ERKO mice were treated for 24h with 10 &#x000b5;M pioglitazone or vehicle control. Real-time quantitative RT-PCR studies on Lpl and PEPCK expression were carried out using total RNA (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;4 per group), as indicated. For details, see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref> and supplemental data. &#x0002a;p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. wt&#x0002b;veh; # p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. wt&#x0002b;Pio. C) ER&#x003b2;-PPAR&#x003b3; interaction in vivo is ligand independent. Analysis of Lpl, PEPCK, CD36, and adiponectin mRNA expression levels in gonadal fat from soy-free-fed and ovariectomized wt female mice, treated for 21 days with DPN (8 mg/Kg) or vehicle control (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;4/group). Real-time quantitative RT-PCR studies were carried out using total RNA prepared from gonadal fat. For details, see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref> and supplemental data. ns: not significant vs. vehicle-treated mice.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.1000108.g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>ER&#x003b2;-PPAR&#x003b3; Interaction <italic>In Vivo</italic> Is Ligand Independent</title><p>To further characterize ER&#x003b2; ligand dependency for its interaction with PPAR&#x003b3; in the mouse model, additional in-vivo studies were performed in estrogen-depleted, ovariectomized wt mice treated with the ER&#x003b2;-ligand DPN. Analysis of PPAR&#x003b3; target genes (Lpl, PEPCK, CD36 and adiponectin) in gonadal fat isolated from these mice revealed no significant differences in the expression level between vehicle and DPN-treated rodents indicating ligand independency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g004">Figure 4C</xref>). These data are consistent with the in-vitro study in 3T3-L1 preadipocytes, where PPAR&#x003b3; activation was not affected by co-treatment with ligands for ER&#x003b2; such as E2 (bar 2 vs. 3, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g001">Figure 1A</xref>) or DPN (data not shown).</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>&#x003b2;ERKO Mice Exhibit Improved Hepatic and Muscular Insulin Signaling</title><p>Given the central role of PPAR&#x003b3; in insulin and glucose metabolism, the metabolic phenotype of &#x003b2;ERKO mice was assessed. No difference in fasting/fed blood glucose food intake, and mean arterial blood pressure was observed between &#x003b2;ERKO and wt mice under HFD (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000108-t002">Table 2</xref>). Body weight gain was significantly enhanced in &#x003b2;ERKO mice, compared to wt mice (mean BW difference &#x003b2;ERKO vs. wt mice after 12 week HFD: 3&#x0002b;/&#x02212;0.4 g, p&#x0003c;0.05, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). Increased body weight in &#x003b2;ERKO mice resulted from increased adipose tissue mass. MRI-analysis of body composition demonstrated significantly higher fat mass in &#x003b2;ERKO mice compared to wt littermates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g005">Figure 5B</xref>), and fat pad weight from gonadal and perirenal depots was increased (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000108-t001">Table 1</xref>). In contrast, liver weight was significantly reduced in &#x003b2;ERKO mice in comparison to wt control littermates (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000108-t001">Table 1</xref>). Reduced hepatic weight likely resulted from decreased TG-accumulation assessed by H/E-staining of liver tissue sections (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g005">Figure 5C</xref>), and by TG quantification in dried liver tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g005">Figure 5D</xref>). In accordance with reduced hepatic TG-content, hepatic insulin signaling was improved. After injection of insulin in the portal vein, liver tissue was dissected and proteins were isolated for Western blot analysis. Insulin-stimulated Akt phosphorylation was enhanced in &#x003b2;ERKO mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g005">Figure 5E</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1000108.s003">Figure S3</xref>). In parallel to decreased TG levels in liver, &#x003b2;ERKO mice had decreased muscular TG-accumulation under HFD and improved insulin signaling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g005">Figure 5F, G</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1000108.s003">Figure S3</xref>). Skeletal muscle and liver are the major insulin responsive tissues, and important sites of glucose metabolism in-vivo. An important mechanism of PPAR&#x003b3;-mediated insulin sensitization involves adipose tissue remodeling and trapping of circulating triglycerides (TG) which protects the liver and skeletal muscle against TG overload. Increased adipose tissue mass in &#x003b2;ERKO mice may protect these animals against TG-overload in liver and skeletal muscle resulting in an improvement of hepatic and muscular insulin sensitivity.</p><fig id="pgen-1000108-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000108.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>&#x003b2;ERKO mice exhibit improved hepatic and muscular insulin signaling.</title><p>A) Body weight development of HFD-fed wt and &#x003b2;ERKO mice. &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. wt-control. B) Change of relative fat mass during 12 weeks of HFD, presented as x-fold over wt mice. &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. wt-control C) H&#x00026;E-stained liver section from HFD-fed wt and &#x003b2;ERKO mice. Representative images (20&#x000d7;magnifications) are shown. D&#x0002b;F) Relative TG content in liver and skeletal muscle of HFD-fed wt and &#x003b2;ERKO mice (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;5 per group). &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. wt-control. E&#x0002b;G) Phosphorylation of Akt kinase in liver and muscle after insulin challenge, as described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>. Representative Western blot analyses using pS473-Akt and total-Akt antibodies are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.1000108.g005"/></fig><table-wrap id="pgen-1000108-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000108.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Relative organ weights of HFD-fed &#x003b2;ERKO mice.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pgen-1000108-t001-1" xlink:href="pgen.1000108.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">wt</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;ERKO</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Gonadal Fat</bold> [mg/g BW]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42,88&#x000b1;3,79</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60,12&#x000b1;5,54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p&#x0003c;0,05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Perirenal Fat</bold> [mg/g BW]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,60&#x000b1;1,41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,552&#x000b1;1,67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p&#x0003c;0,05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Liver</bold> [mg/g BW]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42,63&#x000b1;1,2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35,37&#x000b1;1,44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p&#x0003c;0,01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Heart</bold> [mg/g BW]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,25&#x000b1;0,24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,77&#x000b1;0,23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>Relative weight of gonadal and perirenal fat, liver and heart (mg/g BW). ns: not significant vs. wt-control (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;14 per group).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pgen-1000108-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000108.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Metabolic characterization of HFD-fed &#x003b2;ERKO mice.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pgen-1000108-t002-2" xlink:href="pgen.1000108.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">wt</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;ERKO</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Glucose Fed</bold> [mg/dL]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201 &#x000b1;14,5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">196&#x000b1;16,6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Glucose Fast</bold> [mg/dL]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156&#x000b1;8,54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134&#x000b1;8,287</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Food Intake</bold> [g/day]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,78&#x000b1;0,06</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,39&#x000b1;0,06</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Blood Pressure</bold> [mean BP mmHg]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88&#x000b1;1,7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90&#x000b1;2,1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Energy Expenditure</bold> [kcal/kg/h]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,94&#x000b1;0,32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,44&#x000b1;0,33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Locomotor Activity</bold> [counts/h]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2642,4&#x000b1;719</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2810,5&#x000b1;784</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><p>Glucose level, food intake and mean arterial blood pressure of HFD-fed wt and &#x003b2;ERKO mice (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;14 per group). ns: not significant vs. wt-control. Energy expenditure and locomotor activity was assessed n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;5 mice/ group. Values represent means&#x000b1;SEM.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Systemic Insulin Sensitivity and Glucose Tolerance Are Improved in &#x003b2;ERKO Mice</title><p>Next we investigated insulin and glucose metabolism in &#x003b2;ERKO and wt mice. Whole body glucose disposal was assessed using an oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). Following an oral glucose challenge &#x003b2;ERKO mice on HFD had moderately but significantly improved glucose tolerance compared to HFD-fed wt mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g006">Figure 6A, B</xref>). In addition insulin sensitivity measured by an insulin tolerance test (ITT) was improved in comparison to wt mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g006">Figure 6C, D</xref>). No difference in fasting and fed blood glucose was observed between &#x003b2;ERKO and wt mice under HFD (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000108-t002">Table 2</xref>). Despite an increased fat mass in &#x003b2;ERKO mice, systemic insulin sensitivity and glucose tolerance were significantly improved under HFD when compared to wt-control. To further examine the enhanced weight gain and fat deposition in &#x003b2;ERKO mice, we performed indirect calorimetry and monitored food consumption. Food intake did not differ between wt-control and &#x003b2;ERKO mice (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000108-t002">Table 2</xref>). However, deletion of ER&#x003b2; resulted in a marked increase of food efficiency (ratio of weight gain and food intake, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g006">Figure 6E</xref>). No significant difference in O<sub>2</sub> consumption (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g006">Figure 6F</xref>), energy expenditure (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000108-t002">Table 2</xref>), or locomotor activity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000108-t002">Table 2</xref>) was detected between &#x003b2;ERKO and wt mice. Low RQ values have previously been described for rodents under HFD and in diabetes <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Maxwell1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Both wt and &#x003b2;ERKO mice exhibited low RQ values. &#x003b2;ERKO mice had a significantly higher RQ when compared to wt-controls which may be indicative for attenuated fatty acid (FA) oxidation promoting fat accumulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g006">Figure 6G</xref>). These data show that &#x003b2;ERKO mice are partially protected against HFD induced insulin resistance. Increased fat mass may likely result from increased food efficiency based on reduced oxidative utilization of fat and increased fat storage. The metabolic phenotype of &#x003b2;ERKO mice including increased fat mass, reduced hepatic/muscular TG and improved systemic insulin sensitivity exhibits high similarity to augmented PPAR&#x003b3; activation e.g. under thiazolidinedione (TZD) treatment <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Frias1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1000108-Staels1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>.</p><fig id="pgen-1000108-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000108.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Systemic insulin sensitivity and glucose tolerance are improved in &#x003b2;ERKO mice.</title><p>A&#x0002b;B) Oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT) with 2 g/kg body weight glucose and subsequent glucose analysis from the tail vein was performed as described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>. The area under the curve (AUC) was calculated, as indicated (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;13 per group). &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. wt-control. C&#x0002b;D) An Insulin tolerance test (ITT) was performed by an intraperitoneal injection of 0.5 units/kg body weight insulin and glucose analysis from the tail vein, as described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>. The area under the curve (AUC) was calculated, as indicated (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;13 and n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;10 per group respectively). &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. wt-control. Values represent means&#x000b1;SEM. E) Food efficiency (ratio of weight gain and food intake) was calculated from change in body weight gain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g001">Figure 1G</xref>) and average food intake/ day (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000108-t002">Table 2</xref>). Data are presented as x-fold over wt mice. &#x0002a;&#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.01 vs. wt-control. F&#x0002b;G) O<sub>2</sub> consumption (VO<sub>2</sub>), and respiratory quotient (RQ) from HFD-fed wt and &#x003b2;ERKO mice. RQ was calculated as the ratio between CO<sub>2</sub> produced (VCO<sub>2</sub>) and O<sub>2</sub> consumed (VO<sub>2</sub>) using the calorimetry system described under methods. &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. wt-control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.1000108.g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Disruption of PPAR&#x003b3; Signaling by Antisense Oligonucleotide Injection Reversed the Metabolic Phenotype of &#x003b2;ERKO Mice</title><p>To directly demonstrate the role of PPAR&#x003b3; in HFD-fed &#x003b2;ERKO mice, PPAR&#x003b3; signaling was disrupted by intraperitoneal (i.p.) injection of PPAR&#x003b3; antisense oligonucleotide (ASO). HFD-fed &#x003b2;ERKO mice were injected twice a week for 6 weeks with either PPAR&#x003b3; ASO or control oligonucleotides. PPAR&#x003b3; expression was significantly reduced in liver of ASO-treated &#x003b2;ERKO mice, similar to previously reported results in apoB/BATless mice (data not shown) <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. However, suppression of hepatic PPAR&#x003b3; by ASO injection is unlikely to play an important role in our model, since hepatic PPAR&#x003b3; signaling did not differ between wt and &#x003b2;ERKO mice, respectively. More importantly, i.p. application of PPAR&#x003b3; ASO in &#x003b2;ERKO mice resulted in 63&#x000b1;4.8&#x00025; (p&#x0003c;0.05) reduction of PPAR&#x003b3; expression in gonadal adipose tissue compared to &#x003b2;ERKO mice injected with control oligonucleotides (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g007">Figure 7A</xref>). Accordingly, expression of the PPAR&#x003b3; target genes Lpl, PEPCK, CD36, and adiponectin was markedly decreased in adipose tissue from PPAR&#x003b3; ASO-injected &#x003b2;ERKO mice, and adipocyte diameters were increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g007">Figure 7A, G</xref>). These data corroborate a relevant reduction of adipose PPAR&#x003b3; signaling by ASO intervention. Body weight gain and gonadal fat accumulation in HFD-fed-&#x003b2;ERKO mice were significantly attenuated by PPAR&#x003b3;-ASO injection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g007">Figure 7B, C</xref>). Finally, blockade of adipose PPAR&#x003b3; by ASO led to reversal of the improved insulin response observed in &#x003b2;ERKO mice, and to an impairment of insulin sensitivity and glucose tolerance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g007">Figure 7D&#x02013;F</xref>). Together these data underline the importance of adipose PPAR&#x003b3; signaling for the metabolic phenotype observed in &#x003b2;ERKO mice.</p><fig id="pgen-1000108-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000108.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Disruption of PPAR&#x003b3; signaling by antisense oligonucleotide injection reversed the metabolic phenotype of &#x003b2;ERKO mice.</title><p>ASO's complementary to murine PPAR&#x003b3; and control ASO were injected intraperitoneally twice a week into HFD-fed &#x003b2;ERKO mice for 6 weeks. A) Analysis of PPAR&#x003b3;, Lpl, PEPCK, CD36, and adiponectin mRNA expression levels in gonadal fat from HFD-fed &#x003b2;ERKO mice treated with ASO-control (&#x02212;) or PPAR&#x003b3; ASO (&#x0002b;). Real-time quantitative RT-PCR studies were carried out using total RNA prepared from gonadal fat. For details, see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref> and supplemental data. &#x0002a;p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. ASO-control. B&#x0002b;C) Change of relative fat mass and BW during 6 weeks of HFD in &#x003b2;ERKO mice treated with ASO-control or PPAR&#x003b3; ASO, presented as &#x00025; from ASO-control. &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. ASO-control. D&#x0002b;E) An ITT was performed by an intraperitoneal injection of 0.5 units/kg body weight insulin and glucose analysis from the tail vein, as described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>. The area under the curve (AUC) was calculated, as indicated. &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. ASO-control. F) An OGTT with 2 g/kg body weight glucose and subsequent glucose analysis from the tail vein was performed as described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>. The area under the curve (AUC) was calculated. &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. ASO-control. G) H&#x00026;E-stained gonadal fat section from HFD-fed &#x003b2;ERKO mice treated with ASO-control or PPAR&#x003b3; ASO. Representative images (10&#x000d7;magnifications) are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.1000108.g007"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>ER&#x003b2;-Mediated Inhibition of PPAR&#x003b3; Activity Involves SRC1 and TIF 2</title><p>Nuclear coactivators such as SRC1 and TIF2 are important mediators of ER&#x003b2; and PPAR&#x003b3;-induced transcriptional activation. It has previously been shown that competition of distinct nuclear receptor (NR) for coactivator binding results in a negative cross-talk between NRs <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Lopez1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. To prove whether common coactivators are involved in ER&#x003b2;-PPAR&#x003b3; interactions, SRC1, TIF2, DRIP205 or PGC1&#x003b1; were co-expressed together with ER&#x003b2; and ligand induced PPAR&#x003b3; activation was measured.</p><p>Overexpression of SRC1 and TIF2 prevented the ER&#x003b2;-mediated inhibition of PPAR&#x003b3; activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g008">Figure 8A, B</xref>) whereas the presence of DRIP205 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g008">Figure 8C</xref>) and PGC1&#x003b1; (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1000108.s004">Figure S4</xref>) had no effect. To demonstrate that SRC1 and TIF2 are also involved in ER&#x003b2;-PPAR&#x003b3; interaction in-vivo, we performed ChIP experiments with gonadal fat from HFD-fed &#x003b2;ERKO and wt mice. The adiponectin promoter was selected as a PPAR&#x003b3;-target promoter. Binding of SRC1 and TIF2 to the adiponectin promoter was enhanced in gonadal fat from &#x003b2;ERKO mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g008">Figure 8D</xref>), indicating that the absence of ER&#x003b2; in adipose tissue results in exaggerated coactivator binding to a PPAR&#x003b3; target promoter. Together these data suggest that the coactivators SRC1 and TIF2 are involved in the negative regulation of PPAR&#x003b3; by ER&#x003b2; in vitro and in vivo.</p><fig id="pgen-1000108-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000108.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>ER&#x003b2; inhibits PPAR&#x003b3; activity in a ligand-independent manner involving SRC1&#x0002b;TIF2.</title><p>A&#x02013;C) 3T3-L1 preadipocytes were transfected with the indicated plasmids together with pGal4-hPPAR&#x003b3;DEF, pG5TkGL3 and renilla followed by treatment with 10 &#x000b5;M pioglitazone as indicated. &#x0002a;p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. pSG5&#x0002b;veh; # p&#x0003c;0,05 vs. pSG5&#x0002b;Pio, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pgen.1000108.e001.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. ER&#x003b2;&#x0002b;Pio, ns: not significant vs. ER&#x003b2;&#x0002b;Pio. Values represent means&#x000b1;SEM of at least two independent experiments performed in triplicates. D) ChIP experiment with gonadal fat from HFD-fed wt mice and &#x003b2;ERKO mice. IP was performed using Flag, RNA Pol II, SRC1 and TIF2 as indicated. (&#x02013; no template control (NTC), &#x0002b; genomic DNA, input: 1&#x00025; of the initial probe taken for IP). For details please see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.1000108.g008"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>The present study demonstrates that ER&#x003b2; is a negative regulator of ligand-induced PPAR&#x003b3; activity in-vitro. Consequently, data from &#x003b2;ERKO mice suggest that ER&#x003b2; negatively regulates insulin and glucose metabolism which may, at least in part, result from an impairment of regular adipose tissue function based on a negative cross-talk between ER&#x003b2; and PPAR&#x003b3;. Loss of ER&#x003b2; resulted in enhanced body weight gain and fat accumulation in HFD-fed mice. However, absence of ER&#x003b2; prevented hepatic/ muscular triglyceride overload, preserved regular insulin signaling in liver/ skeletal muscle, and improved whole-body insulin sensitivity and glucose tolerance under HFD. This metabolic phenotype strongly suggested augmented PPAR&#x003b3; signaling in mice lacking ER&#x003b2;. And indeed, PPAR&#x003b3; target genes and PPAR&#x003b3;-DNA binding were markedly induced in gonadal fat from &#x003b2;ERKO mice. Along this line, blockade of adipose PPAR&#x003b3; signaling by PPAR&#x003b3; ASO injection reversed the metabolic changes in &#x003b2;ERKO mice.</p><p>A mutual signaling cross-talk between ERs and PPAR&#x003b3; has been described previously. PPAR&#x003b3; together with its heterodimeric partner RXR&#x003b1; has been shown to suppress ER-induced target gene expression through competitive binding to an ERE site in the vitellogenin A2 promoter <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Keller1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. In accordance with a bidirectional interaction, Wang and colleagues demonstrated that ERs are capable of inhibiting ligand-induced PPAR&#x003b3; activation in two different breast cancer cell lines <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. In contrast to our results, these authors show that basal and agonist-stimulated PPRE-activity is also blocked by ER&#x003b1;. Transcriptional activity of PPAR&#x003b3; differs markedly depending on the cell system and tissues. The highest level of PPAR&#x003b3;-mediated transcription has been described in adipocytes and adipocytic cell lines, where molecular conditions such as cofactor availability seemed to be optimized <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Tontonoz2" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Compared to adipocytes, breast cancer cells exhibit low PPAR&#x003b3; expression and activity reflected by a less than 2-fold induction of PPRE-activity after ligand stimulation <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. The presence of PPAR&#x003b3; suppression by ER&#x003b1; in breast cancer cells might be a result of weak basal PPAR&#x003b3; transcriptional activity in these cells. In contrast, the pronounced activation of the exogenous PPAR&#x003b3; LBD in 3T3-L1 preadipocytes may require more potent inhibitory stimuli which could not be achieved by ER&#x003b1; overexpression in our system.</p><p>Suppression of PPAR&#x003b3;-LBD activation by ER&#x003b2; did not depend on ER&#x003b2; ligands which is consistent with previous reports <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Also our in vivo studies in estrogen-depleted, ovariectomized wt mice treated with the ER&#x003b2;-ligand DPN indicate that PPAR&#x003b3;-ER&#x003b2; interaction is ligand independent. More importantly, overexpression of a truncated form of ER&#x003b2; containing solely the ER&#x003b2;-LBD/ AF2 domain did not induce any inhibitory effect on PPAR&#x003b3; suggesting an important role of ER&#x003b2;'s NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal AF1 domain for ER&#x003b2;-PPAR&#x003b3; interactions. Consistently, activity of the ER-AF1 domain is usually not dependent on ligand activation <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Metzger1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Furthermore, Tremblay and coworkers demonstrated that ER&#x003b2;-AF1 activation involves ligand-independent recruitment of SRC-1, a cofactor involved in ER&#x003b2;-PPAR&#x003b3; interactions in our study <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Tremblay1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. These data corroborate our observation that PPAR&#x003b3; suppression by ER&#x003b2; involves the AF1 domain and ligand-independent interactions with the coactivators SRC1 and TIF2. Repression of PPAR&#x003b3; activity through ER&#x003b2; was reversed by titration of the p160 coactivators, SRC1 and TIF2, suggesting that the suppressive action of ER&#x003b2; is a result of p160 coactivator interaction with ER&#x003b2; thereby preventing the binding of PPAR&#x003b3; to the same coactivators. Similar interactions have been described previously for ER interaction with the thyroid receptor <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Lopez1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>.</p><p>The present study demonstrates for the first time that ER&#x003b2; impairs insulin sensitivity and glucose tolerance under HFD implicating pro-diabetogenic actions of this receptor. In consonance, we could recently demonstrate that ER&#x003b2; has a suppressive role on glucose transporter 4 (GLUT4) expression in skeletal muscle <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Barros1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1000108-Barros2" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. GLUT4 has been identified as the major mediator of insulin-induced glucose uptake in fat and skeletal muscle. In addition, removal of the E2-ER&#x003b2; signaling by ovariectomy in ER&#x003b1;-deficient mice improved glucose and insulin metabolism supporting the diabetogenic effect of ER&#x003b2; <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Naaz1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Loss of ER&#x003b2; resulted in a marked augmentation of adipose PPAR&#x003b3; activity in our model indicating that ER&#x003b2; mediates its metabolic actions by a negative interaction with PPAR&#x003b3; in adipose tissue. This concept is corroborated by a number of observations. HFD-fed &#x003b2;ERKO mice exhibited increased adipose tissue mass in the presence of improved insulin sensitivity and glucose tolerance. These metabolic changes are usually observed under chronic PPAR&#x003b3; stimulation <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Picard1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. PPAR&#x003b3; has been identified as an essential regulator of whole-body insulin sensitivity. Two major mechanisms have been described: (1) Adipose PPAR&#x003b3; protects non-adipose tissue against excessive lipid overload and maintains normal organ function and insulin responses (liver, skeletal muscle) by preserving regular adipose tissue function, and (2) Adipose PPAR&#x003b3; guarantees a balanced and adequate production of adipocytokine secretion such as adiponectin from adipose tissue, factors which are important mediators of insulin action in peripheral tissues <xref rid="pgen.1000108-He1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pgen.1000108-Zhang2" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. Both processes could be observed in &#x003b2;ERKO mice. Further support of this notion comes from clinical actions of anti-diabetic PPAR&#x003b3; agonists (TZD) <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Frias1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1000108-Staels1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Activation of PPAR&#x003b3; by TZDs in diabetic patients resembles the phenotype of &#x003b2;ERKO mice including improved insulin sensitization and glucose tolerance in the presence of weight gain. We also observed increased food efficiency and changes in nutrient partitioning reflected by an increased RQ in &#x003b2;ERKO mice. Loss of ER&#x003b2; appears to result in attenuated fatty acid (FA) oxidation which may favor the storage of TGs in adipose tissue and increased fat accumulation, and may provide a possible explanation for the enhanced weight gain. Interestingly, treatment of obese mice with a synthetic PPAR&#x003b3; agonist has been shown to mediate similar changes including an increase in food efficiency and higher RQ values <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Sell1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. Finally, blockade of PPAR&#x003b3; signaling in adipose tissue of &#x003b2;ERKO mice resulted in a reversal of the metabolic phenotype corroborating the importance of adipose PPAR&#x003b3; in the present model. The observed suppression of hepatic PPAR&#x003b3; activity by ASO injection is unlikely to play a major role since the initial metabolic characterization of untreated &#x003b2;ERKO mice under HFD did not reveal any dysregulation of hepatic PPAR&#x003b3; signaling. In summary, the metabolic phenotype of &#x003b2;ERKO mice is mediated by an augmented adipose PPAR&#x003b3; action, which implies that in the presence of ER&#x003b2;, PPAR&#x003b3; activity might be partially suppressed.</p><p>The notion, that ER&#x003b2;-PPAR&#x003b3; crosstalk requires receptor-p160 interaction, was underlined by our observations in WAT from &#x003b2;ERKO mice. Binding of SRC1 and TIF2 to the PPAR&#x003b3;-regulated adiponectin promoter in WAT was enhanced in the absence of ER&#x003b2;. It has recently been demonstrated that p160 coactivators are important regulators of PPAR&#x003b3; transcriptional activity in WAT <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Picard2" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. In particular, TIF2 has been identified as a nuclear coactivator involved in the adipogenic actions of PPAR&#x003b3;. Future experiments are required to define the functional relevance of TIF2 and SRC1 in our model. So far one may conclude that the metabolic phenotype of HFD-fed &#x003b2;ERKO mice is, at least in part, explained by increased adipose PPAR&#x003b3; activity as a result of exaggerated binding of p160 coactivators to PPAR&#x003b3;-regulated target gene promoters. Diabetogenic actions of ER&#x003b2; are of major significance for the pharmaceutical development of new ER&#x003b2;-selective agonists intended for use against a multitude of diseases such as rheumatoid arthritis or postmenopausal osteoporosis <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Follettie1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1000108-Komm1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. Despite the high tissue selectivity of such compounds, and despite the fact that the actions observed in our study were ligand-independent, one has to be aware of the potentially deleterious actions of ER&#x003b2; on insulin- and glucose metabolism. As a precautionary measure metabolic profiling of new ER&#x003b2; agonist should be performed.</p><p>Collectively, our data provide first evidence that ER&#x003b2; negatively regulates insulin signaling and glucose metabolism that involves an impairment of regular adipose PPAR&#x003b3; function. Moreover our data suggest that the coactivators SRC1 and TIF2 are involved in this inhibition. In consonance, impairment of insulin and glucose metabolism by ER&#x003b2; has significant implications for our understanding of hormone receptor-dependent pathophysiology of metabolic diseases, and is essential for the development of new ER&#x003b2;-selective agonists.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Animal Care and Treatment</title><p>Female estrogen receptor &#x003b2; -/- mice (&#x003b2;ERKO) received from J.-A. Gustafsson (Karolinska Institutet, Huddinge, Sweden) and their wt littermates were housed in a temperature controlled (25&#x000b0;C) facility with a 12-h light/dark cycle and genotyped using genomic DNA isolation kit (Invitek) and PCR primers described elsewhere <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Krege1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. 4&#x02013;5 week old mice were fed ad libitum with a high-fat diet (60&#x00025; kcal from fat, <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Schupp1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>) for 12 weeks. Body weight and food intake were determined throughout the experiment. At start and end of treatment, body composition was determined by nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (Bruker's Minispec MQ10). After 12 weeks' treatment, blood samples were collected from overnight-fasted animals by retroorbital venous puncture under isoflurane anesthesia for analysis of serum adiponectin (mouse-adiponectin ELISA; Linco Research) and glucose (colorimetric glucose test; Cypress Diagnostics). An OGTT using a dose of 2 g/kg body weight (BW) glucose and ITT with intraperitoneally injected 0.5 units/kg BW insulin (Actrapid; Novo Nordisk) were performed. Tail vein blood was used for glucose quantification with a glucometer (Precision Xtra; Abbott). Blood pressure was measured invasively in the abdominal aorta using a solid-state pressure transducer catheter (Micro-Tip 3F; Millar Instruments) under isoflurane anesthesia. Afterwards animals were killed and organs were dissected. For immunohistochemical studies organs were fixed in 4&#x00025; formalin, embedded in paraffin and stained with Haematoxylin/Eosin (H&#x00026;E); for RNA, Western blot analysis and measurement of TG content isolated organs were frozen in liquid nitrogen; for EMSA and Chromatin IP assays abdominal fat was stored in ice-cold PBS with proteinase inhibitors (Complete Mini, Roche), and immediately proceeded as described below.</p><p>For DPN- treatment, 10 week old female C57BL/6J mice were ovariectomized, and after 1 week recovery set on soy-free diet. Subsequently mice were treated for 21 days with DPN (8 mg/kg) or vehicle administered using subcutaneous pellets (Innovative Research of America). Afterwards animals were killed under isoflurane anesthesia and organs were dissected.</p><p>All animal procedures were in accordance with institutional guidelines and were approved.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Antisense Experiments</title><p>ASO complementary to murine PPAR&#x003b3; (Gen-BankTM accession number U09138.1), ISIS 141941, <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-AGTGGTCTTCCATCACGGAG-3&#x02032;</named-content>, and ASO control, ISIS 141923, <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-CCTTCCTGAAGGTTCCTCC-3&#x02032;</named-content> was generously provided by ISIS Pharmaceuticals (Carlsbad, CA, U.S.A.). Both ASO's were injected intraperitoneally twice a week into 6 week-old female &#x003b2;ERKO mice (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;7 per group). Injections were continued over 6 weeks at a dose of 100 mg/kg/week as described previously <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. At the end of the experiment animals were metabolically phenotyped as described above.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Energy Expenditure, Locomotor Activity, and RQ</title><p>After HFD feeding, &#x003b2;ERKO mice and their wt littermates were analyzed for energy expenditure, RQ, and locomotor activity using a custom-made 4-cage calorimetry system (LabMaster; TSE Systems). The instrument consists of a combination of highly sensitive feeding and drinking sensors for automated online measurement. The calorimetry system is an open-circuit system that determines O<sub>2</sub> consumption, CO<sub>2</sub> production, and RQ. A photobeam-based activity monitoring system detects and records every ambulatory movement, including rearing and climbing movements, in every cage. All the parameters can be measured continuously. Mice (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;7 per group) were placed in the calorimetry system cages for 24h.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Explanted Gonadal Fat Pads Experiments</title><p>Tissue samples from gonadal fat were prepared from female wt and &#x003b2;ERKO mice. Explanted gonadal fat samples were washed 3 times with ice-cold Hanks Balanced Salt Solution (HBSS) and treated for 24h with 10 &#x000b5;M pioglitazone or vehicle in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium F2 (DMEM:F12, Invitrogen). Afterwards tissue samples were washed with ice-cold PBS and RNA extraction was performed using trizol (Invitrogen).</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Cell Culture and Differentiation</title><p>3T3-L1 preadipocytes were purchased from the American Type Culture Collection. Preadipocytes were cultured in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium with 10&#x00025; Fetal Bovine Serum (FBS) and 1&#x00025; Pen-Strep (Invitrogen). For differentiation experiments preadipocytes were grown to confluence and after 12h culture medium was supplemented with methylisobutylxanthine (0.5 mM), dexamethasone (0.25 &#x000b5;M), and insulin (1 &#x000b5;g/ml) in DMEM containing 10&#x00025; FBS for 72h <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Schupp1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Afterwards cells were washed with ice-cold PBS and RNA extraction was performed using trizol (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's instructions. For the staining procedure differentiated cells were washed twice with ice-cold PBS, fixed with 4&#x00025; PFA, and stained for 1h at room temperature with Oil-red-O solution.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Transfection and Luciferase Reporter Assays</title><p>Transient transfection and luciferase assays were performed as previously described <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Schupp1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Briefly 3T3-L1 cells were plated in 12-well plates and transfected using lipofectamine 2000 and OptiMEM (Invitrogen) with 100 ng pGal4-hPPAR&#x003b3;DEF; 400 ng pG5TkGL3, TIF2-pSG5, DRIP205-pSG5 (kindly provided by B. Staels, Institut Pasteur de Lille, France), 5 ng pRL-CMV, a renilla luciferase reporter vector (Promega), hPPAR&#x003b3;2-pSG5 and hRXR&#x003b1;-pCDNA, pSG5 (Stratagene), hSRC1-pSG5 (kindly provided by M. Parker, Institute of Reproductive and Developmental Biology, Imperial College London, United Kingdom), pERE-TkGL3 (kindly provided by P.J. Kushner, Metabolic Research Unit and Diabetes Center, University of California, San Francisco, USA), hER&#x003b1;-pSG5 and ER&#x003b2;-pSG5 (kindly provided by P. Chambon, Institut Clinique de la Souris, Illkirch Cedex, France), and PGC1&#x003b1; kindly provided by Addgene, USA. Delta AF1-ER&#x003b2;-pSG5 was cloned from full length ER&#x003b2;-pSG5. After 3h of transfection cells were washed, left for 12h in serum deprived medium (0.5&#x00025; FCS, 1&#x00025; Pen-Strep), and afterwards treated for 24h with 10 &#x000b5;M pioglitazone (Takeda Pharmaceutical Co. Ltd, Japan) or vehicle (DMSO). When treated with E2 or specific ER&#x003b2; agonist diarylpropionitrile (DPN), cells were cultivated in phenol red free DMEM and coal-striped FCS. Luciferase activity was measured 36 h after transfection using the dual-luciferase reporter assay system (Promega). Transfection experiments were performed in triplicate and repeated at least three times.</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>RNA and Protein Analysis</title><p>Total RNA from cultured preadipocytes, abdominal fat tissue and skeletal muscle was isolated using trizol (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's instructions. For real-time PCR analysis RNA samples were DNAse digested (Invitrogen), reverse transcribed using Superscript (Promega), RNasin (Promega), dNTPs (Invitrogen), according to the manufacturer's instructions, and used in quantitative PCR reactions in the presence of a fluorescent dye (Sybrgreen, BioRad). Relative abundance of mRNA was calculated after normalization to 18S ribosomal RNA. Primer sequences are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1000108.s005">Table S1</xref>. For Western blot detection of ER&#x003b2; cells were grown on &#x003a6;10 cm plates and transfected with increasing amount of ER&#x003b2; plasmid or empty vector control. After 24h cells were harvested and WB analysis was performed as following: cells (and tissues for Akt analysis) were lysed in RIPA buffer (50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1&#x00025; Nonidet P-40, 2.5&#x00025; glycerol, 1 mM EGTA, 50 mM NaF, 1 mM Na<sub>3</sub>VO<sub>4</sub>, 10 mM Na<sub>4</sub>P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub>, 100 &#x000b5;M phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride with proteinase inhibitors (Complete Mini, Roche). Lysates (tissues (30 &#x000b5;g) and cells (20 &#x000b5;g)) were analyzed by immunoblotting using antibody raised against ER&#x003b2; (H-150, Santa Cruz), antibody raised against pS473- Akt and total-Akt (Cell Signalling), and secondary horseradish-conjugated antibodies (Amersham). For PPAR&#x003b3; immunoblotting, 20 &#x000b5;g of nuclear fractions used for EMSA were analyzed using antibody raised against PPAR&#x003b3; (E-8, Santa Cruz). For detection, enhanced chemiluminescent substrate kit (Amersham) was used.</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>EMSA</title><p>Nuclear extracts were prepared by using a nonionic detergent method as described previously <xref rid="pgen.1000108-ForystLudwig1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. The inputs were normalized for protein contents, as ER&#x003b2;-deficient mice have increased fat tissue mass. Detection of PPAR&#x003b3; was performed with a [<sup>32</sup>P] &#x003b3;ATP-labeled PPRE oligo (<named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-CAAAACTAGGTCAAAGGTCA-3&#x02032;</named-content>
<named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;- TGACCTTTGACCTAGTTTTG-3&#x02032;</named-content>). The DNA binding reactions were performed with 40 &#x000b5;l of binding buffer (20 &#x000b5;g nuclear extracts, 2 &#x000b5;g of poly(dI-dC), 1 &#x000b5;g of bovine serum albumin (BSA), 5 mM dithiothreitol (DTT), 20 mM HEPES, pH 8.4, 60 mM KCl, and 10&#x00025; glycerol) for 30 min at 37&#x000b0;C. For competition experiments, a cold oligonucleotide probe was used. The reaction products were analyzed via 5&#x00025; polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis using 12.5 mM Tris, 12.5 mM boric acid, and 0.25 mM EDTA, pH 8.3. Gels were dried and exposed to Amersham TM film (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech) at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C using an intensifying screen.</p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title>Chromatin IP</title><p>Abdominal fat tissue (gonadal fat) isolated from wt and &#x003b2;ERKO mice was washed in ice-cold PBS with proteinase inhibitors (Complete Mini, Roche), cut into small pieces, and incubated for 12h in 1&#x00025; formaldehyde, PBS and proteinase inhibitors (Complete Mini, Roche) with rotation at 4&#x000b0;C. Formaldehyde was removed by intensive washing in ice-cold PBS and centrifugation. Samples were lysed in RIPA (with proteinase inhibitors, Complete Mini, Roche), sonicated on ice (Sonopuls HD 2070, 4 times 10s, 100&#x00025;), and centrifuged. Samples from each group were pooled and protein content of clear phase lysates was measured using a Bradford assay (Amersham). For each immunoprecipitation (IP) 1.5 mg of protein was taken. The volume of the samples was kept constant by using dilution buffer (prepared according to Upstate protocol). For preclearance 90 &#x000b5;l of Protein A Sepharose slurry (Amersham) was added, and the samples were rotated for 1h in 4&#x000b0;C. After centrifugation beads were discarded, and 1&#x00025; of supernatant volume per aliquot was used as an input control. The residual volume was incubated with 6 &#x000b5;g of appropriate antibodies (anti-Pol II (C-18, Santa Cruz), anti-Flag (Sigma), anti-SRC1 (M-20, Santa Cruz), anti-TIF2 (C-20, Santa Cruz)). The antibody-bound proteins were then precipitated using 300 &#x000b5;l Protein A Sepharose slurry (Amersham), washed and further processed according to the Upstate protocol.</p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title>Quantification of Hepatic/Muscular Triglycerides</title><p>Triglyceride-content in skeletal muscle and liver was measured as described previously <xref rid="pgen.1000108-Cheng1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. Briefly, tissues were homogenized in liquid nitrogen and treated with ice-cold chloroform/methanol/water mixture (2:1:0.8) for 2 min. After centrifugation the aqueous layer was removed and the chloroform layer was decanted. The mixture was incubated at 70&#x000b0;C for chloroform clearance, and the residues were dissolved in isopropanol, and assessed for the triglyceride content using an enzymatic-calorimetric test (Cypress diagnostics) according to the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec id="s4k"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Results from real-time PCR of cell lines, transfections, and animal experiments were analyzed by ANOVA followed by multiple comparison testing or with paired/unpaired t tests, as appropriate. Data are expressed as mean&#x000b1;SEM or as indicated. Results were considered to be statistically significant at p&#x0003c;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen.1000108.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>ER&#x003b2; inhibits PPAR&#x003b3; activity in vitro. In order to demonstrate a molecular interaction between PPAR&#x003b3; and ER&#x003b2; in a metabolically relevant cell system, we first investigated ligand-dependent PPAR&#x003b3; activity in the presence of &#x003b2; in 3T3-L1 preadipocytes. Cells were transfected with 100 ng of PPAR&#x003b3;, 50 ng of RXR&#x003b1;, 700 ng of PPRE-luc, 5 ng of renilla, and increasing amount of ER&#x003b2;, as indicated. Afterwards cells were treated with the PPAR&#x003b3;-agonist pioglitazone (10 &#x000b5;M), and PPAR&#x003b3; activation was measured using PPRE-luc luciferase assay. Upon pioglitazone stimulation, 3T3-L1 preadipocytes showed increased PPAR&#x003b3; activation. Overexpression of ER&#x003b2; led to a marked inhibition of ligand-dependent PPAR&#x003b3; activity (bar 1 vs. 2 and 3). # p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. control.</p><p>(0.22 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.1000108.s001.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen.1000108.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>ER&#x003b1; does not inhibit PPAR&#x003b3; activity. 3T3-L1 preadipocytes were transfected with the indicated plasmids together with pGal4-hPPAR&#x003b3;DEF, pG5TkGL3 and renilla, followed by treatment with 10 &#x000b5;M pioglitazone or vehicle control; &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. control&#x0002b;veh; &#x000b0; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. control&#x0002b;Pio.</p><p>(0.31 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.1000108.s002.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen.1000108.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>Densitometrical quantification of the Western blot analysis. Densitometrical quantification of the Western blot analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000108-g005">Figure 5E</xref>/G) was performed by calculating the Akt-P/total Akt ratio. &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. wt controls.</p><p>(0.21 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.1000108.s003.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen.1000108.s004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p>PGC1&#x003b1; overexpression does not affect ER&#x003b2;-mediated PPAR&#x003b3; repression. 3T3-L1 preadipocytes were transfected with the PGC1&#x003b1; plasmids together with pGal4-hPPAR&#x003b3;DEF, pG5TkGL3 and renilla and 500 ng ER&#x003b2; followed by treatment with 10 &#x000b5;M pioglitazone as indicated; &#x0002a;p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. pSG5&#x0002b;veh; # p&#x0003c;0,05 vs. pSG5&#x0002b;Pio.</p><p>(0.26 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.1000108.s004.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen.1000108.s005"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>Primer sequences used for qRT-PCR and ChIP analysis.</p><p>(0.05 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.1000108.s005.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank J. Reinemund and H. Funke-Kaiser for help in establishing the ChIP experiments, and M. Sommerfeld for help with the immunohistochemical analysis. The authors thank S. Anker for kindly providing the MRI equipment.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>J&#x000c5;G is shareholder and consultant of KaroBio AB. SB is an employee at ISIS Pharmaceuticals, Carlsbad, California, United States of America.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>AFL is supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG-GK 754 III). MC is supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG-KI 712/ 3-1). TU is supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG-GK 754-III, DFG-GK 865-II). UK is supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG-GK 754-III, DFG-GK 865-II, DFG-KI 712/ 3-1.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pgen.1000108-Nilsson1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Estrogen receptor transcription and transactivation: Basic aspects of estrogen action.</article-title>
<source>Breast Cancer Res</source>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>360</fpage>
<lpage>366</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11250729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Smith1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Malley</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Coregulator function: a key to understanding tissue specificity of selective receptor modulators.</article-title>
<source>Endocr Rev</source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>45</fpage>
<lpage>71</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14769827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Osborne1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiff</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Estrogen-receptor biology: continuing progress and therapeutic implications.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Oncol</source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>1616</fpage>
<lpage>1622</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15755967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-McKenna1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKenna</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Malley</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Teaching resources. An interactive course in nuclear receptor signaling: concepts and models.</article-title>
<source>Sci STKE</source>
<volume>2005</volume>
<fpage>tr22</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16131668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Haslam1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haslam</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Obesity.</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>
<volume>366</volume>
<fpage>1197</fpage>
<lpage>1209</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16198769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-RegitzZagrosek1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Regitz-Zagrosek</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Therapeutic implications of the gender-specific aspects of cardiovascular disease.</article-title>
<source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>425</fpage>
<lpage>438</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16672926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-RegitzZagrosek2"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Regitz-Zagrosek</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmkuhl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Weickert</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Gender differences in the metabolic syndrome and their role for cardiovascular disease.</article-title>
<source>Clin Res Cardiol</source>
<volume>95</volume>
<fpage>136</fpage>
<lpage>147</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16598526</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Barros1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>UF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Estrogen receptors: new players in diabetes mellitus.</article-title>
<source>Trends Mol Med</source>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Carr1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>The emergence of the metabolic syndrome with menopause.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>
<volume>88</volume>
<fpage>2404</fpage>
<lpage>2411</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12788835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Cooke1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Heine</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubahn</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>The role of estrogen and estrogen receptor-alpha in male adipose tissue.</article-title>
<source>Mol Cell Endocrinol</source>
<volume>178</volume>
<fpage>147</fpage>
<lpage>154</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11403904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Heine1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heine</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwamoto</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubahn</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Increased adipose tissue in male and female estrogen receptor-alpha knockout mice.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>97</volume>
<fpage>12729</fpage>
<lpage>12734</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11070086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Naaz1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naaz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zakroczymski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heine</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Effect of ovariectomy on adipose tissue of mice in the absence of estrogen receptor alpha (ERalpha): a potential role for estrogen receptor beta (ERbeta).</article-title>
<source>Horm Metab Res</source>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>758</fpage>
<lpage>763</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12660895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Bryzgalova1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bryzgalova</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zierath</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Galuska</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Evidence that oestrogen receptor-alpha plays an important role in the regulation of glucose homeostasis in mice: insulin sensitivity in the liver.</article-title>
<source>Diabetologia</source>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>588</fpage>
<lpage>597</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16463047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Ohlsson1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohlsson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellberg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Parini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohlooly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Obesity and disturbed lipoprotein profile in estrogen receptor-alpha-deficient male mice.</article-title>
<source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<volume>278</volume>
<fpage>640</fpage>
<lpage>645</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11095962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Semple1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Semple</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Rahilly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>PPAR gamma and human metabolic disease.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Invest</source>
<volume>116</volume>
<fpage>581</fpage>
<lpage>589</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16511590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Kliewer1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kliewer</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Forman</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Borgmeyer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Differential expression and activation of a family of murine peroxisome proliferator-activated receptors.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>91</volume>
<fpage>7355</fpage>
<lpage>7359</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8041794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Picard1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Picard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Auwerx</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>PPAR(gamma) and glucose homeostasis.</article-title>
<source>Annu Rev Nutr</source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>167</fpage>
<lpage>197</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12055342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-YkiJarvinen1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yki-Jarvinen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Thiazolidinediones.</article-title>
<source>N Engl J Med</source>
<volume>351</volume>
<fpage>1106</fpage>
<lpage>1118</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15356308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Matsuzawa1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuzawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>The metabolic syndrome and adipocytokines.</article-title>
<source>FEBS Lett</source>
<volume>580</volume>
<fpage>2917</fpage>
<lpage>2921</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16674947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Okamoto1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kihara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Funahashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuzawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Libby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Adiponectin: a key adipocytokine in metabolic syndrome.</article-title>
<source>Clin Sci (Lond)</source>
<volume>110</volume>
<fpage>267</fpage>
<lpage>278</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16464169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Kadowaki1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kadowaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamauchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Adiponectin and adiponectin receptors.</article-title>
<source>Endocr Rev</source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>439</fpage>
<lpage>451</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15897298</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Guan1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishizuka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chui</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehrke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Corepressors selectively control the transcriptional activity of PPARgamma in adipocytes.</article-title>
<source>Genes Dev</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>453</fpage>
<lpage>461</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15681609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Glass1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Going nuclear in metabolic and cardiovascular disease.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Invest</source>
<volume>116</volume>
<fpage>556</fpage>
<lpage>560</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16511587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Gronemeyer1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gronemeyer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Laudet</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Principles for modulation of the nuclear receptor superfamily.</article-title>
<source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>950</fpage>
<lpage>964</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15520817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Schupp1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schupp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Clemenz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gineste</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Witt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Janke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Molecular characterization of new selective peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma modulators with angiotensin receptor blocking activity.</article-title>
<source>Diabetes</source>
<volume>54</volume>
<fpage>3442</fpage>
<lpage>3452</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16306360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Tontonoz1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tontonoz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiegelman</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Stimulation of adipogenesis in fibroblasts by PPAR gamma 2, a lipid-activated transcription factor.</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>79</volume>
<fpage>1147</fpage>
<lpage>1156</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8001151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Maxwell1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nobbs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Diet-induced thermogenesis in cafeteria-fed rats: a myth?</article-title>
<source>Am J Physiol</source>
<volume>253</volume>
<fpage>E264</fpage>
<lpage>270</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3115113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Frias1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frias</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruszynska</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Olefsky</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Metabolic effects of troglitazone therapy in type 2 diabetic, obese, and lean normal subjects.</article-title>
<source>Diabetes Care</source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>64</fpage>
<lpage>69</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10857970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Staels1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staels</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fruchart</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Therapeutic roles of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor agonists.</article-title>
<source>Diabetes</source>
<volume>54</volume>
<fpage>2460</fpage>
<lpage>2470</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16046315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Zhang1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez-Ono</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Siri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Conlon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Aberrant hepatic expression of PPARgamma2 stimulates hepatic lipogenesis in a mouse model of obesity, insulin resistance, dyslipidemia, and hepatic steatosis.</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>281</volume>
<fpage>37603</fpage>
<lpage>37615</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16971390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Lopez1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinsako</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Titration by estrogen receptor activation function-2 of targets that are downstream from coactivators.</article-title>
<source>Mol Endocrinol</source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>897</fpage>
<lpage>909</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10379889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Keller1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Givel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Perroud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahli</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Signaling cross-talk between peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor/retinoid X receptor and estrogen receptor through estrogen response elements.</article-title>
<source>Mol Endocrinol</source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>794</fpage>
<lpage>804</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7476963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Wang1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilgore</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Signal cross-talk between estrogen receptor alpha and beta and the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma1 in MDA-MB-231 and MCF-7 breast cancer cells.</article-title>
<source>Mol Cell Endocrinol</source>
<volume>194</volume>
<fpage>123</fpage>
<lpage>133</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Tontonoz2"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tontonoz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Budavari</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiegelman</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>mPPAR gamma 2: tissue-specific regulator of an adipocyte enhancer.</article-title>
<source>Genes Dev</source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>1224</fpage>
<lpage>1234</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7926726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Metzger1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Metzger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bornert</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Characterization of the amino-terminal transcriptional activation function of the human estrogen receptor in animal and yeast cells.</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>270</volume>
<fpage>9535</fpage>
<lpage>9542</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7721882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Tremblay1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Labrie</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Giguere</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Ligand-independent recruitment of SRC-1 to estrogen receptor beta through phosphorylation of activation function AF-1.</article-title>
<source>Mol Cell</source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>513</fpage>
<lpage>519</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10230404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Barros2"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>UF</given-names></name><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Muscle GLUT4 regulation by estrogen receptors ERbeta and ERalpha.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>103</volume>
<fpage>1605</fpage>
<lpage>1608</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16423895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-He1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Barak</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hevener</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Adipose-specific peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma knockout causes insulin resistance in fat and liver but not in muscle.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>100</volume>
<fpage>15712</fpage>
<lpage>15717. Epub 12003 Dec 15715</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14660788</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Koutnikova1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koutnikova</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cock</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Houten</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Champy</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Compensation by the muscle limits the metabolic consequences of lipodystrophy in PPAR gamma hypomorphic mice.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>100</volume>
<fpage>14457</fpage>
<lpage>14462. Epub 12003 Nov 14455</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14603033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Zhang2"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Selective disruption of PPARgamma 2 impairs the development of adipose tissue and insulin sensitivity.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>101</volume>
<fpage>10703</fpage>
<lpage>10708. Epub 12004 Jul 10712</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15249658</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Sell1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sell</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Samson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Castriota</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lalonde</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma agonism increases the capacity for sympathetically mediated thermogenesis in lean and ob/ob mice.</article-title>
<source>Endocrinology</source>
<volume>145</volume>
<fpage>3925</fpage>
<lpage>3934</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15131020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Picard2"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Picard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gehin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Annicotte</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Champy</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>SRC-1 and TIF2 control energy balance between white and brown adipose tissues.</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>111</volume>
<fpage>931</fpage>
<lpage>941</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12507421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Follettie1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Follettie</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Keith</surname><given-names>JC</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chelsky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Organ messenger ribonucleic acid and plasma proteome changes in the adjuvant-induced arthritis model: responses to disease induction and therapy with the estrogen receptor-beta selective agonist ERB-041.</article-title>
<source>Endocrinology</source>
<volume>147</volume>
<fpage>714</fpage>
<lpage>723</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16269464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Komm1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Komm</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kharode</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bodine</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Bazedoxifene acetate: a selective estrogen receptor modulator with improved selectivity.</article-title>
<source>Endocrinology</source>
<volume>146</volume>
<fpage>3999</fpage>
<lpage>4008</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15961563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Krege1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krege</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Couse</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Enmark</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Generation and reproductive phenotypes of mice lacking estrogen receptor beta.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>95</volume>
<fpage>15677</fpage>
<lpage>15682</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9861029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-ForystLudwig1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foryst-Ludwig</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Naumann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>p21-activated kinase 1 activates the nuclear factor kappa B (NF-kappa B)-inducing kinase-Ikappa B kinases NF-kappa B pathway and proinflammatory cytokines in Helicobacter pylori infection.</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>275</volume>
<fpage>39779</fpage>
<lpage>39785</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11016939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000108-Cheng1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Cardiomyocyte-restricted peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-delta deletion perturbs myocardial fatty acid oxidation and leads to cardiomyopathy.</article-title>
<source>Nat Med</source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>1245</fpage>
<lpage>1250</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15475963</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>