<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName archivearticle.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Minim Invasive Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Minim Invasive Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MIS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Minimally Invasive Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2090-1445</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2090-1453</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3364001</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22685646</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2012/287613</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="9352" pm="."><plain>Update on Transanal NOTES for Rectal Cancer: Transitioning to Human Trials </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Telem</surname><given-names>Dana A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>David L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bordeianou</surname><given-names>Liliana G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rattner</surname><given-names>David W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sylla</surname><given-names>Patricia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1">Division of Gastrointestinal Surgery, Massachusetts General Hospital, 15 Parkman Street, Wang 460, Boston, MA 02114, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Patricia Sylla: <email>psylla@partners.org</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="9353" pm="."><plain>Academic Editor: Silvana Perretta </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>2012</volume><elocation-id>287613</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 Dana A. Telem et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9354" pm="."><plain>The feasibility of natural orifice translumenal endoscopic surgery (NOTES) resection for rectal cancer has been demonstrated in both survival swine and fresh human cadaveric models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9355" pm="."><plain>In preparation for transitioning to human application, our group has performed transanal NOTES rectal resection in a large series of human cadavers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9356" pm="."><plain>This experience both solidified the feasibility of resection and allowed optimization of technique prior to clinical application. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9357" pm="."><plain>Improvement in specimen length and operative time was demonstrated with increased experience and newer platforms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9358" pm="."><plain>This extensive laboratory experience has paved the way for successful clinical translation resulting in an ongoing clinical trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9359" pm="."><plain>To date, based on published reports, 4 human subjects have undergone successful hybrid transanal NOTES resection of rectal cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9360" pm="."><plain>While promising, instrument limitations continue to hinder a pure transanal approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9361" pm="."><plain>Careful patient selection and continued development of new endoscopic and flexible-tip instruments are imperative prior to pure NOTES clinical application. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="9362" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9363" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9364" pm="."><plain>Just as laparoscopy resulted in a major paradigm shift in the field of gastrointestinal surgery, NOTES has the potential to be equally as ground breaking and likely represents the next step in the evolution of minimally invasive surgery [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9365" pm="."><plain>Proposed advantages of NOTES include faster recovery time, shorter hospital stays, improved pain control, and avoidance of potential abdominal wall complications including wound infection and hernia [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9366" pm="."><plain>The range of operations under investigation is rapidly increasing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9367" pm="."><plain>Currently, transvaginal, transgastric, transesophageal, and transanal approaches have been described. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9368" pm="."><plain>The international and national experience now counts several thousand cases of successfully performed hybrid transvaginal NOTES procedures including but not limited to cholecystectomy, nephrectomy, and vertical sleeve gastrectomy [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9369" pm="."><plain>Progress however, continues to be hampered by instrument limitations as well as safety concerns regarding NOTES translumenal access, particularly regarding access closure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9370" pm="."><plain>Transanal access for colon resection has been proven safe and feasible in both swine and fresh human cadaveric models [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9371" pm="."><plain>The advantages of transanal access for colorectal resection are multiple. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9372" pm="."><plain>First, the availability of well-established platforms such as transanal endoscopic microsurgery (TEM) to gain access to the peritoneal cavity facilitates performance of endorectal and transrectal procedures [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9373" pm="."><plain>Second, creation of the enterotomy though the organ to be resected rather than an otherwise healthy organ obviates concerns regarding safe, reproducible closure associated with other NOTES access points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9374" pm="."><plain>In 2007, Whiteford et al. described the first transanal NOTES radical sigmoidectomy in human cadavers [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9375" pm="."><plain>Although colon and mesenteric dissection could be technically achieved with use of the TEM platform, difficulties were encountered with mobilization of adequate specimen length secondary to instrument inability to overcome anatomic constraints. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9376" pm="."><plain>While instrument limitations continue to be a barrier to pure application of transanal NOTES resection, this approach has since been optimized in both a swine and fresh human cadaveric model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9377" pm="."><plain>Based on this work, human clinical trials are currently underway worldwide [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9378" pm="."><plain>The aim of this paper is to provide a review of our experience with transanal NOTES colorectal resection as well as an update on the current status of human clinical trials worldwide. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="9379" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9380" pm="."><plain>Technique Development </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9381" pm="."><plain>To determine the feasibility of transanal NOTES rectosigmoid resection, a pilot study using a nonsurvival porcine model was performed [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9382" pm="."><plain>Rectosigmoid resection using the TEM platform was replicated in this model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9383" pm="."><plain>A purse-string suture was placed in the distal rectum to prevent fecal outflow and contamination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9384" pm="."><plain>Following this, full-thickness incision of the rectal wall was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9385" pm="."><plain>Upon entry into the presacral space, en-bloc resection of the rectosigmoid colon and its mesentery could be performed endoscopically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9386" pm="."><plain>Once the peritoneal reflection was reached, the peritoneal cavity was entered and dissection of the sigmoid colon continued proximally until anatomic and instrument limitations were encountered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9387" pm="."><plain>The colon was then pulled out through the anus, transected and a stapled colorectal anastomosis performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9388" pm="."><plain>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">1(a)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">1(b)</xref>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9389" pm="."><plain>From this nonsurvival model, several key limitations were identified and addressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9390" pm="."><plain>First, the sharp angle of the sacral promontory and narrow swine pelvis hindered proximal dissection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9391" pm="."><plain>In an attempt to overcome these anatomic limitations, a combined transgastric and transanal approach was attempted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9392" pm="."><plain>While prolonging operative time, dual transanal and transgastric approach improved visualization, retraction, and ultimately mobilization of the proximal colon yielding additional specimen length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9393" pm="."><plain>The addition of transgastric endoscopic access resulted in an average gain of 5.8 cm in colon length [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9394" pm="."><plain>Other anatomic constraints included the flaccid swine bladder which obscures the rectosigmoid, spiral colon configuration, and lack of a true splenic flexure making proximal colonic mobilization more challenging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9395" pm="."><plain>To overcome these anatomic challenges, exposure was improved by positioning animals in the Trendelenburg and right lateral decubitus position. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9396" pm="."><plain>A second impediment centered on technical optimization of the colorectal anastomosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9397" pm="."><plain>A stapled colorectal anastomosis was performed in all animals in this series. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9398" pm="."><plain>Following anastomotic inspection the staple line was noted to be incomplete in 2 out of 9 (22%) animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9399" pm="."><plain>A small posterior anastomotic defect was identified in each case and believed to be secondary to an incomplete purse-string suture on the open distal rectum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9400" pm="."><plain>This discovery led to technique modification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9401" pm="."><plain>A transanal purse string was placed under direct vision using anal retractors, rather than through the proctoscope, with improved results [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9402" pm="."><plain>Despite technical and anatomic limitations, all resected specimens were intact with respect to colon wall and attached mesentery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9403" pm="."><plain>Given the promising results regarding the feasibility of this approach, the next step involved determining safety of application. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9404" pm="."><plain>A two-week survival study using 20 swines was initiated [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9405" pm="."><plain>This study compared outcomes of pure transanal endoscopic resection versus combined transanal and transgastric rectosigmoid resection as described in the pilot study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9406" pm="."><plain>All procedures were performed successfully without transabdominal assistance and all specimens were grossly intact with respect to integrity of colonic wall and attached mesentery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9407" pm="."><plain>The use of transgastric assistance again demonstrated a significant increase in the length of specimen able to be mobilized and resected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9408" pm="."><plain>No mortalities occurred in either group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9409" pm="."><plain>Two morbidities, one intraabdominal abscess and one abdominal wall hematoma, occurred in the dual transgastric and transanal group identified at necropsy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9410" pm="."><plain>Experimental evidence from both the nonsurvival and survival swine studies demonstrated both the feasibility and safety of transanal NOTES rectosigmoid resection using TEM with or without transgastric endoscopic assistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9411" pm="."><plain>This work served as the foundation for transitioning to human application. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="9412" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9413" pm="."><plain>Technique Optimization and Transitioning to Clinical Application </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9414" pm="."><plain>In preparation for human application, fresh human cadaveric models were utilized to optimize this technique. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9415" pm="."><plain>The purpose of this model was to both determine the technical and oncologic feasibility of this technique and eventually optimize this procedure for human clinical trials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9416" pm="."><plain>Since initiation of this protocol, transanal NOTES rectosigmoid resection has been successfully performed in 32 fresh human cadavers [<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9417" pm="."><plain>NOTES transanal endoscopic rectosigmoid resection was performed using transanal dissection alone (<italic>n</italic> = 19), with transgastric endoscopic assistance (<italic>n</italic> = 5) or with laparoscopic assistance (<italic>n</italic> = 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9418" pm="."><plain>Of the 19 cadaveric operations performed via a pure transanal approach, 2 were performed using laparoscopic and TEO instruments through the TEO platform, 8 using endoscopic assistance with a gastroscope (Pentax) inserted through the TEO platform, and 9 utilized endoscopic assistance through a novel rigid endoscopic platform inserted through the TEO platform (ISSA, Storz). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9419" pm="."><plain>The purpose of this novel platform was to provide additional rigidity to the gastroscope. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="9420" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9421" pm="."><plain>Technique </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9422" pm="."><plain>As in swine, the rectum was occluded transanally with a 2-0 vicryl purse-string suture approximately 3-4 cm from the anal verge, above the sphincter complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9423" pm="."><plain>The 7.5 cm TEO proctoscope (Storz, Tuttlingen, Germany) was then inserted transanally and sealed with a faceplate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9424" pm="."><plain>CO<sub>2</sub> was then insufflated (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2(a)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2(b)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9425" pm="."><plain>Circumferential dissection of the rectum was initiated above the anal sphincter complex using electrocautery and TEO dissecting instruments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2(c)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9426" pm="."><plain>Low pressure CO<sub>2</sub> insufflation (9 mm Hg) was used to facilitate dissection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9427" pm="."><plain>Posterior entry into the presacral space was facilitated by CO<sub>2</sub> insufflation and flexible-tip instruments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9428" pm="."><plain>The mesorectum was mobilized sharply, with or without electrocautery or a bipolar device (Autosonix ultrashears, Covidien, Norwalk, CT), and mesorectal dissection proceeded cephalad along the avascular presacral plane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2(d)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9429" pm="."><plain>This plane of dissection was extended medially, laterally, and anteriorly to achieve circumferential rectal mobilization and TME. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9430" pm="."><plain>The shorter proctoscope was replaced with the 15 cm proctoscope to improve exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9431" pm="."><plain>The peritoneal reflection was visualized and divided anteriorly after carefully mobilizing the vagina or prostate from the anterior rectal wall, and the peritoneal cavity was entered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2(e)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9432" pm="."><plain>The peritoneal attachments of the rectosigmoid were divided using electrocautery and a bipolar device (Autosonix). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9433" pm="."><plain>Proximal dissection was continued either via transanal endoscopic dissection alone or with transgastric endoscopic or laparoscopic assistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9434" pm="."><plain>The inferior mesenteric pedicle was taken in all cadavers using a bipolar device or a linear endoscopic stapler (EndoGIA, Covidien) inserted transanally through the TEO platform. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9435" pm="."><plain>In cadavers undergoing sole transanal rectosigmoid resection, dissection into the peritoneal cavity was extended as cephalad as possible using TEO and laparoscopic instruments, with or without transanal endoscopic assistance using a gastroscope (Pentax Medocal Incl, Montvale, NJ, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9436" pm="."><plain>When dissection could not be extended any further, the proctoscope was removed, and the specimen was exteriorized in preparation for specimen extraction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9437" pm="."><plain>Transgastric assistance, when utilized, was performed as previously described [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9438" pm="."><plain>In brief, following maximal transanal rectosigmoid mobilization, peroral transgastric peritoneal access was obtained using a 12.8 mm colonoscope (Pentax). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9439" pm="."><plain>A 4 mm gastrostomy was then made using a needle knife (Cook Medical Inc., Winsont-Salem, NC, USA) and dilated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9440" pm="."><plain>Once access was established, the colonoscope was advanced into the peritoneal cavity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9441" pm="."><plain>In 2 cases, transgastric access and dissection were performed using a novel endoscopic platform (Anubiscope, Storz). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9442" pm="."><plain>The lateral peritoneal attachments of the rectosigmoid, sigmoid, and descending colon was then divided using the needle knife. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9443" pm="."><plain>Transanal and transgastric mobilization were combined until no further mobilization could be safely achieved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9444" pm="."><plain>For operations performed with laparoscopic assistance, 1–3 abdominal trocars were inserted to improve visualization and/or facilitate colon retraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9445" pm="."><plain>This permitted more proximal dissection of the rectosigmoid junction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9446" pm="."><plain>Regardless of operative approach, once the rectosigmoid specimen had been fully mobilized, it was exteriorized transanally, measured and subsequently transected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2(f)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9447" pm="."><plain>A Lone Star retractor (Cooper Surgical, Trumbull, CT, USA) was then positioned and a handsewn coloanal anastomosis performed between the proximal sigmoid colon and distal anorectal cuff as previously described. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.3"><title><text><SENT sid="9448" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9449" pm="."><plain>Technical Feasibility and Optimization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9450" pm="."><plain>In this series of 32 fresh human cadavers, 21 were male and 11 female with mean BMI of 24 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9451" pm="."><plain>Mean operative time was 5.1 hours and mean specimen length 53 cm (range 15 to 91.5 cm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9452" pm="."><plain>A significant improvement in both specimen length and operative time was demonstrated with increased experience [<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9453" pm="."><plain>In addition, comparison by operative approach demonstrated significantly improved specimen length with addition of laparoscopic assistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9454" pm="."><plain>Cases that employed a hybrid transgastric and transanal approach initially resulted in increased specimen length; however, this became less pronounced with increasing experience in transanal dissection alone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9455" pm="."><plain>In 8 (25%) cadavers, an enteric perforation was identified in the sigmoid (<italic>n</italic> = 2), rectum (<italic>n</italic> = 3), or proximal colon (<italic>n</italic> = 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9456" pm="."><plain>Factors associated with complication included obesity, poor cadaver quality, pelvic adhesions, and a redundant sigmoid colon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9457" pm="."><plain>In addition, all enteric perforations occurred in cadavers undergoing pure NOTES rectosigmoid resection during attempted mobilization of the proximal descending colon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9458" pm="."><plain>Limitations in dissecting instruments, current platforms, and proximal visualization are likely responsible for the rate of enteric perforation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9459" pm="."><plain>While the feasibility of pure NOTES colorectal resection could be replicated in fresh human male and female cadavers, the complication rate highlights that clinical application is not yet possible and a hybrid laparoscopic approach is essential. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9460" pm="."><plain>In addition to serving as an experimental platform, this model also enabled standardization of a hybrid laparoscopic procedure prior to clinical trials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9461" pm="."><plain>It allowed for the capability of trouble shooting and overcoming the procedural learning curve prior to human application. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.4"><title><text><SENT sid="9462" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9463" pm="."><plain>Oncologic Feasibility </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9464" pm="."><plain>Another question that needed to be addressed prior to transitioning to human trials pertained to the adequacy of oncologic resection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9465" pm="."><plain>Both cadaveric work done by our group as well as the one by Whiteford et al. [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] illustrate that this operation is oncologically appropriate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9466" pm="."><plain>As total mesorectal excision (TME) remains the gold standard in the treatment of rectal cancer, we evaluated oncologic adequacy in our cadaveric model by specimen assessment following procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9467" pm="."><plain>In our series of 32 cadavers, the mesorectum was intact in 100% of specimens following TME. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9468" pm="."><plain>The capability of performing an adequate oncologic operation was corroborated in 2011 by Rieder et al. [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9469" pm="."><plain>This paper randomized male cadavers to either laparoscopic or transanal sigmoid resection for a lesion simulated at 25 cm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9470" pm="."><plain>Lymph node yield as well as adequate resection margins were evaluated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9471" pm="."><plain>This study demonstrated similar lymph node yield following transanal rectosigmoidectomy when compared to the laparoscopic approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9472" pm="."><plain>Given the distance of the simulated lesion however, laparoscopic assistance was necessary in the transanal group to achieve adequate proximal resection margin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9473" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, results from this study support the feasibility of this technique as an adequate oncologic procedure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="9474" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9475" pm="."><plain>Clinical Trials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9476" pm="."><plain>Success in animal and cadaveric models has led to worldwide human clinical trials [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9477" pm="."><plain>In 2010, our group reported the first hybrid NOTES transanal total mesorectal excision (TME) in a 76-year-old female with a T2N1 rectal cancer treated preoperatively with neoadjuvant therapy [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9478" pm="."><plain>Visualization and assistance during the procedure were aided with a transabdominal 5 mm port that later became the stoma site and 2 mm needle ports of which one was used as a drain site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9479" pm="."><plain>The TME was performed entirely transanally through the TEO platform (Storz, Tuttlingen, Germany) with mobilization of the splenic flexure and proximal intra-abdominal colon performed laparoscopically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9480" pm="."><plain>The specimen was then transected transanally and a handsewn coloanal anastomosis with diverting loop ileostomy was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9481" pm="."><plain>The operative time was 4 hours and 30 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9482" pm="."><plain>The patient did well postoperatively and was discharged home on postoperative day four. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9483" pm="."><plain>The final pathology demonstrated a ypT1N0 tumor with intact mesorectum that included 23 negative lymph nodes and negative proximal, distal and radial margins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9484" pm="."><plain>The patient later underwent ileostomy reversal with good function and has remained free of disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9485" pm="."><plain>Since this report, 3 additional cases have been reported in the literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9486" pm="."><plain>Zorron et al. published a series of 2 patients who underwent successful hybrid NOTES TME for rectal cancer [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9487" pm="."><plain>In this series, mesorectal dissection is described with both an endoscope and with a transrectal rigid single port device. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9488" pm="."><plain>The first case was that of a 54-year-old male who presented with an adenocarcinoma 8 cm from the rectal verge causing 90% stenosis of the lumen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9489" pm="."><plain>Secondary to the obstructing nature of his tumor, the patient did not undergo neoadjuvant therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9490" pm="."><plain>Hybrid transcolonic NOTES TME was performed using a colonoscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9491" pm="."><plain>Following identification of the anal verge, a 2.5 cm posterior incision was performed in the planned line of rectal resection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9492" pm="."><plain>The colonoscope was then inserted directly into the perirectal retroperitoneal space and dissection was performed by directing the endoscope via CO<sub>2</sub> insufflation through a working channel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9493" pm="."><plain>Once dissection reached the level of the peritoneal cavity, pneumoretroperitoneum was lost and dissection was then facilitated by laparoscopic assistance via 3 transabdominal trocars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9494" pm="."><plain>Once dissection was complete, the specimen was removed transanally and a stapled anastomosis and right transverse diverting colostomy were performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9495" pm="."><plain>Operative time was 350 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9496" pm="."><plain>Both the intra- and postoperative courses were uncomplicated and the patient was discharged home on postoperative day 6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9497" pm="."><plain>Pathology revealed an intact mesorectum with 3 out of 12 retrieved lymph nodes positive for tumor (pT3N1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9498" pm="."><plain>Margins were free of tumor. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9499" pm="."><plain>The second patient reported in this series was a 73-year-old female with a diagnosis of rectal adenocarcinoma 6 cm from the anal verge who underwent neoadjuvant therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9500" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the first patient, this patient underwent a hybrid NOTES TME using a transanally inserted rigid, single port device. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9501" pm="."><plain>The single port access device has 3 channels for instrumentation, with 2 additional channels for CO<sub>2</sub> insufflation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9502" pm="."><plain>Using a 10 mm 45-degree laparoscopic camera, in lieu of a flexible colonoscope, the TME dissection was then carried out transanally with laparoscopic assistance as previously described. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9503" pm="."><plain>Operative time was 360 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9504" pm="."><plain>This patient also recovered uneventfully and was discharged home on postoperative day 6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9505" pm="."><plain>Pathology revealed tumor-free margins and intact mesorectum with 2 of 11 lymph nodes positive for tumor (pT3N1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9506" pm="."><plain>The third case was reported by Tuech et al. in 2011 [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9507" pm="."><plain>This report describes a 45-year-old woman with a reported T1sm3 rectal adenocarcinoma 3 cm above the dentate line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9508" pm="."><plain>For this procedure a single port access device, endorec trocar (Aspide, France), was also used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9509" pm="."><plain>This trocar consists of a rigid port with 40 mm outer diameter, three 5 mm, and one 10 mm access channel and an air inlet tube through which CO<sub>2</sub> can be inflated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9510" pm="."><plain>The extraperitoneal rectum was completely mobilized using this device. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9511" pm="."><plain>Once the lateral rectal attachments were divided, the rectovaginal peritoneal reflection was identified and perforated to gain access to the abdominal cavity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9512" pm="."><plain>A second endorec trocar (Aspide, France) was then placed through the proposed ileostomy site and laparoscopic assistance with proximal colonic mobilization ensued. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9513" pm="."><plain>The procedure was performed successfully without complication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9514" pm="."><plain>Operative time was 5 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9515" pm="."><plain>The patient did well postoperatively without complication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9516" pm="."><plain>Pathology revealed a pT1sm3N0 tumor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9517" pm="."><plain>Fifteen lymph nodes were retrieved with the specimen. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9518" pm="."><plain>While the principles of NOTES transanal rectal cancer resection remain the same, the methodology, particularly with respect to transanal dissection, varies between clinical trials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9519" pm="."><plain>The consensus is that the majority of the rectal and mesorectal dissection can be achieved transanally while laparoscopic assistance is needed for proximal colon mobilization and tissue retraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9520" pm="."><plain>It is the preference of our group at this time to use the rigid TEO platform for transanal endoscopic rectal dissection rather than a flexible single port device. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9521" pm="."><plain>The TEO platform comes in 2 lengths, provides rigid stabilization for instrument manipulation, and is an established cost effective, reusable platform readily available at our institution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9522" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, the published reports thus far demonstrate that adequate hybrid NOTES TME can be achieved using flexible or rigid platforms and highlight the importance of continued work and development in this field. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9523" pm="."><plain>As part of our effort to further this work, we are currently enrolling patients into an ongoing United States based Institutional Review Board (IRB) approved prospective clinical trial [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9524" pm="."><plain>Patients selected for this approach include those with biopsy proven resectable adenocarcinoma of rectum located 4–12 cm from anal verge who are otherwise eligible to undergo standard open or laparoscopic low anterior resection with temporary diverting stoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9525" pm="."><plain>Tumors must be preoperatively staged as node negative, T1 (high risk features), T2 or T3 based on pelvic MRI with no evidence of metastasis on staging CT scans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9526" pm="."><plain>For preoperatively staged T3N0 tumors, patients must have completed full-course neoadjuvant treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9527" pm="."><plain>Procedures are performed following the same steps as described in cadavers, using an abdominal and perineal team working simultaneously. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9528" pm="."><plain>Transanal dissection is performed via the TEM platform with laparoscopic assistance through 1–4 abdominal trocars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9529" pm="."><plain>The right lower quadrant trocar is later used as the ileostomy site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9530" pm="."><plain>Following transanal specimen retrieval, a handsewn coloanal anastomosis with diverting ileostomy is performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9531" pm="."><plain>For this protocol, a diverting ileostomy is standard given performance of a low-lying anastomosis in patients who likely will require either neoadjuvant or adjuvant chemoradiation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="9532" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9533" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9534" pm="."><plain>Transanal NOTES rectosigmoid resection is feasible and safe as demonstrated in both a swine and fresh human cadaveric model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9535" pm="."><plain>Clinical application has been promising, with several hybrid laparoscopic and transanal procedures for rectal cancers published to date. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9536" pm="."><plain>While encouraging, instrument limitations continue to hinder a pure transanal approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9537" pm="."><plain>Continued development of new flexible endoscopic platforms and flexible-tip instruments are imperative prior to pure NOTES clinical application in humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9538" pm="."><plain>In addition, the success of clinical application will ultimately rely on careful patient selection and strict adherence to oncologic principles of resection with all planned procedures done in the setting of IRB-approved clinical trials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="9539" pm="."><plain><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sodergreen</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Athanasiou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Teare</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>GZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Darzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural orifice translumenal endoscopic surgery: critical appraisal of applications in clinical practice</article-title><source><italic>Surgical Endoscopy</italic></source><year>2009</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>680</fpage><lpage>687</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19118425</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="9540" pm="."><plain><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rattner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalloo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ASGE/SAGES working group on natural orifice translumenal endoscopic surgery</article-title><source><italic>Surgical Endoscopy and Other Interventional Techniques</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16402290</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="9541" pm="."><plain><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rattner</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwaitzberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kochman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanstrom</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The second SAGES/ASGE white paper on natural orifice transluminal endoscopic surgery: 5 years of progress</article-title><source><italic>Surgical Endoscopy</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>25</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2441</fpage><lpage>2448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21359881</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="9542" pm="."><plain><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NOTES: human experience</article-title><source><italic>Gastrointestinal Endoscopy Clinics of North America </italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18381176</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="9543" pm="."><plain><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zornig</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mofid</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Emmermann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Von Waldenfels</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Felixmüller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scarless cholecystectomy with combined transvaginal and transumbilical approach in a series of 20 patients</article-title><source><italic>Surgical Endoscopy and Other Interventional Techniques</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>22</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1427</fpage><lpage>1429</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18398645</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="9544" pm="."><plain><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gee</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Willingham</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauwers</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Brugge</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rattner</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural orifice transesophageal mediastinoscopy and thoracoscopy: a survival series in swine</article-title><source><italic>Surgical Endoscopy and Other Interventional Techniques</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>22</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2117</fpage><lpage>2122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18636291</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="9545" pm="."><plain><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gee</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Rattner</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transmediastinal Endoscopic Intervention</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Gastrointestinal Surgery</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>15</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1303</fpage><lpage>1305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21671114</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="9546" pm="."><plain><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bazzi</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Stroup</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transrectal hybrid natural orifice transluminal endoscopic surgery (NOTES) nephrectomy in a porcine model</article-title><source><italic>Urology</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>77</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>518</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21376997</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="9547" pm="."><plain><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>NOTES laparoscopic-assisted transvaginal sleeve gastrectomy in humans-description of preliminary experience in the United States</article-title><source><italic>Surgery for Obesity and Related Diseases</italic></source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19656739</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="9548" pm="."><plain><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sylla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cizginer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Survival study of natural orifice translumenal endoscopic surgery for rectosigmoid resection using transanal endoscopic microsurgery with or without transgastric endoscopic assistance in a swine model</article-title><source><italic>Surgical Endoscopy and Other Interventional Techniques</italic></source><year>2010</year><volume>24</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2022</fpage><lpage>2030</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20174948</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="9549" pm="."><plain><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sylla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Willingham</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brugge</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rattner</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NOTES rectosigmoid resection using transanal endoscopic microsurgery (TEM) with transgastric endoscopic assistance: a pilot study in swine</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Gastrointestinal Surgery</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>12</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1717</fpage><lpage>1723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18704596</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="9550" pm="."><plain><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denk</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanström</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiteford</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transanal endoscopic microsurgical platform for natural orifice surgery</article-title><source><italic>Gastrointestinal Endoscopy</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>68</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>954</fpage><lpage>959</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18984102</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="9551" pm="."><plain><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whiteford</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Denk</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanström</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Feasibility of radical sigmoid colectomy performed as natural orifice translumenal endoscopic surgery (NOTES) using transanal endoscopic microsurgery</article-title><source><italic>Surgical Endoscopy and Other Interventional Techniques</italic></source><year>2007</year><volume>21</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1870</fpage><lpage>1874</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17705068</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="9552" pm="."><plain><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zorron</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Flach</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemos</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vassallo</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perirectal NOTES access: “down-to-up” total mesorectal excision for rectal cancer</article-title><comment><italic>Surgical Innovation</italic>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9553" pm="."><plain>In press</comment></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="9554" pm="."><plain><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuech</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bridoux</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kianifard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Natural orifice total mesorectal excision using transanal port and laparoscopic assistance</article-title><source><italic>European Journal of Surgical Oncology</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>37</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>334</fpage><lpage>335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21266304</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="9555" pm="."><plain><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sylla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rattner</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacy</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NOTES transanal rectal cancer resection using transanal endoscopic microsurgery and laparoscopic assistance</article-title><source><italic>Surgical Endoscopy and Other Interventional Techniques</italic></source><year>2010</year><volume>24</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1205</fpage><lpage>1210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20186432</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="9556" pm="."><plain><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Telem</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rattner</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sylla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NOTES transanal rectosigmoid resection with total mesorectal excision in a large human cadaver series</article-title><conf-name>In: Proceedings of the Scientific Session of the 15th World Congress of Endoscopic Surgery</conf-name><conf-date>March 2012</conf-date><conf-loc>Diego, Calif, USA</conf-loc></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="9557" pm="."><plain><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rieder</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Spaun</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name><name><surname>Khajanchee</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A natural orifice transrectal approach for oncologic resection of the rectosigmoid: an experimental study and comparison with conventional laparoscopy</article-title><source><italic>Surgical Endoscopy</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>25</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3357</fpage><lpage>3363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21556994</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="9558" pm="."><plain><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><comment>2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrial.gov/ct2/show/NCT01340755?term=sylla&amp;rank=1">http://clinicaltrial.gov/ct2/show/NCT01340755?term=sylla&amp;rank=1</ext-link></comment></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="9559" pm="."><plain>(a) Tranasanal extraction of specimen following completely NOTES in a swine survival model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9560" pm="."><plain>(b) Intact stapled coloanal anastomosis following specimen transection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="MIS2012-287613.001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="9561" pm="."><plain>(a) Set up for pure NOTES transanal rectosigmoid resection via TEM using standard instruments and endoscopic tools in cadavers using a colonoscope for visualization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9562" pm="."><plain>(b) Set up for transanal NOTES rectosigmoid resection with laparoscopic assistance in cadavers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9563" pm="."><plain>(c) Transanal circumferential and full-thickness rectal dissection through the TEM platform, starting just below the purse-string suture, in a female patient with an upper rectal cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9564" pm="."><plain>(d) Transanal posterior mesorectal dissection using laparoscopic instruments through the TEM platform in a female patient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9565" pm="."><plain>(e) Transanal mobilization of the anterior rectal wall and peritoneal entry through the TEM platform in a female patient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9566" pm="."><plain>(f) Intact rectosigmoid specimen and mesorectum following transanal NOTES procedures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="MIS2012-287613.002"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
