<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" open-status="O" article-type="protocol"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bmjopen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMJ Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2044-6055</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name><publisher-loc>BMA House, Tavistock Square, London, WC1H 9JR</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5961615</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen-2017-017819</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2017-017819</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Rehabilitation Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Protocol</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1506</subject><subject>1727</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="74609" pm="."><plain>Tele-UPCAT: study protocol of a randomised controlled trial of a home-based Tele-monitored UPper limb Children Action observation Training for participants with unilateral cerebral palsy </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-55428162" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sgandurra</surname><given-names>Giuseppina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-55553476" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cecchi</surname><given-names>Francesca</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-55553488" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Beani</surname><given-names>Elena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-55553510" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mannari</surname><given-names>Irene</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-55553520" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maselli</surname><given-names>Martina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-55553527" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Falotico</surname><given-names>Francesco Paolo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-55553536" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Inguaggiato</surname><given-names>Emanuela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-55553541" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Perazza</surname><given-names>Silvia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-55553548" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sicola</surname><given-names>Elisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-55553568" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Feys</surname><given-names>Hilde</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-55553587" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Klingels</surname><given-names>Katrijn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-55553593" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>Adriano</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-55553600" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dario</surname><given-names>Paolo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-27589202" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>Roslyn N</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-45791194" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cioni</surname><given-names>Giovanni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<institution content-type="department">Department of Developmental Neuroscience</institution>, <institution>IRCCS Fondazione Stella Maris</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Pisa</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<institution content-type="department">Department of Clinical and Experimental Medicine</institution>, <institution>University of Pisa</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Pisa</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<institution>The BioRobotics Institute, Polo Sant’Anna Valdera</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Pisa</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<institution content-type="department">Department of Rehabilitation Sciences</institution>, <institution>KU Leuven – University of Leuven</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Leuven</addr-line>, <country>Belgium</country>
</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>
<institution content-type="department">REVAL Rehabilitation Research Center, Biomedical Research Institute</institution>, <institution>Hasselt University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Diepenbeek</addr-line>, <country>Belgium</country>
</aff><aff id="aff6">
<label>6</label>
<institution content-type="department">Children Rehabilitation Unit</institution>, <institution>IRCCS S. Maria Nuova Hospital</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Reggio Emilia</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country>
</aff><aff id="aff7">
<label>7</label>
<institution content-type="department">Department of Neuroscience</institution>, <institution>University of Modena and Reggio Emilia</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Modena</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country>
</aff><aff id="aff8">
<label>8</label>
<institution content-type="department">Queensland Cerebral Palsy and Rehabilitation Research Centre, Centre for Children’s Health Research, Faculty of Medicine</institution>, <institution>The University of Queensland</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Brisbane</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Queensland</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp><label>Correspondence to</label> Professor Giovanni Cioni; <email>gcioni@fsm.unipi.it</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e017819</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>04</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Article author(s) (or their employer(s) unless otherwise stated in the text of the article) 2018. All rights reserved. No commercial use is permitted unless otherwise expressly granted.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2017-017819.pdf"/><self-uri content-type="reviewers-comments-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2017-017819.reviewer_comments.pdf"/><self-uri content-type="draft-revisions-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2017-017819.draft_revisions.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="74610" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="74611" pm="."><plain>A new rehabilitative approach, called UPper Limb Children Action Observation Training (UPCAT), based on the principles of action observation training (AOT), has provided promising results for upper limb rehabilitation in children with unilateral cerebral palsy (UCP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74612" pm="."><plain>This study will investigate if a new information and communication technology platform, named Tele-UPCAT, is able to deliver AOT in a home setting and will test its efficacy on children and young people with UCP. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="74613" pm="."><plain>Methods and analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="74614" pm="."><plain>A randomised, allocation concealed (waitlist control) and evaluator-blinded clinical trial with two investigative arms will be carried out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74615" pm="."><plain>The experimental group will perform AOT at home for 3 weeks using a customised Tele-UPCAT system where they will watch video sequences of goal-directed actions and then complete the motor training of the same actions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74616" pm="."><plain>The control group will receive usual care for 3 weeks, which may include upper limb training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74617" pm="."><plain>They will be offered AOT at home after 3 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74618" pm="."><plain>Twenty-four children with UCP will be recruited for 12 participants per group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74619" pm="."><plain>The primary outcome will be measured using Assisting Hand Assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74620" pm="."><plain>The Melbourne Assessment 2, ABILHAND, Participation and Environment Measure-Children and Youth and Cerebral Palsy Quality of Life Questionnaire will be included as secondary measures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74621" pm="."><plain>Quantitative measures from sensorised objects and participants worn Actigraphs GXT3+ will be analysed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74622" pm="."><plain>The assessment points will be the week before (T0) and after (T1) the period of AOT/standard care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74623" pm="."><plain>Further assessments will be at T1 plus, the week after the AOT period for the waitlist group and at 8 weeks (T2) and 24 weeks (T3) after AOT training. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="74624" pm="."><plain>Ethics and dissemination </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="74625" pm="."><plain>The trial has been approved by the Tuscany Paediatric Ethics Committee (169/2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74626" pm="."><plain>Publication of all outcomes will be in peer-reviewed journals and conference presentations. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="74627" pm="."><plain>Trial registration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="74628" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="NCT03094455" specific-use="clinicaltrial">NCT03094455</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>action observation training</kwd><kwd>unilateral cerebral palsy</kwd><kwd>tele-rehabilitation</kwd><kwd>upper limb</kwd><kwd>randomized controlled trial</kwd><kwd>information and communication technologies</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group id="funding-1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100003196</institution-id><institution>Ministero della Salute</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>special-feature</meta-name><meta-value>unlocked</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="74629" pm="."><plain>Strengths and limitations of this study </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="74630" pm="."><plain>This is the first protocol study where an information and communication technology platform is proposed, called Tele-UPCAT, to deliver the action observation training (AOT) at home. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="74631" pm="."><plain>The study is a well-designed randomised controlled trial aimed to investigate the UPper Limb Children Action Observation Training (UPCAT) approach at home and to measure its efficacy in children, adolescents and young adults with unilateral cerebral palsy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="74632" pm="."><plain>The Tele-UPCAT platform allows individualised customisation of the intervention according to the different levels of upper limb severity and the different ages of participants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="74633" pm="."><plain>The sample size, even if it will be calculated and powered on the previous clinical studies, is modest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="74634" pm="."><plain>The Tele-UPCAT platform does not obtain quantitative measurements of force and pressure hand measurements during AOT session. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list></boxed-text><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="74635" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74636" pm="."><plain>Cerebral palsy (CP) is the most common cause of childhood chronic physical disability in Europe and in other industrialised societies.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> The incident rate is between 2 and 3 per 1000 live births and increases to 40–100 per 1000 live births among very premature and very low birthweight babies, which represent the population with highest rate of neurodevelopmental disorders.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Unilateral cerebral palsy (UCP) (ie, a motor impairment impacting one side of the body more than the other side) constitutes the most frequent form of CP, about 30%–40% of all affected children.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Recent estimations of incidence and prevalence of CP have shown a significant increase in UCP in Europe over the last years.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4 5</xref> The upper limb (UL) of children with UCP is generally more involved than the lower limb, and the consequent disability affects their participation, quality of life, independence at home, school and community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74637" pm="."><plain>Despite this large impact, the current clinical practice for UCP mainly includes consultative intervention or time-limited therapy following pharmacological intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74638" pm="."><plain>In the last decades, targeted UL therapies such as constraint-induced movement therapy, hand–arm bimanual intensive training and combined approaches have emerged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74639" pm="."><plain>Reviews on these models have clearly shown that intensive models of therapy achieves modest to strong effects to improve UL function compared with standard care (SC) and that bimanual and unimanual training demonstrate similar gains in UL outcomes.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6–10</xref> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74640" pm="."><plain>In this field, one of the most recent models is the action observation training (AOT), based on the discovery of the Mirror Neuron System, whose core regions are the ventral premotor and inferior parietal cortex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74641" pm="."><plain>These areas are activated when individuals perform goal-directed motor acts (eg, grasping an object) as well as if they simply observe the performance of the same or a similar action and trigger recruitment of the same network as the actual physical action.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11 12</xref> AOT is mainly based on observation of meaningful actions, and their successive imitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74642" pm="."><plain>AOT has been used as new intervention model in many adult studies for neurological and non-neurological diseases (such as Parkinson’s disease, stroke and orthopaedic surgery), and there is growing evidence of its effectiveness.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13–18</xref> Recent studies carried out in children with CP indicate positive effects on UL function in younger population.<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19–21</xref> We have recently completed a clinical study called UPper Limb Children Action observation Training (UPCAT) with children with UCP based on 3 weeks of AOT, providing evidence of its efficacy in improving UL activity performance in daily activities.<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> To date, the UPCAT study has only been carried out in a clinical rehabilitation setting with children who were living near the two clinical centres and whose parents are willing to commit to a 3-week intensive therapy programme with consequently high costs for both health services and families. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74643" pm="."><plain>In addition, the parents, even if able to participate, found the need to attend every working day for 3 weeks too burdensome and suggested the delivery of the intervention at home. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74644" pm="."><plain>Biotechnologies, telerehabilitation and eHealth provide a promising approach to deliver telemonitored home programmes for a large number of participants at a relatively low cost. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74645" pm="."><plain>In this field, our group has recently experienced the design, the build and the clinical validation of new technological information and communication technologies (ICT) for providing in the first year of life telerehabilitation programmes at home for infants at risk for developing neurodevelopmental disorders<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22–25</xref> In this context, similar approaches could represent viable option in providing AOT programmes at home, in a user-friendly, playful and rehabilitative setting in children. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74646" pm="."><plain>The core of AOT relies on the content of actions to be observed and on the patients’ motivation in carefully observing to imitate and actively replicate them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74647" pm="."><plain>For these reasons, the AOT can be easily carried out at home. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74648" pm="."><plain>The present study protocol, designed as an exploratory randomised controlled trial (RCT), has the purpose to investigate the feasibility of a new ICT platform, named Tele-UPCAT, to provide the UPCAT approach at home. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74649" pm="."><plain>This RCT aims to measure its efficacy in a group of children, adolescents and young adults with UCP comparing the effects of Tele-UPCAT approach (experimental group) with the SC (control group). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74650" pm="."><plain>The primary aim will evaluate the immediate effects (T1, in the week after the end of the treatment) of this new approach (home AOT) on bimanual hand function (Assisting Hand Assessment (AHA)<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26–28</xref>) and assess whether these effects will be retained at a medium-term and long-term follow-up (ie, 8 weeks and 24 weeks after the end of treatment, T2 and T3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74651" pm="."><plain>In addition, the feasibility of the Tele-UPCAT system as a comfortable, reliable and customisable tool for delivering a home AOT to UCP participants and their families will be assessed using semistructured interviews. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74652" pm="."><plain>Secondary aims will investigate the immediate (T1) and long-term clinical effects (T2 and T3) on unimanual capacity (Melbourne Assessment 2 (MA 2)<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> and Box and Block Test (BBT)<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) and on bimanual daily activities at home and in the community (ABILHAND-Kids<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), participation (Participation and Environment Measure – Children and Youth (PEM-CY))<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32 33</xref> and perception of quality of life (Cerebral Palsy Quality of Life Questionnaire (CP-QOL)).<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34–36</xref> Further aims will assess the feasibility of Tele-UPCAT platform on assessing, monitoring and detecting changes during and after the AOT programme by comparing the data of the clinical outcome measures with those of quantitative measurement of manual activity, obtained using sensorised objects and Tele-UPCAT platform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74653" pm="."><plain>Finally, a cost-effective analysis will be carried out using both the perspective of the patient/caregivers and the healthcare system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="74654" pm="."><plain>Methods/design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="74655" pm="."><plain>Study design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74656" pm="."><plain>The Tele-UPCAT trial is an exploratory randomised, allocation concealed (waitlist controlled) and evaluator-blinded clinical trial with two investigative arms using an AOT intensive rehabilitation programme of home-based AOT compared with SC in children and young people with UCP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74657" pm="."><plain>This study is a waitlist-controlled trial, in order to allow all enrolled participants to perform AOT either immediately or after a waitlist period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74658" pm="."><plain>After obtaining informed consent and completing baseline assessment (T0), participants will be block randomised into pairs according to the House functional classification system (HFCS) activity level (grades 2–3, 4–5 and 6–8) and age (5–14 years and 15–20 years),<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37 38</xref> using a computer-generated set of random numbers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74659" pm="."><plain>Randomisation, sequence generation and preparation of group allocation materials will be carried out by an independent researcher who will be not involved in the trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74660" pm="."><plain>Pairs will be divided randomly into two groups with 1:1 experimental/SC (waitlist) ratio. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74661" pm="."><plain>Participants allocated in the experimental group will immediately start AOT for a 3-week period, while those in the SC group will continue with their usual care. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74662" pm="."><plain>A predefined diary for recording all daily activities (eg, times of sleep, weak-up, meals, school, therapies for UL or for lower limb and their dose) will be filled in by all the participants and their parents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74663" pm="."><plain>In addition, to record the acceptability and feasibility of the training, participants and/or families allocated in the experimental group will fill in a multiple choice questionnaire (with box for notes) for ascertaining the perception about their experiences of using the Tele-UPCAT system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74664" pm="."><plain>All participants will be re-evaluated after the period of experimental training/SC (T1) with standardised tests and questionnaires (see outcome measures). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74665" pm="."><plain>T1 will be the primary endpoint aimed at evaluating the short-term effects of AOT according to Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) guidelines (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">figure 1</xref>).<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="74666" pm="."><plain>Flow chart of Tele-UPCAT study according to CONSORT guidelines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74667" pm="."><plain>AHA, Assisting Hand Assessment; AOT, action observation training; BBT, Box and Block Test; CP-QOL, Cerebral Palsy Quality of Life; CONSORT, Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials; MA 2, Melbourne Assessment 2; PEM-CY, Participation and Environment Measure – Children and Youth. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bmjopen-2017-017819f01"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="74668" pm="."><plain>After this phase, participants previously allocated to the experimental group will continue SC, while who started with SC will then commence home-based AOT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74669" pm="."><plain>The participants of this SC group will be reassessed at the end of training (T1 plus). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74670" pm="."><plain>Further assessment of all participants will be performed after 8 weeks (T2) and 24 weeks (T3) from the end of AOT training (T1 or T1 plus, for the experimental and waitlist group, respectively), to evaluate the medium-term and long-term effects of AOT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74671" pm="."><plain>All the assessments will be carried out at home by trained therapists. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74672" pm="."><plain>In summary, assessments will be performed at:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>T0, baseline: the week before the period of AOT/SC.</p></list-item><list-item><p>T1: at 1 week after period of AOT/SC.</p></list-item><list-item><p>T1 plus: the week after period of AOT, for waitlist group.</p></list-item><list-item><p>T2: 8 weeks after end of AOT.</p></list-item><list-item><p>T3: 24 weeks after end of AOT.</p></list-item></list> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74673" pm="."><plain>The details of the study design are reported according to CONSORT guidelines<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">figure 1</xref>), Standard Protocol Items: Recommendations for Intervention Trials (SPIRIT) statement<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> and Template for Intervention Description and Replication (TIDier) Checklist<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41 42</xref> (online <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SP1 SP2 SP3">supplementary materials 1, 2 and 3</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74674" pm="."><plain>The programme of enrolment, interventions and assessments designed according to SPIRIT guidelines are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">figure 2</xref>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="74675" pm="."><plain>Schedule of enrolment, interventions and assessments. AHA, Assisting Hand Assessment; AOT, action observation training; BBT, Box and Block Test; CP-QOL, Cerebral Palsy Quality of Life Questionnaire; MA 2, Melbourne Assessment 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bmjopen-2017-017819f02"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="74676" pm="."><plain>Blinding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74677" pm="."><plain>All the clinical outcome measures (AHA,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26–28</xref> MA-2<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> and BBT<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) will be videotaped by a therapist blind to group assignment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74678" pm="."><plain>Videotapes will be randomised and scored by assessors blind to group allocation and order of assessments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74679" pm="."><plain>During each assessment, all the participants will wear two Actigraphs (wGT3X-BT and wActiSleep-BT), one for each wrist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74680" pm="."><plain>Two independent researchers (two paediatric neurologists) without competing interests will comprise the data monitoring committee for this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74681" pm="."><plain>They will review all adverse events (deciding to stop the trial if necessary), the retention of participant in each study arm and the compliance of study protocol at 12-weekly intervals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74682" pm="."><plain>Each participant will have a study number in a dedicated data file. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74683" pm="."><plain>The file with participant’s numbers and personal data will be stored in a password-protected file, accessible only by the principal investigator. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74684" pm="."><plain>In order to promote participant’s retention, all the assessment will be completed at home. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74685" pm="."><plain>The clinical primary and secondary outcome measures will be completed within 1 week. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74686" pm="."><plain>Enrolled participants are ethically able to withdraw from this study any time and have been notified that their usual follow-up and clinical care would not be impacted. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="74687" pm="."><plain>Study sample and recruitment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74688" pm="."><plain>Enrolment and clinical trial management will be carried out by paediatric neurologists and physiatrists at the Department of Developmental Neuroscience of IRCCS Fondazione Stella Maris (FSM, Pisa, Italy), with the collaboration of the Unit of Children Rehabilitation of S. Maria Nuova Hospital (Reggio Emilia, Italy). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74689" pm="."><plain>Potential participants will be identified according to inclusion criteria (see below), from UCP patients of the clinical departments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74690" pm="."><plain>Suitable participants and their parents will be invited to participate and will be enrolled in the RCT only after written consent has been obtained. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74691" pm="."><plain>Inclusion criteria are participants with:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Confirmed diagnosis of spastic motor type UCP.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3 43</xref> </p></list-item><list-item><p>Aged between 5 years and 20 years at time of recruitment.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Predominant UL spasticity.</p></list-item><list-item><p>HFCS score ≥2, that is, able to passively hold an object in the hand or better.<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37 38</xref> </p></list-item><list-item><p>Cognitive level within normal limits, that is, IQ ≥70, as assessed in the last year prior to recruitment on the Wechsler Preschool and Primary Scale of Intelligence-Third Edition (WPPSI-III),<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children Fourth Edition (WISC-IV)<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> or Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale (WAIS).<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> </p></list-item><list-item><p>Participants and parents willing to commit to the intensive therapy programme for a 3-week period.</p></list-item></list> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74692" pm="."><plain>Participants will be excluded in case of:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Previous orthopaedic surgery or botulinum toxin A (BoNT-A) injection in the UL within 6 months prior to the enrolment of this study.</p></list-item></list> </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="74693" pm="."><plain>Sample size </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74694" pm="."><plain>Even if this study will be planned as an exploratory study, a sample size estimates, according to CONSORT guidelines,<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38 40</xref> have been based on projected treatment effect on the primary outcome measure, AHA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74695" pm="."><plain>Taking account of the study design and the stratification, a minimum sample size of 10 per group will be required in order to detect a 1.40 effect size (value based on our preliminary data) at significant level of 0.05% and 80% power.<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20 21</xref> Considering a 20% of possible drop-outs, a minimum of 12 participants per group will be recruited, with a total sample of 24 participants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="74696" pm="."><plain>Study treatment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74697" pm="."><plain>The Tele-UPCAT system has been designed through the close collaboration between the rehabilitation staff (child neurologists and child therapists) of IRCCS Fondazione Stella Maris and biomedical engineers of BioRobotics Institute Scuola Superiore Sant’Anna. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74698" pm="."><plain>Taking into account the previous clinical experience on UPCAT, the main components of the Tele-UPCAT system (eg, the size of the screen, the need of a guide for alternating the time of observation and of execution and the key words for catching the attention), the AOT library of exercises (eg, the adaptation of the objects for enlarging the exercises to more impaired hands) and the experimental training (eg, time and duration) have been defined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74699" pm="."><plain>In general, the training will be structured in one session per day to be executed five working days for three consecutive weeks (ie, 15 sessions in total). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74700" pm="."><plain>The duration of daily sessions will be about 1 hour per day for a total of 15 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74701" pm="."><plain>The participants undergoing the AOT intervention through the Tele-UPCAT system will watch 3 min first-person video sequences of unimanual or bimanual goal-directed actions followed by their execution for 3 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74702" pm="."><plain>Three different actions will be proposed twice each day. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s2e1"><title><text><SENT sid="74703" pm="."><plain>Tele-UPCAT system </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74704" pm="."><plain>Tele-UPCAT system (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">figure 3</xref>) has been designed and built and will be provided at home by the BioRobotics Institute of Scuola Superiore Sant’Anna (Pontedera, Italy). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="74705" pm="."><plain>Tele-UPCAT platform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74706" pm="."><plain>Set-up of the Tele-UPCAT platform for delivering the AOT at home. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74707" pm="."><plain>It includes an observation module for the presentation of AOT videos (1) selected in the clinical interface (2) by the clinical staff in relation to HFCS level (6–8, 4–5 or 2–3), side of impaired hand and type of interface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74708" pm="."><plain>A dedicated software, aimed at guiding and motivating subjects to perform AOT, is also provided with age-related features (3) for teenagers or little boys and girls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74709" pm="."><plain>The motor performance module for the execution of actions is composed of a kit of common objects and toys, identical to those shown in the videos and a couple of Actigraphs (wGT3X-BT and wActiSleep-BT) worn on both wrists and a button. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74710" pm="."><plain>The integrated camera records subject’s attention during the observation task and exercise execution. AOT, action observation training; HFCS, House functional classification system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bmjopen-2017-017819f03"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="74711" pm="."><plain>It is a platform for delivering AOT designed to be user-friendly, by subjects at home in a playful setting with integrated smart features. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74712" pm="."><plain>The platform has been designed and developed by integrating two different modules:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The observation module (OM) for the presentation of AOT videos and recording of participant’s attention and exercise execution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74713" pm="."><plain>This consists of a computer with 23′ desktop, a dedicated software and a video camera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74714" pm="."><plain>The OM has been obtained by integrating a large all-in-one personal computer (All-in-One touch HP Elite One 800 G2 - L3N93AV), a large switch and a video camera (GoPro HERO Session), which will record a whole field, including subject’s face and hands and table with objects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74715" pm="."><plain>The OM is important to determine whether the participant is looking at the monitor during observation phase and has an overall view of the execution of actions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74716" pm="."><plain>A dedicated software, designed after a deep and specific literature analysis, was developed for guiding and motivating participants through the phases of AOT (observation followed by execution). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74717" pm="."><plain>In addition, the software was customised for the wide age range of participants providing an interactive game with an engaging story different for every day of training for school-aged children, and a slideshow with a voiceover for adolescents and young people. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74718" pm="."><plain>The general architecture of the software is based on the following sequence: observation of a 3 min video followed by execution of the same action for 3 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74719" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, the same video will be replayed and then executed a second time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74720" pm="."><plain>As stated before, a 60 min session, including rest intervals, of three different goal-directed actions of increasing complexity are observed and imitated twice every day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74721" pm="."><plain>At the end of each day, the software will terminate the session and automatically update it for the next day.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The motor performance module (MPM) for the execution of actions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74722" pm="."><plain>This will be mainly composed of a kit of exactly the same common objects and toys shown in the videos and two Actigraphs (wGT3X-BT and wActiSleep-BT; for more details, see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://actigraphcorp.com/support/activity-monitors/gt3x/">http://actigraphcorp.com/support/activity-monitors/gt3x/</ext-link>) worn one for each wrist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74723" pm="."><plain>With this design, it will be possible to measure the UL activity during the AOT, while the lack of sensorised toys embedded in the MPM will not allow to measure quantitative measures of hand activity (eg, force or pressure) during the AOT.</p></list-item></list> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74724" pm="."><plain>The first prototype of Tele-UPCAT system has been widely tested before the beginning of the RCT in order to test the stability and reliability of the system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e2"><title><text><SENT sid="74725" pm="."><plain>AOT library </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74726" pm="."><plain>On the basis of the previous AOT exercises,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20 21</xref> rehabilitation staff (child neurologist and child therapists) has created a library of rehabilitation packages composed of three different series of AOT exercises suitable to be executed at home. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74727" pm="."><plain>They differ for complexity of action and range of UL capabilities conceived in relation to HFCS levels (≤4, 5–6 and 7–8).<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37 38</xref> Each series is organised into customised sequences designed to cover unimanual and bimanual UL goal-directed actions with a variety of objects and toys commonly used in routine life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74728" pm="."><plain>For each series, experimental training is composed of 15 sets (eight unimanual followed by seven bimanual) of routine UL activities, to be completed in 3 weeks (5 days per week). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74729" pm="."><plain>Each set has a general common goal (eg, drinking a glass of water) composed of three sequential tasks of increasing complexity (eg, from picking up a bottle of water, to opening the cap, to pouring the water into a glass). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74730" pm="."><plain>As previously indicated, in order to grade the activities according to the range of capabilities, three series of sets have been planned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74731" pm="."><plain>The actions of each series have the same goal, but the material and type of movement (ie, range of movement and type of grasp) are customised in order to guarantee feasibility of the proposed activity while maintaining the same overall objective (see <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">figure 4</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74732" pm="."><plain>Each action of the three series performed by an actor is videotaped so that the videos show only the hand and arm from the first perspective; each video is then edited to last 3 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74733" pm="."><plain>A right-handed actor uses one or two hands for unimanual and bimanual exercises, respectively, for participants with right UCP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74734" pm="."><plain>For the left UCP, the previous videos were reversed if they maintained the same characteristic of the setting and of the hand movement, while the remaining videos were specifically videotaped. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="74735" pm="."><plain>List of goal-directed actions planned for the AOT training grouped in unimanual (days 1-8) and bimanual (days 9-15) actions </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74736" pm="."><plain>Days </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74737" pm="."><plain>Action A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74738" pm="."><plain>Action B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74739" pm="."><plain>Action C </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74740" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74741" pm="."><plain>Uncover a little ball by lifting a box. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74742" pm="."><plain>Place a little ball in a glass. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74743" pm="."><plain>Fill a glass with water. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74744" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74745" pm="."><plain>Pick coloured card and match it to the same colour. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74746" pm="."><plain>Move a coloured card and place it on a base. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74747" pm="."><plain>Pick a card and place it on the similar one. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74748" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74749" pm="."><plain>Pick up a rubber stamp and move from/to different positions. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74750" pm="."><plain>Pick up a rubber stamp and press it against horizontal plane to print a figure. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74751" pm="."><plain>Pick up a rubber stamp and press it against sloping plane to print a figure. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74752" pm="."><plain>4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74753" pm="."><plain>Pick up coin, put it in piggy bank through the slot on the top <break/>or <break/>pick up a magnet and place it on a horizontal magnetic board. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74754" pm="."><plain>Pick up coin, put it in piggy bank through the vertical slot on the side <break/>or <break/>pick up a magnet and place it on a sloping magnetic board. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74755" pm="."><plain>Pick up coin, put it in piggy bank through the horizontal slot on the side <break/>or <break/>pick up a magnet and place it on a vertical magnetic board. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74756" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74757" pm="."><plain>Pick up a wooden rubber stamp and move to different positions. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74758" pm="."><plain>Pick up a wooden rubber stamp and press it against horizontal plane to print a figure. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74759" pm="."><plain>Pick up a wooden rubber stamp and press it against sloping plane to print a figure. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74760" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74761" pm="."><plain>Move a spray can <break/>or <break/>move the bottle with a little ball inside. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74762" pm="."><plain>Place the spray can on a support <break/>or <break/>remove a little ball from the bottle. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74763" pm="."><plain>Put the spray can into a cup <break/>or <break/>press the catapult and launch a little ball. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74764" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74765" pm="."><plain>Move a container filled with shimmy powder. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74766" pm="."><plain>Open the container. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74767" pm="."><plain>Sprinkle shimmery powder on a paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74768" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74769" pm="."><plain>Place magnetic fish on a paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74770" pm="."><plain>Pick up fishing rod and catch magnetic fish. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74771" pm="."><plain>Pick up magnetic fish and place them in a container. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74772" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74773" pm="."><plain>Move a hole punch. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74774" pm="."><plain>Insert a sheet of paper and make holes. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74775" pm="."><plain>Match holes on sticks. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74776" pm="."><plain>10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74777" pm="."><plain>Wet a cloth placing it in a container with water. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74778" pm="."><plain>Wring cloth and place it in a plate. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74779" pm="."><plain>Open a toy washing machine and insert the cloth inside. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74780" pm="."><plain>11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74781" pm="."><plain>Pick up a card and place it on a support. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74782" pm="."><plain>Pick up a card and insert it in a clothespin. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74783" pm="."><plain>Pick up a card and insert it in a clothespin in a different orientation. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74784" pm="."><plain>12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74785" pm="."><plain>Pick up and handle a piece of Play-Doh. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74786" pm="."><plain>Divide it in two pieces. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74787" pm="."><plain>Open a toy oven and insert a saucepan (with Play-Doh in it). </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74788" pm="."><plain>13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74789" pm="."><plain>Search for coin in the bag and place it on a support. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74790" pm="."><plain>Take the coin and insert it in a wallet. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74791" pm="."><plain>Open a box and place the wallet inside. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74792" pm="."><plain>14 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74793" pm="."><plain>Open a tube of tempera paint. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74794" pm="."><plain>Wet a brush with tempera paint. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74795" pm="."><plain>Make figure using a stencil with the brush dipped in tempera paint. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74796" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74797" pm="."><plain>Move a glitter glue tube. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74798" pm="."><plain>Open it. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="74799" pm="."><plain>Decorate a frame by pasting pieces of mosaic. </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><p><text><SENT sid="74800" pm="."><plain>AOT, action observation training. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="74801" pm="."><plain>(A) Example of the unimanual action B of day 1 for the left hand, with a different pattern of movement, based on subject HFCS level, maintaining the same goal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74802" pm="."><plain>(B) Example of the bimanual action B of day 11 for the right hand, with a different pattern of movement, based on subject HFCS level, maintaining the same goal. HFCS, House functional classification system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bmjopen-2017-017819f04"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2e3"><title><text><SENT sid="74803" pm="."><plain>Experimental training </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74804" pm="."><plain>Before delivering the Tele-UPCAT platform, the training will be customised individually for each participant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74805" pm="."><plain>The rehabilitation staff will select, on the basis of age and HFCS level, from the library the most appropriated AOT rehabilitation packages for each participant, then the engineers will upload them in the OM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74806" pm="."><plain>For the MPM, the therapists will organise a container of all the objects identifying them with numbers relative to the training day (eg, little ball number 1, which means day 1 of the training). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74807" pm="."><plain>In addition, a dedicated printed manual with instructions and guidelines related to the different steps of the training and for system management, and the setup will be provided. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74808" pm="."><plain>The manual contains also all the contacts of both technical and rehabilitation staff for remote assistance in case of any problems during the training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74809" pm="."><plain>Two Actigraphs (wGT3X-BT, wActiSleep-BT) will be initialised for the recording period (3 weeks) to be worn on each wrist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74810" pm="."><plain>The ICT platform will be delivered to the participant’s home by the engineers that are in charge of the installation of the system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74811" pm="."><plain>The families will identify a designated position with a table or a desk of about 80×100 cm near to a socket where the ICT platform will be placed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74812" pm="."><plain>Engineers and rehabilitation staff will train both parents and participants about the correct use of the system, including safety aspects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74813" pm="."><plain>During the first two training days, a therapist will visit each participant and their parents to confirm the set-up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74814" pm="."><plain>During the training sessions, each participant will sit on a chair with both arms placed on a table in front of a platform positioned at about 1 m. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74815" pm="."><plain>Especially when the participant will be a child, a parent will be seated on his or her more impaired side to prompt attention during task execution and assist if necessary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74816" pm="."><plain>The software will guide the participant in the sequence of observations and executions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e4"><title><text><SENT sid="74817" pm="."><plain>Standard care </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74818" pm="."><plain>Participants previously allocated in the SC group will continue their usual care for 3 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74819" pm="."><plain>Usual care for recruited participants could be consisted for physical or occupational therapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74820" pm="."><plain>The frequency, dose and the type of all therapies will be recorded accurately by a diary in both groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="74821" pm="."><plain>Outcome measures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2f1"><title><text><SENT sid="74822" pm="."><plain>Description of sample </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74823" pm="."><plain>Children participating in the study will be classified according to HFCS, which assesses function of the impaired hand in children with CP.<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37 38</xref> This classification consists of nine grades ranging from a hand that is not used at all (grade 0) to one that is used spontaneously and independently from the other one (grade 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74824" pm="."><plain>Due to the general approach in classifying hand functional level, this scale can also be easily applied to young adults with UCP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74825" pm="."><plain>HFCS will be used for all ages as a criterion for inclusion in this study (from grade 2 to grade 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74826" pm="."><plain>In addition, they will be classified according to the Manual Ability Classification System, a classification system of the child’s ability to handle objects in daily activities on one of five levels.<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f2"><title><text><SENT sid="74827" pm="."><plain>Primary outcome measure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74828" pm="."><plain>On the basis of our scientific hypothesis and according to previous clinical experience,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20 21</xref> the primary outcome measure will be the AHA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74829" pm="."><plain>The latest version 5.0 will be used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74830" pm="."><plain>This assessment measures UL function during bimanual activities by evaluating spontaneous use of assisting hand during a semistructured age-appropriated 10–15 min session with specific toys or objects requiring bimanual handling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74831" pm="."><plain>The school-kids form will be used for the assessment of UCP children aged 6–12 years,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26 27</xref> while the adolescent version (Ad-AHA), using the board game ‘Go with the Floe’,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> will be completed with participants older than 13 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74832" pm="."><plain>This last version, even if validated up to 18 years, will be used with potential participants aged 18–20 years to guarantee the same assessment across all participants regardless of age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74833" pm="."><plain>Moreover, AHA has been already used, even if not validated, in young people with UCP.<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48 49</xref> The scale uses a Rasch measurement model, which is a method to convert raw scores into a linear measure located on a unidimensional scale and more specifically to convert them into 0–100 logit-based AHA units, which will be used for the statistical analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74834" pm="."><plain>All AHA assessments will be videotaped in a standardised manner, and the subsequent scoring will be carried out by a certified expert rater who will be masked to group allocation and assessment order.<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26–28</xref> </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f3"><title><text><SENT sid="74835" pm="."><plain>Other outcome measures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74836" pm="."><plain>Other secondary measures will include measures of unimanual capacity (MA-2<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> and BBT<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) and bimanual daily activities at home and in the community (ABILHAND-Kids).<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Moreover, participation and quality of life will also be assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74837" pm="."><plain>All assessment will be performed at T0, T1, T1 plus, T2 and T3 unless otherwise indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74838" pm="."><plain>Questionnaires will be completed by parents and/or participants at home and if doubts will occur, child neurologists or therapists will be available to discuss face to face items not clear to them.<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p>The MA 2<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> measures unilateral UL function, and it is a valid and reliable tool for evaluating quality of UL movement in children with neurological conditions for ages between 2.5 years and 15 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74839" pm="."><plain>MA 2 is a criterion-referenced test that extends and refines the scale properties of the original Melbourne Unilateral Upper Limb assessment (MUUL), and like MUUL, it can also be used for adolescents and young adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74840" pm="."><plain>MA 2 measures four elements of UL movement quality: movement range, accuracy, dexterity and fluency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74841" pm="."><plain>It comprises 14 test items of reaching, grasping, releasing and manipulating simple objects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74842" pm="."><plain>The test is administered by videorecording the child’s performance for subsequent scoring (30 items score). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74843" pm="."><plain>A raw score is provided for each of the four sections (movement range, accuracy, dexterity and fluency) that will be analysed separately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74844" pm="."><plain>It predominantly includes concepts within the body function domain as well as in the activity domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74845" pm="."><plain>Even if the MUUL and also the MA 2 have been validated up to 15 years, the first one has been used in studies involving patients with CP older than 15 year and in adults.<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48 49</xref> We have chosen to use the MA 2 also for participants older than 15 years to guarantee the same assessment across all participants regardless of age instead of using other scales (eg, the Fugl-Meyer Assessment or the Action Research Arm test).<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> </p></list-item><list-item><p>BBT is a quick (2–5 min), simple and inexpensive test, which measures unimanual dexterity in the activity domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74846" pm="."><plain>BBT is composed of a test box with a partition in the middle and 150 wooden blocks (25 mm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74847" pm="."><plain>The patient had to transport as many blocks as possible in 1 min from one compartment to another. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74848" pm="."><plain>First, the patient is asked to perform the test with the unaffected hand and then with the affected hand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74849" pm="."><plain>The number of blocks transported by affected hand in 1 min will be counted and considered for the main analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74850" pm="."><plain>It can be used for a wide range of populations from childhood to adulthood.<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> </p></list-item><list-item><p>ABILHAND-Kids<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> is a semistructured item-response questionnaire on a three-point ordinal scale (impossible, difficult and easy) that measures daily manual activities referred to in the activity domain of International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74851" pm="."><plain>Parents will be instructed to rate their child’s perceived difficulty in performing each activity, taking account the performance of their child when performing the activity without technical or human assistance, regardless of the limb(s) and the strategies used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74852" pm="."><plain>It has been validate for children aged 6–15 years, but it has been used for larger ranges (6–19 years).<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> The questionnaire has been developed using the Rasch measurement model, which provides a method to convert the ordinal raw scores into a linear logit measures located on a unidimensional scale that will be used for the analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74853" pm="."><plain>This questionnaire will be used at all assessment periods.</p></list-item><list-item><p>PEM-CY<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32 33</xref> is a parent-reported instrument that evaluates participation and environment across home (10 items), school (5 items) and community (10 items) settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74854" pm="."><plain>For each item, the parent is asked to identify how frequent (over the past 4 months) the child has participated (eight options: daily to never); how involved the child typically is while participating (five-point scale: very involved to minimally involved); and whether the parent would like to see the child’s participation in this type of activity change (no or yes, with five options for the type of change desired). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74855" pm="."><plain>For each setting, the parent is then asked to report on whether certain features of the environment make it easier or harder for the child to participate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74856" pm="."><plain>The following summary scores will be obtained: total score and score for each of the three setting-specific environmental supportiveness (home, school and community). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74857" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the total number of supports and the total number of barriers will be computed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74858" pm="."><plain>This questionnaire will be used at T0 and T3.</p></list-item><list-item><p>CP-QOL – Child, 4–12 years and CP QOL – Teen, 13–18 years evaluate quality of life in children and adolescents with CP.<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34–36</xref> A score on a 0–100 scale will be obtained for each of computed subdomains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74859" pm="."><plain>In particular, the Children form filled in by the parents assesses seven subdomains (social well-being and acceptance, feelings about functioning, participation and physical health, emotional well-being and self-esteem, access to services, pain and impact of disability and family health) and five subdomains (excluding access to services and family health to the previous) for the children version. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74860" pm="."><plain>The Teen form evaluates seven subdomains (general well-being and participation, communication and physical health, school well-being, social well-being, access to services, family health and feeling about functioning) for the form filled in by the parents and five subdomains (excluding Access to services and Family health to the previous) for those filled in by the caregivers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74861" pm="."><plain>These questionnaires will be used at T0 and T3.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Quantitative measurement during unimanual and bimanual manipulation tasks, executed after the observation of the same tasks, is a new assessment tool that consists of observation, followed by execution of three tasks of increasing difficulty (unimanual lifting, bimanual placing near and bimanual cooperation, holding and pulling) by means of a sensorised object. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74862" pm="."><plain>New technological tools such as sensorised objects can help in assessing the manipulation capabilities (reaching and grasping) in a quantitative but ecological way and the sensitivity to a training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74863" pm="."><plain>Previous studies of the authors were focused on the development of sensorised toys for measuring infant’s manipulation.<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">52–54</xref> Starting from these experiences, a new sensorised object has been designed and developed by the engineers tuning the sensors sensitivity and working range to the needs of participants with UCP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74864" pm="."><plain>Two load cells and a switch embedded in the sensorissed object allow for the measurement of the following parameters: grasping time, maximum grasping force and delay time between unaffected and affected hand in reaching for the object. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74865" pm="."><plain>This set-up is out of Tele-UPCAT system even if it was designed and developed in parallel.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Quantitative measurement of bimanual activities will be performed in all the participants enrolled in the study by means of Actigraph GXT3+, as components of MPM of Tele-UPCAT system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74866" pm="."><plain>Actigraphs wGT3X-BT and wActiSleep-BT, equipped with a Velcro strap bracelet, will be worn, one for each wrists. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74867" pm="."><plain>As a general rule, the experimental group have to wear the Actigraphs during the training sessions and between T0 and T1 and between T1 and T2 (total 6 weeks, 24 hours per day or as much as possible), while the control group is requested to wear them between T0 and T1, between T1 and T1 plus and, if possible, also between T1 plus and T2 (total 9 weeks, 24 hours per day or as much as possible). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74868" pm="."><plain>All the daily activities, experimental training or usual care or removal will be recorded in a dedicated diary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74869" pm="."><plain>The Actigraphs will also be worn by all the participants during each time point of clinical assessments with the outcome measures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74870" pm="."><plain>Data will be mainly relative to the asymmetry index, which is the difference between the mean activity of the dominant with those of the non-dominant hand, and it will be correlated with the clinical scores obtained in the clinical outcome measures (mainly AHA).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Cost effectiveness: a within-trial cost–utility analysis will be conducted to synthesise the costs and benefits of the training programme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74871" pm="."><plain>Resource use (staff time, equipment and facility use) associated with the programme will be collected alongside the RCT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74872" pm="."><plain>Healthcare utilisation will be collected using a resource use questionnaire previously used in CP studies.<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref> Health utility will be derived from the adapted Child Health Utility instrument (CHU-9D),<xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> a quality of life measure designed specifically for economic evaluation and which has been validated in an Australian population.<xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">57–59</xref> </p></list-item><list-item><p>A semiguided face-to-face interview (online <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SP4">supplementary material 4</xref>) about the acceptability of the training will be completed immediately after the training period (T1 or T1 plus). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74873" pm="."><plain>It will be performed by the rehabilitation staff with the aim of investigating participants’ and parents’ opinions about the training. It will explore the customisation of exercises, suitability to UCP children, feasibility at home, required effort by the participants and acceptability of Actigraphs, suitability of the manual and of the software.</p></list-item></list> <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SP4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2017-017819.supp4</object-id><label>Supplementary data</label><p> <inline-supplementary-material id="ss4" xlink:href="bmjopen-2017-017819supp004.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" content-type="local-data"/> </p></supplementary-material> </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="74874" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74875" pm="."><plain>Clinical data will be analysed by means of the Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74876" pm="."><plain>Means and SD of clinical outcome scores for both groups will be calculated to identify potential baseline differences between groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74877" pm="."><plain>As a first step, normality of distributions will be verified by Shapiro-Wilk’s test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74878" pm="."><plain>Between-group differences for all selected outcome measures will be evaluated at T0, by means of t-test for unrelated samples or non-parametric Mann-Whitney U independent sample test for normal or non-normal distributed data, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74879" pm="."><plain>To test our first hypothesis, an intention-to-treat analysis will be carried out, evaluating between-group differences (delta scores) for primary and secondary outcome measures at the primary endpoint (T1), compared with T0 (T1-T0), by means of parametric or non-parametric tests for unrelated samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74880" pm="."><plain>The age, HFCS level, characteristics of usual care (in both groups), supervision of caregiver and acceptability of therapy (measured by semistructured interview) will be analysed for further secondary exploratory analyses (eg, regression modelling) in order to determine if some of these variables are predictive of better responses to the Tele-UPCAT training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74881" pm="."><plain>In addition, a matched-pairs test (t-tests or Wilcoxon) will be carried out in order to assess retention of effects at follow-up periods (T1 or T1 plus, T2 and T3) relative to assessment before AOT training (T0 or T1 for experimental or waitlist group, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74882" pm="."><plain>Bonferroni corrections will not be carried out in relation to the exploratory nature of the current RCT study and the relative small number of the study sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74883" pm="."><plain>To detect if significant changes will correlate to HFCS levels, a correlation analysis between score changes after AOT training (T1 or T1 plus) and assessment before AOT training (T0 or T1) will be carried out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74884" pm="."><plain>Finally, an exploratory within-group analysis will be performed for the waitlist group comparing changes during AOT with respect to those of the first SC period. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="74885" pm="."><plain>Ethics and dissemination </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74886" pm="."><plain>This study protocol describes background, hypotheses, system, clinical and technological outcome measures for a RCT designed to evaluate the Tele-UPCAT system as a new approach to deliver AOT to children and young people with UCP at home. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74887" pm="."><plain>Any deviations from the protocol will be promptly notified to the ethics committee and applied only after its approval. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74888" pm="."><plain>The trial has been registered at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clinicaltrials.gov">http://www.clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link> (identifier NCT03094455). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74889" pm="."><plain>This study protocol is reported according to the SPIRIT statement (SPIRIT 2013)<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> and the TIDier guidelines.<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41 42</xref> We anticipate that the results of this study will be disseminated through peer-reviewed journals and national and international academic conferences only by the professionals directly involved in the clinical trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74890" pm="."><plain>The results of this study will be of interest for rehabilitation trials based on AOT paradigm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74891" pm="."><plain>Referring to a previous RCT study,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20 21</xref> we suggest that the home setting might increase accessibility of rehabilitation to a large number of children and young people with UCP (eg, participants that live far from the clinical centres) with a large range of hand impairments (including also participants with HFCS level lower than 6) and older age (5–20 years instead of 5–15 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74892" pm="."><plain>Moreover, if the Tele-UPCAT study, using a very simple ICT solution, demonstrates to be viable for delivering AOT at home with significant improvements in UL daily activities, it could lead to the application of new solution for cost-efficient rehabilitation programmes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74893" pm="."><plain>Implementation of new smart technologies can (1) provide user-friendly AOT programmes at home; (2) remotely manage treatment by rehabilitation staff, thus increasing the ratio ‘number of patients per therapist’; and (3) offer individualised and intensive training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74894" pm="."><plain>It could become an economical and efficient rehabilitation programme by achieving significant long-lasting effects in UL activity and participation through an easily implementable paradigm that could become an integral part of common clinical practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74895" pm="."><plain>Finally, this approach could become a rehabilitation tool and be applicable to broader populations of CP and other chronic disabilities. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="74896" pm="."><plain>Project status </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74897" pm="."><plain>This project began recruitment on 29 March 2017, and we expect to complete data collection for the last training in November 2017 and close the project in April 2018. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SP1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2017-017819.supp1</object-id><label>Supplementary data</label><p><text><SENT sid="74898" pm="."><plain><inline-supplementary-material id="ss1" xlink:href="bmjopen-2017-017819supp001.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" content-type="local-data"/> </plain></SENT>
</text></p></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SP2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2017-017819.supp2</object-id><label>Supplementary data</label><p><text><SENT sid="74899" pm="."><plain><inline-supplementary-material id="ss2" xlink:href="bmjopen-2017-017819supp002.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" content-type="local-data"/> </plain></SENT>
</text></p></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SP3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2017-017819.supp3</object-id><label>Supplementary data</label><p><text><SENT sid="74900" pm="."><plain><inline-supplementary-material id="ss3" xlink:href="bmjopen-2017-017819supp003.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" content-type="local-data"/> </plain></SENT>
</text></p></supplementary-material></sec><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="74901" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material id="d35e367" content-type="local-data"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="74902" pm="."><plain>Reviewer comments </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2017-017819.reviewer_comments.pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d35e368" content-type="local-data"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="74903" pm="."><plain>Author's manuscript </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2017-017819.draft_revisions.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="74904" pm="."><plain>We would like to acknowledge the contribution of Valentina Menici (paediatric PT), and Irene Braito, MD, for video and material collection, Siresia Bagnoli and Marco Zemolin for the design and the interface storyboard and Vincent Corsentino for English reviewing. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="74905" pm="."><plain><bold>Contributors:</bold> GS is the principal investigator of the project and mainly responsible of the clinical part of it, while FC is the main responsible of the ICT platform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74906" pm="."><plain>GS, EI, HF, KK, RNB, AF and GC designed the research study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74907" pm="."><plain>GS, EB, EI, SP and ES were responsible for the AOT library. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74908" pm="."><plain>GS, SP and ES were in charge for participants’ recruitment in Pisa and identification of type of exercise and software and AF for Reggio Emilia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74909" pm="."><plain>GS and EB will collect the data and will monitor the training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74910" pm="."><plain>FC, IM, MM and FPF with the supervision of PD have designed and built the new platform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74911" pm="."><plain>GS and GC will take the lead roles on preparation of publications on the clinical outcomes of the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74912" pm="."><plain>All authors have read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="other"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="74913" pm="."><plain><bold>Funding:</bold> This trial has been funded by the Italian Ministry of Health to GS and FC (GR-2011-02350053). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="74914" pm="."><plain><bold>Competing interests:</bold> None declared. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="74915" pm="."><plain><bold>Patient consent:</bold> Not required. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="74916" pm="."><plain><bold>Ethics approval:</bold> Tuscany Paediatric Ethics Committee (169/2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="74917" pm="."><plain><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><text><SENT sid="74918" pm="."><plain><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krägeloh-Mann</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Cerebral palsy update</article-title>. <source>Brain Dev</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.braindev.2009.03.009</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19386453</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R2"><text><SENT sid="74919" pm="."><plain><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <collab>Surveillance of Cerebral Palsy in Europe</collab>. <article-title>Surveillance of cerebral palsy in Europe: a collaboration of cerebral palsy surveys and registers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74920" pm="."><plain>Surveillance of Cerebral Palsy in Europe (SCPE)</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source> <year>2000</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>816</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11132255</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R3"><text><SENT sid="74921" pm="."><plain><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cioni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sgandurra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muzzini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <chapter-title>Forms of hemiplegia</chapter-title> : <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cioni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>The spastic forms of cerebral palsy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74922" pm="."><plain>A guide to the assessment of adaptive functions</source>. <publisher-loc>Milan, Italy</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year>:<fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R4"><text><SENT sid="74923" pm="."><plain><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Romundstad</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De La Cruz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Cerebral palsy among children born moderately preterm or at moderately low birthweight between 1980 and 1998: a European register-based study</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source> <year>2011</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>913</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8749.2011.04079.x</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21838820</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R5"><text><SENT sid="74924" pm="."><plain><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Himmelmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uvebrant</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>The panorama of cerebral palsy in Sweden. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74925" pm="."><plain>XI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74926" pm="."><plain>Changing patterns in the birth-year period 2003-2006</article-title>. <source>Acta Paediatr</source> <year>2014</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>618</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/apa.12614</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24575788</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R6"><text><SENT sid="74927" pm="."><plain><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ada</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Constraint-induced movement therapy improves upper limb activity and participation in hemiplegic cerebral palsy: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Physiother</source> <year>2016</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>130</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jphys.2016.05.013</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27323932</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R7"><text><SENT sid="74928" pm="."><plain><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakzewski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ziviani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Systematic review and meta-analysis of therapeutic management of upper-limb dysfunction in children with congenital hemiplegia</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>123</volume>:<fpage>e1111</fpage>–<lpage>e1122</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2008-3335</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451190</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R8"><text><SENT sid="74929" pm="."><plain><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakzewski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ziviani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Efficacy of upper limb therapies for unilateral cerebral palsy: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source> <year>2014</year>;<volume>133</volume>:<fpage>e175</fpage>–<lpage>e204</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2013-0675</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24366991</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R9"><text><SENT sid="74930" pm="."><plain><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inguaggiato</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sgandurra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perazza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Brain reorganization following intervention in children with congenital hemiplegia: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Neural Plast</source> <year>2013</year>;<volume>2013</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/356275</pub-id> </mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R10"><text><SENT sid="74931" pm="."><plain><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maoret</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muzzini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>A randomized trial of upper limb botulimun toxin versus placebo injection, combined with physiotherapy, in children with hemiplegia</article-title>. <source>Res Dev Disabil</source> <year>2014</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>2505</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ridd.2014.06.001</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24995688</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R11"><text><SENT sid="74932" pm="."><plain><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabbri-Destro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rizzolatti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Mirror neurons and mirror systems in monkeys and humans</article-title>. <source>Physiology</source> <year>2008</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physiol.00004.2008</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18556470</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R12"><text><SENT sid="74933" pm="."><plain><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallese</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fadiga</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fogassi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Action recognition in the premotor cortex</article-title>. <source>Brain</source> <year>1996</year>;<volume>119</volume>(<issue>Pt 2</issue>):<fpage>593</fpage>–<lpage>609</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/119.2.593</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8800951</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R13"><text><SENT sid="74934" pm="."><plain><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ertelt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Solodkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Action observation has a positive impact on rehabilitation of motor deficits after stroke</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source> <year>2007</year>;<volume>36 Suppl 2</volume>(<issue>Suppl 2</issue>):<fpage>T164</fpage>–<lpage>T173</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2007.03.043</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17499164</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R14"><text><SENT sid="74935" pm="."><plain><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franceschini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agosti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cantagallo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Mirror neurons: action observation treatment as a tool in stroke rehabilitation</article-title>. <source>Eur J Phys Rehabil Med</source> <year>2010</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20332719</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R15"><text><SENT sid="74936" pm="."><plain><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alegre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodríguez-Oroz</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valencia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Changes in subthalamic activity during movement observation in Parkinson’s disease: is the mirror system mirrored in the basal ganglia?</article-title> <source>Clin Neurophysiol</source> <year>2010</year>;<volume>121</volume>:<fpage>414</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2009.11.013</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20006544</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R16"><text><SENT sid="74937" pm="."><plain><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelosin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bove</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruggeri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Reduction of bradykinesia of finger movements by a single session of action observation in Parkinson disease</article-title>. <source>Neurorehabil Neural Repair</source> <year>2013</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>552</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1545968312471905</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23392919</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R17"><text><SENT sid="74938" pm="."><plain><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buccino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernardini</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Action observation treatment improves recovery of postsurgical orthopedic patients: evidence for a top-down effect?</article-title> <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source> <year>2010</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>1489</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apmr.2010.07.013</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20875504</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R18"><text><SENT sid="74939" pm="."><plain><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caligiore</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mustile</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spalletta</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Action observation and motor imagery for rehabilitation in Parkinson’s disease: A systematic review and an integrative hypothesis</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source> <year>2017</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>210</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2016.11.005</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27865800</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R19"><text><SENT sid="74940" pm="."><plain><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buccino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arisi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gough</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Improving upper limb motor functions through action observation treatment: a pilot study in children with cerebral palsy</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source> <year>2012</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>822</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8749.2012.04334.x</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22765352</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R20"><text><SENT sid="74941" pm="."><plain><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sgandurra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cossu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Upper limb children action-observation training (UP-CAT): a randomised controlled trial in hemiplegic cerebral palsy</article-title>. <source>BMC Neurol</source> <year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>80</fpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2377-11-80</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21711525</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R21"><text><SENT sid="74942" pm="."><plain><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sgandurra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cossu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Randomized trial of observation and execution of upper extremity actions versus action alone in children with unilateral cerebral palsy</article-title>. <source>Neurorehabil Neural Repair</source> <year>2013</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>808</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1545968313497101</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23886886</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R22"><text><SENT sid="74943" pm="."><plain><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sgandurra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lorentzen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inguaggiato</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Effects of home-based early intervention with CareToy system in preterm infants: a Randomized Clinical Trial study</article-title>. <source>PlosOne</source> <year>2017</year>;<volume>22;12</volume>:<elocation-id>e0173521</elocation-id>.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R23"><text><SENT sid="74944" pm="."><plain><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sgandurra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartalena</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cecchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <collab>CareToy Consortium</collab>. <article-title>A pilot study on early home-based intervention through an intelligent baby gym (CareToy) in preterm infants</article-title>. <source>Res Dev Disabil</source> <year>2016</year>;<volume>53-54</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ridd.2016.01.013</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26851385</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R24"><text><SENT sid="74945" pm="."><plain><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sgandurra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartalena</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cioni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <collab>CareToy Consortium</collab>. <article-title>Home-based, early intervention with mechatronic toys for preterm infants at risk of neurodevelopmental disorders (CARETOY): a RCT protocol</article-title>. <source>BMC Pediatr</source> <year>2014</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>268</fpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2431-14-268</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25319764</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R25"><text><SENT sid="74946" pm="."><plain><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rihar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sgandurra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>CareToy: Stimulation and assessment of preterm infant’s activity using a novel sensorized system</article-title>. <source>Ann Biomed Eng</source> <year>2016</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>3593</fpage>–<lpage>605</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10439-016-1669-4</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27287310</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R26"><text><SENT sid="74947" pm="."><plain><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krumlinde-sundholm</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eliasson</surname><given-names>A-christin</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Development of the assisting hand assessment: a rasch-built measure intended for children with unilateral upper limb impairments</article-title>. <source>Scand J Occup Ther</source> <year>2003</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/11038120310004529</pub-id> </mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R27"><text><SENT sid="74948" pm="."><plain><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krumlinde-Sundholm</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holmefur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kottorp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>The assisting hand assessment: current evidence of validity, reliability, and responsiveness to change</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source> <year>2007</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8749.2007.00259.x</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17376135</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R28"><text><SENT sid="74949" pm="."><plain><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Louwers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beelen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holmefur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Development of the Assisting Hand Assessment for adolescents (Ad-AHA) and validation of the AHA from 18 months to 18 years</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source> <year>2016</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>1303</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dmcn.13168</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27291981</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R29"><text><SENT sid="74950" pm="."><plain><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Imms</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Rasch analysis of the melbourne assessment of unilateral upper limb function</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source> <year>2014</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>665</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dmcn.12391</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24494925</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R30"><text><SENT sid="74951" pm="."><plain><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathiowetz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Federman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wiemer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Box and block test of manual dexterity: norms for 6–19 year olds</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Occupational Therapy</source> <year>1985</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/000841748505200505</pub-id> </mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R31"><text><SENT sid="74952" pm="."><plain><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnould</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Renders</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>ABILHAND-Kids: a measure of manual ability in children with cerebral palsy</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2004</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>1045</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15452296</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R32"><text><SENT sid="74953" pm="."><plain><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coster</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bedell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Law</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Psychometric evaluation of the Participation and Environment Measure for Children and Youth</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source> <year>2011</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>1030</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8749.2011.04094.x</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22014322</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R33"><text><SENT sid="74954" pm="."><plain><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khetani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Validity of the Participation and Environment Measure for Children and Youth (PEM-CY) for Health Impact Assessment (HIA) in sustainable development projects</article-title>. <source>Disabil Health J</source> <year>2014</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>226</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dhjo.2013.11.003</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24680052</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R34"><text><SENT sid="74955" pm="."><plain><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mackinnon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Psychometric properties of the quality of life questionnaire for children with CP</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source> <year>2007</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0012162207000126.x</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17209977</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R35"><text><SENT sid="74956" pm="."><plain><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shelly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Quality of life of adolescents with cerebral palsy: perspectives of adolescents and parents</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8749.2008.03194.x</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19191833</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R36"><text><SENT sid="74957" pm="."><plain><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>A systematic review of the psychometric properties of Quality of Life measures for school aged children with cerebral palsy</article-title>. <source>BMC Pediatr</source> <year>2010</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2431-10-81</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21059270</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R37"><text><SENT sid="74958" pm="."><plain><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>House</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gwathmey</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fidler</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>A dynamic approach to the thumb in- palm deformity in cerebral palsy: evaluation and results in fifty-six patients</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg</source> <year>1981</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7462278</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R38"><text><SENT sid="74959" pm="."><plain><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koman</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Quantification of upper extremity function and range of motion in children with cerebral palsy</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source> <year>2008</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>910</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8749.2008.03098.x</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18811712</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R39"><text><SENT sid="74960" pm="."><plain><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cobos-Carbó</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Augustovski</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>[CONSORT 2010 Declaration: updated guideline for reporting parallel group randomised trials]</article-title>. <source>Med Clin</source> <year>2011</year>;<volume>137</volume>:<fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.medcli.2010.09.034</pub-id> </mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R40"><text><SENT sid="74961" pm="."><plain><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tetzlaff</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gøtzsche</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>SPIRIT 2013 explanation and elaboration: guidance for protocols of clinical trials</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>2013</year>;<volume>346</volume>:<fpage>e7586</fpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.e7586</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23303884</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R41"><text><SENT sid="74962" pm="."><plain><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glasziou</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boutron</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Better reporting of interventions: template for intervention description and replication (TIDieR) checklist and guide</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>2014</year>;<volume>348</volume>:<fpage>g1687</fpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.g1687</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24609605</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R42"><text><SENT sid="74963" pm="?"><plain><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakzewski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reedman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Do we really know what they were testing? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74964" pm="."><plain>Incomplete reporting of interventions in randomised trials of upper limb therapies in unilateral cerebral palsy</article-title>. <source>Res Dev Disabil</source> <year>2016</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ridd.2016.09.018</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27736712</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R43"><text><SENT sid="74965" pm="."><plain><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bax</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenbaum</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Executive committee for the definition of cerebral palsy: proposed definition and classification of cerebral palsy</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source>;<volume>2005</volume>:<fpage>571</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R44"><text><SENT sid="74966" pm="."><plain><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> <source>WPPSI-III, Wechsler preschool and primary scale of intelligence</source>. <edition>3rd edn</edition> <publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychological Corporation</publisher-name>, <year>2002</year>.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R45"><text><SENT sid="74967" pm="."><plain><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> <source>WISC-IV, Wechsler intelligence scale for children</source>. <edition>4th edn</edition> <publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychological Corporation</publisher-name>, <year>2003</year>.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R46"><text><SENT sid="74968" pm="."><plain><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> <source>Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale (WAIS-IV-UK) administration and scoring manual</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R47"><text><SENT sid="74969" pm="."><plain><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eliasson</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krumlinde-Sundholm</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rösblad</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>The Manual Ability Classification System (MACS) for children with cerebral palsy: scale development and evidence of validity and reliability</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>549</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0012162206001162</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16780622</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R48"><text><SENT sid="74970" pm="."><plain><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordstrand</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eliasson</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Six years after a modified constraint induced movement therapy (CIMT) program--what happens when the children have become young adults?</article-title> <source>Phys Occup Ther Pediatr</source> <year>2013</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/01942638.2013.757157</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23369068</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R49"><text><SENT sid="74971" pm="."><plain><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reidy</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naber</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Viguers</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Outcomes of a clinic-based pediatric constraint-induced movement therapy program</article-title>. <source>Phys Occup Ther Pediatr</source> <year>2012</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/01942638.2012.694991</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22731797</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R50"><text><SENT sid="74972" pm="."><plain><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Platz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinkowski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Wijck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Reliability and validity of arm function assessment with standardized guidelines for the Fugl-Meyer Test, Action Research Arm Test and Box and Block Test: a multicentre study</article-title>. <source>Clin Rehabil</source> <year>2005</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>404</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1191/0269215505cr832oa</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15929509</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R51"><text><SENT sid="74973" pm="."><plain><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bleyenheuft</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rameckers</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Measuring changes of manual ability with ABILHAND-Kids following intensive training for children with unilateral cerebral palsy</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source> <year>2017</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>505</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dmcn.13338</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27896811</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R52"><text><SENT sid="74974" pm="."><plain><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Passetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cecchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baldoli</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Sensorized toys for measuring manipulation capabilities of infants at home</article-title>. <source>Conf Proc IEEE Eng Med Biol Soc</source> <year>2015</year>;<volume>2015</volume>:<fpage>7390</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/EMBC.2015.7320099</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26737999</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R53"><text><SENT sid="74975" pm="."><plain><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sgandurra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cecchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serio</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Longitudinal study of unimanual actions and grasping forces during infancy</article-title>. <source>Infant Behav Dev</source> <year>2012</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.infbeh.2012.01.003</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22297129</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R54"><text><SENT sid="74976" pm="."><plain><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Serio</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cecchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boldrini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Instrumented toys for studying power and precision grasp forces in infants</article-title>. <source>Conf Proc IEEE Eng Med Biol Soc</source> <year>2011</year>;<volume>2011</volume>:<fpage>2017</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/IEMBS.2011.6090370</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22254731</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R55"><text><SENT sid="74977" pm="."><plain><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Comans</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mihala</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakzewski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>The cost-effectiveness of a web-based multimodal therapy for unilateral cerebral palsy: the Mitii randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source> <year>2017</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>756</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dmcn.13414</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28247406</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R56"><text><SENT sid="74978" pm="."><plain><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Valuation of the Child Health Utility 9D Index</article-title>. <source>Pharmacoeconomics</source> <year>2012</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>729</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/11599120-000000000-00000</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22788262</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R57"><text><SENT sid="74979" pm="."><plain><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ziviani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Randomized controlled trial of web-based multimodal therapy for unilateral cerebral palsy to improve occupational performance</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source> <year>2015</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>530</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dmcn.12705</pub-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25955443</pub-id></mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R58"><text><SENT sid="74980" pm="."><plain><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Move it to improve it (Mitii): study protocol of a randomised controlled trial of a novel web-based multimodal training program for children and adolescents with cerebral palsy</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source> <year>2013</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<elocation-id>e002853</elocation-id> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2013-002853</pub-id> </mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R59"><text><SENT sid="74981" pm="."><plain><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"> <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manetti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cecchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sgandurra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> <article-title>Early stage economic evaluation of caretoy system for early intervention in preterm infants at risk of neurodevelopmental disorders</article-title>. <source>Value Health</source> <year>2015</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>A358</fpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jval.2015.09.683</pub-id> </mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
