<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5551008</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4007</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-017-4007-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="60328" pm="."><plain>Equine skeletal muscle adaptations to exercise and training: evidence of differential regulation of autophagosomal and mitochondrial components </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>Kenneth</given-names></name><address><email>kenneth.bryan@ucd.ie</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>McGivney</surname><given-names>Beatrice A.</given-names></name><address><email>beatrice.mcgivney@plusvital.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Farries</surname><given-names>Gabriella</given-names></name><address><email>gabriella.farries@ucdconnect.ie</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McGettigan</surname><given-names>Paul A.</given-names></name><address><email>pmcget02@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McGivney</surname><given-names>Charlotte L.</given-names></name><address><email>charlotte.herdan@ucdconnect.ie</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gough</surname><given-names>Katie F.</given-names></name><address><email>katie.gough@ucd.ie</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>MacHugh</surname><given-names>David E.</given-names></name><address><email>david.machugh@ucd.ie</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>Lisa M.</given-names></name><address><email>lisa.katz@ucd.ie</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>Emmeline W.</given-names></name><address><email>emmeline.hill@ucd.ie</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0768 2743</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7886.1</institution-id><institution>UCD School of Agriculture and Food Science, </institution><institution>University College Dublin, </institution></institution-wrap>Belfield, D04 V1W8 Ireland </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0768 2743</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7886.1</institution-id><institution>UCD Conway Institute of Biomolecular and Biomedical Research, </institution><institution>University College Dublin, </institution></institution-wrap>Belfield, D04 V1W8 Ireland </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0768 2743</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7886.1</institution-id><institution>UCD School of Veterinary Medicine, </institution><institution>University College Dublin, </institution></institution-wrap>Belfield, D04 V1W8 Ireland </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>9</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>595</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="60329" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="60330" pm="."><plain>A single bout of exercise induces changes in gene expression in skeletal muscle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60331" pm="."><plain>Regular exercise results in an adaptive response involving changes in muscle architecture and biochemistry, and is an effective way to manage and prevent common human diseases such as obesity, cardiovascular disorders and type II diabetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60332" pm="."><plain>However, the biomolecular mechanisms underlying such responses still need to be fully elucidated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60333" pm="."><plain>Here we performed a transcriptome-wide analysis of skeletal muscle tissue in a large cohort of untrained Thoroughbred horses (<italic>n</italic> = 51) before and after a bout of high-intensity exercise and again after an extended period of training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60334" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that regular high-intensity exercise training primes the transcriptome for the demands of high-intensity exercise. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="60335" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par2"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="60336" pm="."><plain>An extensive set of genes was observed to be significantly differentially regulated in response to a single bout of high-intensity exercise in the untrained cohort (3241 genes) and following multiple bouts of high-intensity exercise training over a six-month period (3405 genes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60337" pm="."><plain>Approximately one-third of these genes (1025) and several biological processes related to energy metabolism were common to both the exercise and training responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60338" pm="."><plain>We then developed a novel network-based computational analysis pipeline to test the hypothesis that these transcriptional changes also influence the contextual molecular interactome and its dynamics in response to exercise and training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60339" pm="."><plain>The contextual network analysis identified several important hub genes, including the autophagosomal-related gene <italic>GABARAPL1</italic>, and dynamic functional modules, including those enriched for mitochondrial respiratory chain complexes I and V, that were differentially regulated and had their putative interactions ‘re-wired’ in the exercise and/or training responses. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="60340" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par3"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="60341" pm="."><plain>Here we have generated for the first time, a comprehensive set of genes that are differentially expressed in Thoroughbred skeletal muscle in response to both exercise and training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60342" pm="."><plain>These data indicate that consecutive bouts of high-intensity exercise result in a priming of the skeletal muscle transcriptome for the demands of the next exercise bout. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60343" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, this may also lead to an extensive ‘re-wiring’ of the molecular interactome in both exercise and training and include key genes and functional modules related to autophagy and the mitochondrion. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="60344" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="60345" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12864-017-4007-9) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Equine</kwd><kwd>Skeletal muscle</kwd><kwd>Transcriptome</kwd><kwd>Exercise</kwd><kwd>Training</kwd><kwd>RNAseq</kwd><kwd>Functional module</kwd><kwd>Network analysis</kwd><kwd>Mitochondria</kwd><kwd>Autophagy</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001602</institution-id><institution>Science Foundation Ireland</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>11/PI/1166</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>Emmeline W.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="60346" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par30"><text><SENT sid="60347" pm="."><plain>Equine athletes have a genetic heritage that has been influenced by millions of years of evolution as grazing animals on prairie and steppe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60348" pm="."><plain>More recently, centuries of intense selective breeding in the Thoroughbred horse has led to the refinement of multiple physiological adaptations for athletic performance, resulting in an ideal model of a natural athlete for the investigation of exercise and adaptive training responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60349" pm="."><plain>Equine skeletal muscle shows a remarkable ability to adapt to physical exercise and long-term training; however, the genetic, epigenetic and molecular changes underlying these adaptive responses have yet to be fully elucidated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60350" pm="."><plain>Cyclic muscle contraction during repeated bouts of exercise over time (training or conditioning) is known to induce physiological adaptation in skeletal muscle, which exhibits remarkable plasticity in structure and function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60351" pm="."><plain>In equine athletes, training generally leads to an increase in muscle mass and aerobic capacity but the specific response, in terms of muscle fibre type and metabolic adaptation, depends mainly on the type of training regime (e.g. endurance or sprint type exercise) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], nutrition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] and an individual’s specific genetic potential [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60352" pm="."><plain>Principal genetic determinants of muscle fibre type include the myostatin gene (<italic>MSTN</italic>), which encodes a ligand of the TGF-beta receptor family that negatively regulates muscle growth, and that has been associated with strength and performance in both human [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] and equine athletes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60353" pm="."><plain>Sequence polymorphisms in the equine <italic>MSTN</italic> gene are highly predictive of optimal race distance in Thoroughbred horses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60354" pm="."><plain>Horses homozygous for the ‘sprint’ variant (C-allele or SINE insertion) have 12.5% more type <italic>2X</italic> myofibers than horses with the alternate allele [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60355" pm="."><plain>Following a period of training in Thoroughbred horses an increase in type <italic>2A</italic> and a concurrent decrease in type <italic>2X</italic> fibres along with an overall increase in muscle mass is typically observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60356" pm="."><plain>As type <italic>2A</italic> fibres can sustain high power outputs for longer than <italic>2X</italic> the functional implication of this is increased endurance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60357" pm="."><plain>Concurrent with changes in muscle mass and fibre type, exercise training elicits metabolic adaptations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60358" pm="."><plain>This primarily involves an increased capacity for oxidative phosphorylation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], increased mitochondrial density [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] and a shift toward oxidizing proportionately more fats and less glucose during exercise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par31"><text><SENT sid="60359" pm="."><plain>It has been hypothesized that the adaptive response to training is caused by incremental changes in gene expression following a single bout of exercise, which will “accumulate” during the traing period leading to new baseline levels of gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60360" pm="."><plain>This would result in a significant overlap in the exercise and training response genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60361" pm="."><plain>The alternate hypothesis is that transient differential expression of genes in response to exercise precedes adaptive changes through secondary mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60362" pm="."><plain>In this case little overlap would be seen between the exercise and training response genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60363" pm="."><plain>While there is an assumption that “accumulative” changes play a major role in the adaptive response no study has clearly demonstrated this. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60364" pm="."><plain>In human skeletal muscle the mRNA expression of key transcription factors is transiently induced by exercise training leading to increases in downstream transcriptional and mitochondrial proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60365" pm="."><plain>In equine athletes it has been shown that a single bout of high-intensity exercise consisting of an incremental step-test to fatigue elicits a modulation of the expression of genes involved in metabolism and muscle hypertrophy, signatures of endurance and resistance exercise, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60366" pm="."><plain>Following a period of training the basal levels of genes related to the mitochondrion, oxidative phosphorylation and fatty acid metabolism have been shown to be significantly upregulated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], supporting the hypothesis that training may cause a transcriptional reprogramming of the muscle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par32"><text><SENT sid="60367" pm="."><plain>A range of approaches has been taken to better understand the molecular adaptations to exercise and training with many factors needing to be considered for appropriate experimental design [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60368" pm="."><plain>Generally, the analysis of the impact of an experimental variable (e.g. environment, treatment, mutation, disease etc.) on a cell, tissue or organism results in a list of statistically significant response variables, such as genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60369" pm="."><plain>It is common, owing to the modular architecture of biological systems, to then examine this list for statistical over-representation of known functional modules (e.g. pathways or complexes) to assist biological interpretation (often referred to pathway enrichment analysis, or similar). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60370" pm="."><plain>Although valuable, such analysis is confined by the limits of the current knowledge of functional modules which tends to be biased [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] and incomplete [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60371" pm="."><plain>However, less supervised approaches that are informed more by the similarity of entity (i.e. gene) behaviour, are more open to uncovering unknown or context-specific gene relationships [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par33"><text><SENT sid="60372" pm="."><plain>The function of most genes, or gene products (proteins, miRNA, lncRNAs, etc.), can only be carried out in combination with other biomolecules as part of a functional module [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60373" pm="."><plain>Therefore, to fully elucidate the functional relevance of a set of genes we must also model the related set of molecular interactions and their dynamics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60374" pm="."><plain>There are several methods for direct detection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] or inferral [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>] of molecular interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60375" pm="."><plain>Once determined, the set of molecular interactions may be modelled as a network of nodes (genes) and edges (interactions) and interrogated with an extensive toolbox of established network analysis methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60376" pm="."><plain>Common metrics include the centrality indices ‘degree’ and ‘betweeness’, which are used to measure the importance of individual network nodes in terms of the local connections and their network wide influence respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60377" pm="."><plain>In the context of biomolecular interaction networks, these ‘hub’ and ‘bottleneck’ nodes tend to be fundamentally important to the behaviour of the network [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] and indeed to the biological process, cell, tissue or organism as a whole [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60378" pm="."><plain>Other higher level node grouping or clustering methods, such as ‘community detection’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], allow modelling of the underlying functional modules (e.g. complex or pathway) in a particular molecular interaction network [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60379" pm="."><plain>Other methods extend this concept further to analyse multi-state, or ‘dynamic’ networks recorded over various time points or experimental treatments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par34"><text><SENT sid="60380" pm="."><plain>Although hundreds of thousands of protein-protein interactions (PPIs) have been recorded across many organisms, cell types and experimental conditions and made publicly available [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>], proteome-scale detection of PPIs still remains beyond the budget and expertise of most researchers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60381" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide gene expression analysis, however, is now relatively affordable and commonplace. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60382" pm="."><plain>Thus, high-throughput gene expression data generated for an experimental context is often integrated with the universal set of known molecular interactions (i.e. the global interactome) to infer putative contextual molecular interaction networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60383" pm="."><plain>However, most implementations of this approach only attempt to predict the contextual state of the nodes in the network (e.g. the set of genes expressed in or associated with the condition of interest) and include all associated PPIs as edges, regardless of the experimental conditions or cell types in which they were detected, which is clearly a gross over-simplification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60384" pm="."><plain>It has been recognized for over a decade that genes that exhibit highly correlated co-expression profiles, as determined by Pearson’s correlation coefficient for example, often interact within the same biological module [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60385" pm="."><plain>This raises the prospect of using gene expression information to also infer the contextual state of the edges in a molecular interaction network but this in itself is hampered by exceedingly high false positive rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60386" pm="."><plain>Here we have developed a novel pipeline to integrate contextual information, derived from gene expression data, with publicly available PPI data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] to predict both the nodes and edges in the contextual PPI network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60387" pm="."><plain>Ultimately, this more refined contextual model should lead to an improved elucidation of the interactions and functional modules that are active in each of the experimental conditions considered in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par35"><text><SENT sid="60388" pm="."><plain>In summary, the aim of this study was to investigate changes in the transcriptome of the skeletal muscle of untrained Thoroughbred horses (UR) in response to a single bout of high-intensity sprint exercise (UE), and following an exercise conditioning (training) regime (TR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60389" pm="."><plain>We hypothesised that regular bouts of high-intensity exercise training would prime the transcriptome of Thoroughbred skeletal muscle for the demands of the next exercise bout. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60390" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, by integrating this information on contextual transcriptional changes with known molecular interactions, we also tested the hypothesis that these transcriptional adaptions may lead to a ‘re-wiring’ of the molecular interactome in response to high-intensity exercise and training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60391" pm="."><plain>Lastly we have demonstrated that a refined computational network-based approach, which considers both context-specific nodes (genes) and edges (interactions), has the potential to uncover novel features indicative of specific biological processes when compared to standard supervised approaches. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="60392" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="60393" pm="."><plain>Study cohort </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par36"><text><SENT sid="60394" pm="."><plain>University College Dublin Animal Research Ethics Committee approval, a licence from the Department of Health (B100/3525) and explicit owner/trainer informed consent were obtained for the use of all horses and procedures in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par37"><text><SENT sid="60395" pm="."><plain>The study cohort comprised a subset of Thoroughbred horses, trained for Flat racing at a single training establishment under the management of a single trainer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60396" pm="."><plain>The UR cohort comprised of yearling Thoroughbred horses (<italic>n</italic> = 51; 23 males and 28 females; 19.5 ± 1.5 months old) in submaximal training prior to entering sprint training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60397" pm="."><plain>The UE cohort consisted of the same group of horses undertaking their first or second ‘work day’ (WD, high-intensity sprint exercise simulating a race) on an all-weather gallop. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60398" pm="."><plain>The TR cohort consisted of horses at the end of the racing season following approximately six months of sprint training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60399" pm="."><plain>All horses in this group had achieved “race fitness” with an average of 15.1 ± 9.1 SD WDs (range 6–43). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60400" pm="."><plain>Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> summarises details of sampling and physiological measurements.<SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Cohort information and experimental conditions</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2"/><th>Untrained Rest</th><th>Untrained Exercise</th><th>Trained Rest</th></tr><tr><th>(UR)</th><th>(UE)</th><th>(TR)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td> <italic>n</italic> </td><td>22</td><td>17</td><td>22</td></tr><tr><td>Male</td><td>8</td><td>8</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td>Female</td><td>16</td><td>9</td><td>16</td></tr><tr><td>Mean age in days (Range)</td><td>590 (513–673)</td><td>765 (649–896)</td><td>947.6 (884–1051)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4">Exercise parameters (WD1):</td></tr><tr><td>  <italic>-Mean Peak Velocity (m/s)</italic> </td><td>.</td><td>16.2 (14–17.1)</td><td>.</td></tr><tr><td>  <italic>-Mean Peak Heart Rate (bpm)</italic> </td><td>.</td><td>224 (212–233)</td><td>.</td></tr><tr><td>  <italic>-Mean Peak Plasma Lactate (mmol/l)</italic> </td><td>.</td><td>26.7 (20.8–32.2)</td><td>.</td></tr><tr><td>Mean sub-maximal training weeks prior to sampling (canter)</td><td>0</td><td>4.7 (1.6–13.1)</td><td>27.7 (10.1–47.0)</td></tr><tr><td>Mean work days prior to sampling:</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>15.1 (6–43)</td></tr><tr><td>  <italic>n = 0</italic> </td><td>22</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>  <italic>n = 1</italic> </td><td>0</td><td>17</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>  <italic>n &gt; 1</italic> </td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>22</td></tr><tr><td>  <italic>&gt; 5 n ≤ 11</italic> </td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td>  <italic>&gt; 10 n ≤ 20</italic> </td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>9</td></tr><tr><td>  <italic>n &gt; 20</italic> </td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Number of individuals (<italic>n</italic>), males and females, and mean age are given for experimental cohorts Untrained Rest (UR), Untrained Exercise (UE) and Trained Rest (TR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60401" pm="."><plain>Details of exercise and training regimens for each Thoroughbred cohort prior to sampling day are also shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60402" pm="."><plain>Sampling of the Untrained Exercise (UE) cohort was performed ~4 h post-exercise on the first work day (WD1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60403" pm="."><plain>Sampling of the Trained Rest (TR) cohort was performed after an average of ~15 WDs over a six-month training period</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="60404" pm="."><plain>Tissue sampling time-points </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par38"><text><SENT sid="60405" pm="."><plain>All resting skeletal muscle samples (see protocol below) were collected between 7:30 am and 11:30 am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60406" pm="."><plain>UE samples were collected from a subset of the UR horses (<italic>n</italic> = 46; 23 males and 23 females; 24.6 ± 2.3 months old) approximately four hours following high-intensity exercise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60407" pm="."><plain>The study cohort comprised horses in active race training and therefore the number of biopsies that could be sampled was limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60408" pm="."><plain>A single 4 h post-exercise time-point was selected that represented the time previously shown to have the greatest number of differentially expressed genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] and the greatest magnitude of effect on transcripts in equine skeletal muscle post-exercise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60409" pm="."><plain>In addition, the time point was selected to avoid potential disruption to routine activity on the yard. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par39"><text><SENT sid="60410" pm="."><plain>TR samples were collected at rest following a sprint training period of approximately six months from a subset of the UR horses (<italic>n</italic> = 22; eight males, and 14 females; 31.1 ± 1.5 months old). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60411" pm="."><plain>Only horses that were sampled as part of the UR cohort and had a matching sample in the UE or the TR cohort were used in subsequent analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60412" pm="."><plain>The final experimental cohorts contained <italic>n</italic> = 22 (UR), <italic>n</italic> = 17 (UE) and <italic>n</italic> = 22 (TR) horses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60413" pm="."><plain>Summary statistics are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="60414" pm="."><plain>Exercise and training protocols </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par40"><text><SENT sid="60415" pm="."><plain>Horses exercised six days per week, with gradual introduction and increased frequency of WDs, following which horses entered competitive racing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60416" pm="."><plain>Training was modified based on soundness, fitness and aptitude, with all decisions made by a single trainer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60417" pm="."><plain>Prior to exercise, each horse was fitted with a heart rate (HR) telemetry system (Polar Equine S810i heart rate monitor system) and global positioning system (GPS, GPSports Systems SPI10, Canberra, Australia) which recorded speed, HR and exercise distance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60418" pm="."><plain>The WD exercise protocol was as follows: horses were warmed-up on a horse walker for 10 min (walk and trot) and then walked under saddle for 5–10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60419" pm="."><plain>On the gallop, horses walked for 300 m, trotted for 700 m, walked for approximately 100 m and then galloped up to a maximum velocity for approximately 500-800 m (average distance of 698.8 ± 223.9 m). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="60420" pm="."><plain>Biopsy sampling and RNA sequencing protocols </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par41"><text><SENT sid="60421" pm="."><plain>Percutaneous needle muscle biopsies (approx. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60422" pm="."><plain>300 mg) were obtained from the ventral compartment of the middle gluteal muscle from standing unsedated horses using a previously described method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>] and preserved in RNA<italic>later</italic> (Thermo Fisher, Massachusetts, United States). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60423" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was extracted from approximately 70 mg tissue, using a protocol combining TRIzol reagent (Thermo Fisher, Massachusetts, United States), DNase treatment (RNase free DNase) (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) and RNeasy Mini-Kit (Qiagen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60424" pm="."><plain>RNA was quantified using a Nano Drop ND1000 spectrophotometer V 3.5.27 and RNA quality and purity were assessed using the 18S/28S ratio and RNA integrity number (RIN) on an Agilent Bioanalyser with the RNA 6000 Nano LabChip kit6 (Agilent, Cork, Ireland). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60425" pm="."><plain>The RNA isolated from UR, UE and TR samples had an average RIN of 8.1 (7.2–9.3), 8.2 (7–9.1) and 8.1 (5.4–8.6), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60426" pm="."><plain>RNA sequencing was performed by the Research Technology Support Facility Michigan State University. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60427" pm="."><plain>Indexed, strand-specific Illumina sequencing libraries were prepared using the TruSeq Stranded mRNA Library Preparation Kit LT (Illumina, San Diego, United States). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60428" pm="."><plain>Libraries were pooled with ten indexed libraries per pool and sequenced on an Illumina HiSeq 2500 using Rapid Run flow cell and reagents (Illumina). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60429" pm="."><plain>Dual lane loading was employed, meaning a single pool was loaded across both lanes of the flow cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60430" pm="."><plain>Each pool was sequenced on one flow cell (two lanes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60431" pm="."><plain>Sequencing was performed in a 2 × 100 bp paired end (PE100) format. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60432" pm="."><plain>Sequence data was demultiplexed and converted to FastQ format files. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="60433" pm="."><plain>RNA-seq data pre-processing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par42"><text><SENT sid="60434" pm="."><plain><italic>FASTQC</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>] was used to assess sequencing quality and <italic>STAR</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>] was used to align reads to the horse reference genome (Ensembl release 62). <italic>SAMtools</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>] was used to convert files from Sam to sorted indexed Bam format and <italic>featureCounts</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>] was used to assign reads to exons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60435" pm="."><plain>The correlation between lanes (two technical replicates) for each sample was checked to ensure a correlation of &gt;99% prior to merging data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60436" pm="."><plain>Differentially expressed (DE) genes were identified using the <italic>limma</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>] R package. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60437" pm="."><plain>Count data was scale normalised using the <italic>calcNormFactors</italic> function from the <italic>EdgeR</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>] package. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60438" pm="."><plain>The voom transformation was applied to the normalised data and a linear model was fitted to the data using the horse as a blocking factor to take into account the pair effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60439" pm="."><plain>The empirical Bayes method was used to calculate <italic>P</italic> values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60440" pm="."><plain>Ensembl IDs of small RNAs (BioMart biotypes: <italic>rRNA, snRNA, misc_RNA, snoRNA, miRNA</italic>) were first removed from the dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60441" pm="."><plain>Differentially expressed (DE) genes were defined as those that were significantly upregulated or downregulated (Benjamini-Hochberg corrected <italic>P</italic>-value &lt;0.05) and that were upregulated or downregulated by at least 25% between the two cohorts being compared (i.e. UE versus UR, TR versus UR). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="60442" pm="."><plain>Statistical over-representation analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par43"><text><SENT sid="60443" pm="."><plain>To facilitate a complete downstream analysis pipeline, equine Ensembl IDs were first uniquely mapped (one-to-one relationship only) to their better annotated human orthologs, retrieved from the BioMart database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60444" pm="."><plain>All subsequent analyses were performed with these human orthologs and their annotations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60445" pm="."><plain>Over-representation of the gene ontology (GO) categories [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>] and KEGG and Reactome pathway annotations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>] was performed in an automated manner using the <italic>RDAVIDWebService</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60446" pm="."><plain>The expected or <italic>background</italic> gene list used in the over-representation analysis included all genes that had a one-to-one mapping with human orthologs and were expressed in skeletal muscle during at least one time point (<italic>n =</italic> 14,688). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60447" pm="."><plain>The statistical significance of gene category over-representation was calculated based on the DAVID software EASE score (<italic>P</italic>-value based on a modified Fisher Exact t-test) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>] and corrected for multiple testing using the Benjamini-Hochberg step-down correction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="60448" pm="."><plain>Construction of putative contextual molecular interaction networks </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par44"><text><SENT sid="60449" pm="."><plain>Two dynamic gene interaction networks were constructed, the first to model the molecular interactions before and after exercise in untrained horses (UR vs. UE) and the second to model the training response (UR vs. TR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60450" pm="."><plain>In each case the set of nodes (genes) in the dynamic network were confined to those that had been found to be differentially expressed in the respective response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60451" pm="."><plain>An edge (gene interaction) was drawn between nodes (genes) <italic>a</italic> and <italic>b</italic> if (i) there was any previous experimental evidence of a molecular interaction and (ii) if their expression levels were found to be significantly correlated in the respective cohort (i.e. UR, UE or TR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60452" pm="."><plain>Experimentally validated protein-protein interactions (PPIs) for human, that were annotated to the IMEx (International Molecular Exchange consortium) standard [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>], were then obtained (12–09-2016) from the <italic>IntAct</italic> database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] using the <italic>PSICQUIC</italic> web-service [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>] (see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> for the specific query used). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60453" pm="."><plain>These interactions were recorded across many cell types, tissues and experimental conditions and represent the global set of all possible interactions in human as defined by <italic>IntAct</italic> DB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60454" pm="."><plain>Gene expression correlations were calculated across all samples within the relevant cohort (i.e. UR, UE or TR) using Spearman’s rank correlation and only positive, statistically significant correlations (i.e. greater than the minimum critical value given the number of samples in the cohort) were used to generate contextual edges. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="60455" pm="."><plain>Network analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par45"><text><SENT sid="60456" pm="."><plain>Network analysis and visualization was implemented in the R statistical programming language and primarily used tools from the <italic>igraph</italic> package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60457" pm="."><plain>The most ‘influential’ nodes (genes) in each network were determined based on both degree (edge number) and betweeness (number of shortest paths that pass through that node) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60458" pm="."><plain>These metrics highlight the nodes (genes) that have the most influence on information flow in the network at a local (i.e. hubs) and global (i.e. bottlenecks) level respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60459" pm="."><plain>Hubs are scored based simply on node <italic>degree</italic> (number of edges attached to a node) and bottlenecks are scored based on the node <italic>betweeness</italic> (number of shortest paths that pass through a node). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60460" pm="."><plain>The modular or systems level architecture of a network was interrogated in an unsupervised manner (i.e. based only on network topology) by partitioning the nodes (genes) into groups such that the edge (gene interaction) density was higher within groups than between. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60461" pm="."><plain>This was performed using the <italic>fastgreedy</italic> community detection method, which also utilizes edge weights (based on expression correlation in this case) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] and was also implemented via <italic>igraph</italic>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60462" pm="."><plain>In practice, we retained only non-trivial clusters (i.e. containing two or more genes) and validated these clusters (putative functional modules) by functional enrichment analysis based on pathways and GO terms (implemented as before). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="60463" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="60464" pm="."><plain>Identification of genes and known functional categories associated with the exercise and training responses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par46"><text><SENT sid="60465" pm="."><plain>We applied both a fold-change and multiple test correction cut-off to identify differentially expressed genes in the exercise (UR vs. UE) and training (UR vs. TR) responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60466" pm="."><plain>We identified 3241 genes that were significantly (BH-corrected <italic>P</italic>-value &lt; 0.05) differentially expressed (&gt;1.25-fold) and mapped uniquely to human orthologs in the exercise response (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60467" pm="."><plain>A similar number of genes (3405) were associated with the training response (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60468" pm="."><plain>Approximately one third of the exercise response genes (1025) were also associated with the training response and 95% of genes were expressed in the same direction (relative to UR) in both responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60469" pm="."><plain>There were 2216 and 2380 genes uniquely associated with the exercise or training response respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par47"><text><SENT sid="60470" pm="."><plain>To attempt to uncover the underlying biological processes involved in the adaptation of skeletal muscle to exercise and training, the gene lists derived from differentially expressed transcripts were assessed for statistical over-representation of known functional modules based on five functional annotation schemas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60471" pm="."><plain>Two schemas related to biological pathways (curated by KEGG [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>] and Reactome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>] databases) and three related to <italic>Cellular Component</italic> (CC), <italic>Molecular Function</italic> (MF) and <italic>Biological Process</italic> (BP) gene ontology (GO) sub-categories [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par48"><text><SENT sid="60472" pm="."><plain>For the exercise response gene list several KEGG and Reactome pathways were found to be significantly over-represented and were observed to fall into one of three general themes, namely: energy metabolism (<italic>Integration of energy metabolism: P =</italic> 4.97 × 10<sup>−11</sup> <italic>, Diabetes pathways: P =</italic> 3.57 × 10<sup>−06</sup>, <italic>Oxidative phosphorylation: P =</italic> 0.0047 and <italic>Pyruvate Metabolism and TCA Cycle: P =</italic> 0.0204); muscle contraction (<italic>Muscle contraction: P =</italic> 3.57 × 10<sup>−06</sup> <italic>, Cardiac muscle contraction: P =</italic> 0.0222) and hemostasis (<italic>Hemostasis: P =</italic> 3.76 × 10<sup>−05</sup> <italic>, Signaling by PDGF: P =</italic> 0.0167). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60473" pm="."><plain>There was also significant enrichment for several pathways related to neurodegenerative diseases (<italic>Alzheimer’s Disease: P =</italic> 4.95 × 10<sup>−06</sup> <italic>, Huntington’s Disease:</italic> 9.15 × 10<sup>−06</sup> <italic>and Parkinson’s Disease:</italic> 2.75 × 10<sup>−05</sup>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60474" pm="."><plain>Statistical enrichment was also observed for similar themes for the GO <italic>Biological Process</italic> sub-category (e.g. <italic>Cellular respiration: P =</italic> 0.0004<italic>, Muscle contraction: P =</italic> 0.0004<italic>, Vasculature development: P =</italic> 0.0307). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60475" pm="."><plain>GO term enrichment also provided more refined annotation relating the <italic>Cellular Component</italic> sub-category (e.g. <italic>Mitochondrion: P =</italic> 4.14 × 10<sup>−15</sup> <italic>, Contractile fibre: P = 6</italic>.40 × 10<sup>−11</sup> <italic>, Mitochondrial respiratory chain: P =</italic> 7.41 × 10<sup>−05</sup>) and the <italic>Molecular Function</italic> sub-category (e.g. <italic>Cytoskeletal protein binding: P =</italic> 1.41 × 10<sup>−06</sup> <italic>, Actin binding: P =</italic> 0.0006<italic>).</italic> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par49"><text><SENT sid="60476" pm="."><plain>The functional modules related to muscle contraction were the most downregulated modules associated with the exercise response gene list. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60477" pm="."><plain>For example, the largest over-represented module, <italic>Contractile fibre,</italic> contained 56 genes, which were mostly (44/56) downregulated (mean: −1.52-fold) in exercise relative to the untrained rest cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60478" pm="."><plain>These muscle contraction related modules were also found to be unique to the exercise response (i.e. this theme was not found to be associated with the training response, see below). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60479" pm="."><plain>The top twenty most significantly over-represented functional modules in the exercise response gene list are provided in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S3 and illustrated via five barcharts (one per annotation schema) in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.<SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Cellular functions of the exercise response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60480" pm="."><plain>Bar charts showing over-representation of functional categories (described by KEGG and REACTOME pathways and Gene Ontology: <italic>Biological Process</italic>, <italic>Molecular Function</italic> and <italic>Cellular Component</italic>) for the list of genes (<italic>n</italic> = 3241) that showed statistically significant differential expression, of at least +/− 1.25-fold, between the muscle tissue (<italic>gluteus medius</italic>) from the untrained rest (UR) and the untrained exercise (UE) Thoroughbred cohorts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60481" pm="."><plain>Bars represent the most significant functional modules (up to 20) for each of the five annotation schemas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60482" pm="."><plain>Bar height represents statistical significance (<italic>−log</italic> <sub><italic>10</italic></sub> transformed Benjamini-Hochberg (B-H) Corrected <italic>P</italic>-value) of the over-representation, based on the EASE-score (conservative Fisher Exact t-test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60483" pm="."><plain>Bar color represents the mean differential expression (log<sub>2</sub>(UE/UR) for the genes in this module (see color key). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60484" pm="."><plain>Category name, ID and size (number category genes in gene list/category size) are given above each bar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60485" pm="."><plain>For example it can be seen that the fourth most significant Gene Ontology:<italic>Biological Process</italic> is ‘Cellular respiration’ and that it is one of the most up-regulated functional categories on average (red color) and that 39 out of the 97 genes assigned to this category are differentially expressed between UE and UR cohorts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60486" pm="."><plain>Full results are provided in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S3</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2017_4007_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par50"><text><SENT sid="60487" pm="."><plain>This analysis was also repeated for the exercise-specific subset of 2216 genes (i.e. exclusively associated with the exercise response relative to the training response gene list). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60488" pm="."><plain>KEGG pathways <italic>Dilated cardiomyopathy</italic> and <italic>Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</italic> remained marginally statistically significantly over-represented (<italic>P</italic> = 0.0252 and <italic>P =</italic> 0.0472 resp.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60489" pm="."><plain>Reactome pathways <italic>Muscle contraction</italic> (<italic>P =</italic> 1.52 × 10<sup>−05</sup>) and <italic>Hemostasis</italic> (<italic>P =</italic> 0.0031) and <italic>Transmembrane transport of small molecules</italic> (<italic>P =</italic> 0.0034) also remained significantly over-represented. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60490" pm="."><plain>Significant enrichment for the <italic>Lysosome</italic> (<italic>P =</italic> 0.0437) pathway, which was not found in the full exercise response gene list, was also observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60491" pm="."><plain>Several gene ontology sub-category terms also remained statistically significant, such as <italic>Cytoskeletal binding</italic> (<italic>P =</italic> 4.32 × 10<sup>−05</sup>), <italic>Contractile fibre</italic> (<italic>P =</italic> 1.12 × 10<sup>−06</sup>) and <italic>Membrane lipid metabolic process</italic> (<italic>P =</italic> 0.0057<italic>).</italic> The top twenty most significantly over-represented functional modules for this exercise-specific gene list are given in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S4 and illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.<SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Cellular functions of the exercise-specific response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60492" pm="."><plain>Bar charts showing over-representation of functional categories (described by KEGG and REACTOME pathways and Gene Ontology: <italic>Biological Process</italic>, <italic>Molecular Function</italic> and <italic>Cellular Component</italic>) for the list of genes (<italic>n</italic> = 2216) that showed statistically significant differential expression, of at least +/− 1.25-fold, between the muscle tissue (<italic>gluteus medius</italic>) from the untrained rest (UR) and the untrained exercise (UE) but not the trained rest (TR) Thoroughbred cohorts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60493" pm="."><plain>Bars represent the most significant functional modules (up to 20) for each of the five annotation schemas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60494" pm="."><plain>Bar height represents statistical significance (<italic>−log</italic> <sub><italic>10</italic></sub> transformed Benjamini-Hochberg (B-H) Corrected <italic>P</italic>-value) of the over-representation, based on the EASE-score (conservative Fisher Exact t-test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60495" pm="."><plain>Bar color represents the mean differential expression (log<sub>2</sub>(UE/UR) for the genes in this module (see color key). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60496" pm="."><plain>Category name, ID and size (number category genes in gene list/category size) are given above each bar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60497" pm="."><plain>For example it can be seen that the most significant Reactome pathway is ‘Muscle contraction’ and that it is one of the most down-regulated functional categories on average (blue color) and that 16 out of the 31 genes assigned to this category are differentially expressed between UE and UR cohorts <italic>only</italic> (i.e. not differentially expressed between TR and UR cohorts). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60498" pm="."><plain>Full results are provided in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S4</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2017_4007_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par51"><text><SENT sid="60499" pm="."><plain>For the training response gene list (3405 genes) there was significant enrichment for several KEGG and Reactome pathways related to energy metabolism (e.g. <italic>Oxidative phosphorylation: P =</italic> 3.59 × 10<sup>−08</sup>, <italic>Citrate cycle P =</italic> 5.12 × 10<sup>−05</sup> <italic>, Integration of energy metabolism: P =</italic> 4.66 × 10<sup>−14</sup> <italic>, Diabetes pathways: P =</italic> 3.10 × 10<sup>−08</sup>, <italic>Pyruvate metabolism: P =</italic> 2.93 × 10<sup>−07</sup>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60500" pm="."><plain>Additionally, several KEGG and Reactome pathways related to signal transduction (e.g. <italic>Signaling by GPCR: P =</italic> 8.94 × 10<sup>−14</sup> <italic>, Olfactory transduction: P =</italic> 7.68 × 10<sup>−12</sup> <italic>, Neuroactive ligand-receptor interaction: P =</italic> 0.0001<italic>, Calcium signaling pathway: P =</italic> 0.0190<italic>, Signaling by FGFR: P =</italic> 0.0169 and <italic>Complement and coagulation cascades: P =</italic> 0.03) were also significantly over-represented in the training response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60501" pm="."><plain>There was also a significant enrichment for neurodegenerative disease associated KEGG pathways (e.g. <italic>Alzheimer’s Disease: P =</italic> 6.57 × 10<sup>−06</sup> <italic>, Huntington’s Disease</italic>: 4.5 × 10<sup>−05</sup> <italic>and Parkinson’s Disease:</italic> 2.56 × 10<sup>−13</sup>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60502" pm="."><plain>Gene ontology term analysis for the training response also revealed a highly significant over-representation of neurological processes (<italic>Neurological system process: P = 4</italic>.85 × 10<sup>−27</sup> <italic>, Cognition: P =</italic> 1.92 × 10<sup>−22</sup> <italic>, Sensory perception: P =</italic> 4.21 × 10<sup>−21</sup>) and the extracellular region (<italic>Extracellular region: P =</italic> 1.40 × 10<sup>−10</sup>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60503" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial related molecular functions and components were also significantly over-represented (<italic>Mitochondrial respiratory chain: P =</italic> 1.45 × 10<sup>−08</sup> <italic>, Mitochondrial inner membrane: P =</italic> 2.53 × 10<sup>−08</sup> <italic>, NADH dehydrogenase</italic>/ <italic>Respiratory chain complex I: P =</italic> 1.29 × 10<sup>−06</sup> <italic>, Mitochondrial proton-transporting ATP synthase complex: P =</italic> 0.0007) in the training response gene list. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60504" pm="."><plain>The top twenty most significantly over-represented functional modules for the training response are given in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S5 and illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>.<SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Cellular functions of the training response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60505" pm="."><plain>Bar charts showing over-representation of functional categories (described by KEGG and REACTOME pathways and Gene Ontology: <italic>Biological Process</italic>, <italic>Molecular Function</italic> and <italic>Cellular Component</italic>) for the list of genes (<italic>n</italic> = 3405) that showed statistically significant differential expression, of at least +/− 1.25-fold, between the muscle tissue (<italic>gluteus medius</italic>) from the untrained rest (UR) and the trained rest (TR) Thoroughbred cohorts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60506" pm="."><plain>Bars represent the most significant functional modules (up to 20) for each of the five annotation schemas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60507" pm="."><plain>Bar height represents statistical significance (<italic>−log</italic> <sub><italic>10</italic></sub> transformed Benjamini-Hochberg (B-H) Corrected <italic>P</italic>-value) of the over-representation, based on the EASE-score (conservative Fisher Exact t-test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60508" pm="."><plain>Bar color represents the mean differential expression (log<sub>2</sub>(TR/UR) for the genes in this module (see color key). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60509" pm="."><plain>Category name, ID and size (number category genes in gene list/category size) are given above each bar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60510" pm="."><plain>For example it can be seen that the most significant Gene Ontology:<italic>Biological Process</italic> is ‘Integration of energy metabolism’ and that this functional categories is up-regulated on average (orange color) and that 95 out of the 219 genes assigned to this category are differentially expressed between TR and UR cohorts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60511" pm="."><plain>Full results are provided in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S5</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2017_4007_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par52"><text><SENT sid="60512" pm="."><plain>This analysis was repeated for the training-specific subset of 2380 genes that were uniquely associated with the training response (relative to the exercise response gene list). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60513" pm="."><plain>This training-specific gene list was also enriched for both signalling and neurological related categories (e.g. <italic>Signalling by GPCR:P =</italic> 2.5 × 10<sup>−28</sup> <italic>, Neurological system process: P =</italic> 2.3 × 10<sup>−46</sup>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60514" pm="."><plain>The over-representation of the cellular component: <italic>Extracellular region</italic> was also highly significant (<italic>P =</italic> 1.90 × 10<sup>−16</sup>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60515" pm="."><plain>The top twenty most significantly over-represented functional modules for this training-specific subset are given in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S6 and illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>.<SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Cellular functions of the training-specific response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60516" pm="."><plain>Bar charts showing over-representation of functional categories (described by KEGG and REACTOME pathways and Gene Ontology: <italic>Biological Process</italic>, <italic>Molecular Function</italic> and <italic>Cellular Component</italic>) for the list of genes (<italic>n</italic> = 2380) that showed statistically significant differential expression, of at least +/− 1.25-fold, between the muscle tissue (<italic>gluteus medius</italic>) from the untrained rest (UR) and the trained rest (TR) but not the untrained exercise (UE) Thoroughbred cohorts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60517" pm="."><plain>Bars represent the most significant functional modules (up to 20) for each of the five annotation schemas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60518" pm="."><plain>Bar height represents statistical significance (<italic>−log</italic> <sub><italic>10</italic></sub> transformed Benjamini-Hochberg (B-H) Corrected <italic>P</italic>-value) of the over-representation, based on the EASE-score (conservative Fisher Exact T-Test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60519" pm="."><plain>Bar color represents the mean differential expression (log<sub>2</sub>(UE/UR) for the genes in this module (see color key). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60520" pm="."><plain>Category name, ID and size (number category genes in gene list/category size) are given above each bar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60521" pm="."><plain>For example it can be seen that the most significant Reactome pathway is ‘Signaling by GPCR’ (where GPCR = G protein-coupled receptors) and that it is one of the most up-regulated functional categories on average (orange color) and that 186 out of the 631 genes assigned to this category are differentially expressed between TR and UR cohorts <italic>only</italic> (i.e. not differentially expressed between UE and UR cohorts). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60522" pm="."><plain>Full results are provided in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S6</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2017_4007_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="60523" pm="."><plain>Prediction of molecular interaction networks and their ‘re-wiring’ in exercise and training </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par53"><text><SENT sid="60524" pm="."><plain>The functional relevance of a gene or gene list in a context can only be fully appreciated by also examining how the genes, or their products, interact in that context. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60525" pm="."><plain>We therefore attempted to reconstruct context-specific dynamic PPI networks by integrating our exercise and training response gene lists and per cohort co-expression correlations with the global set of experimentally validated PPIs as described by EBI’s <italic>IntAct</italic> Database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60526" pm="."><plain>First, two dynamic networks were constructed to model how the genes associated with the exercise and training responses may ‘interact’ in each of the experimental cohorts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60527" pm="."><plain>The set of genes (network nodes) in each dynamic interaction network was confined to those genes associated with that response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60528" pm="."><plain>The putative interactions (network edges) were inferred from the gene expression correlations in each experimental cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60529" pm="."><plain>The edges in each dynamic network had two states, the <italic>ground</italic> state, derived from the untrained rest (UR) cohort, and the <italic>active</italic> state, derived by either the exercise (UE) or trained (TR) cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60530" pm="."><plain>Edges were also weighted with cohort specific correlation coefficients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60531" pm="."><plain>To better model the putative contextual protein-protein interactions (PPIs) these correlation-based interaction networks were then rigorously pruned to remove edges with no supporting experimental PPI evidence, retrieved via EBI’s <italic>IntAct</italic> database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60532" pm="."><plain>An overview of this process is illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, where output networks (i)-(vi) reflect Figs. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, and further details are given in <italic>Methods</italic>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60533" pm="."><plain>The final putative dynamic PPI network for the exercise response contained 513 nodes (edgeless nodes were removed) and 514 edges in the untrained rest (UR) state, see Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6(a)</xref>, and 426 nodes and 390 edges in the exercise (UE) state, Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6(b)</xref>.<SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Pipeline for construction of putative dynamic PPI networks in the exercise and training responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60534" pm="."><plain>Each putative contextual PPI network is composed from nodes, <italic>V</italic>, (genes) and edges, <italic>E</italic>, (interactions) related to one of the experimental contexts (cohorts). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60535" pm="."><plain>For example, the putative PPI network for the exercise in the untrained rest state, <italic>(1): G = (V</italic> <sub><italic>UE,</italic></sub> <italic>E</italic> <sub><italic>UR</italic></sub> <italic>)</italic>, contains the nodes (genes) that are associated with exercise (V<sub>UE</sub>) and the edges (based on gene expression correlations) from the untrained rest (E<sub>UR</sub>) cohort that are also supported by known protein-protein interactions (PPIs) in the IntAct molecular interaction database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60536" pm="."><plain>This can be considered the ‘ground state’ of the dynamic exercise network and can be compared to the exercise ‘active state’, <italic>(2): G = (V</italic> <sub><italic>UE,</italic></sub> <italic>E</italic> <sub><italic>UE</italic></sub> <italic>)</italic>, or the sub-network that is exclusive to exercise, <italic>(3):G = (V</italic> <sub><italic>UE – TR</italic></sub> <italic>,E</italic> <sub><italic>UE</italic></sub> <italic>)</italic> to model how these putative PPI interactions might be re-wired in the exercise response and the exercise-specific response respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60537" pm="."><plain>Networks (1)–(3) are illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6(a)-(c)</xref> and networks (4)–(6) are illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7(a)-(c)</xref> </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2017_4007_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></SecTag> <SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Putative dynamic PPI network for the exercise response. <bold>a</bold> The putative PPI network for exercise rest or ‘ground state’ contains 513 nodes (genes), after edgeless nodes were removed, and 514 edges (interactions)(see also Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and <italic>Methods</italic>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60538" pm="."><plain>This network was partitioned by Newman’s <italic>fastgreedy</italic> community detection (based on network topology only and with no prior information relating to gene function) into forty-three communities or node ‘clusters’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60539" pm="."><plain>A subset of twenty-eight of these clusters had greater than two nodes (genes) and were found to be significantly enriched for at least one functional category (described by KEGG, Reactome or Gene Ontology). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60540" pm="."><plain>Node colour and shape (i.e. circle, square, up-pointing triangle and down-pointing triangle) signifies cluster membership (only functionally enriched cluster shown in legend). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60541" pm="."><plain>Node size is proportional to node ‘betweeness’ score, with the largest nodes ‘controlling’ the most network ‘traffic’ (along shortest paths). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60542" pm="."><plain>The top twenty ‘bottleneck’ nodes have white labels. <bold>b</bold> The network for the exercise state, which contains 426 nodes (genes), after edgeless nodes are removed, and 390 edges (interactions). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60543" pm="."><plain>Nodes (genes) are both up (‘+’ nodes) and down-regulated (‘-’ nodes) and ‘re-wired’ (loss/gain of edges) in the exercise response compared to the rest state depicted in (<bold>a</bold>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60544" pm="."><plain>Cluster membership from (<bold>a</bold>) is transposed onto (<bold>b</bold>) to highlight how each cluster changes in the exercise network state (i.e. common nodes are given the same colour and shape with new nodes depicted by <italic>uncoloured circles</italic>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60545" pm="."><plain>For example, it can be seen that Cluster 1 (<italic>red circles</italic>), which is most enriched for the ‘<italic>Contractile fiber’</italic> functional category becomes extensively fragmented into 10 (mostly two-node) clusters and most genes are down-regulated (19/26) signifying possible dysregulation of this functional modules in the exercise response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60546" pm="."><plain>Conversely we also see that the Cluster 6 (<italic>yellow circles</italic>), which is most enriched for ‘<italic>NADH dehydrogenase/ Mitochondrial respiratory chain complex I’</italic>, is mostly up-regulated and remains largely intact, signifying possible coordinated up-regulation of this functional module in the exercise response. <bold>c</bold> Depicts the sub-network of (<bold>b</bold>) whose nodes (genes) are exclusive to the exercise response (i.e. not associated with the training response)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2017_4007_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></SecTag> <SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Putative dynamic PPI network for the training response. <bold>a</bold> The putative PPI network for untrained or ‘ground state’ contains 199 nodes (genes), after edgeless nodes were removed, and 186 edges (interactions)(see also Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and <italic>Methods</italic>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60547" pm="."><plain>This network was partitioned by Newman’s <italic>fastgreedy</italic> community detection (based on network topology only and with no prior information relating to gene function) into forty-three communities or node ‘clusters’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60548" pm="."><plain>A subset of twenty-eight of these clusters had greater than two nodes (genes) and were found to be significantly enriched for at least one functional category (described by KEGG, Reactome or Gene Ontology). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60549" pm="."><plain>Node colour and shape (i.e. circle, square, up-pointing triangle and down-pointing triangle) signifies cluster membership (only functionally enriched cluster shown in legend). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60550" pm="."><plain>Node size is proportional to node ‘betweeness’ score, with the largest nodes ‘controlling’ the most network ‘traffic’ (along shortest paths). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60551" pm="."><plain>The top twenty ‘bottleneck’ nodes have white labels. <bold>b</bold> The network for the trained state, which contains 188 nodes (genes), after edgeless nodes are removed, and 176 edges (interactions). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60552" pm="."><plain>Nodes (genes) are both up (‘+’ nodes) and down-regulated (‘-’ nodes) and ‘re-wired’ (loss/gain of edges) in the training response compared to the untrained state depicted in (<bold>a</bold>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60553" pm="."><plain>Cluster membership from (<bold>a</bold>) is transposed onto (<bold>b</bold>) to highlight how each cluster changes in the trained network state (i.e. common nodes are given the same colour and shape with new nodes depicted by uncoloured circles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60554" pm="."><plain>For example, it can be seen that Cluster 2 (<italic>green circles</italic>), which is most enriched for the ‘<italic>ErbB signaling pathway/Signaling by PDGF’</italic> functional category becomes fragmented into 4 clusters and all visible genes (edgeless nodes are not depicted) are down-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60555" pm="."><plain>Conversely we see that the Cluster 1 (<italic>red circles</italic>), which is most enriched for ‘<italic>NADH dehydrogenase/ Mitochondrial respiratory chain complex I’</italic>, is mostly up-regulated and remains largely intact, signifying possible coordinated up-regulation of this functional module in the training response. <bold>c</bold> Depicts the sub-network of (<bold>b</bold>) whose nodes (genes) are exclusive to the training response (i.e. not associated with the exercise response)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2017_4007_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par54"><text><SENT sid="60556" pm="."><plain>In the exercise network the top twenty most influential genes, in terms of both <italic>degree</italic> and <italic>betweeness</italic> were identified (see Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60557" pm="."><plain>We found that the <italic>GABARAPL1</italic> gene <italic>(GABA type A receptor associated protein like 1)</italic>, which was upregulated (+1.49-fold; <italic>P</italic> = 6.5 × 10<sup>−12</sup>) in the exercise response, was the top hub and bottleneck in both the untrained rest (UR) and exercise (UE) network states. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60558" pm="."><plain>The edges of <italic>GABARAPL1</italic> were partially ‘re-wired’ with it gaining 14 edges, losing 22 and retaining 11 interactors in the exercise state relative to the rest state (see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Section 3.1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60559" pm="."><plain>We also observed that relative influence of other hub and bottleneck genes appeared to change between network states. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60560" pm="."><plain>For example, <italic>DNAJB</italic> (<italic>dnaj hsp40 member B1</italic>), <italic>FN1</italic> (<italic>fibronectin 1</italic>) and <italic>LIMA1</italic> (<italic>LIM domain and actin binding 1</italic>) all had a greater influence in the exercise network state than the rest state as determined by both betweenness rank (<italic>FN1</italic> from 12th to 2nd; <italic>LIMA1</italic> from 73rd to 5th; <italic>DNAJB</italic> from 174th to 3rd) and degree rank (<italic>FN1</italic> from 5th to 2nd; <italic>LIMA1</italic> from 40th to 3rd), see Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60561" pm="."><plain>The additional edges gained by <italic>DNAJB1</italic> in the exercise state included a new putative interaction with, <italic>GABARAPL1</italic>, which effectively boosts the network-wide influence (i.e. betweeness) of <italic>DNAJB1</italic> by proxy.<SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The top twenty hub (based on node degree, <italic>D</italic>) and bottleneck (based on node betweenness, <italic>B</italic>) genes in the Exercise Response network in the Untrained Rest (UR) and Untrained Exercise (UE) states</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="4">Untrained Rest</th><th colspan="4">Untrained Exercise</th><th colspan="4">Unique to Untrained Exercise</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td> <italic>Hubs</italic> </td><td> <italic>D</italic> </td><td> <italic>Bottlenecks</italic> </td><td> <italic>B</italic> </td><td> <italic>Hubs</italic> </td><td> <italic>D</italic> </td><td> <italic>Bottlenecks</italic> </td><td> <italic>B</italic> </td><td> <italic>Hubs</italic> </td><td> <italic>D</italic> </td><td> <italic>Bottlenecks</italic> </td><td> <italic>B</italic> </td></tr><tr><td>GABARAPL1</td><td>33</td><td>GABARAPL1</td><td>20,436</td><td>GABARAPL1</td><td>25</td><td>GABARAPL1</td><td>6905</td><td>FN1</td><td>15</td><td>FN1</td><td>888</td></tr><tr><td>TCTN3</td><td>21</td><td>ESR1</td><td>18,589</td><td>FN1</td><td>19</td><td>FN1</td><td>6881</td><td>LIMA1</td><td>11</td><td>LIMA1</td><td>826</td></tr><tr><td>NDUFA6</td><td>19</td><td>TRIM54</td><td>13,553</td><td>LIMA1</td><td>16</td><td>DNAJB1</td><td>6327</td><td>APOA1</td><td>5</td><td>FLNB</td><td>756</td></tr><tr><td>SIRT4</td><td>18</td><td>GNB4</td><td>13,514</td><td>NDUFA6</td><td>16</td><td>CDC37</td><td>5983</td><td>TRIM54</td><td>5</td><td>APOA1</td><td>394</td></tr><tr><td>FN1</td><td>16</td><td>CDK18</td><td>13,394</td><td>CDC37</td><td>14</td><td>LIMA1</td><td>2799</td><td>TMEM216</td><td>5</td><td>CAV1</td><td>346</td></tr><tr><td>GRB2</td><td>16</td><td>CDC37</td><td>10,875</td><td>MYO18A</td><td>13</td><td>TRIM54</td><td>2444</td><td>ESR1</td><td>5</td><td>ESR1</td><td>246</td></tr><tr><td>NDUFA2</td><td>15</td><td>FLNB</td><td>10,484</td><td>TMEM216</td><td>11</td><td>HSPH1</td><td>2338</td><td>BAG3</td><td>4</td><td>TMEM216</td><td>210</td></tr><tr><td>FASTKD3</td><td>15</td><td>AHNAK</td><td>10,125</td><td>MYO19</td><td>10</td><td>NR4A1</td><td>2210</td><td>TCTN3</td><td>4</td><td>TNS3</td><td>207</td></tr><tr><td>ESR1</td><td>10</td><td>MYO18A</td><td>9786</td><td>SPTBN1</td><td>9</td><td>FLNB</td><td>2123</td><td>TUBB3</td><td>4</td><td>RAB1A</td><td>158</td></tr><tr><td>TRIM54</td><td>9</td><td>TCTN3</td><td>9292</td><td>TRIM54</td><td>8</td><td>SMAD3</td><td>2094</td><td>FLNB</td><td>4</td><td>TUBB3</td><td>156</td></tr><tr><td>NCK1</td><td>9</td><td>GRB2</td><td>8676</td><td>ESR1</td><td>8</td><td>APOA1</td><td>1759</td><td>PIK3R1</td><td>4</td><td>AHNAK</td><td>120</td></tr><tr><td>MEOX2</td><td>8</td><td>FN1</td><td>7852</td><td>TCTN3</td><td>7</td><td>CAV1</td><td>1707</td><td>SMAD3</td><td>3</td><td>KIT</td><td>107</td></tr><tr><td>ATP5F1</td><td>8</td><td>HOMER3</td><td>7598</td><td>FLNB</td><td>7</td><td>RARG</td><td>1691</td><td>KIT</td><td>3</td><td>SCRIB</td><td>106</td></tr><tr><td>CDC37</td><td>8</td><td>ZBTB4</td><td>7364</td><td>MEOX2</td><td>6</td><td>TMEM216</td><td>1659</td><td>TNS3</td><td>3</td><td>FAS</td><td>54</td></tr><tr><td>TMEM216</td><td>8</td><td>CCDC57</td><td>7154</td><td>ATP5F1</td><td>6</td><td>ESR1</td><td>1603</td><td>CAV1</td><td>3</td><td>DMWD</td><td>54</td></tr><tr><td>ACAD9</td><td>7</td><td>CEP57L1</td><td>6650</td><td>SYNPO</td><td>6</td><td>SPTBN1</td><td>1484</td><td>CETN3</td><td>3</td><td>ITPR3</td><td>54</td></tr><tr><td>PCM1</td><td>7</td><td>PCM1</td><td>6593</td><td>SMAD3</td><td>5</td><td>RAB1A</td><td>1322</td><td>RAB1A</td><td>3</td><td>FASN</td><td>54</td></tr><tr><td>HDAC1</td><td>6</td><td>SYNPO</td><td>6545</td><td>TUBB3</td><td>5</td><td>PRKAR1B</td><td>1300</td><td>NR4A1</td><td>3</td><td>ANXA1</td><td>54</td></tr><tr><td>NDUFS2</td><td>6</td><td>PPP1R12B</td><td>6084</td><td>APOA1</td><td>5</td><td>PFKL</td><td>1162</td><td>HSF2</td><td>3</td><td>ELMSAN1</td><td>54</td></tr><tr><td>TTN</td><td>6</td><td>SIRT4</td><td>5093</td><td>PLEC</td><td>5</td><td>MYO19</td><td>1095</td><td>FASN</td><td>3</td><td>STOM</td><td>54</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The top twenty hub and bottleneck genes are also provided for the sub-network that was unique to the Exercise Response (i.e. constructed from genes differentially expressed in response to exercise but not training)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par55"><text><SENT sid="60562" pm="."><plain>We then performed a systems level analysis of the exercise response dynamic network by applying Newman’s <italic>fastgreedy</italic> community detection algorithm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] to cluster the nodes in the network based only upon network topology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60563" pm="."><plain>Twenty-eight non-trivial clusters (i.e. containing at least two genes) were detected in the untrained rest (UR) network state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60564" pm="."><plain>The functional relevance of each of these clusters (de novo putative gene modules) was then evaluated by over-representation analysis and twenty-two clusters were found to be significantly enriched for known functional modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60565" pm="."><plain>The largest clusters were primarily enriched for the cellular components <italic>Contractile fibre</italic> (Cluster 1: 55 genes; <italic>P</italic> = 8.9 × 10<sup>−07</sup>), <italic>Proton-transporting ATP synthase/ Mitochondrial respiratory chain complex V</italic> (Cluster 4: 35 genes; <italic>P =</italic> 2.5 × 10<sup>−10</sup>), <italic>NADH dehydrogenase/ Mitochondrial respiratory chain Complex I</italic> (Cluster 6: 32 genes; <italic>P =</italic> 3.5 × 10<sup>−35</sup>) and the biological process <italic>Pyruvate metabolism and TCA cycle</italic> (Cluster 7: 32 genes; <italic>P =</italic> 2.1 × 10<sup>−18</sup>), see Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6(a)</xref>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60566" pm="."><plain>To illustrate how these clusters are ‘re-wired’ in the exercise state we then overlaid the rest state cluster membership onto the exercise network state, by applying the same node format (colour and shape) to common nodes, see Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6(b)</xref>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par56"><text><SENT sid="60567" pm="."><plain>We observed changes in the interactions of several clusters in the exercise state relative to the rest state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60568" pm="."><plain>The cluster enriched for <italic>Pyruvate metabolism and TCA cycle</italic> (Cluster 7<italic>)</italic> for example, which contained 32 genes that were upregulated (mean:1.41-fold) in the exercise response, became disconnected in the exercise state and had far fewer internal interactions (seven edges) relative to the rest state (39 edges), see Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6(a) and (b)</xref>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60569" pm="."><plain>The top hub within this cluster, <italic>SIRT4</italic> (<italic>sirtulin 4</italic>) which was upregulated in the exercise response (+1.69-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 2.4 × 10<sup>−14</sup>), had 18 interactions in the rest state and only three interactions in the exercise state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60570" pm="."><plain>The cluster enriched for <italic>Contractile fibre</italic> however (Cluster 1) became mostly downregulated (38/55 genes; mean: −1.2-fold) in the exercise state relative to rest state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60571" pm="."><plain>It also lost many putative interactions in the exercise state (22 edges) relative to the rest state (60 edges) and became fragmented. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60572" pm="."><plain>For example, <italic>phosphoinositide-3-kinase regulatory subunit 1</italic> (<italic>PI3KR1)</italic>, which was upregulated in the exercise state (1.7-fold; 8.1 × 10<sup>−12</sup>), formed a new independent sub-cluster. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60573" pm="."><plain>This new cluster included new putative interactions with Cluster 31 members <italic>STAT3</italic> (<italic>signal transducer and activator of transcription 3</italic>) and <italic>SP1</italic> (<italic>Sp1 transcription factor</italic>) which were also upregulated in the exercise response 1.35-fold (<italic>P</italic> = 2.8 × 10<sup>−12</sup>) and 1.26-fold (<italic>P =</italic> 0.0056) respectively (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60574" pm="."><plain>Other clusters, however, were upregulated in a more coordinated manner in the exercise state (i.e. retained many intra-cluster edges). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60575" pm="."><plain>For example, the cluster enriched for <italic>NADH dehydrogenase/Mitochondrial respiratory chain complex I</italic> (Cluster 6), which is upregulated in the exercise response (mean:1.35-fold), retained 23 of its 52 rest state edges in the exercise state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60576" pm="."><plain>Most these retained edges (20/23) were between genes that encode subunits of <italic>NADH dehydrogenase/ Respiratory chain complex I</italic>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60577" pm="."><plain>The top hub in this cluster, in both the rest (19 edges) and exercise state (16 edges), was <italic>NDUFA6</italic> (<italic>NADH: ubiquinone oxidoreductase subunit A6</italic>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60578" pm="."><plain>This cluster (Cluster 6) also became detached from the main network in the exercise state (along with 5 <italic>ATP synthase complex/ Respiratory chain complex V genes</italic> from Custer 5), see Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6(b)</xref>, and its expression appears to be more independent from the rest of the network relative to rest state (where it previously had seven external edges). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par57"><text><SENT sid="60579" pm="."><plain>Some clusters became more central in the exercise state relative to the rest state, as determined by betweeness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60580" pm="."><plain>For example, two genes in the cluster enriched for <italic>Apoptosis</italic> (Cluster 8), namely <italic>CDC37</italic> (<italic>cell division cycle 37;</italic> −1.27-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 1.92 × 10<sup>−07</sup>) and <italic>DNAJB</italic> (<italic>DnaJ Hsp4 member B1;+</italic>4.27-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 3.59 × 10<sup>−14</sup>), gained a greater network influence in the exercise state relative to the rest state, being promoted from 174th and 6th to 3rd and 4th respectively in rank based on betweenness (see Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60581" pm="."><plain>Additionally, two genes in the cluster enriched for <italic>Cytoskeleton</italic> (Cluster 5)<italic>, FN1</italic> (<italic>fibronectin 1; +</italic>1.29-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 0.0018) and <italic>LIMA1</italic> (<italic>LIM domain and actin binding 1;+</italic>1.55-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 9.7 × 10<sup>−12</sup>), were also promoted from 8th and 73rd to 2nd and 5th respectively (see Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par58"><text><SENT sid="60582" pm="."><plain>In the exercise-specific network (genes associated with the exercise but not the training response) the cluster enriched for <italic>Cytoskeleton</italic> (Cluster 5) was the largest upregulated cluster (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6(c)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60583" pm="."><plain>This upregulation also appears to be coordinated as it retained a majority of its intra-cluster interactions (14/26 edges). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60584" pm="."><plain>Genes in this cluster, <italic>FN1</italic> and <italic>LIMA1,</italic> also became the top two bottlenecks in this exercise-specific network. <italic>FLNB</italic> (<italic>filamin B</italic>), which was also upregulated in exercise-specific response (+1.66-fold; <italic>P</italic> = 1.1 × 10<sup>−09</sup>), shared edges with both <italic>FN1</italic> and <italic>LIMA1</italic> and was the third most influential bottleneck in the exercise-specific response network. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par59"><text><SENT sid="60585" pm="."><plain>In the training response putative dynamic PPI network, which was constructed as for the exercise response, there were 199 nodes and 186 edges in the untrained state (UR) and 188 nodes and 176 edges in the trained (TR) state (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60586" pm="."><plain>The top twenty most influential genes, determined by betweenness and degree, are given in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and highlighted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60587" pm="."><plain>As in the exercise response network, <italic>GABARAPL1</italic> was the top bottleneck in the training response network both in the untrained state and trained state and was significantly upregulated (+1.37-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 0.0001) in response to training. <italic>GABARAPL1</italic> was partially ‘re-wired’ in the trained state (15 edges), gaining three and losing seven interactions relative to the untrained state (19 edges) of the network (see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Section 3.2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60588" pm="."><plain>The highest degree node in both states was <italic>NDUFA6</italic> (<italic>NADH ubiquinone oxidoreductase subunit A6</italic>), which was upregulated (+1.36-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 0.0007) in the training response and encodes a subunit of <italic>NADH dehydrogenase/Mitochondrial respiratory complex I</italic>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60589" pm="."><plain>Other top bottlenecks across both the untrained and trained network states included several genes that also encode subunits of this complex (<italic>NDUFA2, NDUFA4, NDUFA6, NDUFB3, NDUFV3</italic>) and <italic>ATP synthase complex</italic>/<italic>Respiratory chain complex V</italic> (<italic>ATP5A1, ATP5B, ATP5C1, ATP5F1, ATP5J2</italic>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60590" pm="."><plain>These genes were all significantly upregulated in the trained cohort (mean:1.38 fold; <italic>P =</italic> 0.0018).<SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The top twenty hub (based on node degree, <italic>D</italic>) and bottleneck (based on node betweenness, <italic>B</italic>) genes in the Exercise Response network in the Untrained Rest (UR) and Trained Exercise (TR) states</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="4">Untrained Rest</th><th colspan="4">Trained Rest</th><th colspan="4">Unique to Trained Rest</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td> <italic>Hubs</italic> </td><td> <italic>D</italic> </td><td> <italic>Bottlenecks</italic> </td><td> <italic>B</italic> </td><td> <italic>Hubs</italic> </td><td> <italic>D</italic> </td><td> <italic>Bottlenecks</italic> </td><td> <italic>B</italic> </td><td> <italic>Hubs</italic> </td><td> <italic>D</italic> </td><td> <italic>Bottlenecks</italic> </td><td> <italic>B</italic> </td></tr><tr><td>NDUFA6</td><td>20</td><td>GABARAPL1</td><td>819</td><td>NDUFA6</td><td>19</td><td>GABARAPL1</td><td>2137</td><td>KDR</td><td>3</td><td>MAPK10</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>GABARAPL1</td><td>19</td><td>NDUFA4</td><td>459</td><td>GABARAPL1</td><td>15</td><td>ATP5C1</td><td>1631</td><td>TUBA1A</td><td>3</td><td>ARRB1</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>NDUFA2</td><td>15</td><td>NDUFA6</td><td>432</td><td>NDUFA2</td><td>14</td><td>SPTBN1</td><td>1135</td><td>NCOA4</td><td>2</td><td>KDR</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>ATP5F1</td><td>8</td><td>NDUFA2</td><td>320</td><td>ATP5F1</td><td>8</td><td>NDUFB3</td><td>1067</td><td>NIN</td><td>2</td><td>JUN</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>GRB2</td><td>7</td><td>GRB2</td><td>177</td><td>SPTBN1</td><td>5</td><td>PRDX2</td><td>935</td><td>JUN</td><td>2</td><td>APP</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>CDC37</td><td>6</td><td>MYO18A</td><td>158</td><td>ACAD9</td><td>5</td><td>NDUFA2</td><td>933</td><td>MAPK10</td><td>2</td><td>NCOA4</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>ACAD9</td><td>6</td><td>ATP5F1</td><td>125</td><td>MYO19</td><td>5</td><td>SYNPO</td><td>842</td><td>ARRB1</td><td>2</td><td>TUBA1A</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>NCK1</td><td>6</td><td>NDUFV3</td><td>98</td><td>MYO18A</td><td>5</td><td>A2M</td><td>814</td><td>APP</td><td>2</td><td>NIN</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>TUBA1A</td><td>5</td><td>ATP5A1</td><td>88</td><td>MAPK6</td><td>4</td><td>NDUFA6</td><td>777</td><td>RIPK4</td><td>2</td><td>RIPK4</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>MYO18A</td><td>5</td><td>ASB16</td><td>85</td><td>ARAF</td><td>4</td><td>MYO18A</td><td>608</td><td>TNKS2</td><td>1</td><td>TNKS2</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>CACNA1A</td><td>4</td><td>ATP5B</td><td>82</td><td>LUZP1</td><td>4</td><td>ARAF</td><td>565</td><td>IPO4</td><td>1</td><td>IPO4</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>ATP5B</td><td>4</td><td>NCK1</td><td>82</td><td>KDR</td><td>4</td><td>MYO19</td><td>549</td><td>EGLN3</td><td>1</td><td>EGLN3</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>HSF2BP</td><td>4</td><td>CAPZB</td><td>78</td><td>PRDX2</td><td>4</td><td>APP</td><td>509</td><td>LUZP1</td><td>1</td><td>LUZP1</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>ATP5C1</td><td>4</td><td>ACAD9</td><td>76</td><td>PDLIM7</td><td>4</td><td>ACAD9</td><td>401</td><td>C1QB</td><td>1</td><td>C1QB</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>MAPK6</td><td>3</td><td>ATP5J2</td><td>76</td><td>SYNPO</td><td>4</td><td>ATP5F1</td><td>395</td><td>C1QA</td><td>1</td><td>C1QA</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>EGLN3</td><td>3</td><td>ATP5C1</td><td>72</td><td>ATP5C1</td><td>4</td><td>TPRN</td><td>323</td><td>SPRY1</td><td>1</td><td>SPRY1</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>HDAC1</td><td>3</td><td>NDUFB3</td><td>64</td><td>HDAC1</td><td>3</td><td>PDLIM7</td><td>320</td><td>FGF2</td><td>1</td><td>FGF2</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>CAPZB</td><td>3</td><td>PHYHIP</td><td>50</td><td>SPRY1</td><td>3</td><td>ACADM</td><td>320</td><td>FGFBP1</td><td>1</td><td>FGFBP1</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>KDR</td><td>3</td><td>DLD</td><td>50</td><td>NDUFS2</td><td>3</td><td>ARRB1</td><td>246</td><td>CACNA1A</td><td>1</td><td>CACNA1A</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>NDUFA4</td><td>3</td><td>PRDX2</td><td>50</td><td>CDC37</td><td>3</td><td>MYO1B</td><td>246</td><td>DYNLL1</td><td>1</td><td>DYNLL1</td><td>0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The top twenty hub and bottleneck genes are also provided for the sub-network that was unique to the Training Response (i.e. constructed from genes differentially expressed in response to training but not exercise)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par60"><text><SENT sid="60591" pm="."><plain>We observed that the network influence, as determined by hub or bottleneck status, of several genes changed in the trained state (TR) relative to the untrained network state (UR). <italic>SPTBN1 (spectrin beta, non-erythrocytic 1),</italic> which was upregulated in response to training (+1.38-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 0.0052), was promoted in rank from 55th in the untrained state, to 3rd top bottleneck in the trained network state. <italic>SPTBN1</italic> maintained its edge with <italic>GABARAPL1</italic> but also appears to have undergone a ‘re-wiring’ of other edges. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60592" pm="."><plain>For example, <italic>SPTBN1</italic> gained edges with ‘unconventional’ myosins (as opposed to Class II myosins that are directly involved in muscle contraction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]), <italic>MYO19</italic> and <italic>MYO18A,</italic> and an actin-associated protein gene <italic>SYNPO</italic> (<italic>synaptopodin</italic>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60593" pm="."><plain>Conversely, the <italic>GRB2</italic> (<italic>growth factor receptor bound protein 2</italic>) gene, which was downregulated (−1.33-fold, <italic>P =</italic> 0.0002) in the training response, became less influential in the trained (TR) state relative to the untrained network state, dropping from 5th to 49th place in the betweenness-based rankings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par61"><text><SENT sid="60594" pm="."><plain>Community analysis, performed as above, uncovered twenty-three clusters within the training response network untrained state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60595" pm="."><plain>Of these, twelve non-trivial (more than two genes) clusters were significantly enriched for one or more known functional category (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7(a)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60596" pm="."><plain>Three of the clusters uncovered were interconnected (six edges) and were enriched for <italic>NADH dehydrogenase/Mitochondrial respiratory complex I</italic> (Cluster 1), <italic>ATP synthase complex</italic>/ <italic>Mitochondrial respiratory complex V</italic> (Cluster 34) and <italic>Pyruvate metabolism and TCA cycle</italic> (Cluster 3)<italic>.</italic> The genes in these clusters were mostly upregulated (i.e. 32/36, 12/14 and 10/20 genes respectively) in the training response (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7(b)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60597" pm="."><plain>These clusters also appeared to be upregulated in a coordinated manner due to the retention of many intra-cluster (internal) edges in the trained network state relative to the untrained state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60598" pm="."><plain>The cluster enriched for <italic>NADH dehydrogenase/ Mitochondrial respiratory complex I</italic> (Cluster 1) retained 32/36 edges, the cluster enriched for <italic>ATP synthase complex</italic>/<italic>Respiratory complex V</italic> (Cluster 34) retained 12/14 edges and the cluster enriched for <italic>Pyruvate metabolism and TCA cycle</italic> (Cluster 3) retained 10/20 edges (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7(b)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60599" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, these three clusters also retained 5/6 inter-cluster edges (between clusters) in the trained network state, implying coordination at the system level also. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60600" pm="."><plain>Another six-gene cluster, enriched for <italic>Signaling by VEGF/Focal adhesion</italic> (Cluster 6), was entirely upregulated (mean: 1.59-fold) in a coordinated manner (retained all intra-cluster edges) in the training state but remained independent from the other clusters (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7(b)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60601" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the above clusters, the cluster enriched for <italic>ERBB Signaling pathway/Signaling by PDGF</italic> (Cluster 2), which was the largest cluster (24 genes), became entirely downregulated (mean: −1.6-fold) and dis-coordinated (retained only 6/25 intra-cluster edges) in the trained network state compared to the untrained network state (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7(b)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60602" pm="."><plain>Another 10-gene cluster, which was enriched for <italic>Unfolded protein binding/ Postsynaptic density</italic> (Cluster 5)<italic>,</italic> contained heatshock protein genes <italic>DNAJB1(DnaJ hsp40 member B1), HSF2BP (heat shock transcription factor 2 binding protein)</italic> and co-chaperone genes <italic>CDC37</italic> (<italic>cell division cycle 37</italic>) and <italic>CDC37L1</italic> (<italic>cell division cycle like 1</italic>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60603" pm="."><plain>This cluster became partially downregulated (five genes; −1.54-fold) and upregulated (five genes; mean: +1.38-fold) and ‘re-wired’ (lost seven edges and gained one) in the training response. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par62"><text><SENT sid="60604" pm="."><plain>The training-specific network (genes associated with the training response but not the exercise response) contained 25 putative interactions and little modular structure (only two modules with a diameter &gt; 2) (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7(c)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60605" pm="."><plain>The largest contained six genes (including three genes from Cluster 13), which were all upregulated (mean: +1.3-fold) in the training response, namely <italic>APP</italic> (<italic>amyloid beta precursor protein</italic>)<italic>, ARRB1</italic>(<italic>arrestin beta 1</italic>), MAPK10 (<italic>mitogen-activated protein kinase 10</italic>), <italic>JUN</italic> (<italic>jun proto-oncogene AP-1 transcription factor subunit</italic>), <italic>EGLN3</italic> (<italic>egl-9 family hypoxia inducible factor 3</italic>), and <italic>CAT</italic> (<italic>catalase</italic>) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7(c)</xref>)<italic>.</italic> Another module containing five genes was also upregulated in response to training (mean:1.49-fold) and contained part of the cluster enriched for <italic>Cytoskeleton</italic> (Cluster 8), namely <italic>KDR</italic> (<italic>kinase insert domain receptor, a.k.a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60606" pm="."><plain>VEGFR-2</italic>)<italic>, NRP1</italic> (<italic>neuropilin 1</italic>) and <italic>FLT4 (fms related tyrosine kinase 4, a.k.a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60607" pm="."><plain>VEGFR-3)</italic>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60608" pm="."><plain>This cluster also gained two additional interactions in the training response, <italic>NCOA4</italic> (<italic>nuclear receptor coactivator 4</italic>) and <italic>USP43</italic> (<italic>ubiquitin specific peptidase 43</italic>), that were present in this training-specific sub-network. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="60609" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par63"><text><SENT sid="60610" pm="."><plain>Using a transcriptome-wide RNA-seq approach in a large cohort of active racehorses, we have for the first time generated a comprehensive set of genes that are differentially expressed in Thoroughbred skeletal muscle in response to both exercise and training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60611" pm="."><plain>We have also developed a novel computational strategy to integrate these data with publicly available, experimentally validated PPIs in a bid to model the contextual interactome, its functional modules and how it may respond to exercise and training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60612" pm="."><plain>We observed that approximately one third of genes that were diffientially expressed in response to a single bout of exercise accumulate with training leading to new baseline levels of gene expression, suggesting that increases in aerobic capacity may be brought about mainly through this mechanism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60613" pm="."><plain>Therefore, consecutive bouts of exercise training seem to result in a priming of the skeletal muscle transcriptome for the demands of the next exercise bout. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60614" pm="."><plain>We have also demonstrated that this may further lead to an extensive ‘re-wiring’ of the molecular interactome in both exercise and training and have identified key genes and functional modules that may be involved in controlling and mediating these responses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par64"><text><SENT sid="60615" pm="."><plain>In this study the training period was six months, therefore it is possible that some of the changes in gene expression attributed to training may be age-related. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60616" pm="."><plain>As this study was undertaken in collaboration with an active racing yard, which offers considerable advantages in terms of cohort size, consistent exercise/training regimen and consistent environmental factors, such as nutrition, certain controls, such as untrained mature horses were not possible to obtain at the same time point as the TR samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60617" pm="."><plain>However, training standards ensured that all time points in the study (&gt;513 days) were well beyond the end of the pubescent period for Thoroughbred horses (&lt;450 days) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60618" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, a small subset of the UR cohort (<italic>N</italic> = 4) was sampled after a two-week period of detraining, Detrained Rest (DR), and while there was some overlap among DE genes (28 genes), there was very little difference in terms of overall DE (144 genes after correction for multiple comparisons) between these two cohorts (See Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Section 5 and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S7.) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par65"><text><SENT sid="60619" pm="."><plain>Our initial functional over-representation analyses supported a central role for modules related to energy metabolism in both the exercise response and training response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60620" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, several functional modules of this type, which were common to both, were more significantly associated with the training response than the exercise response in terms of module significance (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> vs. Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60621" pm="."><plain>For example, the exercise response was enriched for <italic>Integration of energy metabolism</italic> with a significance level of <italic>P</italic> = 4.97 × 10<sup>−11</sup>; however, this increased to a significance level of <italic>P =</italic> 4.66 × 10<sup>−14</sup> in the training response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60622" pm="."><plain>We also observed a similar trend for <italic>Pyruvate metabolism and TCA cycle</italic> (from <italic>P =</italic> 0.0204 to <italic>P =</italic> 2.93 × 10<sup>−07</sup>) and <italic>NADH dehydrogenase/Mitochondrial respiratory chain complex I</italic> (from <italic>P =</italic> 0.0017 to <italic>P =</italic> 1.29 × 10<sup>−06</sup>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60623" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, some functional modules related to energy metabolism were only found to be significantly over-represented in the training response gene list. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60624" pm="."><plain>These included the <italic>Citrate cycle</italic> (<italic>P =</italic> 5.12 × 10<sup>−05</sup>) and the respiratory chain component <italic>Proton-transporting ATP synthase / Respiratory chain complex V</italic> (<italic>P =</italic> 0.0007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60625" pm="."><plain>These results support the hypothesis that trained skeletal muscle may exhibit an unstimulated transcriptome inherently primed to respond to the energy demands of exercise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60626" pm="."><plain>More generally this information also provides support for the view that ‘accumulative’ changes play a role in the adaptive response. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par66"><text><SENT sid="60627" pm="."><plain>There is also some evidence that epigenetic regulation may play a role in modulating these transcriptomic adaptations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60628" pm="."><plain>For example, four of the five genes reported by Barrès and colleagues to be hypomethylated and expressed in human skeletal muscle in response to acute exercise, namely <italic>PPARD (peroxisome proliferator activated receptor delta)</italic>, <italic>PPARGC1A (PPARG coactivator 1 alpha)</italic>, <italic>PDK4 (pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase 4)</italic> and <italic>CS (citrate synthase)</italic>, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>] were significantly upregulated either in the exercise response (<italic>PPARD</italic>:+1.97-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 1.2 × 10<sup>−13</sup>, <italic>PPARGC1A:</italic>+10.17-fold<italic>; P =</italic> 7.25 × 10<sup>−26</sup>, <italic>PDK4</italic>:+2.17-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 0.0092) or the training response (<italic>CS</italic>:+1.33-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 1.40 × 10<sup>−05</sup>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60629" pm="."><plain>In particular, we found that <italic>PPARGC1A</italic>, which was reported by Barrès and colleagues to be hypomethylated in response to acute exercise<italic>,</italic> was the 6th most significantly upregulated gene (10-fold, <italic>P =</italic> 7.25 × 10<sup>−26</sup>) in the exercise response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60630" pm="."><plain>PPARGC1A was also shown previously to be up-regulated at the protein level after high intensity exercise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60631" pm="."><plain>PPARGC1A directly links external physiological stimuli and mitochondrial biogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>], regulates muscle fibre type [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>] and is associated with endurance exercise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60632" pm="."><plain>It has also been shown to mediate the epigenetic regulation of insulin secretion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>] and regulate oxidative energy metabolism during exercise in equine skeletal muscle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60633" pm="."><plain>Our previous work has also supported the involvement of PPARGC1A in the adaptation of equine skeletal muscle to training [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par67"><text><SENT sid="60634" pm="."><plain>Another gene highlighted by Barrès et al., <italic>CS,</italic> which encodes citrate synthase that catalyses the synthesis of citrate from oxaloacetate and acetyl coenzyme A, was upregulated in the TR cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60635" pm="."><plain>This may contribute to the trained cohort’s constitutive priming for exercise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60636" pm="."><plain>Indeed, increased CS activity has previously been reported in trained human [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>] and equine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>] muscle and is a validated biomarker for skeletal muscle mitochondrial density and oxidative adaptation to a training [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par68"><text><SENT sid="60637" pm="."><plain>We also observed that several functional modules uncovered by over-representational analysis were exclusively associated with either the exercise response or the training response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60638" pm="."><plain>Only the exercise response, for example, was significantly enriched for functional modules related to muscle contraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60639" pm="."><plain>The largest module of this type was <italic>Contractile fibre</italic> (<italic>P =</italic> 6.35 × 10<sup>−11</sup>) and contained a majority (44/56) of downregulated genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60640" pm="."><plain>This observation is in line with the previous finding of an inhibitory effect of NAD+/NADH ratio on MYOD1 regulated gene expression and differentiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60641" pm="."><plain>NAD+/NADH ratio is generally found to increase in muscle cells post-exercise in animals but, curiously, not in humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60642" pm="."><plain>We also observed that MYOD1, which is known as a ‘master switch’ of muscle cell differentiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>], was significantly downregulated at the transcript level (−1.9-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 0.0008) but only in the training response, which suggests that it may form part of the adaptive response to training. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par69"><text><SENT sid="60643" pm="."><plain>We also found that the <italic>Hemostasis</italic> pathway was exclusively significantly over-represented (<italic>P</italic> = 3.76 × 10<sup>−05</sup>) in the exercise response, it being mostly (46/69 genes) upregulated in exercise relative to rest cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60644" pm="."><plain>This response included several upregulated growth factors, such as <italic>EGF, Epidermal Growth Factor,</italic> (+1.73–fold; <italic>P =</italic> 6.80 × 10<sup>−08</sup>), <italic>TGF-beta 2</italic>, <italic>transforming growth factor beta 2</italic> (+1.29-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 0.0006) and <italic>VEGFA, vascular endothelial growth factor A,</italic> (+2.33-fold, <italic>P =</italic> 4.67 × 10<sup>−19</sup>), <italic>VEGFC, vascular endothelial growth factor C</italic> (+1.79-fold, <italic>P =</italic> 6.65 × 10<sup>−10</sup>) and <italic>VEGFD vascular endothelial growth factor D,</italic> (+1.48-fold, <italic>P =</italic> 5.77 × 10<sup>−09</sup>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60645" pm="."><plain>This observed association of hemostasis with the exercise but not the training response gene list aligns with recent findings in human of a transient hypercoagulability state post-exercise, particularly in untrained individuals, that is largely reversed in trained individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par70"><text><SENT sid="60646" pm="."><plain>Conversely, the training response gene list was also exclusively enriched for certain functional modules, such as the pathways <italic>Signalling by GPCR</italic> (<italic>P =</italic> 1.22 × 10<sup>−17</sup>) and <italic>Neurological systems processes</italic> (<italic>P = 4</italic>.85 × 10<sup>−27</sup>), that were not associated with the exercise response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60647" pm="."><plain>G-protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs) mediate physiological responses to hormones, neurotransmitters and environmental stimulants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60648" pm="."><plain>The GPCR family also includes opioid receptors (ORs), discussed in further detail below in relation to the network analysis results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par71"><text><SENT sid="60649" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we also observed over-representation of several disease related pathways in both our exercise and training associated gene lists. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60650" pm="."><plain>For example, both gene lists were enriched for Reactome’s <italic>Diabetes pathways</italic>, which were more associated with the training response (<italic>P =</italic> 3.10 × 10<sup>−08</sup> <italic>)</italic> than the exercise response (<italic>P =</italic> 3.57 × 10<sup>−06</sup>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60651" pm="."><plain>It is recognized that regular physical exercise, particularly aerobic and resistance exercise, has considerable health benefits for people with both type 1 and type 2 diabetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60652" pm="."><plain>Our over-representation results also appear to provide some support for a relationship between our exercise phenotypes and diabetes and it would be interesting, in future studies, to investigate the extent of this mechanistic link. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60653" pm="."><plain>We also observed that several neurodegenerative disorders, namely Alzheimer’s Disease (AD), Huntington’s Disease (HD) and Parkinson’s Disease (PD), were amongst the most significantly enriched KEGG categories associated with both the exercise response and the training response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60654" pm="."><plain>The links between these neurodegenerative diseases and mitochondrial dysfunction have been well established [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>] and the over-representation of these pathways may be due in part to the effect that intense exercise has on mitochondrial function in skeletal muscle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60655" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, an early deficit of synaptic mitochondria and motor function has been associated with AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>], physical exercise has been shown to be protective in both AD and PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>] and increased mitochondrial biogenesis has recently been shown to improve symptoms in HD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60656" pm="."><plain>Our results also appear to reflect this mitochondrial-driven mechanistic relationship between exercise and this group of neurodegenerative disorders. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par72"><text><SENT sid="60657" pm="."><plain>Standard over-representation analysis, as performed here, is based on well-established, carefully curated, functional annotations of genes and gene products (e.g. KEGG, Reactome, gene ontology). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60658" pm="."><plain>However, these resources are far from complete. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60659" pm="."><plain>For example 85% of Ensembl genes are not mapped to a KEGG pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], and some genes may have additional undescribed roles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60660" pm="."><plain>For example, the kappa opioid receptor (KOR) signalling pathway, which we discuss below, was not described in sufficient detail by KEGG (only as part of the <italic>Neuro-active ligand receptor pathways</italic>) or fully labelled by Reactome (covers the <italic>mu</italic> but not the <italic>kappa</italic>-OR, see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]) to be identified by our above over-representation analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60661" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, even well established and fully annotated pathways/complexes may behave in an unexpected manner in a particular context (e.g. cell type, species or experimental condition) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60662" pm="."><plain>In addition, due to the group-wise nature of over-representation analysis the chief drivers or regulators of biological processes may not always be apparent (nor are these, of course, necessarily highlighted by basic statistical association of expression gene). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60663" pm="."><plain>These limitations, however, may be somewhat overcome by employing a less supervised, network analysis-based approach. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par73"><text><SENT sid="60664" pm="."><plain>When we constructed our putative contextual PPI networks for exercise and training we first identified the most influential genes in the various states as determined by hub and bottleneck status (see Tables <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60665" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we found that some nodes appeared to gain influence in response to exercise and/or training relative to the untrained rest network state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60666" pm="."><plain>In the exercise response network for example, <italic>FN1</italic> (<italic>fibronectin</italic>) became more influential in the network after exercise relative to the untrained rest state (promoted from 11th to 2nd top bottleneck). <italic>FN1</italic> is involved in cell adhesion, migration, growth and differentiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>], and interestingly, has previously been used as an indicator of myofibre damage, such as may occur after intense exercise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60667" pm="."><plain>Another gene that appeared to become more influential in the post-exercise network state, <italic>LIMA1</italic> (<italic>LIM Domain and actin binding 1</italic>), has been shown to stabilize the vascular capillary network in vitro [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60668" pm="."><plain>This information, and the fact that neither <italic>FN1</italic> nor <italic>LIMA1</italic> expression was associated with the training response, might indicate involvement in muscle or microvascular recovery and repair following intense exercise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60669" pm="."><plain>Continuing in this theme, the top differential bottleneck gene <italic>DNAJB1</italic> (<italic>DnaJ Hsp40 Member B1</italic>), which was significantly (<italic>P =</italic> 3.6 × 10<sup>−14</sup>) upregulated (&gt;4-fold) in response to exercise, has previously been found to be upregulated in skeletal muscle in response to heat shock [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60670" pm="."><plain>Interestingly this is one of the few genes whose expression is also significantly reversed in the training response (−1.6-fold, <italic>P =</italic> 0.0005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60671" pm="."><plain>This also supports previous studies which reported the significant upregulation (between 1.5 fold and 4.8-fold) of heat shock proteins both immediately after and 4 h post-exercise in Thoroughbred horses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60672" pm="."><plain>Together these data suggest that these genes may be involved in the stress response induced by intense exercise in the untrained cohort. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par74"><text><SENT sid="60673" pm="."><plain>Several other genes, such as <italic>SIRT4 (sirtulin 4)</italic>, <italic>GRB2 (growth factor receptor bound protein 2)</italic>, <italic>GNB4</italic> (<italic>G protein subunit beta 4</italic>) and <italic>CDK18</italic> (<italic>cyclin dependent kinase 18</italic>), became less influential in the exercise network state relative to untrained rest network state (i.e. their hub/bottleneck ranks were all down-graded after exercise). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60674" pm="."><plain>Although <italic>SIRT4</italic> had far fewer edges in the exercise state relative to rest state (4 vs. 18 edges) it was highly significantly upregulated (+1.69-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 2.4 × 10<sup>−14</sup>) in the exercise response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60675" pm="."><plain>This perhaps suggests a shift in function in response to exercise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60676" pm="."><plain>SIRT4 has been shown to associate with mitochondria and to have ‘strong and reproducible’ ADP-ribosyltransferase activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>]. <italic>SIRT4</italic> is also required for protection against cell death caused by nutrient starvation via a role in the maintenance of mitochondrial NAD+ levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60677" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the only novel edge that was gained by <italic>SIRT4</italic> in the exercise response was with <italic>SLC25A5 (solute carrier family 25 Member 5),</italic> which was also highly significantly upregulated in the exercise response only (+3.2-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 5.3 × 10<sup>−21</sup> <italic>)</italic> relative to untrained rest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60678" pm="."><plain>SLC25A catalyses the exchange of mitochondrial ATP with cytoplasmic ADP across the mitochondrial inner membrane [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>]. <italic>SIRT4</italic> also retains an edge with <italic>ETHE1</italic> (<italic>persulfide dioxygenase</italic>), which was also upregulated in the exercise response (+1.3-fold; <italic>P</italic> = 9.5 × 10<sup>−08</sup>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60679" pm="."><plain>This mitochondrial matrix sulphur dioxygenase is involved in catabolizing hydrogen sulphide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>], a by-product of energy metabolism that inhibits mitochondrial functioning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60680" pm="."><plain>Together these data suggest that the re-wiring of <italic>SIRT4</italic> interactions in the exercise state may be part of the exercise-induced stress response and may contribute to the maintenance of metabolic homeostasis in mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par75"><text><SENT sid="60681" pm="."><plain>In the trained network, we also observed evidence of a re-wiring of key hubs. <italic>SPTBN1</italic> (<italic>spectrin beta chain non-erythrocytic 1</italic>), which was upregulated in the training response (+1.38-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 0.0052), appears to gain network influence in the trained network state (promoted in rank from 55th to 3rd top bottleneck). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60682" pm="."><plain>Functionally, SPTBN1 is involved in secretion, interacts with calmodulin in a calcium-dependent manner and has been isolated from post-synaptic density preparations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60683" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, <italic>SPTBN1</italic> has previously been shown to be associated with skeletal muscle adaptation, specifically during the torpor phase of hibernation in mammals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60684" pm="."><plain>Metabolic adaptation and the prevention of muscle atrophy during hibernation induced starvation have also been previously linked to athletic endurance adaptions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">108</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60685" pm="."><plain>In further support of a mechanistic connection between these seemingly disparate physiological states, the reduced expression of the <italic>myostatin</italic> (<italic>MSTN</italic>) gene, referred to as the Thoroughbred ‘speed gene’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], has also been associated with hibernation in ground squirrels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">109</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60686" pm="."><plain>Similarly, another gene, <italic>PDK4</italic> (<italic>pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase</italic>), has also been previously associated with hibernation in mammals as well as intense exercise in Thoroughbred horses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60687" pm="."><plain>These data suggest perhaps that a similar biological mechanism may be involved both in the process of muscle growth during training and prevention of muscle wasting during prolonged inactivity and nutrient starvation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par76"><text><SENT sid="60688" pm="."><plain>The inferred contextual network may also provide some additional mechanistic insight into the activity of <italic>SPTBN1</italic> in the context of skeletal muscle adaptations to training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60689" pm="."><plain>In the trained network, the <italic>SPTBN1</italic> bottleneck mediates the ‘flow of information’ between the module containing <italic>GABARAPL1</italic> and the module containing unconventional myosins, <italic>MYO19</italic> and <italic>MYO18A,</italic> and <italic>SYNPO</italic> (<italic>synaptopodin</italic>). <italic>MYO19</italic>, which was upregulated in both the exercise (+1.5-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 3.9 × 10<sup>−08</sup>) and trained (+1.3-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 0.0046) responses, is known to be involved in mitochondrial motility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">111</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60690" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, <italic>SYNPO</italic>, which was downregulated in both the exercise (−1.66-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 6.7 × 10<sup>−14</sup>) and trained (−1.59-fold; <italic>P = 7</italic>.2 × 10<sup>−05</sup>) responses, is known to be part of the post-synaptic density [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">112</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60691" pm="."><plain>ATP and Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux is particularly important at the synapse, and mitochondria are usually present in pre-synaptic terminals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60692" pm="."><plain>Taken together the above ‘re-wiring’ of <italic>SPTNB1</italic> interactors may possibly reflect changes to the neuromuscular junction that occurs in response to exercise and training and may also suggests an increased influence of <italic>SPTNB1</italic> in the training response. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par77"><text><SENT sid="60693" pm="."><plain>Although we observed <italic>MSTN</italic> to be highly significantly downregulated in both the exercise (−5.9-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 1.4 × 10–<sup>19</sup>) and training (−6.4-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 1.5 × 10<sup>−06</sup>) responses, it was absent from our putative contextual PPI networks as none of its contextual (correlation-based) edges were supported by experimentally validated PPIs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60694" pm="."><plain>This may be partially explained by the stringency of our protocol (e.g. the exclusion of inverse co-expression correlations, inclusion only of PPIs supported by IMEX standard) and also lack of recorded interaction evidences for MSTN, due in part to that fact the MSTN ligand generally interacts with membrane-bound proteins, which are under-represented in PPI databases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114">114</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60695" pm="."><plain>However, by examining the larger non-validated correlation-based networks we observed some evidence of a change in <italic>MSTN</italic>-related activity in the exercise and training responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60696" pm="."><plain>We saw a reduction in <italic>MSTN</italic> edges in both the exercise and training network states relative to the untrained rest state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60697" pm="."><plain>Also, approximately 20% (43/231) of exercise-induced <italic>MSTN</italic> edges were also observed in the trained state, suggesting that there may be some sustained adaptation of the MSTN-related signalling network in the trained cohort, although, of course, further support is required to substantiate this. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60698" pm="."><plain>Interestingly however, this list of 43 genes includes <italic>PVALB</italic> (<italic>parvalbumin</italic>), which was the most downregulated gene in both the exercise response (−25.43-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 3.5 × 10<sup>−20</sup>) and the training response (−33.27-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 7.8 × 10<sup>−10</sup>). <italic>PVALB</italic> is involved in calcium sequestration after muscle contraction to support muscle relaxation and a recognized fast-twitch phenotype gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">115</xref>].It has also been found that double-knockout PV−/− mice have prolonged muscle relaxation time, due to the maintenance of muscle Ca<sup>2+</sup> levels, but also generate ~40% more force per contraction than PV +/− and WT animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116">116</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par78"><text><SENT sid="60699" pm="."><plain>By far the most influential gene, as determined by hub and bottleneck analysis, across both the exercise and training response networks was <italic>GABARAPL1</italic> (<italic>GABA type A receptor associated protein like 1</italic>), where it ranked as top bottleneck across all network states (Tables <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60700" pm="."><plain>We found <italic>GABARAPL1</italic> to be highly significantly upregulated (+1.49-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 6.5 × 10<sup>−12</sup>) in response to exercise and significantly upregulated (+1.37-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 0.0001) in the trained cohort compared to the untrained cohort. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par79"><text><SENT sid="60701" pm="."><plain>The product of <italic>GABARAPL1</italic> is a ubiquitin-like modifier associated with the autophagosome and known to cause an increase in cell-surface expression of the G protein-coupled receptor (GPCR) <italic>kappa</italic> type opioid receptor (KOR), through facilitating anterograde trafficking of the receptor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">117</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60702" pm="."><plain>KOR is the product of the <italic>OPRK1</italic> gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60703" pm="."><plain>In our data <italic>OPRK1</italic> mRNA expression showed no association with the exercise response, however it was significantly upregulated (+1.74-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 0.0075) in the training response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60704" pm="."><plain>Taken together this information supports the model of an initial post-translational upregulation of the KOR cell-surface expression by GABARAPL1 in response to exercise and then, upon adaption, a transcriptional upregulation in the trained cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60705" pm="."><plain>However, the downstream effect of the putative upregulation of the KOR in the context of exercise and training still needs to be clarified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60706" pm="."><plain>KOR mediated signal transduction is known to stimulate several kinase cascades depending upon the specific activating ligand [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">118</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60707" pm="."><plain>For example, dynorphin activation of KOR has been shown to be involved in the stress response (e.g. to stressors such as forced swim) in mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">119</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60708" pm="."><plain>This same ligand-receptor interaction has also been associated with pro-addictive behaviour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">120</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60709" pm="."><plain>Further work is needed in this context, but we hypothesize that the regulation of aversive/motivational behaviour by KORs may play a role in the adaptation of the organism to regular and sustained bouts of intense exercise. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par80"><text><SENT sid="60710" pm="."><plain>We can also attempt to extract additional mechanistic and functional insight into <italic>GABARAPL1</italic> in the context of exercise and training from community analysis. <italic>GABARPL1</italic> is a member of the exercise network cluster that is significantly enriched (<italic>P =</italic> 2.56 × 10<sup>−10</sup>) for the <italic>Proton-transporting ATP synthase/Mitochondrial respiratory chain complex V (MRC complex V)</italic>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60711" pm="."><plain>This cluster also has four putative interactions with the cluster that is significantly enriched (<italic>P =</italic> 9.69 × 10<sup>−38</sup>) for <italic>NADH dehydrogenase</italic>/ <italic>Mitochondrial respiratory chain complex I</italic> (<italic>MRC complex I</italic>) (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6(a)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60712" pm="."><plain>In the exercise response, we observed a general upregulation of the genes in both clusters and a general disturbance in the rest of the network (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6(b)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60713" pm="."><plain>These clusters became ‘re-wired’ but remained largely intact except for a major de-coupling of the <italic>MRC complex I-enriched</italic> cluster (along with genes encoding members of <italic>MRC complex V</italic>) from the rest of the network in the exercise state (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6(b)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60714" pm="."><plain>We observed that correspondingly enriched clusters (i.e. also enriched for MRC complexes I and V) were also present and upregulated in the trained state network (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7(b)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60715" pm="."><plain>However, in this case, the upregulation of these clusters was better coordinated with the rest of the network and was not accompanied by the similar de-coupling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60716" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, this apparent ‘de-coupling’ of <italic>MRC complexes I</italic> and <italic>V</italic> during exercise, may be a reflection of the recognized physiological response to oxidative stress known as <italic>uncoupling</italic> and mediated by UCP3 in skeletal muscle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60717" pm="."><plain>This is also supported by the highly significant upregulation of <italic>UCP3</italic> (+4.8-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 7.6 × 10<sup>−22</sup>) in the exercise response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60718" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we did not see the differential expression of <italic>UCP3</italic> in the training response (although we did observe a significant increase (+1.27-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 0.0007) of <italic>UCP1</italic> and a decrease of <italic>UCP2</italic> (+1.47-fold; <italic>P =</italic> 0.0175)). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par81"><text><SENT sid="60719" pm="."><plain>It has been suggested that <italic>NADH dehydrogenase</italic>/ <italic>Mitochondrial respiratory chain complex I</italic> activity is among the major rate-controlling steps in mitochondrial oxidative phosphorylation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">121</xref>], thus its coordinated upregulation in the training response may represent a significant adaption for the overall process of oxidative phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60720" pm="."><plain>The central position of <italic>GABARAPL1</italic> in both the exercise and trained networks may suggest a driver/regulatory role in these responses, perhaps mediated in part via its control of kappa OR cell-surface expression, and downstream effects may include the altered regulation of the components of the mitochondrial respiratory chain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60721" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown that the knock-down of <italic>GABRAPL1</italic> leads to many cellular bioenergetic changes, including increased basal oxygen consumption rate, increased intracellular ATP (possibly due to OR-mediated dysregulation of adenylyl cyclinase/cAMP signalling), increased total glutathione, and an accumulation of damaged mitochondria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">117</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60722" pm="."><plain>It has also recently been reported that the dysregulation of autophagy, in which GABARAPL1 has a central role, is linked to several neuromuscular disorders in human [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">122</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60723" pm="."><plain>In the context of exercise and training, autophagy has already been shown to be activated by high-intensity, but not low-intensity, exercise in human [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123">123</xref>] and to be involved in the maintenance of muscle mass in <italic>Atg7 (autophagy related 7)</italic> knock-out mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">124</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60724" pm="."><plain>It has also been proposed that autophagosomal proteins, of which GABARPL1 is one, may act as sensors for oxidative stress (via redox signalling) and mediate cross-talk between this and other cellular processes such as mitochondrial turnover [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">125</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60725" pm="."><plain>This latter relationship, in particular, would explain the tight coupling of <italic>GABARAPL1</italic>, <italic>NADH dehydrogenase/ Mitochondrial respiratory chain complex I</italic> and <italic>Proton-transporting ATP synthase/Mitochondrial respiratory chain complex V</italic> clusters that we observed in the exercise (rest state) and training networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60726" pm="."><plain>There is already some experimental evidence to support a role for autophagy in muscle cell homeostasis during exercise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126">126</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">127</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60727" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, there is support for GABARAPL1 being directly involved in mediating the autophagic energy stress response in heart muscle, involving both mitophagy and glycophagy, via its interaction starch binding domain 1 (STBD1) protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">128</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60728" pm="."><plain>Our results indicate that <italic>GABARAPL1</italic> may play a central role in the adaption to oxidative stress induced by intense exercise and may also play a key role in the adaptive response to training, perhaps in part via a role in the recycling and upregulation of mitochondria via mitophagy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par82"><text><SENT sid="60729" pm="."><plain>The training response network also contains evidence of ancillary adaptations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60730" pm="."><plain>For example, a small three-gene module, containing <italic>APP (amyloid beta precursor protein), ARRB1(arrestin beta 1)</italic> and <italic>MAPK10 (mitogen-activated protein kinase 10),</italic> that is enriched for <italic>Enzyme inhibitor activity/Response to radiation</italic> was initially disconnected from the main network in the untrained rest state (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7(a)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60731" pm="."><plain>This module however was upregulated and ‘re-wired’ in the trained network state (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7(b)</xref>), gaining several second-degree connections with <italic>GABRAPL1</italic>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60732" pm="."><plain>Importantly, this module was also unique to the trained network (i.e. genes not associated with the exercise response) (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7(c)</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60733" pm="."><plain>Arrestins such as ARRB1 are known to promote agonist-mediated desensitization of G protein-coupled receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">129</xref>] and kappa and delta OR-mediated G protein activation has been shown to be attenuated by over-expression of ARRB1 in fibroblast-like cell lines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">130</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60734" pm="."><plain>This module is also extended with the addition of several genes also unique to the training response (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7(c)</xref>), namely <italic>CAT</italic> (<italic>catalase</italic>) and <italic>EGLN3</italic> (<italic>egl-9 family hypoxia-inducible factor 3</italic>) and <italic>JUN</italic> (<italic>Jun proto-oncogene, AP-1 transcription factor subunit</italic>), which were also upregulated at a transcriptional level in the trained cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60735" pm="."><plain>Catalase helps protect the cell against hydrogen peroxide mediated cytotoxicity especially when levels of pyruvate are low [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR131">131</xref>]. <italic>EGLN3</italic> is one of the most important isoenzymes in modulating the hypoxic response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">132</xref>] and has also been reported to regulate myogenin expression and skeletal muscle differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60736" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, JUN is known to be activated by ORs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133">133</xref>] and has been found to be involved in oxidative stress-mediated suppression of insulin gene expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134">134</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60737" pm="."><plain>Another six-gene cluster in the training response network, that was upregulated in a coordinated manner in response to training, contained genes that encode ligands and receptors of the VEGF signalling pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60738" pm="."><plain>Several of these, namely <italic>KDR</italic>, <italic>NRP</italic>1 and <italic>FLT4</italic>, were exclusive to the training response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60739" pm="."><plain>In support of this, skeletal myofiber VEGFA has been found to be essential for the exercise training response in mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135">135</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60740" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that there may be coordinated upregulation of several genes specific to the training response that may control ancillary processes in the adaptive response to training in the skeletal muscle of the Thoroughbred. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="60741" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par83"><text><SENT sid="60742" pm="."><plain>Functional category over-representation analysis is a commonly used and valuable aid to the biological interpretation of gene/protein lists. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60743" pm="."><plain>However, this analysis may be improved with additional information (e.g. molecular interactions inferred from gene expression) derived from the experimental context in question (e.g. post-exercise skeletal muscle) and a contribution from unsupervised methods (e.g. community analysis) in defining functional classes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60744" pm="."><plain>The absence of these considerations risks underexploiting rich high-throughput datasets and overlooking novel information that might help to expand knowledge of biological systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60745" pm="."><plain>As this is the first demonstration of this computational method, we have applied a stringent implementation to maximize quality over scale; however, in the future more refined implementations could be developed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60746" pm="."><plain>Our results clearly demonstrate that network analysis and its capacity to predict influential nodes is very useful for highlighting putative control points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60747" pm="."><plain>For example, our hypothesis that <italic>GABARAPL1</italic> and autophagy may play a central role in the response to exercise and training was generated solely from this network analysis approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60748" pm="."><plain>Standard over-representation analysis enabled some insight into downstream effects (e.g. enrichment for energy metabolism, neurodegenerative disease etc.) but did not highlight the autophagy process nor point to a putative driver gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60749" pm="."><plain>Neither was this indicated by differential gene expression analysis (<italic>GABARAPL1</italic> was outside the top 250 genes most significantly associated with exercise or training). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60750" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we have demonstrated the benefits of a novel network-based approach, which may serve as a model for future transcriptomics-based investigations into the molecular dynamics of biological systems in health and disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par84"><text><SENT sid="60751" pm="."><plain>Taken together our results, both from the over-representation analysis and our novel network analysis approach, support the involvement of mitochondrial respiratory complexes I (<italic>NADH dehydrogenase</italic>) and V (<italic>ATP Synthase</italic>) in both the exercise and training responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60752" pm="."><plain>As expected, the exercise response in the untrained cohort appeared to include elements of a stress response but also included the downregulation of genes involved in myogenic differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60753" pm="."><plain>Neither of these features were observed in the trained cohort, although we cannot preclude them from a ‘trained’ exercise response based on the current data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60754" pm="."><plain>It is also noteworthy that there is some limited support for the constitutive downregulation of heatshock proteins in the trained cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60755" pm="."><plain>However, we did observe strong indications of the constitutive and coordinated upregulation of the mitochondrial respiratory complexes I and V in the trained cohort, which may suggest that the skeletal muscle has adapted to regular bouts of intense-exercise in this manner, presumably improving the efficiency of oxidative phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60756" pm="."><plain>There is also the suggestion from our network analysis that this upregulation of mitochondrial complexes, and indeed mitochondria, in response to exercise and especially training may be controlled in part by autophagy (and perhaps mitophagy) via <italic>GABARAPL1</italic>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60757" pm="."><plain>Our results also suggested a connection between <italic>GABARAPL1</italic> and the stimulation of/response to GPCR, especially via the opioid receptor, signalling, in both exercise and training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60758" pm="."><plain>The network analysis also suggested that the <italic>SPTBN1</italic> gene may play an important role in the adaptive response and that this response may include re-wiring of its interactions at the post-synaptic neuromuscular junction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60759" pm="."><plain>Somewhat unexpected was the strong overlap between the exercise and training responses and pathways linked to several neurodegenerative diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60760" pm="."><plain>However, there seems to be a strong body of evidence for an established role for mitochondrial dysfunction and autophagy in neurodegenerative disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60761" pm="."><plain>This also supports our hypothesis of the central involvement of these processes in both the exercise and training response in skeletal muscle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60762" pm="."><plain>The involvement of authophagy and mitochondrial activity at the synaptic junction in both neurodegenerative disease and athletic adaptation seems to be a common theme, but further validation of this largely in silico generated hypothesis is required. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60763" pm="."><plain>In recent years autophagy and its role in many cellular processes and diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136">136</xref>] has garnered much interest and already autophagy-enhancing therapeutics have been proposed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137">137</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60764" pm="."><plain>This study has provided further support for this process in relation to exercise (especially intense exercise), provided novel evidence of its central involvement in the adaptation of skeletal muscle to training and identified the autophagosomal gene <italic>GABARAPL1</italic> as a potential regulatory target. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="60765" pm="."><plain>Additional files </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec16"><p><text><SENT sid="60766" pm="."><plain><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12864_2017_4007_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p>Supplementary Information Main Document. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60767" pm="."><plain>(DOCX 110 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material> <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12864_2017_4007_MOESM2_ESM.xls"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p>Supplementary Tables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60768" pm="."><plain>(XLS 2823 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material> </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AD</term><def><p id="Par4">Alzheimer’s Disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AMP</term><def><p id="Par5">Adenosine Monophosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ATP</term><def><p id="Par6">Adenosine Triphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BP</term><def><p id="Par7">Gene Ontology Biological Process</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CC</term><def><p id="Par8">Gene Ontology Cellular Component</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DAVID</term><def><p id="Par9">he Database for Annotation, Visualization and Integrated Discovery</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GO</term><def><p id="Par10">Gene Ontology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HD</term><def><p id="Par11">Huntington’s Disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KEGG</term><def><p id="Par12">Kyoto Encyclopaedia of Genes and Genomes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KOR</term><def><p id="Par13">kappa Opioid Receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MF</term><def><p id="Par14">Gene Ontology Molecular Function</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MHC</term><def><p id="Par15">Myosin Heavy Chain</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>miRNA</term><def><p id="Par16">micro-RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>mRNA</term><def><p id="Par17">messenger RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MSTN</term><def><p id="Par18">Myostatin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MYOD/1</term><def><p id="Par19">Myogenic differentiation 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NADP</term><def><p id="Par20">Nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OR</term><def><p id="Par21">Opioid Receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PD</term><def><p id="Par22">Parkinson’s Disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PPI</term><def><p id="Par23">Protein-protein interaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PSICQUIC</term><def><p id="Par24">Protein Standard Initiative Common Query Interface</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TCA</term><def><p id="Par25">The Citric Acid (Kreb’s) Cycle</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TR</term><def><p id="Par26">Trained rest cohort</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UE</term><def><p id="Par27">Untrained exercise cohort</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UR</term><def><p id="Par28">Untrained rest cohort</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WD</term><def><p id="Par29">Work Day</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="60769" pm="."><plain><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60770" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12864-017-4007-9) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="60771" pm="."><plain>We would like to acknowledge the access to horses facilitated by trainer JS Bolger and assistance from B O’Connor, P O’Donovan and yard staff at Glebe House Stables, Coolcullen, Co. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60772" pm="."><plain>Kilkenny, Ireland. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par85"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="60773" pm="."><plain>This publication has emanated from research conducted with the financial support of Science Foundation Ireland under grant number 11/PI/1166. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par86"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="60774" pm="."><plain>The data sets generated for this paper are included within the article and the associated additional files. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60775" pm="."><plain>The RNA-seq aligned sequence files (BAM format) are available from the EBI ArrayExpress (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress)">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress)</ext-link> under accession number E-MTAB-5447. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval</title><p id="Par87"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="60776" pm="."><plain>University College Dublin Animal Research Ethics Committee approval, a Department of Health License (B100/3525) and explicit owner/trainer informed consent were obtained for the use of all horses and procedures in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>KB performed the downstream bioinformatics analysis, interpreted results and wrote the manuscript. BAM contributed to study design, performed RNA-seq data analysis and contributed to writing the manuscript. GF was involved in sample collection, prepared the samples and contributed to RNA-seq analysis. PAM contributed to study design and implemented an RNA-seq data pre-processing pipeline. CLM was involved in phenotyping and sample collection. KFG was involved in phenotyping and sample collection. DEM contributed to study design and manuscript preparation. LMK designed the study, coordinated phenotyping and sample collection and contributed to manuscript preparation. EWH conceived and designed the study, was involved in phenotyping and sample collection and contributed to results interpretation and writing the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes></SecTag><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par88">All authors read and approved the final manuscript</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par89">None of the authors has any financial or personal relationships that could inappropriately influence or bias the content of the paper. EWH and DEM are shareholders in Plusvital Ltd., an equine nutrition and genetic testing company. Plusvital Ltd. has been granted a license for commercial use of data contained within patent applications: United States Provisional Serial Number 61/136553 and Irish patent application number 2008/0735, Patent Cooperation Treaty filing: A method for predicting athletic performance potential, September 7, 2009. EWH, DEM and LMK are named on the applications. The patent contents are not related to this manuscript. Plusvital Ltd. had no part in the research in the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher’s Note</title><p id="Par90">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="60777" pm="."><plain><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hinchcliff</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaneps</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Geor</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Equine exercise physiology: the science of exercise in the athletic horse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60778" pm="."><plain>New York</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Saunders/Elsevier</publisher-name></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="60779" pm="."><plain><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dingboom</surname><given-names>EGDG</given-names></name><name><surname>Enzerink</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>van Oudheusden</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Weijs</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postnatal muscle fibre composition of the gluteus medius muscle of Dutch Warmblood foals; maturation and the influence of exercise</article-title><source>Equine Vet J</source><year>1999</year><volume>31</volume><issue>Suppl</issue><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>100</lpage></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="60780" pm="."><plain><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rivero</surname><given-names>JLL</given-names></name><name><surname>Talmadge</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Edgerton</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation between myofibrillar ATPase activity and myosin heavy chain composition in equine skeletal muscle and the influence of training</article-title><source>Anat Rec</source><year>1996</year><volume>246</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0185(199610)246:2&lt;195::AID-AR6&gt;3.0.CO;2-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8888961?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8888961</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="60781" pm="."><plain><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawley</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The molecular bases of training adaptation</article-title><source>Sports Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>37</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>763</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00007256-200737090-00001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17722947?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17722947</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="60782" pm="."><plain><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Quiroz-Rothe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivero</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early and long-term changes of equine skeletal muscle in response to endurance training and detraining</article-title><source>Pflugers Arch</source><year>2000</year><volume>441</volume><issue>2–3</issue><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004240000408</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11211112?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11211112</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="60783" pm="."><plain><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rivero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>MARTI-KORFF</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution of exercise intensity and duration to training-linked myosin transitions in thoroughbreds</article-title><source>Equine Vet J</source><year>2006</year><volume>38</volume><issue>S36</issue><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2042-3306.2006.tb05559.x</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="60784" pm="."><plain><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokuriki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of high intensity training on anaerobic capacity of middle gluteal muscle in thoroughbred horses</article-title><source>Res Vet Sci</source><year>2004</year><volume>76</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2003.08.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14672857?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14672857</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="60785" pm="."><plain><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lacombe</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinchcliff</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions of substrate availability, exercise performance, and nutrition with muscle glycogen metabolism in horses</article-title><source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source><year>2003</year><volume>223</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1576</fpage><lpage>1585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.2003.223.1576</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14664443?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14664443</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="60786" pm="."><plain><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Derave</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Everaert</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Beeckman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baguet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Muscle carnosine metabolism and β-alanine supplementation in relation to exercise and training</article-title><source>Sports Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>40</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/11530310-000000000-00000</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20199122?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20199122</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="60787" pm="."><plain><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avellini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiaradia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaiti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of exercise training, selenium and vitamin E on some free radical scavengers in horses (Equus Caballus)</article-title><source>Comp Biochem Physiol B: Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>123</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0305-0491(99)00045-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10425718</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="60788" pm="."><plain><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barrey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Valette</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jouglin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Blouin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Langlois</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heritability of percentage of fast myosin heavy chains in skeletal muscles and relationship with performance</article-title><source>Equine Vet J</source><year>1999</year><volume>31</volume><issue>S30</issue><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2042-3306.1999.tb05236.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10454086</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="60789" pm="."><plain><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Valberg</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mickelson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>McCue</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Haplotype diversity in the equine myostatin gene with focus on variants associated with race distance propensity and muscle fiber type proportions</article-title><source>Anim Genet</source><year>2014</year><volume>45</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>827</fpage><lpage>835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/age.12205</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25160752?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25160752</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="60790" pm="."><plain><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>McGivney</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiston</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>MacHugh</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A genome-wide SNP-association study confirms a sequence variant (g. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60791" pm="."><plain>66493737C&gt; T) in the equine myostatin (MSTN) gene as the most powerful predictor of optimum racing distance for Thoroughbred racehorses</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-11-552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20044946</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="60792" pm="."><plain><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrell</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Conte</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagberg</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Frequent sequence variation in the human myostatin (GDF8) gene as a marker for analysis of muscle-related phenotypes</article-title><source>Genomics</source><year>1999</year><volume>62</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/geno.1999.5984</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10610713?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10610713</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="60793" pm="."><plain><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eivers</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>McGivney</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Govindarajan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>MacHugh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A sequence polymorphism in MSTN predicts sprinting ability and racing stamina in thoroughbred horses</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e8645</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008645</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20098749?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20098749</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="60794" pm="."><plain><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Binns</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boehler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of the myostatin locus (MSTN) as having a major effect on optimum racing distance in the thoroughbred horse in the USA</article-title><source>Anim Genet</source><year>2010</year><volume>41</volume><issue>s2</issue><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2052.2010.02126.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21070290?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21070290</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="60795" pm="."><plain><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tozaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakoi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gawahara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A genome-wide association study for racing performances in thoroughbreds clarifies a candidate region near the MSTN gene</article-title><source>Anim Genet</source><year>2010</year><volume>41</volume><issue>s2</issue><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2052.2010.02095.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21070273?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21070273</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="60796" pm="."><plain><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hill EW, Ryan DP, MacHugh DE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60797" pm="."><plain>Horses for courses: a DNA-based test for race distance aptitude in thoroughbred racehorses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60798" pm="."><plain>Recent Pat DNA Gene Sequences, 2012. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60799" pm="."><plain>6(3):203–8.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="60800" pm="."><plain><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGivney</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>MacHugh</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiston</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MSTN genotypes in thoroughbred horses influence skeletal muscle gene expression and racetrack performance</article-title><source>Anim Genet</source><year>2012</year><volume>43</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>810</fpage><lpage>812</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2052.2012.02329.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22497477?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22497477</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="60801" pm="."><plain><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mickelson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rendahl</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Valberg</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Axelsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bannasch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Binns</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide analysis reveals selection for important traits in domestic horse breeds</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e1003211</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003211</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23349635?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23349635</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="60802" pm="."><plain><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Golland</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Skeletal muscle adaptations to prolonged training, overtraining and detraining in horses</article-title><source>Pflugers Arch</source><year>1998</year><volume>436</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004240050648</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9644221?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9644221</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="60803" pm="."><plain><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McCutcheon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinchcliff</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sams</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Training-induced alterations in glucose metabolism during moderate-intensity exercise</article-title><source>Equine Vet J</source><year>2002</year><volume>34</volume><issue>S34</issue><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2042-3306.2002.tb05386.x</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="60804" pm="."><plain><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pilegaard</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ordway</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Saltin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Neufer</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional regulation of gene expression in human skeletal muscle during recovery from exercise</article-title><source>Am J Physiol-Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2000</year><volume>279</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>E806</fpage><lpage>E814</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11001762?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11001762</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="60805" pm="."><plain><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Flück M, Hoppeler H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60806" pm="."><plain>Molecular basis of skeletal muscle plasticity-from gene to form and function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60807" pm="."><plain>In: Rev Physiol Biochem Pharmacol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60808" pm="."><plain>Springer Berlin Heidelberg; 2003. p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60809" pm="."><plain>159–216.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="60810" pm="."><plain><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lally</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Holloway</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Heigenhauser</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Spriet</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Repeated transient mRNA bursts precede increases in transcriptional and mitochondrial proteins during training in human skeletal muscle</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>588</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>4795</fpage><lpage>4810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2010.199448</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20921196?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20921196</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="60811" pm="."><plain><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Timmons</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Szkop</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple sources of bias confound functional enrichment analysis of global-omics data</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-015-0761-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25583448</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="60812" pm="."><plain><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGivney</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Eivers</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>MacHugh</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>MacLeod</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Gorman</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional adaptations following exercise in thoroughbred horse skeletal muscle highlights molecular mechanisms that lead to muscle hypertrophy</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-10-638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19121221</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="60813" pm="."><plain><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGivney</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>McGettigan</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Loftus</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>MacHugh</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the equine skeletal muscle transcriptome identifies novel functional responses to exercise training</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-11-398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20044946</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="60814" pm="."><plain><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McGlynn</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kharazyan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exercise influences circadian gene expression in equine skeletal muscle</article-title><source>Vet J</source><year>2014</year><volume>201</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2014.03.028</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24888677?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24888677</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="60815" pm="."><plain><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eivers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McGivney</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>MacHugh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PGC-1α encoded by the PPARGC1A gene regulates oxidative energy metabolism in equine skeletal muscle during exercise</article-title><source>Anim Genet</source><year>2012</year><volume>43</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2052.2011.02238.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22404351?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22404351</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="60816" pm="."><plain><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Eivers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McGivney</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>MacHugh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moderate and high intensity sprint exercise induce differential responses in COX4I2 and PDK4 gene expression in thoroughbred horse skeletal muscle</article-title><source>Equine Vet J</source><year>2010</year><volume>42</volume><issue>s38</issue><fpage>576</fpage><lpage>581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2042-3306.2010.00206.x</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="60817" pm="."><plain><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eivers</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>McGivney</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>MacHugh</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Menson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivero</surname><given-names>J-LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alterations in oxidative gene expression in equine skeletal muscle following exercise and training</article-title><source>Physiol Genomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>40</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physiolgenomics.00041.2009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19861432?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19861432</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="60818" pm="."><plain><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Breuer K, Foroushani AK, Laird MR, Chen C, Sribnaia A, Lo R, Winsor GL, Hancock RE, Brinkman FS, Lynn DJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60819" pm="."><plain>InnateDB: systems biology of innate immunity and beyond—recent updates and continuing curation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60820" pm="."><plain>Nucleic Acids Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60821" pm="."><plain>2012;41(D1):D1228–D1233.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="60822" pm="."><plain><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charitou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using biological networks to integrate, visualize and analyze genomics data</article-title><source>Genet Sel Evol</source><year>2016</year><volume>48</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12711-016-0205-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26743767</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="60823" pm="."><plain><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvunis</surname><given-names>A-R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramesh</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ideker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrative approaches for finding modular structure in biological networks</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg3552</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24045689?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24045689</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="60824" pm="."><plain><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartwell</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopfield</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Leibler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From molecular to modular cell biology</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1999</year><volume>402</volume><fpage>C47</fpage><lpage>C52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35011540</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10591225?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10591225</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="60825" pm="."><plain><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinayagam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Dephoure</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gygi</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrimon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The hippo signaling pathway interactome</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2013</year><volume>342</volume><issue>6159</issue><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>740</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1243971</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24114784?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24114784</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="60826" pm="."><plain><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozawa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comprehensive two-hybrid analysis to explore the yeast protein interactome</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>4569</fpage><lpage>4574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.061034498</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11283351?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11283351</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="60827" pm="."><plain><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Belcastro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambesi-Impiombato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Bernardo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How to infer gene networks from expression profiles</article-title><source>Mol Syst Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>78</fpage><?supplied-pmid 17299415?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17299415</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="60828" pm="."><plain><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Regev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pe'er</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Koller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Module networks: identifying regulatory modules and their condition-specific regulators from gene expression data</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2003</year><volume>34</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1165</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12740579?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12740579</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="60829" pm="."><plain><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Koller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discovering molecular pathways from protein interaction and gene expression data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2003</year><volume>19</volume><issue>suppl 1</issue><fpage>i264</fpage><lpage>i272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btg1037</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12855469?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12855469</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="60830" pm="."><plain><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barabasi</surname><given-names>A-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Oltvai</surname><given-names>ZN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Network biology: understanding the cell's functional organization</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg1272</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14735121?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14735121</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="60831" pm="."><plain><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Padi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Quackenbush</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrating transcriptional and protein interaction networks to prioritize condition-specific master regulators</article-title><source>BMC Syst Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12918-015-0228-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25582171</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="60832" pm="."><plain><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Barabási</surname><given-names>A-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Oltvai</surname><given-names>ZN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lethality and centrality in protein networks</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>411</volume><issue>6833</issue><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35075138</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11333967?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11333967</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="60833" pm="."><plain><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clauset</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Finding community structure in very large networks</article-title><source>Phys Rev E</source><year>2004</year><volume>70</volume><issue>6</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevE.70.066111</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="60834" pm="."><plain><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pons P, Latapy M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60835" pm="."><plain>Computing communities in large networks using random walks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60836" pm="."><plain>In: International Symposium on Computer and Information Sciences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60837" pm="."><plain>Istanbul, Turkey - October 26-28, 2005. p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60838" pm="."><plain>284–293.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="60839" pm="."><plain><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Goenawan IH, Bryan K, Lynn DJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60840" pm="."><plain>DyNet: visualization and analysis of dynamic molecular interaction networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60841" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60842" pm="."><plain>2016;32(17):2713–5.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="60843" pm="."><plain><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kerrien S, Aranda B, Breuza L, Bridge A, Broackes-Carter F, Chen C, Duesbury M, Dumousseau M, Feuermann M, Hinz U. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60844" pm="."><plain>The IntAct molecular interaction database in 2012. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60845" pm="."><plain>Nucleic Acids Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60846" pm="."><plain>2011;40(Database issue):D841–6.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="60847" pm="."><plain><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NetworkAnalyst for statistical, visual and network-based meta-analysis of gene expression data</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>823</fpage><lpage>844</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2015.052</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25950236?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25950236</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="60848" pm="."><plain><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ideker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozier</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwikowski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discovering regulatory and signalling circuits in molecular interaction networks</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2002</year><volume>18</volume><issue>suppl 1</issue><fpage>S233</fpage><lpage>S240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/18.suppl_1.S233</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12169552?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12169552</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="60849" pm="."><plain><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards the identification of protein complexes and functional modules by integrating PPI network and gene expression data</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-13-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22214541</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="60850" pm="."><plain><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Spellman</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cluster analysis and display of genome-wide expression patterns</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><issue>25</issue><fpage>14863</fpage><lpage>14868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.25.14863</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9843981?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9843981</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="60851" pm="."><plain><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valette</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>JOUGLIN</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>COUROUCE</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Auvinet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Flaux</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Standardisation of muscular biopsy of gluteus medius in French trotters</article-title><source>Equine Vet J</source><year>1999</year><volume>31</volume><issue>S30</issue><fpage>342</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2042-3306.1999.tb05246.x</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="60852" pm="."><plain><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Krueger F, Kreck B, Franke A, Andrews SR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60853" pm="."><plain>FastQC: a quality control tool for high throughput sequence data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60854" pm="."><plain>Nature methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60855" pm="."><plain>2012;9(2):145–51.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="60856" pm="."><plain><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dobin A, Davis CA, Schlesinger F, Drenkow J, Zaleski C, Jha S, Batut P, Chaisson M, Gingeras TR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60857" pm="."><plain>STAR: ultrafast universal RNA-seq aligner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60858" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60859" pm="."><plain>2013;29(1):15–21.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="60860" pm="."><plain><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Handsaker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wysoker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fennell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Homer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Marth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Abecasis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The sequence alignment/map format and SAMtools</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>2078</fpage><lpage>2079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp352</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19505943?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505943</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="60861" pm="."><plain><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FeatureCounts: an efficient general purpose program for assigning sequence reads to genomic features</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2014</year><volume>30</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>923</fpage><lpage>930</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt656</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24227677?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24227677</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="60862" pm="."><plain><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ritchie ME, Phipson B, Wu D, Hu Y, Law CW, Shi W, Smyth GK. limma powers differential expression analyses for RNA-sequencing and microarray studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60863" pm="."><plain>Nucleic Acids Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60864" pm="."><plain>2015;43(7):e47.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="60865" pm="."><plain><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>EdgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19910308?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="60866" pm="."><plain><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kasprzyk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BioMart: driving a paradigm change in biological data management</article-title><source>Database</source><year>2011</year><volume>2011</volume><fpage>bar049</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/database/bar049</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22083790?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22083790</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="60867" pm="."><plain><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolinski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwight</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eppig</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/75556</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10802651?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10802651</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="60868" pm="."><plain><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Croft</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundo</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Haw</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Milacic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Caudy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Garapati</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamdar</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Reactome pathway knowledgebase</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>42</volume><issue>D1</issue><fpage>D472</fpage><lpage>D477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt1102</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24243840?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24243840</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="60869" pm="."><plain><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirakawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokimatsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>KEGG for linking genomes to life and the environment</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>36</volume><issue>suppl 1</issue><fpage>D480</fpage><lpage>D484</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18077471?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18077471</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="60870" pm="."><plain><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fresno C, Fernández EA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60871" pm="."><plain>RDAVIDWebService: a versatile R interface to DAVID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60872" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60873" pm="."><plain>2013;29(21):2810–1.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="60874" pm="."><plain><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hosack</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lempicki</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identifying biological themes within lists of genes with EASE</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2003-4-10-r70</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="60875" pm="."><plain><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orchard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerrien</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aranda</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhate</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bidwell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bridge</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Briganti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Brinkman</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cesareni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein interaction data curation: the international molecular exchange (IMEx) consortium</article-title><source>Nat Meth</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1931</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="60876" pm="."><plain><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>del-Toro</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumousseau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Orchard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Galeota</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Launay</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Goll</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Breuer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Salwinski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new reference implementation of the PSICQUIC web service</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>41</volume><issue>W1</issue><fpage>W601</fpage><lpage>W606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt392</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23671334?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23671334</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="60877" pm="."><plain><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Csardi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nepusz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The igraph software package for complex network research</article-title><source>InterJ, Complex Systems</source><year>2006</year><volume>1695</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="60878" pm="."><plain><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Opsahl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Agneessens</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Skvoretz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Node centrality in weighted networks: generalizing degree and shortest paths</article-title><source>Soc Networks</source><year>2010</year><volume>32</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socnet.2010.03.006</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="60879" pm="."><plain><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheney</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tails of unconventional myosins</article-title><source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source><year>1999</year><volume>56</volume><issue>3–4</issue><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s000180050426</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11212352?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11212352</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="60880" pm="."><plain><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fortier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornatowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>O'cain</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-related changes in serum insulin-like growth factor-I, insulin-like growth factor-I binding protein-3 and articular cartilage structure in thoroughbred horses</article-title><source>Equine Vet J</source><year>2005</year><volume>37</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2746/0425164054406838</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15651732?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15651732</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="60881" pm="."><plain><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barres</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Treebak</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Caidahl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Krook</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Gorman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zierath</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute exercise remodels promoter methylation in human skeletal muscle</article-title><source>Cell Metab</source><year>2012</year><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2012.01.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22405075?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22405075</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="60882" pm="."><plain><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitaoka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Aida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiraga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takemasa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of high-intensity training on lipid metabolism in thoroughbreds</article-title><source>Am J Vet Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>73</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1813</fpage><lpage>1818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/ajvr.73.11.1813</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23106469?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23106469</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="60883" pm="."><plain><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gygi</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiegelman</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Puigserver</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutrient control of glucose homeostasis through a complex of PGC-1α and SIRT1</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>434</volume><issue>7029</issue><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature03354</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15744310?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15744310</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="60884" pm="."><plain><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarr</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Boss</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Puigserver</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Isotani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional co-activator PGC-1α drives the formation of slow-twitch muscle fibres</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>418</volume><issue>6899</issue><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature00904</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12181572?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12181572</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="60885" pm="."><plain><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lucia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gómez-Gallego</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Barroso</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabadán</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandrés</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>San Juan</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chicharro</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekelund</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Brage</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Earnest</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PPARGC1A genotype (Gly482Ser) predicts exceptional endurance capacity in European men</article-title><source>J Appl Physiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>99</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>344</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.00037.2005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15705733?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15705733</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="60886" pm="."><plain><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Guerra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lupi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rönn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Granhall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Luthman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Masiello</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchetti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Groop</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Prato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epigenetic regulation of PPARGC1A in human type 2 diabetic islets and effect on insulin secretion</article-title><source>Diabetologia</source><year>2008</year><volume>51</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>622</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00125-007-0916-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18270681?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18270681</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="60887" pm="."><plain><label>78.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">McGivney B, Herdan C, Gough K, Katz L, Hill E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60888" pm="."><plain>Effect of training on PPARGC1A and FNDC5 gene expression in thoroughbred horses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60889" pm="."><plain>Equine Vet J 2014, 46(S46):35–35.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR79"><text><SENT sid="60890" pm="."><plain><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leek</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mudaliar</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathieu-Costello</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of acute exercise on citrate synthase activity in untrained and trained human skeletal muscle</article-title><source>Am J Phys Regul Integr Comp Phys</source><year>2001</year><volume>280</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>R441</fpage><lpage>R447</lpage></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR80"><text><SENT sid="60891" pm="."><plain><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitaoka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiraga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Takemasa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of training and detraining on monocarboxylate transporter (MCT) 1 and MCT4 in thoroughbred horses</article-title><source>Exp Physiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>96</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/expphysiol.2010.055483</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21148623?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21148623</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR81"><text><SENT sid="60892" pm="."><plain><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGowan</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Golland</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of prolonged training, overtraining and detraining on skeletal muscle metabolites and enzymes</article-title><source>Equine Vet J</source><year>2002</year><volume>34</volume><issue>S34</issue><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2042-3306.2002.tb05429.x</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR82"><text><SENT sid="60893" pm="."><plain><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vigelsø Hansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dela</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between skeletal muscle mitochondrial citrate synthase activity and whole body oxygen uptake adaptations in response to exercise training</article-title><source>Int J Physiol, Pathophysiol Pharmacol</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25057335</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR83"><text><SENT sid="60894" pm="."><plain><label>83.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fulco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiltz</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Iezzi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kashiwaya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Veech</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sartorelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sir2 regulates skeletal muscle differentiation as a potential sensor of the redox state</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1097-2765(03)00226-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12887892?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12887892</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR84"><text><SENT sid="60895" pm="."><plain><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantó</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerhart-Hines</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Feige</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagouge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Noriega</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Puigserver</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Auwerx</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AMPK regulates energy expenditure by modulating NAD+ metabolism and SIRT1 activity</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2009</year><volume>458</volume><issue>7241</issue><fpage>1056</fpage><lpage>1060</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07813</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19262508?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19262508</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR85"><text><SENT sid="60896" pm="."><plain><label>85.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NAD+/NADH and skeletal muscle mitochondrial adaptations to exercise</article-title><source>Am J Physiol-Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2012</year><volume>303</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>E308</fpage><lpage>E321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.00054.2012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22436696?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22436696</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR86"><text><SENT sid="60897" pm="."><plain><label>86.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tapscott</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The circuitry of a master switch: Myod and the regulation of skeletal muscle gene transcription</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2005</year><volume>132</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2685</fpage><lpage>2695</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.01874</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15930108?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15930108</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR87"><text><SENT sid="60898" pm="."><plain><label>87.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lippi G, Maffulli N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60899" pm="."><plain>Biological influence of physical exercise on hemostasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60900" pm="."><plain>In: In: Semin Thromb Hemost: 2009: © Thieme Medical Publishers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60901" pm="."><plain>New York. p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60902" pm="."><plain>269–76.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR88"><text><SENT sid="60903" pm="."><plain><label>88.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenbaum</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobilka</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The structure and function of G-protein-coupled receptors</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2009</year><volume>459</volume><issue>7245</issue><fpage>356</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08144</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19458711?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19458711</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR89"><text><SENT sid="60904" pm="."><plain><label>89.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colberg</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigal</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yardley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Riddell</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunstan</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dempsey</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Castorino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physical activity/exercise and diabetes: a position statement of the American Diabetes Association</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2016</year><volume>39</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2065</fpage><lpage>2079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc16-1728</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27926890?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27926890</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR90"><text><SENT sid="60905" pm="."><plain><label>90.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Correia SC, Santos RX, Perry G, Zhu X, Moreira PI, Smith MA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60906" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial importance in Alzheimer’s, Huntington’s and Parkinson’s diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60907" pm="."><plain>In: Neurodegenerative Diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60908" pm="."><plain>Springer US. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60909" pm="."><plain>2012; p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60910" pm="."><plain>205–21.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR91"><text><SENT sid="60911" pm="."><plain><label>91.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buchman</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loss of motor function in preclinical Alzheimer’s disease</article-title><source>Expert Rev Neurother</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/ern.11.57</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21539487?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21539487</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR92"><text><SENT sid="60912" pm="."><plain><label>92.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paillard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolland</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>de Souto</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective effects of physical exercise in Alzheimer's disease and Parkinson's disease: a narrative review</article-title><source>J Clin Neurol</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3988/jcn.2015.11.3.212</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26174783?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26174783</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR93"><text><SENT sid="60913" pm="."><plain><label>93.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chandra A, Sharma A, Calingasan NY, White JM, Shurubor Y, Yang XW, Beal MF, Johri A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60914" pm="."><plain>Enhanced mitochondrial biogenesis ameliorates disease phenotype in a full-length mouse model of Huntington’s disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60915" pm="."><plain>Hum Mol Genet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60916" pm="."><plain>2016;25(11):2269–82.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR94"><text><SENT sid="60917" pm="."><plain><label>94.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huberts</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Klei</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moonlighting proteins: an intriguing mode of multitasking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60918" pm="."><plain>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA)-Molecular</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>1803</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>520</fpage><lpage>525</lpage></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR95"><text><SENT sid="60919" pm="."><plain><label>95.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Reactome Opioid Receptor Pathway: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.reactome.org/content/detail/R-HSA-167427">http://www.reactome.org/content/detail/R-HSA-167427</ext-link>.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR96"><text><SENT sid="60920" pm="."><plain><label>96.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leslie JD, Mayor R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60921" pm="."><plain>Complement in animal development: unexpected roles of a highly conserved pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60922" pm="."><plain>Semin Immunol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60923" pm="."><plain>Elsevier US 2013; p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60924" pm="."><plain>39–46.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR97"><text><SENT sid="60925" pm="."><plain><label>97.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pankov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fibronectin at a glance</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>115</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>3861</fpage><lpage>3863</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.00059</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12244123?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12244123</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR98"><text><SENT sid="60926" pm="."><plain><label>98.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crameri</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Langberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnusson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Schrøder</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Olesen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Suetta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Teisner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kjaer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in satellite cells in human skeletal muscle after a single bout of high intensity exercise</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>558</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>340</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2004.061846</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15121802?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15121802</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR99"><text><SENT sid="60927" pm="."><plain><label>99.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chervin-Pétinot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Courçon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Almagro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grichine</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grunwald</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Prandini</surname><given-names>M-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulino-Debrac</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epithelial protein lost in neoplasm (EPLIN) interacts with α-catenin and actin filaments in endothelial cells and stabilizes vascular capillary network in vitro</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2012</year><volume>287</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>7556</fpage><lpage>7572</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M111.328682</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22194609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22194609</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR100"><text><SENT sid="60928" pm="."><plain><label>100.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Carnemolla A, Labbadia JP, Lazell H, Neueder A, Moussaoui S, Bates GP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60929" pm="."><plain>Contesting the dogma of an age-related heat shock response impairment: implications for cardiac-specific age-related disorders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60930" pm="."><plain>Hum Mol Genet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60931" pm="."><plain>2014;23(14):3641–56.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR101"><text><SENT sid="60932" pm="."><plain><label>101.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahuja</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Carobbio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Waltregny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>North</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Castronovo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Maechler</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of insulin secretion by SIRT4, a mitochondrial ADP-ribosyltransferase</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2007</year><volume>282</volume><issue>46</issue><fpage>33583</fpage><lpage>33592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M705488200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17715127?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17715127</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR102"><text><SENT sid="60933" pm="."><plain><label>102.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Baur</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmona</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamming</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza-Pinto</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohr</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutrient-sensitive mitochondrial NAD+ levels dictate cell survival</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>130</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1095</fpage><lpage>1107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2007.07.035</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17889652?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17889652</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR103"><text><SENT sid="60934" pm="."><plain><label>103.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clémençon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Babot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Trézéguet</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mitochondrial ADP/ATP carrier (SLC25 family): pathological implications of its dysfunction</article-title><source>Mol Asp Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>34</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mam.2012.05.006</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR104"><text><SENT sid="60935" pm="."><plain><label>104.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Predmore</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefer</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gojon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrogen sulfide in biochemistry and medicine</article-title><source>Antioxid Redox Signal</source><year>2012</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ars.2012.4612</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22432697?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22432697</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR105"><text><SENT sid="60936" pm="."><plain><label>105.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Módis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Coletta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdélyi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Papapetropoulos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intramitochondrial hydrogen sulfide production by 3-mercaptopyruvate sulfurtransferase maintains mitochondrial electron flow and supports cellular bioenergetics</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2013</year><volume>27</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.12-216507</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23104984?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23104984</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR106"><text><SENT sid="60937" pm="."><plain><label>106.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carlin</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartelt</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Siekevitz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of fodrin as a major calmodulin-binding protein in postsynaptic density preparations</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1983</year><volume>96</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.96.2.443</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 6833363?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6833363</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR107"><text><SENT sid="60938" pm="."><plain><label>107.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fedorov</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name><surname>Goropashnaya</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tøien</surname><given-names>Ø</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Showe</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Showe</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative functional genomics of adaptation to muscular disuse in hibernating mammals</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><year>2014</year><volume>23</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>5524</fpage><lpage>5537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mec.12963</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25314618?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25314618</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR108"><text><SENT sid="60939" pm="."><plain><label>108.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Andres-Mateos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mejias</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Leinwand</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Merriman</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hibernating squirrel muscle activates the endurance exercise pathway despite prolonged immobilization</article-title><source>Exp Neurol</source><year>2013</year><volume>247</volume><fpage>392</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.expneurol.2013.01.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23333568?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23333568</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR109"><text><SENT sid="60940" pm="."><plain><label>109.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Myburgh</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Storey</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myostatin levels in skeletal muscle of hibernating ground squirrels</article-title><source>J Exp Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>214</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>2522</fpage><lpage>2527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jeb.055764</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21753045?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21753045</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR110"><text><SENT sid="60941" pm="."><plain><label>110.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Squire</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coordinate expression of the PDK4 gene: a means of regulating fuel selection in a hibernating mammal</article-title><source>Physiol Genomics</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physiolgenomics.00076.2001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11842126?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11842126</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR111"><text><SENT sid="60942" pm="."><plain><label>111.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Titus</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Motors: unleashing mitochondria</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>R1076</fpage><lpage>R1078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2009.10.053</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20064407?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20064407</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR112"><text><SENT sid="60943" pm="."><plain><label>112.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kremerskothen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Plaas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kindler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Frotscher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnekow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synaptopodin, a molecule involved in the formation of the dendritic spine apparatus, is a dual actin/α-actinin binding protein</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2005</year><volume>92</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-4159.2004.02888.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15659229?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15659229</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR113"><text><SENT sid="60944" pm="."><plain><label>113.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ly</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Verstreken</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitochondria at the synapse</article-title><source>Neuroscientist</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1073858406287661</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16840705?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16840705</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR114"><text><SENT sid="60945" pm="."><plain><label>114.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Removing bias against membrane proteins in interaction networks</article-title><source>BMC Syst Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1752-0509-5-169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21194489</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR115"><text><SENT sid="60946" pm="."><plain><label>115.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakakibara</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Santolini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakim</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Maire</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Six homeoproteins and a linc-RNA at the fast MYH locus lock fast myofiber terminal phenotype</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e1004386</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004386</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24852826?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24852826</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR116"><text><SENT sid="60947" pm="."><plain><label>116.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwaller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhoot</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrbova</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicotera</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pette</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bluethmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunziker</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prolonged contraction-relaxation cycle of fast-twitch muscles in parvalbumin knockout mice</article-title><source>Am J Phys Cell Phys</source><year>1999</year><volume>276</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>C395</fpage><lpage>C403</lpage></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR117"><text><SENT sid="60948" pm="."><plain><label>117.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyer-Guittaut</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Poillet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Bôle-Richard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Benavides</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakrama</surname><given-names>F-Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraichard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Darley-Usmar</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Despouy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of GABARAPL1/GEC1 in autophagic flux and mitochondrial quality control in MDA-MB-436 breast cancer cells</article-title><source>Autophagy</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>986</fpage><lpage>1003</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/auto.28390</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24879149?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24879149</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR118"><text><SENT sid="60949" pm="."><plain><label>118.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruchas</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chavkin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinase cascades and ligand-directed signaling at the kappa opioid receptor</article-title><source>Psychopharmacology</source><year>2010</year><volume>210</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00213-010-1806-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20401607?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20401607</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR119"><text><SENT sid="60950" pm="."><plain><label>119.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Land</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruchas</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemos</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Melief</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chavkin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The dysphoric component of stress is encoded by activation of the dynorphin κ-opioid system</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4458-07.2008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18184783?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18184783</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR120"><text><SENT sid="60951" pm="."><plain><label>120.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruchas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Land</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chavkin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The dynorphin/kappa opioid system as a modulator of stress-induced and pro-addictive behaviors</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>1314</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2009.08.062</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19716811?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19716811</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR121"><text><SENT sid="60952" pm="."><plain><label>121.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ventura</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Genova</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Bovina</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Formiggini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenaz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of oxidative phosphorylation by Complex I in rat liver mitochondria: implications for aging</article-title><source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA)-Bioenergetics</source><year>2002</year><volume>1553</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0005-2728(01)00246-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11997134</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR122"><text><SENT sid="60953" pm="."><plain><label>122.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Castets P, Frank S, Sinnreich M, Rüegg MA. “Get the Balance Right”: Pathological Significance of Autophagy Perturbation in Neuromuscular Disorders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60954" pm="."><plain>J Neuromuscul Dis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60955" pm="."><plain>2016;3(2):127–55.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR123"><text><SENT sid="60956" pm="."><plain><label>123.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwalm</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Benoit</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Naslain</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Prémont</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Prévet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Thienen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Deldicque</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Francaux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of autophagy in human skeletal muscle is dependent on exercise intensity and AMPK activation</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2015</year><volume>29</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>3515</fpage><lpage>3526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.14-267187</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25957282?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25957282</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR124"><text><SENT sid="60957" pm="."><plain><label>124.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masiero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Agatea</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mammucari</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaauw</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Loro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Metzger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Reggiani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiaffino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Autophagy is required to maintain muscle mass</article-title><source>Cell Metab</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2009.10.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19945408?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19945408</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR125"><text><SENT sid="60958" pm="."><plain><label>125.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Autophagy, mitochondria and oxidative stress: cross-talk and redox signalling</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>2012</year><volume>441</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BJ20111451</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22187934?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22187934</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR126"><text><SENT sid="60959" pm="."><plain><label>126.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassik</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Moresi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exercise-induced BCL2-regulated autophagy is required for muscle glucose homeostasis</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>481</volume><issue>7382</issue><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10758</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22258505?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22258505</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR127"><text><SENT sid="60960" pm="."><plain><label>127.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Klionsky</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of autophagy is required for muscle homeostasis during physical exercise</article-title><source>Autophagy</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1405</fpage><lpage>1406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/auto.7.12.18315</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22082869?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22082869</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR128"><text><SENT sid="60961" pm="."><plain><label>128.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delbridge</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mellor</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myocardial autophagic energy stress responses—macroautophagy, mitophagy, and glycophagy</article-title><source>Am J Phys Heart Circ Phys</source><year>2015</year><volume>308</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>H1194</fpage><lpage>H1204</lpage></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR129"><text><SENT sid="60962" pm="."><plain><label>129.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruchas</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Macey</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chavkin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kappa opioid receptor activation of p38 MAPK is GRK3-and arrestin-dependent in neurons and astrocytes</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>281</volume><issue>26</issue><fpage>18081</fpage><lpage>18089</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M513640200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16648139?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16648139</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR130"><text><SENT sid="60963" pm="."><plain><label>130.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Q-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective interference of β-arrestin 1 with κ and δ but not μ opioid receptor/G protein coupling</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><issue>38</issue><fpage>24328</fpage><lpage>24333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.273.38.24328</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9733719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9733719</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR131"><text><SENT sid="60964" pm="."><plain><label>131.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Desagher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Glowinski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Prémont</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pyruvate protects neurons against hydrogen peroxide-induced toxicity</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>9060</fpage><lpage>9067</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9364052?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9364052</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR132"><text><SENT sid="60965" pm="."><plain><label>132.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaelin</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratcliffe</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxygen sensing by metazoans: the central role of the HIF hydroxylase pathway</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>30</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2008.04.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18498744?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18498744</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR133"><text><SENT sid="60966" pm="."><plain><label>133.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kam</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphatidylinositol-3 kinase is distinctively required for μ-, but not κ-opioid receptor-induced activation of c-Jun N-terminal kinase</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2004</year><volume>89</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-4159.2004.02338.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15056283?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15056283</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR134"><text><SENT sid="60967" pm="."><plain><label>134.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaneto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonner-Weir</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of c-Jun N-terminal kinase in oxidative stress-mediated suppression of insulin gene expression</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><issue>33</issue><fpage>30010</fpage><lpage>30018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M202066200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12011047?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12011047</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR135"><text><SENT sid="60968" pm="."><plain><label>135.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delavar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nogueira</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Metzger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Breen</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Skeletal myofiber VEGF is essential for the exercise training response in adult mice</article-title><source>Am J Phys Regul Integr Comp Phys</source><year>2014</year><volume>306</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>R586</fpage><lpage>R595</lpage></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR136"><text><SENT sid="60969" pm="."><plain><label>136.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakatogawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohsumi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamics and diversity in autophagy mechanisms: lessons from yeast</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>458</fpage><lpage>467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm2708</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19491929?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19491929</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR137"><text><SENT sid="60970" pm="."><plain><label>137.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Miah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Culbreth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aschner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Autophagy in neurodegenerative diseases and metal neurotoxicity</article-title><source>Neurochem Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>41</volume><issue>1–2</issue><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11064-016-1844-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26869037?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26869037</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
