<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Musculoskelet Disord</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Musculoskelet Disord</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Musculoskeletal Disorders</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2474</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5778649</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1945</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12891-018-1945-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="69029" pm="."><plain>Radiological changes do not influence clinical mid-term outcome in stemless humeral head replacements with hollow screw fixation: a prospective radiological and clinical evaluation </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Heuberer</surname><given-names>Philipp R.</given-names></name><address><email>philipp.heuberer@kh-herzjesu.at</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brandl</surname><given-names>Georg</given-names></name><address><email>georg.brandl@kh-herzjesu.at</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pauzenberger</surname><given-names>Leo</given-names></name><address><email>leo.pauzenberger@kh-herzjesu.at</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Laky</surname><given-names>Brenda</given-names></name><address><email>brenda.laky@kh-herzjesu.at</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kriegleder</surname><given-names>Bernhard</given-names></name><address><email>bernhard.kriegleder@kh-herzjesu.at</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Anderl</surname><given-names>Werner</given-names></name><address><email>werner.anderl@kh-herzjesu.at</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>St. Vincent Shoulder and Sports Clinic Vienna, Baumgasse 20A, 1030 Vienna, Austria </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Austrian Research group for Regenerative and Orthopedic Medicine (AURROM), Vienna, Austria </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>28</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="69030" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="69031" pm="."><plain>Stemless shoulder arthroplasty is a fairly new concept. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69032" pm="."><plain>Clinical and radiological follow-up is essential to prove implant safety and concept. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69033" pm="."><plain>This prospective single-centre study was performed to evaluate the influence of radiological changes on clinical mid-term outcome following stemless humeral head replacement with hollow screw fixation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="69034" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par2"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="69035" pm="."><plain>Short- and mid-term radiological and clinical evaluations were performed in 73 consecutive shoulders treated mainly for idiopathic and posttraumatic osteoarthritis with stemless humeral head arthroplasty including 40 hemi- (HSA) and 33 total shoulder arthroplasties (TSA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69036" pm="."><plain>Operating times of stemless implantations were compared to 110 stemmed anatomical shoulder prostheses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69037" pm="."><plain>Appearances of humeral radiolucencies or radiological signs of osteolysis or stress shielding were assessed on standardized radiographs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69038" pm="."><plain>Patients’ clinical outcome was evaluated using the Constant score and patients’ satisfaction was documented. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="69039" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par3"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="69040" pm="."><plain>Radiological changes, detected in 37.0%, did not affect clinical outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69041" pm="."><plain>Constant scores significantly improved from baseline to short and mid-term follow-up (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69042" pm="."><plain>The majority of patients (96.2%) were satisfied with the procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69043" pm="."><plain>No loosening of the humeral head component was detected during a mean follow-up of 58 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69044" pm="."><plain>Operating times were significantly shorter with stemless compared to stemmed implants (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="69045" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par4"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="69046" pm="."><plain>Clinical mid-term outcome after stemless humeral head replacement was not affected by radiological changes. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="69047" pm="."><plain>Trial registration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par5"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="69048" pm="."><plain>The institutional review board (St. Vincent Hospital Vienna; 201212_EK01; date of issue: 11.12.2012) approved the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69049" pm="."><plain>The trial was registered at ClinicalTrials.gov (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02754024">NCT02754024</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69050" pm="."><plain>Retrospective registration. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Stemless shoulder arthroplasty</kwd><kwd>Mid-term outcome</kwd><kwd>Radiological and clinical results</kwd><kwd>Hemiarthroplasty</kwd><kwd>Anatomic shoulder arthroplasty</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="69051" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par9"><text><SENT sid="69052" pm="."><plain><bold>S</bold>houlder arthroplasty is the standard treatment for patients with severe shoulder osteoarthritis with numbers continually rising. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69053" pm="."><plain>Modern anatomically designed shoulder arthroplasty systems have proven to provide significant pain relief and improvement of function over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69054" pm="."><plain>Long-term survivorship is mostly affected by implant related complications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69055" pm="."><plain>Although loosening of the glenoid component is more common than stem related problems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], given the growing number of shoulder replacements and revision surgeries, the humeral side becomes increasingly clinically relevant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69056" pm="."><plain>Loosening is not the only indication for revision, as removal of the humeral stem is also required for implant unrelated complications such as infection or secondary rotator cuff tear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69057" pm="."><plain>In revision surgery, complications commonly arise with difficulty of stem removal, cement extraction, bone loss or osteolysis due to polyethylene wear debris, and intraoperative fracture associated with potentially longer operating times, increased risk of infection, nerve injuries, and worse outcome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69058" pm="."><plain>Shaft malunion after fracture, where the deformity does not allow an anatomic positioning of the humeral stem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], is another challenging situation to treat. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par10"><text><SENT sid="69059" pm="."><plain>An expedient alternative is humeral head resurfacing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69060" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, humeral resurfacing is a technically challenging procedure requiring at least 60% of intact humeral head [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69061" pm="."><plain>Firstly, it is mandatory to find the correct centre of rotation to avoid overstuffing and secondly with the remaining head in situ correct glenoid component implantation may be difficult [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par11"><text><SENT sid="69062" pm="."><plain>A contemporary, promising alternative are stemless anatomic shoulder implants, which generally rely on metaphyseal or meta- and epiphyseal fixation, combining the advantages of humeral head resurfacing and common shoulder replacement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69063" pm="."><plain>Potential benefits are (1) the possibility of anatomic shoulder reconstruction regardless of medial and posterior offset of the proximal humerus, caput-collum-diaphyseal angle, and retrotorsion of the humeral head; (2) the ability to perform implantation in fracture sequelae with shaft malunion and secondary post-fracture situations with humeral head deformities; (3) good glenoid exposure; (4) bone stock preservation; and (5) facilitating further revision surgery. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par12"><text><SENT sid="69064" pm="."><plain>The main purpose of this prospective study was to evaluate radiological changes around the humeral component of a stemless shoulder implant with hollow screw fixation and their influence on clinical outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69065" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that clinical mid-term outcome after stemless humeral head replacement would be affected by radiological changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69066" pm="."><plain>Secondary objectives were to compare operating times between stemless and stemmed hemi- and total shoulder arthroplasty and to report short and mid-term clinical outcome after stemless hemi- and total shoulder arthroplasty. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="69067" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par13"><text><SENT sid="69068" pm="."><plain>Between September 2005 and December 2011, a total of 136 shoulder arthroplasties using a stemless humeral head implant were performed by two experienced surgeons (W.A., B.K.) at our clinic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69069" pm="."><plain>The stemless humeral head replacement (Eclipse™ Shoulder Prosthesis, Arthrex Inc., Naples, FL, USA) consists of an anatomical humeral head, which is mounted on a baseplate (trunion) for cortical support at the anatomical neck (epiphyseal fixation) and fixated to the cancellous metaphyseal bone over a screw-in mechanism with a hollow screw (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>The stemless humeral head Eclipse prosthesis consists of three components: the anatomical humeral head; the trunion for epiphyseal fixation; and the hollow cage screw for metaphyseal fixation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69070" pm="."><plain>Published with permission from (Arthrex Inc., Naples, FL, USA)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12891_2018_1945_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par14"><text><SENT sid="69071" pm="."><plain>Indications for surgery included primary or secondary osteoarthritis of the shoulder with severe pain and limited function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69072" pm="."><plain>Patients with any kind of rotator cuff tears, cuff tear arthropathies, axillary nerve lesions, or revision arthroplasty were not suitable for this procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69073" pm="."><plain>HSA was indicated, when the glenoid presented without erosion and macroscopically fairly intact cartilage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69074" pm="."><plain>Included were all patients between 40 and 85 years of age at the time of surgery, who were scheduled for primary anatomical shoulder replacement for the treatment of degenerative, rheumatic, posttraumatic osteoarthritis and fracture sequelae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69075" pm="."><plain>Institutional review board approval (201212_EK01) was obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69076" pm="."><plain>The trial is registered at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> (NCT02754024). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par15"><text><SENT sid="69077" pm="."><plain>A total of 95 eligible patients with 100 stemless humeral head implants signed the written informed consent and were enrolled in the prospective trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69078" pm="."><plain>Patients who died or withdrew before the mid-term follow-up were excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69079" pm="."><plain>During the study period 11 patients died from unrelated causes (five before and six after the short follow-up) and one patient with bilateral implants withdrew from the study before the short follow-up due to an unexpected comorbidity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69080" pm="."><plain>A complete, prospectively collected data set before, two years (short follow-up) and at least 48 months (mid-term follow-up) after surgery, or until indicated revision surgery was required for inclusion of radiographic and clinical evaluation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par16"><text><SENT sid="69081" pm="."><plain>Additionally, operating times of a consecutive cohort of 93 patients (100 implants), who underwent anatomical shoulder arthroplasty with a stemmed anatomical shaft prostheses (Anatomical Shoulder™ System, Zimmer Inc., Warsaw, IN, USA) by the same two experienced surgeons (W.A., B.K.) at our clinic were obtain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="69082" pm="."><plain>Surgical procedure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par17"><text><SENT sid="69083" pm="."><plain>Patients were operated under general anaesthesia combined with an interscalene block. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69084" pm="."><plain>Through a standard deltopectoral approach after tenotomy of the subscapularis tendon and exposition of the humeral head, a resection at the anatomical neck was performed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par18"><text><SENT sid="69085" pm="."><plain>Thereafter, for the stemless procedure, the humeral head size was determined using templates and the best fitting length of a hollow screw, which allows trabecular ingrowth into the bone and fixation to the trunion, was assessed with a measure pin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69086" pm="."><plain>A hole for the cage screw was prepared with a hand coring reamer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69087" pm="."><plain>In case of glenoid replacement, a standard cemented all-polyethylene glenoid component (Arthrex Inc., Naples, FL, USA) was implanted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69088" pm="."><plain>Again the humeral head was exposed and with a centering device, the trunion of the previously determined head size was impacted for epiphyseal fixation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69089" pm="."><plain>Thereafter, the appropriate hollow screw was advanced until the screw head was flush with the neck of the trunion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69090" pm="."><plain>Finally, the correct humeral head was mounted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69091" pm="."><plain>The subscapularis tendon was reattached with two suture anchors (titanium Corkscrew FT-III, Arthrex) and the wound was closed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69092" pm="."><plain>Immediately postoperative, fluoroscopic images in two planes were taken to confirm correct implant positioning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69093" pm="."><plain>Routine follow-ups were scheduled two weeks, three months, one, two, and five years after the procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69094" pm="."><plain>The operating time from incision to final closure for each shoulder replacement was prospectively recorded. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par19"><text><SENT sid="69095" pm="."><plain>Postoperatively, the arm was secured with an abduction cushion (UltraSling, Breg MDSS GmbH, Hannover, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69096" pm="."><plain>The physiotherapy regimen included immediate passive motion and passive assisted motion with closed chain exercises to work scapula-thoracic muscles after up to seven days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69097" pm="."><plain>After six weeks patients were allowed to remove sling; active movements and strengthening exercises started six weeks after implantation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="69098" pm="."><plain>Clinical evaluation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par20"><text><SENT sid="69099" pm="."><plain>Pre- and postoperative clinical and functional investigations included the Constant Score [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] adjusted for age and gender [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69100" pm="."><plain>All clinical evaluations were performed by orthopaedic fellows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69101" pm="."><plain>A single subjective question categorized into very satisfied, satisfied, and unsatisfied was asked to evaluate patient satisfaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69102" pm="."><plain>Complications and necessity of revision surgery were recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69103" pm="."><plain>Clinical outcome before revision surgery was recorded, but not included in short- and mid-term analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="69104" pm="."><plain>Radiographic evaluation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par21"><text><SENT sid="69105" pm="."><plain>Pre-, peri-, two- and five-year postoperative radiographs of the humeral head in anteroposterior and axial view using a fully-digital 2-in-1 system (AXIOM Luminos dRF, Siemens, Munich, Germany) were assessed by one experienced radiologists (rater 2) and two experienced orthopaedic surgeons (rater 1 and 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69106" pm="."><plain>Differences in radiological ratings were discussed to find a consensus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69107" pm="."><plain>In case no consensus could be reached, the final decision was made by the senior author (rater 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69108" pm="."><plain>This grading was used for data analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par22"><text><SENT sid="69109" pm="."><plain>In the event of revision surgery, radiographs obtained before the second procedure were evaluated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69110" pm="."><plain>Presence of or progression of radiolucency, especially around the bone-implant interface, was recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69111" pm="."><plain>Five radiographic zones including the superior and inferior interface (zone 1 and 5) and the interface around the hollow screw (zones 2, 3, and 4) were assessed for radiolucent areas or osteolysis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Anteroposterior radiographs of the stemless humeral head implant showing five radiographic zones including the superior and inferior interface (zone 1 and 5) and the interfaces around the hollow screw (zones 2, 3, and 4), which were used for the assessment of radiolucency and osteolysis</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12891_2018_1945_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par23"><text><SENT sid="69112" pm="."><plain>A radiologic classification system for this specific implant was established using allocations for radiolucent lines similar to Cil et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], and for osteolysis and internal stress shielding similar to Raiss et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69113" pm="."><plain>Radiological findings were grouped into three groups: (group1) no lucency or osteolysis with minor radiolucent lines in one or more zones; (group2) minor radiological findings including major radiolucent lines or partial osteolysis in one or more zones; and (group3) major radiological findings and complete osteolysis in one or more zones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69114" pm="."><plain>Humeral head implants were considered to be at risk of loosening, if complete osteolysis was detectable in two or more zones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69115" pm="."><plain>Possible internal stress shielding (loss in bone density around the hollow screw) was also described. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="69116" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par24"><text><SENT sid="69117" pm="."><plain>For sample size calculation, we assumed that 20% of implants will present with radiological changes and that postoperative Constant scores of those patients will be approximately 70 (60–80) %. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69118" pm="."><plain>Thus, we assume that those patients without radiological changes (80% of patients) will have significantly better Constant scores (approximately 80 (70–90) %). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69119" pm="."><plain>If the true difference in mean Constant scores is 10% (independent <italic>t</italic>-test), we planned to study 10 patients with and 42 without radiological changes to be able to reject the null hypothesis that the population means of the two groups are equal with probability (power) 0.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69120" pm="."><plain>The Type I error probability associated with this test of this null hypothesis is 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69121" pm="."><plain>To account for exclusions and loss to follow-up we enrolled 100 cases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par25"><text><SENT sid="69122" pm="."><plain>Descriptive statistic was used to present patient characteristics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69123" pm="."><plain>Data distribution was assessed by a visual inspection of histograms and the Kolmogorov-Smirnov-test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69124" pm="."><plain>Categorical data were assessed using Fisher’s exact tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69125" pm="."><plain>Differences regarding age- and gender-adjusted Constant scores as well as operating times between two independent groups were calculated using independent t-tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69126" pm="."><plain>Paired t-tests were used to compare age- and gender-adjusted Constant scores between pre- and postoperative assessments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69127" pm="."><plain>Kappa statistic was performed to determine consistency regarding radiographic gradings among raters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69128" pm="."><plain>All data were analysed using SPSS software (PAWS Statistics 21; SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69129" pm="."><plain>Statistical significance was set at a <italic>p</italic>-value of &lt; 0.05 (two-sided). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="69130" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par26"><text><SENT sid="69131" pm="."><plain>Of the 83 patients (87 shoulders) who met inclusion criteria, 11 patients (three with bilateral implants) were lost to follow-up or had incomplete data (follow-up rate: 86.7%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69132" pm="."><plain>Demographics of 72 patients (73 shoulders; Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) were comparable between stemless HSA (<italic>n</italic> = 40) and TSA (<italic>n</italic> = 33) regarding age (68.0 ± 10.1 range, 44–84; vs. 67.2 ± 10.5 range, 40–83; <italic>p</italic> = 0.752); gender (female: 75.0% vs. 54.5%, <italic>p</italic> = 0.085); and indication (idiopathic osteoarthritis: 75.0% vs. 87.9%, posttraumatic osteoarthritis: 15.0% vs. 9.1%, humeral head necrosis: 7.5% vs. 3.0%, and instability arthritis: 2.5% vs. 0%, respectively; <italic>p</italic> = 0.500).<SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Patient demographics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Stemless humeral head replacement (<italic>n</italic> = 73)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Gender (n)</td><td>48 female (65.8%) / 24 male (1 bilateral; 34.2%)</td></tr><tr><td>Mean age at surgery (years)</td><td>67.6 (SD 10.2; range, 40–84)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Indications</td></tr><tr><td> idiopathic osteoarthritis (n)</td><td>59 (80.8%)</td></tr><tr><td> posttraumatic osteoarthritis (n)</td><td>9 (12.3%)</td></tr><tr><td> humeral head necrosis (n)</td><td>4 (5.5%)</td></tr><tr><td> instability arthritis (n)</td><td>1 (1.4%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Abbreviation</italic>: <italic>HSA</italic> hemi shoulder arthroplasty, <italic>SD</italic> standard deviation, <italic>TSA</italic> total shoulder arthroplasty</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par27"><text><SENT sid="69133" pm="."><plain>A comparison of the duration of the surgical procedure between stemless and stemmed HSA as well as TSA showed significantly shorter operating times for stemless shoulder arthroplasty (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of operating times between stemless and stemmed shoulder arthroplasties</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Operating Time<sup>a</sup><break/>(minutes)</th><th>Stemless</th><th>Stemmed</th><th><italic>p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>HSA</td><td>73.2 (SD, 17.8; range, 42–129)</td><td>95.1 (SD, 23.0; range, 35–143)</td><td>&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td>TSA</td><td>95.7 (SD, 20.3; range, 67–163)</td><td>120.7 (SD, 36.4; range, 53–249)</td><td>&lt; 0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Abbreviation</italic>: <italic>HSA</italic> Hemi Shoulder Arthroplasty, <italic>TSA</italic> Total Shoulder Arthroplasty</p><p><sup>a</sup>The values are given as the mean and standard deviation and range in parenthesis</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par28"><text><SENT sid="69134" pm="."><plain>Postoperative clinical assessment was performed after an average of 27.7 (22 to 37) months (short follow-up; <italic>n</italic> = 53) and 58.1 (48 to 87) months (mid-term follow-up; <italic>n</italic> = 53). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69135" pm="."><plain>Radiographs of patients with an indication for revision surgery (<italic>n</italic> = 7) or with revision surgery (<italic>n</italic> = 13) were assessed 38.3 (4 to 99) months postoperatively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69136" pm="."><plain>The reasons for revision surgery and those with an indication for a further procedure are listed in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69137" pm="."><plain>Revision surgery was mainly indicated for secondary glenoid erosion in patients with HSA (61.5%) and secondary rotator cuff tendon tear for patients with TSA (71.4%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69138" pm="."><plain>Not significant, but more patients with HSA (32.5%) compared with TSA (21.2%) were revised (<italic>p</italic> = 0.306). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69139" pm="."><plain>None of the patients required revision surgery for humeral implant loosening. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69140" pm="."><plain>Patients not requiring revision surgery showed no signs of glenoid erosion (HSA), stable glenoid components (TSA), and intact rotator cuff situations at final follow-up.<SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Reasons for Revision Surgery</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>HSA<break/>(<italic>n</italic> = 13)</th><th>TSA<break/>(<italic>n</italic> = 7)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Implant loosening of the humeral head component</td><td>0</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>Secondary glenoid erosion or</td><td>8</td><td>n.a.</td></tr><tr><td>Loosening of the glenoid component</td><td>n.a.</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>Secondary rotator cuff tendon tear (SSP or SSC)</td><td>4</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Postoperative SNOH fracture</td><td>0</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>others</td><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Abbreviation</italic>: <italic>HSA</italic> Hemi Shoulder Arthroplasty, <italic>n.a.</italic> not applicable, <italic>TSA</italic> Total Shoulder Arthroplasty, <italic>SNOH</italic> surgical neck of humeral, <italic>SSC</italic> Subscapularis, <italic>SSP</italic> Supraspinatus</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par29"><text><SENT sid="69141" pm="."><plain>Rater agreements for radiologic gradings were very good (rater 1 and 2: κ = 0.871, 95% confidence interval (CI): 0.764–0.978; rater 1 and 3: κ = 0.920, 95% CI: 0.833–1.000; rater 2 and 3: κ = 0.898, 95% CI: 0.802–0.994). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69142" pm="."><plain>While humeral implant loosening was not the reason for any revision surgery, according to radiological findings, 11.0% (8 of 73) of humeral head implants were found to be at risk of loosening considering complete osteolysis in two or more zones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69143" pm="."><plain>Only three of the 12 revised implants were radiologically at risk of humeral head loosening. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69144" pm="."><plain>However, radiological loosening could not be confirmed intraoperatively in those three TSA cases, which were revised for secondary rotator cuff tears. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69145" pm="."><plain>All other implants showed an uneventful progress over time (Figs. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Anteroposterior radiographs of a seventy-two-year-old woman made immediately after hemi shoulder arthroplasty (<bold>a</bold>), at the short-term follow-up showing no radiolucency or osteolysis (<bold>b</bold>), and at the mid-term follow-up showing osteophyte formation superior around the humeral head implant and inferior (<bold>c</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12891_2018_1945_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Anteroposterior radiographs of a forty-year-old man made immediately after total shoulder arthroplasty (<bold>a</bold>), at the short-term showing partial osteolysis at the inferior trunion bone interface (<bold>b</bold>), and at the mid-term follow-up showing stable partial inferior osteolysis and minor superior radiolucency (<bold>c</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12891_2018_1945_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par30"><text><SENT sid="69146" pm="."><plain>Radiological changes (group 2 and 3) were detected in 37.0% (HSA: 17.8%; TSA: 19.2%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69147" pm="."><plain>Partial osteolysis or major radiolucencies (group 2) were detected in 4.1% with HSA and in 2.7% with TSA, while complete osteolysis in one or more zones (group 3) was present in 13.7% in the HSA and 16.4% in the TSA-group (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par31"><text><SENT sid="69148" pm="."><plain>Patients with revision surgery did not have significantly more complete osteolysis in one or more zones than those without revision surgery (30.0% vs. 30.2%, <italic>p</italic> = 1.000; HSA: 15.4% vs. 29.6%, <italic>p</italic> = 0.451; TSA: 57.1% vs. 30.8%, <italic>p</italic> = 0.377, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69149" pm="."><plain>Internal stress shielding, defined as reduced bone mineral density around the hollow screw, was seen in 42.5% of patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69150" pm="."><plain>The number of implants showing internal stress shielding did not differ between patients with and without a revision procedure (25.0% vs. 47.2%, <italic>p</italic> = 0.112; HSA: 30.8% vs. 48.1%, <italic>p</italic> = 0.333; TSA: 14.3% vs. 46.2%, <italic>p</italic> = 0.202, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69151" pm="."><plain>Further details regarding radiological outcome are provided in Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>.<SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Radiological Outcome with Stemless Humeral Head Replacement at Final Follow-Up</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>HSA<break/>(<italic>n</italic> = 27)</th><th>HSA REV<break/>(<italic>n</italic> = 13)</th><th>TSA<break/>(<italic>n</italic> = 26)</th><th>TSA REV<break/>(<italic>n</italic> = 7)</th><th>TOTAL<break/>(<italic>n</italic> = 73)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Group 1</td><td rowspan="2">18</td><td rowspan="2">9 (4 s OA + 4 s RCT<break/>+ 1 undefined pain)</td><td rowspan="2">16</td><td rowspan="2">3 (1 s RCT + 1 HH Fx<break/>+  1 undefined pain)</td><td rowspan="2">46</td></tr><tr><td>no RL/OL or minor RL in one or more zones</td></tr><tr><td> No radiolucency</td><td>16</td><td>7</td><td>12</td><td>3</td><td>38</td></tr><tr><td> Zone 1 (minor RL)</td><td>1</td><td>2</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td> Zone 5 (minor RL)</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>2</td><td>0</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td> Zone 1 (minor RL) + Zone 5 (minor RL)</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Group 2</td><td rowspan="2">1</td><td rowspan="2">2 (2 s OA)</td><td rowspan="2">2</td><td rowspan="2">0</td><td rowspan="2">5</td></tr><tr><td>major RL or partial OL in one or more zones</td></tr><tr><td> Zone 1 (major RL)</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>2</td><td>0</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td> Zone 1 (partial OL) + Zone 5 (partial OL)</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Group 3</td><td rowspan="2">8</td><td rowspan="2">2 (2 s OA)</td><td rowspan="2">8</td><td rowspan="2">4 (4 s RCT)</td><td rowspan="2">22</td></tr><tr><td>complete OL in one or more zones</td></tr><tr><td> Zone 1 (major OL)</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td> Zone 5 (major OL)</td><td>4</td><td>1</td><td>5</td><td>1</td><td>11</td></tr><tr><td> Zone 1(minorRL) + Zone 5 (majorOL)</td><td>2</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td> Zone 1(majorOL) + Zone 5 (majorOL)</td><td>2</td><td>1</td><td>2</td><td>3</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td>No internal stress shielding</td><td>13</td><td>9 (5 s OA + 3 s RCT<break/>+ 1 undefined pain)</td><td>14</td><td>6 (5 s RCT + 1 HH Fx)</td><td>42</td></tr><tr><td>Internal stress shielding in one zone (1, 2, or 4)</td><td>8</td><td>2 (2 s OA)</td><td>5</td><td>0</td><td>15</td></tr><tr><td>Internal stress shielding in two zones (12, 23, 24, or 34)</td><td>5</td><td>2 (1 s OA + 1 s RCT)</td><td>6</td><td>1 (1 undefined pain)</td><td>14</td></tr><tr><td>Internal stress shielding in three zones (125 or 234)</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Abbreviation</italic>: <italic>HH Fx</italic> Humeral Head Fracture, <italic>HSA</italic> Hemi Shoulder Arthroplasty, <italic>OL</italic> osteolysis, <italic>sec OA</italic> secondary Osteoarthritis, <italic>REV</italic> revision surgery, <italic>RL</italic> radiolucent line, <italic>sec RCT</italic> secondary Rotator Cuff Tear, <italic>TSA</italic> Total Shoulder Arthroplasty</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par32"><text><SENT sid="69152" pm="."><plain>Clinical outcome was not significantly affected by radiological changes (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).<SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Clinical mid-term outcome of 53 stemless humeral head replacements compared to radiological findings</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Radiological findings</th><th>N</th><th>Constant score (%)</th><th><italic>p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>No or minor radiological findings</td><td>37</td><td>78.9 (SD, 15.7; range, 30.5–101.2)</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">0.891</td></tr><tr><td>Major radiological findings</td><td>16</td><td>78.3 (SD, 15.8; range, 49.4–97.5)</td></tr><tr><td>No internal stress shielding</td><td>28</td><td>80.4 (SD, 15.6; range, 49.4–101.2)</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">0.411</td></tr><tr><td>Internal stress shielding<break/>in one or more zones</td><td>25</td><td>76.8 (SD, 15.7; range, 30.5–98.8)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par33"><text><SENT sid="69153" pm="."><plain>Clinical outcome has significantly improved from pre- to both postoperative follow-ups (37.7 ± 15.4% range, 2.4–80.5 vs. 78.8 ± 16.1% range, 40.2–104.9; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001; and vs. 78.7 ± 15.6% range, 30.5–101.2; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), but no significant changes (<italic>p</italic> = 0.947) were detectable between the follow-ups (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69154" pm="."><plain>TSA showed significantly better clinical outcome than HSA at short and mid-term follow-up (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69155" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, at the mid-term follow-up 96.2% of the patients were very satisfied (15 HSA, 20 TSA) or satisfied (10 HSA, 6 TSA).<SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Clinical outcome between hemi- (HSA; <italic>n</italic> = 27) and total shoulder arthroplasty (TSA; <italic>n</italic> = 26) at baseline (HSA: 38.8 ± 17.0% vs. TSA: 36.6 ± 13.9%, <italic>p</italic> = 0.594), at short (HSA: 74.0 ± 16.5% vs. TSA: 83.9 ± 14.4%, <italic>p</italic> = 0.024) and mid-term follow-up (HSA: 73.5 ± 17.3% vs. TSA: 84.2 ± 11.6%, <italic>p</italic> = 0.011)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12891_2018_1945_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></SecTag> </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="69156" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par34"><text><SENT sid="69157" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have been reporting radiological and clinical findings after stemless anatomical shoulder arthroplasty; however, to our knowledge we are the first to compare radiological findings to clinical mid-term outcome in a prospective single-centre trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69158" pm="."><plain>We were not only able to show that clinical and radiological results with the stemless shoulder prosthesis showed favourable improvements from pre- to short and mid-term outcome with no revision surgery due to humeral component loosening, we also had to reject our hypothesis that radiological changes would negatively impact clinical outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69159" pm="."><plain>Constant scores were not significantly different between patients with and without radiological changes in the mid-term follow-up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par35"><text><SENT sid="69160" pm="."><plain>Recently, comparable Constant scores were detected by Habermeyer et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69161" pm="."><plain>In accordance to the literature for stemmed shoulder arthroplasty, TSA showed significantly higher relative Constant Scores than HSA in this study, and values remained stable over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69162" pm="."><plain>As the present study and current literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] demonstrated, stemless shoulder arthroplasty provides similar clinical results as established stemmed arthroplasty systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69163" pm="."><plain>The main focus of our study was the radiologic behaviour of the implant and its influence on clinical outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69164" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the present results regarding radiolucencies and osteolysis are rather different to the findings of Habermeyer et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], who reported an osteolysis rate of not more than 4%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69165" pm="."><plain>Such variations could be explained by the fact that radiographs were assessed and classified differently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69166" pm="."><plain>While we adapted a rather concise nomenclature, Habermeyer did not provide detailed information regarding the classification protocol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69167" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the presence of osteolysis did not affect clinical outcome or revision rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69168" pm="."><plain>Comparable to Habermeyer’s findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], internal stress shielding occurred in half of the implants in one or more zones with the majority around the greater tuberosity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69169" pm="."><plain>Again, no influence on clinical outcome could be seen in either study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par36"><text><SENT sid="69170" pm="."><plain>The majority of abnormal radiological findings occurred either in the superior part of the trunion or in the inferior implant bone interface near the calcar, often leading to partial osteolysis similar to the already known phenomenon described by Raiss [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69171" pm="."><plain>Radiolucencies in the superior and inferior parts of the trunion could be explained with the results of finite element analyses (FEA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69172" pm="."><plain>FEA suggested that superposition of force and moment induced stresses in weak inferior cortical bone support is leading to higher migration values within the inferior trunion-bone interface and is therefore resulting in a shift of the centre of rotation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69173" pm="."><plain>The bone adaptation and resorption around the implant is mostly dependent on the stability of the hollow screw and is caused by axial bending stiffness similar to the concept explained by Nagels et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69174" pm="."><plain>Since such radiological findings were not reflected in the clinical outcome, an arbitrary definition of an implant at risk had to be established. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69175" pm="."><plain>Thus, we assumed that if an implant showed the presence of osteolysis in two or more zones, the humeral head component might become unstable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par37"><text><SENT sid="69176" pm="."><plain>Currently, few different stemless shoulder implant systems are on the market with sporadic report of short-term outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69177" pm="."><plain>A major strengths of the Eclipse prosthesis is that it is the only implant with a different fixation mechanism not relying on impaction implantation and therefore avoiding a potential risk of metaphyseal fracture or implant migration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par38"><text><SENT sid="69178" pm="."><plain>Revision surgeries followed an already well-known pattern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69179" pm="."><plain>In hemiarthroplasties the majority of revisions were due to secondary glenoid erosion (20.5%), which was similar to other studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69180" pm="."><plain>Secondary cuff failure was the main cause for revision (15.2%) in total shoulder arthroplasty. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69181" pm="."><plain>The higher revision rate due to secondary rotator cuff ruptures in the present trial compared to rates (&lt; 8%) reported by Sperling et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] could be explained with the relatively high mean age in the TSA-group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69182" pm="."><plain>Other than that, reasons for revision were traumatic surgical neck of humerus fracture, undefined pain for neglected long head of biceps tendon, and symptomatic mes acromion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69183" pm="."><plain>However, no revision surgery was indicated due to humeral component loosening or polyethylene glenoid component loosening in this patient cohort. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par39"><text><SENT sid="69184" pm="."><plain>Fortunately, but not surprisingly, revision surgery with such a stemless implant compared to stemmed prostheses were fairly easy as the removal of the humeral component does not require any special manoeuvres (e.g. osteotomy) and leaves a rather anatomic situation with the whole metaphysis in place. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par40"><text><SENT sid="69185" pm="."><plain>Last but not least, shorter operating times, another strength of stemless humeral head surgery, with HSA as well as with TSA in comparison with a stemmed anatomic shoulder arthroplasty system could be observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69186" pm="."><plain>This fact is not surprising, but worth mentioning since 20 min less on operating time is a benefit for the patient regarding reduced anaesthesia time and blood loss, not to mention the advantage in time management and therefore cost effectiveness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69187" pm="."><plain>As the humeral component implantation is a rather easy procedure, which is also reflected by the significant shorter operating time compared to stemmed shoulder arthroplasty, the learning curve for this surgical technique is quite steep. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par41"><text><SENT sid="69188" pm="."><plain>Although results of this mid-term trial are promising, long-term outcome regarding implant stability needs to be reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69189" pm="."><plain>Another limitation is that in-depth subjective assessments (e.g. American Shoulder and Elbow Surgeons or quality of life scores) are missing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69190" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, assessment of bone mineral density in the humeral head prior to implantation would have been desirable as bone mineral density might influence implant ingrowth and the possible appearance of osteolysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69191" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, our institution does not offer the possibility to assess bone mineral density in the shoulder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69192" pm="."><plain>However, we believe that the present results outweigh these limitations by the thorough radiographic analysis demonstrating that radiological findings do not influence clinical outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69193" pm="."><plain>We speculate that in the future a humeral head replacement with a shaft may only be indicated under rare circumstances, while the majority of patients, at least according to our results, can be successfully treated with a stemless humeral head replacement. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="69194" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par42"><text><SENT sid="69195" pm="."><plain>Promising clinical mid-term results with or without minor radiographic findings suggest that the concept of this stemless humeral head prosthesis might be an expedient alternative to existing shoulder replacements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69196" pm="."><plain>Anatomical cutting of the humeral head and hollow screw fixation allow a familiar access to the glenoid combined with a shaft independent, less complex bone-sparing surgery along with shorter operating times and favourable revision situation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>FEA</term><def><p id="Par6">Finite element analyses</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HSA</term><def><p id="Par7">Hemi shoulder arthroplasties</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TSA</term><def><p id="Par8">Total shoulder arthroplasties (TSA)</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><p>The authors acknowledge the contribution of Dr. Sylvia Salem to this study.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par43">No funding was received for this study.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par44">The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec></ack></SecTag><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>WA and PRH made substantial contributions to conception and design; GB, LP, and BK collected data; PRH and BL performed analysis and interpretation of data; PRH, GB, LP, BL, BK, and WA have been involved in drafting the manuscript as well as revising it critically for important intellectual content. The final manuscript has been read and approved by all authors.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par45">The study was approved by the institutional review board of the St. Vincent Hospital Vienna, Austria (201212_EK01). The written informed consent was signed by all patients.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par46">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par47">The first (PRH) and senior author (WA) are consultants for Arthrex, Inc. However, the authors have not received any financial payments or other benefits related to the subject of this article. The other authors do not have any conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher’s Note</title><p id="Par48">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="69197" pm="."><plain><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bohsali</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>Bois</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirth</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complications of shoulder arthroplasty</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source><year>2017</year><volume>99</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.16.00935</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28145957?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28145957</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="69198" pm="."><plain><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sperling</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cofield</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Revision surgery following total shoulder arthroplasty: analysis of 2588 shoulders over three decades (1976 to 2008)</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source><year>2011</year><volume>93</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1513</fpage><lpage>1517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.93B11.26938</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22058304?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22058304</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="69199" pm="."><plain><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sajadi</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuckerman</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Revision shoulder arthroplasty: an analysis of indications and outcomes</article-title><source>J Shoulder Elb Surg</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>308</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jse.2009.05.016</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="69200" pm="."><plain><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Sperling</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cofield</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Schleck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complications of total shoulder arthroplasty: are they fewer or different?</article-title><source>J Shoulder Elb Surg</source><year>2006</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jse.2005.05.005</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="69201" pm="."><plain><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farng</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zingmond</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Krenek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Soohoo</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors predicting complication rates after primary shoulder arthroplasty</article-title><source>J Shoulder Elb Surg</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>557</fpage><lpage>563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jse.2010.11.005</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="69202" pm="."><plain><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iacobellis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Berizzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Biz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Camporese</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of proximal humeral fractures with reverse shoulder arthroplasty in elderly patients</article-title><source>Musculoskelet Surg</source><year>2015</year><volume>99</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12306-014-0331-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24917462?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24917462</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="69203" pm="."><plain><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shoulder arthroplasty for treatment of the sequelae of proximal humerus fractures</article-title><source>Orthopade</source><year>2007</year><volume>36</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1037</fpage><lpage>1049</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00132-007-1157-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17960361?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17960361</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="69204" pm="."><plain><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kontakis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tosounidis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Galanakis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Megas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prosthetic replacement for proximal humeral fractures</article-title><source>Injury</source><year>2008</year><volume>39</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1345</fpage><lpage>1358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.injury.2008.09.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19036360?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19036360</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="69205" pm="."><plain><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>SEA</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cementless surface replacement arthroplasty of the shoulder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69206" pm="."><plain>5- to 10-year results with the Copeland mark-2 prosthesis</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source><year>2001</year><volume>83</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.83B2.11238</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11284568?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11284568</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="69207" pm="."><plain><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pape</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Raiss</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldinger</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Loew</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of short-term results after CUP prosthesis with cemented glenoid components and total shoulder arthroplasty: a matched-pair analysis</article-title><source>Z Orthop Unfall</source><year>2010</year><volume>148</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>674</fpage><lpage>679</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0029-1186202</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20135592?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20135592</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="69208" pm="."><plain><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Constant CR, Murley AH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69209" pm="."><plain>A clinical method of functional assessment of the shoulder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69210" pm="."><plain>Clin Orthop Relat Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69211" pm="."><plain>1987;(214):160-164.</mixed-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="69212" pm="."><plain><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yian</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramappa</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Arneberg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The constant score in normal shoulders</article-title><source>J Shoulder Elb Surg</source><year>2005</year><volume>14</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>128</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jse.2004.07.003</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="69213" pm="."><plain><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Veillette</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-Sotelo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sperling</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Schleck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cofield</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Revision of the humeral component for aseptic loosening in arthroplasty of the shoulder</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source><year>2009</year><volume>91</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.91B1.21094</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19092008?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19092008</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="69214" pm="."><plain><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raiss</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Deutsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruckner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Loew</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boileau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Walch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radiographic changes around humeral components in shoulder arthroplasty</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source><year>2014</year><volume>96</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>e54</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.M.00378</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24695931?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24695931</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="69215" pm="."><plain><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Habermeyer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichtenberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tauber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Magosch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Midterm results of stemless shoulder arthroplasty: a prospective study</article-title><source>J Shoulder Elb Surg</source><year>2015</year><volume>24</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1463</fpage><lpage>1472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jse.2015.02.023</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="69216" pm="."><plain><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gartsman</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Roddey</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammerman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shoulder arthroplasty with or without resurfacing of the glenoid in patients who have osteoarthritis</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source><year>2000</year><volume>82</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/00004623-200001000-00004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10653081?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10653081</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="69217" pm="."><plain><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sperling</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cofield</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowland</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Minimum fifteen-year follow-up of Neer hemiarthroplasty and total shoulder arthroplasty in patients aged fifty years or younger</article-title><source>J Shoulder Elb Surg</source><year>2004</year><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>604</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jse.2004.03.013</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="69218" pm="."><plain><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Churchill</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuinard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiater</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Freehill</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>E</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Holloway</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lassiter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical and radiographic outcomes of the Simpliciti Canal-sparing shoulder arthroplasty system: a prospective two-year multicenter study</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source><year>2016</year><volume>98</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>552</fpage><lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.15.00181</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27053583?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27053583</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="69219" pm="."><plain><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huguet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>DeClercq</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rio</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Teissier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zipoli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><collab>Group T</collab></person-group><article-title>Results of a new stemless shoulder prosthesis: radiologic proof of maintained fixation and stability after a minimum of three years' follow-up</article-title><source>J Shoulder Elb Surg</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>852</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jse.2009.12.009</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="69220" pm="."><plain><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magosch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Habermeyer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachmaier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Metcalfe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biomechanics of metaphyseal fixed humeral head replacement</article-title><source>Obere Extremität</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11678-011-0150-0</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="69221" pm="."><plain><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagels</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stokdijk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozing</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stress shielding and bone resorption in shoulder arthroplasty</article-title><source>J Shoulder Elb Surg</source><year>2003</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mse.2003.22</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="69222" pm="."><plain><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Alami</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Baque</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Walch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Boileau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complications of unconstrained shoulder prostheses</article-title><source>J Shoulder Elb Surg</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>666</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jse.2010.11.017</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="69223" pm="."><plain><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sperling</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Walch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahoney</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuckerman</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complications in total shoulder arthroplasty</article-title><source>Instr Course Lect</source><year>2013</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23395020?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23395020</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="69224" pm="."><plain><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Osteoporosis and orthopedic surgery: effect of bone health on total joint arthroplasty outcome</article-title><source>Curr Rheumatol Rep</source><year>2013</year><volume>15</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>371</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11926-013-0371-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24085661?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24085661</pub-id></element-citation> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
