<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName archivearticle.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2196853</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">0104038</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200104038</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11449000</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Targeted ablation of NrCAM or ankyrin-B results in disorganized lens fibers leading to cataract formation </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moré</surname><given-names>Margret I.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kirsch</surname><given-names>Frank-P.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rathjen</surname><given-names>Fritz G.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x1c84c40N0x3631568">Max-Delbrück Center for Molecular Medicine, D-13092 Berlin, Germany</aff><author-notes><fn><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Address correspondence to Fritz G. Rathjen, Max-Delbrück-Center für Molekulare Medizin, Robert-Rössle-Strasse 10, D-13092 Berlin, Germany. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Tel.: 49-30-9406-3709. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Fax: 49-30-9406-3730. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>E-mail: rathjen@mdc-berlin.de </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>9</day><month>7</month><year>2001</year></pub-date><volume>154</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>4</month><year>2001</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2001</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>6</month><year>2001</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2001, The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike–No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The NgCAM-related cell adhesion molecule (NrCAM) is an immunoglobulin superfamily member of the L1 subgroup that interacts intracellularly with ankyrins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We reveal that the absence of NrCAM causes the formation of mature cataracts in the mouse, whereas significant pathfinding errors of commissural axons at the midline of the spinal cord or of proprioceptive axon collaterals are not detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Cataracts, the most common cause of visual impairment, are generated in NrCAM-deficient mice by a disorganization of lens fibers, followed by cellular disintegration and accumulation of cellular debris. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The disorganization of fiber cells becomes histologically distinct during late embryonic development and includes abnormalities of the cytoskeleton and of connexin50-containing gap junctions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, analysis of lenses of ankyrin-B mutant mice also reveals a disorganization of lens fibers at postnatal day 1, indistinguishable from that generated by the absence of NrCAM, indicating that NrCAM and ankyrin-B are required to maintain contact between lens fiber cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Also, these studies provide genetic evidence of an interaction between NrCAM and ankyrin-B. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>cell adhesion; Ig superfamily; L1 subgroup; cataract; axon outgrowth</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The transmembrane glycoprotein NgCAM-related cell adhesion molecule (NrCAM)* is a member of the L1 subgroup of immunoglobulin (Ig)-like cell adhesion proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>This subgroup is composed of NrCAM, neurofascin, close homologue of L1 (CHL1), and L1 itself in vertebrates, and neuroglian and tractin in invertebrates (Brümmendorf et al., 1998; Hortsch, 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Like L1, NrCAM contains six Ig-like domains and five fibronectin type III (FNIII)-like repeats, a hydrophobic stretch, and a highly conserved cytoplasmic segment (Grumet et al., 1991; Kayyem et al., 1992). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>A crucial role of the L1 subgroup of proteins in neural development is exemplified by a broad spectrum of neuroanatomical and neurological disorders caused by the knock out of the murine L1 gene (Dahme et al., 1997; Cohen et al., 1998; Demyanenko et al., 1999) and by mutations in the human L1 gene that affect the binding activity and trafficking of L1 (De Angelis et al., 1999; Moulding et al., 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>As also shown for other L1 subgroup members, NrCAM reveals a complex homo- and heterophilic binding pattern and is implicated in cell–cell contact processes (Mauro et al., 1992). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In in vitro bioassays it can promote axonal growth by binding to neurofascin, F11, or receptor protein tyrosine phosphatase (RPTP)β/ζ (Morales et al., 1993; Volkmer et al., 1996; Sakurai et al., 1997) and can mediate interactions between neurons and glial cells via axonin-1 (Suter et al., 1995). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In ovo antibody perturbation experiments indicate that NrCAM is important for commissural axons of the chicken spinal cord to grow across the midline through the floor plate and for proprioceptive axon collaterals to extend ventrally within the spinal cord (Stoeckli and Landmesser, 1995; Fitzli et al., 2000; Perrin et al., 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>NrCAM has also been found to be expressed specifically at the node of Ranvier in rat where it interacts with the cytoskeletal adaptor protein ankyrin-G (Lambert et al., 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Binding to ankyrin appears to be a common feature of L1 subfamily members and requires a highly conserved sequence within their cytoplasmic tails (Davis and Bennett, 1994). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>This interaction appears to be inhibited by tyrosine phosphorylation as demonstrated for neurofascin (Tuvia et al., 1997), whereas clustering of the L1 subfamily member neuroglian at adhesion sites activates ankyrin binding followed by a redistribution of spectrin (Jefford and Dubreuil, 2000). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In this paper, we describe the generation of NrCAM knock-out mice by gene targeting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The mice are viable and fertile, but smaller than heterozygous or wild-type littermates, and they show a slight motor defect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Although NrCAM−/− neurons, unlike wild-type, are unable to grow on neurofascin and F11 in cell culture, NrCAM−/− mice have no significant abnormalities on a histological level in any of their neural tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Also, unexpectedly, their commissural axons cross the spinal cord midline normally. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we observed cataract formation due to a loss of intercellular communication between lens fiber cells followed by disintegration of cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>A similar disorganization of lens fiber cells was also observed in ankyrin-B–deficient mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>These observations suggest that NrCAM and ankyrin-B–deficient mice might provide further insights into cataractogenesis, one of the most common causes of visual impairment (Francis et al., 1999, 2000; Graw, 1999). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The NrCAM locus and derivation of mutant mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>To study the function of NrCAM in an in vivo situation, we generated a mouse strain deficient for this gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>To do this, we first characterized the NrCAM locus surrounding the ATG using a mouse embryonic stem (ES) cell BAC clone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>A long and a short arm was subcloned from the BAC clone to construct the targeting vector to destroy the start codon within exon 4 (Fig. 1 a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Electroporated ES cells were screened for homologous recombination and used to create chimeric mice via blastocyst injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The correct integration of the targeting vector and a deletion of the ATG-containing exon was confirmed by Southern hybridization as shown in Fig. 1 b and using the PauI-NheI fragment (region deleted in the mutant) as probe (not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, the replacement of the ATG-containing exon by the neo cassette in the mutant mice was shown by PCR (Fig. 1 c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>To detect NrCAM at the protein level, we generated polyclonal antibodies against a glutathione S-transferase fusion protein of the FNIII domains 1–4 of NrCAM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemical studies and an immunoblot from brains of both wild-type and NrCAM-deficient mice (Fig. 1 d; not shown) show the absence of NrCAM in the mutants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>NrCAM gene disruption. (a) Map of the targeting vector, and of part of the genomic locus before and after homologous recombination with the targeting vector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The position of exons 5, 6, and 8 as well as the exon numbering was adopted from the human NrCAM locus (Dry et al., 2001). neo, PGKneopA cassette; tk, MC1TKpA cassette; H, HindIII; K, KpnI; S, SacI; P, PauI; B, BamHI; N, NheI; Sp, SpeI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Only relevant restriction sites are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The positions of the external Southern blot probe, as well as the PCR primers, are indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>(b) Southern blot of DNA from tail biopsies of wild-type, heterozygous, and homozygous mice, using the restriction enzymes BamHI and KpnI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>(c) PCR of genomic DNA using the primers Mimo71 and Moré1 (c), and the primers neoL1 and Moré1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>(d) Immunoblot blot analysis using whole brain from adult wild-type and NrCAM−/− mice using polyclonal antibody 463 against NrCAM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The NrCAM band is completely absent in the mutants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Additional bands are due to nonspecific binding activity of the antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>To demonstrate equal loading, a parallel blot was analyzed with polyclonal antibodies to L1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Molecular weight markers are indicated on the left. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Immunohistological studies using neural tissue as well as immunoblots of brain and lens tissue using a polyclonal antibody provided by M. Grumet also reveal that NrCAM is absent (not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="0104038f1"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>NrCAM-deficient mice develop a mature cataract </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>NrCAM-deficient mice are viable and fertile. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Although the gross anatomy of the nervous system appears normal, mutant mice develop a mature cataract in their lenses that becomes visible from the outside of the eye after 4 mo of age (Fig. 2 c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>This cataract development was found to be progressive: 1-mo-old mice had lenses that were slightly less translucent in the nuclear region than wild-type lenses, and 4-mo-old mice already had a white opaque lens center. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>9-mo-old mice had completely opaque lenses (Fig. 2 a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>However, we could observe some variance in the degree of opacity and size as demonstrated by the comparison of lenses of several 11-mo-old NrCAM−/− siblings (Fig. 2 b; compare also 4-mo-old lenses in Fig 2 a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Upon piercing mutant cataract lenses with forceps, material was extruded, indicating liquefication of secondary lens fibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>After removal of the lens capsule and its adhering tissue, only the hardened interior of primary lens fibers remained, looking not transparent like in wild-type but whitish, with an irregular surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>All adult NrCAM-deficient mice examined to date had a cataract indicating a penetrance of 100%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>NrCAM-deficient mice develop cataracts and reveal reduced body weight and motor disabilities. (a) Stages of cataract development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>From left to right: 1.5-mo-old NrCAM+/− lens; NrCAM−/− littermate; both lenses from 4-mo-old NrCAM−/− mouse; 9-mo-old NrCAM−/− lens; same magnification as in b. (b) Lens pairs from 11-mo-old NrCAM−/− siblings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>(c) Eye of a freshly killed 4-mo-old NrCAM mouse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>(d) Weights of NrCAM+/− and NrCAM−/− littermates during postnatal development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Black line and symbols, NrCAM+/− animals; light line and symbols, NrCAM−/− animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>(e) Rotarod test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The number of times the animals fell from the rod in 3 min is indicated for a nonmoving rod and the rod rotating with 6.5 rpm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Each animal was confronted without prior rod experience, first with the nonmoving rod, and after a recovery time, with the rotating rod. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="0104038f2"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>In addition to cataract formation, NrCAM deleted mice are slightly smaller and show a slight impairment of their motor abilities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>To analyze the occurrence of the growth deficit, we followed the weights of 12 littermates during postnatal development (Fig. 2 d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>At birth, most NrCAM−/− mice were already relatively lighter than their heterozygous littermates and, at postnatal day (P)9.5, all NrCAM-deficient mice were lighter than their same-sexed heterozygous control siblings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>At P15 to P35, the weight differences were most apparent; however, mutant animals stayed at ∼80% of the weight of their control siblings for their entire lifetime (not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>To analyze whether the absence of NrCAM had an effect on the motor ability, we tested female NrCAM-deficient mice and wild-type control mice of similar weight for their ability to stay on a motionless or rotating rotarod. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Generally, mutant mice fell from the rod at a higher frequency, especially when the rod was moving (Fig. 2 e). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Localization of NrCAM in the lens </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>NrCAM has been studied so far primarily in the developing nervous system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>To investigate its function in the formation of cataracts, we first analyzed the distribution of NrCAM and its extracellular ligands in chick as well as in mouse lenses at various developmental stages by histological methods and Western blotting. Fig. 3 a gives an overview of the lens architecture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Antibodies against NrCAM stain the cell surface of secondary fiber cells in mouse (Fig 3 c) as well as in chick sections (Fig. 3, d and e), showing regular staining patterns depending on the direction and position of the section. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The fiber cells are flattened hexagons in cross-section (Fig. 3, c and d), and the radial cell surfaces are highlighted more than the tangential cell surfaces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>A longitudinal section of the mouse or chick lens results in a pattern of parallel lines, each line representing the neighboring cell surfaces of two lens fiber cells (Fig. 3 e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The expression of NrCAM in the primary lens fibers was still visible in P12 mouse lenses, but very low in adult mouse lenses (not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, no NrCAM expression was observed in the lens epithelium or the lens capsule (Fig. 3 f), or the cell surface of fiber cells bordering the capsule (Fig. 3 g), indicating that the contact formation between lens epithelial cells and between lens fiber cells and capsule is not mediated by NrCAM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Expression of NrCAM in lens. (a) Schematic overview of an adult mouse lens as central longitudinal section. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The lens has a spheric shape with a symmetry around its rotational axis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>It contains primary lens fibers that are formed during early embryonic development and secondary lens fibers that are formed during later embryonic development and throughout life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The anterior end (pointing upwards) has a monolayer of epithelial cells that can divide and migrate towards the sides of the lens, followed by an elongation and maturation process, in which the nucleus and other organelles are lost and characteristics of secondary fiber cells are adopted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>For clarity, the capsule, epithelial cells, and lens fibers are not drawn to scale (adapted from Bassnett et al., 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>(b) Immunoblot of mouse lens proteins using 463 polyclonal antibody against NrCAM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Proteins of lenses from animals aged as indicated are loaded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>(c–e) Same magnification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>(c) Noncentral longitudinal section through 9-mo-old wild-type mouse secondary lens fibers stained with polyclonal antibodies against NrCAM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>(d) E14 chick noncentral longitudinal lens section stained with monoclonal antibody number 3 against chick NrCAM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>(e) E14 chick lens longitudinal section stained with polyclonal antibodies against NrCAM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>(f and g) Mouse P12 noncentral longitudinal lens sections stained with polyclonal antibodies against NrCAM. ca., capsule; ep., epithelium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>(f) side-front region with epithel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The outer edge of the capsule is marked. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>(g) Posterior edge of the lens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>(h and i) Immunoblots of E14 brain (B) and lens (L) lysates reveal that only NrCAM, but no other family members or extracellular NrCAM interaction partner is present in the lens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Since antibodies to anti-CHL1 or anti-RPTPβ/ζ are available only for mouse proteins, these were not tested in chick. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>For the other proteins, the chick immunoblot is shown for reasons of availability or quality of the antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Molecular weight markers are indicated on the left. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>(h) Expression of NrCAM, NrCAM homologues NgCAM (species homologue of mouse L1), neurofascin, and CHL1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Note that neurofascin is expressed in several molecular weight forms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>(i) Expression of extracellular NrCAM interaction partners F11, axonin-1, and RPTPβ/ζ. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="0104038f3"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Analysis of immunoblots of lens homogenates of mice or chick reveals that NrCAM is prominently expressed in the lens during postnatal development and that the expression is reduced during adulthood (Fig. 3 b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>No other L1 subfamily proteins, including the NrCAM ligand neurofascin, are expressed in the lens at any stage (Fig. 3 h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Also, other heterophilic extracellular ligands of NrCAM such as the F11 protein, axonin-1 or RPTPβ/ζ, are absent from the lens (Fig. 3 i). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, chick lens NrCAM is consistently slightly larger than chick brain NrCAM (Fig. 3 h), whereas mouse lens NrCAM has approximately the same size as the smaller of two almost comigrating bands of brain NrCAM (not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>These size differences might be due to posttranslational modifications such as glycosylation or to alternative splicing of its pre-mRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>In summary, the absence of the currently known NrCAM ligands suggests a homophilic binding mode of NrCAM between opposing lens fiber membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>However, heterophilic binding of NrCAM to a so far uncharacterized membrane protein expressed on lens fibers cannot be excluded. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Histological analysis of cataract development in NrCAM-deficient mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>To begin to understand the importance of NrCAM for the development and maintenance of a functional translucent lens, we investigated lenses of NrCAM−/− mice of different stages by standard histological methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>In mouse lenses of E14.5 embryos that consist predominantly of primary lens fibers, no significant morphological changes were observed in the NrCAM mutant (Fig. 4 a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>At E18, secondary lens fibers have developed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Even though there are roundish large-appearing cells especially at the anterior pole close to the suture in the mutant, most of the fiber cells remain ordered in the transition zone as in wild type (Fig. 4, b and c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Also, at P12 there are many fiber cells remaining in a somewhat ordered context, in particular in the periphery, but the number of rounded disoriented cells among the secondary lens fibers increases towards the nucleus of the lens (Fig. 4 d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>By 2 mo, the regular wild-type pattern (Fig. 4 e) of cross-sectioned secondary lens fibers is severely disturbed in the NrCAM−/− lens (Fig. 4 f), as shown here for the region around the posterior pole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The cell shape and arrangement is still most ordered for the cells that have migrated inwards from the epithelium more recently (Fig. 4 g, upper right). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>But even among these cells, there are some cells that start to round up, becoming shorter and thicker (arrow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Other cells have lost their integrity completely, creating distinct zones of cellular debris (Fig. 4 g, *). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Persisting cells are intensely stained, rounded, and have lost their orientation (Fig. 4 g, arrowhead). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>At regions half-way to the center of the lens, especially at the posterior region, we observe deformed cells that have lost contact to each other completely (Fig. 4 h). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Cataract histology of NrCAM-deficient mice. From the emergence of secondary lens fibers onwards, NrCAM-deficient lens fibers develop a rounded instead of elongated shape, indicating loss of cell–cell contact. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The phenotype is progressive and leads to a disintegration of lens fibers and accumulation of cellular debris. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>(a) NrCAM−/− E14.5 longitudinal section, HE stained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>(b and c) NrCAM−/− E18 longitudinal sections, HE stained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>(d) NrCAM−/− P12 noncentral longitudinal section, anterior region, TB stained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>(c–k) Positions of sections in the lens are indicated in l. (e) 2-mo-old wild-type posterior region in noncentral longitudinal section, HE stained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>(f) Same as e, but with NrCAM−/−. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>(g–h) 2-mo-old NrCAM−/− central longitudinal section, TB stained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>(g) One-third of the way to the center side-front region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>(h) Half-way to the center posterior region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>(i–k) 8-mo-old NrCAM−/− lens in longitudinal noncentral section, HE stained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>(i) Marginal region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>(j) Anterior region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>(k) Posterior region. *Cellular debris; arrowheads, intensely stained rounded cell; arrows, examples of secondary fiber cells in the process of rounding up due to contact loss of neighboring cells; open arrows, cells in the process of disintegration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="0104038f4"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>At the age of 8 mo, the cataract has progressed even further. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The only intact region remains the zone of inward migrating cells at the lens equator, but even these cells start to round up soon (Fig. 4 i, arrow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>In Fig. 4 j, even the cells directly below the epithelium appear swollen and are in the process of losing touch with neighboring cells (compare with Fig. 4 g). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The lens now contains a large amount of liquefied cellular debris that may develop due to metabolic imbalances (Fig. 4 j). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The cells towards the posterior pole (Fig. 4 k) also exhibit less integrity than in the 2-mo-old lens (compare with Fig. 4 f). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The primary lens fibers of NrCAM−/− mice show no abnormalities at E14 (Fig. 4 a), and only slight irregularities can be observed at P12 (not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>In the adult, they become less ordered and less elongated than in wild type, but due to their rigidity, a solid lens nucleus is preserved (not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>At all stages, the lens epithelium of NrCAM−/− lenses appears to be normal; however, the posterior lens capsule was observed to be thinner (Fig. 4 f) than in heterozygous or wild-type controls in some cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>In contrast to cataracts caused by some other mutations, there is no vacuole formation at any stage in NrCAM−/− lenses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The cornea, iris, ciliary body, and retina do not show any abnormalities on a histological level (not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Disorganization of lens fibers in the absence of ankyrin-B </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>NrCAM, as well as other L1 subfamily members, have been shown to interact with the cytoskeletal linker proteins of the ankyrin family that associate via spectrin with F-actin (Davis and Bennett, 1994; Tuvia et al., 1997; Jefford and Dubreuil, 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>To study whether the interaction between NrCAM and ankyrin is important for the development of lens structure, we first analyzed the expression of ankyrins in lens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>To date, there are three different ankyrin genes known. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Western blot analysis using a polyclonal antibody against ankyrins previously revealed that lens ankyrin did not comigrate with erythrocyte ankyrin, but instead had the molecular weight as would be expected of ankyrin-B (Dola et al., 1990). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Consistently, specific monoclonal antibodies confirm the presence of ankyrin-B, but not ankyrin-G, in the lens (Fig. 5 a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Examination of the staining pattern of ankyrin-B in the secondary lens fibers by immunohistological methods (Fig. 5 b) shows that the pattern of localization matches that of NrCAM (Fig. 3 c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Like NrCAM, ankyrin-B is also not expressed at the cell membranes of fiber cells contacting the capsule, nor in the capsule itself (Fig. 5 d); however, ankyrin-B is expressed in the epithelial cells (Fig. 5 c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>This localization of ankyrin-B makes an interaction between these two proteins in lens fiber cells likely. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Ankyrin-B but not -G is expressed in the lens. (a) Immunoblot of brain and lens lysates using antibodies against ankyrin-B or -G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The molecular weight markers are indicated on the left. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>(b) Longitudinal noncentral section of 9-mo-old mouse lens stained with antibodies against ankyrin-B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>(c) Same as b, but anterior region showing expression of ankyrin-B in the epithelium but not the capsule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>(d) P12 longitudinal lens section showing that the lens fiber membranes neighboring the capsule do not express ankyrin-B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The capsule position is indicated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="0104038f5"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>For this reason, we reanalyzed whether ankyrin-B−/− mice previously generated (Scotland et al., 1998) also develop a disorganized lens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Since most ankyrin-B−/− mice do not survive beyond P1, we had to analyze the lenses of ankyrin-B−/− mice at this stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the organization of secondary lens fibers at the anterior pole was severely disturbed in the ankyrin-B−/− lenses (Fig. 6 , a and b), closely resembling the lenses of NrCAM−/− mice at a similar stage (Fig. 4, b and c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the lenses of control siblings revealed an ordered arrangement of lens fibers (Fig. 6, c and d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Even though the lens epithelium strongly expresses ankyrin-B, its absence had no significant effect on the organization of epithelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The observation that the absence of the cytoskeletal linker protein ankyrin-B results in a disorganization of lens fiber cells similar to that observed in the absence of NrCAM suggests that NrCAM mediated cell–cell contact between lens fibers requires a direct link to the actin cytoskeleton. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The absence of ankyrin-B causes similar lens fiber disorganization as the absence of NrCAM. (a and b) Longitudinal section through a P0.5 ankyrin-B−/− lens, HE stained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Arrows, rounded abnormal shaped cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>(c and d) Longitudinal section through a P0.5 ankyrin-B+/+ sibling lens, HE stained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>(e) Longitudinal section through a P1 ankyrin-B−/− lens, stained with the F-actin stain FITC-phalloidin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Arrows, aggregates of F-actin. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="0104038f6"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>To investigate the effect of the absence of ankyrin-B on the organization of F-actin, we performed phalloidin staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Abnormal cellular arrangement at the anterior pole of 1-d-old ankyrin-B−/− mice was also detected using this staining method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>In addition the stain was nonuniform and some F-actin aggregates were observed (Fig. 6 e, filled arrowheads). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Consistently, similar cytoskeletal disturbances were observed in NrCAM−/− lenses at this stage (not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>NrCAM was still targeted to the plasma membrane in ankyrin-B–deficient lenses, however, we observed a tendency to a more nonuniform membrane distribution in rounded lens cells (not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Disorganization of F-actin and Connexin50 in NrCAM-deficient mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>At P12 abnormally shaped NrCAM−/− lens fibers also show irregularities in their F-actin, including some aggregates (Fig. 7 a, filled arrowheads). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Other cells, mostly cells of the marginal zone that originated from dividing epithelial cells more recently, still show a normal uniform F-actin distribution below their membranes, resembling wild-type cells (Fig. 7 a, open arrowheads). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>By the age of 2.5 mo, the cataractous lens shows severe disorganization of the actin cytoskeleton, including F-actin aggregates below the entire membrane surface of rounded cells (Fig. 7 b, filled arrowheads). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>A normal F-actin arrangement only remains within cells very close to the marginal zone (Fig. 7 b, open arrowheads). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The cellular debris as well as some lens fibers in the process of disintegration are devoid of F-actin (not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Ankyrin-B is capable of binding to spectrin, which in turn binds to actin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Consistently, the distribution of ankyrin-B in NrCAM-deficient lenses resembled that of F-actin, including aggregate formation (not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Disorganization of F-actin and connexin50 in the absence of NrCAM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>(a and b) P12 and 2.5-mo-old, respectively, lateral-anterior longitudinal section through an NrCAM−/− lens, stained with FITC-phalloidin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Filled arrowheads, examples of F-actin aggregates; open arrowheads, examples of bordering cell membranes with a still normal ordered F-actin arrangement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>(c and d) 1-mo-old lenses stained with monoclonal antibodies against the gap junctional protein connexin50. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>(c) wild type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>(d) NrCAM−/−. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Arrows, con-nexin50 aggregates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="0104038f7"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>To examine the effect of the absence of NrCAM on gap junctions, we performed immunohistological stains using antibodies against connexin50. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Although wild-type lenses have a regular arrangement of connexin50-containing gap junctions, 1-mo-old NrCAM-deficient lenses show a reduced number of these gap junctions especially towards inner layers of secondary lens fibers, and especially at the lens poles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>In addition, we observe aggregates of connexin50, especially in the more interior layers of secondary lens fibers that have a higher occurrence of abnormally shaped cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>We conclude that NrCAM is not required for the localization of connexin50 to gap junctions when they are first created, but that it is required for gap junction maintenance, most likely indirectly by enabling cell–cell contact. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Axonal pathfinding in the spinal cord and neurite outgrowth of NrCAM−/− cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Previous studies on NrCAM indicated a role for NrCAM in axonal pathfinding by in ovo antibody perturbation experiments (Stoeckli and Landmesser, 1995; Perrin et al., 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we analyzed the growth of commissural axons and proprioceptive axons of the spinal cord by dye tracing and immunohistological studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>In DiI tracings of E11.5, E12.5, and E13.5, commissural axons, followed by open book preparations (Fig. 8 , a and b), we found that commissural axons crossed the floor plate in NrCAM-deficient embryos as completely, as in heterozygous or wild-type controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>In seven E11.5 NrCAM-deficient embryos, we counted 676 single fluorescent commissural axons, and only 10 of them showed an aberrant growth, in that they grew rostrally or caudally on the ipsilateral side of the floor plate for a short distance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>However, 7 of these 10 axons still crossed the midline at a point more rostrally or caudally, and proceeded in the correct path after that. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>This amounts to a pathfinding error rate of 1.48%, a frequency comparable to that encountered in wild type (11 of 741 axons). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, significant pathfinding errors of commisural axons were also not observed in ankyrin-B–deficient mice (unpublished data). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Analysis of axonal pathfinding and neurite extension. In NrCAM-deficient mice, commissural axons cross the spinal cord midline (floor plate) as efficiently as in wild type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Rostral is up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>(a and b) Open book preparations of DiI tracing of E12.5 commissural axons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>(a) Heterozygote. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>(b) NrCAM−/−. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The broken lines indicate the location of the floor plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>(c and d) Immunostains of E15 proprioceptive neurons in forelimb region of the spinal cord using antibodies against parvalbumin reveal no differences in the pathfinding of proprioceptive collaterals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>(c) Wild-type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>(d) NrCAM−/−. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>(e–m) 24-h neurite outgrowth of whole brain embryonal neurons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Unlike wild type, NrCAM-deficient neurons are unable to grow on the subtrates F11 or neurofascin (NF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>However, they can grow on the complexes F11–tenascin-R or NF–tenascin-R (TN-R), since instead of NrCAM β1 integrins and at least one additional protein are used as receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>(e, h, and k) E12 wild-type neurons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>(f, g, i, j, l, and m) NrCAM−/− neurons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>(e and f) No substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>(g) Surface blocked with BSA, followed by incubation with TN-R before neuron seeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>(h and i) F11 as substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>(j) F11 as substrate, then BSA blockage and TN-R treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>(k and l) Neurofascin-Fc as substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>(m) Neurofascin-Fc as substrate, then BSA blockage and TN-R treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="0104038f8"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>One explanation of the slight motor defect observed for NrCAM−/− mice would be pathfinding errors of proprioceptive neurons in the spinal cord, since these neurons are responsible for sensing body positions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>However, a selective stain of these axons in E15 embryos using antibodies against parvalbumin revealed no significant abnormalities (Fig. 8, c and d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Further histological studies within the developing nervous system including retina, cerebellum, and spinal cord using antibodies to various neural proteins do not reveal any gross anatomical defects within NrCAM mutant mice (not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Previous cell culture analyzes using embryonal chicken tectal neurons show an inhibition of neurite growth on immobilized F11 or neurofascin (Morales et al., 1993; Volkmer et al., 1996) by NrCAM antibodies, indicating that NrCAM acts as neuronal receptor protein for these substrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, if TN-R is complexed with F11 or neurofascin, β1 integrins and at least one additional protein are used as receptors (Volkmer et al., 1998; Zacharias et al., 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>To analyze these observations further, embryonic brains of control or NrCAM−/− mice were dissociated, and single cells were seeded on a surface coated with substrate proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>After 24-h incubation, NrCAM−/− neurite formation was absent or almost absent on F11 or neurofascin (Fig. 8, i and l), resembling the situation on uncoated culture dishes (Fig. 8, e and f), whereas wild-type neurons extended long neurites on F11 or neurofascin (Fig. 8, h and k). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>As expected, growth on poly-l-lysine or laminin-1 (not shown) was unaffected by the mutation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>When F11 or neurofascin-coated surfaces were complexed with tenascin-R NrCAM-deficient neurons were able to extend neurites similar to wild-type neurons (Fig. 8, j and m; not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>No neurite growth of NrCAM−/− neurons was detected on surfaces blocked with BSA and subsequently incubated with TN-R (Fig. 8 g), or on surfaces coated with F11 or neurofascin and blocked with BSA (not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>These results confirm our previous cell culture observations with chicken neurons in antibody perturbation experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>NrCAM, previously not known to be expressed in the lens, is essential for maintenance of lens transparency and an ordered arrangement of lens fiber cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the absence of ankyrin-B causes similar lens fiber disorganization as the absence of NrCAM, and both mutations cause cytoskeletal disarrangement, providing a genetic link between the interaction of NrCAM and ankyrin-B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Unexpectedly, significant pathfinding errors of commissural axons at the midline and of proprioceptive collaterals of the spinal cord are not detectable in the absence of NrCAM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>NrCAM and other L1 subfamily members and their ligands are expressed in the developing nervous system in a dynamic and partially overlapping pattern (Brümmendorf and Rathjen, 1995; Brümmendorf et al., 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>In contrast, only NrCAM, but none of its family members nor its ligands, are expressed in the lens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Thus, no other family member can compensate a loss of NrCAM in these cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>This might be the reason for this deleterious effect on the structure of lens fibers caused by the absence of NrCAM in contrast to the situation within the developing nervous system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>It is likely that the lens phenotype results from a perturbation of the maintenance of contacts between lens fiber cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>The absence of the currently known ligands of NrCAM suggests that this contact is mediated by homophilic binding of NrCAM on lens fibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The consequences of the lack to establish appropriate contacts between cell membranes may result in the failure to form water channels by aquaporins or gap junctions, as indicated here by the irregular distribution and decrease of connexin50-containing gap junctions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Water channels and gap junctions are important for the transport of water or ions, metabolites, and second messengers and allow communication between metabolically inert lens fibers deep within the lens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Gap junctional channels that bridge the extracellular space are formed by members of the connexin gene family, in particular in lenses, by connexin50, -46, and -43, that allow transport of small molecules and facilitate the continuous flow (&lt;1 kD) of ions, metabolites, and second messengers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>This flow appears to be important for lens clarity, as demonstrated by analysis of connexin50 and -46 mutant mice (Gong et al., 1997; White et al., 1998) and mutations in humans (Shiels et al., 1998; Mackay et al., 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The absence of connexin50 in mice results in reduced growth of the lens and the eye and the appearance of zonular pulverulent nuclear cataracts, however intercellular communication is not completely lost in these mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>In the absence of connexin50, lenses develop a nuclear cataract that is associated with the proteolysis of crystallins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Mutations within the major intrinsic protein, which also is important for intercellular communication of the lens fibers, causes lamellar cataracts in humans and mice (Shiels and Bassnett, 1996; Berry et al., 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>The major intrinsic protein that forms tetramers within the plasma membrane regulates the transport of water in an energy- and direction-independent manner (Heymann et al., 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Other mutations in humans or mice known to cause cataracts include genes encoding crystallins, which constitute the main cytoplasmic proteins in lens and the transcription factor PITX3 (Semina et al., 1998; Francis et al., 1999; Graw, 1999). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>As shown by lens fiber disorganization in the ankyrin-B−/− lens, NrCAM function requires a link to the cytoskeleton via ankyrin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>In addition, the transmembrane protein NrCAM, as well as the cytoskeletal linker protein ankyrin-B may function directly in maintaining an ordered cytoskeleton in the lens, for example, by anchoring the cytoskeleton to the lens membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Alternatively or in addition, the observed disarrangement of F-actin may be caused indirectly due to the perturbed lens metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Both NrCAM and ankyrin-B, but most likely the cytoskeleton as a whole, may also be important for the suprastructural organization of cytoplasmic proteins such as the crystallins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Thus, crystallins might not be able to maintain their normal organization in NrCAM-deficient lenses, thus creating opacification. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Although the NrCAM (human chromosome 7q22-31) (Burmeister et al., 1996; Lane et al., 1996) and ankyrin-B (human chromosome 4q25-q27) (Tse et al., 1991) loci have not been mapped so far to cataract formation in humans, our studies in mice might contribute to the understanding of cataract formation in humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>NrCAM is very similar to L1, the founder of this subfamily of adhesion proteins within the Ig superfamily. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Missense mutations within the L1 gene have been shown to result in a broad spectrum of neurological disorders with different degrees of severity (Wong et al., 1995; Brümmendorf et al., 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>It is conceivable that point mutations within the NrCAM gene affecting its homophilic binding activity might also cause cataract formation to different degrees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>It is therefore not unlikely to implicate the NrCAM gene in recessive forms of inherited human cataracts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>In addition, the inherited deletion or mutation of one NrCAM or ANK2 allele could increase the susceptibility to age-related cataract formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>An inherited complete absence of ankyrin-B, however, might be lethal at early stages, as observed for mice (Scotland et al., 1998). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Mapping the NrCAM locus and derivation of mutant mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>To obtain information about the mouse NrCAM locus, a PCR screen in a mouse ES BAC library was done using primers derived from rat cDNA sequence of NrCAM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Probes for mapping were created by PCR, using the rat cDNA sequence information for the primer design, and mouse genomic DNA for template. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>The BAC clone was mapped using 15 common restriction enzymes, and a long and short arm was subcloned from it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>The short arm (EMBL/GenBank/DDBJ accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AF346472">AF346472</ext-link>) consists of the 600-bp (PvuII-PvuII) fragment just upstream of the NrCAM exon containing the ATG (exon 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>The long arm consists of the NheI-SpeI 6-kb fragment, containing DNA from 1 kb downstream of exon 4 (NheI) to 0.5 kb downstream of exon 7 (SpeI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Short and long arms were inserted into the bluescript-derived vector pTG1 (Atugen) containing a neo cassette and TK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>The targeting vector was electroporated into E14.1 ES cells (129/ola) and screened by PCR screen (using neoL1 5′-CCTGCGTGCAATCCATCTTGTTCAATG-3′ and Moré1 5′-GAATAGATCAGTCGGGTCACTGAGG-3′). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Blastocyst injection and transfer into pseudopregnant foster mice were done by Atugen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>14 chimeric mice derived from one ES cell clone were obtained, of which 5 were germline chimeras. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>The chimeras were crossed with C57/BL6 mice, and the resulting heterozygous animals were crossed with each other to obtain homozygous mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Genotyping of the mice was done by PCR using Taq polymerase (GIBCO BRL) and the above primers for detection of the disrupted allele as well as Moré1 combined with Mimo71 (5′-CAGGAAGAGAATCAGGGGCACTC-3′) for detection of the wild-type allele. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, genomic Southern blotting was performed using a digoxygenin-labeled SacI-NheI fragment as external probe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>The correct integration of the targeting vector was confirmed using a Dig-labeled PauI-NheI fragment (region deleted in the mutant) as probe (not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Generation of polyclonal antibodies against NrCAM and immunoblot analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The rat cDNA clone number 22 of NrCAM (obtained from V. Bennett, Duke University, Durham, NC) was used to create a DNA fragment coding for NrCAM FNIII domains 1–4 via PCR, using Pfu polymerase, MIMO62 5′-CGGGATCCGCAGCCAACACAACGCTGGACAGT-3′, and MIMO50 5′-CGGAATTCGCCTGCACCTACATCAGGTGGAAGA-3′. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>The fragment was digested with EcoRI and BamHI and cloned into pGEX-6P-1 (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech), and then cloned into pQE30 (QIAGEN) using BamHI and SalI to create pMIM463. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>His-tagged NrCAM was expressed and purified under denaturing conditions according to the manufacturers' instructions (QIAGEN and CLONETECH Laboratories, Inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>[TALON metal affinity resin]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>One rabbit was immunized with doses of 100 μg of renatured purified protein, first in complete Freund's adjuvants, followed every second week by a dose in incomplete Freund's adjuvants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Serum of the immunized rabbit was applied to protein A–Sepharose (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech) to purify the IgG fraction, followed by affinity purification on nitrocellulose-immobilized NrCAM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>For the immunoblots, tissue was homogenized in RIPA buffer (1 M NaCl, 0.02 M EDTA, 0.1% SDS, 1% Triton X-100, 1 M Tris, pH 7.4) containing protease inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Laemmli SDS-PAGE buffer was added, and samples were boiled for 5 min and centrifuged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was used for SDS-PAGE (one lane containing the soluble fraction from 4 mg of tissue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>After electrophoresis, the proteins were blotted onto nitrocellulose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>In the first antibody reaction, 10 μg/ml 463 antibody were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>The secondary antibody was 0.25 μg/ml goat anti–rabbit alkaline phosphatase antibody (Dianova). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>For antiankyrin immunoblots, cytoskeletal proteins were extracted by high salt before SDS-PAGE. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Animal handling, documentation of mouse growth, and motor ability </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>For the growth curves, a male NrCAM−/− mouse was mated with a female NrCAM+/− mouse, resulting a large litter of 12 pups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>The pups were marked and weighed at various time points. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>For the rotarod test, a plastic rotarod inside a large box was used, driven by a small electric engine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Female mice weighing 13.8–14.3 g on average for NrCAM−/− and slightly younger control mice, respectively, were confronted without prior rod experience first with the nonmoving rod; and after a recovery time with the rod, rotating at 6.5 rpm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>The number of times the animals fell from the rod in 3 min was counted, and animals were put back onto the rod immediately after each fall. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Mice were genotyped after the experiment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>DiI tracing of commissural axons in the spinal cord </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>E11.5, E12.5, and E13.5 embryos of NrCAM+/− and NrCAM−/− mixed litters were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA)/PBS overnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>The spinal cord was exposed by removing overlying tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>A saturated solution of DiI in ethanol was injected through a filament-containing pulled-out glass injection needle into the lateral spinal cord. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Generally, 3–4 injections were done per spinal cord, spaced out over it's entire length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Tracing was done for 2.5 d at 37°C in 4% PFA/PBS, followed by an open book preparation of the spinal cord (Stoeckli and Landmesser, 1995). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Tracings were viewed under a fluorescence microscope and documented using an Axiocam digital camera (ZEISS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Images were converted to black and white and inverted using Adobe® Photoshop™. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Histological examinations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>10–14 μm cryostat sections (using a Leica cryostat) were done on tissues previously fixed in 4% PFA/PBS and equilibrated in 30% sucrose/PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>For immunohistology, the sections were blocked with 10% normal goat serum, 0.1% BSA/PBS, and incubated with the primary antibody (5–10 μg/ml in blocking solution, for 2 h at room temperature (RT) or overnight at 4°C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>After several PBS washing steps, secondary antibody (3 μg/ml goat anti–rabbit Cy3 or rabbit anti–mouse Cy3; Dianova) was applied for 2 h at RT, followed by several PBS washes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Fluorescence images were documented using a fluorescence microscope and a confocal scanning microscope (Bio-Rad Laboratories). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Monoclonal antibody against connexin50 was obtained from Zytomed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>For phalloidin stains, sections were blocked with 0.2% BSA/PBS and incubated with the (1 μg/ml) FITC–phalloidin for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>After several TBS/0.1% Triton X-100 washing steps, fluorescence images were documented using a fluorescence microscope and the confocal scanning microscope. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>For JB4 sections (Polysciences, Inc.), whole eyes were fixed in 75% ethanol/25% acetic acid, dehydrated in 100% ethanol, and embedded using the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>1-μm sections were done using a semithin microtome (model HM360; Microm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>The sections were stained using toluidine blue (TB) or hematoxylin/eosin (HE) stain and documented using a microscope with phase–contrast setting and an Axiocam digital camera (ZEISS). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Neurite outgrowth assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Under sterile conditions, eight-well chamber slide gaskets (Lab-Tek) were attached to hydrophobic petriPERM dishes (Heraeus). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>The proteins F11, neurofascin-Fc (isoform 15), and TN-R were purified as described elsewhere (Volkmer et al., 1996; Zacharias et al., 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Wells were coated with 100 μl of PBS containing 10 μg of substrate and incubated overnight at 4°C in a moist atmosphere. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>To obtain substrate–TN-R complexes, the primary substrate was first blocked with 100 μg/ml BSA in PBS for 1 h at RT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>This was followed by a PBS wash and an incubation with 5 μg/ml TN-R in PBS for 4 h at RT. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Mouse neurons were prepared from E12 total brains using a published protocol and were seeded onto the prepared substrate-binding petriperm surfaces in neurobasal medium (GIBCO BRL) (containing the additives B27, glutamine, and penicillin/streptomycin) at a concentration of 20,000 cells/well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Neurite outgrowth was documented using phase–contrast microscopy and an Axiocam digital camera after 24 h of incubation at 37°C under cell culture conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>The authors are grateful to V. Bennett for providing us with rat NrCAM cDNA clones, as well as with antibodies against ankyrin-B and -G, and most of all, ankyrin-B+/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>We thank M. Richter and M. Schachner for antibodies against CHL1, M. Grumet for antibodies against NrCAM, R.U. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Margolis and A. Faissner for antibodies against RPTPβ/ζ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>We are grateful for the expert technical help of Y. Klosowski and advice of L. Li, A. Garratt, and C. Birchmeier concerning the analysis of mutant mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Thanks to G. Lewin for the introduction into DiI tracing and to F. Pfrieger and I. Haupt for the introduction into the mouse neuron cell culture technique. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>We thank J. Graw and D.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Beebe for their helpful discussions and advice concerning cataracts and acknowledge the critical reading of the manuscript by J. Graw, M. Koroll, K. Sharma, A. Garratt, and U. Zacharias. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>We thank S. Kenwrick for information on the human NrCAM location prior publication. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by DFG grant SFB515 to F.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Rathjen, and a Liebig habilitation stipend of the Verband der Chemischen Industrie to M.I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Moré. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><label>*</label><p><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations used in this paper: CHL1, close homologue of L1; ES, embryonic stem; FNIII, fibronectin type III; HE, hematoxylin/eosin; Ig, immunoglobulin; NrCAM, NgCAM-related cell adhesion molecule; PFA, paraformaldehyde; RT, room temperature; RPTP, receptor protein tyrosine phosphatase; TB, toluidine blue. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Bassnett, S., H. Missey, and I. Vucemilo. 1999. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Molecular architecture of the lens fiber cell basal membrane complex. J. Cell Sci. 112:2155–2165. <?supplied-pmid 10362545?>10362545 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib2"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Berry, V., P. Francis, S. Kaushal, A. Moore, and S. Bhattacharya. 2000. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Missense mutations in MIP underlie autosomal dominant ‘polymorphic’ and lamellar cataracts linked to 12q. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Genet. 25:15–17. <?supplied-pmid 10802646?>10802646 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib3"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Brümmendorf, T., and F.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Rathjen. 1995 Cell adhesion molecules 1: immunoglobulin superfamily. Prot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Profile. 2:963–1108. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib4"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Brümmendorf, T., S. Kenwrick, and F.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Rathjen. 1998. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Neural cell recognition molecule L1: from cell biology to human hereditary brain malformations. Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>Opin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Neurobiol. 8:87–97. <?supplied-pmid 9568396?>9568396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib5"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Burmeister, M., Q. Ren, G.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Makris, D. Samson, and V. Bennett. 1996. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Genes for the neuronal immunoglobulin domain cell adhesion molecules neurofascin and Nr-CAM map to mouse chromosomes 1 and 12 and homologous human chromosomes. Mamm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Genome. 7:558–559. <?supplied-pmid 8672144?>8672144 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib6"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Cohen, N.R., J.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Taylor, L.B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>Scott, R.W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>Guillery, P. Soriano, and A.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Furley. 1998. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Errors in corticospinal axon guidance in mice lacking the neural cell adhesion molecule L1. Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Biol. 8:26–33. <?supplied-pmid 9427628?>9427628 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib7"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Dahme, M., U. Bartsch, R. Martini, B. Anliker, M. Schachner, and N. Mantei. 1997. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Disruption of the mouse L1 gene leads to malformations of the nervous system. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Genet. 17:346–349. <?supplied-pmid 9354804?>9354804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib8"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Davis, J.Q., and V. Bennett. 1994. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Ankyrin binding activity shared by the neurofascin/L1/NrCAM family of nervous system cell adhesion molecules. J. Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Chem. 269:27163–27166. <?supplied-pmid 7961622?>7961622 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib9"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>De Angelis, E., J. MacFarlane, J.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Du, G. Yeo, R. Hicks, F.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Rathjen, S. Kenwrick, and T. Brümmendorf. 1999. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Pathological missense mutations of neural cell adhesion molecule L1 affect hemophilic and heterophilic binding activities. EMBO J. 18:4744–4753. <?supplied-pmid 10469653?>10469653 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib10"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Demyanenko, G.P., A.Y. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Tsai, and P.F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Maness. 1999. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Abnormalities in neuronal process extension, hippocampal development, and the ventricular system of L1 knockout mice. J. Neurosci. 19:4907–4920. <?supplied-pmid 10366625?>10366625 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib11"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>Dola, A., M. Katar, P. Hussain, and H. Maisel. 1990 Ankyrin of the ocular lens. Ophthalmic Re s. 22:295–301. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib12"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>Dry, K., S. Kenwrick, A. Rosenthal, and M. Platzer. 2001 The complete sequence of the human locus for NrCAM (NgCAM-related cell adhesion molecule) reveals a novel alternative exon in chick and man and conserved genomic organisation for the L1 subfamily. Gene. In press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib13"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>Fitzli, D., E.T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>Stoeckli, S. Kunz, K. Siribour, C. Rader, B. Kunz, S.V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Kozlov, A. Buchstaller, R.P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>Lane, D.M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>Suter, W.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Dreyer, and P. Sonderegger. 2000. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>A direct interaction of axonin-1 with NgCAM–related cell adhesion molecule (NrCAM) results in guidance, but not growth of commissural axone. J. Cell Biol. 149:951–968. <?supplied-pmid 10811834?>10811834 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib14"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>Francis, P.J., V. Berry, A.T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>Moore, and S. Bhattacharya. 1999. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>Lens biology: development and human cataractogenesis. Trends Genet. 15:191–196. <?supplied-pmid 10322486?>10322486 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib15"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>Francis, P.J., V. Berry, S.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>Bhattacharya, and A.T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>Moore. 2000. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>The genetics of childhood cataract. J. Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>Genet. 37:481–488. <?supplied-pmid 10882749?>10882749 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib16"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>Gong, X., E. Li, G. Klier, Q. Huang, Y. Wu, H. Lei, N.M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>Kumar, J. Horwitz, and N.B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>Gilula. 1997. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>Disruption of alpha3 connexin gene leads to proteolysis and cataractogenesis in mice. Cell. 91:833–843. <?supplied-pmid 9413992?>9413992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib17"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>Graw, J. 1999. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>Cataract mutations and lens development. Prog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>Retin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>Eye Res. 18:235–267. <?supplied-pmid 9932285?>9932285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib18"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>Grumet, M., V. Mauro, M.P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>Burgoon, G.M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>Edelman, and B.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>Cunningham. 1991. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>Structure of a new nervous system glycoprotein, Nr-CAM, and its relationship to subgroups of neural cell adhesion molecules. J. Cell Biol. 113:1399–1412. <?supplied-pmid 2045418?>2045418 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib19"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>Heymann, J.B., P. Agre, and A. Engel. 1998. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>Progress on the structure and function of aquaporin 1. J. Struct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>Biol. 121:191–206. <?supplied-pmid 9615438?>9615438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib20"><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>Hortsch, M. 2000. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>Structural and functional evolution of the L1 family: are four adhesion molecules better than one? Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>Cell Neurosci. 15:1–10. <?supplied-pmid 10662501?>10662501 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib21"><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>Jefford, G., and R.R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>Dubreuil. 2000. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>Receptor clustering drives polarized assembly of ankyrin. J. Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>Chem. 275:27726–27732. <?supplied-pmid 10871626?>10871626 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib22"><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>Kayyem, J.F., J.M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>Roman, E.J. de la Rosa, U. Schwarz, and W.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>Dreyer. 1992. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>Bravo/Nr-CAM is closely related to the cell adhesion molecules L1 and Ng-CAM and has a similar heterodimer structure. J. Cell Biol. 118:1259–1270. <?supplied-pmid 1512296?>1512296 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib23"><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>Lambert, S., J.Q. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>Davis, and V. Bennett. 1997. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>Morphogenesis of the node of Ranvier: co-clusters of ankyrin and ankyrin-binding integral proteins define early developmental intermediates. J. Neurosci. 17:7025–7036. <?supplied-pmid 9278538?>9278538 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib24"><text><SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>Lane, R.P., X.N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>Chen, K. Yamakawa, J. Vielmetter, J.R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>Korenberg, and W.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>Dreyer. 1996. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>Characterization of a highly conserved human homolog to the chicken neural cell surface protein Bravo/Nr-CAM that maps to chromosome band 7q31. Genomics. 35:456–465. <?supplied-pmid 8812479?>8812479 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib25"><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>Mackay, D., A. Ionides, Z. Kibar, G. Rouleau, V. Berry, A. Moore, A. Shiels, and S. Bhattacharya. 1999. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>Connexin46 mutations in autosomal dominant congenital cataract. Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>Hum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>Genet. 64:1357–1364. <?supplied-pmid 10205266?>10205266 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib26"><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>Mauro, V.P., L.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>Krushel, B.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>Cunningham, and G.M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>Edelman. 1992. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>Homophilic and heterophilic binding activities of Nr-CAM, a nervous system cell adhesion molecule. J. Cell Biol. 119:191–202. <?supplied-pmid 1527169?>1527169 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib27"><text><SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>Morales, G., M. Hubert, T. Brümmendorf, U. Treubert, A. Tarnok, U. Schwarz, and F.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>Rathjen. 1993. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>Induction of axonal growth by heterophilic interactions between the cell surface recognition proteins F11 and NrCAM/Bravo. Neuron. 11:1113–1122. <?supplied-pmid 8274278?>8274278 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib28"><text><SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>Moulding, H.D., R.L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>Martuza, and S.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>Rabkin. 2000. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>Clinical mutations in the L1 neural cell adhesion molecule affect cell-surface expression. J. Neurosci. 20:5696–5702. <?supplied-pmid 10908608?>10908608 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib29"><text><SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>Perrin, F.E., F.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain>Rathjen, and E. Stoeckli. 2001 Distinct subpopulations of sensory afferents require F11 or axonin-1 for growth to their target layers within the spinal cord of the chick. Neuron. In press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib30"><text><SENT sid="551" pm="."><plain>Sakurai, T., M. Lustig, M. Nativ, J.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="554" pm="."><plain>Hemperly, J. Schlessinger, E. Peles, and M. Grumet. 1997. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="558" pm="."><plain>Induction of neurite outgrowth through contactin and Nr-CAM by extracellular regions of glial receptor tyrosine phosphatase β. J. Cell Biol. 136:907–918. <?supplied-pmid 9049255?>9049255 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib31"><text><SENT sid="560" pm="."><plain>Scotland, P., D. Zhou, H. Benveniste, and V. Bennett. 1998. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="564" pm="."><plain>Nervous system defects of AnkyrinB (-/-) mice suggest functional overlap between the cell adhesion molecule L1 and 440-kD AnkyrinB in premyelinated axons. J. Cell Biol. 143:1305–1315. <?supplied-pmid 9832558?>9832558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib32"><text><SENT sid="566" pm="."><plain>Semina, E.V., R.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="567" pm="."><plain>Ferrell, H.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="568" pm="."><plain>Mintz-Hittner, P. Bitoun, W.L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="570" pm="."><plain>Alward, R.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="571" pm="."><plain>Reiter, C. Funkhauser, H.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="573" pm="."><plain>Daack, and J.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="574" pm="."><plain>Murray. 1998. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="575" pm="."><plain>A novel homeobox gene PITX3 is mutated in families with autosomal-dominant cataracts and ASMD. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="576" pm="."><plain>Genet. 19:167–170. <?supplied-pmid 9620774?>9620774 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib33"><text><SENT sid="577" pm="."><plain>Shiels, A., and S. Bassnett. 1996. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="579" pm="."><plain>Mutations in the founder of the MIP gene family underlie cataract development in the mouse. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="580" pm="."><plain>Genet. 12:212–215. <?supplied-pmid 8563764?>8563764 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib34"><text><SENT sid="581" pm="."><plain>Shiels, A., D. Mackay, A. Ionides, V. Berry, A. Moore, and S. Bhattacharya. 1998. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="587" pm="."><plain>A missense mutation in the human connexin50 gene (GJA8) underlies autosomal dominant “zonular pulverulent” cataract, on chromosome 1q. Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="588" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="589" pm="."><plain>Hum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="590" pm="."><plain>Genet. 62:526–532. <?supplied-pmid 9497259?>9497259 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib35"><text><SENT sid="591" pm="."><plain>Stoeckli, E.T., and L. Landmesser. 1995. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="593" pm="."><plain>Axonin-1, Nr-CAM, and Ng-CAM play different roles in the in vivo guidance of chick commissural neurons. Neuron. 14:1165–1179. <?supplied-pmid 7541632?>7541632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib36"><text><SENT sid="594" pm="."><plain>Suter, D.M., G.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="595" pm="."><plain>Pollerberg, A. Buchstaller, R.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="597" pm="."><plain>Giger, W.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="598" pm="."><plain>Dreyer, and P. Sonderegger. 1995. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="600" pm="."><plain>Binding between the neural cell adhesion molecules axonin-1 and nr-cam/bravo is involved in neuron-glia interaction. J. Cell Biol. 131:1067–1081. <?supplied-pmid 7490283?>7490283 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib37"><text><SENT sid="602" pm="."><plain>Tse, W.T., J.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="603" pm="."><plain>Menninger, T.L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="604" pm="."><plain>Yang-Feng, U. Francke, K.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="606" pm="."><plain>Sahr, S.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="607" pm="."><plain>Lux, D.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="608" pm="."><plain>Ward, and B.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="609" pm="."><plain>Forget. 1991. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="610" pm="."><plain>Isolation and chromosomal localization of a novel nonerythroid ankyrin gene. Genomics. 10:858–866. <?supplied-pmid 1833308?>1833308 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib38"><text><SENT sid="611" pm="."><plain>Tuvia, S., T.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="612" pm="."><plain>Garver, and V. Bennett. 1997. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="614" pm="."><plain>The phosphorylation state of the FIGQY tyrosine of neurofascin determines ankyrin-binding activity and patterns of cell segregation. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="615" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="616" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="617" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="618" pm="."><plain>USA. 94:12957–12962. <?supplied-pmid 9371782?>9371782 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib39"><text><SENT sid="619" pm="."><plain>Volkmer, H., R. Leuschner, U. Zacharias, and F.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="622" pm="."><plain>Rathjen. 1996. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="623" pm="."><plain>Neurofascin induces neurites by heterophilic interactions with axonal NrCAM while NrCAM requires F11 on the axonal surface to extend neurites. J. Cell Biol. 135:1059–1069. <?supplied-pmid 8922386?>8922386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib40"><text><SENT sid="625" pm="."><plain>Volkmer, H., U. Zacharias, U. Nörenberg, and F.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="628" pm="."><plain>Rathjen. 1998. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="629" pm="."><plain>Dissection of complex molecular interactions of neurofascin with Axonin-1, F11, and Tenascin-R, which promote attachment and neurite formation of tectal cells. J. Cell Biol. 142:1083–1093. <?supplied-pmid 9722619?>9722619 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib41"><text><SENT sid="631" pm="."><plain>White, T.W., D.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="632" pm="."><plain>Goodenough, and D.L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="633" pm="."><plain>Paul. 1998. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="634" pm="."><plain>Targeted ablation of connexin50 in mice results in microphthalmia and zonular pulverulent cataracts. J. Cell Biol. 143:815–825. <?supplied-pmid 9813099?>9813099 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib42"><text><SENT sid="636" pm="."><plain>Wong, E.V., S. Kenwrick, P.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="638" pm="."><plain>Willems, and V. Lemmon. 1995. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="640" pm="."><plain>Mutations in the cell adhesion molecule L1 cause mental retardation. Trends Neurosci. 18:168–172. <?supplied-pmid 7778187?>7778187 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib43"><text><SENT sid="641" pm="."><plain>Zacharias, U., U. Nörenberg, and F.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="643" pm="."><plain>Rathjen. 1999. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="644" pm="."><plain>Functional interactions of the immunoglobulin superfamily member F11 are differentially regulated by the extracellular matrix proteins Tenascin-R and Tenascin-C. J. Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="646" pm="."><plain>Chem. 274:24357–24365. <?supplied-pmid 10446214?>10446214 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
