<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?properties manuscript?><?origin nihpa?><?iso-abbr Nat. Neurosci.?><?submitter-system nihms?><?submitter-canonical-name Nature Publishing Group?><?submitter-canonical-id NATURE-STRUCTUR?><?submitter-userid 1045?><?submitter-authority publisher?><?submitter-login nature-structure?><?submitter-name Nature Publishing Group (obsolete)?><?domain nihpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9809671</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">21092</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Neurosci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat. Neurosci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature neuroscience</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1097-6256</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1546-1726</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3965909</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24162653</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3564</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">nihpa560004</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>EZH2-mediated H3K27 trimethylation mediates neurodegeneration in ataxia-telangiectasia </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Jiali</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>Ronald P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mallimo</surname><given-names>Elyse M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Swerdel</surname><given-names>Mavis R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kusnecov</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Herrup</surname><given-names>Karl</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Cell Biology and Neuroscience, Rutgers University, 604 Allison Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Dept. of Psychology, Rutgers University, 152 Frelinghuysen Road, Piscataway, NJ 08855 USA</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Division of Life Sciences, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology, Clear Water Bay, Kowloon, Hong Kong, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="FN1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed: <email>Jli@dls.rutgers.edu</email>, Phone: 732-445-3118, Facsimile: 732-445-1794, Facsimile: (852) 2358-1552 And <email>herrup@ust.hk</email>, Phone: (852) 2358-7308, Facsimile: (852) 2358-1552</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>01</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1745</fpage><lpage>1753</lpage><permissions><license xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms"><license-p>Users may view, print, copy, and download text and data-mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The symptoms of ataxia-telangiectasia (A-T) include a progressive neurodegeneration caused by ATM protein deficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>We previously found that nuclear accumulation of histone deacetylase-4, HDAC4, contributes to this degeneration; we now report that increased histone H3K27 trimethylation (H3K27me3) mediated by polycomb repressive complex 2 (PRC2) also plays an important role in the A-T phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Enhancer of zeste homolog 2 (EZH2), a core catalytic component of PRC2, is a new ATM kinase target, and ATM-mediated S734 phosphorylation of EZH2 reduces protein stability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Thus, PRC2 formation is elevated along with H3K27me3in ATM deficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>ChIP-sequencing shows a significant increase in H3K27me3 ‘marks’ and a dramatic shift in their location. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The change of H3K27me3 chromatin-binding pattern is directly related to cell cycle re-entry and cell death of ATM-deficient neurons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Lentiviral knockdown of EZH2 rescues Purkinje cell degeneration and behavioral abnormalities in Atm−/− mice, demonstrating that EZH2 hyperactivity is another key factor in A-T neurodegeneration. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p id="P2"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Ataxia-telangiectasia (A-T) is a multisystem disease characterized by neurodegeneration in the central nervous system (CNS)1–4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The earliest and most profound neuropathology involves the Purkinje and granule cells of the cerebellum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>A-T is caused by mutation of the A-T mutated (ATM) gene, which is ubiquitously expressed throughout development and encodes a serine/threonine protein kinase of the phosphatidylinositol-3 kinase-related kinase (PIKK) family5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The best-known function of ATM is to ensure the integrity of the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>After DNA damage, ATM activates cell cycle checkpoints, arresting the cycle until DNA repair is complete6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Its role in maintaining the health and survival of neurons is complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Consistent with its function in DNA damage repair7, ATM protects post-mitotic neurons from degeneration by suppressing the cell cycle8–10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>But ATM is also required for neuronal vesicle trafficking11 and maintaining HDAC4 (histone deacetylase 4) in the cytoplasm12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Both of these processes are crucial for neuronal viability and yet neither is directly induced by DNA damage12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>These later observations hint at a complex web of nerve cell phenotypes that are dependent on ATM function and suggest that the mechanisms behind the neurodegeneration in A-T are multifaceted and still incompletely defined. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P3"><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Our finding of ectopic nuclear HDAC4 in ATM deficiency and the subsequent genome-wide alterations in the acetylation marks on histones H3 and H4 led us to explore other aspects of the histone code. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Polycomb group (PcG) family proteins are transcriptional repressors that epigenetically modify chromatin and participate in the establishment and maintenance of many cell fates13–17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>PcG proteins participate in both stem cell self-renewal and tumorigenesis as well as in brain development18,19. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>In mammals, there are two distinct polycomb protein complexes: polycomb repressive complex 1 (PRC1) and PRC220. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The PRC2 complex consists of EZH2 (enhancer of zeste homolog 2), SUZ12 (suppressor of zeste 12) and EED (embryonic ectoderm development)21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>EZH2 catalyzes the addition of methyl groups to histone H3 at Lys 27 (H3K27) in target gene promoters, leading to epigenetic silencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>EZH2 plays a role in X-chromosome inactivation, germ line development, cell fate decisions and stem cell pluripotency14,15,22,23. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>EZH2 is overexpressed in aggressive solid tumors and its overexpression has been implicated in cancer progression and metastases15,24,25; its knockdown leads to decreased proliferation of cancer cells and a delay in the G2/M transition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>During development and stem cell maturation, CDK1/EZH2 or CDK2/EZH2 interactions integrate developmental cues and cell cycle activity to control self-renewal or differentiation15,25. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>EZH2 also regulates the balance between self-renewal and differentiation of cortical neurons26,27. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P4"><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Histone modification is a major form of epigenetic gene regulation that plays a critical role in many neuronal processes28,29. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Spurred by our finding of dramatic HDAC4-mediated histone acetylation changes in Atm-deficient neurons, we asked whether EZH2-mediated H3K27 trimethylation (H3K27me3) is also affected by a defect of ATM function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>We now report that in the cerebella of A-T patients and in A-T mouse models, the levels of H3K27 trimethylation are elevated due to the loss ATM-dependent EZH2 phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>This phosphorylation normally de-stabilizes EZH2 thus reducing its association with the PRC2 complex and subsequent H3K27 methylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>ChIP-sequencing using H3K27me3 antibody reveals genome-wide differences in this histone mark between wild type and Atm−/−. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>These differences help to drive the CNS symptoms of A-T; knockdown of EZH2 prevents cell cycle reentry and neuronal death in Atm-deficient neurons and improves behavior of Atm−/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>We propose a model of A-T in which EZH2-mediated hypermethylation of H3K27me3 is a crucial step leading to the degeneration of the Atm-deficient neurons. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="S1"><title><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S2"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Elevated H3K27me3 in A-T brains </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P5"><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>EZH2-mediated H3K27 trimethylation is a key activity of the polycomb epigenetic system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>It affects many processes including proliferation, tumorigenesis as well as brain development15,22,30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>We became interested in EZH2 as a possible player in ataxia-telangiectasia (A-T) because of its roles of in cell cycle regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>ATM-deficient Purkinje and granule cells both reenter the cell cycle before dying in human A-T and in its Atm−/− mouse model10,31. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>We speculated that if EZH2 were involved, the disease process in the A-T nervous system might derive in part from the over-activation of PRC2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>As H3K27 is the main target of EZH2, first, we examined H3K27me3 in human cerebellar cortex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Purkinje and granule cell nuclei contained low levels of H3K27me3 in healthy control cerebellar sections (Fig. 1a, top and Fig. 1b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Yet, as predicted by our hypothesis, both neuronal types in sections from A-T patients showed enhanced nuclear H3K27me3 staining; H3K9me3 was unaffected (Fig. 1a, bottom and Fig. 1b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Western blots of tissue extracts validated the immunostaining – elevated levels of H3K27me3 in A-T compared to control (Fig. 1c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>We next repeated these observations in Atm−/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Immunostaining for H3K27me3 (Fig. 1d, upper and Fig. 1e), but not H3K9me3 (Fig. 1d, lower and Fig. 1e), was substantially increased in Atm−/− Purkinje cell nuclei. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>We also found increased H3K27me3 in mouse Atm−/− neocortex and hippocampus (Fig. 1f; Supplementary Fig. 1a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>As expected, an increased interaction of H3K27me3 with EZH2 was also found in ATM-deficiency (Supplementary Fig. 1b–c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Thus, there is a close association between elevated H3K27me3 and Atm-deficiency in both humans and mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S3"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>EZH2 is an ATM target </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P6"><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The remarkable change in the levels of H3K27me3 in A-T brain suggested that EZH2 might be a novel ATM target. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Analysis of the EZH2 protein sequence predicts that two serines, S652 and S734, are highly probable sites of ATM phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>We could find no comparably favorable sites in the EZH1 histone methyltransferase, or in other members (e.g., Suz12) of the polycomb repressor complex 2 (PRC2) to which EZH2 belongs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>To determine whether these two EZH2 sites are used as ATM targets in vivo, we prepared cerebellar extracts from control and A-T patients as well as from wild type and Atm−/− mice and performed immunoprecipitation with EZH2 or EZH1 antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Western blots of the immunoprecipitates were then probed with an antibody against a phosphorylated serine or threonine in the context of a following glutamine residue (P[S/T]Q), the canonical ATM/ATR target site32,33. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>A strong P[S/T]Q signal was found on the EZH2 band in control samples but not in A-T or Atm−/− extracts (Fig. 2a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>We found no P[S/T]Q signal in either genotype using EZH1 immunoprecipitates (Fig. 2a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>We verified that S734 is the predominant ATM site on EZH2 by performing ATM in vitro kinase assays using GST-EZH2 fusion proteins as substrates (Fig. 2b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The phosphorylation signal was nearly lost when the EZH2-S734A mutant was used as substrate; the 2SA (S652A/S734A) double mutation blocked the phosphorylation signal entirely. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>This indicates S734 is the major ATM phosphorylation site, but S652 may serve as an alternate kinase target. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>To confirm whether ATM-mediated EZH2 phosphorylation responds to DNA damage in vivo, GFP-EZH2 wild type or the non-phosphorylatable 2SA mutant was overexpressed in human A-T fibroblasts with Flag-ATM wild type or the kinase dead (KD) mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>A strong P[S/T]Q signal was found with etoposide treatment when GFP-EZH2-WT was expressed with Flag-ATM-WT (Fig. 2c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Expression of either the EZH2-2SA mutant (lane 6) or the ATM-KD mutant (lane 3) significantly reduced the response. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S4"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>ATM phosphorylation of EZH2 blocks its assembly into the PRC2 complex </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P7"><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>In mature neurons, the levels of EZH2 are normally very low26, a finding that we verified in wild type mouse and human disease-free cerebella (Fig. 2d–e and Supplementary Fig. 2a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>In A-T cerebellum and Atm−/− cerebellum by contrast, we found that levels of EZH2 were significantly higher (Fig. 2d–e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Elevated levels of EZH2 were also found in other Atm−/− brain regions such as neocortex and hippocampus (Fig. 2e, Supplementary Fig. 2b) suggesting that this effect may be a general one. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The enhanced levels of EZH2 protein in ATM-deficient neurons were likely not a result of increased transcription; by reverse transcription PCR (RT-PCR), EZH2 mRNA levels were nearly equal in the two genotypes (Supplementary Fig. 2c–d). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P8"><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>As a core protein of the polycomb repressive complex 2 (PRC2), the function and enzymatic activity of EZH2 relies on its physical interaction with the other PRC2 proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>When we overexpressed EZH2in N2a cells, we found that, compared to wild type EZH2, the association with EED and Suz12 was stronger with the non-phosphorylatable 2SA mutant and weaker with the 2SD phosphomimetic mutant (Fig. 2f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>To assess whether the stability of EZH2 affects its ability to participate in PRC2 complex formation, we used the protein synthesis inhibitor cycloheximide to block new protein synthesis, then followed the degradation of the existing pools of protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>After overexpression in N2a cells, wild type EZH2 had a protein half-life of 17.3 hrs (Fig. 2g–h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The half-life of the phosphomimetic mutant (2SD) was comparable (not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>By contrast, the non-phosphorylatable 2SA mutant proved remarkably stable (t½ ~ 2 days; Fig. 2g–h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>In all cases, stability was directly correlated with increased EZH2 binding to H3K27me3 (Fig. 2f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Endogenous EZH2 protein in human A-T fibroblasts behaved similarly – more stable after cycloheximide treatment than EZH2 in control fibroblasts (Supplementary Fig. 3a–b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Next we tested whether inhibiting protease activity with ALLN blocked the degradation of non-phosphorylatable EZH2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>When given 24 hours after transfection of GFP-EZH2, protease inhibition blocked the degradation of the 2SA EZH2 mutant (Supplementary Fig. 3c–d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that PRC2 complex formation is enhanced in ATM deficiency and that this protects EZH2 from degradation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S5"><title><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>H3K27me3 chromatin-binding correlates with down-regulated transcription </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P9"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The substantially increased levels of H3K27me3 in ATM-deficient neurons led us to ask whether the evidence of altered chromatin remodeling was related to the elevated levels of EZH2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>We thus performed H3K27me3 chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) from Atm−/− cerebellar cortex, and found a substantial (4-fold) increase in the number of H3K27me3 binding sites in Atm−/− compared to wild type chromatin (Fig. 3a, Supplementary Fig. 4a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>In addition, this increase was accompanied by a substantial shift in the pattern of binding; just 5% of the sites identified in wild type chromatin overlapped with the sites found in Atm−/−. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Most of the Atm−/− binding sites (93%) were not represented in the wild type; and of the total wild type sites identified only 23% were found in Atm−/− as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Despite these local shifts in discrete binding sites at the genomic level, the increased in H3K27me3 density was uniformly distributed over genome (Supplementary Fig. 4b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Analyzed by gene function, a large proportion of H3K27me3 targets are in categories that include neuronal function and cell cycle regulation (Table S1), but the peaks in the different genotypes did not show a striking difference in gene ontology (GO – Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Among genes identified in this analysis were Slit1, Synj2, and Nlgn1 – genes with important function in synaptic development and maintenance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The H3K27me3 marking of each of these genes was confirmed by qPCR (Fig. 3b–c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>We also found H3K27me3 enrichment in promoter areas of cell cycle regulatory genes cdkn2a and cdkn2b in Atm−/− samples compared to wild type (Supplementary Fig. 5a–b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>All ChIP-qPCR assays displayed increased enrichment of H3K27me3 within the Atm−/− peak predicted by sequencing and peak finding, confirming our ChIPseq analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P10"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>We next performed microarray analysis on RNA samples from wild type and Atm−/− cerebellar cortex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Topping the list of down-regulated genes were several associated with Purkinje and granule cells, such as Purkinje cell protein 2 (pcp2 – also known as L7) and gamma-amino butyric acid A receptor subunit alpha 6 (gabra6), engrailed-1 and -2 (en1, en2) (Fig. 3d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Moreover, several neuronal genes described above based on enrichment of H3K27me3 in their promoters’ regions – mef2a, cdk5rap2, slit1, synj2, and nlgn1 – are among the down-regulated genes identified by expression array (Table S2–3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The GO analysis of the down regulated genes also highlighted developmental processes (Table S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>To assess the direct effect of enrichment of H3K27me3 in the promoter regions of these genes, we examined mRNA expression in wild type and Atm−/− cerebella. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Consistent with microarray data, we found a significant reduction of gene expression in Atm−/− samples (Fig. 3e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Although consistent with the ChIP data, we note that the loss could be due in part to the death of these cell types as well as to reduced gene expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S6"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>EZH2 has a direct effect on postmitotic neurons </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P11"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Our previous work on HDAC4 had led us to conclude that the ATM-dependent effects on histone acetylation were independent of DNA damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>By contrast, ATM-mediated EZH2 phosphorylation responds robustly to DNA damage (Fig. 2c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>To pursue this difference we treated normal human fibroblasts or differentiated rodent N2a cells with ionizing radiation (IR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>In control fibroblasts we saw a reduction of EZH2 and H3K27me3 (Fig. 4a–c), while in A-T fibroblast lines IR had virtually no effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Log phase N2a cells responded in a manner similar to ATM-deficient fibroblasts (Fig. 4a and c), suggesting that the ATM effect was more pronounced in differentiated, non-mitotic cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P12"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>We next asked whether ATM-mediated EZH2 phosphorylation was involved in the ability of ATM to regulate the neuronal cell cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>In differentiated N2a cells, 2SA-EZH2, but not wild type or 2SD-EZH2, significantly increased the level of BrdU incorporation (Fig. 4d–e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>We found the same effect of an acute reduction of EZH2 in primary ATM-deficient neurons by using EZH2 shRNA (shezh2) lentiviral particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The efficiency of viral infection was identified by examining EZH2 and H3K27me3 level (Supplementary Fig. 6a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>As expected, knockdown of EZH2 significantly blocked BrdU incorporation (Fig. 5a–b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>There was no effect from EZH1 shRNA (shezh1) infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Knocking down EZH2 also prevented etoposide-induced activation of the cell death pathway in Atm−/− primary neurons (Fig. 5c–d), consistent with the defective DNA damage response found in A-T brain34. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P13"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>This reversal of the A-T cell cycle phenotype suggests that for neurons to keep their cell cycle in check they must maintain a constitutive ATM activity that keeps the levels of EZH2 low. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>We found that this suppression of EZH2-dependent histone methylation is also important for maintaining the proper structure of the neuronal dendrite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>We measured spine density in cultured E16.5 neocortical neurons from wild type and Atm−/− brains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Mutant cortical neurons have a markedly reduced number of spines along a given length of dendrite (as previously reported for cerebellar Purkinje cells35). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Knockdown of EZH2, however, partially rescued this effect and led to an increase of spine density in Atm−/− primary neurons (Fig. 5e–f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>For wild type neurons, no dramatic changes occurred after shezh2 infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The improved Atm−/− dendritic structure achieved by decreasing EZH2 was associated with changes in mRNA for specific neuronal genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Using qPCR after shezh2 infection, we found significant increase of neuronal genes such slit1, synj2 and nlgn1 (Supplementary Fig. 6b and c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>By contrast, the mRNA levels of cell cycle regulatory genes such as pcna and cyclin A were decreased (Supplementary Fig. 6b and d). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S7"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Knocking down Ezh2 prevents neurodegenerative process of Atm−/− mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P14"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have documented a degenerative process in AtmtmlBal mutant mouse cerebellum10,12,31. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>To examine the effect of ezh2 knockdown on this process, we surgically delivered shezh2-GFP expressing lentivirus into live adult mouse cerebellum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Three to four weeks after virus delivery, the efficiency of the EZH2 shRNAs was evaluated both by GFP expression (Supplementary Fig. 7a) and by the level of EZH2 immunoreactivity (Supplementary Fig. 7b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>We found that the elevated levels of EZH2 in Atm−/− cerebellum were reduced after shezh2 infection; the same virus had little effect in wild type brains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Additionally, immunostaining for H3K27me3 revealed a dramatic reduction in cerebellar neurons of shezh2-injected Atm−/− mice (Supplementary Fig. 7b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>We also monitored cell cycle re-entry and the initiation of cell death in these preparations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>We found that in Atm−/− cerebellar GFP-positive neurons, reduction of EZH2 and H3K27me3 not only reduced the expression of cell cycle proteins such as cyclin A (Fig. 6a–b, red) and PCNA (Supplementary Fig. 8a), it also partially inhibited the activation of caspase-3 (Fig. 6c–d, red). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The Purkinje cell marker calbindin also revealed a substantial attenuation of Atm−/− Purkinje cell atrophy after injection of shezh2 (Fig. 6e–f). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P15"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>We next sought to determine if these in vivo improvements in the molecular profile of the Atm−/− cerebellar neurons was reflected in their cytological properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>While a previous study found no evidence of Purkinje cell loss in the AtmtmlAwb allele of Atm36, by applying the optical fractionator cell counting technique, we found a slight reduction in PCs counts in Atmtm1Bal homozygous mice (Table S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>This difference is too small, however, to serve as a reference for lentiviral shezh2 rescue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>We therefore analyzed the structural properties of Purkinje cells in a 2mm diameter area surrounding the injection site of the shezh2-encoding lentivirus and found several important changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>First, by H&amp;E staining we noted a reduction in the number of Purkinje cells with the large cytoplasmic vacuoles described previously31,10 (Supplementary Fig. 8b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>In addition, when we stained mouse cerebellum using the rapid Golgi stain (Supplementary Fig. 9) we noted changes in both the dendrites and spine density of the Purkinje cells in the infected areas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Although there was no significant difference in Purkinje cell density between wild type and Atm−/− cerebella with or without shezh2 viral infection, we found that the cross sectional Purkinje cell dendritic profile area was reduced in untreated Atm−/− mice compared to wild type (Fig. 6g and h; Table S6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>This shrinkage was reversed in the areas surrounding the injection and the difference between injected and uninjected brains was significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, knockdown of ezh2 significantly increased the spine density of Purkinje cells in Atm−/− mice in contrast to controls (Fig. 6g and i). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P16"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>To verify the direct effect of loss of ATM-mediated EZH2 phosphorylation on the degenerative process of Purkinje cells in ATM-deficiency, we co-injected lentiviral particles encoding human wild type EZH2, a non-phosphorylatable mutant (2SA, which has the S652A, S734A mutations) or a phosphorylation mimic mutant (2SD, which has the S652D, S734D mutations) together with ezh2 shRNA (which is specific for the mouse Ezh2 message) into the cerebella of wild-type and Atm−/− adult mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>One week after injection of the two lentiviruses, gene transfer was monitored by immunohistochemistry using a human-specific EZH2 antibody (Fig. 7 and Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>S10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>In infected Atm−/− cerebellar neurons, EZH2 phosphorylation mimic mutant (2SD) prevented cell cycle reentry (Fig. 7a and d) and caspase-3 activation (Fig. 7b and e) as well as Purkinje cell atrophy (Fig. 7c and f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>By contrast, EZH2 non-phosphorylatable mutant (2SA) resulted in cell cycle reentry and caspase-3 activation as well as Purkinje cell atrophy in both Atm−/− and wild-type mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>As expected, wild type human EZH2 directly lead to cyclin A and caspase-3 re-appearance in the Atm−/− mutant but not in the wild type, however, overexpression of unmodified human EZH1 had little effect on either wild-type or Atm−/− neurons. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S8"><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Knocking down Ezh2 attenuates behavioral abnormalities of Atm−/− mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P17"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Although Atm mutant mice lack the profound ataxia found in human A-T, they do have reduced motor coordination compared to wild type mice12,37–39. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Therefore, to test the role of enhanced EZH2 stability in this phenotype, we injected shezh2-encoding lentiviral particles into mouse cerebellum at postnatal day 18 (P18) – an age at which the areas reached by viral infection should be greater than in the adult. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Three weeks after intracerebellar infusions, when transgene expression should be maximal, we subjected animals to rota-rod testing and measured locomotor activity in an open field. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>In the rota-rod test, the shezh2-injected Atm−/− mice showed a significant delay in falling (p &lt; 0.05) compared to Atm−/− mutants infused with shezh1 or shgapdh (Fig. 8a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, spontaneous open field activity (measured as distance travelled) was significantly greater in shezh2-injected Atm−/− mice, and approached wild type values (Fig. 8b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>A secondary parameter of ataxic behavior, rearing, was also different dependent on genotype and treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Wild type mice reared more often (p &lt; 0.05), compared with mutants receiving virus encoding shezh1 or shgapdh. However, shezh2-treated Atm−/− mice showed a reversal of this deficiency (Fig. 8c). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S9"><title><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P18"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>We have previously shown that nuclear accumulation of HDAC4 plays a critical role in A-T neurodegeneration12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>In the current work we have uncovered a role for EZH2-mediated histone methylation in the A-T neurodegenerative process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In A-T and Atm−/− mouse brain, histone H3K27 trimethylation showed a significant increase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Further, in the absence of ATM the histone methyltransferase, EZH2, is stabilized, is more readily incorporated into the PRC2 complex and displays enhanced binding to H3K27. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The elevation in H3K27me3 was quantified by a genome-wide analysis that represents the first unbiased, high-resolution mapping of H3K27me3 occupancy in the ATM-deficient brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The increase in chromatin sites where H3K27me3 associates in Atm−/− brain is correlated with a shift in the expression of a variety of cell cycle and neurotrophic genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The result is an EZH2-induced increase in neuronal process degeneration, cell cycle reentry, suppression of neuronal genes, and induction of the apoptotic process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The physiological relevance of these changes in the epigenome is underlined by our finding that knockdown of EZH2 can partially rescue the behavioral disabilities found in Atm−/− mice, a finding with immediate therapeutic interest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>In the aggregate, therefore, our data define a pathological role for elevated EZH2-mediated H3K27me3 in the etiology of A-T. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P19"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>EZH2 was discovered based on its functions during embryogenesis, yet the current work highlights its importance to signaling in the adult brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Other kinases have also been shown to modulate adult EZH2 activity including AKT, CDK1, CDK2 and p38 kinase15,25,40,41. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Adding ATM to this list further integrates the pattern of histone methylation into the signaling activity of a cell by providing evidence that the levels and location of H3K27me3 can respond to DNA damage and oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>This can be seen directly in the alteration of EZH2 levels observed after ionizing radiation or etoposide treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>We note that while Cdk1-mediated EZH2 phosphorylation increases H3K27 methylation15,30, AKT-mediated EZH2 phosphorylation on serine 21 prevents it41. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>This suggests that EZH2 regulation in response to a change in cellular state is complex and bi-directional. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P20"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>ATM deficiency leads to enhanced histone methylation, which is generally associated with a more compact form of chromatin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The observation that DNA damage, which activates ATM, leads to a substantial reduction in histone methylation suggests that activated ATM, by accelerating the degradation of EZH2, would be expected to reduce chromatin condensation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>This would lead to a more open chromatin structure that could aid in the access of the various DNA repair proteins to the injured double helix and suggests a new and previously unrecognized way in which ATM helps in the DNA repair process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>We note that this concept is fully consistent with work showing slower rates of DNA repair in heterochromatin compared with euchromatin42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Previous studies indicate that EZH2 plays a role in determining cancer cell response during the DNA damage response43; two additional studies demonstrate that EZH2 contributes to cancer progression44,45. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Thus our data suggest that ATM-mediated degradation of EZH2 during the DNA damage response is likely to serve a protective function in brain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P21"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Note that as ATM activity increases not only would histone methylation decrease, but because HDAC4 would be less likely to move to the nucleus, the levels of histone deacetylation should decrease12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>These two changes would act in consort with one another; both changes in the histone code would favor a more open chromatin configuration and thus more efficient DNA repair. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Additional insight into the consequences of the ATM-dependent changes in the histone code can be achieved by comparing the H3K27me3 sites defined in this study with the nuclear HDAC4 chromatin binding we reported previously12 (Supplementary Fig. 11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The locations of the two ‘marks’ overlap at only ~2% of the sites in the wild-type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>In ATM-deficiency, however, the overlap increases to more than 5%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The dual epigenetic marks would be predicted to induce gene silencing in the Atm mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The H3K27me3-HDAC4 intersection peaks also appear to be particularly enriched in areas likely to contain cis-acting regulatory sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>This can be seen most easily by comparing the distribution of these areas with those defined by randomly selected peak sets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the H3K27me3-HDAC4 intersections are more likely to select marks within a reasonable cis-acting distance of a gene and are therefore more likely to regulate adjacent gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>It should be noted that while it may be important in determining the A-T phenotype, this overlapping subset of marks comprises only a small fraction of the total, suggesting that the two systems – methylation and acetylation – have largely independent functions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P22"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, our study presents evidence to suggest an expanded epigenetic regulatory model for the neurodegenerative process in A-T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>ATM-deficiency leads to abnormal alteration in EZH2-dependent polycomb epigenetic system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>We propose that changes in the status of cell cycle and neuronal survival gene expression in A-T brain is not only dependent on the consequences of HDAC4 nuclear accumulation; it also relies on PRC2 complex-mediated H3K27me3 changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Identification of a role for ATM in the polycomb silencing system expands our understanding of the dynamic changes underlying histone modifications in the A-T neurodegenerative processes and suggests novel therapeutic targets for treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S10" specific-use="web-only"><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S11"><title><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Antibodies and chemical regents </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P23"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Antibodies against EZH1, EZH2, EED and SUZ12, Aldolase C, calbindin, H3K27me3, alpha Tublin, BrdU and cleaved caspase3 were obtained from Abcam. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Antibodies against EZH2, H3K27me3 and H3K9me3, total histone 3 and phospho-S/T[Q] were obtained from Cell Signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Antibodies against cyclin A and cyclin D1 and β–actin were from Santa Cruz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Antibodies specific against human EZH1 and EZH2 were obtained from Abcam. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Secondary antibodies used for immunocytochemistry were as follows: Alexa 488-labeled chicken anti-mouse or anti-rabbit; Alexa 594-labeled donkey anti-mouse or anti-rabbit (Invitrogen, Eugene, OR); all were used at a dilution of 1:500. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>DAPI (4′,6′-diamidino-2-phenylindol) was used as a nuclear counter stain at 1 μg/ml. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S12"><title><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Constructs and Plasmids </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P24"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>myc-EZH2 and GST-EZH2 were provided by Dr. Mien-chie Hung (The University of Texas M.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, TX) and Haojie Huang (Stony Brook University Medical Center, Stony Brook, NY). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Site-direct mutation of GFP-EZH2 on S652&amp;734/A andS652&amp;734/D and GST-EZH2 on S734A and S652&amp;734/A were performed by Quik Change Mutagenesis Kit (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S13" sec-type="subjects"><title><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Human subjects </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P25"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Human autopsy tissue from four individuals diagnosed with A-T and four age-matched controls was obtained from UCLA Medical Center and Children’s Hospital Los Angeles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Brain tissue was routinely fixed, paraffin embedded, and sectioned at 10 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>All A-T cases were confirmed both clinically and by post-mortem examination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The average age of the subjects was 21 years for the A-T patients and 25 years for non-A-T controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The non-A-T controls were free of any known CNS neurological diseases at the time of death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Human frozen tissue was secured from 4 additional individuals diagnosed with A-T and four age-matched controls; samples were obtained from NICHD Brain and Tissue Bank of Developmental Disorders at the University of Maryland, Baltimore, MD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S14"><title><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P26"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>AtmtmBal/+ mice were a gift from Dr. Yang Xu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Timed pregnancies were established from these matings; the date of appearance of a vaginal plug was considered embryonic day 0.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Embryos were taken at embryonic day 16.5 (E16.5) for either cortical cultures or histology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Animals were allowed to survive for 7 days before sacrifice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>All animal procedures were carried out in accordance with Rutgers University IACUC standards. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The animal facilities at Rutgers University are fully AAALAC accredited. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S15"><title><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Human fibroblast and N2a cell culture </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P27"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>All human control and A-T primary fibroblast cell lines described in this paper were purchased from the Coriell Cell Repository. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Fibroblasts were cultured in fibroblast medium (Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium [DMEM] supplemented with 15% fetal bovine serum [FBS; Hyclone], 1 mM glutamine [Invitrogen], 1% nonessential amino acids [Invitrogen], and penicillin/streptomycin [Invitrogen]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>N2a cells were cultured in DMEM medium supplemented with 10% FBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>To differentiate N2a cells, 24 hours after seeding, culture medium was replaced by DMEM with 1 mM dbcAMP and 0.25% FBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Cells were kept in this differentiation medium for 3–7 days before use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S16"><title><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Primary Neuronal Cultures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P28"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Embryonic cortical neurons were isolated by standard procedures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>For ATM-deficient cultures, all embryos from an AtmtmBal/+ x Atmtm1Bal/+ mating were harvested and treated separately then retrospectively genotyped by PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Isolated E16.5 embryonic cerebral cortices were treated with 0.25% Trypsin-EDTA and dissociated into single cells by gentle trituration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Cells were suspended in Neurobasal medium supplemented with B27 and 2 mM glutamine, then plated on coverslips or dishes coated with poly-L-Lysine (5 mg/mL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>All cultures were grown for a minimum of 5 days in vitro (DIV) before any treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed on a minimum of three cultures from three separate embryos; each condition was examined in triplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>All transfections were carried out using Lipofectamine 2000 after 4–5 DIV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Live imaging of GFP was performed on a heated stage in a controlled 5% CO2 atmosphere at 7–10 DIV. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S17"><title><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemistry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P29"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>For DAB/bright field staining, all paraffin-embedded human sections were deparaffinized inxylene and then rehydrated through graded ethanol to water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The sections were pretreated in 0.3% hydrogen peroxide in methanol for 30 min to remove endogenous peroxidase activity, rinsedin Tris-buffered saline (TBS), and then treated with 0.1 M citrate buffer in a microwave at sufficient power to keep the solution at 100°C for 20 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Sections were cooled in the same buffer at room temperature (RT) for 30 min and rinsed in TBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Slides were incubated in 10% goat serum in PBS blocking solution for1 h at RT, after which primary antibody was applied to the sections that were then incubated at 4°C overnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The sections were washed three times in TBS before applying the secondary antibody (Vector Laboratories). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Secondary antibody was applied for 1 h at RT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Afterwards, sections were rinsed three times in TBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Rinsed sections were then incubated in Vectastain ABC Elitereagent for 1 h and developed using diaminobenzidine, according to the protocol of the manufacturer (Vector Laboratories). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The sections were counterstained with hematoxylin, and after dehydration all sections were mounted in Permount under a glass coverslip. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Control sections were subjected to the identical staining procedure, except for the omission of the primary antibody. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S18"><title><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescence </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P30"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>All paraffin-embedded human sections were deparaffinized inxylene and then rehydrated through graded ethanol to water and PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>For the mouse, cryostat sections were first rinsed in PBS, Subsequent steps were identical for paraffin and cryostat material. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>After rehydration, sections were treated in antigen unmasking solution (low pH) for 30 min at 100°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>After the slides had cooled in buffer for 30 min at room temperature, slides were rinsed in PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Then sections were incubated in 10% goatserum in PBS to block nonspecific binding for 1 h at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>All primary antibodies were diluted in PBS containing 0.5% Triton X-100 and 5% goat serum and incubated with sections overnight at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>After rinsing in PBS, they were incubated for 1 h with secondary antibody, which was conjugated with various fluorescent labeled secondary antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>All sections were mounted in ProLong® Gold antifade reagent with DAPI (Invitrogen) under a glass coverslip. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>All experiments were conducted in triplicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S19"><title><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>ChIP-quantitative real-time PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P31"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>After immunoprecipitation, recovered chromatin fragments were analyzed by real-time PCR using primer pairs specific for 150–250-base-pair (bp) segments corresponding to mouse gene promoter regions (regions upstream of the start codon, near the first exon). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Real-time PCR was performed using EXPRESS SYBR® GreenER™ qPCRSupermix Universal (Invitrogen) on ABI Prism® 7900HT Sequence Detection System (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The relative quantities of immunoprecipitated DNA fragments were calculated by comparison with a standard curve generated by serial dilutions of input DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Data were derived from three independent amplifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>All PCR primer sequences can be found in Table S7. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S20"><title><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>RNA extraction and reverse transcription PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P32"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>RNA was prepared using PureLink micro-to-midi total RNA purification system (Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Semi-quantitative RT-PCR was performed with Superscript III one-step RT-PCR system with platinum Taq High Fidelity (Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>For quantitative Real-time PCR, cDNA was prepared by using oligonucleotide (dT), random primers, and a Thermo Reverse Transcription kit (Signal way Biotechnology). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>All qPCRs were performed using EXPRESS SYBR® GreenER™ qPCRSupermix Universal (Invitrogen) on ABI Prism® 7900HT Sequence Detection System (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>The mRNA level of tubulin or 36B4 was used as an internal control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>All RT-PCR primers are shown on Table S8. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S21"><title><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Western blotting and immunoprecipitation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P33"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>For Western blots, protein extracts from mouse tissue or primary cultures were separated with SDS–PAGE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>For immunoprecipitation, protein extracts were subsequently incubated for overnight at 4°C with the primary antibodies and Protein G Dynabeads (Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The precipitates were washed twice with a lysis buffer and then were resolved on SDS-PAGE gel. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S22"><title><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>In vitro kinase assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P34"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>N2A cells overexpressing wild type Flag-ATM were lysed in TNN buffer and immunoprecipitated with protein G Dynabeads beads (20 μl) and anti-Flag antibody (Sigma). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Kinase reactions were performed using precipitated ATM on beads (~ 15 μl) with either GST-tagged EZH2, the GST-tagged EZH2S734A and GST-tagged EZH2S652&amp;734A purified from bacteria (~ 1 μg protein) in a kinase buffer (50 mM Hepes at pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 6 mM MgCl2, 4 mM MnCl2, 10% glycerol, 1 mM dithiothreitol, 0.1 mM NaOV and 15 μ Ci of [γ-32P] ATP] and incubated at 30 °C for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Proteins were separated by SDS–PAGE, transferred to nitrocellulose membranes and visualized by autoradiography. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S23"><title><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>BrdU incorporation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P35"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>For BrdU labeling, 10 μm BrdU was added to the Neurobasal media at DIV6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>After labeling for 24 hours, the primary neurons were then fixed, and DNA was hydrolyzed by exposing the cells to 2N HCl for 10 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Specimens were then neutralizing in 0.1 M sodium borate (pH 8.6) for 10 minutes and then rinsed extensively in PBS (3X) for 45 min before treatment with blocking reagent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Non-specific antibody binding was blocked by exposing the fixed cells to 5% normal goat serum in 0.1% Triton-X for 1 hour before application of the BrdU primary antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Total cells number was based on DAPI-positive nuclei. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Counts were made of BrdU-positive, DAPI-positive and double-positive cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S24"><title><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P36"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>ChIP was performed with mouse cerebellar cortex fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) solution and stored at −80 °C before use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Brains were cut into small (~1 mm3) pieces and chemically cross-linked by 1% PFA in 1xDPBS solution for 15 min at room temperature, then homogenized, resuspended, lysed in TNN lysis buffers with RNAse, followed by digestion of chromatin DNA with micrococal nuclease (NEB). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>TNN lysates were then incubated with nuclease 10–15 min at 37°C (1 μl, 2000U) plus 1 ml lysate plus 10 μl 0.5 M CaCl2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>The reaction was stopped with 100 μl 0.5 M EDTA on ice, then sonicated to shear crosslinked DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>We used a Branson S450 digital Sonifier at 20% power and delivered ten 30-s pulses (60-s pause between pulses) during which all samples were immersed in an ice bath. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>The resulting whole-cell extract was incubated overnight at 4 °C with 30 μl of Dynal Protein G magnetic beads that had been preincubated with 5 μg of the appropriate antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Beads were washed five times with TNN lysis buffer and once with 1xChIP buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Bound complexes were eluted from the beads by heating to 65 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Whole-cell extract DNA (reserved from the sonication step) was treated to reverse crosslinks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Immunoprecipitated DNA and whole-cell extract DNA were then purified by treatment with 50 mM NaCl and proteinase K for 2 hours at 65 °C with rotation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Purified DNA samples were normalized and subjected to PCR analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Antibodies used for pull downs were: anti-H3K27me3 and anti-histone3, mouse and rabbit IgG were from Cell Signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>After immunoprecipitation, recovered chromatin fragments were subjected to semi-quantitative PCR or real-time PCR for 32–40 cycles, using primer pairs specific for 150–500 bp segments as described in the text. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S25"><title><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>ChIP sequencing analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P37"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>ChIP sequencing libraries were constructed from anti-H3k27me3-immunoprecipitated chromatin using the SOLiD™ DNA fragment library kit (Invitrogen) following the standard ChIP-Seq protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Libraries containing Atm+/+ or Atm−/− samples were bar-coded, applied to beads with emulsion PCR, enriched, and sequenced using the SOLiD™ System v4 at the Centre for Applied Genomics at SickKids Hospital, Toronto. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>A sample prepared without immunoprecipitation from Atm+/+ was used as the input control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Sequenced 50-nt reads and quality strings were aligned to the mouse genome (mm9) using Bowtie 0.12.546 to identify the single, best-quality match location. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Results were converted to BAM format using Samtools. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Peaks were selected, comparing Atm+/+ or Atm−/− against the input control, using Find Peaks 4.047. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Resulting bed-formatted files were imported into the ChIPpeakAnno package48 in R/BioConductor for analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Peak tracks were created and visualized using the UCSC Genome Browser where subsets of peaks were chosen for qPCR validation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S26"><title><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Microarray Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P38"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>RNA was hybridized with the Illumina WG-6 arrays at the Sanford Burnham microarray core facility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Samples from three independent animals were run for each genotype (Atm+/+ and Atm−/−). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Data were extracted using GenomeStudio and imported into R/BioConductor using the lumi package and then fit to a linear model using the limma package. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S27"><title><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>shRNA Knockdown in primary neurons </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P39"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>The hairpin sequences for MISSION® shRNA Lentiviral Transduction Particles including shezh1, shezh2, shgapdh (Table S9) were from Sigma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>After 3 days in culture, primary neurons were infected using a multiplicity of infection (moi) between 5 and 10 to provide an efficiency of infection above 70%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Samples were collected 3–5 days later and different assays were performed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S28"><title><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Lentivirus production and cerebellar injections </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P40"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Lentiviral preparation and cerebellar microinjection were conducted as previous described12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Briefly, premade iLenti™ constructs including a set of ezh1 siRNA-GFP and a set of ezh2 siRNA-GFP were from Applied Biological Material Inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>(Table S10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Human EZH2 and EZH1 lentiviral constructs were from GeneCopoeia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Site-direct mutation of lentiviral EZH2 to 2SA (S652A/S734A) and 2SD (S652D/S734D) were performed by QuikChange Mutagenesis Kit (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>The high lentiviral particle titers were prepared with Lenti-Pac™ Expression Packaging Kits (GeneCopoeia) in HEK 293T cells and purified by Ultra-Pure Lentivirus purification Kits (Applied Biological Material Inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Vancouver). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Stereotaxic intra-cerebellar infusions were delivered to wild type and Atm−/− mice (8 weeks of age) under isoflurane anesthesia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Mice were positioned in a Kopf stereotaxic apparatus and burr holes drilled into the skull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>A 5 μl Hamilton syringe fitted with a 33-gauge needle was lowered into the cerebellum for vector delivery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>The coordinates of the burr hole and ventral location for infusion were: −7.2 mm from bregma, 1.0 mm lateral from the midline, and 3 mm ventral. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>For each cerebellum, slow infusion over 15 minutes of 3–5 μl of lentiviral particles (1–5×109 TU/ml), was performed; the needle was withdrawn 5 min after completing infusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>For knocking down endogenous EZH2 and overexpressing human EZH2, we delivered shezh2: human EZH1,2 lentiviruses as 1:1 ratio in 2-month old mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>After surgery, animals were injected subcutaneously with 0.3 ml pre-warmed saline to avoid dehydration, and were allowed 7 days recovery prior to tissue collection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>For behavioral experiments, lentiviruses were injected into mouse cerebellum at postnatal day 18 (P18), and 3 weeks later, trained for tests of motor behavior. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S29"><title><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Rota-rod test </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P41"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>The rota-rod consisted of a felt-covered steel cylinder fitted to a rotating pump with variable speed settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Age-matched animals were initially trained for two days to walk on the rota-rod, with each day consisting of two 5-minute training trials (inter-trial interval: 2 hr), with the rota-rod speed adjusted to accelerate from 6 rpm to 40 rpm over a 5 min period each day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>After 1 week, mice were returned for testing using the rota-rod adjusted to 10 and 16 rpm over a 5 min test period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Latency to fall off was measured in seconds using a stopwatch by an observer blind to experimental treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S30"><title><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Open-Field Test </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P42"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>The open-field test was conducted as previously described12,49. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Briefly, a four-sided chamber was used as the open field (63 × 57 × 28 cm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>The floor of the arena was divided into a grid of 30 squares. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>After placing a mouse at the center of the arena, locomotor activity was measured over a 5-minute period using an overhead camera connected to a videotape recorder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Mouse movement behavior was digitally tracked using video-tracking software (Spontaneous Motor Activity Recording and Tracking (SMART), San Diego instruments, San Diego, CA) by running the videotape recording through a Dell computer containing a frame grabber. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>In addition to obtaining a measure of distance travelled (measured in cm), an observer blind to experimental treatment scored animals for rearing behavior. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>A rear was defined as an animal raising both front paws off the floor and extending the head and torso upward. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Both rearing numbers and distance travelled were divided into one-minute bins across the 5-minute test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>This was conducted to determine whether changes in behavior between the various groups were time dependent relative to initial exposure to the apparatus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S31"><title><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Stereological analysis of Purkinje cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P43"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Golgi neurohistological staining was performed following a modification of classical Golgi procedure described previously50. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Briefly, mice were killed by cervical dislocation, and the freshly dissected brain was processed with FD Rapid GolgiStain kit™ by FD NeuroTechnologies, Inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>(Ellicott City, MD), and counterstained with cresyl violet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>To examine morphological alteration of Purkinje neurons, six randomly selected cerebellar sagittal cryosections (60 μm) through the entire cerebellum were observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>The numbers of Purkinje cells per cerebellum were estimated with the optical fractionator technique on a Leica microscope using Stereologer software (IPLab Scanalytics Software). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Purkinje cells were counted and analyzed according to the parameters of the optical dissector described as below. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>The optical fractionator probe randomly selected locations within each contour to place a 3-dimensional (250×250×10 μm) counting box within the defined tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Statistical comparisons between different groups were made using a one-factor analysis of variance (ANOVA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Post-hoc comparisons were made using the Bonferroni-Dunn test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S32"><title><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P44"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>All non-behavioral data are presented as the means ± SEM of a minimum of three replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>With the exception of the behavioral data, we evaluated statistical differences by Student’s t test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Behavioral data were analyzed by two-way ANOVAs, with repeated measures included for the open field data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Post hoc testing used Neuman-Keuls or Bonferroni t-tests where appropriate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Effects were considered significant at p &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>No statistical methods were used to predetermine sample size, but sample sizes were similar to those described in previous related studies12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>No randomization of samples was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Data distribution was assumed to be normal but this was not formally tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>No blinding was done. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>The number of samples or cells examined in each analysis is shown in the legends. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S33"><title><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>1</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS560004-supplement-1.pdf" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1388" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>10</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS560004-supplement-10.jpg" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1392" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><label>11</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS560004-supplement-11.jpg" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1396" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD4"><label>12</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS560004-supplement-12.jpg" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1400" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD5"><label>13</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS560004-supplement-13.jpg" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1404" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD6"><label>14</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS560004-supplement-14.jpg" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1408" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD7"><label>15</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS560004-supplement-15.doc" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1412" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD8"><label>2</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS560004-supplement-2.docx" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1416" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD9"><label>3</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS560004-supplement-3.jpg" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1420" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD10"><label>4</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS560004-supplement-4.jpg" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1424" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD11"><label>5</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS560004-supplement-5.jpg" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1429" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD12"><label>6</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS560004-supplement-6.jpg" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1433" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD13"><label>7</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS560004-supplement-7.jpg" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1437" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD14"><label>8</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS560004-supplement-8.jpg" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1441" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD15"><label>9</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS560004-supplement-9.jpg" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1445" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack id="S34"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>We thank Dr. Yang Xu (UCSD, San Diego) for providing AtmtmBal mutant strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>We thank Dr. Richard Gatti (UCLA, Los Angles) for sharing human A-T paraffin-fixed samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Human frozen tissue was obtained from NICHD Brain and Tissue Bank of Developmental Disorders at the University of Maryland, Baltimore, MD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Special thanks to Dr. Rishen Ma (Mount Sinai School of Medicine) for the help in stereological analysis of Purkinje cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>We thank Drs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Michael B. Kastan (Duke Univeristy), Haojie Huang (SUNY at Stony Brook) and Mien-chie Hung (The University of Texas M.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Anderson Cancer Center, Houston) for providing the Flag-ATM, myc-EZH2 and GST-EZH2 plasmids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>The long-term support of the A-T Children’s Project is gratefully acknowledged as is the support of Rutgers University. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>This work was also funded by grants from the NIH: NS20591 and NS71022 to K.H.; RC1 CA147187 to R.P.H. and MH60706 and NIEHS P30 ES05022 to A.K. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><fn id="FN2" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>J.L. and K.H. designed the experiments, analyzed data and wrote the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>J.L. carried out biochemistry experiments and ChIP-qPCR and semi-quantitative PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>M.S and R.P.H. developed, carried out and analyzed data for ChIP-seq analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>J.L., E.M. and A.K. carried out the mouse cerebellar lentiviral injections and behavioral tests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></SecTag><fn id="FN3"><p><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Accession codes </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>The resulting H3K27me3 ChIP sequence files and quality scores are available from the NIH SRA, accession number SRA051384. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Microarray data are available at NIH GEO accession GSE50951. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="R1"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>1SedgwickRPBoderEProgressive ataxia in childhood with particular reference to ataxia-telangiectasiaNeurology10705715196014444443 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R2"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>2BoderEAtaxia-telangiectasia: some historic, clinical and pathologic observationsBirth Defects Orig Artic Ser1125527019751096982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R3"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>3LavinMFShilohYAtaxia-telangiectasia: a multifaceted genetic disorder associated with defective signal transductionCurr Opin Immunol845946419968794004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R4"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>4BitonSBarzilaiAShilohYThe neurological phenotype of ataxia-telangiectasia: solving a persistent puzzleDNA Repair (Amst)710281038200818456574 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R5"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>5SavitskyKA single ataxia telangiectasia gene with a product similar to PI-3 kinaseScience2681749175319957792600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R6"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>6BakkenistCJKastanMBDNA damage activates ATM through intermolecular autophosphorylation and dimer dissociationNature421499506200312556884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R7"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>7DarIBitonSShilohYBarzilaiAAnalysis of the ataxia telangiectasia mutated-mediated DNA damage response in murine cerebellar neuronsJ Neurosci2677677774200616855104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R8"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>8YangYHerrupKLoss of neuronal cell cycle control in ataxia-telangiectasia: a unified disease mechanismJ Neurosci2525222529200515758161 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R9"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>9RimkusSAMutations in String/CDC25 inhibit cell cycle re-entry and neurodegeneration in a Drosophila model of Ataxia telangiectasiaGenes Dev2212051220200818408079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R10"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>10LiJChenJVintersHVGattiRAHerrupKStable brain ATM message and residual kinase-active ATM protein in ataxia-telangiectasiaJ Neurosci317568757721593342 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R11"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>11LiJHanYRPlummerMRHerrupKCytoplasmic ATM in neurons modulates synaptic functionCurr Biol1920912096200919962314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R12"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>12LiJNuclear accumulation of HDAC4 in ATM deficiency promotes neurodegeneration in ataxia telangiectasiaNat Med18783790201222466704 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R13"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>13CaoRZhangYThe functions of E(Z)/EZH2-mediated methylation of lysine 27 in histone H3Curr Opin Genet Dev14155164200415196462 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R14"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>14JuanAHPolycomb EZH2 controls self-renewal and safeguards the transcriptional identity of skeletal muscle stem cellsGenes Dev25789794201121498568 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R15"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>15WeiYCDK1-dependent phosphorylation of EZH2 suppresses methylation of H3K27 and promotes osteogenic differentiation of human mesenchymal stem cellsNat Cell Biol138794201121131960 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R16"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>16FrancisNJFollmerNESimonMDAghiaGButlerJDPolycomb proteins remain bound to chromatin and DNA during DNA replication in vitroCell137110122200919303136 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R17"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>17SurfaceLEThorntonSRBoyerLAPolycomb group proteins set the stage for early lineage commitmentCell Stem Cell728829820804966 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R18"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>18HirabayashiYPolycomb limits the neurogenic competence of neural precursor cells to promote astrogenic fate transitionNeuron63600613200919755104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R19"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>19SauvageauMSauvageauGPolycomb group proteins: multi-faceted regulators of somatic stem cells and cancerCell Stem Cell729931320804967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R20"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>20MargueronRReinbergDThe Polycomb complex PRC2 and its mark in lifeNature469343349201121248841 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R21"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>21CaoRZhangYSUZ12 is required for both the histone methyltransferase activity and the silencing function of the EED-EZH2 complexMol Cell155767200415225548 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R22"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>22BrackenAPEZH2 is downstream of the pRB-E2F pathway, essential for proliferation and amplified in cancerEMBO J2253235335200314532106 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R23"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>23SuIHPolycomb group protein ezh2 controls actin polymerization and cell signalingCell121425436200515882624 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R24"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>24VaramballySGenomic loss of microRNA-101 leads to overexpression of histone methyltransferase EZH2 in cancerScience32216951699200819008416 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R25"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>25ZengXChenSHuangHPhosphorylation of EZH2 by CDK1 and CDK2: a possible regulatory mechanism of transmission of the H3K27me3 epigenetic mark through cell divisionsCell Cycle10579583201121278485 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R26"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>26PereiraJDEzh2, the histone methyltransferase of PRC2, regulates the balance between self-renewal and differentiation in the cerebral cortexProc Natl Acad Sci U S A1071595715962201020798045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R27"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>27MohnFLineage-specific polycomb targets and de novo DNA methylation define restriction and potential of neuronal progenitorsMol Cell30755766200818514006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R28"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>28ChouliarasLEpigenetic regulation in the pathophysiology of Alzheimer’s diseaseProg Neurobiol90498510201020097254 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R29"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>29FagioliniMJensenCLChampagneFAEpigenetic influences on brain development and plasticityCurr Opin Neurobiol19207212200919545993 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R30"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>30ChenSCyclin-dependent kinases regulate epigenetic gene silencing through phosphorylation of EZH2Nat Cell Biol1211081114201020935635 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R31"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>31KuljisROXuYAguilaMCBaltimoreDDegeneration of neurons, synapses, and neuropil and glial activation in a murine Atm knockout model of ataxia-telangiectasiaProc Natl Acad Sci U S A94126881269319979356511 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R32"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>32TianBYangQMaoZPhosphorylation of ATM by Cdk5 mediates DNA damage signalling and regulates neuronal deathNat Cell Biol11211218200919151707 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R33"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>33DemonacosCA new effector pathway links ATM kinase with the DNA damage responseNat Cell Biol6968976200415448695 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R34"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>34BitonSNuclear ataxia-telangiectasia mutated (ATM) mediates the cellular response to DNA double strand breaks in human neuron-like cellsJ Biol Chem2811748217491200616627474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R35"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>35ChenPOxidative stress is responsible for deficient survival and dendritogenesis in purkinje neurons from ataxia-telangiectasia mutated mutant miceJ Neurosci231145311460200314673010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R36"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>36BarlowCATM is a cytoplasmic protein in mouse brain required to prevent lysosomal accumulationProc Natl Acad Sci U S A97871876200010639172 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R37"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>37BarlowCAtm-deficient mice: a paradigm of ataxia telangiectasiaCell8615917119968689683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R38"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>38GuevenNDramatic extension of tumor latency and correction of neurobehavioral phenotype in Atm-mutant mice with a nitroxide antioxidantFree Radic Biol Med419921000200616934683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R39"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>39BrowneSETreatment with a catalytic antioxidant corrects the neurobehavioral defect in ataxia-telangiectasia miceFree Radic Biol Med36938942200415019978 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R40"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>40KanekoSPhosphorylation of the PRC2 component Ezh2 is cell cycle-regulated and up-regulates its binding to ncRNAGenes Dev2426152620201021123648 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R41"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>41ChaTLAkt-mediated phosphorylation of EZH2 suppresses methylation of lysine 27 in histone H3Science310306310200516224021 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R42"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>42GoodarziAAJeggoPLobrichMThe influence of heterochromatin on DNA double strand break repair: Getting the strong, silent type to relaxDNA Repair (Amst)912731282201021036673 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R43"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>43ChouDMA chromatin localization screen reveals poly (ADP ribose)-regulated recruitment of the repressive polycomb and NuRD complexes to sites of DNA damageProc Natl Acad Sci U S A1071847518480201020937877 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R44"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>44StefanssonOAEstellerMEZH2-mediated epigenetic repression of DNA repair in promoting breast tumor initiating cellsBreast Cancer Res13309201121672285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R45"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>45ZeidlerMThe Polycomb group protein EZH2 impairs DNA repair in breast epithelial cellsNeoplasia710111019200516331887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R46"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>46LangmeadBTrapnellCPopMSalzbergSLUltrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genomeGenome Biol10R25200919261174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R47"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>47FejesAPFindPeaks 3.1: a tool for identifying areas of enrichment from massively parallel short-read sequencing technologyBioinformatics2417291730200818599518 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R48"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>48ZhuLJChIPpeakAnno: a Bioconductor package to annotate ChIP-seq and ChIP-chip dataBMC Bioinformatics11237201020459804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R49"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>49CooperJFKusnecovAWMethylmercuric chloride induces activation of neuronal stress circuitry and alters exploratory behavior in the mouseNeuroscience14810481064200717764854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R50"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>50FriedlandDRLosJGRyugoDKA modified Golgi staining protocol for use in the human brain stem and cerebellumJ Neurosci Methods1509095200616081162 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Hypermethylation of H3K27 in human A-T and mouse Atm<sup>−/−</sup> cerebellum</title><p><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>a) Paraffin sections of human cerebellar cortex from individuals who died with no known brain disease or with a diagnosis of A-T were immunostained with H3K27me3 and H3K9me3 antibodies (red). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>Aldolase C immunostaining (green) was used as a marker of Purkinje cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>The white arrows indicate labeled neurons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 50 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>b) The relative intensity of H3K27me3 immunostaining illustrated in panel a). * = p &lt; 0.05 by Student’s t-test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent SEM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>c) The protein level of H3K27me3 increases in A-T cerebellum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>Nuclear protein extracts from frozen cerebellar cortex were probed on western blots with H3K27me3 and H3K9me3 antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>Total histone 3 (H3) was used as a loading control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>Full-length blots are presented in Supplementary Figure 12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>d) Ten micron cryostat sections of wild type (left panels) and Atm−/− (right panels) mouse cerebellum were immunostained with H3K27me3 and H3k9me3 (red). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>Aldolase C immunostaining (green) was used as a marker of Purkinje cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>The white arrows indicate labeled Purkinje neurons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 50 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>e) The relative intensity of H3K27me3 immunostaining illustrated in panel d). * = p &lt; 0.05 by Student’s t-test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>Error bar represents SEM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>f) The protein level of H3K27me3 increases dramatically in Atm−/− mouse cerebellum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Nuclear protein extracts from adult mouse cerebellar cortex were probed on western blots with H3K27me3 and H3K9me3 antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>H3 was used as a loading control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>Full-length blots are presented in Supplementary Figure 12. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms560004f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>ATM-mediated EZH2 phosphorylation prevents PRC2 formation and H3K27 methylation</title><p><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>a) Protein extracts from mouse and frozen human cerebellar cortex were immunoprecipitated with the EZH2 and EZH1, and blotted with the [S/T]Q or EZH2 and EZH1 antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>Tubulin was used as a loading control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>Full-length blots are presented in Supplementary Figure 12. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>b) ) In vitro ATM kinase confirmed EZH2 as a novel ATM target. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>N2a cell extract (100 μg) was immunoprecipitated with the 2C1 anti-ATM antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>Kinase reactions (upper panel) were performed in the presence of purified GST-tagged EZH2, GST-tagged EZH2S734A and GST-tagged EZH2S652&amp;734A (2SA) (1 μg of each) as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>Coomassie blue staining (lower panel) was used to demonstrate total protein load. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>Full-length blots are presented in Supplementary Figure 12. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>c) GFP-EZH2 and Flag-ATM were transfected into human A-T fibroblast cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>Lysates were immunoprecipitated with anti-GFP antibody and blotted with phosphor-[S/T]Q antibody plus anti-GFP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>Flag antibody was used to test expression of Flag-ATM-WT and KD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>Full-length blots are presented in Supplementary Figure 12. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>d) The protein level of EZH2 increases dramatically in A-T cerebellum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>Nuclear protein extracts from frozen cerebellar cortex were probed on western blots with EZH2 and EZH1 antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>Tubulin was loading control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>Full-length blots are presented in Supplementary Figure 12. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>e) The protein level of EZH2 increases dramatically in Atm−/− mouse cerebellum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>Nuclear protein extracts from adult mouse cerebellar cortex were probed on western blots with EZH2 and EZH1 antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>Full-length blots are presented in Supplementary Figure 12. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>f) PRC2 formation and H3K27 methylation is depended on ATM-mediated EZH2 phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>GFP-EZH2 WT and phosphorylation mutant (2SA) and phosphorylation mimic (2SD) were overexpressed in N2a cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>PRC2 complex were evaluated by examination of SUZ12, EED and H3K27me3 from EZH2 immunoprecipitates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>Full-length blots are presented in Supplementary Figure 12. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>g) ATM-dependent EZH2 phosphorylation is critical to EZH2 degradation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>GFP-EZH2 WT and the non-phosphorylatable mutant (2SA) were overexpressed in N2a cells followed by treatment with CHX for different times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>GFP-EZH1 was control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>Full-length blots are presented in Supplementary Figure 12. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>h) Quantification of three repetitions of the experiment illustrated in panel g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>Data represent the mean ± SD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms560004f2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Shifted H3K27me3 chromatin-binging pattern is related to downregulated neuronal genes in Atm<sup>−/−</sup> mouse cerebellum</title><p><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>a) An illustration of H3K27me3 ChIP-seq peak distribution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>The numbers of peaks per bin (1% of genome) are plotted by chromosomal position, comparing Atm+/+ (red) with Atm−/− (blue). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>b) Semi-quantitative RT-PCRs from product of H3K27me3 ChIP show increased enrichment of H3K27me3 binding to promoter regions of mef2a, slit1, synj2, nlgn1 and cdk5rap2 in Atm−/− cerebellum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>Full-length gel are presented in Supplementary Figure 12. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>c) Following total H3 ChIP or H3K27me3 ChIP from wild-type and Atm−/− cerebellar cortex, quantitative real-time PCR analysis was performed for the presence of specific neuronal target genes (* = p &lt; 0.01). gapdh was used as a control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>d) Microarray results are summarized in a volcano plot of log2 fold change (Atm+/+ - Atm−/−) versus log10 of the p value adjusted for multiple measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>The top 25 downregulated (red) and upregulated (green) genes are colored, with the top 10 genes labeled. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>Dashed lines indicate 2-fold up or down (vertical) and p = 0.05 (horizontal). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>e) Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was performed with specific primers for target genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was extracted from mouse cerebellar cortex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>Data represent the mean ± SD of three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms560004f3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>ATM-dependent EZH2 phosphorylation affects neuronal cell cycle and DNA damage response</title><p><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>a) Human control and A-T fibroblast and N2a cells (non-differentiated and differentiated) were immunostained with H3K27me3 with or without γ–radiation (10 Gy) treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 50 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>b–c) Protein extracts from control and A-T fibroblast (b) and N2a cells (c) with or without γ–radiation (IR) were probed on western blots with the antibodies indicated at left. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>Full-length blots are presented in Supplementary Figure 12. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>d) ATM-dependent EZH2 phosphorylation affected BrdU incorporation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>N2a cells were transfected with GFP-EZH2 WT (wild type), 2SA and 2SD at Day1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>Differentiation media was added at Day3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>BrdU (Red) was added to the medium to assess cell cycle activity at Day5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>Scale bar = 25 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>e) Quantification of BrdU incorporation illustrated in panel d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>The bars represent the percentage of BrdU/GFP double positive cells to total GFP positive cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>Each bar represents the average of three independent experiments; error bars denote SEM (* = p &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms560004f4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Knockdown of EZH2 prevents cell death and cell cycle reentry in Atm<sup>−/−</sup> neurons</title><p><text><SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>a) E16.5 cortical neurons were infected at DIV3 with either control lentivirus (shezh1) or virus encoding shezh2. On DIV6, BrdU was added to the medium to assess cell cycle activity (red) in Map2-positve neurons (green). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 50 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>b) Map2/BrdU double-labeled cells were counted in replicate cultures, their numbers are displayed as a percent of the total number of Map2-positive cells (* = p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>c) E16.5 cortical neurons were infected at DIV3 with either control lentivirus (shezh1) or virus encoding shezh2. On DIV7, after treatment with etoposide for 3 hours, cells were fixed and stained with cleaved caspase-3 antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>Scale bar, 50 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>d) Cell death was quantified by counting the number of activated caspase-3 immunostained cells and expressing these numbers as a percentage of the total Map2-positive cells (*, p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>e) E16.5 cortical neurons were infected at DIV3 with either control lentivirus (shezh1) or virus encoding shezh2. On DIV14, cells were fixed and stained with V-GLUT and Map2 antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>Scale bar = 5 μM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>f) Quantification of mean spine density for cultured neurons; genotype and lentiviral infection as indicated (error bars = SEM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>Sample numbers: nAtm+/+&amp;GFP = 20, nAtm−/−&amp;GFP = 21, nAtm+/+&amp;shezh1 = 26, nAtm−/−&amp;shezh1 = 23, nAtm+/+&amp;shezh2 = 28, and nAtm−/−&amp;shezh2=33. *** = p &lt; 0.01, NS = p &gt; 0.05 by Mann-Whitney test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms560004f5"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Knockdown of EZH2 prevents neurodegeneration of Atm<sup>−/−</sup> mice</title><p><text><SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>a) Representative images of cyclin A- and GFP-stained PCs show the effects of knockdown of ezh2. Scale bar, 50 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>b) Quantification of the cyclin A staining shown in panel a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>Each bar represents the average of three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>Error bar = SEM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>c) Representative images of cleaved caspase-3- and GFP-stained PCs show the effects of knockdown of ezh2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>d) Quantification of the staining shown in panel c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>Each bar represents the average of three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>Error bar = SEM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>e) Representative images of calbindin-stained PCs show the effects of knockdown of ezh2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>The white arrows mark degenerating PCs with atrophy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>Scale bar = 50 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>f) Quantification of the staining shown in panel e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>Each bar represents the average of three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>Error bar = SEM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>g) Representative Golgi-stained images of the dendritic arbors and distal spine density of PCs show the effects of lentiviral delivery of shezh2 on degenerative progression in Atm−/− cerebellum. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>h–i) Quantitative assessments of dendritic profiles and density of PCs shown in panel g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>There were significant differences in PCs dendritic profile areas (ANOVA; F(2,14) = 3.6; p&lt; 0.005) and spine density (ANOVA: F(2,14) = 18.7; p&lt; 0.01) between wild type and Atm−/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>The dendritic profiles (F(2,14) = 6.7; p&lt; 0.005) and spine density (F(2,14) = 13.6; p&lt; 0.01) of Purkinje cells in Atm−/− mice with shezh2 infection was significantly increased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>The counted PCs cell numbers: nAtm+/+&amp;shgdph = 26, nAtm−/−&amp;shgdpah = 29, nAtm+/+&amp;shezh2 = 27, nAtm−/−&amp;shezh2 = 31. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>Each bar represents the average of three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>Error bar =SEM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms560004f6"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Effect of ATM-dependent EZH2 phosphorylation on the degeneration of Purkinje cell</title><p><text><SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>a–b) Representative images of Cyclin A- and cleaved caspase3-stained Purkinje cells show the effects of lentiviral delivery of different EZH2 mutants on degenerative progression in Atm−/− mouse cerebellum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>Brain sections collected 1 week after injection were stained with Cyclin A and cleaved caspase3 (Red) and compared with ectopic EZH2 positive neurons (green). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>Non-phosphorylatable mutant = 2SA; phosphorylation mimic mutant = 2SD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>c) Representative images of calbindin-stained Purkinje cells show the effects of lentiviral delivery of different EZH2 mutants on Purkinje cell atrophy in Atm−/− mouse cerebellum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>Brain sections collected 1 week after injection were stained with calbindin (Red) and compared with ectopic EZH2 positive neurons (green). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>d–f) Quantification of the staining shown in panel a–c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>Each bar represents the average of three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>Error bar = SEM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms560004f7"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Knockdown of EZH2 reverses neurological behavioral abnormalities of Atm<sup>−/−</sup> mice</title><p><text><SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>a) Rota-rod testing demonstrated thatshezh2-injected Atm−/− mice had longer latency-to-fall times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>Time measured to remain on the rota-rod was analyzed by a two-way ANOVA, and found to reveal a significant genotype x treatment interaction (F(2,45) = 23.1, p&lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>A marked main effect of genotype was also observed (F(1,45) = 656.4, p&lt; 0.0001), reflecting the ataxia in Atm−/− mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>b–c) Locomotor activity and rearing in the open field were measured across one-minute bins for a total of five consecutive minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>(b) For distance travelled, a two-way ANOVA with repeated measures revealed significant effects of genotype (F(1,45) = 37.8, p&lt; 0.0001), treatment (F(2,45) = 3.9, p&lt; 0.027) and a genotype x treatment interaction (F(2,45) = 3.7, p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>The latter was supported by a clear separation of values in Atm−/− mice between those given shezh2 and those administered shezh1 and shgapdh. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>(c) For rearing, significant main effects (Group: F(1,45) = 172.4, p&lt; 0.0001; Treatment: F(2,45) = 25.0, p&lt; 0.0001) and an interaction (F(2,45) = 13.8, p &lt; 0.0001) were similarly observed, once again contributed to by the deviation to normal wild type numbers by shezh2-infused Atm−/− mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms560004f8"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
