<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gbe</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">gbe</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Genome Biology and Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1759-6653</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3730352</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evt101</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">evt101</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>A Comparative Analysis of Mitochondrial ORFans: New Clues on Their Origin and Role in Species with Doubly Uniparental Inheritance of Mitochondria </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Milani</surname><given-names>Liliana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evt101-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="evt101-COR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ghiselli</surname><given-names>Fabrizio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evt101-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guerra</surname><given-names>Davide</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evt101-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Breton</surname><given-names>Sophie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evt101-AFF2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Passamonti</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evt101-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="evt101-AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Dipartimento di Scienze Biologiche, Geologiche ed Ambientali, University of Bologna, Bologna, Italy</aff><aff id="evt101-AFF2"><sup>2</sup>Département de Sciences Biologiques, Université de Montréal, Montréal, Québec, Canada</aff><author-notes><corresp id="evt101-COR1">*Corresponding author: E-mail: <email>liliana.milani@unibo.it</email>.</corresp><fn><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Associate editor: Bill Martin </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>3</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1408</fpage><lpage>1434</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Despite numerous comparative mitochondrial genomics studies revealing that animal mitochondrial genomes are highly conserved in terms of gene content, supplementary genes are sometimes found, often arising from gene duplication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial ORFans (ORFs having no detectable homology and unknown function) were found in bivalve molluscs with Doubly Uniparental Inheritance (DUI) of mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>In DUI animals, two mitochondrial lineages are present: one transmitted through females (F-type) and the other through males (M-type), each showing a specific and conserved ORF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The analysis of 34 mitochondrial major Unassigned Regions of Musculista senhousia F- and M-mtDNA allowed us to verify the presence of novel mitochondrial ORFs in this species and to compare them with ORFs from other species with ascertained DUI, with other bivalves and with animals showing new mitochondrial elements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Overall, 17 ORFans from nine species were analyzed for structure and function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Many clues suggest that the analyzed ORFans arose from endogenization of viral genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The co-option of such novel genes by viral hosts may have determined some evolutionary aspects of host life cycle, possibly involving mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The structure similarity of DUI ORFans within evolutionary lineages may also indicate that they originated from independent events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>If these novel ORFs are in some way linked to DUI establishment, a multiple origin of DUI has to be considered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>These putative proteins may have a role in the maintenance of sperm mitochondria during embryo development, possibly masking them from the degradation processes that normally affect sperm mitochondria in species with strictly maternal inheritance. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>mitochondrial ORFans</kwd><kwd>mitochondrial inheritance</kwd><kwd>Doubly Uniparental Inheritance of mitochondria</kwd><kwd>endogenous virus</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><counts><page-count count="27"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Comparative mitochondrial genomics revealed that animal mitochondrial DNAs (mtDNAs) are highly conserved in terms of gene content (Boore 1999; Gissi et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>These small, typically circular and intron-less molecules encode 2 ribosomal RNAs, 22 transfer RNAs, and 13 protein subunits of the mitochondrial respiratory complexes and ATP synthase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The other subunits of the electron transport chain and all the proteins involved in other mitochondrial functions, such as mtDNA replication and expression, are encoded by the nucleus (Boore 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>However, supplementary genes are sometimes found in mtDNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Many mechanisms are responsible for the origin of such new genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>For example, novel mitochondrial Open Reading Frames (ORFs) can arise from gene duplication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>In bivalve molluscs, a cox2 duplication is found in the clam Ruditapes philippinarum (Bivalvia, Veneridae) (Okazaki M and Ueshima R, unpublished data; GenBank AB065375.1) and in the mussel Musculista senhousia (Bivalvia, Mytilidae) (Passamonti et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Moreover, nad2 duplication is at the origin of two novel ORFs in the oyster genus Crassostrea (Bivalvia, Ostreidae) (Wu et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Extra elements were also found in Cnidaria mtDNA, either from duplication of extant genes or not: a duplicated cox1 in some hydroidolinan hydrozoans (Cnidaria, Hydrozoa), two novel ORFs in Medusozoa (Kayal et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>2011), and a novel ORF in every octocoral (Cnidaria, Anthozoa) that has been screened to date (McFadden et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>One of the two medusozoan ORFs shares several conserved motifs characteristic of the polymerase domain typical of family B-DNA polymerases (polB; Shao et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The other ORF, named ORF314, do not resemble any other known protein. Kayal et al. (2011) attributed the origin of these two extra elements to an ancient invasion by a linear plasmid that caused the linearization of the mtDNA in Medusozoa, consistent with a previously established hypothesis for polB-like sequences found in the linear mtDNA of fungi and algae (Mouhamadou et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The conservation of both sequence length and position suggested some level of selection pressure for their maintenance in the mtDNA of most medusozoans (Kayal et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The octocoral extra ORF is recognized as a putatively DNA mismatch repair protein (mtMutS) (Pont-Kingdon et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>1995; Claverie et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>2009; Bilewitch and Degnan 2011; Ogata et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>As for medusozoan ORFs, mtMutS was supposed to be originated by horizontal gene transfer, but in this case either through an epsilonproteobacterium or a viral infection (Claverie et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>2009; Bilewitch and Degnan 2011; Ogata et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, novel mitochondrial ORFs have been also discovered in bivalve molluscs with Doubly Uniparental Inheritance (DUI) of mitochondria (Skibinski et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>1994a, 1994b; Zouros et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>1994a, 1994b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Specifically, in metazoans, mitochondria are commonly inherited maternally by Strictly Maternal Inheritance (SMI) (Birky 2001), whereas in DUI animals two mitochondrial lineages are present: one transmitted through females (F-type) and the other through males (M-type). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In DUI bivalves, females inherit F-type mtDNA, whereas males inherit both F- and M-types (Skibinski et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>1994a, 1994b; Zouros et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>1994a, 1994b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>In DUI bivalves (orders Mytiloida, Unionoida, and Veneroida), two novel lineage-specific ORFs were found, one in the F-mtDNA (fORF) and one in the M-mtDNA (mORF) (Breton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>2009; Breton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>2011a, 2011b; Ghiselli et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>These novel ORFs have been hypothesized to be responsible for the different mode of mtDNA transmission and the maintenance of gonochorism in DUI bivalves (Breton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>2009, 2011a, 2011b). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>In all the analyzed DUI Mytilus species, the novel fORF is localized in the Largest Unassigned Region (LUR) and encodes a putative protein of more than 100 amino acids (aa), suggesting its maintenance in the subfamily Mytilinae for more than 10 million years (Breton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>2011b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>A fORF is present also in the F-mtDNA of Musculista senhousia, a DUI mytilid of the subfamily Crenellinae (Breton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>2011b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>In the venerid R. philippinarum, the fORF is localized in the Female Largest Unassigned Region (FLUR), whereas the mORF in the Male Unassigned Region 21 (Ghiselli et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the two lineage-specific ORFs found in the freshwater mussel Venustaconcha ellipsiformis (Bivalvia, Unionidae), the fORF (found between tRNA-Glu and nad2) and the mORF (found between tRNA-Asp and nad4L), are both translated (Breton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>2009), and the female-transmitted novel protein is not only present in mitochondria but also in the nuclear membrane and in egg nucleoplasm (Breton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>2011a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>These findings might support an involvement of these novel mitochondrial genes in some, still unknown, key biological functions in bivalve species with DUI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>For instance, it has been suggested that the newly identified mtORFs in DUI bivalves might have a role in determining the fate of sperm mitochondria in fertilized eggs, maybe leading to the two distribution patterns of spermatozoon mitochondria observed in DUI early embryos: the aggregated pattern, in which these mitochondria form a cluster along the cleavage furrow in two-blastomere embryos and among blastomeres in four-cell embryos, and the dispersed pattern, in which sperm mitochondria are randomly scattered (Cao et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>2004; Cogswell et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>2006; Milani et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>2011, 2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The analysis of 34 mitochondrial major Unassigned Regions (URs) of M. senhousia F- and M-mtDNA allowed us to verify the presence of novel mitochondrial ORFs in this species and to compare them with novel ORFs from other bivalve species with ascertained DUI, with other bivalves and with animals showing new mitochondrial elements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>We found that many features are shared by all novel ORFs, allowing us to formulate an hypothesis on their possible shared origin. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Gametes Collection, DNA Extraction, PCRs, and Sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>M. senhousia specimens from Venice lagoon (Italy) were induced to spawn in sea water with oxygen peroxide, according to Morse et al. (1977). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Each spawning was analyzed with a light microscope to sex specimens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Sperm and eggs were collected and then centrifuged at 3,000 × g; after that, sea water was removed and replaced with ethanol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Gametes were stored at −20 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Total DNA extraction from gametes of 11 females and 12 males was performed with DNeasy Tissue Kit (Qiagen) following manufacturer instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>All polymerase chain reactions (PCRs) were executed on a 2720 Thermal Cycler (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>All primers were provided by Invitrogen™ (see list of primers in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary material S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Long PCRs, using gamete DNA extractions as template, were performed to obtain a segment containing the whole Largest Unassigned Region (LUR) (i.e., in both mtDNAs, the region between rrnL and cob); in the F-mtDNA, this region also contains the Female Unassigned Region 2 (FUR2) (see Passamonti et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>2011 for annotation details). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Primers for long-PCRs are the same used in Passamonti et al. (2011): M-mtDNA from sperm was amplified with primers M-16S103F and M-cob386R, whereas F-mtDNA from eggs with primers F-16S142F and F-cob383R (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary material S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Both segments were amplified with Herculase II Fusion Enzyme kit (Stratagene) in a 50 µl reaction volume composed of 10 µl 5× Herculase II Run Buffer, 0.5 µl of 100 mM dNTP mix, 1.25 µl of 10 µM primers, 0.5 µl of Herculase II Fusion DNA Polymerase, 5 µl of total DNA, and 31.5 µl of Nuclease-free water (Ambion Inc.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Long PCR cycles followed the same scheme for the M- and the F-mtDNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The reactions started with an initial denaturation at 95 °C for 5 min, then 30 cycles of denaturation at 95 °C for 20 s, annealing at 48 °C for 20 s and extension at 68 °C for 10 s, then a final extension at 68 °C for 8 min. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Long PCR products were used as a template to amplify single overlapping segments of the LURs and the FUR2 with standard PCRs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Primers for standard PCRs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary material S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) were designed with Primer3 (Rozen and Skaletsky 2000) on the two complete M. senhousia F- and M-mtDNAs (GenBank accession nos. GU001953–4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>GoTaq® Flexi Dna Polymerase (Promega) kit was used for standard PCRs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Reactions were performed in a 50 µl volume composed of 10 µl of 5× Green GoTaq Flexi Buffer, 6 µl of 25 mM MgCl2, 1 µl of 40 µM dNTP mix (10 µM each dNTP), 2.5 µl of 10 µm primers, 0.25 µl of GoTaq Dna Polymerase 5 U/µl, 4 µl of template DNA from the long PCRs, and 24 µl of Nuclease-free water (Ambion Inc.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>LURs and FUR2 were amplified with the following cycle: initial denaturation at 95 °C for 2 min, 30 cycles of denaturation at 95 °C for 30 s, annealing at 48 °C for 30 s, extension at 72 °C for 90 s, and a final extension at 72 °C for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>All PCR products were purified with Wizard SV Gel and PCR clean-up System (Promega) kit, GenElute PCR clean-up kit, and GenElute Extraction kit (Sigma-Aldrich), following manufacturer instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Sequencing was performed at Macrogen Inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>(Seoul, South Korea). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Sequences were assembled and aligned with MEGA5 (Tamura et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Novel Mitochondrial ORFs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide Level: Sequence Conservation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>We used ORF Finder (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gorf">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gorf</ext-link>, last accessed July 23, 2013) to assess the presence of novel ORFs in DUI species LURs present in GenBank, using the invertebrate mitochondrial genetic code. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>For DUI species, novel mitochondrial sex-specific ORFs were already described and confirmed in literature (Mytilus spp., M. senhousia: Breton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>2011b; V. ellipsiformis: Breton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>2009; R. philippinarum: Ghiselli et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The obtained sequences of M. senhousia FUR2 and 689 annotated mt LURs of four Mytilus species (Mytilus californianus, Myt. edulis, Myt. galloprovincialis, and Myt. trossulus) (Bivalvia, Mytilidae) were checked to assess the conservation of the ORFs described in Passamonti et al. (2011) and Breton et al. (2011b) (last GenBank access: September 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The new sequences of M. senhousia LURs were also searched for the presence of novel ORFs (only the longest ORFs found in all sequences were considered). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>In the analyzed DUI species, we will refer to the ORFs present either in the F or the M mtDNA (i.e., lineage-specific ORFs) as fORF and mORF, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>For comparison, ORFs were searched also in the LUR of the venerid Paphia euglypta, a species in which the presence of DUI has not been investigated yet (only one LUR sequence is available; table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Specific names are given to non-lineage-specific extra mtORFs, comprising mtORFs in non-DUI species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>p-distances of novel ORFs of M. senhousia and other DUI species were calculated with MEGA5 (Tamura et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>2011) using the bootstrap method on all suitable sequences available in GenBank. Table 1Sequences Used in the AnalysesSpeciesmt GenomeAccession NumberORFMollusca, Bivalvia    Musculista senhousiaFGU001953Mse-FORF, Mse-ORF-BKC243365–75Mse-FORFKC243354–64Mse-ORF-BMGU001952Mse-ORF-BKC243376–87Mse-ORF-B    Mytilus californianusFAY515227Mca-FORFMAF188284Mca-MORF1, Mca-MORF2    Mytilus edulisFAY350784Med-FORFMAY823623Med-MORF    Mytilus galloprovincialisFAY497292Mga-FORFMHM027630Mga-MORF    Mytilus trossulusFGU936625Mtr-FORFMAF188282Mtr-MORF    Ruditapes philippinarumFAB065375Rph-FORFKC243324–31Rph-FORFMAB065374Rph-MORFKC243347–53Rph-MORF    Venustaconcha ellipsiformisFFJ809753Vel-FORFMFJ809752Vel-MORF    Paphia euglyptaGU269271Peu-ORFCnidaria    Pelagia noctilucaJN700949Pno-ORF314    Alatina moseriYP_005353032.1Amo-PolB    Incrustatus comauensisAFU34533.1Ico-mtMutSNote.—Mitochondrial genome type is specified only for ascertained DUI species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>ORF column is the name given to the amino acid sequence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Protein Level: Structural and Functional Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The above-mentioned ORFs were translated and analyzed at the amino acid level (see table 1 for the sequences in which the analyzed ORFs are included, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary material S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online, for amino acid sequences). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>We will refer to the translations of fORFs and mORFs of DUI species as FORF and MORF, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>To find Signal Peptides (SPs) we used Phobius (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://phobius.sbc.su.se/">http://phobius.sbc.su.se/</ext-link>, last accessed July 23, 2013; Käll et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>2004), InterProScan (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/pfa/iprscan/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/pfa/iprscan/</ext-link>, last accessed July 23, 2013; Zdobnov and Apweiler 2001), PrediSi (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.predisi.de/">http://www.predisi.de/</ext-link>, last accessed July 23, 2013; Hiller et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>2004), and SignalP 4.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/SignalP/">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/SignalP/</ext-link>, last accessed July 23, 2013; Petersen et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>2011) softwares, while TMpred (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ch.embnet.org/software/TMPRED_form.html">http://www.ch.embnet.org/software/TMPRED_form.html</ext-link>, last accessed July 23, 2013; Hofmann and Stoffel 1993), Phobius (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://phobius.sbc.su.se/">http://phobius.sbc.su.se/</ext-link>, last accessed July 23, 2013; Käll et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>2004), InterProScan (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/pfa/iprscan/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/pfa/iprscan/</ext-link>, last accessed July 23, 2013; Zdobnov and Apweiler 2001), Prodiv-TMHMM (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://topcons.cbr.su.se/">http://topcons.cbr.su.se/</ext-link>, last accessed July 23, 2013; Bernsel et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>2009), and Rhythm (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://proteinformatics.charite.de/rhythm/index.php?site=references">http://proteinformatics.charite.de/rhythm/index.php?site=references</ext-link>, last accessed July 23, 2013) were used to localize putative transmembrane helices (TM-helices). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Atome 2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://atome.cbs.cnrs.fr/AT2/meta.html">http://atome.cbs.cnrs.fr/AT2/meta.html</ext-link>, last accessed July 23, 2013; Pons and Labesse 2009), I-Tasser (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zhanglab.ccmb.med.umich.edu/I-TASSER/">http://zhanglab.ccmb.med.umich.edu/I-TASSER/</ext-link>, last accessed July 23, 2013; Zhang 2008), and HHpred (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://toolkit.tuebingen.mpg.de/hhpred">http://toolkit.tuebingen.mpg.de/hhpred</ext-link>, last accessed July 23, 2013; Söding et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>2005) were used to find similarities with known proteins and to find clues on the possible functions of the mtORFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Alignments of the putative novel mitochondrial proteins were performed with PSI-COFFEE (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tcoffee.crg.cat/apps/tcoffee/do:psicoffee">http://tcoffee.crg.cat/apps/tcoffee/do:psicoffee</ext-link>, last accessed July 23, 2013; Di Tommaso et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial novel ORFs recently found in Cnidaria were included in the function analysis for comparison: two putatively active proteins, DNA polymerase beta (PolB) (Alatina moseri: Cnidaria, Cubozoa, Alatinidae) (Smith et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>2011) and DNA mismatch repair protein (mtMutS) (Incrustatus comauensis: Cnidaria, Anthozoa, Clavulariidae) (McFadden and van Ofwegen 2013), and ORF-314 (Pelagia noctiluca: Cnidaria, Scyphozoa, Discomedusae) (Kayal et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>2011) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary material S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Last accession to databases was in September 2012. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>p-distances of amino acid sequences of each novel ORFs were calculated using the bootstrap method with MEGA5 (Tamura et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Percentage of amino acid difference of novel proteins and of all mtDNA-encoded protein genes were calcultated with MEGA5 (as in Breton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>2011a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>For the Myt. edulis species complex (i.e., Myt. edulis, Myt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Galloprovincialis, and Myt. trossulus), pairwise sequence difference was first calculated for each gene and the results were then exported to Microsoft Excel for calculations of means and standard deviations (SDs). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Novel Mitochondrial Open Reading Frames in Bivalves </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The obtained M. senhousia LUR (FLUR of 11 females, 4,518–4,643 bp; MLUR of 12 males, 2,812–2,854 bp) and FUR2 (11 females, 542–543 bp) sequences were deposited in GenBank (FLUR accession nos.: KC243354–64; MLUR accession nos.: KC243376–87; FUR2 accession nos.: KC243365–75). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The fORF, found in FUR2 on the heavy strand (as all standard coding genes) (fig. 1), is conserved in all samples (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online): its start and stop codons are always ATC and TAA, respectively, and its length is always 366 bp (121 aa). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>For nucleotidic p-distance see table 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Another ORF, ORF-B, has been identified in MLUR and FLUR in the middle of Subunits B, on the reverse strand (fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>In all males, ORF-B is always 318 bp long and its start and stop codons are ATG and TAA, respectively (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>In females, Subunit B is duplicated (fig. 1) and ORF-B is not conserved as in males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The start codon is always ATG, and the stop codons can be TAA or TAG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Subunit B can contain one complete ORF-B (342–408 bp; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) or two overlapping ORFs, together forming an ORF-B, due to a deletion of one T in a five-T string which breaks the frame. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Two females showed only the version with the two overlapping ORFs, never showing the complete ORF-B sequence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>1.—Largest Unassigned Regions (LURs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Schematic structure of female (F) and male (M) LURs of Musculista senhousia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Triangles indicate tRNAs. Table 2p-Distance (p-D) and Standard Error Values of Novel Mitochondrial ORFs in DUI BivalvesSpeciesORFNucleotideTranslationNp-DSEp-DSEMusculista senhousiafORF0.0190.0040.0350.01011Male ORF-B0.0040.0020.0080.00412Female ORF-Ba0.0240.0050.0560.0128Overall ORF-Bb0.0300.0060.0630.01420Mytilus californianusfORF0.0050.0030.0140.0084mORF10.0150.0090.0310.0214mORF20.0110.0070.0330.0224Mytilus edulisfORF0.0130.0020.0260.006134mORF0.0170.0040.0390.01225Mytilus galloprovincialisfORF0.0240.0040.0480.00916mORF0.0290.0080.0620.02147mORF (edulis-like)c0.0230.0070.0420.01714Mytilus trossulusfORF0.0070.0020.0140.0058mORF0.0250.0070.0460.0169Ruditapes philippinarumfORF0.0090.0030.0110.0068mORF0.0040.0020.0000.0007Venustaconcha ellipsiformisfORF0.0000.0000.0000.0003Note.—Number of ORF sequences used for each species is dependant on the number of available and suitable sequences on GenBank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>p-distances of Myt. edulis, Myt. galloprovincialis, and Myt. trossulus mORFs were calculated only on the last part of the ORF immediately following the poly-A sequence (see text for details). N = number of sequences used.aOnly complete female ORF-B were considered.bMale ORF-B and complete female ORF-B were considered.cmORF sequences matching Myt. edulis mORF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>mt LURs of four Mytilus species (GenBank accession nos. in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) were searched for the presence of the novel lineage-specific ORF described in Breton et al. (2011b): only the longest f- and mORFs were considered, as the shortest ones are often parts of them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>A total of 201 Mytilus sequences containing complete ORFs were found (downloaded in September 2012): 197 fORFs and 17 mORFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Many mORFs were found showing frame-disrupting mutations (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>These alterations were more common in the first part of the expected mORF in Myt. edulis, Myt. galloprovincialis, and Myt. trossulus, before and inside a long poly-A sequence (from 17 to 48 nucleotides), while the last part is usually conserved in comparison to the ORFs described in Breton et al. (2011b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>p-distances of Myt. edulis, Myt. galloprovincialis, and Myt. trossulus mORFs, because of alignment issues, were calculated only on the part of the ORF following the poly-A sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>As indicated by the p-distance analysis (table 2), Mytilus spp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>fORFs are less variable than mORFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>In R. philippinarum the situation is the opposite, as mORF is more conserved than fORF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>For V. ellipsiformis only three fORF sequences were available, but they show a remarkable conservation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>An ORF was also found in the LUR of the venerid P. euglypta. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Putative Novel Proteins from Bivalve Mitochondrial ORFs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Table 1 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary material S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online, show sequences of the analyzed novel ORFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>A global alignment including all the analyzed amino acid sequences was not possible due to their divergence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), but groups with some similarities were found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Mse-ORF-B translation has practically the same amino acid sequence in the two genomes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S4</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Mytilid FORFs are largely similar among each other (fig. 2A), most of all those of Myt. edulis complex (Med-, Mga-, and Mtr-FORFs) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S5</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>With the only exception of Mca-MORFs, Mytilus MORFs are also highly similar (fig. 2B; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S6</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), and show a characteristic string of lysines (poly-K region) of variable length (8–12 aa; translation of a poly-A nucleotide sequence), absent from MORFs of other species and from FORFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Downstream the poly-K region, Mytilus MORFs show a high similarity among each other, whereas in their N-terminus they are quite variable (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S6</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Although Mytilus FORFs and MORFs appear different between each other (see for example Myt. edulis, fig. 3A), Rph-FORF and MORF show several shared domains (fig. 3B), and also Vel-FORF and MORF have a big domain in their N-terminal showing similarity (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S7</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>2.—(A) PSI-Coffee alignment of FORFs of family Mytilidae (accession nos.: GU001953, AY515227, AY350784, AY497292, GU936625); (B) PSI-Coffee alignment of MORFs of Mytilus species (accession nos.: AY823623, HM027630, AF188282). Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>3.—(A) PSI-Coffee alignment of Mytilus edulis FORF and MORF (accession nos. of sequences containing the ORF are reported in the figure); (B) PSI-Coffee alignment of Ruditapes philippinarum FORF (accession nos. of entire FLURs: KC243324–31) and MORF (accession nos. of entire MUR21 sequences: KC243347–53). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Shared domains among the novel putative proteins are boxed in figure 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Amino acid p-distances are reported in table 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>A common feature of all ORFs amino acid sequences (with the exception of R. philippinarum MORF and V. ellipsiformis FORF) is their major p-distance value in respect to their own nucleotidic sequences: this indicates that non-synonymous mutations are more common than synonymous mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The variability of FORFs and MORFs was confirmed by the amino acid sequence difference analysis of all mtDNA-encoded protein genes (fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Our findings, together with previous studies (Breton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>2009, 2011a), showed that lineage-specific mitochondrial proteins are among the fastest evolving proteins coded by the mtDNA of the analyzed species. Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>4.—Functional domains in FORFs and MORFs (position in the amino acid sequence as identified by HHpred). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Sequences with similarities are boxed in the same color and with the same type of line; red: similarities among FORFs; blue: similarities among MORFs; orange: K = poly-K region; S = poly-S region (see also PSI-Coffee alignments, figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>2 and 3 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S2–S18</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Numbers indicate sequence length. Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>5.—Percentage of amino acid difference of novel proteins and of all mtDNA-encoded protein genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Amino acid divergence (% amino acid difference) was calcultated with MEGA5 for each mt protein coding gene among: (A) F mt genomes [for (i) Mytilus spp.; (ii) Mytilidae, i.e., Mytilus spp. and Musculista senhousia; (iii) Mytilidae + the venerid Ruditapes philippinarum; and (iv) Mytilidae + the venerid R. philippinarum + the unionoid Venustaconcha ellipsiformis], (B) M mt genomes [for (i) Mytilus spp.; (ii) Mytilidae, i.e., Mytilus spp. and M. senhousia; (iii) Mytilidae + the venerid R. philippinarum; and (iv) Mytilidae + the venerid R. philippinarum + the unionoid V. ellipsiformis], and (C) between F and M mt genomes [for (i) Mytilus spp.; (ii) R. philippinarum; and (iii) V. ellipsiformis]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>For the Mytilus edulis species complex (i.e., Myt. edulis, Myt. galloprovincialis, and Myt. trossulus), pairwise sequence difference was first calculated for each gene and the results were then exported to Microsoft Excel for calculations of means and SDs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>For both R. philippinarum and V. ellipsiformis only, one whole F mtDNA and one whole M mtDNA are present in database and no error can be calculated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Omitted comparisons are due to the impossibility to obtain a good alignment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Note: F mtDNA = female mitochondrial genome; M mtDNA = male mitochondrial genome. Mytilus spp. = Myt. edulis species complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Accession nos. mitochondrial genomes (F-type and M-type mtDNA, respectively): Myt. edulis NC_006161 and AY823623; Myt. galloprovincialis NC_006886 and AY363687; Myt. trossulus DQ198231 and DQ198225; M. senhousia GU001953 and GU001954; R. philippinarum AB065375.1 and AB065374.1; V. ellipsiformis FJ809753 and FJ809752. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>A SP was found in the N-terminus of all FORFs (table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Among the TM-helices, the N-terminal helix coincides with the SP sequence (table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Besides this helix, one more TM-helix supported by at least two programs was found in Mga-FORF, in Mtr-FORF, and in Rph-FORF (table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>A sound SP was not always found in MORFs, even if some softwares point to the same SP sequence with a low score (table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Also in this case, the N-terminal TM-helices coincide with the SP sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Other probable TM-helices detected by at least two of the softwares were found in Mse-ORF-B, Med-MORF, and in Rph-MORF (table 3). Table 3Signal Peptide and Transmembrane-Helix Prediction in the Novel Putative ProteinsSignal PeptideFORFMseMcaMedMgaMtrRphVelSoftware    Phobius1–20—1–20*1–20*1–18*1–18—    InterProScan1–201–31——1–181–181–44    PrediSi1–28—1–20*1–20*1–18*1–181–44*    SignalP 4.01–201–20*1–20*1–20*1–18*—1–44*MORFMseORFBMcaMedMgaMtrRphVelSoftware    Phobius—- (1–13)—1–34—1–18—    InterProScan1–5- (1–18)———1–181–40    PrediSi—- (1–16)*1–22*1–34*1–591–171–40    SignalP 4.01–6*- (1–14)1–21*1–34*1–59*1–181–40*Transmembrane HelicesFORFMseMcaMedMgaMtrRphVelSoftware    TMpred4–233–258–298–2931–521–18/40–5921–42    Phobius—————7–27/39–6221–42    InterProScan—————5–23/42–6221–41    Prodiv-TMHMM5–275–25/35–559–295–25/28–4826–473–23/39–5921–42    Rhythm6–234–23—18–3733–505–27/40–6221–42MORFMseORFBMcaMedMgaMtrRphVelSoftware    TMpred40–61- (-)69–96**19–3541–57**1–23/16–38/46–6421–39    Phobius—- (-)——38–5642–6220–38    InterProScan—- (-)—20–3838–565–27/41–6121–41    Prodiv-TMHMM41–61- (-)65–8621–4138–593–23/44–64—    Rhythm—- (-)—17–3441–5720–37/46–6421–38Note.—Signal peptide: Only signal peptides statistically supported (Phobius posterior label probability &gt; 0.5; PrediSi score &gt; 0.5; SignalP score &gt; D-cutoff 0.5; significance test not provided by InterProScan) or found at least by two softwares are shown; *Significance &lt; 0.5; (n) = Mca-MORF2 results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Transmembrane helices: Only transmembrane helices considered significant (TMpred score &gt; 500; Phobius posterior label probability &gt; 0.5; significance test not provided by the other softwares) or found by at least two softwares are shown; **TMpred score &lt; 500; values in bold indicate helices not overlapping with the predicted signal peptide; (n) = Mca-MORF2 results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Novel Mitochondrial ORFs: Function Prediction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Atome 2, I-Tasser, and HHpred found domains similar, in structure or ligands, to known proteins, in both FORFs (tables 4, 5 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S2–S8</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) and MORFs (tables 4, 5 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S9–S16</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>FORF highest probability hits include proteins involved in nucleic acid binding and transcription (e.g., helicase/hydrolase, transcription factors), in some cases with specific aspects of nucleic acid processing, like RNA modification (e.g., Med-FORF and Vel-FORF), and methylation (e.g., Mtr-FORF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Other hits are proteins with a membrane association, for example involved in transport across membrane, in cell adhesion, but also receptors, most of all involved in hormone signalling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Many proteins point to a role in immune response, for example in cytokine release for immune system activation (e.g., Mca-FORF). Table 4Function Analysis of Novel Mitochondrial ORFsMse-FORFMca-FORF Hormone receptor/Cell adhesion, migration, proliferation/Immune responseAtome2 (highest probability): Chemokine (13), highest score 75.17 Human tissue factor, score 70.69 Eotaxin (2), score 67.89 and 62.51 Erythrocyte binding antigen 175, score 54.15I-Tasser (confirmation): Cell division protein kinase 9/Protein Tat, Z-score 0.79 RhoGAP protein, Z-score 0.90Glypican-1, Z-score 0.62 Small-inducible cytokine A13, Z-score 0.91 Erythrocyte binding antigen 175, Z-score 0.63HHpred (confirmation): SARS receptor-binding domain-like, probability 54.78, aa 31–61 Small inducible cytokine A1 precursor, probability 27.01, aa 5–91Protein binding/transportI-Tasser (highest probability): Exportin-5, Z-score 0.75 Cullin-5, Z-score 0.69 Nucleoporin NUP170, Z-score 0.84 BRO1 protein, TM-score &gt; 0.5 GTP-binding nuclear protein Ran, TM-score &gt; 0.5Nucleic acid bindingI-Tasser (highest probability): Telomeric repeat-binding factor (2), TM-score &gt; 0.5 ATP-dependent RNA helicase (2), TM-score &gt; 0.5Membrane associationHHpred (highest probability): More than 40 hits, highest probability 75.84, aa 1–21Transcription factor translocatorHHpred (highest probability): Glucocorticoid receptor-like (10), highest probability 64.44, aa 68–85  Transport across membrane/Receptor/Immune responseAtome2 (highest probability): Unique short US2 glycoprotein, score 82.16 Killer cell immunoglobulin-like receptor 2DL1 (2), highest score 75.39 Pertussis toxin subunit 5, score 55.44 Putative ABC type-2 transporter, score 54.92I-Tasser (confirmation): Receptor-type adenylate cyclase (2), TM-score &gt; 0.5HHpred (confirmation): RAB6-interacting protein 2 (2), highest probability 62.09, aa 39–99 Integral membrane protein, probability 48.70, aa 10–38 TonB Periplasmic protein TonB, probability 45.44, aa 44–75 NIPSNAP, probability 35.39, aa 12–34 Membrane protein, probability 31.83, aa 54–66 Membrane or secreted protein, probability 30.95, aa 3–51 Transport protein Sec24A (2), probability 30.88, aa 3–51 Membrane protein containing DUF1112, probability 28.02, aa 14–66Cell adhesion and migration/Hormone receptorAtome2 (highest probability): Fibronectin, score 70.61 PfEMP1 variant 2 of strain MC, score 58.80 Human tissue factor (2), highest score 52.67Helicase activity/Replication/Immune responseI-Tasser (highest probability): Antiviral helicase SKI2, Z-score 0.68 Proliferating cell nuclear antigen PcnA, Z-score 0.85 Infectivity protein G3P, Z-score 0.62 Cyclophilin-like domain, Z-score 0.59HHpred (confirmation): SKI2/RNA helicase, probability 50.91, aa 101–123 Peptidyl-prolyl isomerase G/cyclophilin G, probability 38.59, aa 17–69Cytoskeleton/Cytokine release/Immune system activationHHpred (highest probability): Keratin (9 hits), highest probability 76.37, aa 25–95Transcription regulatorHHpred (highest probability): Sterol regulatory element binding protein (2), highest probability 71.01, aa 17–66 CG17964-PH, isoform H, probability 28.03, aa 54–122 Med-FORFMga-FORF DNA binding and replicationAtome2 (highest probability): Uncharacterized protein AF_1548, score 85.31 Exotoxin A, score 74.29 Minichromosome maintenance protein, score 63.74I-Tasser (highest probability): Minichromosome maintenance protein (3), highest Z-score 1.64, TM-score &gt; 0.5 ATPase involved in replication control (3), highest Z-score 1.31, TM-score &gt; 0.5 P97 (Cell division cycle), TM-score &gt; 0.5HHpred (confirmation): Zinc fingers (2), highest probability 35.41, aa 13–32 and 36–42Development/Growth hormone receptor/Cell adhesionAtome2: Nicotinamidase, score 59.05 Human tissue factor (2 hits), highest score 52.26 Fibronectin, score 51.93Lyase/Hydrolase activityHHpred (highest probability): Cyanase C-terminal domain (2), highest probability 54.52, aa 5–16Immune response/RNA binding and processingHHpred (highest probability): Cyclophilin/Peptidylprolyl isomerase (13), highest probability 46.01, aa 59–163Cell adhesion/Lipid metabolismHHpred (highest probability): GYF domain (2 hits), highest probability 39.73, aa 16–28 Malonyl-CoA decarboxylase (4), highest probability 36.39, aa 14–29  DNA binding and replicationAtome2 (highest probability): Uncharacterized protein AF_1548, score 82.33 Exotoxin A, score 72.53 Minichromosome maintenance protein, score 62.01I-Tasser (highest probability): Minichromosome maintenance protein (2), highest Z-score 1.64, TM-score &gt; 0.5 ATPase involved in replication control (3), highest Z-score 1.21, TM-score &gt; 0.5HHpred (confirmation): Zinc fingers (2), highest probability 36.31, aa 13–32, 36–42 NPH4/transcription factor, probability 30.20, aa 31–114Development/Growth hormone receptor/Cell adhesionAtome2: Human tissue factor, score 56.15 Fibronectin, score 52.65 Nicotinamidase, score 44.75 Tudor domain-containing protein 5 (Germ line integrity), score 43.50Lyase/Hydrolase activityHHpred (highest probability): Cyanase C-terminal domain (2), highest probability 55.41, aa 5–16Lipid metabolism/Cell adhesionHHpred (highest probability): Malonyl-CoA decarboxylase (6), highest probability 39.89, aa 14–29 GYF domain (3 hits), highest probability 39.13, aa 16–28 Mtr-FORFRph-FORF Ligase activityAtome2 (highest probability): d-alanine—poly(phosphoribitol) ligase subunit 1 (3), highest score 80.77Lipid metabolismAtome2 (highest probability): Acetyl-coenzyme A synthetase (3), highest score 79.06Receptor/Membrane-associated protein/Immune responseAtome2: Unique short US2 glycoprotein, score 65.52 Interleukin 18 binding protein/Cytokine, score 50.72I-Tasser (confirmation): Gramicidin synthetase 1, Z-score 2.25 d-alanine—poly(phosphoribitol) ligase subunit 1, Z-score 2.12Cytoskeleton-associated proteinI-Tasser (highest probability): Kinesin-like protein Nod, TM-score &gt; 0.5 Tubulin (3), TM-score &gt; 0.5 Integrin alpha-X, TM-score 0.498HHpred (confirmation): Actin-like ATPase domain (2), highest probability 45.12, aa 49–57Methylation (DNA, RNA, protein)HHpred (highest probability): More then 20 hits (21), highest probability 61.81, aa 5–149Immune response/Viral infection cofactor (large region) Cyclophilin, probability 26.70, aa 15–110  Nuclear transportAtome2 (highest probability): Nuclear transport factor 2 (2), highest score 85.83 NTF2-related export protein 1, score 79.17I-Tasser (highest probability): Nuclear transport factor 2 (3), highest Z-score 0.72, TM-score &gt; 0.5 p15 (Export of mRNAs through nuclear pore complexes) (2), TM-score &gt; 0.5 Nuclear RNA export factor 2, TM-score &gt; 0.5 mRNA transport regulator Mtr2, TM-score &gt; 0.5 Rasputin (Similar to nuclear transport factor 2), TM-score &gt; 0.5HHpred (confirmation): DNA double-strand break repair transporter domain, probability 49.97, aa 77–88DNA replication/Transcription/Nucleic-acid bindingHHpred (highest probability): 20 hits Highest probability 86.90, with HemY family protein, aa 3–67 Zinc fingers, probability 86.88Atome2 (confirmation): Polymerase PB2, score 56.13 Restriction endonuclease Hpy99I, score 52.92 Cyclin (3), highest score 52.40 DNA gyrase inhibitor YacG, score 50.57Transport across membrane/Amino-acid transporterHHpred: About 30 hits, highest probability 86.47, aa 2–75Receptor siteHHpred: Neurotoxin type G, probability 63.95, aa 77–120Membrane-associated protein/Immune responseHHpred: Macoilin/transmembrane protein 57 (2), probability 50.56, aa 1–113 LysM domain, probability 33.34, aa 115–123Atome2 (confirmation): HLA class II histocompatibility antigen, score 47.74 Vel-FORF Nuclear proteins/Nuclear transport/RNA processingAtome2 (highest probability): Poly(A) polymerase, score 84.27 Ran GTPase-activating protein 1, score 60.97 Chimera of Histone H2B.1 and Histone H2A.Z, score 49.66I-Tasser (confirmation): VP1/mRNA-capping machine (2), highest Z-score 0.82 Poly(A) polymerase (2), highest Z-score 0.70 ATP-dependent DNA helicase RecG-related protein, Z-score 0.71DNA binding/TranscriptionAtome2 (highest probability): Bifunctional protein GlmU, score 58.95 Serine/threonine-protein phosphatase (2), highest score 58.24 SAGA-associated factor 73, 21.79HHpred (highest probability): ComGC (2), highest probability 94.43, aa 2–38 CG13581-PA transcription factor, probability 39.77, aa 77–89Membrane-associated proteinsAtome2 (highest probability): Bactericidal permeability-increasing protein, score 53.65 Photosystem II reaction center protein I, score 31.82HHpred (confirmation): More than 10 hits in the N-terminus of the sequenceHormone receptor/TranscriptionI-Tasser (highest probability): Progesterone receptor ligand-binding domain, TM-score &gt; 0.5 Androgen receptor ligand-binding domain, TM-score &gt; 0.5 AncCR, TM-score &gt; 0.5 Mineralocorticoid receptor (nuclear receptor), TM-score &gt; 0.5Immune system/Transport across membraneHHpred: C-type LECtin family member (clec-35) (7), highest probability 78.84, aa 19–86 Mca-MORF1Mca-MORF2 Transposition regulation/DNA binding and integration/TranscriptionAtome2 (highest probability): Transposase (3), highest score 76.46 Protein RDM1/RNA-directed DNA methylation, score 65.30 Modification methylase TaqI, score 55.99 Nuclear factor NF-kappa-B p100 subunit, score 55.42 Replication termination protein, score 54.13 DNA-binding protein RAP1, score 50.90I-Tasser (confirmation): C25G10.02, chromosome I (Hydrolase/DNA duplexes separation), Z-scores &gt; 1 Rad50 (Hydrolase/DNA-double strand break repair), Z-scores &gt; 1 Replication factor c small subunit, TM-scores &gt; 0.5 O-sialoglycoprotein endopeptidase/protein kinase (Hydrolase), TM-scores &gt; 0.5HHpred (highest probability): “Winged helix” DNA-binding domain (2), highest probability 88.51, aa 7–25 C2H2 and C2HC zinc fingers (3), highest probability 80.42, aa 16–32 Transcription factor E2F-4, winged-helix (2), highest probability 60.60, aa 7–16Hormone signalingI-Tasser (highest probability): Parathyroid hormone (4), Z-score &gt; 1HHpred (confirmation): Kazal-type inhibitors/growth factor receptor (9), highest probability 68.60, aa 13–20ApoptosisI-Tasser (highest probability): Apoptosis regulator BCL-2 (4), TM-scores &gt; 0.5 Apoptosis regulator BAK, TM-score &gt; 0.5Signaling/Regulation of cytoskeleton formation/Cell proliferationHHpred (highest probability): GTPase-activator protein (47), highest probability 87.22UbiquitinationHHpred (highest probability): UBA-like (4), highest probability 72.94, aa 1–15Membrane associationHHpred (highest probability): Tim10-like/Mitochondrial translocase (2), highest probability 68.38, aa 19–28Atome2, confirmation: Photosystem I reaction center subunit IX, score 43.87  Protein foldingAtome2 (highest probability): Huwentoxin-II, score 79.45 Alanine racemes, score 76.95 Heat shock 70 kDa protein 8/Chaperone (2), highest score 55.37 BAG-family molecular chaperone regulator-1, score 47.88Cytokine/Immune response/Cell proliferation/Embryonic developmentAtome2 (highest probability): Interleukin-6 receptor subunit beta, score 71.60 Interleukin-1 beta, score 40.82 Erythropoietin receptor, score 54.98 Tumor necrosis factor ligand superfamily member 13, score 50.90 Natural killer cell activating receptor, score 46.35 Myeloid antimicrobial peptide 27, score 41.93 Tumor necrosis factor receptor associated protein 2, score 41.37 T-cell immunoglobulin and mucin domain-containing protein 4, score 39.37I-Tasser (confirmation): Tumor protein P73 (cell cycle control), Z-score &gt; 1Membrane associationAtome2 (highest probability): Rieske protein, score 71.25 NADH-cytochrome b5 reductase 3, score 70.00 ATP synthase subunit alpha, score 39.91DNA replication, recombination, and repairHHpred (highest probability): Methylated DNA-protein cysteine methyltransferase (24), highest probability 80.02, aa 13–19I-Tasser (confirmation): DNA topoisomerase I, TM-score &gt; 0.5Receptor/Signaling (Immune response)HHpred (highest probability): XII secretory phospholipase A2 precursor, probability 76.62, aa 18–24 Toxin_33/Waglerin family (acetylcholine receptor), probability 70.71, aa 11–20 Immunoglobulin domain (12), highest probability 62.63, aa 5–21 Tumor necrosis factor receptor superfamily member 17 (2), highest probability 60.38, aa 16–25 Med-MORFMga-MORF Membrane associationAtome2 (highest probability): Alcohol dehydrogenase 4/Oxidoreductase, score 77.67I-Tasser (highest probability): AP-2 complex subunit beta-2, Z-score 0.64UbiquitinationAtome2 (highest probability): UPF0147 protein Ta0600/Ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme E2, 72.27Cytokine/Receptor/Immune responseI-Tasser (highest probability): Complement C5A anaphylatoxin, Z-score 0.61 Glutathione S-transferase omega-2, Z-score 0.58 Discoidin domain receptor 2, Z-score 0.74 Receptor protein-tyrosine kinase erbB-3, Z-score 0.55 Interleukin-13, Z-score 0.63 Coagulogen, Z-score 0.56Atome2 (confirmation): Interleukin-12 subunit alpha, score 51.43 Tumor necrosis factor alpha-induced protein 3, score 44.65HHpred (highest probability): Glutathione transferase domain/Thioredoxin (3), highest probability 67.32, aa 33–49 CG33975-PA/Glucocorticoid induced gene 1, probability 64.83, aa 20–51 Nuclear Hormone Receptor family, probability 61.43, aa 28–69TranscriptionHHpred (highest probability): Zinc finger protein 395 and 704, highest probability 57.58, aa 43–51 SLC2A4 regulator, 52.80, aa 43–51Glycoprotein/Membrane association/Cell–cell connectionHHpred: Protocadherin (13), highest probability 59.36, aa 53–61 (poli-K region, aa 55–62)  Cytoskeleton dynamics/Cell proliferation and differentiation/Hormone signalingAtome2 (highest probability): FGFR1 oncogene partner, score 88.04 HIV-1 envelope protein chimera/Chemokine receptor, score 59.63 Filamin-binding LIM protein 1, score 55.61 Sprouty-related, EVH1 domain-containing protein 1, score 34.00 Vasodilator-stimulated phosphoprotein, score 30.93 Protein enabled homolog, score 26.03 Proliferation-associated protein 2G4, score 25.29I-Tasser (confirmation): Gamma filamin (2), highest Z-score 0.72HHpred (highest probability): Actin, probability 87.91, aa 1–16 EPS8/epidermal growth factor receptor kinase substrate 8-like protein 1, probability 71.11, aa 4–15Immune responseI-Tasser (highest probability): Glutathione S-transferase (5 hits), TM-scores &gt; 0.5Transcription factor/Nucleic-acid binding/Differentiation and developmentHHpred (highest probability): Helix-loop-helix (bHLH) protein, Human Nulp1 (2), highest probability 87.71, aa 3–16 PEP-CTERM putative exosortase interaction domain, probability 59.70, aa 1–10 Sp1 transcription factor, probability 57.36, aa 5–61 Josephin domain containing 3, probability 50.13, aa 6–15 Kruppel-like factor (Growth-factor pathways), probability 48.23, aa 54–61Signal transduction/Cell proliferationHHpred: Smoothened homolog (2), highest probability 81.43, aa 4–21Membrane-associated protein/Hormone receptorHHpred: Extracellular solute-binding protein (2), highest probability 74.34, aa 5–60 EEV glycoprotein, probability 69.62, aa 7–36 Lipoprotein, probability 56.70, aa 5–39 FIG1, Factor-induced gene 1 protein (Mating/Pheromone-regulated membrane protein) (2), highest probability 51.63, aa 28–47Glycoprotein/Membrane association/Cell–cell connectionHHpred: Protocadherin (26), highest probability 75.96, aa 7–14 (poli-K region, aa 7–15) Mtr-MORFRph-MORF Growth hormone receptor/Cell adhesion, migration, proliferation during embryonic developmentAtome2 (highest probability): Human tissue factor (2), highest score 90.71 Skeletal dihydropyridine receptor, score 61.37 Angiostatin, score 47.55 Fibronectin, score 46.00Membrane-binding proteinsAtome2 (highest probability): Complexin (2), highest score 52.74HHpred (confirmation): N-acetylglucosaminyl-phosphatidylinositol de-n-acetylase, probability 76.89, aa 9–38 Membrane protein, probability 75.99, aa 26–47Cell growth and differentiation/signalingI-Tasser (highest probability): T-lymphoma invasion and metastasis-inducing protein 2, Z-score 0.75 C3, Z-score 0.64 KEX1(DELTA)P, Prohormone-processing serine carboxypeptidase, Z-score 0.74Cell differentiationHHpred: Gametogenetin binding protein 2, probability 71.72, aa 3–40Microtubule associationHHpred: Kinectin 1 microtubule-dependent transport, probability 68.69, aa 26–63Nucleic-acid binding/Transcription factor/DNA repair ATPaseHHpred (highest probability): Helix-loop-helix (bHLH) protein; Human Nulp1 (2), highest probability 95.13, aa 23–37 Telomeric telomer cycle, DNA-binding, protein binding, probability 68.11, aa 51–64 PHD FINGER domain, probability 62.04, aa 25–63 DNA double-strand break repair ATPase Rad50, probability 61.51, aa 42–70SignalingHHpred: Cysteine alpha-hairpin motif, probability 65.87, aa 70–77Glycoprotein/Membrane association/Cell–cell connectionHHpred: Protocadherin, highest probability 74.29, aa 25–37 (poli-K region, aa 25–37)  Ubiquitination factorsAtome2 (highest probability): 26S proteasome regulatory subunit rpn10, score 78.22HHpred (confirmation): Zinc ion binding, ubiquitin interaction motif-containing protein (2), highest probability 59.68, aa 72–95 NEDD8 ultimate buster-1/Ubiquitin-like protein, probability 41.84, aa 73–96Membrane associationAtome2 (highest probability): L-aspartate dehydrogenase/Oxidoreductase, score 71.39 Transient receptor potential cation channel subfamily V member 1, score 59.26 Unique short US2 glycoprotein, score 34.59TranscriptionI-Tasser (highest probability): Archaeal transcriptional regulator TrmB, Z-score 1.04Atome2 (confirmation): Tumor suppressor p53-binding protein 1, score 57.01HHpred (confirmation): Restricted Tev Movement 2 (hormone receptor), probability 41.60, aa 61–94 Forkhead-associated phosphopeptide binding domain 1 isoform 19, probability 31.88, aa 68–101 Exonuclease, probability 30.93, aa 69–99Immune resistanceHHpred (highest probability): CRISPR-associated DEAD/DEAH-box helicase Csf4, probability 71.11, aa 144–165Cytoskeleton organization/Cell proliferation, migration, differentiation/Immune responseHHpred (highest probability): Structural maintenance of chromosomes (3), highest probability 63.66, aa 65–140 Translation proteins SH3-like domain, 58.57, aa 61–75 RAD50 (4), highest probability 35.41, aa 163–172 Subunit of MRX complex with Mre11p and Xrs2p, probability 29.87, aa 163–172 Gelsolin (6), highest probability 46.96, aa 40–146 Villin (6), highest probability 36.65, aa 40–146 C15A11.5/Collagen family member, probability 42.97, aa 1–41 CG14217-PB, isoform B (Serine threonine kinase), probability 42.82, aa 69–91 Mitochondrial tumor suppressor 1 isoform 5, probability 38.92, aa 65–101 EGF/Laminin, probability 32.22, aa 64–99 Keratin (2), highest probability 30.68, aa 63–109 Segment polarity protein Dishevelled (Development), probability 29.40, aa 66–94 CG12047-PC, isoform C (Centrosome/spindle organization), probability 28.75, aa 65–78Atome2 (confirmation): Thymosin beta-4, score 36.83 Adseverin, score 36.03 I-Tasser (confirmation): Proliferating cellular nuclear antigen 1, Z-score 1.03 Guanine nucleotide-binding protein G(q) subunit alpha, Z-score 0.61 Chimera of Gelsolin domain 1 and C-Terminal domain of thymosin Beta-4, Z-score 0.74 Vel-MORFMse-ORF-B Protein foldingAtome2 (highest probability): Chaperone protein ClpB (2), highest score 89.09Actin cytoskeleton and cell polarity regulator/Cell differentiation and adhesion/Cell cycleAtome2 (highest probability): Myosin-7 (2), highest score 82.66 Rho-associated protein kinase 1, score 65.91 Tropomyosin alpha-1 chain, score 53.16 DNA topoisomerase 4 subunit A, score 53.11 Cell division protein ZapB, score 52.81I-Tasser (highest probability): ATP-dependent helicase/nuclease subunit A, Z-score 1.19 YIIU, Z-score 0.61 Spectrin (4), highest Z-scores 1.19 Myosin-5A, Z-score 1.19 Cdc42-interacting protein 4, Z-score 0.63 Desmoplakin, TM-score 0.47HHpred (confirmation): Keratin (6) (cytokine release/immune system), highest probability 94.31, aa 81–171 Laminin (5) (cytokine release/immune system), highest probability 93.43, aa 41–218Membrane protein/ Receptor/Immune responseAtome2 (highest hits): C-Jun-amino-terminal kinase-interacting protein 4 Isoform 4 (Sperm surface protein), score 73.95HHpred (highest probability): More than 20 hits of antigens, all probabilities higher than 90, aa 12–218 Nuclear pore complex proteins, 15 hits, all probabilities higher than 90, aa 41–220I-Tasser (confirmation): Sensor protein (3), TM-scores &gt; 0.5 Methyl-accepting chemotaxis transducer (MCPs), TM-score &gt; 0.5 Invasin IPAD, TM-score &gt; 0.5 Cell invasion protein SIPD, TM-score &gt; 0.5 Pathogenicity island 1 effector protein, TM-score &gt; 0.5 Translocator protein bid, TM-score &gt; 0.5 Toll-like receptor 5b and variable lymphocyte receptor B.61 chimeric protein, TM-score &gt; 0.5Transcription factor/Nucleic-acid binding and transportHHpred: Basic leucine zipper (bZIP) transcription factor (2), highest probability 92.14, aa 44–171 Nucleotide binding, probability 91.76, aa 90–213 mRNA localization machinery, probability 90.81, aa 50–171  Cytoskeleton organization/Cell adhesion, migration, proliferation/Immune responseAtome2 (highest probability): Myomesin-1, score 90.17 Fibronectin, score 66.05 Fibrinogen-binding protein, score 32.61Hormone receptorAtome2 (highest probability): Human tissue factor (hormone signaling/cell adhesion) (2), highest score 82.66HHpred (confirmation): F11G11.10/Collagen family member, probability 41.10, aa 36–69 Alpha-actinin, probability 38.91, aa 70–85 TyrPK_CSF1-R (Cytokine/Immune response), probability 31.97, aa 95–102 Fibrinogen-binding protein/cell adhesion complex (3), highest probability 30.60, aa 82–93 PDGF Platelet-derived and vascular endothelial growth factors, probability 21.10, aa 13–28Membrane associationAtome2 (highest probability): Unique short US2 glycoprotein, score 77.87I-Tasser (highest probability): mRNA export factor Mex67 (Associated to nuclear pores), Z-score 0.90SignalingI-Tasser (highest probability): Sensor protein (3 hits), TM-scores &gt; 0.5Nucleic acid binding/Immune responseHHpred (highest probability): Recombination-activating protein 2 (2), highest probability 79.31, aa 9–33 Nucleic acid-binding proteins (4), highest probability 74.26, aa 94–105I-Tasser (confirmation): Transcription intermediary factor 1-alpha, Z-score 0.66 DNA polymerase sliding clamp C, Z-score 0.66 Peu-ORFPno-ORF314 Cell differentiation during embryogenesis/Hormone receptorAtome2 (highest probability): Cytoplasmic FMR1-interacting protein 1, score 61.36 Tumor necrosis factor alpha/Cytokine, score 54.49 Atrial natriuretic peptide receptor A, score 52.42 Mesoderm development candidate 2, score 44.10I-Tasser (confirmation): Mesoderm development candidate 2, Z-score 0.73 Cytoplasmic FMR1-interacting protein 1, Z-score 0.92HHpred (confirmation): FnI-like domain (Cell adhesion/migration during embryonic development) (4), highest probability 62.25, aa 52–64 Jun-like transcription factor/Mitogen-activated protein kinases (Cellular responses to cytokines/Cell proliferation/differentiation), probability 50.47, 2–26 Resistin/Cytokine (2), highest probability 46.20, aa 49–63DNA replicationI-Tasser (highest probability): Proliferating cell nuclear antigen, Z-score 0.81 DNA polymerase processivity factor, Z-score 0.69 Poly [ADP-ribose] polymerase 15, Z-score 0.63 Flap structure-specific endonuclease (DNA repair/replication), Z-score 0.70HHpred (confirmation): Proliferating cell nuclear antigen, probability 42.24, aa 6–22Immune resistanceHHpred (highest probability): CRISPR-associated DxTHG motif protein, probability 75.05, aa 4–17Nucleic-acid binding/Transcriptional regulatorHHpred (highest probability): More than 40 hits, highest probability 60.91, aa 34–66  Nucleic-acid binding and transcriptionAtome2 (highest probability): Small protein B, score 82.73 ATP-dependent RNA helicase SUPV3L1, mitochondrial, score 69.03 DNA topoisomerase 4 subunit A, score 50.41I-Tasser (highest probability): Anti-sigma F factor (Prokaryote gene expression regulation) (6), highest Z-score 0.68 Transcriptional regulator LRPA (2), highest Z-score 0.64 Conserved domain protein/Transcriptional regulator, score 0.57 Bromodomain and PHD finger-containing protein 3; SPOIIAA, score 0.69HHpred: Histone-fold (2), highest probability 58.93, aa 62–77 CCAAT-BOX DNA binding protein subunit B, probability 50.87, aa 64–77Cell differentiation during embryogenesisAtome2 (highest probability): Mesoderm development candidate 2, score 79.76Membrane associationI-Tasser (highest probability): Sulfate transporter, TM-score 0.608Viral proteinHHpred (highest probability): 8 hits, highest probability 82.37, aa 3–59 I-Tasser (highest probability): Capsid protein P27 (2), highest Z-score 0.92Protein foldingHHpred (highest probability): LDLR chaperone BOCA, probability 77.86, aa 2–52Immune responseHHpred: Immunoglobulin domain, probability 45.90, aa 79–103 Note.—Hits with the highest probability are reported for each of the three programs together with eventual confirmation of the same biological process from the other two softwares. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Norm. Z-score &gt; 1 = good alignment; TM-score &gt; 0.5 = similar fold with query (Zhang 2008; Xu and Zhang 2010); (n) = number of the same hit (protein), when more than one. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>See also <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S2–S16</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online. Table 5Hits to Viral Proteins Found in Novel Mitochondrial ORFsDUI sp.HitsPositionFORF MseProtein Tat [Atome2; score 54.94] (Nuclear transcriptional activator of viral gene expression/Cell division)n.a.Protein Tat [I-Tasser; norm. Z-score 0.79]n.a.Protein Tat [HHpred; probability 25.94]62–73SARS receptor-binding domain-like [HHpred; 54.78]31–61Hepatitis E virus ORF-2 (Capsid protein/Pro-apoptotic gene expression activation/Host–cell cytoplasm) [HHpred; 23.74]61–69Fijivirus P9-2 protein (Unknown function) [HHpred; probability 23.19]8–50 McaUnique short US2 glycoprotein (Viral protein/Transport across membrane/Immune recognition masking) [Atome2; score 82.16]n.a.Pre-neck appendage protein (Bacteriophage) (5 hits) [Atome2; score 57.87–51.81]n.a.Antiviral helicase SKI2 [I-Tasser; norm. Z-score 0.68]n.a.Infectivity protein G3P (Viral protein) [I-Tasser; norm. Z-score 0.62]n.a.Cyclophilin-like domain (Viral infection cofactor/RNA and protein processing) [I-Tasser; norm. Z-score 0.59]n.a.Phage small terminase subunit (DNA binding/Endonuclease activity/Viral capsid assembly) [HHpred; probability 44.52]8–45 MedRetrovirus capsid dimerization domain-like (2) [HHpred; probability 35.34, 29.28]14–43 MgaRetrovirus capsid dimerization domain-like (2) [HHpred; probability 35.47, 30.09]14–43 MtrUnique short US2 glycoprotein (Viral protein/Transport across membrane/Immune recognition masking) [Atome2; score 65.52]n.a.Positive stranded ssRNA viruses [HHpred; probability 28.66]16–54 RphPolymerase PB2 (Polymerase; Viral RNA replication) [Atome2; score 56.13]n.a. VelVP1, the protein that forms the mRNA-capping machine (Viral protein) (2) [I-Tasser; norm. Z-score 0.82, 0.70]n.a.Fibritin (Viral protein) [I-Tasser; norm. Z-score 0.64]n.a.MORF McaORF1Early 35 kDa protein (Apoptosis-preventing protein/Protease inhibitor/Response to the viral infection) [Atome2; score 47.39]n.a.Phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase regulatory subunit alpha (Host–virus interaction/Signaling/Transferase) [Atome2; score 44.26]n.a.V-bcl-2 (Viral protein/Apoptosis) [I-Tasser; TM-score &gt; 0.5]n.a. McaORF2Circulin A (Cyclic peptide/Virus cytopathic effects and replication inhibitor) [I-Tasser; norm. Z-score &gt; 1]n.a.First immunoglobulin (Ig) domain of nectin-3 (Poliovirus receptor related protein 3/Cell adhesion) [HHpred; probability 62.63]12–21Coxsackie virus and adenovirus receptor (Glycoprotein A33; CTX-related type I transmembrane protein) [HHpred; probability 51.10]5–21Coxsackie virus and adenovirus receptor (Car), domain 1 [Homo sapiens, TaxId: 9606] [HHpred; probability 49.70]12–21Hepatitis A virus cellular receptor 1 [Mus musculus] [HHpred; probability 45.53]12–25 MedReplicase polyprotein 1ab (Viral protein/RNA, DNA duplex-unwinding activities/ATPase/Deubiquitination) [Atome2; score 58.58]n.a.Macro domain of Non-structural protein 3 (Viral protein/RNA binding protein) [I-Tasser; norm. Z-score 0.70]n.a. MgaHIV-1 envelope protein chimera (Viral envelope glycoprotein/Chemokine receptor) [Atome2; score 59.63]n.a.Proliferation-associated protein 2G4 (Viral Translation/Growth regulation/Androgen receptor/Transcriptional regulation) [Atome2; score 25.29]n.a.Viral protein [I-Tasser; norm. Z-score 0.72]n.a. Mtr—— RphUnique short US2 glycoprotein (Viral protein/Transport across membrane/Immune recognition masking) [Atome2; score 34.59]n.a.Viral protein/Signaling protein [I-Tasser; norm. Z-score 0.57]n.a.CRISPR-associated DEAD/DEAH-box helicase Csf4 (Phage genomic sequence insertion/Resistance against mobile genetic elements: viruses, transposable elements, conjugative plasmids) [HHpred; probability 71.11]144–165d.172.1 gp120 core (56502) SCOP seed sequence: d1g9mg_ (Viral envelope receptor) [HHpred; probability 34.78]125–157 Vel—— MseORFBUnique short US2 glycoprotein (Viral protein/Transport across membrane/Immune recognition masking) [Atome2; score 77.87]n.a.Gag-Pol polyprotein (Capsid protein/Host nucleus) [Atome2; score 54.53]n.a.Glycosyltransferase (Mannosyltransferase) (Capsid viral protein/Transferase) [I-Tasser; norm. Z-score 0.90]n.a.VAC_I5L (dsDNA viruses, no RNA stage; Poxviridae) (Membrane-associated protein) [HHpred; probability 31.24]6–24Other sp. PeuTerminase small subunit (Viral protein) [Atome2; score 56.08]n.a.CAG38821 (Viral protein) [I-Tasser; norm. Z-score 0.77]n.a.Terminase small subunit (Viral protein) [I-Tasser; norm. Z-score 0.84]n.a.DNA polymerase processivity factor (DNA binding/Transferase/Viral protein) [I-Tasser; norm. Z-score 0.69]n.a.CRISPR-associated DxTHG motif protein (Phage genomic sequence insertion/Resistance against mobile genetic elements: viruses, transposable elements, conjugative plasmids) [HHpred; probability 75.05]4–17 Pno-ORF314Capsid protein P27 (Viral protein) (2) [I-Tasser; norm. Z-score 0.92, 0.86]n.a.Retrovirus capsid protein, N-terminal core domain (Viral replication) [HHpred; probability 82.37]21–50RSV capsid protein {Rous sarcoma virus [TaxId: 11886]} [HHpred; probability 80.17]21–59JSRV capsid, capsid protein P27; zinc-finger, metal-binding {Jaagsiekte sheep retrovirus} (Viral protein) [HHpred; probability 78.55]21–59Capsid protein P27; retrovirus, N-terminal core domain {Mason-pfizer monkey virus} (Viral protein) [HHpred; probability 74.21]21–59GAG polyprotein capsid protein P27; retrovirus, immature GAG{Rous sarcoma virus} (Viral protein) [HHpred; probability 48.94]21–50Capsid protein P27; viral protein, retrovirus, GAG; 7.00 A {Mason-pfizer monkey virus} [HHpred; probability 44.98]22–59Capsid protein; two independent domains helical bundles, virus/viral protein {Rous sarcoma virus} [HHpred; probability 43.53]21–47Tat binding protein 1 (TBP-1)-interacting protein (TBPIP) (Eukaryotic protein/Modulates the inhibitory action of human TBP-1 on HIV-Tat-mediated transactivation) [HHpred; probability 38.93]3–50Note.—Norm. Z-score &gt; 1 = good alignment; TM-score &gt; 0.5 = similar fold with query (Zhang 2008; Xu and Zhang 2010); (n) = number of the same hit (protein); position: amino acid position in the query sequence; n.a. = non applicable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>MORF hits with the highest probability include membrane-associated proteins with a role in nucleic acid binding and transcription, mainly related to signalling for cell differentiation and development (e.g., embryonic development). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Some ORFs appear to be involved in DNA recombination and repair, in transposition regulation, and DNA integration of foreign elements (e.g., Mca-MORF1 and Rph-MORF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Moreover, several hits are proteins that regulate cytoskeleton formation and dynamics, from cell polarity regulation to cell proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Other hits point to a role in ubiquitination and apoptosis with high probability (e.g., Mca-MORF1, Med-MORF, and Rph-MORF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Finally, many of the proteins have a role in immune response, for example in cytokine release (e.g., Mca-MORF2 and Med-MORF). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>We found similar hits in Peu-ORF and Pno-ORF314 (tables 4 and 5 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S17</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S18</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), connected with nucleic acid binding and transcription, with membrane association (Pno-ORF314), with signalling for cell differentiation during embryogenesis, with foreign elements (mobile genetic element and viral proteins), and with immune response regulation (Pno-ORF314). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>All the hits come from different animal and plant proteins, from both unicellular and pluricellular organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The position of the most represented functional domains is reported in figure 5 (see also table 1 for acronyms). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>On the whole, with the only exception of Mtr-MORF and Vel-MORF, every analyzed protein showed hits referred to viral proteins (table 5 and fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>In some cases (Mse-FORF, Mca-FORF, Mse-ORF-B, and Rph-MORF) the similarity with viral proteins was confirmed by all the three softwares used, in other cases (Mtr-FORF, Mca-MORF, Med-MORF, and Mga-MORF) by two of the softwares, and for the remaining proteins (Med-FORF, Mga-FORF, Rph-FORF, and Vel-FORF) by one program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the same first four hits found by HHpred are present in all the novel putative proteins analyzed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary table S19</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), except for Amo-PolB, which showed complete homology with base-excision repair DNA polymerases, mainly polymerase beta (HHpred probability: 100.0), and Ico-mtMutS, which showed a complete homology with a DNA mismatch repair protein (HHpred probability: 100.0), in both cases with hits from many organisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Novel ORFs Characterization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>As mentioned, mt genomes of bivalve species with DUI have novel lineage-specific ORFs of unknown origin and function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Generally, homologous proteins, or their fragments, have similar structure because structures diverge much more slowly than their sequences (Chothia and Lesk 1986). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Depending on the degree of divergence between them, homologous proteins may also maintain similar cellular function, ligands, protein interactions partners, or enzymatic mechanisms (Todd et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Because bivalve novel ORFs do not have known homologous (i.e., they are ORFans; Fischer and Eisenberg 1999), we performed multiple analyses of their structure, in order to infer the function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>These ORFs are found in extra-genic regions, often inside the LUR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Except for M. senhousia ORF-B, that is found in both mt genomes (in the middle of LUR Subunit B), the other analyzed ORFs are lineage-specific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>ORF-B nucleotide sequence is extremely conserved between the two mt genomes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), but considering that in some M. senhousia females the complete ORF-B is absent, ORF-B might not be functional in females. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Lineage-specific mitochondrial ORFs were found in all the analyzed DUI species (table 1; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary material S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>In Mytilus male genomes, the last part of the mORFs, after the poly-A region, is the most conserved (fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>A number of mORFs found in sequences annotated as Myt. galloprovincialis are identical to Myt. edulis mORF, and probably derive from hybridization that is extremely common inside the Myt. edulis complex: these “edulis-like” mORFs are more conserved than Myt. galloprovincialis own mORF and fORF, but are more diverse than Myt. edulis own mORF, from which they seem to derive (table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, Myt. edulis complex mORFs could be the same element, considering the extreme conservation of most of their sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Instead, M. californianus has two largely overlapping putative mORFs that do not contain a poly-A sequence like the other three species and are completely diverse from them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>This is not surprising given the high divergence between Myt. edulis complex and M. californianus mitochondrial genomes (Zouros 2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Putative TM-helices were not found in all the analyzed proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>In some cases the same region was identified as SP (table 3): being SP a peptide chain of hydrophobic amino acids, it can be difficult for softwares to discern it from a TM-helix (Käll et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>A clue in favour of a membrane association of MORFs comes from the poly-lysine (Med-, Mga-, and Mtr-MORF) and poly-serine (Rph-MORF) regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Poly-lysine motif is required for membrane lipid binding (Bouaouina et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>2012), and poly-serine domains characterize proteins anchored to bacterial outer membrane (Howard et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Being mitochondria derived from alpha-proteobacteria (Andersson et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>1998), we can hypothesize a similar membrane association in these organelles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the first four hits found with HHpred are the same for both FORFs and MORFs of DUI bivalves (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary table S19</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), and for Peu-ORF and Pno-ORF314. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Two of these hits are involved in the anchor to cell membrane/surface (LPXTG-motif cell wall anchor domain and outer membrane insertion C-terminal signal); the other two are typical of proteins involved in transcription (X-X-X-Leu-X-X-Gly heptad repeats) and in post-transcriptional processes (pentatricopeptide repeats, PPR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>The detected motifs are not long enough to claim a functional homology, but their involvement in membrane binding and in transcription is sustained also by other hits (see tables 4 and 5; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S2–S16</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The existence of Vel-FORF and MORF was shown by western blot analysis (Breton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>2009), and Vel-FORF was shown to be present in mitochondria and in the nuclear membrane (Breton et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>2011a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Likely, these novel mitochondrial proteins have a role in different cellular compartments, thus including domains that allow them to interact with several substrates such as membranes, cytoskeleton, and nucleic acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>It is important to investigate the existence of ORF translation products in other DUI species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>We are performing these kind of analyses and first data confirm the existence of Rph-MORF protein (Milani et al. in preparation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, increasing the number of analyzed DUI species and sequences may help in explaining the evolutionary dynamics that led to the highest similarity found between FORF and MORF of some species (i.e., Rph-FORF/-MORF and Vel-FORF/-MORF) in comparison to other species (i.e., Myt. edulis complex) (see alignments and fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The similarity region between an ORF and a known protein sometimes includes a large part of the protein, even with high probability (see for example Vel-MORF), in other cases, as said before, it is found in short amino acid sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>In such cases we are confident we retrieved sound similarities, because the same homolog proteins from very distant taxa, from both unicellular and pluricellular organisms, are present among the hits (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S2–S16</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Overall, the analyzed ORFs show many common functions (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S2–S16</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), but, when we consider only hits with the highest scores, FORFs are more similar among each other than with MORFs, and vice-versa (tables 4 and 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>FORFs appear to be involved in transcription regulation and in immune response, also linked to cell adhesion, migration, and proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>MORFs appear to have a main role in cytoskeleton organization (cell differentiation during embryonic development), but also capable, as FORFs, of nucleic acid binding and transcription regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>FORFs and MORFs appear to share a role as signalling molecules, more specifically involved in hormone signalling and immune response regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, some MORFs show similarity with DNA replication, recombination, and repair proteins (see for example the transposition regulation and DNA binding-integration hits of Mca-MORF1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Moreover, hits of ubiquitination and apoptosis regulation proteins are found in almost all ORFs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S2–S16</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="252" pm="?"><plain>Are Novel Mitochondrial ORFans of Viral Origin? </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>The sequences analyzed in this article do not show homologies with any known mitochondrial protein, therefore they unlikely originated from recent duplication events, as instead happened for nad2 in Crassostrea (Wu et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>2012), for cox2 in R. philippinarum F-mtDNA (Okazaki M and Ueshima R, unpublished data), and in M. senhousia M-mtDNA (Passamonti et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Another origin should be taken into account for these proteins and the observed hits to viral proteins provide a possible working hypothesis: bivalve ORFs could have arisen from different events of insertion, thus showing a narrow distribution similar to other ORFans (Yu and Stoltzfus 2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>The analyzed ORFs show a higher amino acid substitution rate than the typical mitochondrial coding genes (fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Lineage-specific genes evolve at a faster rate than broadly distributed genes, in both bacteria and eukaryotes (Daubin and Ochman 2004a, 2004b; Yu and Stoltzfus 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>One reason could be that lineage-specific genes participate more in lineage-specific adaptation, therefore evolving faster (Cai and Petrov 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the lineage-specific novel mtORFs may experience such a kind of evolutionary pressure, maybe for features related to sexual differentiation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>A large amount of pathways toward new gene origin through the domestication of parasitic genome sequences has been documented (Kaessmann 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>In addition to their infectious properties, which enable them to spread horizontally between individuals and across species, many viruses can also become part of the genetic material of their host, a process that is called endogenization: endogenous viruses have integrated into the germ line of their host, allowing for vertical transmission and fixation in the host population (Boeke and Stoye 1997; Belshaw et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>2004; Feschotte and Gilbert 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Viruses are able to integrate both in eukaryote and prokaryote genomes: for example, ORFans present in bacterial genomes are hypothesized to have been acquired through horizontal transfer from viruses (Daubin and Ochman 2004a, 2004b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Quite remarkably, the initiator protein DnaC in bacteria and the mitochondrial DNA replication and transcription apparatus have been recently documented to have a viral origin (Forterre 2010 and references therein). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>In the light of what reported above about endogenization in prokaryotes, a viral origin of novel mitochondrial genes is not unconceivable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Novel ORFs were recently found also in the linear mitochondrial genome of Medusozoa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Using the same approach as for bivalve novel ORFs, we found a complete homology of Amo-PolB with the polymerase beta of several organisms and of Ico-mtMutS with a DNA mismatch repair protein (thus confirming the results obtained by Smith et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>2011 and McFadden and van Ofwegen 2013, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>In both cases, the function of the novel mitochondrial proteins is supported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Instead, even if the product of ORF314 was proposed to act in concert with PolB in the maintenance of chromosome ends, it did not show a sound similarity with any other protein in database (Kayal et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we found that it shares many predicted functions with the novel mitochondrial ORFs of bivalves (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary table S18</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>In fact, almost all the analyzed bivalve ORFs, together with Pno-ORF314, show hits pointing to immune response and viral proteins (tables 4 and 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Viruses can manipulate the host cell molecular machinery to counteract antiviral defences and to control the expression of their own genes, moreover viral sequences can be co-opted for host cell functions (Feschotte and Gilbert 2012), contributing to host genome evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>For example, a viral gene has been co-opted to serve an important function in the physiology of mammals: syncytin is the envelope gene of a human endogenous defective retrovirus and is important in human placental morphogenesis and probably in the immune tolerance of the developing embryo (Mi et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, recent data attest that some genes involved in mammal placental development derive from domestication of multiple retrovirus-derived genes (Nakagawa et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Similarly, we think that virus-derived novel mitochondrial proteins may have acquired new functions in the host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>All the analyzed ORFs show an involvement in transcription regulation, like many virus-derived sequences that have been incorporated into the regulatory system of mammalian genes (Britten and Davidson 1969; Feschotte 2008; Cohen et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Role in Immune Response and Apoptosis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Microbial invasion generally causes an immune reaction (Galluzzi et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Mitochondria play a central role in primary host defence mechanisms against viral infections, and a number of viral proteins interact with mitochondria to regulate cellular responses (Ohta and Nishiyama 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Once viruses infect their hosts, they activate signalling pathways leading to the production of specific molecules (i.e., chemokines and cytokines) (Bryant and Fitzgerald 2009; Takeuchi and Akira 2009), and viruses have developed strategies to evade host immune responses: because signalling from recognition receptors converges in mitochondria, it is plausible that viruses would target mitochondrial processes to evade immune responses (Ohta and Nishiyama 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>A clue in favor of an interaction between novel mitochondrial ORFs and immune system comes from the many hits pointing to receptors and signaling molecules involved in immune response (antigens and cytokines above all). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Some of these hits are present in both FORFs (Mse-FORF, Mca-FORF, Mtr-FORF, Vel-FORF; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S6</ext-link>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S8</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) and MORFs (Mca-MORF2, Med-MORF, Mga-MORF, Rph-MORF, Vel-MORF; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S11–S13</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S15</ext-link>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S16</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), as in other analyzed ORFs (Mse-ORF-B, Peu-ORF; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S9</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S17</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>In Vel-MORF, the homology region almost coincides with the whole sequence (table 4 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary table S16</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Proteins reported in literature as acting in bivalve immune response (Gestal et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>2008, and references therein) have homology with the analyzed mitochondrial ORFs, as for example, tumor necrosis factors (see hits found in Vel-FORF, Mca-MORF2, Med-MORF, Peu-ORF; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S8</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S11</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S12</ext-link>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S17</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), interleukins (a group of cytokines; hits found in Mtr-FORF, Mca-MORF2, Med-MORF; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S6</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S11</ext-link>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S12</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), transforming growth factor (Kruppel-like factor; hits found in Mse-FORF, Mga-MORF; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S2</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S13</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) and platelet-derived growth factor (hit found in Mse-ORF-B; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary table S9</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>All the reported findings strongly support a link between these mitochondrial novel proteins and the immune response of bivalves. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Microbial invasion also has a role in apoptosis regulation (Galluzzi et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>2008): viruses have acquired the capacity to control host cell apoptosis and inflammatory responses, thus evading immune reactions (Galluzzi et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Mitochondria have a central role also in apoptosis and, for this reason, a number of viral proteins are targeted to mitochondria to regulate this mechanism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, hits of structural analogues with apoptotic factors were found with high probability in Mca-MORF1 (apoptosis regulator BCL-2, four hits with TM-scores &gt; 0.5, and apoptosis regulator BAK, TM-score &gt; 0.5) (table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>It is known that several viral polypeptides are homologues of host-derived apoptosis-regulatory proteins, such as members of the BCL-2 family (Galluzzi et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>2008), some of which assemble on the mitochondrial membrane (Wei et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>2001; Kuwana et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>2002; Nutt et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>2002). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Viral BCL-2 homologues (vBCL-2) do not show significant sequence similarity with their host counterparts, but exhibit high structural resemblance (White et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>1991; Cuconati and White 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>This seems exactly the case of Mca-MORF1, in which the similarity with both BCL-2 and BAK proteins was detected in the structure, not in the sequence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary table S10</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, viral proteins with a three-dimensional folding similar to BCL-2 are glycoprotein always showing a transmembrane domain flanked by positively charged amino acids (typically lysines) and followed by an hydrophilic tail (Wang et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>2002; Douglas et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>2007; Kvansakul et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>This domain is required for both the mitochondrial outer membrane targeting and the anti-apoptotic function (Douglas et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>2007; Kvansakul et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, all these characters are shared by Mytilus MORFs and Rph-MORF (the latter with serines instead of lysines). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Moreover, in some FORFs (Med-FORF, Mga-FORF, and Peu-ORF; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S4</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S5</ext-link>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S17</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), N-terminal homeodomain (PHD)-like regions were found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Recently, several PHD-containing viral proteins have been identified to promote immune evasion by down-regulating proteins that govern immune recognition by functioning as E3 ubiquitin ligases (Coscoy and Ganem 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Other hits specifically related to E3 ubiquitin ligases were found (Mse-FORF, Rph-FORF, Vel-FORF, Mse-ORF-B, Mca-MORF2; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">supplementary tables S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S7–S9</ext-link>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S11</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>For all above-mentioned, we propose that the novel ORFs here analyzed may have originated from viral elements with a function in immune response and apoptosis control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Interaction with Cytoskeleton: Mitochondrial Segregation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>MORFs, together with viral hits, show many hits related to cytoskeleton/cytoskeleton-binding proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>For example, among viral hits we obtained capsid proteins and Trans-activator of transcription (Tat) proteins, a regulatory protein that enhances the efficiency of viral transcription and alters microtubule dynamics, promoting proteasomal degradation and a mitochondrion-dependent apoptotic pathway (Chen et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>2002; Aprea et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>2006; Egelé et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Envelope proteins generally induce a perinuclear clustering of mitochondria by altering cytoskeleton conformation, interacting for example with keratins and microtubules, thus promoting the aggregation of these organelles (Doorbar et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>1991; Galluzzi et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Taking into account that mitochondria appear to respond to some viral infection by migrating with viral tegument proteins (Ohta and Nishiyama 2011), we suggest that these novel ORFs might have a role in the aggregation and localization of mitochondria, producing the aggregated and dispersed patterns of distribution of spermatozoon mitochondria observed in early DUI embryos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Many other hits are connected with cytoskeleton, such as microtubule-binding proteins, actin-binding proteins, cytoskeleton proteins themselves, and proteins with a role in cytoskeleton organization (table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, several endosymbiotic pathogens can use proteins expressed on their surface to ensure their survival and/or alter host processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>These surface proteins can cause cytoskeleton remodeling, as best demonstrated in Listeria monocytogenes: this endosymbiont induces actin to assemble on its surface, propelling it through the cytoplasm and allowing its transport between host cells, bypassing host defense mechanisms (Ireton and Cossart 1997, and references therein). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>It is possible that MORFs bind some cytoskeleton elements, and, if they were membrane-associated proteins, they could be responsible for spermatozoon mitochondria positioning in DUI embryos. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Targeting and Export of Mitochondrial Novel Proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>It is well established that the nucleus regulates organelle gene expression through anterograde regulation (Woodson and Chory 2008 and references therein). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, several studies have recently demonstrated that signals from organelles regulate nuclear gene expression by retrograde signaling (Butow and Narayan 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>It appears likely that, given the complex cross-talk between the nucleus and mitochondria, not only chemical messengers but also exported proteins may participate in transducing signals from mitochondrion to nucleus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>A deeply studied example is the retrograde signaling that characterizes plants with Cytoplasmic Male Sterility (CMS) (Abad et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>1995; Fujii and Toriyama 2008; Nizampatnam et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>CMS is known to be associated with the expression of novel mitochondrial ORFs and the accumulation of these novel proteins at proper spatial or temporal development stages induces male sterility (Fujii and Toriyama 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Moreover, some of these proteins contain a hydrophobic N terminus, commonly found in membrane-bound proteins (Abad et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>1995 and references therein) so that it was hypothesized that they are mitochondrial membrane-bound proteins that might lead to disruption of the mitochondrial membrane integrity in the anther tissues, leading to pollen death (Nizampatnam et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>2009, and references therein). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>The possibility of binding membranes is a feature in common with the here studied novel bivalve ORFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>In fact, many hits of the novel bivalve mitochondrial ORFs we analyzed were identified as proteins with a function on the cytoplasmic side of mitochondrial outer membrane (table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>For example, bivalve mitochondrial novel proteins may tag the surface of mitochondria: MORFs may have a role in the maintenance of sperm mitochondria aggregation in the first stages of development, possibly masking them from the degradation that normally affects mitochondria carried from sperm in species with the more usual maternal inheritance of mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>This could be possible thanks to the features that novel ORFs share with anti-apoptotic factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Maybe, a similar mechanism involving novel ORF integration in the mitochondrial genome of females makes FORFs responsible for the inheritance of F-type mitochondria in DUI species, but, in this case, no evident difference from a SMI mechanism for mitochondrial transmission could be seen. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>The presence of mitochondrial proteins in diverse cellular extramitochondrial sites, such as endoplasmic reticulum and nucleus, supports the existence of specific export mechanisms by which certain proteins exit mitochondria (Soltys and Gupta 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Mitochondria are derived from bacteria from which they probably inherited protein exit pathways used to elude host defense mechanism before the endosymbiont became an essential organism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Some of these protein exit mechanisms might have been retained and/or modified in mitochondria, allowing certain mitochondrial proteins to have additional functions in other subcellular compartments (Soltys and Gupta 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>For example, besides the export of mitochondrial ribosomes in the cytoplasm, some mitochondrially encoded proteins are present on the cell surface as histocompatibility antigens, and are therefore exported from mitochondria (Soltys and Gupta 2000, and references therein). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>These peptides derive from partial sequences of mitochondrial genes (e.g., N-terminus of NADH dehydrogenase subunit 1, in mouse and humans; internal region of ATPase 6, in rat) probably by proteolysis of parent molecules inside mitochondria or in the cytoplasm, before being transported to the cell surface (Soltys and Gupta 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>More than one mechanism by which mitochondrial matrix macromolecules are exported may exist but the processes are not fully clear yet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>For example, the presence versus the detachment by peptidase of part of the protein sequence (for example an N-terminal SP) was proposed to be the cause of the re-targeting of mitochondrial proteins, and the use of protein import machinery, the leakage from breaks in the mitochondrial membranes during fission and/or fusion, membrane fusion with other organelles (e.g., endoplasmic reticulum and nucleus), the existence of protein transporters, the autotransport through lipids (as observed for heat shock proteins), and vesicle-mediated export involving vesicle budding (as in gram-negative bacteria) are other proposed mechanisms (Soltys and Gupta 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>In our case, given the presence of a SP in many of the analyzed ORFs, this N-terminal sequence may be used to target the proteins to sites outside mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>It is possible that proteins with post-transcriptional cleavage of the SP remain attached at the mitochondrial outer membrane, whereas peptide complete with the SP may be targeted elsewhere in the cell. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>The Origin of Mitochondrial Novel ORFs and Implications for DUI Evolution </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>As mentioned, many clues point to a viral origin of novel mitochondrial ORFs, even if the probability of the hits is sometimes low and the regions of similarity of short length (table 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>As in the case of ORFans, this can be due to the extreme limited sampling of viral sequences (Daubin and Ochman 2004a, 2004b; Lerat et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>2005). Suttle (2005) estimated that the virus population size in the ocean alone is ∼4 × 1030, with a phage diversity of ∼108 (Rohwer 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>For this reason, a significant fraction of the ORFs without detectable viral homologs may have arisen from not yet sequenced or extinct viruses (Yin and Fischer 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Moreover, many ORFans may remain without viral homologs if they have experienced rapid evolution after the integration in the new genome, diverging to the extent that no homology to viral proteins is detectable (Charlebois et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>2003; Domazet-Loso and Tautz 2003; Daubin and Ochman 2004a; Siew and Fischer 2004; Yin and Fischer 2006). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>The co-option of such novel genes by viral hosts may have determined some evolutionary aspects of host life cycle, possibly involving mitochondria (Forterre 2006; Koonin 2006), and, as supposed for ORFans (Hendrix et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>2000; Juhala et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>2000), bivalve mtORFs might now be involved in key cellular functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>The study of novel mitochondrial proteins expression during the bivalve life cycle could help in understanding their function and their possible interaction with nuclear genomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>We can hypothesize that viral selfish elements may have colonized the mitochondrial genome in male bivalves promoting its segregation into primordial germ cells, thus allowing the transmission to next generations and leading to DUI achievement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>If this is true, the insertion event and the appearance of DUI might be causally linked, and some implications on the origin and evolution of DUI become evident. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>DUI presents a scattered distribution in bivalves, and two main hypotheses have been proposed so far to account for this: 1) an unique ancient origin and subsequent reversion to standard maternal inheritance in some lineages, or 2) multiple independent origins during bivalve evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>If these novel ORFs are in some way linked to DUI establishment, a multiple origin of DUI should not be discarded, even if it is in contrast to the mostly accepted evolutionary scenario of a single origin of DUI (Zouros 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>The overall function similarity among all analyzed ORFs supports their origin from elements of the same kind, but the impossibility to obtain a comprehensive good alignment and their conservation only among close relative species may indicate that either they originated from independent events or their fast evolution wiped out sequence similarities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Both hypotheses cannot be definitely accepted or discarded. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Finally, the general mechanism proposed above for the transmission of selfish elements would imply that bivalves are in some way prone to viral integration in the mitochondrial genome and therefore in DUI establishment, and maybe that other animals can have experienced such kind of mitochondrial transmission modification but no evidence has been found so far. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">Supplementary materials S1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">tables S1–S19</ext-link>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt101/-/DC1">figures S1–S7</ext-link> are available at Genome Biology and Evolution online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gbe.oxfordjournals.org/">http://www.gbe.oxfordjournals.org/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_5_7_1408__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_evt101_Supplementary_Figures.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_evt101_Supplementary_Material.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_evt101_Supplementary_Tables.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>The authors thank Eleonora Sparnanzoni for her precious help in lab work. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the Italian Ministero dell’Università e della Ricerca Scientifica funding (PRIN09) and by the Donazione Canziani bequest. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>Literature Cited</title><ref id="evt101-B1"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>AbadARMehrtensBJMackenzieSASpecific expression in reproductive tissues and fate of a mitochondrial sterility-associated protein in cytoplasmic male-sterile beanPlant Cell199572712857734962 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B2"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>AnderssonSGThe genome sequence of Rickettsia prowazekii and the origin of mitochondriaNature19983961331409823893 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B3"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>ApreaSTubulin-mediated binding of human immunodeficiency virus-1 Tat to the cytoskeleton causes proteasomal-dependent degradation of microtubule-associated protein 2 and neuronal damageJ Neurosci.2006264054406216611822 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B4"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>BelshawRLong-term reinfection of the human genome by endogenous retrovirusesProc Natl Acad Sci U S A.20041014894489915044706 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B5"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>BernselAViklundHHennerdalAElofssonATOPCONS: consensus prediction of membrane protein topologyNucleic Acids Res.200937W465W46819429891 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B6"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>BilewitchJPDegnanSMA unique horizontal gene transfer event has provided the octocoral mitochondrial genome with an active mismatch repair gene that has potential for an unusual self-contained functionBMC Evol Biol.20111122821801381 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B98"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>BirkyCWJrThe inheritance of genes in mitochondria and chloroplasts: laws, mechanisms, and modelsAnnu Rev Genet.20013512514811700280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B7"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>BoekeJDStoyeJPCoffinJMHughesSHVarmusHRetrotransposons, endogenous retroviruses, and the evolution of retroelementsRetroviruses1997Plainview (NY)Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press343435 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B8"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>BooreJLAnimal mitochondrial genomesNucleic Acids Res.1999271767178010101183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B9"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>BouaouinaMA conserved lipid-binding loop in the kindlin FERM F1 domain is required for kindlin-mediated αIIbβ3 integrin co-activationJ Biol Chem.20122876979699022235127 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B10"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>BretonSComparative mitochondrial genomics of freshwater mussels (Bivalvia: Unionoida) with doubly uniparental inheritance of mtDNA: gender-specific open reading frames and putative origins of replicationGenetics20091831575158919822725 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B11"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>BretonSNovel protein genes in animal mtDNA: a new sex determination system in freshwater mussels (Bivalvia: Unionoida)?Mol Biol Evol.2011a281645165921172831 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B12"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>BretonSEvidence for a fourteenth mtDNA-encoded protein in the female-transmitted mtDNA of marine mussels (Bivalvia: Mytilidae)PLoS One2011b6e1936521556327 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B13"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>BrittenRJDavidsonEHGene regulation for higher cells: a theoryScience19691653493575789433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B14"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>BryantCFitzgeraldKAMolecular mechanisms involved in inflammasome activationTrends Cell Biol.20091945546419716304 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B15"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>ButowRANarayanGAMitochondrial signaling: the retrograde responseMol Cell.20041411515068799 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B16"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>CaiJJPetrovDARelaxed purifying selection and possibly high rate of adaptation in primate lineage-specific genesGenome Biol Evol.2010239340920624743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B17"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>CaoLKenchingtonEZourosEDifferential segregation patterns of sperm mitochondria in embryos of the blue mussel (Mytilus edulis)Genetics200416688389415020473 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B19"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>CharleboisRLClarkeGDBeikoRGSt JeanACharacterization of species-specific genes using a flexible, web-based querying systemFEMS Microbiol Lett.200322521322012951244 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B20"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>ChenDWangMZhouSZhouQHIV-1 Tat targets microtubules to induce apoptosis, a process promoted by the pro-apoptotic Bcl-2 relative BimEMBO J.2002216801681012486001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B22"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>ChothiaCLeskAMThe relation between the divergence of sequence and structure in proteinsEMBO J.198658238263709526 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B23"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>ClaverieJMMimivirus and Mimiviridae: giant viruses with an increasing number of potential hosts, including corals and spongesJ Invertebr Pathol.200910117218019457438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B24"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>CogswellATKenchingtonELZourosESegregation of sperm mitochondria in two- and four-cell embryos of the blue mussel Mytilus edulis: implications for the mechanism of doubly uniparental inheritance of mitochondrial DNAGenome20064979980716936788 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B25"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>CohenCJLockWMMagerDLEndogenous retroviral LTRs as promoters for human genes: a critical assessmentGene200944810511419577618 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B26"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>CoscoyLGanemDPHD domains and E3 ubiquitin ligases: viruses make the connectionTrends Cell Biol.20031371212480335 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B27"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>CuconatiAWhiteEViral homologs of BCL-2: role of apoptosis in the regulation of virus infectionGenes Dev.2002162465247812368257 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B28"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>DaubinVOchmanHBacterial genomes as new gene homes: the genealogy of ORFans in E. coliGenome Res.2004a141036104215173110 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B29"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>DaubinVOchmanHStart-up entities in the origin of new genesCurr Opin Genet Dev.2004b1461661915531155 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B30"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Di TommasoPT-Coffee: a web server for the multiple sequence alignment of protein and RNA sequences using structural information and homology extensionNucleic Acids Res.201139W13W1721558174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B31"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Domazet-LosoTTautzDAn evolutionary analysis of orphan genes in DrosophilaGenome Res.2003132213221914525923 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B32"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>DoorbarJElySSterlingJMcLeanCCrawfordLSpecific interaction between HPV-16 E1-E4 and cytokeratins results in collapse of the epithelial cell intermediate filament networkNature19913528248271715519 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B99"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>DouglasAECorbettKDBergerJMMcFaddenGHandelTMStructure of M11L: a myxoma virus structural homolog of the apoptosis inhibitor, Bcl-2Protein Sci.20071669570317384234 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B33"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>EgeléCModulation of microtubule assembly by the HIV-1 Tat protein is strongly dependent on zinc binding to TatRetrovirology200856218613978 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B34"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>FeschotteCTransposable elements and the evolution of regulatory networksNat Rev Genet.2008939740518368054 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B35"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>FeschotteCGilbertCEndogenous viruses: insights into viral evolution and impact on host biologyNat Rev Genet.20121328329622421730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B36"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>FischerDEisenbergDFinding families for genomic ORFansBioinformatics19991575976210498776 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B37"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>ForterrePThe origin of viruses and their possible roles in major evolutionary transitionsVirus Res.200611751616476498 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B38"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>ForterrePCaetano-AnnolésGThe universal tree of life and the Last Universal Cellular Ancestor: revolution and counterrevolutionsEvolutionary genomics and systems biology2010Hoboken (NJ)John Wiley and Sons, Inc5862 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B39"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>FujiiSToriyamaKGenome barriers between nuclei and mitochondria exemplified by cytoplasmic male sterilityPlant Cell Physiol.2008491484149418625609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B40"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>GalluzziLBrennerCMorselliETouatZKroemerGViral control of mitochondrial apoptosisPLoS Pathog.20084e100001818516228 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B41"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>GestalCStudy of diseases and the immune system of bivalves using molecular biology and genomicsRev Fish Sci.200816133156 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B100"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>GhiselliFStructure, transcription and variability of metazoan mitochondrial genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Perspectives from an unusual mitochondrial inheritance systemGenome Biol Evol.2013Advance Access published July 23, 2013, doi:10.1093/gbe/evt112 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B42"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>GissiCIannelliFPesoleGEvolution of the mitochondrial genome of Metazoa as exemplified by comparison of congeneric speciesHeredity200810130132018612321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B43"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>HendrixRWLawrenceJGHatfullGFCasjensSThe origins and ongoing evolution of virusesTrends Microbiol.2000850450811121760 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B44"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>HillerKGroteAScheerMMünchRJahnDPrediSi: prediction of signal peptides and their cleavage positionsNucleic Acids Res.200432W375W37915215414 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B45"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>HofmannKStoffelWTMbase—a database of membrane spanning proteins segmentsBiol Chem Hoppe-Seyler.1993374166 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B46"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>HowardMBEkborgNATaylorLEHutchesonSWWeinerRMIdentification and analysis of polyserine linker domains in prokaryotic proteins with emphasis on the marine bacterium Microbulbifer degradansProtein Sci.2004131422142515075401 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B47"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>IretonKCossartPHost-pathogen interactions during entry and actin-based movement of Listeria monocytogenesAnnu Rev Genet.1997311131389442892 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B48"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>JuhalaRJGenomic sequences of bacteriophages HK97 and HK022: pervasive genetic mosaicism in the lambdoid bacteriophagesJ Mol Biol.2000299275110860721 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B49"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>KaessmannHOrigins, evolution, and phenotypic impact of new genesGenome Res.2010201313132620651121 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B50"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>KällLKroghASonnhammerELLA combined transmembrane topology and signal peptide prediction methodJ Mol Biol.20043381027103615111065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B51"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>KayalEEvolution of linear mitochondrial genomes in medusozoan cnidariansGenome Biol Evol.2011411222113796 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B52"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>KooninEVSenkevichTGDoljaVVThe ancient Virus World and evolution of cellsBiol Direct.200612916984643 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B53"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>KuwanaTBid, Bax, and lipids cooperate to form supramolecular openings in the outer mitochondrial membraneCell200211133134212419244 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B101"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>KvansakulMA structural viral mimic of prosurvival Bcl-2: a pivotal role for sequestering proapoptotic Bax and BakMol Cell20072593394217386268 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B54"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>LeratEDaubinVOchmanHMoranNAEvolutionary origins of genomic repertoires in bacteriaPLoS Biol.20053e13015799709 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B55"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>McFaddenCSSánchezJAFranceSCMolecular phylogenetic insights into the evolution of Octocorallia: a reviewIntegr Comp Biol.20105038941021558211 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B56"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>McFaddenCSvan OfwegenLPA second, cryptic species of the soft coral genus Incrustatus (Anthozoa: Octocorallia: Clavulariidae) from Tierra del Fuego, Argentina, revealed by DNA barcodingHelgol Mar Res.201367137147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B57"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>MiSSyncytin is a captive retroviral envelope protein involved in human placental morphogenesisNature200040378578910693809 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B58"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>MilaniLGhiselliFMauriziiMGPassamontiMDoubly uniparental inheritance of mitochondria as a model system for studying germ line formationPLoS One20116e2819422140544 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B59"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>MilaniLGhiselliFPassamontiMSex-linked mitochondrial behavior during early embryo development in Ruditapes philippinarum (Bivalvia Veneridae) a species with the Doubly Uniparental Inheritance (DUI) of mitochondriaJ Exp Zool B Mol Dev Evol.201231818218922544715 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B60"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>MorseDEDuncanHHookerNMorseAHydrogen peroxide induces spawning in molluscs, with activation of prostaglandin endoperoxide synthetaseScience1977196298300403609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B61"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>MouhamadouBBarrosoGLabarèreJMolecular evolution of a mitochondrial polB gene, encoding a family B DNA polymerase, towards the elimination from Agrocybe mitochondrial genomesMol Genet Genomics.200427225726315365817 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B62"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>NakagawaSDynamic evolution of endogenous retrovirus-derived genes expressed in bovine conceptuses during the period of placentationGenome Biol Evol.2013529630623335121 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B63"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>NizampatnamNRHarinathDYaminiKNSujathaMDinesh KumarVExpression of sunflower cytoplasmic male sterility-associated open reading frame, orfH522 induces male sterility in transgenic tobacco plantsPlanta2009229987100119151958 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B64"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>NuttLKBax and Bak promote apoptosis by modulating endoplasmic reticular and mitochondrial Ca2+ storesJ Biol Chem.20022779219922511741880 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B65"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>OgataHTwo new subfamilies of DNA mismatch repair proteins (MutS) specifically abundant in the marine environmentIntl Soc Microbial Ecol J.2011511431151 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B66"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>OhtaANishiyamaYMitochondria and virusesMitochondrion20111111220813204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B67"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>PassamontiMRicciAMilaniLGhiselliFMitochondrial genomes and Doubly Uniparental Inheritance: new insights from Musculista senhousia sex-linked mitochondrial DNAs (Bivalvia Mytilidae)BMC Genomics20111244221896183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B68"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>PetersenTNBrunakSvon HeijneGNielsenHSignalP 4.0: discriminating signal peptides from transmembrane regionsNat Methods.2011878578621959131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B69"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>PonsJ-LLabesseG@TOME-2: a new pipeline for comparative modeling of protein–ligand complexesNucleic Acids Res.200937W485W49119443448 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B70"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>Pont-KingdonGA coral mitochondrial MutS geneNature19953751091117753165 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B72"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>RohwerFGlobal phage diversityCell200311314112705861 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B73"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>RozenSSkaletskyHJKrawetzSMisenerSPrimer3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmersBioinformatics methods and protocols: methods in molecular biology2000Totowa (NJ)Humana Press365386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B74"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>ShaoZGrafSChagaOYLavrovDVMitochondrial genome of the moon jelly Aurelia aurita (Cnidaria, Scyphozoa): a linear DNA molecule encoding a putative DNA-dependent DNA polymeraseGene20063819210116945488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B75"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>SiewNFischerDStructural biology sheds light on the puzzle of genomic ORFansJ Mol Biol.200434236937315327940 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B76"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>SkibinskiDOGallagherCBeynonCMMitochondrial DNA inheritanceNature1994a3688178188159240 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B77"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>SkibinskiDOGallagherCBeynonCMSex-limited mitochondrial DNA transmission in the marine mussel Mytilus edulisGenetics1994b1388018097851776 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B78"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>SmithDRFirst complete mitochondrial genome sequence from a box jellyfish reveals a highly fragmented linear architecture and insights into telomere evolutionGenome Biol Evol.20114525822117085 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B79"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>SödingJBiegertALupasANThe HHpred interactive server for protein homology detection and structure predictionNucleic Acids Res.200533W244W24815980461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B80"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>SoltysBJGuptaRSMitochondrial proteins at unexpected cellular locations: export of proteins from mitochondria from an evolutionary perspectiveInt Rev Cytol.200019413319610494626 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B81"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>SuttleCAViruses in the seaNature200543735636116163346 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B82"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>TakeuchiOAkiraSInnate immunity to virus infectionImmunol Rev.2009227758619120477 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B83"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>TamuraKMEGA5: Molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methodsMol Biol Evol.2011282731273921546353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B84"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>ToddAEOrengoCAThorntonJMEvolution of function in protein superfamilies, from a structural perspectiveJ Mol Biol.20013071113114311286560 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B85"><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>WangHWSharpTVKoumiAKoentgesGBoshoffCCharacterization of an anti-apoptotic glycoprotein encoded by Kaposi’s sarcoma-associated herpesvirus which resembles a spliced variant of human survivinEMBO J.2002212602261512032073 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B86"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>WeiMCProapoptotic BAX and BAK: a requisite gateway to mitochondrial dysfunction and deathScience200129272773011326099 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B87"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>WhiteECiprianiRSabbatiniPDentonAAdenovirus E1B 19-kilodalton protein overcomes the cytotoxicity of E1A proteinsJ Virol.199165296829781851867 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B88"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>WoodsonJDChoryJCoordination of gene expression between organellar and nuclear genomesNat Rev Genet.2008938339518368053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B89"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>WuXNew features of Asian Crassostrea oyster mitochondrial genomes: a novel alloacceptor tRNA gene recruitment and two novel ORFsGene201250711211822846367 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B90"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>XuJZhangYHow significant is a protein structure similarity with TM-score=0.5?Bioinformatics20102688989520164152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B91"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>YinYFischerDOn the origin of microbial ORFans: quantifying the strength of the evidence for viral lateral transferBMC Evol Biol.200666316914045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B92"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>YuGStoltzfusAPopulation diversity of ORFan genes in Escherichia coliGenome Biol Evol.201241176118723034216 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B93"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>ZdobnovEMApweilerRInterProScan—an integration platform for the signature-recognition methods in InterProBioinformatics20011784784811590104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B94"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>ZhangYI-TASSER server for protein 3D structure predictionBMC Bioinformatics200894018215316 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B95"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>ZourosEBiparental inheritance through uniparental transmission: the doubly uniparental inheritance (DUI) of mitochondrial DNAEvol Biol.201240131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B96"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>ZourosEOberhauser BallASaavedraCFreemanKRMitochondrial DNA inheritanceNature1994a3688188159241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt101-B97"><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>ZourosEOberhauser BallASaavedraCFreemanKRAn unusual type of mitochondrial DNA inheritance in the blue mussel MytilusProc Natl Acad Sci U S A.1994b91746374678052604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
