<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Dev Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin. Dev. Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CDI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Clinical and Developmental Immunology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-2522</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1740-2530</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3671266</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/412768</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>RANKL Cytokine: From Pioneer of the Osteoimmunology Era to Cure for a Rare Disease </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lo Iacono</surname><given-names>Nadia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pangrazio</surname><given-names>Alessandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abinun</surname><given-names>Mario</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bredius</surname><given-names>Robbert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zecca</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>Harry C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vezzoni</surname><given-names>Paolo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Villa</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sobacchi</surname><given-names>Cristina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>UOS/IRGB, Milan Unit, CNR, Milano, Italy</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Humanitas Clinical and Research Center, Via Manzoni 113, 20089 Rozzano, Italy</aff><aff id="I3"><sup>3</sup>Great North Children's Hospital, Institute for Cellular Medicine, Newcastle University, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK</aff><aff id="I4"><sup>4</sup>Department of Pediatrics, Leiden University Medical Center, Leiden, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="I5"><sup>5</sup>Pediatric Hematology/Oncology, Foundation IRCCS, San Matteo, Pavia, Italy</aff><aff id="I6"><sup>6</sup>Department of Pathology, Veteran's Affairs Medical Center, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Cristina Sobacchi: <email>cristina.sobacchi@humanitasresearch.it</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editor: Giacomina Brunetti </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>2013</volume><elocation-id>412768</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2013 Nadia Lo Iacono et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Since its identification, the RANKL cytokine has been demonstrated to play a crucial role in bone homeostasis and lymphoid tissue organization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Genetic defects impairing its function lead to a peculiar form of autosomal recessive osteopetrosis (ARO), a rare genetic bone disease presenting early in life and characterized by increased bone density due to failure in bone resorption by the osteoclasts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) is the only option for the majority of patients affected by this life-threatening disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>However, the RANKL-dependent ARO does not gain any benefit from this approach, because the genetic defect is not intrinsic to the hematopoietic osteoclast lineage but rather to the mesenchymal one. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Of note, we recently provided proof of concept of the efficacy of a pharmacological RANKL-based therapy to cure this form of the disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Here we provide an overview of the diverse roles of RANKL in the bone and immune systems and review the clinical features of RANKL-deficient ARO patients and the results of our preclinical studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>We emphasize that these patients present a continuous worsening of the disease in the absence of a cure and strongly wish that the therapy we propose will be further developed. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>In accordance with the ancient Latin maxim, “In medio stat virtus”, in all the organisms the physiology of many biological functions is based on the equilibrium between the opposite activities of different cell types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In vertebrates, homeostasis of the skeletal tissue is accomplished by the balance between bone synthesis, performed by the osteoblasts, and bone resorption, carried out by the osteoclasts; in addition, other cell types, such as osteocytes and immune cells, as well as soluble factors, such as cytokines and hormones, cooperate to the same end [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Altering this balance leads to diseases characterized by either a decrease (as in osteoporosis) or increase (as in osteopetrosis) in bone mass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The term “osteopetrosis” (from the Ancient Greek οστέον, osteon = bone, + πέτρος, petros = stone) defines a number of monogenic disorders characterized by increased bone density due to failure in bone resorption by the osteoclasts, large multinucleated cells of hematopoietic origin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The most severe form is the autosomal recessive osteopetrosis (ARO), which presents soon after birth and is often lethal unless treated with hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT), providing the precursor cells for the differentiation of functional osteoclasts in the host [2–5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Subgroups of patients with ARO are distinguished based on the affected gene [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Among them, the RANKL dependent is the most peculiar, since it bears defects in a gene mainly expressed, in bone, by mesenchymal-derived cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Thus, HSCT is not a valid therapeutic option for this subset of patients [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the discovery of RANKL has represented the beginning of a new scientific field, called “osteoimmunology”, tightly linking the bone to the immune system [8, 9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Indeed, this cytokine is multitasking, with roles ranging from bone remodeling to lymphoid tissue organization [10, 11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Its importance has recently been highlighted by the development of a monoclonal antibody against RANKL (denosumab, Amgen Inc., Thousand Oaks, CA, USA) approved in the clinical practice for the treatment of postmenopausal osteoporosis and cancer-related osteolysis [12] and under evaluation in a Phase 4 clinical trial for rheumatoid arthritis (clinical trial identifier: NCT01770106). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Here we summarize the many roles of RANKL in the bone and immune systems, review the clinical features of RANKL-deficient ARO patients, and discuss the results of preclinical studies on a RANKL-based pharmacological therapy holding great promise for these patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>RANKL in Bone </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>RANKL, also called TNF-related activation induced cytokine, TRANCE; osteoclast differentiation factor, ODF; and osteoprotegerin ligand, OPGL, is a type II transmembrane protein belonging to the TNF superfamily, whose gene was cloned fifteen years ago by four different groups contemporaneously [13–16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>It exists predominantly in a membrane-bound form, with a short cytoplasmic N-terminal domain and a single transmembrane region, but a soluble form can be generated through alternative splicing [17] or through the cleavage by matrix metalloproteinases and ADAMs (disintegrin and metalloproteinase domain-containing proteins) [18–20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>RANKL aggregates into homotrimers through conserved and specific residues in the extracellular domain, and trimerization is essential for the activation of its cognate receptor RANK [21–24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Recently, the crystal structure of human RANKL in complex with its decoy receptor osteoprotegerin (OPG) has been determined, too, and showed that in this case a different mode of interaction takes place, directly blocking the accessibility of residues of RANKL important for RANK recognition [25, 26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>RANKL is broadly expressed, including both skeletal and extra-skeletal sites and many diverse cell types, such as T and B lymphocytes, mammary epithelial cells, keratinocytes, vascular endothelial cells, and synovial fibroblasts [15, 17, 27–29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In the bone, it is produced mainly by cells of mesenchymal origin, osteoblasts, hypertrophic chondrocytes, and bone marrow (BM) stromal cells; recently, osteocytes have been identified as another source of this cytokine [30–32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Its expression is positively regulated by several factors, such as parathyroid hormone (PTH) and 1,25 dihydroxyvitamin D3, which bind to a distal control region (DCR) located 76 kb upstream of the murine Rankl transcription start site [33]; deletion of the DCR in mouse significantly affects Rankl production and the rate of bone remodeling [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Other factors stimulating Rankl expression are calcium, glucocorticoids, prostaglandin E2, interleukin (IL)-1α, IL-6, IL-11, and IL-17, while the canonical Wnt signaling and transforming growth factor (TGF)-β pathways downregulate it [29, 35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Together with M-CSF, RANKL is the master cytokine driving osteoclast differentiation through the binding to its receptor RANK and the activation of different intracellular signaling cascades, involving an increasing number of molecules; among them, TRAF6, NF-kB, ERK1/2, JNK, and p38 have ultimately, as target gene NFATc1, the crucial transcription factor in osteoclastogenesis [12, 36, 37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The strongest evidence for the role of RANKL during osteoclastogenesis came from gene inactivation in murine models [38–40], leading to osteoclast-poor osteopetrosis already present at birth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>At 1 month of age, Rankl −/− mice were severely growth retarded due to poor nutrition secondary to lack of tooth eruption and displayed shortened long bones with club-shaped ends, thinning of the calvariae, generalized increase in bone density with very little marrow space, marked chondrodysplasia with thick, irregular growth plates, and relative increase in hypertrophic chondrocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>At an older age, Rankl −/− mice developed rounded faces, likely due to osteopetrotic changes of the facial skeleton. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The phenotype was only partially rescued by transgenic overexpression under a lymphocyte-specific promoter, highlighting the importance of RANKL local delivery in many skeletal compartments [39, 40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>More recently, conditional knockout models have been generated by specifically targeting the gene in chondrocytes, at different stages of the osteoblast lineage or in osteocytes [41, 42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The deletion of the gene in chondrocytes or in the osteoblasts led to severe osteopetrosis in mice at birth, while the deletion in the osteocytes caused a pathologic bone phenotype only later in postnatal life, suggesting a different contribution of these cell types in bone modeling and remodeling [31, 32, 43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In addition, during the screening of N-ethyl-N-nitrosourea (ENU)-mutagenized mice, Douni and colleagues have recently reported a new mouse model bearing a G278R substitution in Rankl (Rankl tles/tles); this mutation was predicted to impair trimerization, affecting the bone phenotype to the same extent as in the Rankl −/− mouse [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Other osteoclast differentiation pathways independent from the RANKL/RANK axis have been reported, such as those driven by TGFβ or LIGHT [45–47]; however, the phenotype of the murine models above described, as well as the osteopetrotic features of Rank knockout mice [48–50], clearly indicates that in vivo those alternative pathways cannot completely substitute for a lack of signal from the RANKL/RANK system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, an over activity of this pathway has been described to contribute to conditions characterized by excessive bone loss or destruction such as osteoporosis, cancer-related osteolysis, and Paget's disease [51, 52], giving thus the rationale for the establishment of an anti-RANKL therapy in these patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>RANKL in the Immune System </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>At the very beginning of its story, RANKL was described as a dendritic cell (DC) survival factor allowing efficient priming of T cells [13, 14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, this cell type did not appear to be affected in Rankl −/− mice, as far as it was investigated [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>However, these mice displayed other clear immunological defects, even though with some differences likely due to the genetic background. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Kong and colleagues reported reduced thymus size and cellularity, thymocyte development block at the stage CD4−CD8−CD44−CD25+, and defective cytokine production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>They also found spleen enlargement and block in the progression of B220+CD25− pro-B cells to B220+CD25+ pre-B cells, in the presence of intact splenic architecture, with normal distribution of red and white pulp, normal T- and B-cell segregation and normal primary follicle structure [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>In an independent Rankl −/− model, Kim and colleagues described altered splenic microarchitecture and defects in B-cell follicle formation and in marginal zone integrity in the majority of Rankl −/− mice [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>In the same model, red pulp expansion, white pulp reduction, and regions of intense extramedullary hematopoiesis in the spleen occur, together with severe reduction in thymic medulla [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Also in the Rankl tles/tles mouse, thymic hypoplasia and enlarged spleen have been reported [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Moreover, all these models displayed complete lack of lymph nodes (LNs; cervical LNs were seldom present) and smaller Peyer's patches [38, 44, 53]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>These findings are consistent with the diverse functions RANKL exerts in the immune system: during LN organogenesis, together with LTαβ, it regulates the colonization of the forming anlagen by CD45+CD4+CD3− cells [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>In the thymus, it is required for autoimmune regulator (AIRE)-expressing medullary thymic epithelial cell maturation [55–58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>In the skin, after different environmental stimuli, it mediates immunosuppression by increasing regulatory T-cell numbers [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>In the gut, it initiates the development of antigen-sampling M cells in the intestinal epithelium [60] and is essential for the CXCL13-dependent maturation of cryptopatches into isolated lymphoid follicles in the small intestine [61]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>In addition, several reports have highlighted the cross-talk between immune and bone cells through this molecule, and the importance of the contribution of immune cells becomes particularly evident in pathological conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>For example, Th1 and Th2 cells inhibit osteoclastogenesis through the production of IFN-γ and IL-4, while Th17 cells induce osteoclast formation and osteolysis in rheumatoid arthritis (RA) via the IL-17-mediated induction of RANKL expression on synovial fibroblasts [9, 62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>In addition, a role for B cells in the pathogenesis of RA has been suggested by the significant efficacy of the treatment with an anti-CD20 antibody in cases showing an inadequate response to anti-TNF therapies [63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>RANKL produced by B cells also contributes to bone resorption during periodontal infection [64, 65] and to the increase in osteoclasts and trabecular bone loss occurring upon estrogen withdrawal [66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Based on these interconnections, the RANKL/RANK axis has rightly been defined an essential regulator of both immune responses and bone physiology [67], and it is largely expected that alterations in one system will also affect the other. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>RANKL-Dependent ARO Patients: A Small Group of Great Interest </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>In 2007 our group described for the first time mutations in the RANKL gene in 6 patients from 4 families affected by ARO [7]; in this review we refer to these individuals using the same nomenclature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, we identified 3 additional patients with mutations in RANKL; no detailed clinical data are available for 2 of them (referred to as S5 and S6); for the remaining one (referred to as S7), the entire clinical history is herein reported for the first time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The mutation details are reported in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>No other reports on this ARO subset exist in the literature, to the best of our knowledge; therefore, at present RANKL-dependent ARO represents about 3% of all ARO forms in our cohort of about 300 patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>In the original work, onset of the disease was reported to range from 2 days to 1 year of age; at diagnosis, patients presented with fractures (4 of 6), visual impairment (5 of 6; S2A, S2B, and S4 underwent bilateral optic nerve decompression, without benefit), neurological defects (hydrocephalus, nystagmus; 4 out of 6), hepatosplenomegaly (from minimal to important, in all of them), and lack of palpable lymph nodes but no overt immunological defects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Three of them received full HSCT before the molecular diagnosis (S1, S2A, and S3A); they showed good levels of hematological engraftment but no improvement in bone remodeling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>This prompted us to hypothesize a role for an osteoclast-extrinsic factor in the pathogenesis of the disease in these individuals, as also suggested by the evidence of lack of osteoclasts in the bone biopsy specimen of 4 of them and by the ability to differentiate functional osteoclasts from the patients' PBMCs in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Indeed, all of them bore homozygous mutations in RANKL gene: patient S1 carried a deletion of five nucleotides in intron 7 resulting in skipping of exon 7 and in-frame deletion encompassing amino acids (aa) 145–177. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Patients S2A, S2B and S4 displayed a single nucleotide substitution in exon 8 causing a missense mutation; the same amino acid change was subsequently found in patients S5 and S6 [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Patients S3A and S3B bore a deletion of two nucleotides in exon 8 leading to a frameshift at the C-terminus of the protein [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Based on early crystallographic studies [21], these mutations were predicted to affect regions important for RANKL trimerization or for the interaction with RANK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The same mutations were further investigated subsequently by in vitro osteoclastogenesis assays using mutant constructs [36] and by crystallographic studies of the murine RANKL ectodomain in complex with the RANK ectodomain [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>In their study, Crockett and colleagues could not draw definitive conclusions regarding the possibility that the mutant products, in particular the missense mutation, maintain a residual activity or rather completely lose their function [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, Ta and colleagues confirmed that the deletion of aa 145–177 abolished the interaction with RANK and the frameshift affected conformation and binding activity; the missense mutation proved to be more difficult to analyze possibly due to protein instability or misfolding [24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Regarding the immunological compartment, at the time of our first work, 3 patients had already received HSCT, therefore were not candidates to such studies; in the remaining ones, although exhaustive analyses were not possible due to difficulty in obtaining blood samples from the patients, we did not find differences with normal controls with regard to B- and T-cell subsets, T-cell proliferation and propensity to apoptosis; however, we detected lower levels of both Th1 and Th2 cytokines in one patient (S2B) after stimulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The recently identified patient S7 was born from consanguineous parents (first degree consanguinity) of Lebanese origin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The disease presented soon after birth with hypocalcemic seizures, increased bone density, several fractures, pancytopenia, failure to thrive, and cranial nerve involvement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>She received a first HSCT from an HLA-matched family donor (healthy brother) at 2 years of age; lack of bone rescue raised the hypothesis of poor engraftment, so a second transplantation was performed 1 year later. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>In this case, full engraftment was documented by karyotype analysis and subsequently confirmed using DNA sequencing, but again there was no benefit on bone architecture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>In spite of the early and severe clinical picture at presentation, the patient became a long-term survivor and was referred to our center for genetic investigation at 22 years of age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The analysis revealed the presence of a c.667C&gt;T mutation in RANKL, leading to premature termination of translation (p.Arg223X), in the homozygous state; the same nucleotide change was found in the heterozygous state in her mother and in her healthy brother (the paternal DNA was not available for investigation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The possibility that a truncated protein might be produced from this mutated allele has not been verified; however, if synthesized, the predicted peptide would lack a large part of the extracellular domain and both homodimerization and receptor-binding functions are expected to be importantly impaired. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Followup of RANKL-Deficient Patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The followup of the patients originally described and of patient S7 clearly show progressive worsening of clinical features in all of them. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>At 11 years of age, 10 years after transplantation, patient S1 showed neurological deterioration due to increasing compression of cerebro-bulbar structures; afterwards she was lost to followup. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>At 14 years of age, 5 years post-HSCT, patient S2A developed hemolytic anemia, requiring repeated transfusions and chelation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>No adequate response to steroids, high-dose intravenous immunoglobulins (i.v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Ig), or rituximab therapy was achieved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>At 16 years of age she displayed very severe growth retardation with both weight and height well below the 0.4th centile for age (height 109 cm, weight 26 kg), refractory to a trial with growth hormone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Bone defects included deformities, particularly affecting legs and knees and partially due to recurrent fractures, and severely impaired dentition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>She also had an episode of osteomyelitis of her toe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>At present, she is 18 years old with delayed puberty. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>She has recently been diagnosed with depression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Her younger sister, patient S2B, at 10 years of age was severely growth retarded too (height 94.5 cm, weight 13.8 kg, both well below the 0.4th centile for age, and almost identical to her sister's growth pattern). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Dentition was delayed, complicated by gum infection and more recently by chronic bilateral parotid and mandibular bone abscesses with sinusitis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>She had experienced recurrent fractures at a younger age, which are properly healed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Like S2A, she developed anemia and became transfusion dependent at 11 years of age, soon requiring the use of chelating agents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Severe sleep apnea led to adenoidectomy; in addition, a reservoir was placed to resolve hydrocephalus several years ago. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>At present, she is 13 years old, has nocturnal continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP), and is complaining of recurrent and severe pounding headaches. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>At 19 years of age, 11 years post-HSCT, patient S3A shows multiple poorly healing, traumatic fractures of her lumbar spine and progressive kyphosis of her neck secondary to lack of support by muscles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>She is extremely growth retarded (height 118.5 cm, weight 27 kg, and both well below the 0.4th centile for age) with delayed puberty and defective dentition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>She is anemic (Hb 5.5 mmol/L; normal range 7.5–10.0 mmol/L) and thrombocytopenic (123 × 109/L; normal range 150–400 × 109/L) but does not require transfusions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>At 4.5 years of age, her younger cousin, patient S3B displayed several neurological problems, including facial nerve palsy, headache, deterioration of hearing, due to progressive narrowing of the posterior fossa, and foramen magnum, as demonstrated by CT scan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The insertion of a ventriculoperitoneal (VP) shunt was required. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>At present, she is 6 years old, with severe growth retardation (height 94.6 cm, weight 13.6 kg, and both well below the 0.4th centile for age), has abnormal delayed dentition, poorly healing bone fractures, and recurrent ear and upper airway infections. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Patient S4 experienced multiple fractures which are, however, properly healed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Upper airway obstruction and hypoxic encephalopathy led to tracheostomy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>At present, he is 6.5 years old and shows moderate growth retardation (height 105 cm, weight 16 kg, and both on the 4th centile) and markedly delayed tooth eruption (only 2 in lower jaws). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>He has episodes of severe agonizing headaches; CT and MRI brain scans showed a crowded posterior fossa and Chiari I malformation, but there were no signs of raised intracranial pressure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>He has also recently had an episode of inflammatory synovitis of his left ankle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Patient S7 is now 22 years old, 18 years after the second transplant, and shows very severe growth retardation similarly to the other patients (height 120 cm, weight 38 kg, and both well below the 0.4th centile for age). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Severe bone deformities involve all skeletal segments, with tendency to turricephaly, beak-like nose, exophthalmos, hypoplasia of the facial, and a more profound involvement of the spine, knees and legs (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>In the past years, she had very frequent bone fractures, in some cases with poor healing, requiring surgical intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Dental eruption is largely incomplete. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The girl is totally blind and unable to articulate complete sentences, even though she can hear properly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Psychomotorial development is severely retarded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Episodes of agitation have been reported, with outbursts of anger and violence towards others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless an MRI scan performed at the last control showed diffuse thickening of all the bones of the skull but a very mild cerebral atrophy with absence of other signs of central nervous system degeneration or deterioration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>In addition, she suffers from recurrent pulmonary and upper airway infections. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Overall, these data demonstrate the need for the development of targeted approaches which could at least improve the quality of life of these patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>A Pharmacological Therapy for RANKL-Dependent ARO: Preclinical Data Hold Promise </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Since the identification of RANKL as the essential factor required for the osteoclastogenic process, exogenous administration of the soluble cytokine to murine and rat models have shown a great impact on bone metabolism and structure [15, 68–72]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>In 1998, Lacey and colleagues tested the response of wild-type mice to a 3-day treatment with murine recombinant RANKL (aa 158–316) injected subcutaneously at different doses (1, 5, 25, and 100 μg/day split in two administrations) [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>They showed a rapid, significant, and dose-dependent increase in blood-ionized calcium level, a reduction in bone volume, and an increase in osteoclast cell size, with no change in osteoclast number. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Soon after, the same group verified the effect of RANKL administration through a different route, that is, intravenously; doses ranged from 0.01 to 0.5 mg/kg, and mice were maintained either on a classic diet or on a low-calcium diet for 48 hours, in order to rule out the influence of gut calcium absorption [68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>They showed that the level of whole blood-ionized calcium increased dose-dependently after 1 hour and concluded that the observed effect was due to the activation of preexisting osteoclasts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>In addition, they evaluated the role of RANKL in osteoclast survival through the subcutaneous injection of either saline or RANKL (1 mg/kg/day) in wild-type mice for 7 days, followed by a single OPG dose (10 mg/kg) [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>They observed a two-fold increase in osteoclast number in RANKL-treated mice, while loss of stimulation by OPG administration rapidly led to osteoclast disappearance, thus pointing to an important role for RANKL in osteoclast survival. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>In 2008, Lloyd and colleagues observed that bone turnover was greatly accelerated by the administration of soluble RANKL to wild-type mice (human recombinant RANKL, aa 143–317; dose 0.4 or 2 mg/kg/day split in two subcutaneous injections, for 10 days), with deleterious effects on both cortical and trabecular bone [70], in agreement with a possible role of this cytokine in the etiology of conditions characterized by pathological bone loss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The same group reported similar results after continuous RANKL infusion in rats for 28 days (2 doses: 35 μg/kg/day or 175 μg/kg/day), supporting also the appropriateness of this model for the study of high-turnover bone diseases [71]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>In the same line, Tomimori and colleagues developed a model of rapid bone loss based on intraperitoneal daily injections of RANKL (a fusion protein of glutathione S-transferase (GST) and the extracellular domain of human RANKL, aa 140–317; dosages 0.5, 1, and 2 mg/kg) in wild-type mice, showing a dose-dependent decrease in bone mineral density (BMD) within 50 hours [72]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Based on these in vivo evidences, when the human RANKL-dependent ARO subgroup was first identified [7], it was rather obvious to suggest that a pharmacological RANKL-based approach might be considered for the therapy of these patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>To test this hypothesis, we conducted a preclinical study treating Rankl −/− mice with subcutaneous injections of RANKL (soluble recombinant murine RANKL, amino acids 158–316, kindly provided by Amgen, Inc., Thousand Oaks, CA, USA; dosages 0.5, 1, or 2 mg/kg) from the first week of life, every 48 hours, for 1 month [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>At sacrifice, we performed histological analysis of bone and all the main organs, including spleen, thymus, lung, heart, liver, kidney, pancreas, and mammary gland. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The 1 mg/kg dose proved to be able to almost completely rescue the bone defect, by restoring osteoclast differentiation and resorption (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Douni and colleagues reported a similar result in the bone compartment in their Rankl tles/tles mouse model, through the daily subcutaneous injection of RANKL (GST-fusion protein of murine RANKL, residues 158–316, dose 150 μg/kg) from 13 days of age for 2 weeks [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Besides bone rescue, we also demonstrated that our protocol at the 1 mg/kg dose importantly ameliorated the hematolymphoid compartment of the treated Rankl −/− mice, with a restoration of the hematopoietic function within the bone marrow and an improvement of splenic and thymic architecture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Of note, no adverse effect was detected with this treatment regimen over the 1-month period of followup [54]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>A Step Further Towards Patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Our preclinical studies in Rankl −/− mice provided an important proof of concept of the efficacy of a RANKL-based pharmacological therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Further investigation is required to precisely identify all the possible toxic events related to RANKL administration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Our preliminary studies revealed detrimental effects associated with a clear overtreatment [53]; however, it should be considered that, when transferred to patients, many readouts of this therapy, such as serum calcium levels, concentration of a crosslink peptide sequence of type I collagen (CTX) in blood or urine, bone density by radiographic analysis, and immunophenotype, are easily available and indicative of the impact on bone metabolism, the immune system, and other physiological functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Once a satisfactory bone response is obtained, the treatment regimen could be modified, for example, by dose tapering or periodical discontinuation, before adverse events arise. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>As shown by the clinical data reported above, the RANKL-dependent ARO patients in our cohort, now in their teens in many cases, are in poor conditions, with some irreversible deficits (i.e. blindness) already established. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>We expect that the therapy we propose will stop further degeneration of the many impaired biological functions and will ameliorate their quality of life by reestablishing osteoclast formation and resorptive activity and improving the hematopoietic compartment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>A major benefit is expected in the younger patients (S3B and S4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The recent identification of a new RANKL-dependent ARO patient (S7) suggests that, while this subtype of the disease has been considered extremely rare, its frequency might be higher than expected: in fact, other patients, transplanted in the nineties before the characterization of the genetic basis of human osteopetrosis, might carry mutations in the RANKL gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>If they are still alive, they could be candidate to this new therapy, too. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The RANKL cytokine has been a pioneering discovery in the field of osteoimmunology; the elucidation of its signaling pathway has shown the first of the many, and continuously increasing, interconnections between the bone and immune systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>In the last years, a great interest has been deserved to therapies aimed at blocking this pathway and designed for diseases with increased bone resorption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the recognition of direct RANKL involvement in a genetic rare disease can constitute one of the few cases in which the result of a genetic study could also be translated into a replacement therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>It is desirable that efforts from different entities, including research centers, clinics, charities, and biotech industries, might be joined in order to overcome the safety and regulatory issues and ultimately to give these patients not only a hope but a cure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></body><back><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><ack><title>Conflict of Interests</title><p>All authors state that they have no conflict of interests.</p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The authors thank Professor Yongwon Choi for providing them with Rankl +/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>This work was partially supported by PRIN Project [20102M7T8X_003 to A.V.], Telethon Foundation (Grant GGP12178 to C.S.), Giovani Ricercatori from Ministero della Salute [Grant GR-2008-1134625 to C.S.], PRIN Project [200999KRFW-002 to P.V.], and PNR-CNR Aging Program 2012–2014. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>1SimsNAWalshNCIntercellular cross-talk among bone cells: new factors and pathwaysCurrent Osteoporosis Reports201210210911722427140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>2CocciaPFKrivitWCervenkaJSuccessful bone-marrow transplantation for infantile malignant osteopetrosisThe New England Journal of Medicine1980302137017082-s2.0-00188910886986555 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>3GerritsenEJVossenJMFasthABone marrow transplantation for autosomal recessive osteopetrosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>A report from the working party on inborn errors of the european bone marrow transplantation groupJournal of Pediatrics19941256, part 18969027996361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>4DriessenGJAGerritsenEJAFischerALong-term outcome of haematopoietic stem cell transplantation in autosomal recessive osteopetrosis: an EBMT reportBone Marrow Transplantation20033276576632-s2.0-1244428960513130312 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>5MazzolariEForinoCRazzaAPortaFVillaANotarangeloLDA single-center experience in 20 patients with infantile malignant osteopetrosisThe American Journal of Hematology20098484734792-s2.0-6774909344019507210 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>6VillaAGuerriniMMCassaniBPangrazioASobacchiCInfantile malignant, autosomal recessive osteopetrosis: the rich and the poorCalcified Tissue International20098411122-s2.0-5814930829719082854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>7SobacchiCFrattiniAGuerriniMMOsteoclast-poor human osteopetrosis due to mutations in the gene encoding RANKLNature Genetics20073989609622-s2.0-3454752105817632511 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>8RhoJTakamiMChoiYOsteoimmunology: interactions of the immune and skeletal systemsMolecular Cell200417119 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>9TakayanagiHNew developments in osteoimmunologyNature Reviews Rheumatology201281168468923070645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>10HanadaRLeibbrandtAHanadaTCentral control of fever and female body temperature by RANKL/RANKNature200946272725055092-s2.0-7084909681019940926 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>11HanadaRHanadaTSiglVSchramekDPenningerJMRANKL/RANK-beyond bonesJournal of Molecular Medicine20118976476562-s2.0-7995993660621445556 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>12LaceyDLBoyleWJSimonetWSBench to bedside: elucidation of the OPG-RANK-RANKL pathway and the development of denosumabNature Reviews Drug Discovery201211540141922543469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>13AndersonDMMaraskovskyEBillingsleyWLA homologue of the TNF receptor and its ligand enhance T-cell growth and dendritic-cell functionNature199739066561751792-s2.0-00307146059367155 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>14WongBRRhoJArronJTRANCE is a novel ligand of the tumor necrosis factor receptor family that activates c-Jun N-terminal kinase in T cellsThe Journal of Biological Chemistry19972724025190251942-s2.0-144442720439312132 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>15LaceyDLTimmsETanHLOsteoprotegerin ligand is a cytokine that regulates osteoclast differentiation and activationCell19989321651769568710 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>16YasudaHShimaNNakagawaNOsteoclast differentiation factor is a ligand for osteoprotegerin/osteoclastogenesis-inhibitory factor and is identical to TRANCE/RANKLProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America1998957359736022-s2.0-00325842089520411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>17IkedaTKasaiMUtsuyamaMHirokawaKDetermination of three isoforms of the receptor activator of nuclear factor-κB ligand and their differential expression in bone and thymusEndocrinology20011424141914262-s2.0-0035054126 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>18LumLWongBRJosienREvidence for a role of a tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α)-converting enzyme-like protease in shedding of TRANCE, a TNF family member involved in osteoclastogenesis and dendritic cell survivalThe Journal of Biological Chemistry19992741913613136182-s2.0-003353219110224132 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>19HikitaATanakaSEctodomain shedding of receptor activator of NF-κB ligandAdvances in Experimental Medicine and Biology2007602152117966383 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>20HikitaATanakaNYamaneSInvolvement of a disintegrin and metalloproteinase 10 and 17 in shedding of tumor necrosis factor-α Biochemistry and Cell Biology20098748193 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>21LamJNelsonCARossFPTeitelbaumSLFremontDHCrystal structure of the TRANCE/RANKL cytokine reveals determinants of receptor-ligand specificityJournal of Clinical Investigation200110879719792-s2.0-003478460611581298 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>22ItoSWakabayashiKUbukataOHayashiSOkadaFHataTCrystal structure of the extracellular domain of mouse RANK ligand at 2.2-Å resolutionThe Journal of Biological Chemistry20022778663166362-s2.0-003715515711733492 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>23LiuCWalterTSHuangPStructural and functional insights of RANKL-RANK interaction and signalingJournal of Immunology201018412691069192-s2.0-77953623660 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>24TaHMNguyenGTTJinHMStructure-based development of a receptor activator of nuclear factor-κB ligand (RANKL) inhibitor peptide and molecular basis for osteopetrosisProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America20101074720281202862-s2.0-7865055081521059944 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>25LuanXLuQJiangYCrystal structure of human RANKL complexed with its decoy receptor osteoprotegerinJournal of Immunology20121891245252 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>26NelsonCAWarrenJTWangMWTeitelbaumSLFremontDHRANKL employs distinct binding modes to engage RANK and the osteoprotegerin decoy receptorStructure201220111971198223039992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>27KartsogiannisVZhouHHorwoodNJLocalization of RANKL (receptor activator of NFκB ligand) mRNA and protein in skeletal and extraskeletal tissuesBone19992555255342-s2.0-003283685410574572 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>28NakashimaTKobayashiYYamasakiSProtein expression and functional difference of membrane-bound and soluble receptor activator of NF-κB ligand: modulation of the expression by osteotropic factors and cytokinesBiochemical and Biophysical Research Communications200027537687752-s2.0-003461858010973797 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>29O’BrienCAControl of RANKL gene expressionBone20104649119192-s2.0-7795053798919716455 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>30AtkinsGJFindlayDMOsteocyte regulation of bone mineral: a little give and takeOsteoporosis International20122382067207922302104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>31O'BrienCANakashimaTTakayanagiHOsteocyte control of osteoclastogenesisBone201354225826322939943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>32XiongJO'BrienCAOsteocyte RANKL: new insights into the control of bone remodelingJournal of Bone and Mineral Research201227349950522354849 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>33FuQManolagasSCO’BrienCAParathyroid hormone controls receptor activator of NF-κB ligand gene expression via a distant transcriptional enhancerMolecular and Cellular Biology20062617645364682-s2.0-3374779271316914731 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>34GalliCZellaLAFretzJATargeted deletion of a distant transcriptional enhancer of the receptor activator of nuclear factor-κB ligand gene reduces bone remodeling and increases bone massEndocrinology200814911461532-s2.0-3754900642517932217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>35TakahashiNMaedaKIshiharaAUeharaSKobayashiYRegulatory mechanism of osteoclastogenesis by RANKL and Wnt signalsFrontiers in Bioscience2011162130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>36CrockettJCMellisDJScottDIHelfrichMHNew knowledge on critical osteoclast formation and activation pathways from study of rare genetic diseases of osteoclasts: focus on the RANK/RANKL axisOsteoporosis International20112211202-s2.0-78651479733 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>37MellisDJItzsteinCHelfrichMHCrockettJCThe skeleton: a multi-functional complex organ: the role of key signalling pathways in osteoclast differentiation and in bone resorptionJournal of Endocrinology2011211213114321903860 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>38KongYYYoshidaHSarosiIOPGL is a key regulator of osteoclastogenesis, lymphocyte development and lymph-node organogenesisNature199939767173153232-s2.0-00336114679950424 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>39KimNOdgrenPRKimDKMarksSCJr.ChoiYDiverse roles of the tumor necrosis factor family member TRANCE in skeletal physiology revealed by TRANCE deficiency and partial rescue by a lymphocyte-expressed TRANCE transgeneProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America2000972010905109102-s2.0-003471860910984520 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>40OdgrenPRKimNMacKayCAMason-SavasAChoiYMarksSCJr.The role of RANKL (TRANCE/TNFSF11), a tumor necrosis factor family member, in skeletal development: effects of gene knockout and transgenic rescueConnective Tissue Research200344supplement 12642712-s2.0-1224430784412952207 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>41XiongJOnalMJilkaRLWeinsteinRSManolagasSCO'BrienCAMatrix-embedded cells control osteoclast formationNature Medicine2011171012351241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>42NakashimaTHayashiMFukunagaTEvidence for osteocyte regulation of bone homeostasis through RANKL expressionNature Medicine2011171012311234 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>43NakashimaTTakayanagiHNew regulation mechanisms of osteoclast differentiationAnnals of the New York Academy of Sciences20111240E13E1822360322 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>44DouniERinotasVMakrinouEA RANKL G278R mutation causing osteopetrosis identifies a functional amino acid essential for trimer assembly in RANKL and TNFHuman Molecular Genetics201221478479822068587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>45ItonagaISabokbarASunSGTransforming growth factor-β induces osteoclast formation in the absence of RANKLBone200434157642-s2.0-094230065314751563 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>46KimNKadonoYTakamiMOsteoclast differentiation independent of the TRANCE-RANK-TRAF6 axisJournal of Experimental Medicine200520255895952-s2.0-2434443352416147974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>47HemingwayFKashimaTGKnowlesHJAthanasouNAInvestigation of osteoclastogenic signalling of the RANKL substitute LIGHTExperimental Molecular Pathology201394238038523391709 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>48DougallWCGlaccumMCharrierKRANK is essential for osteoclast and lymph node developmentGenes and Development19991318241224242-s2.0-003356834110500098 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>49LiJSarosiIYanXQRANK is the intrinsic hematopoietic cell surface receptor that controls osteoclastogenesis and regulation of bone mass and calcium metabolismProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America2000974156615712-s2.0-1294426242310677500 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>50KapurRPYaoZIidaMHKMalignant autosomal recessive osteopetrosis caused by spontaneous mutation of murine RankJournal of Bone and Mineral Research20041910168916972-s2.0-2164446944715355564 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>51GoesslCKatzLDougallWCThe development of denosumab for the treatment of diseases of bone loss and cancer-induced bone destructionAnnals of the New York Academy Science201212632940 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>52ChungPYvan HulWPaget's disease of bone: evidence for complex pathogenetic interactionsSeminars in Arthritis and Rheumatism201241561964121959292 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>53KimDMebiusREMacMickingJDRegulation of peripheral lymph node genesis by the tumor necrosis factor family member TRANCEJournal of Experimental Medicine200019210146714782-s2.0-003469409011085748 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>54Lo IaconoNBlairHCPolianiPLOsteopetrosis rescue upon RANKL administration to Rankl(-/-) mice: a new therapy for human RANKL-dependent AROJournal of Bone and Mineral Research201227122501251022836362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>55RossiSWKimMYLeibbrandtARANK signals from CD4+3- inducer cells regulate development of Aire-expressing epithelial cells in the thymic medullaJournal of Experimental Medicine20072046126712722-s2.0-3425033645417502664 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>56AkiyamaTShimoYYanaiHThe tumor necrosis factor family receptors RANK and CD40 cooperatively establish the thymic medullary microenvironment and self-toleranceImmunity20082934234372-s2.0-5134911124318799149 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>57HikosakaYNittaTOhigashiIThe cytokine RANKL produced by positively selected thymocytes fosters medullary thymic epithelial cells that express autoimmune regulatorImmunity20082934384502-s2.0-5134909289318799150 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>58DesantiGECowanJEBaikSDevelopmentally regulated availability of RANKL and CD40 ligand reveals distinct mechanisms of fetal and adult cross-talk in the thymus medullaJournal of Immunology20121891255195526 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>59LoserKMehlingALoeserSEpidermal RANKL controls regulatory T-cell numbers via activation of dendritic cellsNature Medicine20061212137213792-s2.0-33845543666 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>60KnoopKAKumarNButlerBRRANKL is necessary and sufficient to initiate development of antigen-sampling M cells in the intestinal epitheliumJournal of Immunology20091839573857472-s2.0-77950491661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B61"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>61KnoopKAButlerBRKumarNNewberryRDWilliamsIRDistinct developmental requirements for isolated lymphoid follicle formation in the small and large intestine: RANKL is essential only in the small intestineThe American Journal of Pathology201117941861187121854748 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B62"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>62KikutaJWadaYKowadaTDynamic visualization of RANKL and Th17-mediated osteoclast functionJournal of Clinical Investigations20131232866873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B63"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>63ChanACCarterPJTherapeutic antibodies for autoimmunity and inflammationNature Reviews Immunology2012105301316 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B64"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>64HanXKawaiTEastcottJWTaubmanMABacterial-responsive B lymphocytes induce periodontal bone resorptionJournal of Immunology200617616256312-s2.0-29644446802 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B65"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>65HanXLinXSeligerAREastcottJKawaiTTaubmanMAExpression of receptor activator of nuclear factor-κB ligand by B cells in response to oral bacteriaOral Microbiology and Immunology20092431901962-s2.0-6744913794319416447 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B66"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>66OnalMXiongJChenXRANKL expression by B lymphocytes contributes to ovariectomy-induced bone lossThe Journal of Biological Chemistry201228735298512986022782898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B67"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>67LeibbrandtAPenningerJMRANK/RANKL: regulators of immune responses and bone physiologyAnnals of the New York Academy of Sciences200811431231502-s2.0-5654909857519076348 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B68"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>68BurgessTLQianYXKaufmanSThe ligand for osteoprotegerin (OPGL) directly activates mature osteoclastsJournal of Cell Biology199914535275382-s2.0-003351922110225954 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B69"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>69LaceyDLTanHLLuJOsteoprotegerin ligand modulates murine osteoclast survival in vitro and in vivoThe American Journal of Pathology2000157243544810934148 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B70"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>70LloydSAJYuanYYKostenuikPJSoluble RANKL induces high bone turnover and decreases bone volume, density, and strength in miceCalcified Tissue International20088253613722-s2.0-4584911795618465074 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B71"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>71YuanYYKostenuikPJOminskyMSSkeletal deterioration induced by RANKL infusion: a model for high-turnover bone diseaseOsteoporosis International20081956256352-s2.0-4314909580018038244 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B72"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>72TomimoriYMoriKKoideMEvaluation of pharmaceuticals with a novel 50-hour animal model of bone lossJournal of Bone and Mineral Research2009247119412052-s2.0-7034911696719257825 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>X-rays of patient S7 at the last followup showing right scoliotic deviation of the dorsal spine, knee valgus, and deviation of the tibia with multiple fractures of the tibia and fibula. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CDI2013-412768.001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Preclinical studies in Rankl −/− mice. Rankl −/− mice were injected with either 1 mg/kg RANKL (below) or PBS (above) every 48 hours starting within the first week of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Mice were sacrificed after 1 month (P30) or after 3 months (P90). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Periodic acid-Schiff staining (bone in pink, cartilage in violet) of femur sections showed in RANKL-treated mice rescue of the bone defect at P30 and pathological reduction of the bone content at P90, clearly indicating overtreatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Scale bar: 200 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CDI2013-412768.002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Molecular findings in RANKL-dependent ARO patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Patient </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Genomic changea </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>cDNA changeb </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Protein change/effectc </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>S1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>g.38250_38253delAGCT g.38250_38253delAGCT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>c.532+4_532+8delAGCTc.532+4_532+8delAGCT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>r.434_532del r.434_532del </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>S2A and S2B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>g.43825T&gt;A g.43825T&gt;A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>c.596T&gt;A c.596T&gt;A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>p.Met199Lys p.Met199Lys </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>S3A and S3B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>g.44057_44058delCG g.44057_44058delCG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>c.828_829delCG c.828_829delCG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>p.Val277TrpfsX5 p.Val277TrpfsX5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>S4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>g.43825T&gt;A g.43825T&gt;A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>c.596T&gt;A c.596T&gt;A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>p.Met199Lys p.Met199Lys </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>S5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>g.43825T&gt;A g.43825T&gt;A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>c.596T&gt;A c.596T&gt;A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>p.Met199Lys p.Met199Lys </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>S6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>g.43825T&gt;A g.43825T&gt;A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>c.596T&gt;A c.596T&gt;A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>p.Met199Lys p.Met199Lys </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>S7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>g.43896C&gt;T g.43896C&gt;T </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>c.667C&gt;T c.667C&gt;T </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>p.Arg223X p.Arg223X </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>
<sup>a</sup>Accession number genomic sequence of the <italic>RANKL</italic> gene: NG_008990.1. </p></fn><fn><p>
<sup>
b</sup>Accession number of the <italic>RANKL</italic> transcript variant 1: NM_003701.3; the numbering used starts with nucleotide +1 for the A of the ATG-translation initiation codon. </p></fn><fn><p>
<sup>
c</sup>Accession number of the RANKL protein isoform 1: NP_003692.1.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
