<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gbe</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">gbe</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Genome Biology and Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1759-6653</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3814192</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24048281</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evt134</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">evt134</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>In Silico Ionomics Segregates Parasitic from Free-Living Eukaryotes </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Greganova</surname><given-names>Eva</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evt134-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evt134-AFF2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Steinmann</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evt134-AFF3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mäser</surname><given-names>Pascal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evt134-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evt134-AFF2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="evt134-COR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fankhauser</surname><given-names>Niklaus</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evt134-AFF4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="evt134-AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Swiss Tropical and Public Health Institute, Basel, Switzerland</aff><aff id="evt134-AFF2"><sup>2</sup>University of Basel, Switzerland</aff><aff id="evt134-AFF3"><sup>3</sup>Institute of Biochemistry and Molecular Medicine, University of Bern, Switzerland</aff><aff id="evt134-AFF4"><sup>4</sup>Institute of Cell Biology, ETH Zurich, Zürich, Switzerland</aff><author-notes><corresp id="evt134-COR1">*Corresponding author: E-mail: <email>pascal.maeser@unibas.ch</email>.</corresp><fn><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Associate editor: Geoff McFadden </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>10</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1902</fpage><lpage>1909</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Ion transporters are fundamental to life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Due to their ancient origin and conservation in sequence, ion transporters are also particularly well suited for comparative genomics of distantly related species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Here, we perform genome-wide ion transporter profiling as a basis for comparative genomics of eukaryotes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>From a given predicted proteome, we identify all bona fide ion channels, ion porters, and ion pumps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Concentrating on unicellular eukaryotes (n = 37), we demonstrate that clustering of species according to their repertoire of ion transporters segregates obligate endoparasites (n = 23) on the one hand, from free-living species and facultative parasites (n = 14) on the other hand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>This surprising finding indicates strong convergent evolution of the parasites regarding the acquisition and homeostasis of inorganic ions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Random forest classification identifies transporters of ammonia, plus transporters of iron and other transition metals, as the most informative for distinguishing the obligate parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Thus, in silico ionomics further underscores the importance of iron in infection biology and suggests access to host sources of nitrogen and transition metals to be selective forces in the evolution of parasitism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>This finding is in agreement with the phenomenon of iron withholding as a primordial antimicrobial strategy of infected mammals. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>parasite genomics</kwd><kwd>convergent evolution</kwd><kwd>ion homeostasis</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Inorganic ions are essential to life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>All cells maintain transmembrane gradients of potassium (K+), sodium (Na+), calcium (Ca2+), and chloride ions (Cl−), and the resulting membrane potential allows electrical signal transduction and drives nutrient uptake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Other ions such as iron (Fe2+), magnesium (Mg2+), copper (Cu2+), and zinc (Zn2+) are important nutrients themselves, functioning as cofactors for metalloproteins and stabilizers of large organic molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Polyatomic ions such as sulfate (), nitrate (), phosphate (), or ammonium () may serve as inorganic sources of macronutrients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The majority of essential micronutrients are ions too, for example, cobalt (Co2+), manganese (Mn2+), iodine (I−), and molybdenum (). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>As many of these ions are harmful at higher concentrations, ion homeostasis is fundamental for cell function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The importance of ion homeostasis is also illustrated by the large number of natural toxins that perturb it, by forming ion-conducting pores into phospholipid bilayers or by interfering with the function of ion transporters. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The term “ionomics” was coined for high-throughput measurements of inorganic nutrients (the ionome) in cells and tissues, usually by atomic emission spectroscopy (Salt et al. 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Ionomics quantifies the elemental composition and applied to the screening of reverse genetic mutants, it provided insights into the molecular mechanisms of ion homeostasis in Saccharomyces cerevisiae (Eide et al. 2005) and Arabidopsis thaliana (Baxter et al. 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Ionomics combined with forward genetics was used to study natural variation of ion concentrations in plants (Buescher et al. 2010) and mice (Fleet et al. 2011) and their potential association with metabolic disorders in humans (Sun et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In particular, ionomics has further highlighted the role of ion transporters as the key players in ion homeostasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Ionomics enabling the identification and characterization of transporters (Rus et al. 2006; Ciavardelli et al. 2010; Lowry et al. 2012), we reasoned that the genome-wide profiling of ion transporters would in turn permit to draw conclusions about the physiology of the ionomes of different organisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The TC system for Transporter Classification (Saier et al. 2006, 2009) recognizes three different classes of ion transporters: ion channels, ion porters (uniporters, symporters, and antiporters), and ion pumps (ATPases). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Here, we construct profiles for all known families of ion transporters and use these profiles for “in silico ionomics,” aiming to elucidate convergence as well as divergence in the evolution of the molecular mechanisms of ion homeostasis in eukaryotes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Proteome Files and CEGMA Completeness </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Predicted proteomes were obtained from UniProt (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.uniprot.org">www.uniprot.org</ext-link>, last accessed October 1, 2013) and Integr8 (<ext-link ext-link-type="ftp" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.ebi.ac.uk/pub/databases/integr8/">ftp://ftp.ebi.ac.uk/pub/databases/integr8/</ext-link>, last accessed October 1, 2013) and tested for completeness as follows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Profiles were downloaded from the CEGMA database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://korflab.ucdavis.edu/Datasets/cegma/">http://korflab.ucdavis.edu/Datasets/cegma/</ext-link>, last accessed October 1, 2013) and the full set of 458 core eukaryotic proteins (Parra et al. 2007) was run with hmmscan of the HMMer 3.0 package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hmmer.janelia.org">http://hmmer.janelia.org</ext-link>, last accessed October 1, 2013) against a diverse set of eukaryote reference proteomes: Caenorhabditis elegans, Chlamydomonas reinhardtii, Dictyostelium discoideum, Drosophila melanogaster, Danio rerio, Encephalitozoon cuniculi, Entamoeba histolytica, Giardia lamblia, Homo sapiens, Kluyveromyces lactis, Leishmania major, Mus musculus, Plasmodium falciparum, S. cerevisiae, Schizosaccharomyces pombe, Trypanosoma brucei, T. cruzi, Theileria parva, and Trichomonas vaginalis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The 100 best-scoring profiles returned hits of expectancy (E) values ≤10−50 against all the reference proteomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>These 100 profiles were then used to assess the completeness of additional proteomes (Ascaris suum, A. thaliana, Brugia malayi, Candida albicans, Cryptosporidium hominis, C. muris, C. parvum, Cryptococcus neoformans, Coccmyxa subellipsoidea, Chlorella variabilis, Leishmania braziliensis, L. infantum, L. mexicana, Magnaporthe grisea, Meloidogyne hapla, Micromonas pusilla, Ostreococcus lucimarinus, Oryza sativa, Plasmodium berghei, P. chabaudi, P. knowlesi, P. vivax, P. yoelii, Pediculus humanus, Polysphondylium pallidum, Paramecium tetraurelia, Schistosoma japonicum, Theileria annulata, Trypanosoma congolense, T. vivax, Toxoplasma gondii, Trichinella spiralis, Tetrahymena thermophila), which were only included if they contained a hit for at least 99 of the 100 profiles at a cutoff of E ≤ 10−30. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Ion Transporter Reference Sets and Redundancy Reduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Lists of known families of channels (TC 1.A, n = 37), porters (TC 2.A, n = 96), and pumps (TC 3.A, n = 51) were obtained from TCDB (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tcdb.org">http://www.tcdb.org</ext-link>, last accessed October 1, 2013), and all ion transporter families (n = 78) were sorted out by hand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>In case of overlap with parental terms (superfamilies), only the nonredundant children (families) were kept (n = 75; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>For each ion transporter family, all the amino acid sequences that had been annotated with the corresponding TCDB accession in the manually curated section of UniProt were retrieved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Each of these sequence sets was redundancy-reduced as follows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>A Smith–Waterman local alignment (Smith and Waterman 1981) was performed for all pairs of sequences, and if the resulting score reached 75% or more of the score of the self-alignment of the shorter sequence (i.e., the maximally attainable alignment score), the shorter sequence was removed from the set. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Ion Transportome HMM Library </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Before converting the redundancy-reduced sets of ion transporter reference sequences into profiles, predicted ankyrin repeats and cyclic nucleotide binding domains were removed from the sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>These domains were identified with hmmsearch of the HMMer 3.0 package using the profiles Ank (PF00023) and cNMP_binding (PF00027) from Pfam (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pfam.sanger.ac.uk/">http://pfam.sanger.ac.uk/</ext-link>, last accessed October 1, 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The parts matching these profiles with E &lt; 10−8 were replaced with letters X in each sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Then, a ClustalW multiple alignment (Thompson et al. 1994) was performed for each sequence set and converted into a position-dependent scoring matrix with hmmbuild. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The resulting profiles were concatenated to a HMM library for ion transporters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Negative control libraries were constructed by randomly selecting sets of 61 entries from the Pfam-A database (version 26.0: 13,672 entries). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>All the steps as outlined in figure 1 were carried out with self-made Perl scripts. Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>1.—Overview on the in silico approach for ionomics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Screening and Clustering of Proteomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The above profile libraries were used to screen predicted proteomes with hmmscan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>When counting the number of hits per profile (fig. 2), every protein in a given proteome was allowed to score only once, that is, with the profile against which it had the highest score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>A cutoff E-value of &lt;10−10 was used to call a hit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>For clustering (fig. 4), a 65-tuple vector was constructed for each proteome which consisted of the respective best scores to each profile. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Hierarchical clustering of these vectors was performed with the R library (R Core Team 2013) Pvclust which implements multiscale bootstrap resampling (n = 10,000) to estimate “approximately unbiased” (au) errors, where P = (100 − au)/100 (Suzuki and Shimodaira 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Distance metric (Canberra) and clustering algorithm (McQuitty) were chosen as to maximize the number of species in significant clusters (au ≥ 95). Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>2.—Predicted ion transporters in eukaryotes as percentage of the total proteome (A) or in absolute numbers (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The data are in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">supplementary table S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Random Forests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Decision tree classification was performed using the randomForest (Liaw and Wiener 2002) package for the R statistical language (R Core Team 2013), which implements an ensemble learning method developed by Breiman (2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>A random forest consisting of 5,000 trees was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>At each node of the decision trees, the classification quality before and after splitting the set was quantified by using the Gini coefficient as a measure increasing proportionally to higher inequality of the predictions (i.e., parasite) in a set. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>A Profile Library for All Known Ion Transporters </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The TCDB transporter database contains more than 600 different families of transmembrane channels, pores, and porters (Saier et al. 2006, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>We concentrated on transporters which solely have inorganic ions for substrates; ion-dependent porters of organic nutrients (e.g., the Na+-coupled glucose transporter) were excluded from the present analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>A total of 75 nonredundant ion transporter families were identified, which subdivided as follows: 35 different kinds of ion channels; 30 ion anti-, sym-, or uniporters; and 10 ATP-dependent ion pumps (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>We then constructed for each ion transporter family a position-dependent scoring profile as outlined in figure 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Reference protein sequences had been obtained from the manually curated section of the UniProt database (Magrane 2011) and had been redundancy-reduced based on all pairwise alignments (Smith and Waterman 1981). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Redundancy reduction minimized bias of the set of reference sequences while preserving diversity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>It turned out to be necessary to purge the reference sequences from cyclic nucleotide-binding sites (Shabb and Corbin 1992) and ankyrin repeats (Li et al. 2006) before making the profiles as otherwise, these promiscuous domains returned hundreds of false-positive hits that bore no resemblance to ion channels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The resultant 75 profiles were concatenated to a HMM library (Eddy 2009) for ion transporters which is available from the authors on request. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Genome-Wide Prediction of Ion Transporters </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The ion transportome profile library was used to scan predicted proteomes from fully sequenced genomes of the different eukaryote kingdoms, that is, the opisthokonts (fungi, animals), archaeplastida (plants, algae), excavates (kinetoplastids, trichomonas, giardia), chromalveolates (apicomplexa, one ciliate), and amoebozoa (entamoeba, slime molds); rhizaria are still missing from the list of sequenced genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Only proteomes of a CEGMA completeness ≥99% were included (fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The aim was to identify all the different ion transporters from a given species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The numbers of predicted ion transporters per proteome varied greatly between the different species, from more than 500 in C. elegans or A. thaliana to less than 30 in The. parva and E. cuniculi (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">supplementary table S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Plants and metazoa generally possessed more ion transporters than unicellular eukaryotes (P &lt; 0.0001, two-tailed Mann–Whitney U test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>This held true also when the numbers of ion transporters were normalized by proteome size: Multicellular species devoted a 2-fold greater portion of their proteomes to ion transporters than unicellular organisms (2.14% vs. 1.06%; P &lt; 0.0001, two-tailed Mann–Whitney U test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The fraction of multispanning transmembrane proteins, that is, proteins predicted by Phobius (Käll et al. 2004) to contain two or more transmembrane domains, was the same in both groups (13.1% vs. 12.8%; fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Overall, the difference between multicellular and unicellular eukaryotes was most pronounced regarding the predicted numbers of ion channels (fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>A striking exception was Par. tetraurelia which, with 443 predicted ion channels, possessed the largest number of different ion channel subunits of all the analyzed eukaryotes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>This is in agreement with previous reports (Haynes et al. 2003). Paramecium tetraurelia was followed by C. elegans (372 predicted ion channels) and Dan. rerio (337 predicted ion channels; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">supplementary table S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Comparing the predicted numbers of hits per proteome also indicated that free-living or facultative parasitic eukaryotes possess more individual ion transporters than obligate endoparasites (fig. 2B and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">supplementary table S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>To further investigate this phenomenon, we concentrated on unicellular eukaryotes only (to exclude the strong effect arising from the differences between multi- and unicellularity; fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Clustering Proteomes According to Ionomic Landscape </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The numbers of predicted transporters per proteome being a somewhat crude and arbitrary measure, we used the achieved scores against the ion transporter profiles as a refined and unbiased parameter of a given proteome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Thus, an “ionomic landscape” vector was built for every proteome, consisting of the top scores against the ion transporter profiles of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online. Figure 3 depicts these vectors as a heat map where darker shades represent higher scores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The data are shown in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">supplementary table S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online (only 65 different ion transporter profiles were used as 10 appeared to be prokaryote-specific and did not return a hit in any of the analyzed eukaryotes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Although the different unicellular eukaryotes analyzed achieved similar top scores toward the known families of ion pumps (fig. 3, right), the situation was different regarding ion channels and ion porters, which appeared to be generally underrepresented in obligate endoparasites as compared with free-living species or facultative parasites (fig. 3, left and middle). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Parasites such as Cryptosporidia, Microsporidia, or Theileria appeared to be devoid of bona fide cation channels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The ionomic landscape vectors were hierarchically clustered in an unbiased way: A selection of distance metrics and clustering algorithms were combined with the program pvclust, and the resulting trees were ranked based on the number of leaves in statistically significant clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The best scoring tree is shown in figure 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Its topology deviates from a phylogenetic tree in several aspects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The microsporidian E. cuniculi does not cluster with the fungi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The free-living amoebozoa D. discoideum and P. pallidum do, whereas Ent. histolytica groups with Tri. vaginalis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The ciliate Par. tetraurelia clusters with the free-living green algae rather than with alveolates (which are all parasitic), and the trypanosomatids are sister to Toxoplasma and the malaria parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Strikingly, the first and main division of the ionomic tree of unicellular eukaryotes is into eukaryotes with free-living life stages on one side and obligate endoparasites on the other. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>This separation was statistically significant as the probability of splitting the 37 analyzed species by chance into the 23 obligate parasites and 14 facultative parasites or free-living species equals (23! × 14! × 2)/37! = 3.3 × 10−10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>In addition, we carried out the same procedure of representing and clustering HMMer hits based on sets of 65 randomly chosen profiles from the Pfam database of protein families (Punta et al. 2011); a separation of parasites from free-living species never occurred (data not shown). Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>3.—Ion transporter repertoires of unicellular eukaryotes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The heatmap represents the best HMMer scores achieved by the different proteomes (rows) against the profiles for the different families of ion transporters (columns). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Profiles that did not return a hit of score &gt;20 in any of the proteomes are not shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The data are in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">supplementary table S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online. Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>4.—Hierarchical clustering of ionomic landscapes segregates obligate parasites from eukaryotes with free-living life stages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The tree was produced with pvclust using Canberra distance and McQuitty’s similarity analysis. au are shown in gray, where P = (100 − au)/100. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Convergent Evolution of Parasites </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>We concluded that the topology of the tree in figure 4 reflects convergent evolution between obligate endoparasitic eukaryotes, in particular loss of ion channel and ion porter genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>To elucidate which of the ion transporter families contribute the strongest signal for the observed distinction of the parasites, we performed a random forest classification after having assigned to each species an attribute parasite or nonparasite, the latter also comprising facultative parasitic species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The same input vectors were used as for hierarchical clustering (fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The random forest method generated training and validation sets by random resampling of the input vectors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>A total of 5,000 trees were used to determine the impact of each ion transporter family on prediction accuracy regarding parasite status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Gini coefficients served as a measure for inequality (node impurity) of the predictions. Figure 5 depicts the impact of individual transporter families on the sum of all Gini coefficients in the forest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Five families stood out with a mean Gini decrease &gt;1, namely the high-affinity ammonia transporters (AMT; 1.A.11.2), the natural resistance-associated macrophage proteins (NRAMP; 2.A.55), the BOR1-type boron transporters (2.A.31.3), the ZIP family of zinc–iron permeases (2.A.5), and the heavy metal transporter of the ABC-B superfamily (HMT; 3.A.1.210). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>BOR1 transporters were missing in all obligate endoparasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>ZIP and HMT transporters were present but different, consistently returning lower scores against the respective profiles than the hits from nonparasitic eukaryotes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>AMT transporters were absent except in T. cruzi, and NRAMP transporters only occurred in Plasmodium spp. and Tox. gondii (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">supplementary table S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Note that only the combined information from the various ion transporter families distinguished the parasites. Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>5.—Random forest analysis measuring the effect of each ion transporter family on the ability to distinguish obligate endoparasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The typical substrates of the transporters are indicated on the right. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Ion transporters are well suited for comparative genomics of evolutionary distant species as 1) most of the known ion transporter families are ancient as reflected by their ubiquitous occurrence in bacteria, archaea, and eukaryotes (Ward et al. 2009); and 2) many ion transporters possess conserved pore loops (MacKinnon 1995) that function as substrate selectivity filters and are readily detectable in silico. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, ion homeostasis is vital for all cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Here, we describe a novel approach for comparative genomics and apply it to ion transporters as summarized in figure 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>We have identified 75 nonredundant families of ion transporters from the Transporter Classification Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), 65 of which occur in eukaryotes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">supplementary table S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Having constructed hidden Markov model-based profiles for each family, we scanned predicted high-quality proteomes of various eukaryotes and identified all the bona fide ion channels for each species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Although all types of eukaryotes devote around 12% of their proteome to multispanning transmembrane proteins (fig. 2), there are marked differences in the fractions of ion transporters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>One major division appeared to be between multicellular (i.e., animals and plants) and unicellular eukaryotes, the former devoting larger fractions of their proteomes to ion channels and ion porters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>This can be explained by the expansion of gene families in multicellular but not in unicellular eukaryotes (Wolf and Koonin 2013), with the notable exception of Paramecium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Another, more interesting division across the eukaryotes appeared to be between obligate parasites and nonparasitic or facultative parasitic species, the obligate parasites possessing fewer individual ion transporters (fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>This may be explained by selective gene loss in the obligate parasites (Wolf and Koonin 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>To further investigate this phenomenon, we concentrated on unicellular eukaryotes, eliminating the dominant effect of multicellularity versus unicellularity (fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The analyzed unicellular endoparasites were highly heterogeneous regarding their phylogeny (fungi, trypanosomatids, apicomplexa, amoebozoa, and excavates) as well as habitat of the life stages (intracellular in compartment, intracellular cytosolic, extracellular). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>However, all the analyzed proteomes were similar in that they exhibited a markedly reduced diversity of ion channels and ion porters, but not ion pumps (fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>There are likely to be unknown families of ion transporters that remain to be discovered, and it is conceivable that such families are overrepresented in the parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>In any case, using the diversity of the presently known families of ion transporters as a basis for hierarchical clustering, it was possible to segregate obligate endoparasites from free-living and facultative parasitic eukaryotes (i.e., species with a free-living life stage). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Such a separation between obligate endoparasitic and free-living species has not been observed in many related analyses performed based on predicted gene products other than ion channels, for example, enzymes of pyrimidine metabolism (Ali et al. 2013), vitamin B (Stoffel et al. 2006), or porphyrin synthesis (Godel et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, the only contender category of proteins that would allow a similar distinction is the enzymes of purine de novo synthesis, a pathway which appears to be missing in all obligate endoparasitic eukaryotes (Hassan and Coombs 1988; de Koning et al. 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The picture presented by the ion transporters (fig. 3) is less clear-cut as no single protein is absent from all obligate endoparasites while present in the free-living eukaryotes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the present approach to in silico ionomics demonstrates that there is convergent evolution among unrelated parasites with respect to ion transporters (fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>By applying random forest classification to the data set, we were able to demonstrate that the most distinctive features of the obligate parasites were the lack of predicted ammonia transporters and transporters of iron or other transition metals (fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>All obligate endoparasites salvage nitrogen-containing nutrients from their hosts such as amino acids, purines, or pyrimidines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>These provide them with an ample source of organic nitrogen, rendering the transporters of inorganic nitrogen redundant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Hence, the independent loss of ammonia transporters as a consequence of a metabolic streamlining in parasites—with the notable exception of T. cruzi, which is the only obligate endoparasite among the unicellular eukaryotes that scores high against the ammonium transporter profile (TC 1.A.11.2; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">supplementary table S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The observed loss of transporters of divalent cations might have a similar explanation as suggested earlier for the ammonium transporter, the parasites accessing iron from their hosts in other form than free Fe2+ or Fe3+. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>African trypanosomes express unique, glycosylphosphatidylinositol-anchored receptors on their surface for mammalian transferrin, a glycoprotein that transports Fe3+ in the blood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The heterodimeric receptor is internalized by endocytosis upon binding of host transferrin (Taylor and Kelly 2010). Trichomonas, Toxoplasma, and Entamoeba also obtain iron from mammalian iron-binding proteins such as lactoferrin, transferrin, or ferritin (Lopez-Soto et al. 2009; Horvathova et al. 2012; Ortiz-Estrada et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Malaria parasites probably cover their iron requirement from ferric heme, the oxidized end product of hemoglobin degradation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Although the majority of heme molecules polymerize to hemozoin in the food vacuole, some escape to the parasite’s cytosol where they may serve as an iron source after degradation (Ginsburg 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>For many other parasites, the pathways of iron salvage remain unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>However, the general importance of iron acquisition for pathogens is illustrated by the phenomenon of iron withholding, a typical defensive response of mammals (Ganz 2009; Weinberg 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The peptide hormone hepcidin functions as a master regulator of iron absorption and distribution in mammals, and its expression is critically determined by infection and inflammation (Drakesmith and Prentice 2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>We conclude that there is strong convergence among obligate endoparasites in the loss of ion transporters (possibly combined with divergence in new strategies for ion uptake) and propose access to organic ammonia and iron to contribute to the selective forces in the evolution of parasitism. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evt134/-/DC1">Supplementary tables S1–S3</ext-link> are available at Genome Biology and Evolution online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gbe.oxfordjournals.org/">http://www.gbe.oxfordjournals.org/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_5_10_1902__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_evt134_clustering.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="supp_evt134_supplement.xlsx"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation (Sinergia grant number CRSII3_127300). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>Literature Cited</title><ref id="evt134-B1"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>AliJAPyrimidine salvage in Trypanosoma brucei bloodstream forms and the trypanocidal action of halogenated pyrimidinesMol Pharmacol.20138343945323188714 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B2"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>BaxterIPurdue ionomics information management system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>An integrated functional genomics platformPlant Physiol.200714360061117189337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B3"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>BreimanLManual for setting up, using, and understanding2003Random Forest v4.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>[cited 2013 Oct 1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/~breiman/Using_random_forests_v4.0.pdf">http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/∼breiman/Using_random_forests_v4.0.pdf</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B4"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>BuescherENatural genetic variation in selected populations of Arabidopsis thaliana is associated with ionomic differencesPLoS One20105e1108120559418 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B5"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>CiavardelliDPhenotypic profile linked to inhibition of the major Zn influx system in Salmonella enterica: proteomics and ionomics investigationsMol Biosyst.2010760861920959928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B6"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>de KoningHPBridgesDJBurchmoreRJPurine and pyrimidine transport in pathogenic protozoa: from biology to therapyFEMS Microbiol Rev.200529987102016040150 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B7"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>DrakesmithHPrenticeAMHepcidin and the iron-infection axisScience201233876877223139325 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B8"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>EddySRA new generation of homology search tools based on probabilistic inferenceGenome Inform.20092320521120180275 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B9"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>EideDJCharacterization of the yeast ionome: a genome-wide analysis of nutrient mineral and trace element homeostasis in Saccharomyces cerevisiaeGenome Biol.20056R7716168084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B10"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>FleetJCReplogleRSaltDESystems genetics of mineral metabolismJ Nutr.201114152052521270371 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B11"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>GanzTIron in innate immunity: starve the invadersCurr Opin Immunol.200921636719231148 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B12"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>GinsburgHIron acquisition by Plasmodium sppParasitol Today19991546610511692 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B13"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>GodelCThe genome of the heartworm, Dirofilaria immitis, reveals drug and vaccine targetsFASEB J.2012264650466122889830 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B14"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>HassanHFCoombsGHPurine and pyrimidine metabolism in parasitic protozoaFEMS Microbiol Rev.1988447833078769 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B15"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>HaynesWJLingKYSaimiYKungCPak paradox: paramecium appears to have more K(+)-channel genes than humansEukaryot Cell.2003273774512912893 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B16"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>HorvathovaLTranscriptomic identification of iron-regulated and iron-independent gene copies within the heavily duplicated Trichomonas vaginalis genomeGenome Biol Evol.201241017102922975721 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B17"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>KällLKroghASonnhammerELA combined transmembrane topology and signal peptide prediction methodJ Mol Biol.20043381027103615111065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B18"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>LiJMahajanATsaiMDAnkyrin repeat: a unique motif mediating protein-protein interactionsBiochemistry200645151681517817176038 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B19"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>LiawAWienerMClassification and regression by random forestR News200221822 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B20"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Lopez-SotoFEntamoeba histolytica uses ferritin as an iron source and internalises this protein by means of clathrin-coated vesiclesInt J Parasitol.20093941742618848948 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B21"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>LowryDBMapping of ionomic traits in Mimulus guttatus reveals mo and cd qtls that colocalize with mot1 homologuesPLoS One20127e3073022292026 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B22"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>MacKinnonRPore loops: an emerging theme in ion channel structureNeuron1995148898927538310 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B23"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>MagraneMUniProt ConsortiumUniprot knowledgebase: a hub of integrated protein dataDatabase (Oxford)20112011bar00921447597 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B24"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Ortiz-EstradaGIron-saturated lactoferrin and pathogenic protozoa: could this protein be an iron source for their parasitic style of life?Future Microbiol.2012714916422191452 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B25"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>ParraGBradnamKKorfICEGMA: a pipeline to accurately annotate core genes in eukaryotic genomesBioinformatics2007231061106717332020 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B26"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>PuntaMThe pfam protein families databaseNucleic Acids Res.201140D290D30122127870 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B27"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>R Core TeamR: a language and environment for statistical computing2013Vienna (Austria)R Foundation for Statistical Computing </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B28"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>RusANatural variants of AtHKT1 enhance Na+ accumulation in two wild populations of arabidopsisPLoS Genet.20062e21017140289 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B29"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>SaierMHJrTranCVBaraboteRDTCDB: the transporter classification database for membrane transport protein analyses and informationNucleic Acids Res.200634D181D18616381841 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B30"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>SaierMHJrYenMRNotoKTamangDGElkanCThe transporter classification database: recent advancesNucleic Acids Res.200937D274D27819022853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B31"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>SaltDEBaxterILahnerBIonomics and the study of the plant ionomeAnnu Rev Plant Biol.20085970973318251712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B32"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>ShabbJBCorbinJDCyclic nucleotide-binding domains in proteins having diverse functionsJ Biol Chem.1992267572357261313416 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B33"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>SmithTFWatermanMSIdentification of common molecular subsequencesJ Mol Biol.19811471951977265238 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B34"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>StoffelSABiosynthesis and uptake of thiamine (vitamin B1) in bloodstream form Trypanosoma brucei brucei and interference of the vitamin with melarsen oxide activityInt J Parasitol.20063622923616375907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B35"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>SunLAssociations between ionomic profile and metabolic abnormalities in human populationPLoS One20127e3884522719963 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B36"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>SuzukiRShimodairaHPvclust: an R package for assessing the uncertainty in hierarchical clusteringBioinformatics2006221540154216595560 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B37"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>TaylorMCKellyJMIron metabolism in trypanosomatids, and its crucial role in infectionParasitology201013789991720152063 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B38"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>ThompsonJDHigginsDGGibsonTJClustal W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choiceNucleic Acids Res.199422467346807984417 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B39"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>WardJMMäserPSchroederJIPlant ion channels: gene families, physiology, and functional genomics analysesAnnu Rev Physiol.200971598218842100 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B40"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>WeinbergEDIron availability and infectionBiochim Biophys Acta.2009179060060518675317 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="evt134-B41"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>WolfYIKooninEVGenome reduction as the dominant mode of evolutionBioessays20133582983723801028 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
