<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Neurotherapeutics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Neurotherapeutics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Neurotherapeutics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1933-7213</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1878-7479</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3210356</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22002087</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">76</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13311-011-0076-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Cellular Treatments for Spinal Cord Injury: The Time is Right for Clinical Trials </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Fehlings</surname><given-names>Michael G.</given-names></name><address><email>Michael.Fehlings@uhn.on.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vawda</surname><given-names>Reaz</given-names></name><address><email>reaz.vawda@uhnresearch.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.417188.3</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000100124167</institution-id><institution/><institution>University Health Network, Toronto Western Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Toronto, ON M5T 2S8 Canada </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>704</fpage><lpage>720</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>More than 1 million people in the United States live with a spinal cord injury (SCI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Despite medical advances, many patients with SCIs still experience substantial neurological disability, with loss of motor, sensory, and autonomic function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Cell therapy is ideally suited to address the multifactorial nature of the secondary events following SCI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Remarkable advances in our understanding of the pathophysiology of SCI, structural and functional magnetic resonance imaging, image-guided micro-neurosurgical techniques, and transplantable cell biology have enabled the use of cell-based regenerative techniques in the clinic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>It is important to note that there are more than a dozen recently completed, ongoing, or recruiting cell therapy clinical trials for SCI that reflect the views of many key stakeholders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The field of regenerative neuroscience has reached a stage in which the clinical trials are scientifically and ethically justified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Although experimental models and analysis methods and techniques continue to evolve, no model will completely replicate the human condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>It is recognized that more work with cervical models of contusive/compressive SCI are required in parallel with clinical trials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>It is also important that the clinical translation of advances made through well-established and validated experimental approaches in animal models move forward to meet the compelling needs of individuals with SCI and to advance the field of regenerative neuroscience. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>However, it is imperative that such efforts at translation be done in the most rigorous and informed fashion to determine safety and possible efficacy, and to provide key information to clinicians and basic scientists, which will allow improvements in regenerative techniques and the validation and refinement of existing preclinical animal models and research approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The field of regenerative neuroscience should not be stalled at the animal model stage, but instead the clinical trials need to be focused, safe, and ethical, backed up by a robust, translationally relevant preclinical research strategy. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s13311-011-0076-7) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Spinal cord injury</kwd><kwd>Neural progenitor</kwd><kwd>Mesenchymal stem cell</kwd><kwd>Bone marrow</kwd><kwd>Clinical trial</kwd><kwd>Cell transplantation</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The American Society for Experimental NeuroTherapeutics, Inc. 2011</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Spinal Cord Injury </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Spinal cord injury (SCI), which results from sudden or sustained trauma or progressive neurodegeneration, is a devastating condition whereby sufferers experience significant functional and sensory deficits, as well as emotional, social, and financial burdens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>They also have an increased risk of cardiovascular complications, deep vein thrombosis, osteoporosis, pressure ulcers, autonomic dysreflexia, and neuropathic pain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The estimated annual global incidence of SCI is 15 to 40 cases per million. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In the United States (U.S.), approximately 1.275 million individuals are affected, with more than 12,000 new cases each year [1–3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Despite advances in pre-hospital care, medical and surgical management, and rehabilitation approaches, many SCI sufferers still experience substantial neurological disability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Intensive efforts are underway to develop effective neuroprotective and neuroregenerative strategies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Given the debilitating consequences of SCI, and the significant advances in micro-neurosurgical techniques, image-guided surgery coupled with major progress in our understanding of the biology of cell-based therapeutic strategies for central nervous system (CNS) repair and regeneration through the large number of pre-clinical studies, as well as past clinical trials, we argue that the timing is optimal to commence and extend clinical trial investigations of cellular transplants for SCI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>While it is acknowledged that much remains to be learned regarding the biology of transplantable cells, it is only with a balanced investigative approach, combining preclinical research with careful controlled clinical trials, that significant advances can be made in the field [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The significant advances that have been made on the basis of pre-clinical studies carried out in rodent models of SCI have enabled clinical trials demonstrating the safety of cell therapy for SCI to proceed, and have informed researchers of the knowledge gaps that remain to be addressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Given that no experimental model, rodent or otherwise, will completely mimic the human condition, it is an unrealistic hurdle or criterion for all pre-clinical findings to be validated in larger animal models, such as pigs and primates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>This would be financially and practically unfeasible for most laboratories and would place such a lengthy and unnecessary delay on the clinical translation of important developments already made, as to be detrimental to the field. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Indeed, this has been recognized by the U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Food and Drug Administration (FDA) in allowing a clinical trial of embryonic stem cell-derived cells in SCI to proceed on the basis of pre-clinical safety demonstrated exclusively in rodent models (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clinicaltrial.gov">www.clinicaltrial.gov</ext-link>; clinical trial identifier: NCT01217008). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Moreover, it is important to note that rodent contusion/compression models of SCI are generally “incomplete” with partial sparing of motor and sensory functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>These models closely mimic most patients with severe, partial lesions with an American Spinal Injury Association (ASIA) impairment (ASI) scale rating of AIS B or C. Given that most trials of cell therapy have been carried out in AIS A patients (the safest to inject, but also the least likely to show cell therapy-induced benefit), there is a need for future clinical trials to include patients actually modeled in the laboratory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In addition, there is a compelling need for preclinical researchers to develop valid models of compressive/contusive cervical SCI, given that approximately 50 to 60% of human SCIs involve the cervical region [2, 3, 5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Epidemiology: Incidence and Impact on Sufferers and Healthcare </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The estimated annual global incidence of SCI is 15 to 40 cases per million. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In the U.S., approximately 1.275 million individuals are affected, with more than 12,000 new cases each year [1, 6, 7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The most common causes of traumatic SCI are road traffic accidents, falls, occupational mishaps, and sports-related injuries, resulting in contusion and compression of the spinal cord [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Approximately 55% of SCIs occur at the cervical level (C1 to C7-T1) with a mortality of 10% in the first year following injury and an expected lifespan of only 10 to 15 years postinjury, and thoracic (T1 to T11), thoracolumbar (T11-T12 to L1-L2), and lumbosacral (L2 to S5) injuries each account for approximately 15% of SCI [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Depending on the age of the patient, the severity, and the level of SCI, the lifetime cost of healthcare and other injury-related expenses can reach $25 million [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Cell therapy can potentially enhance the quality of life of those affected by SCI, while reducing their financial and practical dependence on other individuals and ultimately on the society as a whole. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Pathophysiology </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>SCIs involve a primary (the physical injury) and a secondary injury (the subsequent cascade of molecular and cellular events that amplify the original injury) [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The primary injury damages both upper and lower motor neurons and disrupts motor, sensory, and autonomic (including cardiac output, vascular tone, and respiration) functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Pathophysiological processes occurring in the secondary injury phase, which are rapidly instigated in response to the primary injury in an attempt to homeostatically control and minimize the damage, are paradoxically, largely responsible for exacerbating the initial damage and creating an inhibitory milieu, which prevents endogenous efforts of repair, regeneration, and remyelination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>These secondary processes include inflammation, ischemia, lipid peroxidation, production of free radicals, disruption of ion channels, axonal demyelination, glial scar formation (astrogliosis), necrosis, and programmed cell death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, endogenous repair and regenerative mechanisms are used during the secondary phase of injury to minimize the extent of the lesion (through astrogliosis), reorganize blood supply through angiogenesis, clear cellular debris, and reunite and remodel damaged neural circuits, and as such offer exploitable targets for therapeutic intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The spatial and temporal dynamics of these secondary mediators (for more detail see Figley et al. [10]) are fundamental to SCI pathophysiology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>A multitude of characteristics of cells tested both pre-clinically and clinically make them ideal for SCI repair and form the basis of the possible mechanisms by which they can promote functional recovery, which are anti-inflammatory, immunomodulatory [11–13], anti-gliotic [14], pro-oligodendrogliogenic [15, 16], pro-neuronogenic [17], pro-axonogenic, and secrete various anti-apoptotic and pro-angiogenic neurotrophic factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Given the pathophysiological targets of SCI [10], transplanted cells should: 1) enable regenerating axons to cross any cysts or cavities, 2) functionally replace dead or damaged cells, and/or 3) create an environment supportive of axonal regeneration and/or myelination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>However, given the multifactorial nature of SCI and its dynamic pathophysiological consequences, the success of future clinical trials of cell therapy will likely depend on the informed co-administration of multiple strategies, including pharmacological and rehabilitation therapies [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Cell Therapy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Cell therapy is particularly well suited to addressing the multifactorial nature of the pathophysiology of secondary SCI, and as such its potential has been a focus in regenerative medicine for many years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Different sources and types of cells, including stem/progenitor cells (embryonic stem cells, neural progenitor cells, bone marrow mesenchymal cells) and non-stem cells (olfactory ensheathing cells [OECs] and Schwann cells) have been, and/or are being tested in clinical trials for SCI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Others are still in the pre-clinical stages of testing [18] (Table 1).Table 1A Comparison of the Different Cell Types and Sources Currently In* Consideration or being Considered for Clinical Trials for SCIWJ/UCMfMPCBMSC*ES*iPSfNPCaNPC*OEC*SC*SKPAdipMPCIsolationPracticalitiesEasyChallengingChallengingChallengingChallengingChallengingChallengingChallengingChallengingLess challengingEasyEthical considerationsNoneSignificantConsiderableSignificantNoneSignificantConsiderableFewConsiderableFewFewDifferentiation potentialBone✓✓✓PluripotentPluripotentNeuralNeural--Peripheral myelin✓Fat✓✓✓✓Cartilage✓✓✓✓StoragePre-isolation✓✕✕✕✕✕✕✕✕✕?Post-isolation✓✓✓✓✓✓✓✓✓✓✓ImmunogenicityLowLowLowLowLowLow?LowLowLowImmunosuppressant/Anti-inflammatory✓✓✓??✓????Tumourigenicity✕✕✕✓✓✕✕✕✕?✕Transfection✓✓✓✓✓✓✓✓✓?Safety/Risk✓✓✓✓?✓✓✓✓?✓Pathotropism✓✓✓??✓????AutologousPotentialNo✓✕Potential✕✕✓✓✓✓adipMPC = Adipose tissue-derived mesenchymal cells; aNPC = Adult neural progenitor cells; BMSC = bone marrow mesenchymal/stromal cell; ES = embryonic stem cells; fMPC = Foetal mesenchymal progenitor cells; fNPC = fetal neural progenitor cells; iPS = induced pluripotent stem cells; OEC = olfactory ensheathing cells; SC = Schwann cells; SCI = spinal cord injury; SKP = skin-derived precursors; WJ/UCM = Wharton’s Jelly cells/umbilical cord matrix cells </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The advantages and disadvantages of each cell source and type being considered or already in clinical trials for SCI have been extensively described and compared elsewhere [10, 19–22], and reflect their potential in the clinic (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>A recent systematic review [23] has highlighted the paucity of data on the transplantation of human cells into the most clinically relevant models of SCI (chronic, cervical) especially in larger-than-rodent animals and nonhuman primates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>However, while the latter would be useful for optimizing surgical and cell delivery parameters and strategies, we argue that is it unreasonable to require that all pre-clinical data be verified in these models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The reason for this is that they do not replicate all the details of the human condition, in addition to being prohibitively costly and unfeasible for many, if not most, laboratories that would contribute substantially to the field through the study of well-established and better characterized rodent models. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>A systematic review of pre-clinical investigations of cell therapies for SCI has recently been conducted by a consensus panel convened by the senior author (MGF) [23–25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Although we acknowledge the urgent need for further investigations using cervical models to reflect the predominance of SCIs at this level, a considerable amount of information can be obtained from an examination of the published literature, especially in thoracic SCI models, particularly with regard to safety, even though the variation in the sources of each cell type, culture conditions, age of donor, and recipient can make comparisons between studies difficult. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Indeed, so far, most patients being enrolled in the phase I safety trials (including the Geron trial on GRNOP1 cells [see below]), have been those who suffered thoracic SCIs with an AIS A rating for locomotor function. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Current Clinical Trials of Cell Therapy for SCI </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>There are currently more than a dozen recently completed, ongoing, or recruiting cell therapy clinical trials for SCI listed on clinicaltrials.gov [26], of which 2 do not involve stem cells per se (a phase I trial of OECs in thoracic AIS A subjects [clinical trial identifier: NCT01231893], and a phase II trial of activated macrophages in cervical and thoracic SCI [clinical trial identifier: NCT00073853], subsequently suspended due to financial constraints experienced by the sponsor). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Most trials are phase I or I/II clinical safety and feasibility studies, indicating that cellular treatments for SCI developed in the laboratory are still in the very early stages of clinical translation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>These trials build on the development of micro-neurosurgical techniques and image-guided approaches that facilitate the safe targeting of the injured CNS with cell-based approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The safety of such techniques is borne out by the experience of the Florida group with fetal cell-based transplantation for SCI associated with syringomyelia in the 1990s [27], and the more recent efforts of MacKay-Sim and St. John [22] with OECs in patients with thoracic SCIs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The following section discusses the different cell types and sources used in past and current clinical trials, and critically evaluates the scientific evidence justifying their use in the clinic. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Bone Marrow Mesenchymal/Stromal Cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Bone marrow mesenchymal/stromal cells (BMSCs) are isolated from the stromal compartment of bone marrow, which also comprises hematopoietic stem cells by virtue of their adherence to tissue culture plastic and/or their expression of distinct cell surface antigenic markers and nonexpression of hematopoietic stem cells markers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>They have anti-inflammatory and immunomodulatory effects, mesodermal differentiation potential, and secrete several neurotrophic factors, making them attractive candidates in CNS cell rescue and as autologous transplanted cellular sources of trophic support for endogenous and co-implanted cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Contrary to recurring claims of their neurogenic differentiation potential in vitro or in vivo, there is no conclusive evidence to support these claims [28]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Most current and recently completed trials involve autologous BMSC transplantation, given the well-established safety record of using these cells as part of bone marrow transplants for leukemia, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, and multiple sclerosis (MS) sufferers (see as follows). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, most studies of BMSCs have been carried out in rats (likely due to practical considerations due to size differences from mice and also due to closer modeling of the clinical situation), which were found to have a beneficial effect of BMSC administration after thoracic SCI, largely as a result of neurotrophic factor secretion [29, 30] and possibly also anti-inflammatory cytokine secretion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Intra-spinal (within or adjacent to the injury site), as well and intrathecal and systemic (intravenous) delivery have been successful in most studies [31–33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Porcine and nonhuman primate studies have been carried out to further support their clinical use [34, 35], and as in rodent studies, found that BMSCs promote a certain degree of axonal regrowth and sprouting, at least in transection models [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>This strongly supports their use in trials of thoracic SCI. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>However, the use of BMSCs in SCI does present certain issues, their migration beyond the injection site (for intra-spinally delivered cells) is limited, and inter-donor variability in efficacy and immunomodulatory potency might be reflected in variable clinical outcome [37], making their evaluation as therapy for SCI difficult. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Studies of BMSCs in cervical contusion-compression models have yet to be carried out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>BMSCs have, in all but 2 studies by the same group, been used in subacute and acute models [38–41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Based on the limited number of pre-clinical studies in chronic models, it is not yet possible to evaluate their efficacy in the latter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>It is also not known whether BMSCs provide functional preservation of axons or de novo axonal regrowth across the lesion site in contusion-compression models, as these are more difficult to distinguish in these models, unlike in transection models [42–46]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Ongoing clinical studies and those carried out to date have enrolled small patient numbers and have used autologous BM-derived cells rather than purified stromal cells (understandable from a practical perspective) [47–50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>A recently published dose escalation trial examined autologous BMSCs in patients with chronic SCI [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Although BMSCs were safe, they were not found to be beneficial in this cohort of patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Having clearly established the safety and feasibility of the clinical use of BM-derived cells specifically for SCI in these trials, and as suggested by Tetzlaff et al. [23] in 2011 (coauthored by MGF) based on the pre-clinical literature, we now urge the immediate testing of BMSCs in properly designed and executed clinical trials using International Campaign for Cures of Spinal Cord Injury Paralysis (ICCP) guidelines in SCI patients carefully selected as the most likely to benefit (acute and subacute thoracic SCI with a rating of AISA A or B on the impairment scale). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>It is worth mentioning the Canadian Bone Marrow Transplant (BMT) clinical trials for MS led by Freedman et al. [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>These have shown that immunomodulation through an intravenous infusion of autologous bone marrow-derived cells can not only reduce, but also halt relapses and halt the formation of new MS lesions, reduce brain atrophy, and overall reduce disease burden [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The inflammatory component of SCI and subsequent demyelination of surviving axons are serious limiting factors in the efficacy of early cell therapy for SCI, as implanted cells are more likely to be eliminated by the host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>It is therefore worth considering interventions to modify the inflammatory milieu to enhance donor cell survival and efficacy, as in the newly initiated clinical trial of autologous BMSCs in children suffering from SCI (Table 2) (clinical trial identifier: NCT01328860). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, and considering the 1 case of neoplasms in a recipient of fetal neural progenitor cells (NPCs) reported by Amariglio et al. [53], the question of whether this strategy may increase the oncogenic risk of cell therapy must be considered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>It is noteworthy that no BMT-related tumors have been reported by the Canadian MS BMT study.Table 2Clinical Trials of Cell Therapy for SCI Listed on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clinicaltrials.gov">www.clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link> StatusStudyNCTCellsAdministration routePhaseCountrySponsor/InvestigatorDurationNumbers enrolledRecruitingTransfer of bone marrow-derived stem cells for the treatment of SCINCT 01162915Autologous BMSCs, expanded ex vivo Intrathecal infusion, single doseI, single centreUSATCA Cellular Therapy, LLC; Gabriel P. LasalaJuly 2010-June 201210CompletedCell transplant in SCI patientsNCT 00816803Autologous bone marrow?I/IIEgyptCairo University, Cancer Institute of New Jersey, UMDNJ/RWJMS; Hatem E. SabaawyMay 2005-Dec 200880Condition: Chronic SCIProcedure: physical therapyRecruitingTransplantation of autologous OECs in complete human SCINCT 01231893Autologous olfactory mucosa ensheathing cells (OECs) and fibroblastsIntra-spinalIPolandWroclaw Medical University; Wlodzimierz Jarmundowicz, Pawel TabakowMay 200810Other: rehabilitationTerminatedTreatment for acute SCINCT 00695149BMSCInto cerebrospinal fluidI/IIJapanTranslational Research Informatics CenterJuly 2005-Mar 201023CompletedAutologous adipose-derived MSCs transplantation in patients with SCINCT 01274975Autologous adipose-derived MSCsIntravenous infusion, 4 × 108 cellsIKoreaRNL Bio Company Ltd, SangHan KimJuly 2009-Feb 20108RecruitingSafety and feasibility of umbilical cord blood cell transplant into injured spinal cord Drug: +/− methylprednisolone drug: +/− lithiumNCT 01046786Umbilical cord blood mononuclear cell, dose comparisonIntra-spinalI/IIChinaChina Spinal Cord Injury NetworkJan 2010-June 201220CompletedSafety and Efficacy of Autologous Bone Marrow Stem Cells in Treating SCI Condition: Acute, subacute and chronic SCI Procedure: laminectomyNCT 01186679Autologous bone marrowIntrathecalI/IIIndiaInternational Stemcell Services Limited, Arvind BhatejaJan 2008-Aug 201012Enrolling by invitationUmbilical cord blood mononuclear cell transplant to treat chronic SCINCT 01354483HLA-matched umbilical cord blood mononuclear cellsI/IIChinaTreating Center of Spinal Cord Injury Chengdu Army Kunming General Hospital (Dr Hui Zhu )Sep 2010-Dec 201220Other : methylprednisolone, sodium succinate or lithium carbonate plus rehabilitationSuspendedAutologous incubated macrophages for patients with complete SCIs condition: Acute SCINCT 00073853Autologous incubated macrophagesIntra-spinalIIUSA, IsraelProneuron Biotechnologies, Marcus FoundationSep 200361B.I.R.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>(Israel-U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Binational Industrial Research and Development); Daniel Lammertse, Nachshon Knoller, Marca Sipski, Edward BenzelRecruitingSafety study of GRNOPC1 in SCINCT 01217008GRNOPC1 (ES cell-derived oligodendrocytic progenitors)Intra-spinal, single dose of 2 million cellsIUSAGeron, Gary K. Steinberg, David Apple, Richard G Fessler, James S Harrop, Shekar KurpadOct2010-Oct 201210Condition: Complete T3-T9 level sub-acute (7–14 days post-injury) SCIRecruitingAutologous stem cells for SCI in childrenNCT 01328860AutologousIntravenous infusionIUSAMemorial Hermann Healthcare System, James E. BaumgartnerApr 2011-Oct 201410Condition: Primary SCI, to minimize secondary SCIBMSCsRecruitingAutologous bone marrow stem cell transplantation in patients with SCINCT 01325103Autologous BMSCIntra-spinalIBrazilHospital Sao Rafael; Ricardo R. dos SantosJuly 2010-Jan 201320RecruitingStudy of human CNS stem cells (HuCNS-SC) in patients with thoracic SCI Condition: subacute thoracic (T2-T11) SCINCT 01321333HuCNS-SC cellsSingle dose, intramedullaryI/IISwitzerlandStemCells, Inc.; Armin CurtMar 2011-Mar 201612Phase I trials are generally small studies to ensure that the new drug or procedure is safe and well tolerated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Phase II trials are to test efficacy in a small group of well defined, treated and control patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Phase III trials are large multi-centre studies to test the efficacy and safety of the treatment in a large number of patients as a prelude to introducing the drug or procedure to clinical practice.BMSCs = bone marrow mesenchymal/stromal cells; CNS = cerebrospinal fluid; ES = embryonic stem cell; HLA = human leukocyte antigen; HuCNS-SC cells = xxxxxxx cells; MSCs = xxxx; NCT = xxxxxx; OECs = olfactory ensheathing cells; SCI = spinal cord injury; </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>OECs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>OECs can be isolated autologously from the nerve fiber layer of the olfactory bulb, as well as the lamina propria of the olfactory epithelium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>They support the constant regeneration of olfactory axons from the PNS (the olfactory mucosa) into the CNS (the olfactory bulb) [54], and, as such, represent cells potentially capable of creating a microenvironment permissive for axonogenesis across the inhibitory lesion site into levels of the spinal cord caudal to the injury site. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>OECs have also been used in a few clinical trials [22, 55, 56] and smaller studies that do not necessarily conform to the strict criteria and protocols of formal clinical trials [ICCP guidelines]), with some measure of success, at least from the safety and feasibility perspective [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>These trials were initiated on the basis of promising results reported in transection SCI models [57–61], which have been variably replicated [62–67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>There are several possible reasons for this, including known differences between sources of OECs [68], differences in culture conditions, and their changing phenotype in prolonged culture [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Studies are ongoing to address these differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, beneficial effects have been reported in 2 separate clinical trials for chronic SCI, admittedly undertaken by the same group [60, 61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Of note, these trials were carried out despite the fact that only 2 studies (by the same group) have examined human olfactory bulb OECs in SCI [70, 71], which tested fetal OECs implanted 1 week postinjury in a rat model of moderate-to-severe thoracic contusion SCI [70] and hemisection SCI [71]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Six weeks after transplantation, cavitation and gliotic scarring were reduced and functional recovery was superior in human OEC-treated rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, OECs alone have not been found to confer functional benefit in subacute or chronic thoracic contusion SCI, but can do so when combined with Schwann cells (SCs) [72–74]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>For balance, clinical trials have been carried out on the basis of a small, but compelling, body of scientific evidence [75, 76] for functional benefit in SCI, even though the patients selected for these trials have not always matched the pre-clinical models used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>At least 2 of these trials [60, 61] have reported functional improvement in small patient cohorts, which may be confirmed by future pre-clinical studies on human OECs of various anatomical derivations to support future clinical trials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The safe use of OECs in clinical trials for other conditions, such as ischemic stroke, further strengthens the case for their use in SCI (clinical trial identifier: NCT01327768). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>NPCs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>NPCs can be generated from embryonic stem (ES) cells (ESCs), which are derived from the inner cell mass of the embryo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The latter have indefinite self-renewal capacity and are pluripotent, with the potential to generate all cell types of the body, making them a potentially limitless source of cells for therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>However, they are not without their problems (Table 1), including and especially the moral dilemmas and the practical constraints of their embryonic derivation, their karyotypic instability with repeated freeze-thaw cycles [77, 78] and their teratogenicity in the host. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Pre-clinical studies have shown that animals transplanted with human ESC-derived oligodendrocytic progenitors (OPCs) show a marked improvement in functional recovery following SCI [79–84]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>After observing such promising pre-clinical data, extensive pre-clinical studies were conducted to characterize the safety and efficacy of these human ESCs exclusively in rodent models [85].1 The Geron trial, which was originally approved by the FDA, but then halted due to concerns of abnormal cyst formation, was reinitiated and approved for phase I clinical trials in the U.S. in October 2010, using human ESC-derived OPCs implanted within 2 weeks into patients with thoracic SCI, after the FDA was satisfied with pre-clinical safety data generated by Geron, but not without considerable objection and controversy [86–88]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In addition to the data from Keirstead’s group (which has not been independently verified), and the unpublished data generated by Geron for the FDA, the initiation of this clinical trial is further supported by behavioral and histological data from studies implanting glial restricted progenitors (GRPs) [89] and OPCs [90, 91] isolated from embryonic and postnatal rodents in SCI models, albeit indirectly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Although these predominantly show astroglial differentiation of GRP implanted within the blunt contusion-induced thoracic lesion site, there is a shift toward oligodendrocytic specification beyond the injury site correlated with the degree of functional improvement [92–94], both of which can be enhanced by transduction of factors, such as D15A, BDNF, and/or NT-3 [95]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>GRP implantation was also shown to be neuroprotective and inhibited neuropathic pain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Although more studies are required on the effects of GRPs and OPCs of various derivations in subacute and chronic cervical models, the overall picture emerging from the current literature and reports of undisclosed safety studies by Geron on ESC-derived OPCs is one that favors the continuation of this clinical trial primarily on the grounds of verification of safety, and secondarily on the grounds of efficacy in humans. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Neural progenitor cells can also be derived from several regions of the fetal, postnatal, and adult CNS, including the subventricular zone of the brain, the central canal of the spinal cord, the hippocampus, and the cortex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>They can be expanded in culture as nonadherent neurospheres, which have the potential to generate all 3 neural cell types with the appropriate conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The key advantage of this NPC source is the amenability to in vitro manipulation (including immortalization; see below) prior to implantation, as well as the lack of tumorigenicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>However, autologous derivation of the CNS NPCs would be unfeasible for cell therapy purposes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>On the basis of promising results in the highly and clinically relevant primate models [96–98]), the canine cervical contusion models of SCI, and cell number-dependent locomotor recovery in acute, subacute, and chronic thoracic rodent models (stemcellsinc.com) [99–102], a recently listed clinical trial in Switzerland sponsored by the biotechnology firm StemCells Inc. is the only one currently recruiting to treat SCI sufferers with nonimmortalized fetal human CNS stem cells (HuCNS-SC) (clinical trial identifier: NCT01321333). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Despite an origin of the fetal brain, they are regulated and often referred to as adult NPCs, because they are nonembryonic (stemcellsinc.com). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>These have been previously tested for the fatal infantile demyelination disorder Pelizaeus-Merzbacher disease (clinical trial identifier: NCT01005004) and neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis (also referred to as Batten disease) (clinical trial identifier: NCT00337636). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>In the latter, they have recently been shown to persist without causing harm for as long as 2.5 years after implantation into immunosuppressed patients (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.internationaldrugdiscovery.com/ViewArticle.aspx?ContentID=2474">http://www.internationaldrugdiscovery.com/ViewArticle.aspx?ContentID=2474</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>There is a lack of trials of NPCs in SCI, in spite of the bulk of pre-clinical findings to date in support of the potential of fetal and adult neural stem/progenitor cells (particularly the former) in experimental SCI models [23], which is likely to reflect ethical concerns as to their origins and practical issues hindering their isolation and directed differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Another possible explanation for the absence of clinical trials of NPCs for SCI is that the mechanisms through which NPCs provide functional benefit (including immunomodulation and angiogenesis) are only now beginning to be understood, dismissing the absolute requirement in all cases for cellular replacement by highly purified populations of pre-differentiated NPC-derived neural cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Also, aims of axonal regeneration through the injury site have been replaced pre-clinically by more realistic objectives of remyelination [23] and provision of trophic support for endogenous precursors and axons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>This makes NPCs much more promising candidates for cell therapy for SCI and probably heralds their increased use in clinical trials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>In spite of the gaps in this field remaining to be filled by further pre-clinical research, there is a compelling amount and strength of evidence along with extensive safety and efficacy testing that has been undertaken by the biotechnology firms sponsoring such trials (including Geron and Stem Cells Inc.) to gain FDA approval. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>These support clinical trials of fetal, adult, and ESC-derived NPCs for SCI repair, although the considerable ethical and practical challenges and concerns imposed by their origins and derivation should not be ignored. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>SCs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>SCs myelinate axons of the peripheral nervous system and can also remyelinate spared CNS axons as occurs after SCI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>They are promising in that they are obtainable autologously and are not tumorigenic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>SCs are the longest studied cell type in the cell field of transplantation research [103, 104]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>It has been shown that transplantation of SCs, but also OECs and BMSCs promote the invasion of host SCs into the lesion site after SCI [105, 106], and although this might be interpreted as endogenous SCs playing a role in repair, it might paradoxically hinder the endogenous repair process [107]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The consequences of schwannosis, referring to the invasion of host SCs into the post-SCI lesion site, need further study to elucidate the possible undesirable side effects of SC transplantation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>SC transplants have been studied the most in thoracic models of contusion-compression and transection SCI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Although they are demonstrably effective at promoting sensory axonal sprouting, when transplanted alone they are not capable of stimulating corticospinal tract regeneration or of allowing axons that have penetrated the graft site to grow across and re-enter the CNS parenchymal microenvironment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Although neonatal SCs have not been shown to be effective in cervical crush SCI [108], subarachnoid neonatal rodent SC transplantation after clip compression-induced thoracic SCI has demonstrated dramatic functional improvement after injecting only 50,000 cells into young rats (100–140 g; 45–60 days old) [109]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Of the studies on adult nerve-derived SCs, only approximately one quarter have carried out BBB assessment of functional outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Of these, only 2 of 5 studies in subacute and chronic thoracic contusion SCI have reported improved functional motor outcome (BBB scores) with SC transplantation alone [73, 74]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The remaining studies, which were performed by the same group, combined SCs and either OECs or other molecules [72, 110–113]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>In studies of SCs in transection models of SCI, all the required controls often have not been included [114], making interpretation of their results difficult. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>A phase I clinical safety and feasibility trial of purified autologous sural nerve-derived has already been conducted according to ICCP guidelines2 in 33 stable chronic mid-thoracic (T6-9) SCI patients with AIS motor scores A to C [115], despite a lack of studies on adult human SCs without co-administered therapies in cervical and thoracic contusion spinal cord lesion models [116–118]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>All patients received intensive rehabilitation pre-surgery and post-surgery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Four patients aged 22 to 43 were followed up for as long as 1 year post-transplant and so far have been reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>This trial found autologous adult SC transplantation to be safe (no pathological findings were reported), although a beneficial outcome was found (as rated by using the ASIA motor scale) in only 1 patient with incomplete SCI that could not be attributed to cell treatment since the donor cells could not be localized by magnetic resonance imaging. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Similarly, human SCs have been examined pre-clinically in spinal cord demyelination models [119, 120], and they have been implanted into MS patients, demonstrating safety and feasibility, as well as remyelination [121]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>These trials offer partial support for clinical trials of SCs for SCI, from the safety aspect, as well as from the point of view of remyelinating the injured spinal cord. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>However, the deleterious consequences of contaminating fibroblasts demonstrated by pre-clinical studies [120] will greatly impact future clinical trials of SCs for SCI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>It is clear that more clinically relevant studies are required to examine the potential of human SCs in SCI, even in conjunction with other cells and therapies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, preliminary data from the first trials are encouraging by helping to establish the safety of SC transplantation for SCI. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Promising Cell Sources Evaluated in Pre-Clinical Studies but Not Yet in Clinical Trials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>In addition to the cell sources and types mentioned so far, there are other promising cell sources with the potential to be used in cell therapy clinical trials for SCI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>However, apart possibly from fetal and immortalized NPCs, their safety and efficacy in clinically relevant experimental SCI models still remain to be more extensively studied. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Human Adult and Immortalized NPCs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>As previously mentioned, NPCs can be derived from the adult, as well as the fetal CNS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>It is generally recognized that adult-derived progenitor cells tend to fare less well than their fetal and embryonic counterparts in terms not only of proliferative and differentiation potentials, but also in regard to postimplantation survival, migration, and integration within the recipient CNS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>However, the serious and well-founded ethical and practical concerns of using material of fetal and embryonic derivation have limited their study at the clinical level, at least to date. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>From our own work and that of other groups, the predominating oligodendrogenic differentiation potential of adult rodent NPCs has been demonstrated following intra-spinal [122, 123] or intravenous [124] implantation into a range of rat and murine models (i.e., thoracic contusion), compression, and cervical transection SCI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The efficacy of NPCs can be enhanced by co-administered chondroitinase treatment [122, 123]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>As with some other cell types, however, there have been indications of increased neuropathic pain, which remain to be confirmed [125]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The conditional immortalization of cells might provide a partial solution to limiting the use of fetal and embryonic tissue, overcoming the limited supply of cells irrespective of donor age, removing a source of variability between clinical trials and enabling extensive characterization of cell lines prior to clinical application. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Clinically approved, conditionally immortalized fetal cortical NPCs (ReN001 or CTX0E03) of human origin are already in a phase I clinical trial for stroke in Scotland, UK (Pilot Investigation of Stem Cells in Stroke; clinical trial identifier: NCT01151124). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>These cells have been developed by the biotechnology firm ReNeuron using a karyotypically stable immortalization platform to enable cells to proliferate in culture and differentiate when induced without oncogenic transformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Although this clinical trial will not include SCI patients, the results of this trial will be very interesting and relevant because stroke and SCI share many common pathophysiological mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The large differences in cells (including age of donor, immortalization strategy, culture conditions) and the models used make a direct comparison between studies challenging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>For instance, no study has yet compared the efficacy of adult versus fetal NPCs lines using the same immortalization strategy and in the same SCI model; in fact, no study has yet been published on immortalized adult NPCs in SCI, an approach which would limit the use of an ethically objectionable and difficult to procure posthumous source of cells in limited supply. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>There are also no direct comparisons of functional outcome between adult and fetal NPCs in SCI, and between different times of implantations following SCI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>It has been shown that implantation of fetal NPCs into the acutely compressed or contused (and microenvironment of the highly inflammatory) thoracic spinal cord is unsuccessful compared to a subacute (7–9 days post-SCI) implantation time point [126]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>This suggests that implanting in the subacute stages of SCI would be more likely to provide benefit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, immortalized fetal human NPCs (ReN001; ReNeuron) have been shown to have anti-inflammatory properties (to the extent that stroke patients in the Pilot Investigation of Stem Cells in Stroke trial are not being immunosuppressed following implantation of these cells). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>This suggests that NPCs could potentially be implanted in the acute stages of SCI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Clearly, more pre-clinical studies are required to investigate this to determine the likely outcomes of cell implantation at different times following SCI. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Finally, NPCs are a heterogenous population of cells, and differences in culture methods and durations are likely to create and amplify differences in efficacy, depending on the particular models used, as well as the design specifics of each study examining them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>However, there has been extensive pre-clinical safety testing (reneuron.com; similar to Geron and its GRNOPC1 cell line, and Stem Cells Inc. and its HuCNS-SC adult NPC line) of at least 1 line of immortalized fetal NPCs carried out by ReNeuron prior to implantation into stroke patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>This addresses important questions regarding the safety and tolerability of their clinical use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Human Wharton’s Jelly Cells/Umbilical Cord Matrix Cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Nonembryonic tissues, such as bone marrow, peripheral and umbilical cord blood, and umbilical cord matrix [127, 128] represent plentiful, ethical, and easily accessible sources of mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) for neural repair [129]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>BMSCs, currently the main source of autologous stem cells (apart from adipose stem cells, incubated macrophages, olfactory mucosal cells and OECs, of which the latter three are not stem cells per se), are already in several clinical trials as mentioned. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The human umbilical cord consists of an outer layer of amniotic epithelial cells enclosing a gelatinous matrix known as Wharton’s jelly cells (WJCs) [130], which harbors a stem cell population of WJCs [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Although WJCs are similar to MSCs from other sources (umbilical cord blood, amniotic fluid, bone marrow, and fetal blood), there are several clinically important advantages to using WJCs for cell transplantation (for more detail see Vawda et al. [131, 132]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Most importantly, WJCs are more highly proliferative and can thus be more rapidly and extensively propagated than adult BMSCs [129, 133], but unlike the latter, WJCs can undergo repeated freeze–thaw cycles without a significant loss of viability, mesodermal differentiation potential, and without accumulating karyotypic abnormalities [129, 133]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>WJCs are readily obtainable without ethical constraints after normal and Caesarean births. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>They are thought to be nonimmunogenic, and may even have the capacity to suppress the immune response [134], potentially making them suitable for allogeneic transplantation [125]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>WJCs are highly pathotropic following transplantation [135]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Of greatest relevance to SCI, they secrete a wide range of trophic factors known to promote neural cell survival (including FGF2 and SDF-1a) [136], which would make them useful for cell rescue and as support cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Unlike ES and induced pluripotent stem (iPS) cells [137], WJCs are nontumorigenic following transplantation [133, 135, 136], and they even exhibit anti-tumor properties [138, 139]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Two studies so far have examined the use of WJCs in SCI models, but were poorly conceived and designed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, they did indicate that WJC administration into SCI models can potentially promote repair and recovery through the release of trophic factors [140, 141]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Fetal Human Mesenchymal Progenitor Cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Fetal human mesenchymal progenitor cells can be isolated by cardiocentesis from first trimester fetal blood and have been characterized by Campagnoli et al.’s group [142]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Fetal human mesenchymal progenitor cells are antigenically and morphologically similar to adult BMSCs and virtually indistinguishable from WJCs, and they have already been clinically used in Sweden for osteogenesis imperfecta [143]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Given the source of fetal human mesenchymal progenitor cells from elective abortions, there are serious ethical and practical issues constraining more widespread clinical use, but their potential in SCI cannot be ignored. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Immunosuppression might not be necessary for successful donor fetal MPC survival and engraftment, not only without rejection but leading to functional benefit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>In 2005, Le Blanc et al.’s [143] team in Sweden transplanted allogeneic human leukocyte antigen-mismatched male fetal liver MSCs into an immunocompetent patient with osteogenesis imperfecta (a genetic bone defect caused by dysfunctional collagen) in utero at 32 weeks of gestation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>This study found successful engraftment and osteogenic differentiation of donor cells, leading to functional recovery. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Skin-Derived Progenitors </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Nearly a decade ago, Miller’s group described a population of multipotent progenitor cells residing within the adult dermis (termed skin-derived precursors [SKPs]) [144–146] with the potential to generate myelinating cells [105, 147–152] and enable axons to grow across the lesion site (unlike SCs) when injected intra-spinally after SCI [105]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>On the basis of convincing histological and behavioral data in the latter study, the potential for autologous transplantation of treated SKPs for SCI is obvious. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>It is interesting to note the similarity between this study and one on BMSCs, which were found to further promote axonal sprouting when treated pre-implantation with growth factors [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>However, more studies of the effects of SKP injection in direct comparison with SCs into more clinically relevant models of SCI, including cervical and chronic models, would be required to characterize the safety parameters of this cell source and to determine the optimal implantation criteria to maximize functional benefit post-SCI. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Induced Pluripotent Stem Cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Recently, the discovery of iPS cells has opened a new potential therapeutic approach for regenerative neuroscience, although iPS cells have not yet been used clinically in SCI cell therapy [153–155]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>We recently reviewed the potential of iPS cells in SCI [154]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Given the novel nature of the technology and the safety and reliability of recent variations on the induction technique, these cells are not yet ready for use in clinical trials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>As with ES cells, there are well-founded concerns in regard to the teratomatous potential of iPS cells in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>In addition, their controlled differentiation remains to be thoroughly compared to ES cells and conditions optimized for the subsequent derivation of each neural lineage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Of note, Tsuji et al. [156] recently derived “safe” mouse iPS cells and observed trilineage neural differentiation and functional recovery in a contusion model of SCI without teratoma formation [156]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>A further concern is the inherent variability of the differentiation and proliferative potential of different iPS cell lines, an issue also raised by different ES cell lines and by the low transduction rates of current transfection strategies, and the requirement for extensive retrospective characterization to ensure ES cell-like phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>This needs to be resolved to be able to allow the “individualization” of iPS technology to derive patient-specific lines for autologous transplantation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Even then, the time required to generate and characterize (and if required genetically manipulate) iPSC lines would render individualized iPSC-based treatment impractical. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>More likely is that a set of well-characterized iPSC lines will be generated and tested pre-clinically for subsequent administration into SCI patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>In this situation, the immunogenicity of iPSCs is a major obstacle that will need to be addressed [157]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>As such, although clinical trials for these cells may be a possibility in time, the current state of the field would not warrant them. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Endogenous Progenitors </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Stem/progenitor cells have been identified in the central canal adult of the mammalian spinal cord [158, 159]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>They proliferate extensively following SCI [160] or in response to the infusion of exogenous growth factors into the fourth ventricle of the adult brain [161], which can also reduce inflammation, and generate astrocytes and oligodendrocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Although the potential of stimulating the proliferation and subsequent differentiation of endogenous NPCs to effect repair is clear, it needs to be seen alongside the possible risks that supra-physiological levels of neurotrophic factors within the cerebrospinal fluid might carry, including epileptogenesis and oncogenesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Recommendations for the Conduct and Evaluation of Pre-Clinical Studies and Clinical Trials of Cell Therapies for SCI </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The absolute requirement for international peer-reviewed assessment, regulation, independent monitoring and duplication, complete transparency, and accurate record keeping of every step of the process of designing, initiating, and executing clinical trials cannot be over-emphasized [162]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>In this regard, a series of guidelines and criteria has recently been published, and the principles for ethical implementation of clinical trials in patients with SCI have been established by the ICCP panel [163–166]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>These include a sound evidentiary basis and compelling clinical rationale for conducting a clinical trial, registration with clinicaltrials.gov, protection of the rights of participants and volunteers through informed consent, the absence of renumeration beyond basic expenses for patients and participating institutions, the absence of charges made to the patients for experimental treatments, which should not be misrepresented as established treatments, a prospective, controlled design, objective independent outcome assessments, adequate follow-up time to monitor neurological and safety issues, and oversight by an independent authority. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>This will minimize the likelihood of adverse effects of treatment, and if they do occur, the investigators will be informed as to possible ways to avoid them, overcome them, or manage them in future. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Amariglio et al. [53] published a report of a young boy with ataxia telangiectasia who had received a multi-donor-derived intrathecal injection of fetal human NPCs and developed a benign multi-focal brain and spinal cord glioneuronal neoplasm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>It has been suggested that the dysfunctional immune system of ataxia telangiectasia patients increased the risk of this particular recipient to develop donor cell-derived neoplasms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>There are serious doubts remaining in regard to the details of this clinical case, especially relating to the karyotypic status of the implanted cells after culture and immediately prior to implantation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>This is a genuine concern, which deserves further investigation, as highlighted by the oncogenic potential of ES cell-derived neural cells reported by Roy et al. [167]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>However, unfortunately, it is unlikely that this particular case will yield any useful information for future studies and trials, given the lack of details on the cells, their origin, their isolation, and the implantation procedure, and any co-administered treatments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Although we advocate a combined strategy of careful exploration of cell-based therapies in phase I and II trials in humans, and intensive pre-clinical evaluation of these approaches in cervical models of SCI, it is important to emphasize that clinical investigation needs to follow sound ethical and scientific principles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>One of the key principles involves establishing a sound scientific basis for the preclinical research [23, 24, 162, 168, 169]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Concluding Remarks </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The National Institutes of Health translational roadmap (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://commonfund.nih.gov/clinicalresearch/overview-translational.aspx">http://commonfund.nih.gov/clinicalresearch/overview-translational.aspx</ext-link>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://CTSAweb.org/">http://CTSAweb.org/</ext-link>) was drafted to validate animal models and protocols developed in the laboratory, and to drive the implementation of pre-clinical studies and basic research, thus enabling scientists to begin addressing and overcoming the issues and challenges emanating from the clinic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>In this regard, immediate, further, and larger clinical trials are justified for cells already proven safe and even effective through extensive laboratory testing, and/or through past and ongoing clinical trials, such as autologous BMSCs, OECs, olfactory mucosal cells, NPCs, and ESC-derived OPCs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Given the paucity of studies carried out in more clinically relevant models of SCI, such as chronic cervical SCI [23], current clinical trials are justified primarily on the basis of pre-clinical studies conducted predominantly in thoracic models to determine the relative safety and feasibility of the cellular interventions currently at our disposal in thoracic SCI, and to iron out neurosurgical technical and logistical issues, and also to objectively evaluate functional outcome to determine efficacy using internationally recognized and established standards. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>It is acknowledged that animal models are continuing to evolve and improve so as to more closely reflect the clinical situation [6–8, 170–177], and that better and more accurate standardized analysis techniques (including the CatWalk system [178]) will enable more objective assessment of functional outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>However, we argue that there is a real and urgent need to press ahead with human trials on the basis of relevant solid scientific pre-clinical evidence gathered from well-established models analyzed using thoroughly validated techniques. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The feasibility of this approach is amply demonstrated by the ongoing trials of ESC-derived OPCs (GRNOPC1) by Geron. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Although the case in support of clinical trials of cell therapies for SCI generates vigorous debate and divergent views, it is our strong view that the field is now at a stage in which advancement into phase I and early phase II trials is justified and essential to move the field forward. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Certainly, an important principle in considering the clinical translation of a therapeutic strategy is the need for replication of results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>However, this principle may be more complex when a biotechnology company is driving the translational process, given the considerations of protecting intellectual property. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the need for data from 1 laboratory to be replicated using identical conditions and cells may be an unrealistic and unreasonable challenge to meet, given the pressure on researchers to publish novel rather than confirmatory data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Therefore, there will always be differences between studies, even on the same cell type (or types) or the same model (or models) that might make a direct comparison of results difficult. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, it is precisely those differences that are the most informative and pave the way ahead toward new developments and findings preceding clinical trials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Taking into account the various issues at hand, it is our view that, while this is by no means a clear-cut situation, there are nonetheless sufficient pre-clinical and earlier clinical safety studies of satisfactory quality and reliability carried out so far to justify the immediate translation into the clinic of a greater number of pre-clinical findings, such as the clinical trial of OECs by Mackay-Sim et al.’s [55] group, and Mackay-Sim and St. John’s [179], the work on fetal cells by Giovanini et al.’s [27] group and the phase I Procord trial on macrophages [85]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Finally, no clinical intervention is 100% risk-free. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>The decision to forge ahead with clinical trials of cell therapy for SCI relies on striking a balance between the current and anticipated burden of SCI and the potential risks of cell therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Setbacks are an expected feature of novel therapies (as in the case of bone marrow transplantation, development of the polio vaccine, and initial gene therapy trials), and as difficult as setbacks can be to contemplate and overcome, they have been overcome, and they have even provided vital clinical and scientific information that has enabled subsequent therapies to be made safe and effective. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Without the clinical translation of the firmly established basic scientific findings, however, we will be stuck at the preclinical level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Advances in the application of regenerative neuroscience to SCI can only be made with an investigative approach that balances excellent preclinical research with rigorous, ethical clinical trials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="SecESM1"><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.ESM 1(PDF 510 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn id="Fn1"><label>1</label><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>There is a precedent for the approval for a clinical trial being given on the basis of rodent-only pre-clinical data (i.e., the ProCord Phase I and II trials of incubated macrophages) [85, 180]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="Fn2"><label>2</label><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>A series of guidelines has recently been published and the principles for ethical implementation of clinical trials in patients with SCI have been established by the ICCP panel [163–166]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="SUPPL"><fn><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s13311-011-0076-7) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>Dr Madeleine O'Higgins (Communications Specialist) for help with editing and proofreading the manuscript. Full conflict of interest disclosure is available in the <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">electronic supplementary material</xref> for this article.</p><sec id="d29e2080"><title>Open Access</title><p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>1.SekhonLHFehlingsMGEpidemiology, demographics, and pathophysiology of acute spinal cord injurySpine (Phila Pa 1976)20012624 supplS2S1210.1097/00007632-200112151-0000211805601 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>2.ASpinal cord injury facts and figures at a glance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Birmingham, AL: National Spinal Cord Injury Statistical Center, 2010. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>3.One Degree of Separation: Paralysis and Spinal Cord Injury in the United States. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Christopher and Dana Reeve Foundation, 2010. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>4.FehlingsMGTigheASpinal cord injury: the promise of translational researchNeurosurg Focus200825E110.3171/FOC.2008.25.11.E1<?supplied-pmid 18980469?>18980469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>5.Spinal cord injury facts and statistics: Rick Hansen Spinal Cord Injury Registry, 2006. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>6.DunhamKASiriphornAChompoopongSFloydCLCharacterization of a graded cervical hemicontusion spinal cord injury model in adult male ratsJ Neurotrauma2010272091210610.1089/neu.2010.1424<?supplied-pmid 21087156?>21087156 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>7.UsvaldDVodickaPHlucilovaJAnalysis of dosing regimen and reproducibility of intraspinal grafting of human spinal stem cells in immunosuppressed minipigsCell Transplant2010191103112210.3727/096368910X503406<?supplied-pmid 20412634?>20412634 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>8.VodickaPSmetanaKJrDvorankovaBThe miniature pig as an animal model in biomedical researchAnn N Y Acad Sci2005104916117110.1196/annals.1334.015<?supplied-pmid 15965115?>15965115 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>9.TatorCHFehlingsMGReview of the secondary injury theory of acute spinal cord trauma with emphasis on vascular mechanismsJ Neurosurg199175152610.3171/jns.1991.75.1.0015<?supplied-pmid 2045903?>2045903 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>10.Figley SA, Austin JW, Rowland JW, Fehlings MG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Pathophysiology of spinal cord injury. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>The Cervical Spine, 5th ed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Lippincott, Williams and Wilkins, 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>11.WangLShiJvan GinkelFWNeural stem/progenitor cells modulate immune responses by suppressing T lymphocytes with nitric oxide and prostaglandin E2Exp Neurol200921617718310.1016/j.expneurol.2008.11.017<?supplied-pmid 19109951?>19109951 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>12.PluchinoSGrittiABlezerEHuman neural stem cells ameliorate autoimmune encephalomyelitis in non-human primatesAnn Neurol20096634335410.1002/ana.21745<?supplied-pmid 19798728?>19798728 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>13.OkamuraRMLebkowskiJAuMPriestCADenhamJMajumdarASImmunological properties of human embryonic stem cell-derived oligodendrocyte progenitor cellsJ Neuroimmunol200719213414410.1016/j.jneuroim.2007.09.030<?supplied-pmid 17996308?>17996308 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>14.JaderstadJJaderstadLMLiJCommunication via gap junctions underlies early functional and beneficial interactions between grafted neural stem cells and the hostProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20101075184518910.1073/pnas.0915134107<?supplied-pmid 20147621?>20147621 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>15.BaiLLennonDPEatonVHuman bone marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells induce Th2-polarized immune response and promote endogenous repair in animal models of multiple sclerosisGlia2009571192120310.1002/glia.20841<?supplied-pmid 19191336?>19191336 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>16.ArriolaAKielMEShiYMcKinnonRDAdjunctive MSCs enhance myelin formation by xenogenic oligodendrocyte precursors transplanted in the retinaCell Res20102072873110.1038/cr.2010.63<?supplied-pmid 20440303?>20440303 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>17.ZhangJWangBXiaoZOlfactory ensheathing cells promote proliferation and inhibit neuronal differentiation of neural progenitor cells through activation of Notch signalingNeuroscience200815340641310.1016/j.neuroscience.2008.02.067<?supplied-pmid 18400409?>18400409 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>18.Hernandeza J, Torres-Espina A, Navarro X. Adult Stem Cell Transplants for Spinal Cord Injury Repair: Current State in Preclinical Research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Curr Stem Cell Res Ther 2011;Sep 1;6(3):273–287. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>19.Ruff CA, Wilcox JT, Fehlings MG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Cell-based transplantation strategies to promote plasticity following spinal cord injury. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Exp Neurol 2011; Feb 17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>PMID:21333647. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>20.RuffCAFehlingsMGNeural stem cells in regenerative medicine: bridging the gapPanminerva Med201052125147<?supplied-pmid 20517196?>20517196 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>21.ZhangHTChengHYCaiYQComparison of adult neurospheres derived from different origins for treatment of rat spinal cord injuryNeurosci Lett200945811612110.1016/j.neulet.2009.04.045<?supplied-pmid 19394407?>19394407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>22.Mackay-SimASt. JohnJAOlfactory ensheathing cells from the nose: Clinical application in human spinal cord injuriesExp Neurol201122917418010.1016/j.expneurol.2010.08.025<?supplied-pmid 20832402?>20832402 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>23.TetzlaffWOkonEBKarimi-AbdolrezaeeSA systematic review of cellular transplantation therapies for spinal cord injuryJ Neurotrauma2011281611168210.1089/neu.2009.1177<?supplied-pmid 20146557?>20146557 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>24.KwonBKHillyerJTetzlaffWTranslational research in spinal cord injury: a survey of opinion from the SCI communityJ Neurotrauma201027213310.1089/neu.2009.1048<?supplied-pmid 19751098?>19751098 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>25.KwonBKSekhonLHFehlingsMGEmerging repair, regeneration, and translational research advances for spinal cord injurySpine (Phila Pa)19763521 supplS263S270 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>26.Gensel JC, Donnelly DJ, Popovich PG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Spinal cord injury therapies in humans: an overview of current clinical trials and their potential effects on intrinsic CNS macrophages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Expert Opin Ther Targets 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>27.GiovaniniMAReierPJEskinTAWirthEAndersonDKCharacteristics of human fetal spinal cord grafts in the adult rat spinal cord: influences of lesion and grafting conditionsExp Neurol199714852354310.1006/exnr.1997.6703<?supplied-pmid 9417830?>9417830 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>28.LuPBleschATuszynskiMHInduction of bone marrow stromal cells to neurons: differentiation, transdifferentiation, or artifact?J Neurosci Res20047717419110.1002/jnr.20148<?supplied-pmid 15211585?>15211585 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>29.Novikova LN, Brohlin M, Kingham PJ, Novikov LN, Wiberg M. Neuroprotective and growth-promoting effects of bone marrow stromal cells after cervical spinal cord injury in adult rats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Cytotherapy 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>30.LuPJonesLLTuszynskiMHAxon regeneration through scars and into sites of chronic spinal cord injuryExp Neurol200720382110.1016/j.expneurol.2006.07.030<?supplied-pmid 17014846?>17014846 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>31.UrdzikovaLJendelovaPGlogarovaKBurianMHajekMSykovaETransplantation of bone marrow stem cells as well as mobilization by granulocyte-colony stimulating factor promotes recovery after spinal cord injury in ratsJ Neurotrauma2006231379139110.1089/neu.2006.23.1379<?supplied-pmid 16958589?>16958589 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>32.OhtaMSuzukiYNodaTBone marrow stromal cells infused into the cerebrospinal fluid promote functional recovery of the injured rat spinal cord with reduced cavity formationExp Neurol200418726627810.1016/j.expneurol.2004.01.021<?supplied-pmid 15144853?>15144853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>33.FanLDuFChengBCPengHLiuSQMigration and distribution of bone marrow stromal cells in injured spinal cord with different transplantation techniquesChin J Traumatol2008119497<?supplied-pmid 18377712?>18377712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>34.ZuritaMVaqueroJBonillaCFunctional recovery of chronic paraplegic pigs after autologous transplantation of bone marrow stromal cellsTransplantation20088684585310.1097/TP.0b013e318186198f<?supplied-pmid 18813110?>18813110 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>35.DengYBLiuXGLiuZGLiuXLLiuYZhouGQImplantation of BM mesenchymal stem cells into injured spinal cord elicits de novo neurogenesis and functional recovery: evidence from a study in rhesus monkeysCytotherapy2006821021410.1080/14653240600760808<?supplied-pmid 16793730?>16793730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>36.Kim M. Regeneration of completely transected spinal cord using scaffold of poly(D,L-lactide-co-glycolide)/small intestinal submucosa seeded with rat bone marrow stem cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Tissue Eng Part A 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>37.NeuhuberBTimothy HimesBShumskyJSGalloGFischerIAxon growth and recovery of function supported by human bone marrow stromal cells in the injured spinal cord exhibit donor variationsBrain Res20051035738510.1016/j.brainres.2004.11.055<?supplied-pmid 15713279?>15713279 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>38.VaqueroJZuritaMOyaSSantosMCell therapy using bone marrow stromal cells in chronic paraplegic rats: systemic or local administration?Neurosci Lett200639812913410.1016/j.neulet.2005.12.072<?supplied-pmid 16423458?>16423458 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>39.ZuritaMVaqueroJBone marrow stromal cells can achieve cure of chronic paraplegic rats: functional and morphological outcome one year after transplantationNeurosci Lett2006402515610.1016/j.neulet.2006.03.069<?supplied-pmid 16713677?>16713677 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>40.ZuritaMVaqueroJFunctional recovery in chronic paraplegia after bone marrow stromal cells transplantationNeuroreport2004151105110810.1097/00001756-200405190-00004<?supplied-pmid 15129154?>15129154 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>41.de HaroJZuritaMAyllonLVaqueroJDetection of 111In-oxine-labeled bone marrow stromal cells after intravenous or intralesional administration in chronic paraplegic ratsNeurosci Lett200537771110.1016/j.neulet.2004.11.060<?supplied-pmid 15722177?>15722177 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>42.KamadaTKodaMDezawaMTransplantation of bone marrow stromal cell-derived Schwann cells promotes axonal regeneration and functional recovery after complete transection of adult rat spinal cordJ Neuropathol Exp Neurol2005643745<?supplied-pmid 15715083?>15715083 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>43.KamadaTKodaMDezawaMTransplantation of human bone marrow stromal cell-derived Schwann cells reduces cystic cavity and promotes functional recovery after contusion injury of adult rat spinal cordNeuropathology201131485810.1111/j.1440-1789.2010.01130.x<?supplied-pmid 20573032?>20573032 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>44.van der KooyDMcGintyJFKodaLYGerfenCRBloomFEVisceral cortex: a direct connection from prefrontal cortex to the solitary nucleus in ratNeurosci Lett19823312312710.1016/0304-3940(82)90238-5<?supplied-pmid 6185887?>6185887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>45.KodaMNishioYKamadaTGranulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF) mobilizes bone marrow-derived cells into injured spinal cord and promotes functional recovery after compression-induced spinal cord injury in miceBrain Res2007114922323110.1016/j.brainres.2007.02.058<?supplied-pmid 17391650?>17391650 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>46.KodaMKamadaTHashimotoMAdenovirus vector-mediated ex vivo gene transfer of brain-derived neurotrophic factor to bone marrow stromal cells promotes axonal regeneration after transplantation in completely transected adult rat spinal cordEur Spine J2007162206221410.1007/s00586-007-0499-3<?supplied-pmid 17885772?>17885772 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>47.CalleraFdo NascimentoRXDelivery of autologous bone marrow precursor cells into the spinal cord via lumbar puncture technique in patients with spinal cord injury: a preliminary safety studyExp Hematol20063413013110.1016/j.exphem.2005.11.006<?supplied-pmid 16459180?>16459180 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>48.ChernykhERStupakVVMuradovGMApplication of autologous bone marrow stem cells in the therapy of spinal cord injury patientsBull Exp Biol Med200714354354710.1007/s10517-007-0175-y<?supplied-pmid 18214319?>18214319 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>49.YoonSHShimYSParkYHComplete spinal cord injury treatment using autologous bone marrow cell transplantation and bone marrow stimulation with granulocyte macrophage-colony stimulating factor: phase I/II clinical trialStem Cells2007252066207310.1634/stemcells.2006-0807<?supplied-pmid 17464087?>17464087 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>50.SaitoFNakataniTIwaseMSpinal cord injury treatment with intrathecal autologous bone marrow stromal cell transplantation: the first clinical trial case reportJ Trauma200864535910.1097/TA.0b013e31815b847d<?supplied-pmid 18188099?>18188099 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>51.FreedmanMSBar-OrAAtkinsHLThe therapeutic potential of mesenchymal stem cell transplantation as a treatment for multiple sclerosis: consensus report of the International MSCT Study GroupMult Scler20101650351010.1177/1352458509359727<?supplied-pmid 20086020?>20086020 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>52.AtkinsHFreedmanMImmune ablation followed by autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplantation for the treatment of poor prognosis multiple sclerosisMethods Mol Biol200954923124610.1007/978-1-60327-931-4_16<?supplied-pmid 19378207?>19378207 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>53.AmariglioNHirshbergAScheithauerBWDonor-derived brain tumor following neural stem cell transplantation in an ataxia telangiectasia patientPLoS Med20096e100002910.1371/journal.pmed.1000029<?supplied-pmid 19226183?>19226183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>54.DoucetteRPNS-CNS transitional zone of the first cranial nerveJ Comp Neurol199131245146610.1002/cne.903120311<?supplied-pmid 1748741?>1748741 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>55.Mackay-SimAFeronFCochraneJAutologous olfactory ensheathing cell transplantation in human paraplegia: a 3-year clinical trialBrain2008131pt 92376238610.1093/brain/awn173<?supplied-pmid 18689435?>18689435 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>56.FeronFPerryCCochraneJAutologous olfactory ensheathing cell transplantation in human spinal cord injuryBrain2005128pt 122951296010.1093/brain/awh657<?supplied-pmid 16219671?>16219671 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>57.LuJFeronFMackay-SimAWaitePMOlfactory ensheathing cells promote locomotor recovery after delayed transplantation into transected spinal cordBrain2002125pt 1142110.1093/brain/awf014<?supplied-pmid 11834589?>11834589 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>58.LuJFeronFHoSMMackay-SimAWaitePMTransplantation of nasal olfactory tissue promotes partial recovery in paraplegic adult ratsBrain Res200188934435710.1016/S0006-8993(00)03235-2<?supplied-pmid 11166728?>11166728 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>59.ZhangXKlueberKMGuoZInduction of neuronal differentiation of adult human olfactory neuroepithelial-derived progenitorsBrain Res20061073–107410911910.1016/j.brainres.2005.12.059<?supplied-pmid 16455065?>16455065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>60.LimaCPratas-VitalJEscadaPHasse-FerreiraACapuchoCPeduzziJDOlfactory mucosa autografts in human spinal cord injury: a pilot clinical studyJ Spinal Cord Med200629191206<?supplied-pmid 16859223?>16859223 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>61.LimaCEscadaPPratas-VitalJOlfactory mucosal autografts and rehabilitation for chronic traumatic spinal cord injuryNeurorehabil Neural Repair201024102210.1177/1545968309347685<?supplied-pmid 19794133?>19794133 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>62.RuitenbergMJPlantGWHamersFPEx vivo adenoviral vector-mediated neurotrophin gene transfer to olfactory ensheathing glia: effects on rubrospinal tract regeneration, lesion size, and functional recovery after implantation in the injured rat spinal cordJ Neurosci20032370457058<?supplied-pmid 12904465?>12904465 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>63.StewardOSharpKSelvanGA re-assessment of the consequences of delayed transplantation of olfactory lamina propria following complete spinal cord transection in ratsExp Neurol200619848349910.1016/j.expneurol.2005.12.034<?supplied-pmid 16494866?>16494866 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>64.DeumensRKoopmansGCHonigWMChronically injured corticospinal axons do not cross large spinal lesion gaps after a multifactorial transplantation strategy using olfactory ensheathing cell/olfactory nerve fibroblast-biomatrix bridgesJ Neurosci Res20068381182010.1002/jnr.20768<?supplied-pmid 16477623?>16477623 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>65.DeumensRKoopmansGCHonigWMOlfactory ensheathing cells, olfactory nerve fibroblasts and biomatrices to promote long-distance axon regrowth and functional recovery in the dorsally hemisected adult rat spinal cordExp Neurol20062008910310.1016/j.expneurol.2006.01.030<?supplied-pmid 16527274?>16527274 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>66.LuPYangHCulbertsonMGrahamLRoskamsAJTuszynskiMHOlfactory ensheathing cells do not exhibit unique migratory or axonal growth-promoting properties after spinal cord injuryJ Neurosci200626111201113010.1523/JNEUROSCI.3264-06.2006<?supplied-pmid 17065452?>17065452 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>67.BretznerFLiuJCurrieERoskamsAJTetzlaffWUndesired effects of a combinatorial treatment for spinal cord injury–transplantation of olfactory ensheathing cells and BDNF infusion to the red nucleusEur J Neurosci2008281795180710.1111/j.1460-9568.2008.06462.x<?supplied-pmid 18973595?>18973595 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>68.RichterMWFletcherPALiuJTetzlaffWRoskamsAJLamina propria and olfactory bulb ensheathing cells exhibit differential integration and migration and promote differential axon sprouting in the lesioned spinal cordJ Neurosci200525107001071110.1523/JNEUROSCI.3632-05.2005<?supplied-pmid 16291943?>16291943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>69.AuERichterMWVincentAJSPARC from olfactory ensheathing cells stimulates Schwann cells to promote neurite outgrowth and enhances spinal cord repairJ Neurosci2007277208722110.1523/JNEUROSCI.0509-07.2007<?supplied-pmid 17611274?>17611274 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>70.GorrieCAHaywardICameronNEffects of human OEC-derived cell transplants in rodent spinal cord contusion injuryBrain Res2010133782010.1016/j.brainres.2010.04.019<?supplied-pmid 20399758?>20399758 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>71.DengCGorrieCHaywardISurvival and migration of human and rat olfactory ensheathing cells in intact and injured spinal cordJ Neurosci Res2006831201121210.1002/jnr.20817<?supplied-pmid 16498634?>16498634 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>72.PearseDDSanchezARPereiraFCTransplantation of Schwann cells and/or olfactory ensheathing glia into the contused spinal cord: survival, migration, axon association, and functional recoveryGlia200755976100010.1002/glia.20490<?supplied-pmid 17526000?>17526000 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>73.TakamiTOudegaMBatesMLWoodPMKleitmanNBungeMBSchwann cell but not olfactory ensheathing glia transplants improve hindlimb locomotor performance in the moderately contused adult rat thoracic spinal cordJ Neurosci20022266706681<?supplied-pmid 12151546?>12151546 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>74.BarakatDJGaglaniSMNeravetlaSRSurvival, integration, and axon growth support of glia transplanted into the chronically contused spinal cordCell Transplant20051422524010.3727/000000005783983106<?supplied-pmid 15929557?>15929557 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>75.KalincikTChoiEAFeronFOlfactory ensheathing cells reduce duration of autonomic dysreflexia in rats with high spinal cord injuryAuton Neurosci2010154202910.1016/j.autneu.2009.10.001<?supplied-pmid 19896908?>19896908 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>76.KalincikTJozefcikovaKSutharsanRMackay-SimACarrivePWaitePMSelected changes in spinal cord morphology after T4 transection and olfactory ensheathing cell transplantationAuton Neurosci2010158313810.1016/j.autneu.2010.05.011<?supplied-pmid 20594923?>20594923 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>77.DraperJSMooreHDRubanLNGokhalePJAndrewsPWCulture and characterization of human embryonic stem cellsStem Cells Dev20041332533610.1089/scd.2004.13.325<?supplied-pmid 15345125?>15345125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>78.DraperJSSmithKGokhalePRecurrent gain of chromosomes 17q and 12 in cultured human embryonic stem cellsNat Biotechnol200422535410.1038/nbt922<?supplied-pmid 14661028?>14661028 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR79"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>79.CloutierFSiegenthalerMMNistorGKeirsteadHSTransplantation of human embryonic stem cell-derived oligodendrocyte progenitors into rat spinal cord injuries does not cause harmRegen Med2006146947910.2217/17460751.1.4.469<?supplied-pmid 17465839?>17465839 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR80"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>80.KeirsteadHSNistorGBernalGHuman embryonic stem cell-derived oligodendrocyte progenitor cell transplants remyelinate and restore locomotion after spinal cord injuryJ Neurosci2005254694470510.1523/JNEUROSCI.0311-05.2005<?supplied-pmid 15888645?>15888645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR81"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>81.FaulknerJKeirsteadHSHuman embryonic stem cell-derived oligodendrocyte progenitors for the treatment of spinal cord injuryTranspl Immunol20051513114210.1016/j.trim.2005.09.007<?supplied-pmid 16412957?>16412957 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR82"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>82.NistorGITotoiuMOHaqueNCarpenterMKKeirsteadHSHuman embryonic stem cells differentiate into oligodendrocytes in high purity and myelinate after spinal cord transplantationGlia20054938539610.1002/glia.20127<?supplied-pmid 15538751?>15538751 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR83"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>83.SharpJFrameJSiegenthalerMNistorGKeirsteadHSHuman embryonic stem cell-derived oligodendrocyte progenitor cell transplants improve recovery after cervical spinal cord injuryStem Cells201028152163<?supplied-pmid 19877167?>19877167 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR84"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>84.BottaiDCigogniniDMadaschiLEmbryonic stem cells promote motor recovery and affect inflammatory cell infiltration in spinal cord injured miceExp Neurol201022345246310.1016/j.expneurol.2010.01.010<?supplied-pmid 20100476?>20100476 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR85"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>85.KnollerNAuerbachGFulgaVClinical experience using incubated autologous macrophages as a treatment for complete spinal cord injury: phase I study resultsJ Neurosurg Spine2005317318110.3171/spi.2005.3.3.0173<?supplied-pmid 16235699?>16235699 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR86"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>86.BretznerFGilbertFBaylisFBrownstoneRMTarget populations for first-in-human embryonic stem cell research in spinal cord injuryCell Stem Cell2011846847510.1016/j.stem.2011.04.012<?supplied-pmid 21549321?>21549321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR87"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>87.WirthE3rdLebkowskiJSLebacqzKResponse to Frederic Bretzner, et al. Target populations for first-in-human embryonic stem cell research in spinal cord injuryCell Stem Cell2011847647810.1016/j.stem.2011.04.008<?supplied-pmid 21549322?>21549322 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR88"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>88.SolbakkJHZolothLThe tragedy of translation: the case of “first use” in human embryonic stem cell researchCell Stem Cell2011847948110.1016/j.stem.2011.04.009<?supplied-pmid 21549323?>21549323 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR89"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>89.MitsuiTShumskyJSLeporeACMurrayMFischerITransplantation of neuronal and glial restricted precursors into contused spinal cord improves bladder and motor functions, decreases thermal hypersensitivity, and modifies intraspinal circuitryJ Neurosci2005259624963610.1523/JNEUROSCI.2175-05.2005<?supplied-pmid 16237167?>16237167 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR90"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>90.BambakidisNCMillerRHTransplantation of oligodendrocyte precursors and sonic hedgehog results in improved function and white matter sparing in the spinal cords of adult rats after contusionSpine J20044162610.1016/j.spinee.2003.07.004<?supplied-pmid 14749190?>14749190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR91"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>91.LeeKHYoonDHParkYGLeeBHEffects of glial transplantation on functional recovery following acute spinal cord injuryJ Neurotrauma20052257558910.1089/neu.2005.22.575<?supplied-pmid 15892602?>15892602 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR92"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>92.EnzmannGUBentonRLWoockJPHowardRMTsoulfasPWhittemoreSRConsequences of noggin expression by neural stem, glial, and neuronal precursor cells engrafted into the injured spinal cordExp Neurol200519529330410.1016/j.expneurol.2005.04.021<?supplied-pmid 16087174?>16087174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR93"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>93.HanSSLiuYTyler-PolszCRaoMSFischerITransplantation of glial-restricted precursor cells into the adult spinal cord: survival, glial-specific differentiation, and preferential migration in white matterGlia20044511610.1002/glia.10282<?supplied-pmid 14648541?>14648541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR94"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>94.HillCEProschelCNobleMAcute transplantation of glial-restricted precursor cells into spinal cord contusion injuries: survival, differentiation, and effects on lesion environment and axonal regenerationExp Neurol200419028931010.1016/j.expneurol.2004.05.043<?supplied-pmid 15530870?>15530870 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR95"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>95.CaoQXuXMDevriesWHFunctional recovery in traumatic spinal cord injury after transplantation of multineurotrophin-expressing glial-restricted precursor cellsJ Neurosci2005256947695710.1523/JNEUROSCI.1065-05.2005<?supplied-pmid 16049170?>16049170 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR96"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>96.IwanamiAYamaneJKatohHEstablishment of graded spinal cord injury model in a nonhuman primate: the common marmosetJ Neurosci Res20058017218110.1002/jnr.20435<?supplied-pmid 15772980?>15772980 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR97"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>97.IwanamiAKanekoSNakamuraMTransplantation of human neural stem cells for spinal cord injury in primatesJ Neurosci Res20058018219010.1002/jnr.20436<?supplied-pmid 15772979?>15772979 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR98"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>98.YamaneJNakamuraMIwanamiATransplantation of galectin-1-expressing human neural stem cells into the injured spinal cord of adult common marmosetsJ Neurosci Res20108813941405<?supplied-pmid 20091712?>20091712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR99"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>99.SalazarDLUchidaNHamersFPCummingsBJAndersonAJHuman neural stem cells differentiate and promote locomotor recovery in an early chronic spinal cord injury NOD-scid mouse modelPLoS One20105e1227210.1371/journal.pone.0012272<?supplied-pmid 20806064?>20806064 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR100"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>100.HooshmandMJSontagCJUchidaNTamakiSAndersonAJCummingsBJAnalysis of host-mediated repair mechanisms after human CNS-stem cell transplantation for spinal cord injury: correlation of engraftment with recoveryPLoS One20094e587110.1371/journal.pone.0005871<?supplied-pmid 19517014?>19517014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR101"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>101.CummingsBJUchidaNTamakiSJAndersonAJHuman neural stem cell differentiation following transplantation into spinal cord injured mice: association with recovery of locomotor functionNeurol Res20062847448110.1179/016164106X115116<?supplied-pmid 16808875?>16808875 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR102"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>102.CummingsBJUchidaNTamakiSJHuman neural stem cells differentiate and promote locomotor recovery in spinal cord-injured miceProc Natl Acad Sci U S A2005102140691407410.1073/pnas.0507063102<?supplied-pmid 16172374?>16172374 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR103"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>103.DuncanIDAguayoAJBungeRPWoodPMTransplantation of rat Schwann cells grown in tissue culture into the mouse spinal cordJ Neurol Sci19814924125210.1016/0022-510X(81)90082-4<?supplied-pmid 7217983?>7217983 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR104"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>104.DuncanIDMilwardEAGlial cell transplants: experimental therapies of myelin diseasesBrain Pathol1995530131010.1111/j.1750-3639.1995.tb00607.x<?supplied-pmid 8520730?>8520730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR105"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>105.BiernaskieJSparlingJSLiuJSkin-derived precursors generate myelinating Schwann cells that promote remyelination and functional recovery after contusion spinal cord injuryJ Neurosci2007279545955910.1523/JNEUROSCI.1930-07.2007<?supplied-pmid 17804616?>17804616 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR106"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>106.HillCEMoonLDWoodPMBungeMBLabeled Schwann cell transplantation: cell loss, host Schwann cell replacement, and strategies to enhance survivalGlia20065333834310.1002/glia.20287<?supplied-pmid 16267833?>16267833 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR107"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>107.BruceJHNorenbergMDKraydiehSPuckettWMarcilloADietrichDSchwannosis: role of gliosis and proteoglycan in human spinal cord injuryJ Neurotrauma20001778178810.1089/neu.2000.17.781<?supplied-pmid 11011818?>11011818 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR108"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>108.AgudoMWoodhooAWebberDMirskyRJessenKRMcMahonSBSchwann cell precursors transplanted into the injured spinal cord multiply, integrate and are permissive for axon growthGlia2008561263127010.1002/glia.20695<?supplied-pmid 18484102?>18484102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR109"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>109.FirouziMMoshayediPSaberiHTransplantation of Schwann cells to subarachnoid space induces repair in contused rat spinal cordNeurosci Lett2006402667010.1016/j.neulet.2006.03.070<?supplied-pmid 16644115?>16644115 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR110"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>110.GoldenKLPearseDDBlitsBTransduced Schwann cells promote axon growth and myelination after spinal cord injuryExp Neurol200720720321710.1016/j.expneurol.2007.06.023<?supplied-pmid 17719577?>17719577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR111"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>111.MeijsMFTimmersLPearseDDBasic fibroblast growth factor promotes neuronal survival but not behavioral recovery in the transected and Schwann cell implanted rat thoracic spinal cordJ Neurotrauma2004211415143010.1089/neu.2004.21.1415<?supplied-pmid 15672632?>15672632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR112"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>112.PearseDDMarcilloAEOudegaMLynchMPWoodPMBungeMBTransplantation of Schwann cells and olfactory ensheathing glia after spinal cord injury: does pretreatment with methylprednisolone and interleukin-10 enhance recovery?J Neurotrauma2004211223123910.1089/0897715041953876<?supplied-pmid 15453992?>15453992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR113"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>113.PearseDDPereiraFCMarcilloAEcAMP and Schwann cells promote axonal growth and functional recovery after spinal cord injuryNat Med20041061061610.1038/nm1056<?supplied-pmid 15156204?>15156204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR114"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>114.FouadKSchnellLBungeMBSchwabMELiebscherTPearseDDCombining Schwann cell bridges and olfactory-ensheathing glia grafts with chondroitinase promotes locomotor recovery after complete transection of the spinal cordJ Neurosci2005251169117810.1523/JNEUROSCI.3562-04.2005<?supplied-pmid 15689553?>15689553 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR115"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>115.SaberiHMoshayediPAghayanHRTreatment of chronic thoracic spinal cord injury patients with autologous Schwann cell transplantation: an interim report on safety considerations and possible outcomesNeurosci Lett2008443465010.1016/j.neulet.2008.07.041<?supplied-pmid 18662744?>18662744 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR116"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>116.SchaalSMKitayBMChoKSSchwann cell transplantation improves reticulospinal axon growth and forelimb strength after severe cervical spinal cord contusionCell Transplant200716207228<?supplied-pmid 17503734?>17503734 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR117"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>117.GuestJDHesseDSchnellLSchwabMEBungeMBBungeRPInfluence of IN-1 antibody and acidic FGF-fibrin glue on the response of injured corticospinal tract axons to human Schwann cell graftsJ Neurosci Res19975088890510.1002/(SICI)1097-4547(19971201)50:5&lt;888::AID-JNR24&gt;3.0.CO;2-W<?supplied-pmid 9418975?>9418975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR118"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>118.GuestJDRaoAOlsonLBungeMBBungeRPThe ability of human Schwann cell grafts to promote regeneration in the transected nude rat spinal cordExp Neurol199714850252210.1006/exnr.1997.6693<?supplied-pmid 9417829?>9417829 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR119"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>119.KohamaILankfordKLPreiningerovaJWhiteFAVollmerTLKocsisJDTransplantation of cryopreserved adult human Schwann cells enhances axonal conduction in demyelinated spinal cordJ Neurosci200121944950<?supplied-pmid 11157080?>11157080 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR120"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>120.BrierleyCMCrangAJIwashitaYRemyelination of demyelinated CNS axons by transplanted human schwann cells: the deleterious effect of contaminating fibroblastsCell Transplant200110305315<?supplied-pmid 11437076?>11437076 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR121"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>121.HalfpennyCBennTScoldingNCell transplantation, myelin repair, and multiple sclerosisLancet Neurol20021314010.1016/S1474-4422(02)00004-2<?supplied-pmid 12849543?>12849543 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR122"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>122.IkegamiTNakamuraMYamaneJChondroitinase ABC combined with neural stem/progenitor cell transplantation enhances graft cell migration and outgrowth of growth-associated protein-43-positive fibers after rat spinal cord injuryEur J Neurosci2005223036304610.1111/j.1460-9568.2005.04492.x<?supplied-pmid 16367770?>16367770 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR123"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>123.Karimi-AbdolrezaeeSEftekharpourEWangJSchutDFehlingsMGSynergistic effects of transplanted adult neural stem/progenitor cells, chondroitinase, and growth factors promote functional repair and plasticity of the chronically injured spinal cordJ Neurosci2010301657167610.1523/JNEUROSCI.3111-09.2010<?supplied-pmid 20130176?>20130176 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR124"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>124.BottaiDMadaschiLDi GiulioAMGorioAViability-dependent promoting action of adult neural precursors in spinal cord injuryMol Med20081463464410.2119/2008-00077.Bottai<?supplied-pmid 18654659?>18654659 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR125"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>125.HofstetterCPHolmstromNALiljaJAAllodynia limits the usefulness of intraspinal neural stem cell grafts; directed differentiation improves outcomeNat Neurosci2005834635310.1038/nn1405<?supplied-pmid 15711542?>15711542 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR126"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>126.OkadaSIshiiKYamaneJIn vivo imaging of engrafted neural stem cells: its application in evaluating the optimal timing of transplantation for spinal cord injuryFaseb J20051918391841<?supplied-pmid 16141363?>16141363 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR127"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>127.MitchellKEWeissMLMitchellBMMatrix cells from Wharton's jelly form neurons and gliaStem Cells200321506010.1634/stemcells.21-1-50<?supplied-pmid 12529551?>12529551 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR128"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>128.WangHSHungSCPengSTMesenchymal stem cells in the Wharton's jelly of the human umbilical cordStem Cells2004221330133710.1634/stemcells.2004-0013<?supplied-pmid 15579650?>15579650 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR129"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>129.WeissMLMedicettySBledsoeARHuman umbilical cord matrix stem cells: preliminary characterization and effect of transplantation in a rodent model of Parkinson's diseaseStem Cells20062478179210.1634/stemcells.2005-0330<?supplied-pmid 16223852?>16223852 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR130"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>130.La RoccaGAnzaloneRCorraoSIsolation and characterization of Oct-4+/HLA-G + mesenchymal stem cells from human umbilical cord matrix: differentiation potential and detection of new markersHistochem Cell Biol200913126728210.1007/s00418-008-0519-3<?supplied-pmid 18836737?>18836737 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR131"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>131.VawdaRKenneaNKMehmetHPottenCSClarkeRBWilsonJRenehanAGStem cells in neurodegeneration and injuryTissue stem cells2006LondonTaylor &amp; Francis Pubs271293 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR132"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>132.VawdaRWoodburyJCoveyMLevisonSWMehmetHStem cell therapies for perinatal brain injuriesSemin Fetal Neonatal Med20071225927210.1016/j.siny.2007.02.003<?supplied-pmid 17553762?>17553762 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR133"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>133.TroyerDLWeissMLWharton's jelly-derived cells are a primitive stromal cell populationStem Cells20082659159910.1634/stemcells.2007-0439<?supplied-pmid 18065397?>18065397 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR134"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>134.WeissMLAndersonCMedicettySImmune properties of human umbilical cord Wharton's jelly-derived cellsStem Cells2008262865287410.1634/stemcells.2007-1028<?supplied-pmid 18703664?>18703664 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR135"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>135.WeissMLMitchellKEHixJETransplantation of porcine umbilical cord matrix cells into the rat brainExp Neurol200318228829910.1016/S0014-4886(03)00128-6<?supplied-pmid 12895440?>12895440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR136"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>136.LundRDWangSLuBCells isolated from umbilical cord tissue rescue photoreceptors and visual functions in a rodent model of retinal diseaseStem Cells20072560261110.1634/stemcells.2006-0308<?supplied-pmid 17053209?>17053209 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR137"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>137.FongCYGauthamanKBongsoATeratomas from pluripotent stem cells: A clinical hurdleJ Cell Biochem201011176978110.1002/jcb.22775<?supplied-pmid 20665544?>20665544 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR138"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>138.GantaCChiyoDAyuzawaRRat umbilical cord stem cells completely abolish rat mammary carcinomas with no evidence of metastasis or recurrence 100 days post-tumor cell inoculationCancer Res2009691815182010.1158/0008-5472.CAN-08-2750<?supplied-pmid 19244122?>19244122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR139"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>139.AyuzawaRDoiCRachakatlaRSNaive human umbilical cord matrix derived stem cells significantly attenuate growth of human breast cancer cells in vitro and in vivoCancer Lett2009280313710.1016/j.canlet.2009.02.011<?supplied-pmid 19285791?>19285791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR140"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>140.YangCCShihYHKoMHHsuSYChengHFuYSTransplantation of human umbilical mesenchymal stem cells from Wharton's jelly after complete transection of the rat spinal cordPLoS ONE20083e333610.1371/journal.pone.0003336<?supplied-pmid 18852872?>18852872 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR141"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>141.Zhang L, Zhang HT, Hong SQ, Ma X, Jiang XD, Xu RX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Cografted Wharton's jelly cells-derived neurospheres and BDNF promote functional recovery after rat spinal cord transection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Neurochem Res 2009. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR142"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>142.CampagnoliCRobertsIAKumarSBennettPRBellantuonoIFiskNMIdentification of mesenchymal stem/progenitor cells in human first-trimester fetal blood, liver, and bone marrowBlood2001982396240210.1182/blood.V98.8.2396<?supplied-pmid 11588036?>11588036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR143"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>143.Le BlancKGotherstromCRingdenOFetal mesenchymal stem-cell engraftment in bone after in utero transplantation in a patient with severe osteogenesis imperfectaTransplantation2005791607161410.1097/01.TP.0000159029.48678.93<?supplied-pmid 15940052?>15940052 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR144"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>144.TomaJGAkhavanMFernandesKJIsolation of multipotent adult stem cells from the dermis of mammalian skinNat Cell Biol2001377878410.1038/ncb0901-778<?supplied-pmid 11533656?>11533656 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR145"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>145.TomaJGMcKenzieIABagliDMillerFDIsolation and characterization of multipotent skin-derived precursors from human skinStem Cells20052372773710.1634/stemcells.2004-0134<?supplied-pmid 15917469?>15917469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR146"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>146.FernandesKJMcKenzieIAMillPA dermal niche for multipotent adult skin-derived precursor cellsNat Cell Biol200461082109310.1038/ncb1181<?supplied-pmid 15517002?>15517002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR147"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>147.BiernaskieJAMcKenzieIATomaJGMillerFDIsolation of skin-derived precursors (SKPs) and differentiation and enrichment of their Schwann cell progenyNat Protoc200612803281210.1038/nprot.2006.422<?supplied-pmid 17406538?>17406538 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR148"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>148.FernandesKJKobayashiNRGallagherCJAnalysis of the neurogenic potential of multipotent skin-derived precursorsExp Neurol2006201324810.1016/j.expneurol.2006.03.018<?supplied-pmid 16678161?>16678161 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR149"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>149.FernandesKJMillerFDIsolation, expansion, and differentiation of mouse skin-derived precursorsMethods Mol Biol200948215917010.1007/978-1-59745-060-7_10<?supplied-pmid 19089355?>19089355 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR150"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>150.FernandesKJTomaJGMillerFDMultipotent skin-derived precursors: adult neural crest-related precursors with therapeutic potentialPhilos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci200836318519810.1098/rstb.2006.2020<?supplied-pmid 17282990?>17282990 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR151"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>151.BiernaskieJMillerFDWhite matter repair: skin-derived precursors as a source of myelinating cellsCan J Neurol Sci201037suppl 2S34S41<?supplied-pmid 21246933?>21246933 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR152"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>152.McKenzieIABiernaskieJTomaJGMidhaRMillerFDSkin-derived precursors generate myelinating Schwann cells for the injured and dysmyelinated nervous systemJ Neurosci2006266651666010.1523/JNEUROSCI.1007-06.2006<?supplied-pmid 16775154?>16775154 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR153"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>153.ZhangFCitraFWangDAProspects of induced pluripotent stem cell technology in regenerative medicineTissue Eng Part B Rev20111711512410.1089/ten.teb.2010.0549<?supplied-pmid 21210760?>21210760 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR154"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>154.SalewskiRPEftekharpourEFehlingsMGAre induced pluripotent stem cells the future of cell-based regenerative therapies for spinal cord injury?J Cell Physiol2010222515521<?supplied-pmid 20020443?>20020443 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR155"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>155.ParsonsXHTengYDSnyderEYImportant precautions when deriving patient-specific neural elements from pluripotent cellsCytotherapy20092511110.1080/14653240903180092 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR156"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>156.TsujiOMiuraKOkadaYTherapeutic potential of appropriately evaluated safe-induced pluripotent stem cells for spinal cord injuryProc Natl Acad Sci U S A2010107127041270910.1073/pnas.0910106107<?supplied-pmid 20615974?>20615974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR157"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>157.ZhaoTZhangZNRongZXuYImmunogenicity of induced pluripotent stem cellsNature201147421221510.1038/nature09971<?supplied-pmid 21572395?>21572395 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR158"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>158.MeletisKBarnabe-HeiderFCarlenMSpinal cord injury reveals multilineage differentiation of ependymal cellsPLoS Biol20086e18210.1371/journal.pbio.0060182<?supplied-pmid 18651793?>18651793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR159"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>159.HawrylukGWFehlingsMGThe center of the spinal cord may be central to its repairCell Stem Cell2008323023210.1016/j.stem.2008.08.009<?supplied-pmid 18786407?>18786407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR160"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>160.YamamotoSYamamotoNKitamuraTNakamuraKNakafukuMProliferation of parenchymal neural progenitors in response to injury in the adult rat spinal cordExp Neurol200117211512710.1006/exnr.2001.7798<?supplied-pmid 11681845?>11681845 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR161"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>161.MartensDJSeabergRMvan der KooyDIn vivo infusions of exogenous growth factors into the fourth ventricle of the adult mouse brain increase the proliferation of neural progenitors around the fourth ventricle and the central canal of the spinal cordEur J Neurosci2002161045105710.1046/j.1460-9568.2002.02181.x<?supplied-pmid 12383233?>12383233 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR162"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>162.DietrichWDConfirming an experimental therapy prior to transfer to humans: what is the ideal?J Rehabil Res Dev2003404 suppl 1636910.1682/JRRD.2003.08.0063<?supplied-pmid 15077650?>15077650 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR163"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>163.FawcettJWCurtASteevesJDGuidelines for the conduct of clinical trials for spinal cord injury as developed by the ICCP panel: spontaneous recovery after spinal cord injury and statistical power needed for therapeutic clinical trialsSpinal Cord20074519020510.1038/sj.sc.3102007<?supplied-pmid 17179973?>17179973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR164"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>164.LammertseDTuszynskiMHSteevesJDGuidelines for the conduct of clinical trials for spinal cord injury as developed by the ICCP panel: clinical trial designSpinal Cord20074523224210.1038/sj.sc.3102010<?supplied-pmid 17179970?>17179970 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR165"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>165.SteevesJDLammertseDCurtAGuidelines for the conduct of clinical trials for spinal cord injury (SCI) as developed by the ICCP panel: clinical trial outcome measuresSpinal Cord20074520622110.1038/sj.sc.3102008<?supplied-pmid 17179972?>17179972 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR166"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>166.TuszynskiMHSteevesJDFawcettJWGuidelines for the conduct of clinical trials for spinal cord injury as developed by the ICCP Panel: clinical trial inclusion/exclusion criteria and ethicsSpinal Cord20074522223110.1038/sj.sc.3102009<?supplied-pmid 17179971?>17179971 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR167"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>167.RoyNSClerenCSinghSKYangLBealMFGoldmanSAFunctional engraftment of human ES cell-derived dopaminergic neurons enriched by coculture with telomerase-immortalized midbrain astrocytesNat Med2006121259126810.1038/nm1495<?supplied-pmid 17057709?>17057709 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR168"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>168.AboodyKCapelaANiaziNSternJHTempleSTranslating stem cell studies to the clinic for CNS repair: current state of the art and the need for a Rosetta stoneNeuron20117059761310.1016/j.neuron.2011.05.007<?supplied-pmid 21609819?>21609819 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR169"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>169.HyunILindvallOAhrlund-RichterLNew ISSCR guidelines underscore major principles for responsible translational stem cell researchCell Stem Cell2008360760910.1016/j.stem.2008.11.009<?supplied-pmid 19041777?>19041777 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR170"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>170.ClementeCDWindleWFRegeneration of severed nerve fibers in the spinal cord of the adult catJ Comp Neurol195410169173110.1002/cne.901010304<?supplied-pmid 13233357?>13233357 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR171"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>171.WindleWFRegeneration in the spinal cord of the cat in relation to observations on a human subjectTrans Am Neurol Assoc1954132335<?supplied-pmid 13238376?>13238376 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR172"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>172.GuthLBrewerCRCollinsWFGoldbergerMEPerlERCriteria for evaluating spinal cord regeneration experimentsSurg Neurol198014392<?supplied-pmid 6893764?>6893764 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR173"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>173.ChengHCaoYOlsonLSpinal cord repair in adult paraplegic rats: partial restoration of hind limb functionScience199627351051310.1126/science.273.5274.510<?supplied-pmid 8662542?>8662542 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR174"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>174.NavarroRUsvaldDMotlikJChronic spinal compression model in mini pig: a systematic behavioral and quantitative neuropathological studyJ Crit Care201025e21-e </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR175"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>175.RaoreBFedericiTTaubJCervical multilevel intraspinal stem cell therapy: assessment of surgical risks in Gottingen minipigsSpine (Phila Pa 1976)201136E164E17110.1097/BRS.0b013e3181d77a4721099736 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR176"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>176.LimJHPiedrahitaJAJacksonLGhashghaeiTOlbyNJDevelopment of a model of sacrocaudal spinal cord injury in cloned Yucatan minipigs for cellular transplantation researchCell Reprogram201012689697<?supplied-pmid 21108536?>21108536 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR177"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>177.Guizar-Sahagun G, Grijalva I, Hernandez-Godinez B, et al. New approach for graded compression spinal cord injuries in Rhesus macaque: method feasibility and preliminary observations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>J Med Primatol 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR178"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>178.HamersFPKoopmansGCJoostenEACat Walk-assisted gait analysis in the assessment of spinal cord injuryJ Neurotrauma20062353754810.1089/neu.2006.23.537<?supplied-pmid 16629635?>16629635 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR179"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>179.Mackay-Sim A, St. John JA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>Olfactory ensheathing cells from the nose: Clinical application in human spinal cord injuries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>Exp Neurol 2010. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR180"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>180.JonesLAA phase 2 autologous cellular therapy trial in patients with acute, complete spinal cord injury: pragmatics, recruitment, and demographicsSpinal Cord20104879880710.1038/sc.2010.29<?supplied-pmid 20386555?>20386555 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
