<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3400600</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22829935</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-13971</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0041268</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy and Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Musculoskeletal System</subject><subj-group><subject>Muscle</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Population Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic Polymorphism</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Human Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Mitochondrial Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Mitochondrial Myopathy</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Research Design</subject><subj-group><subject>Cohort Studies</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Sports and Exercise Medicine</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Acyl Coenzyme A Synthetase Long-Chain 1 (ACSL1) Gene Polymorphism (rs6552828) and Elite Endurance Athletic Status: A Replication Study </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">ACSL1 Gene Polymorphism and Athletic Performance</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Yvert</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Zi-Hong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Santiago</surname><given-names>Catalina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Yang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yan-Chun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gómez-Gallego</surname><given-names>Félix</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fiuza-Luces</surname><given-names>Carmen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Verde</surname><given-names>Zoraida</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Muniesa</surname><given-names>Carlos A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oliván</surname><given-names>Jesús</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Santalla</surname><given-names>Alfredo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>Jonatan R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lucia</surname><given-names>Alejandro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biomedicine, European University of Madrid, Madrid, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Biology Center, China Institute of Sport Science, Beijing, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Science and Research Center of Beijing Sports University, Beijing, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Faculty of Sports Sciences, European University of Madrid, Madrid, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>
<addr-line>Faculty of Sports Sciences, Pabo de Olavide University, Seville, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff6">
<label>6</label>
<addr-line>Department of Physical Education and Sport, School of Sport Sciences, University of Granada, Granada, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff7">
<label>7</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biosciences and Nutrition at NOVUM, Unit for Preventive Nutrition, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Garatachea</surname><given-names>Nuria</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Zaragoza, Spain</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>alejandro.lucia@uem.es</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: ZHH CS JRR AL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: TY ZHH CS YH YCL FGG CFL ZV CAM JO AS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: TY ZHH JRR AL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: FGG ZHH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: AL JRR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Read the manuscript critically and approved it (all authors besides the 2 who wrote it): TY ZHH CS YH YCL FGG CFL ZV CAM JO AS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>7</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>e41268</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Yvert et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The aim of this study was to determine the association between the rs6552828 polymorphism in acyl coenzyme A synthetase (ACSL1) and elite endurance athletic status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>We studied 82 Caucasian (Spanish) World/Olympic-class endurance male athletes, and a group of sex and ethnically matched healthy young adults (controls, n = 197). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The analyses were replicated in a cohort of a different ethnic origin (Chinese of the Han ethnic group), composed of elite endurance athletes (runners) [cases, n = 241 (128 male)] and healthy sedentary adults [controls, n = 504 (267 male)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In the Spanish cohort, genotype (P = 0.591) and minor allele (A) frequencies were similar in cases and controls (P = 0.978). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>In the Chinese cohort, genotype (P = 0.973) and minor allele (G) frequencies were comparable in female endurance athletes and sedentary controls (P = 0.881), whereas in males the frequency of the G allele was higher in endurance athletes (0.40) compared with their controls (0.32, P = 0.040). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The odds ratio (95%CI) for an elite endurance Chinese athlete to carry the G allele compared with ethnically matched controls was 1.381 (1.015–1.880) (P-value = 0.04). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Our findings suggest that the ACSL1 gene polymorphism rs6552828 is not associated with elite endurance athletic status in Caucasians, yet a marginal association seems to exist for the Chinese (Han) male population. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="4"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Elite athletic status is a complex phenotype, with several genetic polymorphisms, many of which remain to be identified, contributing to athletic success, whether individually or in combination with other polymorphisms [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide association (GWA) can help identifying novel candidate polymorphisms associated with elite endurance status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>This type of studies evaluates association of genetic variation with outcomes or traits of interest by using 100,000 to 1 million or more markers across the genome without any previous hypotheses about potential mechanisms [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>A GWA study was recently conducted by Bouchard et al. [3] in sedentary Caucasians to study the association of 324,611 single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and the trainability of one of the main phenotype traits indicative of human endurance performance, i.e. maximal oxygen uptake (VO2max). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The strongest association with the training response of VO2max was found to acyl coenzyme A synthetase long-chain 1 (ACSL1) gene polymorphism (rs6552828). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The ACSL1 gene is a candidate to explain individual variability in endurance performance, as well as in some health-related phenotypes, owing to its potential role in aerobic metabolism at the adypocite, cardiomyocite, liver and skeletal muscle fiber level [4], [5], [6], [7], [8], [9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The findings of GWA studies should be further explored in genetic association studies focused on those SNPs showing the highest level of association [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Thus, the purpose of the present case:control study was to determine the association between the ACSL1 rs6552828 polymorphism and elite endurance athletic status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>To this end, we studied a cohort that comprised Caucasian (Spanish) World/Olympic-class endurance male athletes (cases), and sex and ethnically-matched healthy young adults (controls). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>We also studied a replication cohort of a different ethnic origin (Chinese of the Han ethnic group), composed of elite endurance athletes (cases), and healthy sedentary adults (controls). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Owing to the important putative role of ACSL1 in aerobic-related phenotypes [4], [5], [6], [7], [8], [9] we hypothesized that the ACSL1 rs6552828 polymorphism is associated with elite endurance athletic status. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The research project was in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki, it was approved by the corresponding University Review Boards [Universidad Europea de Madrid (UEM), Spain and China Institute of Sport Science (Beijing, China)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Written consent was obtained from each participant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Our study adhered to most of the recent guidelines for STrengthening the REporting of Genetic Association studies (STREGA), including issues such as replication, selection of participants, rationale for choice of genes and variants, statistical methods or relatedness [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s2a1"><title><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Spanish cohort </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The population [n = 383, all unrelated Spanish (Caucasian for ≥3 generations) healthy males] originally comprised: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>93 endurance elite athletes aged 19–39 years (cases). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>This sample included 22 elite endurance runners (mostly 5,000–10,000 m specialists). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>All had participated at least twice in previous Olympiads and 11 of them were medallists in previous World or Europe Championships. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Their mean±SD VO2max was 78.0±1.7 ml·kg−1·min−1 (range: 69, 87). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The sample also included 32 professional road cyclists who were all Tour de France finishers, included three top-3 finishers in this race and several stage winners in the three main tour races (Tour, Giro, Vuelta). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Their mean±SD maximal oxygen uptake (VO2max) was 74.5±1.7 ml·kg−1·min−1 (62, 86). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The endurance athletic cohort also comprised 39 rowers [VO2max: 71.7±0.8 ml·kg−1·min−1 (58, 87) or 5.2±0.1 L·min−1 (4.2, 6.0)] who were among the best in the World, i.e. each had won ≥ one bronze, silver or gold medal in the lightweight category (skip or scull, including a total of 6 gold medals) in the World Championships held during 1997–2006. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The mean VO2max of the whole athletic cohort was 73.7±6.4 ml·kg−1·min−1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>197 healthy, non-athletic controls aged 19–32 years (VO2max: 50.2±0.3 ml·kg−1·min−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>All were undergraduate Physical Education students from the same university (UEM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Inclusion and exclusion criteria for this group were to be free of any diagnosed cardiorespiratory disease and not to be engaged in competitive sports or in formal, supervised exercise training (i.e. performing less than 3 structured weekly sessions of strenuous exercise as running, swimming, bicycling, and weight lifting) or to have a family history of competitive sports participation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The VO2max values of runners, cyclists and rowers were obtained using a breath-by-breath system (Oxycon Pro System, Jaeger, Wuerzburg, Germany) in laboratory treadmill, cycle-ergometer or rower-ergometer tests performed until volitional exhaustion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The VO2max of controls was estimated from the time to complete 2,000 meter tests [11]; the tests were performed inside a 400-meter outdoor track under similar environmental conditions (temperature, ∼23–24°C; relative humidity, 45–55%; barometric pressure, ∼720 mmHg). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2a2"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Replication cohort </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The population [n = 751, men and women, all unrelated of Chinese descent (Han origin) for ≥3 generations] comprised: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>246 (131 men, 115 women) unrelated elite endurance runners aged 19 to 37 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>They were the best Chinese runners in middle-distance (1,500 m) (n = 18, 10 men, 8 women) 3,000 to 10,000 m track events (n = 164; 90 men, 74 women) and marathon in the last years (n = 64; 31 men, 33 women), including World record holders, and most of whom had participated in at least one World-championship or Olympiad. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>505 (267 men, 238 women) healthy unrelated control participants aged 19 to 23 years [non-athletic undergraduate students from the China Agricultural University (Beijing) with no self-reported history (or family history) of competitive sports participation]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Genotyping </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Our study followed recent recommendations for replicating genotype-phenotype association studies [12]: genotyping was performed specifically for research purposes, and the researchers in charge of genotyping were totally blinded to the participants' identities [DNA samples were tracked solely with bar-coding and personal identities were only made available to the main study researcher (in Spain or China) who was not involved in actual genotyping]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s2b1"><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Spanish cohort </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>We obtained DNA from participants' blood or saliva samples over years 2004–2008 and used the classical phenol-chloroform DNA extraction protocol with alcoholic precipitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA was resuspended in 50 µl milli-Q H2O and stored at −20°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Genotyping was performed during April–May 2011 in the Genetics laboratory of the UEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) amplification was performed using a StepOne™ Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Allelic discrimination analysis for the ACSL1 rs6552828 polymorphism was performed with predesigned Applied Biosystems TaqMan® SNP Genotyping Assays on demand (Assay ID: C__30469648_10). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b2"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Replication cohort </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>We obtained samples of peripheral whole blood from elite athletes (during years 2003 and 2004, and 2009–2010) and controls (2004 and 2011) and extracted genomic DNA using a Wizard Genomic DNA Purification Kit (Promega, Madison, Wisconsin, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Genotype analyses were performed during June–July 2011 in the Science and Research Centre of the Beijing Sports University (Beijing, China). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>For high-throughput genotyping of the ACSL1 rs6552828 polymorphism, we used a matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry (MALDI-TOF MS) platform (Sequenom, San Diego, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Primers for PCR and single base extension were designed by using the Assay Designer software package (Sequenom, San Diego, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The DNA sample was diluted to 5 ng/µl, and 1 µl of DNA was combined with 0.95 µl of water, 0.625 µl of PCR buffer containing 15 mM MgCl2, 1 µl of 2.5 mM dNTP, 0.325 ul of 25 mM MgCl2, 1 µl of PCR primers and 0.1 µl of 5units/µl HotStar Taq (Qiagen, Düsseldorf, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The PCR conditions were as follows: 94°C for 15 min followed by 45 cycles at 94°C 20 s, 56°C 30 s, and 72°C 1 min, and a final incubation at 72°C 3 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>After PCR amplification, the remaining dNTPs were dephosphorylated by adding1.53 µl of water, 0.17 µl of Shrimp Alkaline Phosphatase (SAP) buffer, and 0.3 units of SAP (Sequenom, San Diego, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The reaction was placed at 37°C for 40 min, and the enzyme was deactivated by incubation at 85°C for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Thereafter, the single base extension (SBE) over the SNP was combined with 0.755 µl of water, 0.2 µl of 10X iPLEX buffer (Sequenom, San Diego, CA, USA), 0.2 µl of termination mix, 0.041 µl of iPLEX enzyme (Sequenom, San Diego, CA, USA), and 0.804 µl of 10 µM extension primer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The SBE conditions were as follows: 94°C 30 s, 94°C 5 s, 5 cycles at 52°C for 5 s, 40 cycles at 80°C for 5 s, and final extension at 72°C for 3 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The reaction mix was desalted by adding 6 mg of cation exchange resin (Sequenom, San Diego, CA, USA), mixed and resuspended in 25 µl of water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The completed genotyping reactions were spotted onto a 384 well Spectro Chip using a MassARRAY® Nanodispenser and determined by a matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometer (Sequenom, San Diego, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Genotype calling was performed in real time with MassARRAY® RT software (version 3.0.0.4) and analyzed using the Massarray Typer software, version 3.4 (Sequenom, San Diego, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Genotypic and allele frequencies were compared among sedentary controls and endurance athletes using the χ2 test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>We used logistic regression analysis to analyse the association of the ACSL1 rs6552828 polymorphism with elite endurance athletic status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The analyses were conducted in Spanish and Chinese separately, and in the case of the Chinese population, the analyses were conducted separately for men and women. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>All statistical analyses were performed using the PASW (v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>18.0 for WINDOWS, Chicago) and the α was set at 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Spanish cohort </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>There were no failures in sample collection, DNA acquisition or genotyping procedures, except for 11 athletes, for which the amount of DNA gathered from saliva was insufficient to allow ACSL1 rs6552828 genotype assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Genotype distributions met Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) in both controls and athletes (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Genotype (P = 0.591) and minor allele (A) frequencies were similar in sedentary controls and athletes (P = 0.978). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The odds ratio (OR) and 95% confidence interval (95%CI) for the association between carriage of the A allele of the ACSL1 rs6552828 polymorphism and athletic status was 0.997 (0.819–1.214). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0041268-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0041268.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Genotype frequencies [n(%)] of ACSL1 rs6552828 polymorphism in Spanish controls (n = 197) and elite endurance athletes (n = 82). </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0041268-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0041268.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Controls </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Endurance </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>AA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>25 (12.7%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>14 (17.1%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>AG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>98 (49.7%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>37 (45.1%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>GG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>74 (37.6%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>31 (37.8%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>MAF </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>0.37 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>0.39 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>HWE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>0.395 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>0.605 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>MAF, minor allele frequency (A); HWE, Hardy Weinberg Equilibrium. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Genotype: χ2 = 1.052, P = 0.591; Allele: χ2 = 0.001, P = 0.978. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Replication cohort </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>There were no failures in sample collection, DNA acquisition or genotyping procedures, except for 1 participant (female) in the control group, and 5 (3 male, 2 female) in the athlete's group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Genotype distributions were in HWE except for male endurance athletes (P = 0.035, Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>In females, genotypic (P = 0.973) and allele frequencies (P = 0.881) were similar in endurance and controls, whereas in males both genotypic (P = 0.019) and allelic (P = 0.040) differed in endurance and controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The odds ratio (95%CI) for an elite endurance Chinese athlete of having the G allele compared with ethnically-matched controls was 0.975 (0.697–1.364, P = 0.881) for females, whereas in males, the odds ratio of having the G allele was 1.381 (1.015–1.880, P = 0.04). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0041268-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0041268.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Genotype frequencies [n(%)] of ACSL1 rs6552828 polymorphism in Chinese controls (n = 504, 267 men, 237 women) and elite endurance athletes (n = 241, 128 men, 113 women). </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0041268-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0041268.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Controls </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Endurance </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Males </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>AA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>122 (45.7%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>40 (31.3%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>AG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>115 (43.1%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>73 (57.0%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>GG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>30 (11.2%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>15 (11.7%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>MAF </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>0.32 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>0.40 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>HWE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>0.712 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>0.035 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Females </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>AA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>102 (43.0) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>49 (43.4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>AG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>110 (46.4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>53 (46.9) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>GG </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>25 (10.5) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>11 (9.7) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>MAF </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>0.33 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>0.33 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>HWE </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>0.560 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>0.539 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>MAF, minor allele frequency (G); HWE, Hardy Weinberg Equilibrium. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Males: Genotype: χ2 = 7.961, P = 0.019; Allele: χ2 = 4.226, P = 0.040. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Females: Genotype: χ2 = 0.055, P = 0.973; Allele: χ2 = 0.022, P = 0.881. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The main finding of our study was that the ACSL1 rs6552828 SNP, located in the first intron of the ACSL1 gene, 715 bp and 718 bp upstream of exon 2 and the start codon, respectively, was not associated with elite endurance athletic status in Spanish men, yet a marginal association was found in Chinese men. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The ACSL1 gene is a putative candidate to explain individual variability in endurance performance, as well as in some health related phenotypes, owing to its potential role in aerobic metabolic adaptations to regular exercise, at the adypocite, cardiomyocite, liver and skeletal muscle fiber level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Long-chain acyl coenzyme A (acyl-CoA) synthetase (ACSL) isoenzymes, of which ACSL1 is the main and most studied isoenzyme convert free fatty acids (FFA) to acyl coenzyme A (acyl-CoA) in an ATP-dependent manner, simultaneously activating and trapping FFA within cells [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Activation of FFA to acyl-CoA is required before FFAs can be oxidized to provide ATP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>ACSL1 is highly expressed in major energy-metabolizing tissues such as fat, liver, and skeletal muscles [5], [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Recent research also supports evidence for an important role of ACSL1 in heart metabolism [14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The role of ACSL1 in FFA oxidation in different tissues has been shown using transgenic mice models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Mice lacking ACSL1 specifically in adipose tissue have defects in adipose FFA oxidation [9], whereas those unable to express ACSL1 in heart ventricles show compensatory catabolism of glucose and amino acids leading to mTOR activation and cardiac hypertrophy without lipid accumulation or dysfunction [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>In contrast, mice overexpressing ACSL1 specifically at the heart level show markedly impaired metabolic homeostasis with accumulation of triglycerides and phospholipids [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>ACSL1 is a candidate to explain individual differences in some several disease and endurance exercise-related phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Recent research has shown that the ACSL1 rs9997745 polymorphism influences the risk of metabolic disease, most likely via disturbances in FFA metabolism [16]; no individual or combined association was however found for other SNPs of this gene, i.e. rs4862417, rs13120078, rs12503643 and the one we studied here, rs6552828. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>A GWA study recently conducted by Bouchard et al. [3] on 324,611 SNPs identified a set of 21 SNPs accounting for 49% of the variance in the trainability of VO2max [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The strongest association with the training response of VO2max was found to ACSL1 rs6552828. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>In the single-SNP analyses, rs6552828 explained 6.1% of the variance in the response of VO2max. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Homozygotes of the rs6552828 minor allele (AA) had 125 mL/min (−28%) and 63 mL/min (−17%) lower VO2max response than the common allele homozygotes (GG) and the heterozygotes (AG) respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, in our study the A allele was less frequent in elite male endurance Chinese athletes compared with their controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>It must be also kept in mind that the A allele was the major allele in the Chinese cohort, which highlights inter-ethnic differences in genotype distributions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, there is no functional data on the rs6552828 SNP; thus, we can only speculate about mechanisms underlying our findings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The intronic location of this SNP has the potential to affect mRNA stability or to modulate ACSL1 gene transcriptional activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Indeed, non-coding SNPs could regulate the alternative splicing of mRNA leading to changes in gene expression [17] and phenotype traits [18], [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Non-coding SNPs can also influence the binding of transcription factors [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Another possibility is that the ACSL1 is part of the group of candidate genes, among which are calcineurin genes [21], but many of which are yet to be identified, whose cumulative effect explains, at least partly, individual variations in endurance performance in the Chinese Han population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>It could also be possible that the rs6552828 SNP may be a surrogate marker for other functional ACSL1 SNPs in the region. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>We believe the results of our study are overall valid, as all the following criteria were met [2]: cases clearly presented the main study phenotype (i.e. being an elite athlete), as we studied some of the best elite endurance athletes world-wide, participants within both cohorts were ethnically-matched, genetic assessment was accurate and unbiased, genotype distributions were in HWE in the control group of the two cohorts, and we used a replication cohort of a different ethnic origin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Current body of knowledge on genetic factors associated with exercise phenotypes and athletic status comes mainly from research performed on Caucasian populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Further investigations are thus needed with other ethnic groups and populations as the one studied here, i.e. representing an important fraction of the total planet population. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>In summary, our findings suggest that the ACSL1 gene polymorphism rs6552828 is marginally associated with male elite endurance status in Chinese (Han) population yet such association was not found in Chinese females or in a different (Caucasian) cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Our findings exemplify the need for further genetic association studies in the field of sport sciences to use at least two cohorts of a different ethnic background in order to increase the generalisability of their results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: Co-authors Alejandro Lucia and Jonatan R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Ruiz are PLoS ONE Editorial Board members. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>This does not alter the authors' adherence to all the PLoS ONE policies on sharing data and materials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Funding: The present study was funded by the Consejo Superior de Deportes (grant #UPR12) Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation (RYC-2010-05957) and Fondo de Investigaciones Sanitarias (ref. # PS09/00194), and grants from China Institute of Sport Science (Grant code: 2011-03) and grants from Ministry of Science and Technology of the People's Republic of China (Grant code: 2003BA904B04). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0041268-Eynon1"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>1 EynonNRuizJROliveiraJDuarteJABirkR 2011 Genes and elite athletes: a roadmap for future research. J Physiol 589 3063 3070 21540342 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Attia1"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>2 AttiaJIoannidisJPThakkinstianAMcEvoyMScottRJ 2009 How to use an article about genetic association: B: Are the results of the study valid? JAMA 301 191 197 19141767 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Bouchard1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>3 BouchardCSarzynskiMARiceTKKrausWEChurchTS 2011 Genomic predictors of the maximal O2 uptake response to standardized exercise training programs. J Appl Physiol 110 1160 1170 21183627 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Hall1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>4 HallAMSmithAJBernlohrDA 2003 Characterization of the Acyl-CoA synthetase activity of purified murine fatty acid transport protein 1. J Biol Chem 278 43008 43013 12937175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Coleman1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>5 ColemanRALewinTMMuoioDM 2000 Physiological and nutritional regulation of enzymes of triacylglycerol synthesis. Annu Rev Nutr 20 77 103 10940327 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Mashek1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>6 MashekDGLiLOColemanRA 2006 Rat long-chain acyl-CoA synthetase mRNA, protein, and activity vary in tissue distribution and in response to diet. J Lipid Res 47 2004 2010 16772660 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Martin1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>7 MartinGSchoonjansKLefebvreAMStaelsBAuwerxJ 1997 Coordinate regulation of the expression of the fatty acid transport protein and acyl-CoA synthetase genes by PPARalpha and PPARgamma activators. J Biol Chem 272 28210 28217 9353271 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Schoonjans1"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>8 SchoonjansKStaelsBAuwerxJ 1996 Role of the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor (PPAR) in mediating the effects of fibrates and fatty acids on gene expression. J Lipid Res 37 907 925 8725145 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Ellis1"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>9 EllisJMLiLOWuPCKovesTRIlkayevaO 2010 Adipose acyl-CoA synthetase-1 directs fatty acids toward beta-oxidation and is required for cold thermogenesis. Cell Metab 12 53 64 20620995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Little1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>10 LittleJHigginsJPIoannidisJPMoherDGagnonF 2009 Strengthening the reporting of genetic association studies (STREGA): an extension of the STROBE Statement. Hum Genet 125 131 151 19184668 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Daniels1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>11 DanielsJGilbertJR 1979 Oxygen Power: Performance Tables for Distance Runners. Oxygen Power 5 15  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Chanock1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>12 ChanockSJManolioTBoehnkeMBoerwinkleEHunterDJ 2007 Replicating genotype-phenotype associations. Nature 447 655 660 17554299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Black1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>13 BlackPNDiRussoCC 2003 Transmembrane movement of exogenous long-chain fatty acids: proteins, enzymes, and vectorial esterification. Microbiol Mol Biol Rev 67 454 472 table of contents 12966144 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Ellis2"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>14 EllisJMMentockSMDepetrilloMAKovesTRSenS 2011 Mouse cardiac acyl coenzyme a synthetase 1 deficiency impairs Fatty Acid oxidation and induces cardiac hypertrophy. Mol Cell Biol 31 1252 1262 21245374 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Chiu1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>15 ChiuHCKovacsAFordDAHsuFFGarciaR 2001 A novel mouse model of lipotoxic cardiomyopathy. J Clin Invest 107 813 822 11285300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Phillips1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>16 PhillipsCMGoumidiLBertraisSFieldMRCupplesLA 2010 Gene-nutrient interactions with dietary fat modulate the association between genetic variation of the ACSL1 gene and metabolic syndrome. J Lipid Res 51 1793 1800 20176858 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Mercado1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>17 MercadoPAAyalaYMRomanoMBurattiEBaralleFE 2005 Depletion of TDP 43 overrides the need for exonic and intronic splicing enhancers in the human apoA-II gene. Nucleic Acids Res 33 6000 6010 16254078 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Sasabe1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>18 SasabeTFurukawaAMatsusitaSHiguchiSIshiuraS 2007 Association analysis of the dopamine receptor D2 (DRD2) SNP rs1076560 in alcoholic patients. Neurosci Lett 412 139 142 17196743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Saxena1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>19 SaxenaRVoightBFLyssenkoVBurttNPde BakkerPI 2007 Genome-wide association analysis identifies loci for type 2 diabetes and triglyceride levels. Science 316 1331 1336 17463246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-Knight1"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>20 KnightJC 2005 Regulatory polymorphisms underlying complex disease traits. J Mol Med 83 97 109 15592805 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0041268-He1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="?"><plain>21 HeZHHuYLiYCYvertTSantiagoC 2011 Are calcineurin genes associated with athletic status? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>A function, replication study. Med Sci Sports Exerc 43 1433 1440 21233773 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
