<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plospath</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Pathogens</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7366</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7374</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3020925</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21249233</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PLPA-RA-3770R3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1001256</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Virology</subject><subject>Virology/Host Invasion and Cell Entry</subject><subject>Virology/Virion Structure, Assembly, and Egress</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>HCMV Spread and Cell Tropism are Determined by Distinct Virus Populations </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">HCMV Virus Populations</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Scrivano</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sinzger</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nitschko</surname><given-names>Hans</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koszinowski</surname><given-names>Ulrich H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>Barbara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Max von Pettenkofer-Institut für Virologie, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München, München, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Institut für Medizinische Virologie, Eberhard Karls Universität Tübingen, Tübingen, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Britt</surname><given-names>William J.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Alabama at Birmingham, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>adlerb@lmb.uni-muenchen.de</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: LS BA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: LS CS HN BA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: UHK BA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: BA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e1001256</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>7</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Scrivano et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) can infect many different cell types in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Two gH/gL complexes are used for entry into cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) shows no selectivity for its host cell, whereas formation of a gH/gL/gO complex only restricts the tropism mainly to fibroblasts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Here, we describe that depending on the cell type in which virus replication takes place, virus carrying the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex is either released or retained cell-associated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>We observed that virus spread in fibroblast cultures was predominantly supernatant-driven, whereas spread in endothelial cell (EC) cultures was predominantly focal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>This was due to properties of virus released from fibroblasts and EC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Fibroblasts released virus which could infect both fibroblasts and EC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In contrast, EC released virus which readily infected fibroblasts, but was barely able to infect EC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The EC infection capacities of virus released from fibroblasts or EC correlated with respectively high or low amounts of gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) in virus particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Moreover, we found that focal spread in EC cultures could be attributed to EC-tropic virus tightly associated with EC and not released into the supernatant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Preincubation of fibroblast-derived virus progeny with EC or beads coated with pUL131A-specific antibodies depleted the fraction that could infect EC, and left a fraction that could predominantly infect fibroblasts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>These data strongly suggest that HCMV progeny is composed of distinct virus populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>EC specifically retain the EC-tropic population, whereas fibroblasts release EC-tropic and non EC-tropic virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Our findings offer completely new views on how HCMV spread may be controlled by its host cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Author Summary </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>gH/gL complexes of herpesviruses are supposed to promote fusion of the viral envelope with cellular membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The gH/gL core complex associates with additional proteins which define the tropism for certain cell types by promoting binding to specific receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Two alternative gH/gL complexes of human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) define the cell tropism, the entry pathway and the spread of virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Formation of a gH/gL/gO complex during infection determines release of infectious virus into the supernatant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex determines the tropism for endothelial cells (EC) and promotes focal spread. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Here, we could show that HCMV-infected cells produce EC-tropic and non EC-tropic virus populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>While fibroblasts release both populations into the supernatant, EC predominantly release the non EC-tropic population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Different host cells of HCMV thus may direct the distribution of virus progeny. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) is ubiquitously distributed in the human population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In immunocompetent adults infections are mainly asymptomatic, but in immunocompromised patients like transplant recipients or AIDS patients life threatening infections occur at a high rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>HCMV is also the leading cause of birth defects among congenitally transmitted viral infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>HCMV replicates in vivo and in vitro in many different host cells including epithelial cells, connective tissue cells, hepatocytes, various leukocyte populations and vascular endothelial cells (reviewed in [1]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The broad host cell range implicates that either an ubiquitous cellular receptor, recognized by one protein or protein complex in the viral envelope, mediates entry, or that HCMV uses elaborate combinations of different viral envelope proteins to employ different cellular receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>More than 10 glycoproteins have been identified in HCMV particles [2], including the essential glycoproteins gB, gH, gL, gM and gN, which all play a role in the virus entry process [3]–[7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Although a number of cellular surface proteins have been identified to bind these envelope proteins and play a role in virus particle attachment or promoting intracellular signaling after binding [8]–[13], none of them is currently considered to be a functional entry receptor. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The best candidates for binding to entry receptors are the HCMV gH/gL complexes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The gH/gL complex has been shown to promote fusion of cellular membranes [7] and can either form a gH/gL/gO [14], [15] or a gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex [16]–[18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>HCMV isolates from patients are consistently able to form both gH/gL complexes [19], [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>In contrast, many HCMV laboratory strains express only the gH/gL/gO complex, which restricts virus entry to few cell types like fibroblasts and neuronal cells [21], [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Leukocytes, dendritic, epithelial and endothelial cells (EC) can only be infected by virus expressing the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex [16], [17], [22], [23], which can also promote infection of fibroblasts [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Virus strains expressing only gH/gL/gO enter fibroblasts through fusion at the plasma membrane [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>When fibroblast infection is promoted by gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) only, then entry is through pH-sensitive endocytosis [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>It is currently not clear whether gH/gL/gO complexes exert their function by directly initiating entry [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>gO has been shown to be incorporated in the virus envelope of the HCMV strain AD169, a laboratory strain which does not express the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex [2], [27], but not in the envelope of the clinical isolate TR [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Deletion of gO in a virus background, which still allows formation of the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex, strongly impairs release of infectious virus particles from infected cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Virus spread becomes focal and dependent on the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex [24], [26], [28]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the gH/gL/gO complex, the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex has been found to be consistently incorporated into virions [16]–[18], [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The exact roles of the individual proteins of the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex are not known, but pUL128, pUL130 and pUL131A are all needed to form a functional complex with gH/gL and to have this complex incorporated into virions [16]–[18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Although the data are controversal, the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex very likely promotes entry into endothelial and epithelial cells through an endocytotic pathway [30]–[33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>There is also good evidence for epithelial cells that binding and uptake of virus is promoted through a cell type-specific receptor for the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Viruses lacking both, gO and pUL(128,130,131A), are not viable, indicating that at least one of the two gH/gL complexes is needed for infection [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>It is not known whether both gH/gL complexes are incorporated in one particle or whether they are incorporated into distinct particles, and how the usage of the complexes for entry is regulated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The formation of distinct gH/gL complexes is not restricted to HCMV and has also been described for EBV and HHV-6 [35], [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>For EBV, a gH/gL/gp42 and a gp42-negative gH/gL complex have been described. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The latter binds to integrins αvß6 and αvß8 and promotes entry into epithelial cells by fusion at the plasma membrane [37]–[39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The gH/gL/gp42 complex binds to HLA-DR ß and promotes entry into B-cells by an endocytotic route [38]–[40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>During virus production in B-cells, gp42 is intracellularly targeted to HLA-DR ß, where it is vulnerable for degradation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Consequently, B-cells release virus particles, which are low in gH/gL/gp42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>This virus is directed towards epithelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Epithelial cells on the other hand do not express HLA-DR ß and produce virus which is high in gH/gL/gp42 and is directed to B-cells [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Thus, the EBV host cell tropism is switched by alternate replication in B- or epithelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>For HHV-6 a gH/gL/gO and a gH/gL/Q1/Q2 complex have been identified [36], [41], [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The latter has a high affinity for the HHV-6 cellular receptor CD46 [41], whereas the gH/gL/gO complex does not bind CD46 [36]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Here, we show that, similar to EBV, also HCMV progenies derived from different cell types differ in their cell tropism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Fibroblast-derived virus progeny could readily infect fibroblasts and EC, whereas EC-derived virus progeny was barely able to infect EC, and this difference in tropism was reflected by a respectively high or low content of the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex in virus particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>EC-tropism could be depleted from fibroblast-derived virus progeny, indicating that this progeny is composed of distinct populations of virus particles with different EC infection capacities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Spread patterns in culture and cell disruption experiments indicated that fibroblasts readily released EC-tropic and non EC-tropic virus particles, whereas EC selectively retained the EC-tropic population. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>HCMV shows different spread patterns in fibroblast and EC cultures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>When fibroblasts and EC are infected with HCMV in vitro, virus homogeneously spreads in fibroblast cultures whereas spread in endothelial cell cultures stays focal [17], [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Here, we infected fibroblasts and EC with the HCMV strains VR1814 and TB40/E, two clinical isolates passaged on endothelial cells, and vTB40-BAC4, a virus derived from TB40/E and cloned as a bacterial artificial chromosome (BAC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Infections were performed at a low multiplicity of infection (m.o.i.), and 2 or 8 days after infection cells were stained for HCMV immediate early 1 (ie1) protein expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Numbers of initially infected HFF or EC were comparable (Fig. 1A, VR1814, day 2 and data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>When fibroblasts were infected, HCMV homogeneously spread throughout the culture indicating release of virus from infected cells and infection via free supernatant virus (Fig. 1A, day 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>In contrast, EC infection remained focal indicating virus transmission which delivers virus particles from cell-to-cell, without releasing it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>This spread pattern in EC cultures was comparable for all HCMV strains tested and independent of whether a microvascular cell line (TIME) or primary macrovascular endothelial cells (HUVEC) were infected (Fig. 1A, day 8, lower panels). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Focal spread in EC cultures could be completely inhibited by neutralizing anti-HCMV antibodies in human serum or anti-pUL131A antibodies (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>S1), indicating that virus spread in EC cultures was not due to direct cell-to-cell spread. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Spread in fibroblast cultures was restricted from supernatant-driven spread to focal spread by human antiserum and not inhibited at all by anti-pUL131A antibodies (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1001256-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1001256.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>HCMV spread in fibroblast and EC cultures. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>(A) HFF, TIME cells and HUVEC were infected with VR1814, TB40/E and vTB40-BAC4 as described in Materials and Methods to obtain equal numbers of initially infected cells (m.o.i. on HFF: 0.1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The initial infection (day 2) as well as virus spread (day 8) were monitored by staining for HCMV ie1 protein expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>(B) Growth curves of vTB40-BAC4 on HFF, TIME cells and HUVEC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Cells were infected as described in Materials and Methods to obtain equal numbers of initially infected cells (m.o.i. on HFF: 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Cell culture supernatants were harvested at the indicated time points post infection and virus titers determined by a TCID50 assay performed on HFF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>(C) Infection capacities of supernatant-derived vTB40-BAC4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>HFF, TIME cells and HUVEC were infected at an m.o.i. of 1 with day 8 supernatants obtained from the growth curves under (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Infection capacities were monitored by staining for ie1 protein expression 48 hours post infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Except where indicated, supernatants used for infection were titrated by a TCID50 assay on HFF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1001256.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>To test whether the focal spread could be attributed to differences in release of infectious virus, we performed growth curves of vTB40-BAC4 on HFF, TIME cells and HUVEC, and measured virus release into the supernatants by titration on fibroblasts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>HFF and EC equally released high amounts of virus into their supernatants (Fig. 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>As spread of infection in EC cultures was focal although EC released virus in abundance, focal spread might be due to the inability of EC supernatant virus to infect EC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Indeed, although HFF and EC supernatants comparably infected fibroblasts, the capacities of EC-derived supernatants to infect EC were very low (Fig. 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>In the experiment shown, spread in HUVEC cultures appeared more cell-associated than in TIME cell cultures, where also single cells in between foci were ie1-positive (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>This correlated with the lower HUVEC infection capacity of EC-derived supernatants when compared to the TIME cell infection capacity (Fig. 1C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Quantification of HCMV infection capacities using a TB40-BAC4-derived virus expressing firefly luciferase </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Infection capacities on different cell types are often compared by methods, which depend on counting infected cells which are either stained for viral antigen or GFP- expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>These methods reach their technical limits, when the infection capacities strongly differ on the cell types to be tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>It is very difficult to obtain reliable cell counts on the less permissive cell type, without at the same time saturating infection on the more permissive cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Saturation yet, would lead to an overestimation of the infection capacity on the less permissive cells, when related to the more permissive cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>To circumvent these problems and to simplify the analysis, we used a luciferase reporter virus to monitor infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>An SV40 promoter-driven luciferase expression cassette was inserted into BAC4-FRT5-9, a TB40-BAC4-derived BACmid lacking the genes UL5 to UL9 and carrying an FRT site at the position of the deleted locus (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>S2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Virus was reconstituted from BAC4-FRT5-9 (vBAC4-FRT5-9) and BAC4-luc (vBAC4-luc). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Virus growth of these mutants in HFF and EC was comparable to growth of the parental vTB40-BAC4 (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>S2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Both, vBAC4-FRT5-9 and vBAC4-luc, also showed comparable spread patterns in HFF and EC cultures (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>S2C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>We used vBAC4-luc to evaluate EC and fibroblast infection capacities of virus preparations on HFF and TIME cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The luciferase signals obtained from HFF and TIME cell infections were related to each other and expressed as TIME/HFF infection ratios, and thus, represent relative EC infection capacities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>After infection, phosphono acetic acid (PAA) was added to block the viral DNA replication and the further amplification of the luciferase signal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Thus, the luciferase activity evaluates infection of cells in a fashion analogous to staining cells for HCMV ie1 protein expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Indeed, when infection with one and the same virus preparation was evaluated either by counting ie1-positive cells or by measuring the luciferase activity in cell lysates, both methods always gave comparable results (Fig. 2A and data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The assay proved to be linear over a wide range of m.o.i and highly sensitive (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1001256-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1001256.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>vBAC4-luc as a tool to study infection capacities. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>(A) HFF and in parallel TIME cells were infected on 96 well plates at an m.o.i. of 0.3 with a cell culture supernatant derived from HFF infected with vBAC4-luc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>After infection, PAA was added and 48 hours later cells either stained for HCMV ie1 protein expression or lysed and subjected to a luciferase assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The experiment was performed in triplicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>For ie1 staining, three independent wells were infected and one microscopic field per well was counted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>For the luciferase assay, lysates from three wells were analysed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Shown are means +/− SD of these triplicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The TIME cell infection capacity was related to the HFF infection capacity which was set to 100%, and the ratio expressed in percent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>(B) HFF and TIME cells were infected with serial 5-fold dilutions of a supernatant derived from HFF infected with vBAC4-luc starting at an m.o.i of 0.5 and 48 hours later analysed by a luciferase assay performed in triplicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The background level of the luciferase assay is indicated by the dotted line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>(C) Two independent luciferase assays using different batches of HFF and TIME cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Three TIME cell and three HFF supernatants from three independent infections with vBAC4-luc were assayed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>For the luciferase assay, cells were infected at an m.o.i. of 0.1 and analysed in triplicates 48 hours after infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Shown are means +/− SD of three supernatants tested in triplicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>(D) HFF, TIME cells and HUVEC were infected at an m.o.i. of 0.02 (centrifugal enhancement) with supernatants from vBAC4-luc, vBAC4-luc/UL131Astop and vBAC4-luc/ΔgO infections of HFF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>48 hours after infection cells were subjected to a luciferase assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Shown are means +/− SD of luciferase activities determined in triplicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1001256.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>It is a standard observation in the field that one and the same HCMV preparation yields variable results, when repeatedly titrated on different target cell batches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>When we tested HFF- and TIME cell-derived supernatants in independent luciferase assays, the results strongly depended on the quality of the cells used and varied with e.g. passage number and time after passage (Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Virus preparations derived from infected HFF and TIME cells (virus source) were tested twice, using different batches of HFF and TIME cells (assay 1 and 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>In assay one, the infection capacities of the supernatants on HFF and TIME cell differed much more than in assay two (Fig. 2C, upper panel), and consequently, the TIME/HFF infection ratios were in the range of 8 and 1.5% in assay one and in the range of 40 and 6% in assay two. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>(Fig. 2C, lower panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Yet, when the TIME/HFF infection ratios of the HFF supernatants were divided by the TIME/HFF infection ratios of the TIME cell supernatants, the quotients were comparable in both assays (assay one: 6.9, assay two: 7.5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the properties of virus preparations to be compared to each other were always tested in parallel. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>EC infection strictly depends on the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex [16], [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The mutant vBAC4-luc/UL131Astop does not express pUL131A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex is not formed, and the mutant cannot infect EC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The mutant vBAC4-luc/ΔgO does not express gO and promotes entry into EC and also HFF via the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex [24], [26]–[28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>We compared both mutants and the parental vBAC4-luc in the luciferase assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Confirming the data from Figure 1C, supernatant from a vBAC4-luc infection of HFF showed a lower capacity to infect EC, when compared to the capacity to infect HFF (Fig. 2D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>vBAC4-luc/UL131Astop infected HFF, whereas the luciferase signals obtained from infected HUVEC and TIME cells remained below the detection limit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>vBAC4-luc/ΔgO equally well infected HFF, TIME cells and HUVEC and thus showed an infection pattern clearly different from the parental vBAC4-luc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Taken together, the luciferase assay proved to be highly sensitive, to allow quantitative measurements over a wide range of m.o.i., and to reflect what is seen, when infection is detected by staining cells for ie1 protein expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>With the luciferase assay described above, we could compare the properties of virus progenies from HFF and EC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Supernatants of infected HFF and EC were harvested 6 days after infection, titrated on HFF, and the viral DNA content determined by real-time PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The ratios of infectious virus to viral DNA copy numbers were comparable for HFF- and EC-derived supernatants (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>These supernatants were then used to infect HFF and TIME cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Forty-eight hours later, infection was monitored by the luciferase assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Although virus derived from all three cell types showed a comparable infection of HFF (data not shown), EC-derived virus was significantly less capable in infecting EC than fibroblast-derived virus (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>On average, the TIME/HFF infection ratios were about fourfold lower for virus released from EC than for virus released from HFF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1001256-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1001256.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Virus released from EC shows a lower capability to infect EC than virus released from fibroblasts. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>HFF, TIME cells and HUVEC were infected with vBAC4-luc as described in Materials and Methods to obtain equal numbers of initially infected cells (m.o.i. on HFF: 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Supernatants from these infections were harvested 6 days after infection and titrated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>HFF and TIME cells were then infected with these supernatants at an m.o.i. of 0.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>After infection, PAA was added to the cultures, and 48 h later, cells were lysed and subjected to a luciferase assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The capacity of supernatant virus to infect EC was expressed as the ratio of TIME cell infection to HFF infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>HFF infection was set to 100%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Shown are means +/−SD of at least five independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>EC-derived supernatants were significantly less capable to infect EC than fibroblast-derived supernatants (Student's t test). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1001256.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The capacity of supernatant virus to infect EC correlates with UL128 protein content in virions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Incorporation of gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) glycoprotein complexes into virions [16], [17] is a prerequisite to infect endothelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>As virus released from EC was less capable in infecting EC than virus released from fibroblasts, we asked whether this difference can be associated with the abundance of gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complexes incorporated into virions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>We determined the gB and gH levels, and, representative for the presence of the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex, the pUL128 content in EC- and HFF-derived virions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Virus particles were pelleted from EC- or HFF-derived supernatants, lysed, and their gB, gH and pUL128 protein content determined by Western blot analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The amounts of gB and gH in virus pellets from HFF and EC supernatants always showed a constant relation (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Yet, HFF-derived virus particles contained more pUL128 protein than EC-derived virus particles (Fig. 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>This could be quantitatively analysed by measuring the gB band intensities of the lysates, which reflect the particle amounts loaded, and then, relating the pUL128 band intensities to the respective gB bands (Fig. 4A, middle panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, the pUL128/gB ratios mirror the TIME/HFF infection ratios (Fig. 4B, lower panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Thus, a low EC infection capacity correlated with a low level of gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complexes in virions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, total cell lysates of the respective infected cells showed that EC and HFF expressed comparable amounts of pUL128 (Fig. 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>This indicated that the differences in EC infection capacities observed are created at a late stage during maturation or release of virus progeny. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>To exclude that the observed differences between EC- and HFF-derived supernatants are due to non-infectious particles or contaminations with cell membrane components, gradient-purified virus from infections of HFF and HUVEC were analysed in the Western blot as described above (Fig. 4C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The pUL128/gB ratios again mirrored the TIME/HFF infection ratios of the supernatants, the virus was purified from. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1001256-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1001256.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>EC infection capacities correlate with pUL128 protein content of virus particles. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>HFF, TIME cells and HUVEC were infected with vTB40-BAC4 or vBAC4-luc for the gradient purified virus as described in Materials and Methods to obtain equal numbers of initially infected cells (m.o.i. on HFF: 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Supernatants were harvested, when cells showed about 80% CPE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>(A) Supernatant-derived particles were concentrated by ultracentrifugation and pUL128 and gB protein levels detected by Western blot analysis of undiluted or 1∶4 diluted lysates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The pUL128 band intensities of undiluted samples are expressed as ratios of pUL128 band intensities to gB band intensities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>This ratio was set to 100% for the HFF-derived particles and the ratios for HUVEC and TIME cell-derived particles expressed relative to the HFF value (middle panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The virus preparations were additionally tested for their TIME/HFF infection ratios by staining infected HFF and TIME cells for ie1 protein expression 48 h after infection (lower panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>(B) Cellular expression levels of gB and pUL128 were monitored by Western blot analysis of total cell lysates of infected cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>(C) Analysis of gradient-purified virus derived from HFF and HUVEC infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Cells were infected as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Virus was purified from the supernatants on glycerol/tartrate gradients as described in Materials and Methods and virus preparations analysed as described under (A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1001256.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Endothelial cells produce, but not readily release EC-tropic HCMV </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Whereas the virus released by EC is low in gH/gL/pUL(128,130,13A) complexes, focal spread in EC cultures was highly efficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Like EC infection by supernatant virus, it can be blocked by anti-pUL128, anti-pUL130 and anti-pUL131A antibodies [16], [17], [44], [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>This indicates that pUL(128,130,131A) are accessible to antibodies and promote infection of neighboring cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>We tested different cellular preparations for the presence of cell-associated EC-tropic virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>HUVEC and as a control HFF were infected with vBAC4-luc, and 6 days after infection supernatants were harvested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed to remove loosely bound virus and then homogenized using cell douncers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Aliquots of the total homogenates, containing the disrupted cells and virus freed by cell disruption, were saved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Homogenates were then cleared by centrifugation at 3,500×g to separate supernatants containing virus, which can be released by physical disruption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The pellets of cell debris, containing virus which is not released from cells, were also resuspended. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>These four preparations were then tested on HFF and TIME cells by the luciferase assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Virus supernatants from HFF and HUVEC showed a high and a low EC infection capacity, respectively (Fig. 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>All three homogenate preparations from HFF showed a reduced EC infection capacity, when compared to HFF supernatant virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Notably, the two HUVEC preparations, which contained cell debris showed an about tenfold higher EC infection capacity than the HUVEC supernatants (Fig. 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Thus, the progeny able to infect EC is released by HFF, but remained tightly associated with cellular structures in the case of EC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The differences observed are not due to different quantities of virus in the different preparations, because all HFF- and HUVEC-derived preparations showed high luciferase values, when tested on HFF (Fig. 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The tenfold differences between HUVEC-derived preparations, containing broken cells, and those without cells are due to high and low luciferase values on TIME cells, respectively (Fig. 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Highly EC-tropic virus could neither be released from EC by sonication nor by several rounds of freezing and thawing (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Taken together, the data show that HFF readily release, whereas HUVEC tightly retain EC-tropic virus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1001256-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1001256.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Endothelial cells retain EC-tropic virus particles. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>HFF were infected with vBAC4-luc as described in Materials and Methods to obtain equal numbers of initially infected cells (m.o.i. on HFF: 0.2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Six days after infection supernatants were harvested, cells homogenized as described in Materials and Methods and different fractions of the homogenates tested on HFF and TIME cells for their infection capacities by luciferase assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>(A) shows the TIME/HFF infection ratios and (B) the absolute luciferase activities of the different cell preparations on HFF and TIME cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Shown are means +/− SD of three independent experiments assayed in triplicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>For HFF all homogenate preparations were significantly less EC-tropic than the cell culture supernatants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>For HUVEC the total homogenates and the resuspended pellets were significantly more EC-tropic than the cell culture supernatants (Student's t test). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1001256.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>HFF release virus progeny, which is not homogeneous </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Virus released from EC is only poorly tropic for EC, whereas virus associated with EC shows a much higher tropism for EC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Virus released from HFF is highly EC-tropic and virus found in the particulate fraction of disrupted HFF rather shows a lower tropism for EC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>One explanation would be that HCMV progeny is heterogeneous and consists of distinct virus populations with regard to their EC-tropism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>EC show a propensity to retain EC-tropic virus and release non EC-tropic virus, whereas HFF readily release both, EC-tropic and non EC-tropic virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The hypothesis, that HFF progeny is a mixture of EC-tropic and non EC-tropic virus is testable by separation of EC-tropic and non EC-tropic virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>As HUVEC strongly retain EC-tropic virus, they might serve to specifically bind EC-tropic virus and deplete HFF virus progeny of its EC-tropic fraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>We preincubated HFF-derived supernatant virus with HUVEC or with HFF, pelleted the cells, and analysed the HFF and TIME cell infectivity of virus remaining in the supernatants (Fig. 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Preincubation with HUVEC removed about 30 to 90% and preincubation with HFF about 99% of the infectious virus from supernatants, when tested on HFF (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>The TIME/HFF infection ratios of the non-bound virus in supernatants preincubated with HUVEC was drastically and significantly reduced to the level observed in supernatants of HCMV-infected HUVEC (Fig. 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Preincubation with HFF in contrast, although it removed the bulk of infectivity, only weakly reduced the EC infection propensity of the non-bound virus (Fig. 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Thus, HUVEC, which retained EC-tropic virus in infection, were a good matrix for binding EC-tropic virus, whereas HFF, which readily released EC-tropic virus into the supernatant, were a weak matrix for EC-tropic virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The depletion of EC-tropism strongly suggested that HFF virus progeny was heterogeneous and composed of distinct virus populations, which could be sorted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>To find out whether the depletion of EC-tropism is based on removing virus particles expressing the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex, we coincubated HFF-derived virus progeny with protein G sepharose beads to which we had bound anti-pUL131A antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Beads coated with antibodies specific for pUL131A, but not uncoated beads or beads coated with preimmune serum, depleted about 70% of the EC-tropism (Fig. 6B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>This strongly implied that depletion of EC-tropism is through retaining virions, expressing the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1001256-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1001256.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>HFF virus progeny can be depleted of EC-tropic virus by coincubation with endothelial cells and beads coated with anti-pUL131A antibodies. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>(A) 2×106 HFF or HUVEC were incubated (90 min, 37°C) with 130,000 TCID50 vBAC4-luc diluted in 30 µl DMEM (5% FCS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Then 500 µl of DMEM (5% FCS) was added, the cells pelleted by centrifugation at 300×g for 5 min and the supernatants cleared at 3,500×g for 15 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>As a control 130,000 TCID50 vBAC4-luc diluted in 30 µl DMEM (5% FCS) were mock-incubated and mock-treated as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>HFF and TIME cells were infected with the supernatants from the coincubations and the controls and subjected to a luciferase assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>TIME/HFF infection ratios of the supernatants after coincubation were expressed as % of the TIME/HFF infection ratios of the control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Shown are the means of TIME/HFF infection ratios +/− SD determined in six independent experiments each assayed in triplicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>(B) 30 µl of a 50% protein G sepharose preparation (GE Healthcare, Germany) were coincubated overnight with 300 µl rabbit anti-pUL131A antiserum (1∶10 diluted in PBS) or as controls preimmune serum (1∶10 diluted in PBS) or PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Then, beads were washed 3 times with PBS and coincubated for 2 hours at RT with 130,000 TCID50 vBAC4-luc diluted in 500 µl DMEM without serum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>After coincubation beads were pelleted and 5% FCS added to the supernatants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Then, HFF and TIME cells were infected with these supernatants and subjected to a luciferase assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Shown are the means of TIME/HFF infection ratios +/− SD determined in triplicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The TIME/HFF infection ratios of virus coincubated with anti-UL131A antibody coated beads was significantly different from the values obtained from virus coincubated with preimmune serum-coated beads. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1001256.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>The use of different receptor binding proteins to mediate entry into different cell types, and the use of different entry pathways even into one cell type is a common feature of herpesvirus entry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Herpesviruses have additionally developed strategies, which may route infection in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>For EBV, the group of L. Hutt-Fletcher has pioneered the paradigm that epithelial cells produce a virus progeny high in gH/gL/gp42 complexes, which promotes B-cell infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>B-cells in turn, produce virus progeny low in gH/gL/gp42 complexes which efficiently infect epithelial cells, but not B-cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Although not absolute, this relative switch of cell tropism after alternate replication in epithelial and B-cells directs infection from one cell type to the other. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Here, we propose that also different producer cells of HCMV may direct the infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>gH/gL/gO complex formation is needed for release of infectious virus from any infected cell type tested so far [24], [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Incorporation of gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complexes into virions is essential for infection of e.g. endothelial, epithelial, and dendritic cells, and for leukocytes [16], [17], [22], [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>If gO is missing, then the infection spreads predominantly focal and depends on the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex, even in cell types, which usually do not depend on this complex for infection [24], [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Our initial observation was that virus spread in fibroblast cultures differed from virus spread in EC cultures [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Spread in fibroblast cultures appeared supernatant- driven, whereas spread in EC cultures was focal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>A strictly cell-associated virus spread in EC cultures had also been observed by the group of G. Gerna, who reported that propagation in HUVEC strictly depended on passage of cells and could not be achieved by supernatant virus [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>We offer an explanation for the focal spread in EC cultures by showing that EC predominantly release virus, which is not EC-tropic, but at the same time tightly retain EC-tropic virus which may then be transferred to neighboring cells only. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Virus transfer was accessible to neutralizing antibodies and dependent on the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex, as we could show in Figure S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Focal spread was completely blocked by a neutralizing human antiserum and by anti-pUL131A antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, when infected HFF cultures were treated in a similar way, a neutralizing human antiserum blocked infection by free virus, but left a focal spread of virus, indicating that for HFF a direct cell-to-cell spread mechanism may be possible [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Anti-pUL131A antibodies could not at all inhibit spread in HFF cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>These data confirmed earlier studies by our group, which showed that only gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) dependent virus spread, like spread in EC cultures, or spread of a delta gO mutant in fibroblast cultures could be inhibited by anti-pUL131A antibodies [17], [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Similar to the EBV model, supernatants from infected HFF showed a higher capacity to infect EC than EC-derived supernatants, and we could show that the biochemical basis for that is a respectively high and low content of gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex in virions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The question, which arose then, was, what causes the observed difference in gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>For EBV it has been described that in infected B-cells HLA-DR ß binds the gp42 protein of the gH/gL/gp42 complex, which promotes B-cell infection, holds it back intracellularly, and thus, makes it vulnerable for degradation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>As a consequence, B-cells release mainly virions containing a two-part gH/gL complex, which cannot infect B-cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Epithelial cells, which do not express HLA-DR ß, do not retain gp42 and thus, release virus, which contains more of the three-part gH/gL/gp42 complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>The mechanisms, by which the differences in the released populations of virions in HCMV are achieved, appear to be different. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>For HCMV, we found that EC and fibroblasts produce heterogeneous virus progenies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>EC release a virus progeny, which is not EC-tropic, and retain a progeny, which is highly EC-tropic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>HFF release an EC-tropic progeny. which can be depleted of its EC-tropism by using HUVEC or protein G sepharose beads coated with antibodies directed against pUL131A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>This strongly suggested that HFF progeny is composed of distinct EC-tropic and non EC-tropic virus populations, and that the EC-tropic population most likely is a population with a high gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>If HFF-derived virus progeny was homogeneous, a specific depletion only of EC-tropic virus would not be possible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, HUVEC, which retain EC-tropic virus in infection experiments, were a good matrix to retain EC-tropic virus in the test tube, whereas HFF, which readily release EC-tropic virus in infections, were a bad matrix. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Thus, we propose that the difference in cell tropism of virus released from EC and fibroblasts is the result of a sorting process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>EC strongly and specifically retain EC-tropic virus through the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>HFF release EC-tropic and non EC-tropic virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Thus, for HCMV, not protein components of gH/gL complexes are retained in a cell-type specific manner, but rather mature virions carrying the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex in their envelopes. Figure 7 depicts the EBV and HCMV models for virus spread side by side. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1001256-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1001256.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>HCMV and EBV models for virus spread in cell culture. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>The EBV model proposes a switch of cell tropism through depletion of gp42 from B-cell derived virus progeny resulting in a gp42low progeny versus a gp42high progeny released from epithelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>The HCMV model proposes the production of a heterogeneous virus progeny from fibroblasts and EC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Fibroblasts release EC-tropic and non-EC tropic viruses which results in a pUL128high progeny, whereas EC release a non EC-tropic pUL128low progeny and retain the EC-tropic virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>This results in a switch of the spread mode. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The tropism of virus progenies is indicated by color codes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1001256.g007"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Future experiments will have to show where and how EC-tropic virus is held back. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>It has recently been shown that overexpression of gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) in epithelial cells interferes with HCMV infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>It has been postulated that this reflects binding of the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex to the respective entry receptor [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>This was not observed for fibroblasts and thus, an HCMV entry receptor binding to gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) and expressed on EC would be a good candidate also for retaining EC-tropic virus by infected EC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>How virus is then transferred to neighboring cells, will also have to be investigated in the future. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>An attractive model would be a mechanism as described for MHV-68, for which it has been shown that virus particles attached to and moving on plasma membrane fronds are directly transferred to neighboring cells [47]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Assuming that gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complexes are incorporated into virus progeny at random, EC-tropism of a virus particle might be defined by a threshold level of gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complexes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, high levels of gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complexes in turn could also block release from EC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Thus, the levels of gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complexes could define whether a particle is EC-tropic or not, whether it is retained by EC during infection, and whether it can be depleted from supernatants by EC-preincubation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>This could also explain, why progeny of a ΔgO virus, which expresses only the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex, readily spreads cell-associated and can barely be released from EC [24], [28]. ΔgO virus progeny can equally well infect EC and HFF (Fig 2D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Wildtype TB40-BAC4 virus progeny, in contrast, shows a higher propensity to infect HFF (Fig. 2D), which could be explained by being a mixture of EC-tropic and non EC-tropic particles. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>For EBV, it has been observed that virus bound to the surface of resting B cells is 103-104 times more infectious for epithelial cells than cell-free virus [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>For HCMV it has not yet been tested whether surface-bound virus could promote a switch of cell tropism. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>We restricted our experiments to endothelial cells and fibroblasts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Macrophages, dendritic cells, and epithelial cells also strictly depend on the gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) complex for their infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Whether their infection also follows the pattern of the EC infection shown here, will have to be investigated in the future. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Recently, it has been published by Wang et al. [30] that HCMV progenies derived from epithelial cells and fibroblast also differ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>They reported that both cell types release progenies which can readily infect epithelial cells and fibroblasts, but differ with respect to the pathway they use to enter epithelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>They found a twofold higher gH/gL/pUL(128,130,131A) content in epithelial cell-derived particles, which they considered as marginal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>As they used an AD169 mutant, in which UL131A had been repaired, it will have to be clarified, whether their findings reflect that epitheliotropic virus produced in epithelial cells is, in contrast to our findings in EC, not retained, or whether the observed differences are due to differences of the HCMV strains used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>It has recently been shown that AD169 incorporates gO into virions, whereas HCMV strain TR does not [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>This suggests that strain-specific differences may indeed affect gH/gL-dependent processes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Whether our observations made in cell culture, reflect features valid for all HCMV strains, and what role a switch in tropism and spread patterns may play in vivo, will be the subject of future research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>It will be of particular interest to find out whether the relative propensity of different cell types to release virus plays a crucial role in establishment of infection and transfer of virus to new hosts or the fetus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>For HCMV, it has been shown that primary isolation of EC-tropic virus depends on infected cells as a source of virus, whereas fibroblast infection can also be achieved with cell-free virus sources like throat washes and amniotic fluid [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>This might already be an indication that cells lining the compartments, where these fluids are produced, do not release EC-tropic virus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Cells and viruses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Primary human foreskin fibroblasts (HFF) (PromoCell, Germany) were used from passage 12 to 22 and maintained in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM) supplemented with 10% fetal calf serum, 2 mM L-glutamine, 100 units/ml penicillin and 100 µg/ml streptomycin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Primary human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVEC) (LONZA, USA) were used from passage 1 to 6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>HUVEC and TIME (telomerase-immortalized human microvascular endothelial) cells [49] were maintained in an EGM-2 MV BulletKit medium system (LONZA, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>The HCMV strains used were VR1814 [19], TB40/E [50] and TB40/E cloned as a BAC (TB40-BAC4) [51]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>BAC mutagenesis and construction of recombinant HCMV </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>The HCMV strain TB40/E cloned as a bacterial artificial chromosome (BAC) (TB40-BAC4) [51] was used for HCMV BAC mutagenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>A 48 bp FRT site was inserted into the TB40-BAC4, thereby disrupting the open reading frames (ORFs) UL5, UL6, UL7, UL8 and UL9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Briefly, a linear PCR fragment containing a kanamycin-resistance gene flanked by two 48 bp FRT sites and sequences homologous to the HCMV UL5 and UL9 coding regions was generated using the primers UL5pcp15for (5′-ATGTTTCTAGGCTACTCTGACTGTGTAGATCCCGGCTTTGCTGTATATCGTGTATCTAGACGGGGGTGTCCAGGGTTTTCCC-3′) and UL9pcp15rev (5′-ATTGTTGTAACGATAACTAAGGGTATGATCCACATTGTATGTGGGGTGGCAGTATCGTGTCTTCCGGCTCGTATGTTGTGTGG-3) and pCP15 as template [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>The PCR product was inserted into TB40-BAC4 by homologous recombination in E. coli, thereby deleting 3,066 kb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>The kanamycin-resistance gene was subsequently excised by FLP-mediated site-directed recombination [53], and the resulting BAC mutant called BAC4-FRT5-9. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>To generate a luciferase reporter HCMV, the SV40-driven firefly luciferase expression cassette was excised from pGL3-promoter (Promega) with Sal I and Bgl II, filled in by Klenow polymerase and inserted into the pOriR6K-zeo plasmid linearized by EcoR V. The resulting plasmid pO6-Luc was inserted into BAC4-FRT5-9 via FLP-mediated FRT recombination mutagenesis using the temperature-sensitive expression plasmid pCP20 [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>The resulting BAC mutant was called BAC4-Luc. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>The BAC mutants BAC4-Luc/ΔgO and BAC4-Luc/UL131Astop were cloned into the BAC4-Luc background as described previously [24], [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Deletions and insertions were controlled by restriction pattern analysis and subsequent sequencing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Reconstitution of virus from recombinant BACmids </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>BACmids were reconstituted to virus by transfection of BAC DNA into HFF using FugeneHD transfection reagent (Roche Diagnostics) according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Transfected cells were propagated until viral plaques appeared and the supernatants from these cultures used for further propagation of virus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Preparation of virus stocks, concentration of virus particles, virus titration and infections </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Virus stocks were prepared from supernatants of infected HFF, HUVEC or TIME cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Supernatants were cleared of cellular debris by centrifugation for 15 min at 3,500×g and stored at −80°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>For Western Blot analysis of HCMV particles, virus was concentrated from cell culture supernatants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Briefly, 200 ml supernatant from infected cells showing about 90% CPE was cleared of cellular debris by centrifugation at 3,500×g for 15 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Then, virus was pelleted from cleared supernatant by ultracentrifugation at 80,000×g for 70 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Virus pellets were resuspended in 1.5 ml 0.04 mol/l sodium phosphate pH 7.4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Virus titers of cleared supernatants were determined by a TCID50 assay performed on 96 well plates on HFF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>To infect cells, medium was removed from 90% confluent cell monolayers and replaced by virus diluted in DMEM containing 5% FCS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>For some experiments, virus infection was enhanced by a centrifugation step (30 min, 860×g at room temperature), followed by incubation at 37°C for 90 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>To compare infectivity of virus derived from fibroblasts and endothelial cells, subsequent infections were performed in DMEM 5% FCS/EGM-2 mixed at a ratio of 1∶1, to exclude medium effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>During infections, medium was exchanged every second day in a way that supernatants harvested contained virus released during the preceding 48 hours. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>As HCMV in general more readily infects fibroblasts than EC, in all experiments, where infections of EC and fibroblasts (spread patterns and growth curves) were compared, the infections were adapted in a way that EC were infected with more virus than fibroblasts to achieve comparable numbers of ie1-positive cells after 48 hours. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Gradient purification of virions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>For gradient purification of virions, supernatants from infected cell cultures showing approximately 100% late-stage CPE were cleared of cell debris by centrifugation for 10 min at 2,800×g. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Supernatants were then ultracentrifuged for 70 min at 80,000×g. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Pellets containing virions were resuspended in 1 ml PBS and transferred onto a preformed, linear glycerol/tartrate gradient (15–35% sodium tartrate and 30–40% glycerol in 0.04 mol/l sodium phosphate pH 7.4), which was ultracentrifuged for 45 min at 80,000×g. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>The virion-containing band was harvested with a syringe and the virions were washed and pelleted by an additional ultracentrifugation for 70 min at 80,000×g. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>The pellet was resuspended in 0.04 mol/l sodium phosphate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Indirect immunofluorescence </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>HCMV-infected cells were fixed in 50% acetone/50% methanol, stained using a mouse anti-ie1 antibody (anti-ie1; Perkin Elmer) and detected with a Cy3-coupled goat anti-mouse antibody (Dianova). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>For counterstaining of cell nuclei, cells were incubated in PBS containing 5 µg/ml Hoechst 333258 (Invitrogen) for 1 min. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Luciferase assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>HFF and TIME cells were grown in 96 well plates (20,000 cells/well) and infected in triplicates at an m.o.i. between 0.02 and 0.5 for 90 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Inoculi were then replaced by medium supplemented with 300 µg/ml phosphono acetic acid (PAA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>48 h after infection cells were lysed in 50 µl lysis buffer (25 mM Tris/H3PO4, 2 mM CDTA, 2 mM DTT, 10% glycerol, 5% Triton-X 100) and luciferase activity was determined for 20 µl of lysate with a luciferase assay system (Promega) according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Western blot analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Virus particles or infected cells were lysed in 6× sample buffer (300 mM Tris-HCl (pH 6.8), 10% SDS, 30% glycerol, 5% ß-mercaptoethanol, 0.01% (w/v) bromphenolblue, 0.01% (w/v) phenolred), separated on 15% polyacrylamide gels and transferred onto nitrocellulose (Amersham Biosciences). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Membranes were blocked with 5% low-fat milk in TBS and stained for gB or pUL128 using mouse anti-gB antibody (2F12; Abcam) or mouse anti-pUL128 antibody (4B10, kindly provided by T. Shenk, University of Princeton, USA), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>The specific protein bands were detected by using an peroxidase-coupled anti-mouse antibody (Dianova) and the SuperSignal West Dura Extended Duration Kit (Perbio). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>The intensities of protein bands were quantified using the Fujifilm Intelligent Light Box LAS-300 and the Image reader LAS-300. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Non-saturated light signals were analysed to determine the protein amounts using ImageQuant 5.0 software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>The pUL128 levels were related to gB levels of the respective samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Homogenization of cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Cells were infected in 6 cm dishes, and 6 days after infection the supernatants (4 ml) harvested and cleared of cellular debris (3,500×g, 15 min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Cell monolayers were washed with cold PBS, scraped and cells dounced in 4 ml DMEM medium supplemented with 5% FCS using tight fit hand homogenizers (Sartorius-Stedium). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>3.5 ml of the total homogenized cells were pelleted (3,500×g, 15 min), the supernatant removed (supernatant of homogenized cells) and the pellets resuspended in fresh 3.5 ml DMEM medium supplemented with 5% FCS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Accession numbers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>GeneBank/EMBL/DDBJ accession number for TB40-BAC4 is EF999921. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1001256.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Neutralizing antibodies block focal spread of HCMV in EC cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>HFF and HUVEC were infected with vBAC4-luc as described in Materials and Methods to obtain equal numbers of initially infected cells (m.o.i. on HFF: 0.1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>After infection, cells were washed three times with medium and then fresh medium (no serum) or serum diluted in medium was added (1∶25 dilutions of the HCMV-negative and -positive sera and a 1∶10 dilution of the anti-pUL131A rabbit antiserum [17]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Cells were incubated in the presence of the antisera for 8 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Initial infection (day 2) as well as virus spread (day 8) were monitored by staining for HCMV ie1 protein expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>The HCMV-positive antiserum showed a complete and the HCMV-negative serum no neutralization of HFF and EC infections when tested with free virus (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>(0.56 MB TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="ppat.1001256.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1001256.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Growth properties of vBAC4-FRT5-9 and vBAC4-luc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>(A) Schematic presentation of TB40-BAC4 derived mutants BAC4-FRT5-9 and BAC4-luc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>The UL and US regions, the positions of internal and terminal repeats (dark grey), the open reading frames UL5 and UL9, the BAC cassette (light grey), the position of the FRT-site and the insertion of a luciferase expression cassette are indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>(B) Growth curves of vTB40-BAC4, vBAC4-FRT5-9 and vBAC4-luc on HFF, TIME cells and HUVEC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Cells were infected as described in Materials and Methods to obtain equal numbers of initially infected cells (m.o.i. on HFF: 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Cell culture supernatants were harvested at the indicated time points post infection and virus titers determined by a TCID50 assay performed on HFF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>(C) Spread of vBAC4-FRT5-9 and vBAC4-luc in HFF and endothelial cell cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>HFF were infected with vBAC4-FRT5-9 and vBAC4-luc at an m.o.i. of 0.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>For TIME cells and HUVEC the m.o.i. were adapted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>The initial infections (day 2) as well as virus spread (day 8) were monitored by staining for HCMV ie1 protein expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>(0.63 MB TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="ppat.1001256.s002.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>We thank Heike Hofmann for excellent technical assistance and Heiko Adler for critically reading the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft through an individual grant to Barbara Adler (AD131/3-1) and through the Schwerpunktprogramm SPP1130 Infections of the endothelium (AD131/2-3 and SI779/3-3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analyis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ppat.1001256-Sinzger1"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>1 SinzgerCDigelMJahnG 2008 Cytomegalovirus cell tropism. Curr Top Microbiol Immunol 325 63 83 18637500 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Varnum1"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>2 VarnumSMStreblowDNMonroeMESmithPAuberryKJ 2004 Identification of proteins in human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) particles: the HCMV proteome. J Virol 78 10960 10966 15452216 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Britt1"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>3 BrittWJ 1984 Neutralizing antibodies detect a disulfide-linked glycoprotein complex within the envelope of human cytomegalovirus. Virology 135 369 378 6330979 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Isaacson1"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>4 IsaacsonMKComptonT 2009 Human cytomegalovirus glycoprotein B is required for virus entry and cell-to-cell spread but not for virion attachment, assembly, or egress. J Virol 83 3891 3903 19193805 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Mach1"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>5 MachMKropffBDal MontePBrittW 2000 Complex formation by human cytomegalovirus glycoproteins M (gpUL100) and N (gpUL73). J Virol 74 11881 11892 11090188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Compton1"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>6 ComptonT 2004 Receptors and immune sensors: the complex entry path of human cytomegalovirus. Trends Cell Biol 14 5 8 14729174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Kinzler1"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>7 KinzlerERComptonT 2005 Characterization of human cytomegalovirus glycoprotein-induced cell-cell fusion. J Virol 79 7827 7837 15919936 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Wright1"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>8 WrightJFKuroskyAWasiS 1994 An endothelial cell-surface form of annexin II binds human cytomegalovirus. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 198 983 989 8117306 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Pietropaolo1"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>9 PietropaoloRLComptonT 1997 Direct interaction between human cytomegalovirus glycoprotein B and cellular annexin II. J Virol 71 9803 9807 9371650 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Keay1"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>10 KeaySBaldwinB 1992 The human fibroblast receptor for gp86 of human cytomegalovirus is a phosphorylated glycoprotein. J Virol 66 4834 4838 1321272 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Wang1"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>11 WangXHuongSMChiuMLRaab-TraubNHuangES 2003 Epidermal growth factor receptor is a cellular receptor for human cytomegalovirus. Nature 424 456 461 12879076 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Soroceanu1"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>12 SoroceanuLAkhavanACobbsCS 2008 Platelet-derived growth factor-alpha receptor activation is required for human cytomegalovirus infection. Nature 455 391 395 18701889 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Wang2"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>13 WangXHuangDYHuongSMHuangES 2005 Integrin alphavbeta3 is a coreceptor for human cytomegalovirus. Nat Med 11 515 521 15834425 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Li1"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>14 LiLNelsonJABrittWJ 1997 Glycoprotein H-related complexes of human cytomegalovirus: identification of a third protein in the gCIII complex. J Virol 71 3090 3097 9060671 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Huber1"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>15 HuberMTComptonT 1998 The human cytomegalovirus UL74 gene encodes the third component of the glycoprotein H-glycoprotein L-containing envelope complex. J Virol 72 8191 8197 9733861 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Wang3"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>16 WangDShenkT 2005 Human cytomegalovirus virion protein complex required for epithelial and endothelial cell tropism. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 102 18153 18158 16319222 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Adler1"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>17 AdlerBScrivanoLRuzcicsZRuppBSinzgerC 2006 Role of human cytomegalovirus UL131A in cell type-specific virus entry and release. J Gen Virol 87 2451 2460 16894182 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Ryckman1"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>18 RyckmanBJRainishBLChaseMCBortonJANelsonJA 2008 Characterization of the human cytomegalovirus gH/gL/UL128-131 complex that mediates entry into epithelial and endothelial cells. J Virol 82 60 70 17942555 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Grazia1"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>19 GraziaRMBaldantiFPercivalleESarasiniADe GiuliL 2001 In vitro selection of human cytomegalovirus variants unable to transfer virus and virus products from infected cells to polymorphonuclear leukocytes and to grow in endothelial cells. J Gen Virol 82 1429 1438 11369888 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Baldanti1"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>20 BaldantiFPaolucciSCampaniniGSarasiniAPercivalleE 2005 Human cytomegalovirus UL131A, UL130 and UL128 genes are highly conserved among field isolates. Arch Virol 151 1225 1233 16380811 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Wang4"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>21 WangDShenkT 2005 Human cytomegalovirus UL131 open reading frame is required for epithelial cell tropism. J Virol 79 10330 10338 16051825 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Hahn1"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>22 HahnGRevelloMGPatroneMPercivalleECampaniniG 2004 Human cytomegalovirus UL131-128 genes are indispensable for virus growth in endothelial cells and virus transfer to leukocytes. J Virol 78 10023 10033 15331735 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Gerna1"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>23 GernaGPercivalleELilleriDLozzaLFornaraC 2005 Dendritic-cell infection by human cytomegalovirus is restricted to strains carrying functional UL131-128 genes and mediates efficient viral antigen presentation to CD8+ T cells. J Gen Virol 86 275 284 15659746 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Jiang1"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>24 JiangXJAdlerBSampaioKLDigelMJahnG 2008 UL74 of human cytomegalovirus contributes to virus release by promoting secondary envelopment of virions. J Virol 82 2802 2812 18184717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Compton2"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>25 ComptonTNepomucenoRRNowlinDM 1992 Human cytomegalovirus penetrates host cells by pH-independent fusion at the cell surface. Virol 191 387 395  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Scrivano1"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>26 ScrivanoLEsterlechnerJMuhlbachHEttischerNHagenC 2010 The m74 gene product of murine cytomegalovirus (MCMV) is a functional homolog of human CMV gO and determines the entry pathway of MCMV. J Virol 84 4469 4480 20181688 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Ryckman2"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>27 RyckmanBJChaseMCJohnsonDC 2009 HCMV TR strain glycoprotein O acts as a chaperone promoting gH/gL incorporation into virions, but is not present in virions. J Virol 84 2597 2609 20032193 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Wille1"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>28 WillePTKnocheAJNelsonJAJarvisMAJohnsonDC 2009 An HCMV gO-null mutant fails to incorporate gH/gL into the virion envelope and is unable to enter fibroblasts, epithelial, and endothelial cells. J Virol 84 2585 2596 20032184 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Schuessler1"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>29 SchuesslerASampaioKLScrivanoLSinzgerC 2010 Mutational mapping of UL130 of human cytomegalovirus defines peptide motifs within the C-terminal third as essential for endothelial cell infection. J Virol 84 9019 9026 20592093 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Wang5"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>30 WangDYuQCSchroerJMurphyEShenkT 2007 Human cytomegalovirus uses two distinct pathways to enter retinal pigmented epithelial cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 104 20037 20042 18077432 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Bodaghi1"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>31 BodaghiBSlobbe-van DrunenMETopilkoAPerretEVossenRC 1999 Entry of human cytomegalovirus into retinal pigment epithelial and endothelial cells by endocytosis. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci 40 2598 2607 10509655 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Ryckman3"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>32 RyckmanBJJarvisMADrummondDDNelsonJAJohnsonDC 2006 Human cytomegalovirus entry into epithelial and endothelial cells depends on genes UL128 to UL150 and occurs by endocytosis and low-pH fusion. J Virol 80 710 722 16378974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Sinzger2"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>33 SinzgerC 2008 Entry route of HCMV into endothelial cells. J Clin Virol 41 174 179 18203656 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Ryckman4"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>34 RyckmanBJChaseMCJohnsonDC 2008 HCMV gH/gL/UL128-131 interferes with virus entry into epithelial cells: evidence for cell type-specific receptors. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 105 14118 14123 18768787 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Borza1"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>35 BorzaCMHutt-FletcherLM 2002 Alternate replication in B cells and epithelial cells switches tropism of Epstein-Barr virus. Nat Med 8 594 599 12042810 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Mori1"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>36 MoriYAkkapaiboonPYonemotoSKoikeMTakemotoM 2004 Discovery of a second form of tripartite complex containing gH-gL of human herpesvirus 6 and observations on CD46. J Virol 78 4609 4616 15078943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Chesnokova1"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>37 ChesnokovaLSNishimuraSLHutt-FletcherLM 2009 Fusion of epithelial cells by Epstein-Barr virus proteins is triggered by binding of viral glycoproteins gHgL to integrins alphavbeta6 or alphavbeta8. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 106 20464 20469 19920174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Miller1"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>38 MillerNHutt-FletcherLM 1992 Epstein-Barr virus enters B cells and epithelial cells by different routes. J Virol 66 3409 3414 1316456 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-HuttFletcher1"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>39 Hutt-FletcherLM 2007 Epstein-Barr virus entry. J Virol 81 7825 7832 17459936 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Spriggs1"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>40 SpriggsMKArmitageRJComeauMRStrockbineLFarrahT 1996 The extracellular domain of the Epstein-Barr virus BZLF2 protein binds the HLA-DR beta chain and inhibits antigen presentation. J Virol 70 5557 5563 8764069 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Mori2"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>41 MoriYYangXAkkapaiboonPOkunoTYamanishiK 2003 Human herpesvirus 6 variant A glycoprotein H-glycoprotein L-glycoprotein Q complex associates with human CD46. J Virol 77 4992 4999 12663806 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Akkapaiboon1"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>42 AkkapaiboonPMoriYSadaokaTYonemotoSYamanishiK 2004 Intracellular processing of human herpesvirus 6 glycoproteins Q1 and Q2 into tetrameric complexes expressed on the viral envelope. J Virol 78 7969 7983 15254169 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Gerna2"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>43 GernaGPercivalleESarasiniARevelloMG 2002 Human cytomegalovirus and human umbilical vein endothelial cells: restriction of primary isolation to blood samples and susceptibilities of clinical isolates from other sources to adaptation. J Clin Microbiol 40 233 238 11773121 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Macagno1"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>44 MacagnoABernasconiNLVanzettaFDanderESarasiniA 2010 Isolation of human monoclonal antibodies that potently neutralize human cytomegalovirus infection by targeting different epitopes on the gH/gL/UL128-131A complex. J Virol 84 1005 1013 19889756 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Gerna3"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>45 GernaGSarasiniAPatroneMPercivalleEFiorinaL 2008 Human cytomegalovirus serum neutralizing antibodies block virus infection of endothelial/epithelial cells, but not fibroblasts, early during primary infection. J Gen Virol 89 853 865 18343825 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Digel1"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>46 DigelMSampaioKLJahnGSinzgerC 2006 Evidence for direct transfer of cytoplasmic material from infected to uninfected cells during cell-associated spread of human cytomegalovirus. J Clin Virol 37 10 20 16815742 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Gill1"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>47 GillMBEdgarRMayJSStevensonPG 2008 A gamma-herpesvirus glycoprotein complex manipulates actin to promote viral spread. PLoS ONE 3 e1808 18350146 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-ShannonLowe1"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>48 Shannon-LoweCDNeuhierlBBaldwinGRickinsonABDelecluseHJ 2006 Resting B cells as a transfer vehicle for Epstein-Barr virus infection of epithelial cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 103 7065 7070 16606841 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Venetsanakos1"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>49 VenetsanakosEMirzaAFantonCRomanovSRTlstyT 2002 Induction of tubulogenesis in telomerase-immortalized human microvascular endothelial cells by glioblastoma cells. Exp Cell Res 273 21 33 11795943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Sinzger3"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>50 SinzgerCSchmidtKKnappJKahlMBeckR 1999 Modification of human cytomegalovirus tropism through propagation in vitro is associated with changes in the viral genome. J Gen Virol 80 2867 2877 10580048 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Sinzger4"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>51 SinzgerCHahnGDigelMKatonaRSampaioKL 2008 Cloning and sequencing of a highly productive, endotheliotropic virus strain derived from human cytomegalovirus TB40/E. J Gen Virol 89 359 368 18198366 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Cherepanov1"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>52 CherepanovPPWackernagelW 1995 Gene disruption in Escherichia coli: TcR and KmR cassettes with the option of Flp-catalyzed excision of the antibiotic-resistance determinant. Gene 158 9 14 7789817 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Bubic1"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>53 BubicIWagnerMKrmpoticASauligTKimS 2004 Gain of virulence caused by loss of a gene in murine cytomegalovirus. J Virol 78 7536 7544 15220428 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1001256-Bubeck1"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>54 BubeckAWagnerMRuzsicsZLotzerichMIglesiasM 2004 Comprehensive mutational analysis of a herpesvirus gene in the viral genome context reveals a region essential for virus replication. J Virol 78 8026 8035 15254174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
