<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3804621</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24204832</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-27633</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077454</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The <italic>AP2</italic>-Like Gene <italic>OitaAP2</italic> Is Alternatively Spliced and Differentially Expressed in Inflorescence and Vegetative Tissues of the Orchid <italic>Orchis italica</italic>
</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Alternative Splicing of <italic>OitaAP2</italic> in <italic>Orchis italica</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Salemme</surname><given-names>Marinella</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sica</surname><given-names>Maria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iazzetti</surname><given-names>Giovanni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gaudio</surname><given-names>Luciano</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aceto</surname><given-names>Serena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>Department of Biology, University of Naples Federico II, Napoli, Italy</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>M. de Bruin</surname><given-names>Robertus A.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University College London, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>serena.aceto@unina.it</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: SA. Performed the experiments: MS MS GI. Analyzed the data: SA LG. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MS MS GI LG SA. Wrote the paper: SA.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e77454</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2013 Salemme et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Salemme et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The AP2/ERF proteins are plant-specific transcription factors involved in multiple regulatory pathways, from plant organ development to response to various environmental stresses. One of the mechanisms that regulates the <italic>AP2-like</italic> genes involves the microRNA miR172, which controls their activity at the post-transcriptional level. Extensive studies on <italic>AP2-like</italic> genes are available in many different species; however, in orchids, one of the largest plant families, studies are restricted to a few species, all belonging to the Epidendroideae subfamily. In the present study, we report the isolation of an <italic>AP2-like</italic> gene in the Mediterranean orchid <italic>Orchis italica</italic> (Orchidoideae). The <italic>OitaAP2</italic> locus includes 10 exons and 9 introns, and its transcript is alternatively spliced, resulting in the long <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and the short <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> isoforms, with the latter skipping exon 9. Both isoforms contain the conserved target site for miR172, whose action is demonstrated by the presence of cleaved <italic>OitaAP2</italic> mRNA. The <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> mRNAs are present in the tepals and lip before and after anthesis at different expression levels. In addition, the <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> isoform is expressed in the ovary before pollination and in the root and stem. The isoform-specific expression pattern suggests a functional differentiation of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> alternatively spliced transcripts. The expression profile of miR172 is complementary to that of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> isoforms in inflorescence tissues before anthesis, whereas after anthesis and in ovary tissue before and after pollination, this relationship disappears, suggesting the existence of <italic>OitaAP2</italic> inhibitory mechanisms in these tissues that differ from that involving miR172.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the 2009 Regione Campania Grant L.R. N5/2002. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The large plant-specific superfamily APETALA2/Ethylene-Responsive element-binding Factor (AP2/ERF) includes transcription factors involved in various regulatory pathways. The highly conserved DNA-binding domain AP2 is shared by all members of the superfamily <xref rid="pone.0077454-Weigel1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Okamuro1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Based on the number of AP2 domains and the presence of other functional domains, the superfamily is divided into three families: AP2-like/AINTEGUMENTA (ANT), ERF-like and RAV. The AP2-like/ANT family, in which two AP2 domains are present <xref rid="pone.0077454-Kim1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, includes proteins that act in multiple stages and tissues during plant development <xref rid="pone.0077454-Jofuku1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Klucher1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Riechmann1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Boutilier1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Sequence comparison revealed that the AP2-like group can be further divided into AP2 and the RELATED TO AP2 (RAP2) groups <xref rid="pone.0077454-Okamuro1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. The ERF-like family and the RAV family are both characterized by a single AP2 domain, and their members are involved in the response to various environmental stresses <xref rid="pone.0077454-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Haake1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Dubouzet1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Gutterson1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. In addition to the single AP2 domain, the RAV family contains the DNA-binding domain B3 <xref rid="pone.0077454-Kagaya1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>.</p><p>The AP2-like proteins (both AP2 and RAP2) are encoded by mRNAs containing a conserved target site for the microRNA miR172 that regulates their activity at the post-transcriptional level, predominantly through mRNA cleavage and translational inhibition <xref rid="pone.0077454-Rhoades1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Aukerman1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. To date, a number of studies have analyzed the <italic>AP2-</italic>like genes; the majority of studies have focused on dicots and occasionally monocots (mainly Poaceae) <xref rid="pone.0077454-Chuck1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-GilHumanes1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Sharoni1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, gymnosperms <xref rid="pone.0077454-Vahala1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Nilsson1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Shigyo1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> and ferns <xref rid="pone.0077454-Kim1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>.</p><p>The <italic>AP2</italic>-like genes are involved in reproductive phase transition and flower development. Within the ABCDE model of flower development <xref rid="pone.0077454-Bowman1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Coen1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Pelaz1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Pinyopich1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, the <italic>AP2-</italic>like genes belong to the A-class and, alone or together with the B-class genes, are mainly involved in the specification of the identity of outer floral whorls (sepals and petals) <xref rid="pone.0077454-Jofuku1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Bowman1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Kunst1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Wollmann1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Yant1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, in ovule, seed and post-embryonic development <xref rid="pone.0077454-Jofuku1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Jofuku2" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Ohto1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Wurschum1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Guillaumot1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. The A- and C-class functions are mutually exclusive, even though recent studies conducted in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> demonstrated that the balance in expression of these two gene classes, moreso than the presence/absence of their gene products, regulates the correct formation of outer and inner floral whorls <xref rid="pone.0077454-Wollmann1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. AP2-like proteins interact with their specific binding sites located within intron 2 of the C-class <italic>AG</italic> gene, repressing its expression <xref rid="pone.0077454-Dinh1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. In addition to their role in flower development, some <italic>AP2</italic>-like genes are also expressed in vegetative tissues <xref rid="pone.0077454-Okamuro1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Licausi1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Rashid1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>.</p><p>The analysis of genes involved in the flower development pathway in model species is of great relevance (e.g., <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and <italic>Oryza</italic>) to the understanding of the general mechanisms that govern the formation of the floral organs. However, as revealed by the extension of the study of the B- and C-class genes to non-model species (such as orchids), gene functions often do not overlap, completely or in part, between these species and model species <xref rid="pone.0077454-Zahn1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-MondragonPalomino1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Salemme1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Salemme2" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>.</p><p>The family Orchidaceae is one of the largest among the flowering plants and is characterized by highly diversified flowers and reproductive strategies. The orchid flower is zygomorphic, with three outer tepals, two inner lateral tepals and an inner median tepal called labellum or lip. The male and female reproductive tissues are fused into a single structure known as column, at the base of which the ovary is located. The pollen grains (pollinia) are located at its top.</p><p>To date, studies of the <italic>AP2</italic>-like genes in orchids are restricted to species belonging to the subfamily Epidendroideae. The <italic>DcruAP2</italic> gene of <italic>Dendrobium crumenatum</italic> is expressed in all floral organs <xref rid="pone.0077454-Xu1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, and the twelve <italic>EpAP2</italic>-like genes of <italic>Erycina pusilla</italic> are expressed at different levels in flower and vegetative tissues <xref rid="pone.0077454-Lin1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. The function of the microRNA mir172 in the cleavage of <italic>AP2</italic>-like mRNA was also demonstrated in <italic>E. pusilla</italic> and <italic>Phalaenopsis aphrodite</italic> (Epidendroideae) <xref rid="pone.0077454-Lin1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-An1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>.</p><p>In this study we report the isolation, genomic characterization and expression analysis of the <italic>AP2</italic>-like gene <italic>OitaAP2</italic> in the orchid <italic>Orchis italica</italic> (Orchidoideae) and demonstrate that it is subjected to alternative splicing. In addition, we verified the presence of cleaved products generated by the interaction of miR172 with its specific target site within the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> mRNA, analyzed the expression pattern of miR172 within the floral tissues of <italic>O. italica</italic> and compared it to that of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> gene.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Isolation of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> cDNA</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from floral buds of <italic>O. italica</italic> using the TRIzol Reagent (Ambion). After DNase treatment (Ambion), RNA was quantified using a Nanodrop 2000c spectrophotometer (ThermoScientific) and reverse-transcribed (1 &#x000b5;g) using the Advantage RT-PCR kit (Clontech) and oligo dT primer. The degenerate forward primer AP2F2 (Table 1), which matches a region of the nucleotide sequence encoding the conserved AP2 domain, and the oligo dT primer were used to amplify 1 &#x000b5;l of cDNA using the LongAmp Taq PCR Kit (New England Biolabs), following the manufacturer instructions. The amplification products were cloned into the pGEM-T Easy vector (Promega), and several clones were sequenced using the plasmid primers T7 and SP6 and an ABI 310 Automated Sequencer (Applied Biosystems). Based on the obtained nucleotide sequences, two specific reverse primers (AP2R1 and AP2R2, Table 1) that anneal downstream of the region encoding the AP2 domains were designed to amplify the 5&#x02032;-coding and UTR terminus of the putative <italic>AP2</italic>-like cDNA using the FirstChoice RLM-RACE Kit (Ambion). The amplification product was cloned and sequenced as described above. The nucleotide sequences of the 5&#x02032;- and 3&#x02032;- regions of the putative <italic>AP2</italic>-like gene were overlapped using the software BIOEDIT <xref rid="pone.0077454-Hall1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, and the resulting full length sequence (called <italic>OitaAP2</italic>) was used to perform BLAST analysis.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0077454-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077454.t001</object-id><caption><title>Table 1. Nucleotide sequences of the primers used to amplify the cDNA and the genomic DNA of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> locus of <italic>Orchis italica.</italic>
</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0077454-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0077454.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Direction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence (5&#x02032;-3&#x02032;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Position</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2F8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">ATGGTGCTAGATCTCAACGTGTCAT</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2F4new</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">CATCAAACTCCTCTGTTCTCAATG</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89&#x02013;112</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2F1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GATGGGARTCKCAYATYTGGGA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">509&#x02013;530</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2F6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GGAAGAATTTGTGCATATTCTTCGG</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">690&#x02013;714</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2F5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">CTTCACAAATGTGGGCGGTG</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">766&#x02013;785</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2R5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">CACCGCCCACATTTGTGAAG</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">785&#x02013;766</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2F2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGGGARGCTMGNATGGGNCARTT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">780&#x02013;806</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2RealF_iso</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">CAAGAAATTGAAGGAAAGGGCCATGG</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1089&#x02013;1101; 1207&#x02013;1219</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2F4old</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GAGCATCCTCATGTTTGGGGCAG</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1153&#x02013;1175</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2R4old</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">CTGCCCCAAACATGAGGATGCTC</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1175&#x02013;1153</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2RealF</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">TGTGTACCCCGGATTATTTCCT</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1176&#x02013;1197</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2R2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">AGGAAATAATCCGGGGTACACA</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1197&#x02013;1176</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2R1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">TTTCTGGGGCCAAGTGGTCATGGT</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1260&#x02013;1237</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">APF3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">TGCAGCATCATCAGGATTC</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1296&#x02013;1314</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">APR3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GAATCCTGATGATGCTGCA</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1314&#x02013;1296</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2R9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">TCAGCTCTGAAAGAAGTGATGACG</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1431&#x02013;1407</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2R4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">CCTCTGGCTTCATTTGATATTGAG</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1558&#x02013;1535 (5&#x02032;-UTR)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>The primer positions are numbered starting from the first base of the ATG start codon (position 1) of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> cDNA.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Based on the BLASTX results, the amino acid sequences of AP2-like proteins were downloaded and aligned to the virtual translation of the OitaAP2 cDNA using the CLUSTAL OMEGA online tool. The resulting alignment was manually adjusted and used to construct the Maximum Likelihood tree using the software MEGA5 <xref rid="pone.0077454-Tamura1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>.</p><p>Several primers pairs were designed and used in PCR amplifications of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> cDNA to verify the existence of alternative splicing events (Table 1). All the obtained amplification fragments were cloned and sequenced as described above. The alternatively spliced form of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> gene was named <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Amplification of genomic DNA</title><p>Genomic DNA was extracted from <italic>O. italica</italic> leaf tissue <xref rid="pone.0077454-Doyle1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref> and used as a template in amplification reactions using several primer pairs (Table 1). PCR amplifications were performed using the LongAmp Taq PCR Kit (New England Biolabs) following the manufacturer instructions. The genomic region that includes intron 9 was particularly difficult to amplify. Different approaches were used, producing partially successful results that allowed us to map the position of intron 9. In brief, starting from 200 ng of genomic DNA of <italic>O. italica</italic>, a single strand elongation reaction was conducted using the AP2R4 primer (Table 1, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g001">Figure 1b</xref>). A poly-C tail was added to the 3&#x02032;-OH end of the obtained single stranded DNA using Terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase (Invitrogen). The reaction product was PCR-amplified using the forward primer 5&#x02032;-GGCCACGCGTCGACTAGTACGGGIIGGGIIGGGIIG-3&#x02032; and the nested <italic>OitaAP2</italic>-specific reverse primer AP2R9 (Table 1). All amplification products were cloned and sequenced as described above. The obtained nucleotide sequences were aligned and compared to the sequence of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> cDNAs.</p><fig id="pone-0077454-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077454.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Alternative splicing, mir172 target site and genomic organization of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> gene of <italic>O. italica</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Agarose gel electrophoresis of the PCR amplification products of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> cDNA with different primer pairs: lane 1, AP2F4new/AP2RealR; lane 2, AP2F4new/AP2R5; lane 3, AP2F5/APR3; lane 4, AP2RealF_iso/AP2R4; lane 5, AP2F5/AP2R2; lane 6, 100 bp DNA ladder (Thermo Scientific); lane 7, DNA Marker III (Thermo Scientific). (<bold>b</bold>) Schematic representation of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> cDNA with the relative positions of the primers used in the PCR amplifications. Black boxes represent the 5&#x02032;- and 3&#x02032;-UTRs; white boxes represent the exons; gray box represents the alternatively spliced region; dotted lines highlight the region corresponding to the miR172 target site with the black arrow indicating the cleavage point. (<bold>c</bold>) Agarose gel electrophoresis of the PCR amplification product of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> cDNA fragment cleaved by miR172 (lane 1); lane 2, 100 bp DNA ladder (Thermo Scientific). (<bold>d</bold>) Schematic representation of the genomic organization of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> gene. Black boxes represent the 5&#x02032;- and 3&#x02032;-UTRs; white boxes represent the exons; gray box represents the alternatively spliced exon; continuous lines represent introns; dotted lines indicate the two alternative splicing events; numbers indicate the length of introns (bp); question marks indicate the unknown size of intron 9.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0077454.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Identification of the miR172-cleaved <italic>OitaAP2</italic> mRNA</title><p>The 5&#x02032;-end of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> mRNA cleavage product produced by miR172 was determined by a modified 5&#x02032;-RACE <xref rid="pone.0077454-Llave1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref> using the RLM-RACE GeneRace kit (Invitrogen). In brief, starting from 500 ng of total RNA extracted from early column tissue, the 5&#x02032; adaptor was ligated to the 5&#x02032;-terminus of the RNA without any enzymatic treatment to remove the 5&#x02032; cap. After reverse transcription, cDNA was amplified with the GeneRace 5&#x02032; Primer and the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> gene-specific reverse primer AP2R4 (Table 1) that anneals within the 3&#x02032;-UTR, downstream of the miR172 cleavage site. The amplification product was cloned and sequenced as described above.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Expression analysis of <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and miR172</title><p>Total RNA was extracted as described above from outer and inner tepal, lip and column dissected from inflorescence of <italic>O. italica</italic> at two different stages: before anthesis (early, &#x0223c;9 mm diameter size) and after anthesis (late). In the early stage (the bud stage), cell division and flower organ formation are already completed; however, cell elongation is still occurring. Total RNA was extracted from unpollinated ovary tissue and, after manual fertilization, from ovary tissue collected 3, 7 and 10 days after pollination (dap). Before pollination, the ovules of <italic>O. italica</italic> are immature, and the megaspore mother cell is undergoing the first meiotic division. At 3 days after pollination, the female gametophyte is completely developed; at 7 days after pollination, fertilization has occurred and the seeds are in early developmental stages; at 10 days after pollination, the seeds are almost mature with seed coats completely developed (Barone Lumaga, personal communication). In addition, total RNA was extracted from root, stem and leaf tissue. After DNase treatment, RNA was quantified as described above.</p><p>For expression analysis of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> gene, 350 ng of total RNA from each tissue was reverse transcribed as described above. The isoform-specific primer pairs AP2RealF/APR3 and AP2RealF_iso/APR3 (Table 1) that selectively amplify a fragment of the two alternatively spliced <italic>OitaAP2</italic> mRNAs were used in the Real Time RT-PCR experiments.</p><p>For expression analysis of the microRNA miR172, the Poly(T) Adaptor RT-PCR method was used <xref rid="pone.0077454-Shi1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. Starting from 350 ng of total RNA from each tissue, a poly-T adaptor was ligated to the 3&#x02032;-terminus of the miRNAs and subsequently, reverse transcription was performed. The forward primer specific for miR172 was designed based on the nucleotide sequence of miR172 in <italic>P. aphrodite</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0077454-An1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref> and was used in combination with the poly-T adaptor reverse primer during the Real Time PCR experiments <xref rid="pone.0077454-Shi1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. The Poly(T) Adaptor RT-PCR product of several samples was cloned and sequenced, confirming the specificity of the amplification reaction.</p><p>Real time PCR experiments were performed on 30 ng of first strand cDNA from each tissue using the actin <italic>OitaAct</italic> as an endogenous control gene (GenBank accession number AB630020) using the conditions previously described <xref rid="pone.0077454-Salemme1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. Reactions were run in technical and biological triplicates. The Real Time PCR Miner online tool <xref rid="pone.0077454-Zhao1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref> was used to calculate PCR efficiency and optimal threshold cycle (C<sub>T</sub>) for each well. The mean relative expression ratio (rER) and standard deviation of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> gene and of the miR172 microRNA in the different tissues were calculated within each technical triplicate using <italic>OitaAct</italic> as the endogenous control gene and leaf cDNA as the reference sample <xref rid="pone.0077454-Schefe1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. Subsequently, the mean rER relative to each tissue of each biological replicate was averaged and standard deviation was calculated. Differences in the relative expression levels of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> isoforms and mir172 between and/or among the different tissues were assessed by the two-tailed t test and ANOVA followed by the Tukey HSD post-hoc test, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>In situ hybridization</title><p>Inflorescences before anthesis were fixed in 4% (v/v) paraformaldehyde, 0.5% (v/v) glutaraldehyde, 0.1% Triton X-100 and 4% dimethylsulfoxide in phosphate-saline buffer 1X for 16 h at 4&#x000b0;C <xref rid="pone.0077454-Javelle1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref> and then dehydrated through an ethanol series, paraffin embedded and sectioned at 7 &#x000b5;m.</p><p>Two different digoxigenin-labeled sense and antisense RNA probes, one corresponding to exon 9 and specific for the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> isoform and the other including the 3&#x02032;-end of exon 8 followed by the 5&#x02032;-end of exon 10 and specific for the <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> isoform, were synthesized using the T7 and SP6 RNA polymerases and the DIG RNA Labeling kit (Roche). Hybridization and immunological detection of the signals with alkaline phosphatase was performed using the DIG Nucleic Acid Detection kit (Roche) following the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="s3a"><title>The <italic>OitaAP2</italic> cDNA: alternative splicing</title><p>The isolation of <italic>OitaAP2</italic> cDNA was performed using first strand cDNA from the inflorescence of <italic>O. italica</italic> as a template in PCR reactions conducted in the presence of a degenerate forward primer that anneals within the region encoding the AP2 domain 1 and the poly-T reverse primer. This reaction produced two different amplification fragments of &#x0223c;1200 and 1100 bp that were cloned and sequenced. Alignment of the two sequenced fragments revealed their full nucleotide identity, excluding a 105 bp region that was absent in the shorter fragment. BLAST analysis showed that both fragments encode a partial AP2-like protein. Based on these preliminary results, specific reverse primers were designed to obtain the 5&#x02032;-terminus of these cDNAs, and, subsequently, a number of forward and reverse specific primers were designed (Table 1) to verify whether the observed fragments could be the product of an alternative splicing event. PCR amplifications of the cDNA from <italic>O. italica</italic> inflorescence were conducted with different primer pairs. When the forward primer AP2F4new (which anneals 88 bp downstream of the ATG start codon) was used in combination with the AP2RealR primer (which anneals 191 bp upstream of the TGA stop codon), two amplification fragments (1173 and 1068 bp) were produced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g001">Figure 1a, lane 1</xref>), whereas a single fragment (698 bp) was obtained when the AP2F4new primer was used in combination with the AP2R5 reverse primer (which anneals within the region encoding the AP2 domain 2) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g001">Figure 1a, lane 2</xref>). Two amplification fragments (549 and 444 bp) were produced when the forward primer AP2F5 (reverse and complement of AP2R5) was used in combination with the APR3 reverse primer (which anneals &#x0223c;60 bp downstream of AP2RealR) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g001">Figure 1a, lane 3</xref>). A single amplification fragment (360 bp) was obtained when the primer AP2RealF_iso, which anneals 13 bp upstream and 13 bp downstream of the region missing in the shortest fragment, was used in combination with AP2R4 (which anneals within the 3&#x02032;-UTR) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g001">Figure 1a, lane 4</xref>). A single amplification fragment (433 bp) was obtained when the forward primer AP2F5 was used in combination with the AP2R2 primer (that anneals within the region absent in the shortest fragment) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g001">Figure 1a, lane 5</xref>). The relative primer positions are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g001">Figure 1b</xref>.</p><p>These results might be explained by a number of different phenomena (e.g. gene duplication, transposition events, etc). However, all the evidences strongly suggest the existence of an alternative splicing event resulting in two isoforms of different sizes named <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic>. The deletion of 105 bp, which differentiates the two isoforms, is in frame with the main ORF. The entire cDNA sequence of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> cDNA of <italic>O. italica</italic> is 2264 bp (GenBank accession number KF152921), whereas the size of the <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> cDNA is 2159 bp (accession number KF152922). Both <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and <italic>OitaAP2</italic>_<italic>ISO</italic> include identical 5&#x02032;- and 3&#x02032;-UTRs of 560 and 273 bp, respectively.</p><p>BLAST analysis revealed the highest similarity with the <italic>AP2</italic>-like loci <italic>EpAP2-11</italic> of the orchid <italic>Erycina pusilla</italic> (74% nucleotide and 68% amino acid identity) and <italic>DcruAP2</italic> of <italic>Dendrobium crumenatum</italic> (72% nucleotide and 60% amino acid identity), followed by the <italic>RAP2-7</italic>-like genes of <italic>Glycine max</italic>, <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> and other species. The amino acid alignment of the virtually translated sequence of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> (476 residues) and <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> (441 residues) cDNAs with the AP2-like sequences of different species retrieved from GenBank shows the presence of the two conserved AP2 domains (AP2R1 and AP2R2). In addition, upstream of the AP2 domains are the canonical Motifs 1 and 2 and a nuclear localization signal. A short conserved amino acid stretch located at the C-terminus corresponds to the target site of the microRNA miR172 on the <italic>AP2</italic> mRNA (data not shown). The maximum likelihood (ML) tree shows that the OitaAP2 and OitaAP2_ISO sequences are positioned within the RAP2 group of the AP2-like transcription factors, strictly related to the sequences of the other orchid species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g002">Figure 2</xref>). All these features indicate that the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> locus of <italic>O. italica</italic> is member of the <italic>AP2-</italic>like gene subfamily, where it seems to be orthologous to RAP2-7.</p><fig id="pone-0077454-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077454.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Maximum likelihood tree constructed on the alignment of the AP2-like amino acid sequences belonging to both AP2 and RAP2 groups.</title><p>Numbers indicate the bootstrap percentages (on 1000 replicates). The abbreviations used (those obtained in the present study are in bold) are in agreement with the GenBank definitions. <italic>Actinidia deliciosa</italic> AdelAP2-like (AER60526); <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> AthaRAP2-7 and AthaAP2 (NP_001189625 and NP_195410, respectively); <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> BdisRAP2-7-like (XP_003569031); <italic>Cucumis sativus</italic> CsatRAP2-7-like (XP_004148250); <italic>Dendrobium crumenatum</italic> DcruAP2-like (AAZ95247); <italic>Erycina pusilla</italic> EpAP2-11 and EpAP2-12 (AGI62047 and AGI62048, respectively); <italic>Fragaria vesca</italic> FvesRAP2-7-like (XP_004295997); <italic>Glycine max</italic> GmaxRAP2-7-like (XP_003542008); <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> HvulAP2-like (AAL50205); <italic>Ipomea nil</italic> InilAPETALA2B (BAD36744); <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic> MtruAP2 (XP_003606515); <italic>Orchis italica</italic> OitaAP2 and OitaAP2_ISO (KF152921 and KF152922, respectively); <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> OsatAP2-like (AAO65862); <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> SlycSlAP2e (NP_001233891); <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> TaesAP2-like (AAU88192); <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> VvinRAP2-7-like (XP_002284749); <italic>Zea mays</italic> ZmayAP2IDS1 (NP_001104904).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0077454.g002"/></fig><p>Both the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> cDNAs contain the conserved 21 bp sequence that represents the target site of miR172 on the mRNA. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, miR172 represents a negative post-transcriptional regulator of <italic>AP2</italic>; it cleaves the <italic>AP2</italic> mRNA and acts predominantly by translational inhibition <xref rid="pone.0077454-Aukerman1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Schwab1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>. This regulatory mechanism seems to be conserved among plant species <xref rid="pone.0077454-Lauter1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Chuck2" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-VarkonyiGasic1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. Using a modified 5&#x02032;RACE reaction <xref rid="pone.0077454-Llave1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, the miR172 5&#x02032;-end cleavage product of the <italic>OitaAP2/OitaAP2_ISO</italic> mRNA was successfully amplified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g001">Figure 1c</xref>). Cloning and sequencing of this fragment (&#x0223c;290 bp) revealed the position of the cleavage site within the miR172 target site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g001">Figure 1b</xref>). The nucleotide sequence of the other fragment (&#x0223c;390 bp) detectable in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g001">Figure 1c</xref> showed it is a PCR artifact. According to the results obtained in <italic>P. aphrodite</italic> and <italic>E. pusilla</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0077454-Lin1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-An1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, this finding demonstrates that in orchids, the regulatory mechanism that determines the translational repression of <italic>OitaAP2</italic> through miR172 is conserved.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Genomic structure of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> locus</title><p>Based on the differential splicing observed for the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> mRNA, it was necessary to characterize the genomic organization of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> locus of <italic>O. italica</italic>. To evaluate and compare the structure of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> gene with that of known <italic>AP2</italic>-like genes, the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> locus was amplified from genomic DNA using multiple primer pairs. Sequence comparison of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> cDNAs with the genomic sequence of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> locus (accession number KF152923) revealed the presence of 10 exons and 9 introns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g001">Figure 1d</xref>).</p><p>This gene structure appears conserved for the <italic>AP2</italic> genes of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, grapevine <xref rid="pone.0077454-Velasco1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref> and apple <xref rid="pone.0077454-Velasco2" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>, all of which constitute 10 exons and 9 introns. The twelve <italic>AP2</italic>-like genes of the orchid <italic>E. pusilla</italic> show an intron number ranging from 7 to 11; however, the specific structure of the <italic>EpAP2-11</italic> gene, the putative ortholog of <italic>OitaAP2</italic>, is not reported <xref rid="pone.0077454-Lin1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. The size of the exons and the position of the introns are quite conserved among the <italic>AP2</italic>-like genes. All the introns of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> gene have a relatively small size (ranging from 81 to 492 bp), with the only exception possibly represented by the intron 9. Numerous attempts to amplify this intron were unsuccessful; however, the only approach that resulted in a positive result allowed us to map the position and obtain a partial sequence of intron 9 (&#x0223c;340 bp). Two hypotheses could explain the difficulties in PCR amplification of this genomic region: the great size of intron 9 and/or its base composition, which might inhibit the polymerase activity. As the amplification condition tested allowed us to amplify large introns (up to 16,000 bp) in other orchid genes (e.g., <italic>OitaAG</italic> and <italic>OitaSTK</italic>) <xref rid="pone.0077454-Salemme2" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref> and the single strand DNA extension was interrupted a few hundred nucleotides upstream of the 3&#x02032;-end of intron 9, the hypothesis of a complex base composition seems more likely than that of an intron size greater than 16,000 bp.</p><p>All the introns identified contain the canonical 5&#x02032;GT and 3&#x02032;AT, with the only exception being intron 4, which presents a non-canonical 5&#x02032;GC donor splicing site. CENSOR analysis of the intron sequences showed traces of mobile elements belonging to class I and II transposable elements within the longest intron 5 (Chapaev-16_HM), intron 8 (Copia-10_TC-I) and part of the sequence of intron 9 (CR1-23_CQ) of <italic>OitaAP2</italic>. This result further confirms the abundance of mobile elements within orchid genomes, as detected for the <italic>OitaAG</italic> and <italic>OitaSTK</italic> genes <xref rid="pone.0077454-Salemme2" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>.</p><p>Nucleotide comparison of the genomic sequence of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> locus with the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> cDNA reveals that the isoform <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> is produced through differential splicing of the region spanning intron 8 to intron 9, with skipping of exon 9 (105 bp) that preserves the correct reading frame (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Alternative splicing of the <italic>AP2</italic>-like genes was reported in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> within the ANT group <xref rid="pone.0077454-Lin1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref> and more recently in kiwifruit within the AP2 group <xref rid="pone.0077454-VarkonyiGasic1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. To date, alternative splicing of the <italic>RAP2</italic>-like genes has not been described. Similarly to <italic>O. italica</italic>, the region involved in the alternative splicing of the <italic>AdAP2</italic> locus of kiwifruit spans from intron 8 to 9 and includes an unusually large intron. However, the alternative kiwifruit isoform <italic>AdAP2&#x00394;</italic>, whose functional significance is unknown, retains an additional fragment (named exon 9a) that alters the main reading frame and introduces a stop codon and a putative polyadenylation site, excluding the miR172 target site from the transcript.</p><fig id="pone-0077454-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077454.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Region of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> locus of <italic>O. italica</italic> involved in the alternative splicing.</title><p>Nucleotide alignment spans from exon 8 to exon 10 and includes intron sequences. Boxes indicate exons; Ns indicate unknown nucleotides of intron 9.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0077454.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Expression pattern of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> isoforms</title><p>Real-time RT-PCR experiments were performed to reveal the expression pattern of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> gene in <italic>O. italica</italic>. Isoform-specific reverse primers were used to distinguish between the expression profile of <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> in floral tissues from early and late inflorescence. The melting curve plots demonstrated the effectiveness of the primers used. The mean PCR efficiency for each gene (the target isoforms <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> and the endogenous control <italic>OitaAct</italic>) showed comparable values (data not shown). Both isoforms are ubiquitously expressed in the perianth in early and late inflorescence and are absent in the column (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Specifically, in the early inflorescence <italic>OitaAP2</italic> is more highly expressed in the outer and inner tepals than in the lip, whereas in the same tissues <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> is expressed at levels always significantly lower than those detected for <italic>OitaAP2</italic>. In late inflorescence, the expression level of <italic>OitaAP2</italic> decreases in the outer tepals and increases in the inner tepals and lip, whereas the amount of <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> mRNA increases in outer and inner tepals and, more strongly, in the lip (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g004">Figure 4</xref>). RNA <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization confirms the expression of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and presumably of the <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> isoform in all the organs of the perianth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g005">Figure 5</xref>). The relative expression ratio of <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> was evaluated also in ovary tissue before and after pollination (at 3, 7 and 10 dap) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g006">Figure 6</xref>). Both isoforms are expressed only in ovary before pollination, where the <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> is significantly more abundant than <italic>OitaAP2</italic>. RNA <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization confirms the expression of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and presumably of the <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> isoform in the ovary tissue before pollination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Relative expression analysis of <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> in vegetative tissues revealed very low amounts of <italic>OitaAP2</italic> mRNA, with a slight increase in stem tissue. In contrast, the expression of the <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> isoform is significantly higher in root and stem tissue (Figure 7).</p><fig id="pone-0077454-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077454.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Relative expression ratio (rER) of <italic>OitaAP2</italic>, <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> and mir172 in different tissues of <italic>O. italica</italic> at early and late stages.</title><p>Te_out, outer tepal; Te_inn, inner tepal; Co, column. Bars represent standard deviation of the biological replicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0077454.g004"/></fig><fig id="pone-0077454-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077454.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>RNA <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization of <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> in inflorescence tissue of <italic>O. italica</italic>.</title><p>Sections were hybridized with <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> antisense (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>) and sense (<bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold>) probes. Te_out, outer tepal; Te_inn, inner tepal; Co, column; Ov, ovary; Po, pollinia.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0077454.g005"/></fig><fig id="pone-0077454-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077454.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Relative expression ratio (rER) of <italic>OitaAP2</italic>, <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> and mir172 in ovary tissue of <italic>O. italica</italic> before and after pollination.</title><p>Ov_np, unpollinated ovary; Ov_3dap, Ov_7dap, and Ov_10dap, ovary 3, 7 and 10 days after pollination, respectively. Bars represent standard deviation of the biological replicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0077454.g006"/></fig><fig id="pone-0077454-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077454.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Relative expression ratio (rER) of <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> in vegetative tissues of <italic>O. italica</italic>.</title><p>Ro, root; St, stem; Le, leaf. Bars represent standard deviation of the biological replicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0077454.g007"/></fig><p>In orchids, the <italic>DcruAP2</italic> gene of <italic>D. crumenatum</italic> is expressed in all floral organs and leaves without differential splicing <xref rid="pone.0077454-Xu1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, and ML phylogenetic analysis revealed that this gene is orthologous to the <italic>EpAP2-12</italic> gene of <italic>E. pusilla</italic>, whereas the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> gene of <italic>O. italica</italic> is orthologous to the <italic>EpAP2-11</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g002">Figure 2</xref>), homologous to the <italic>RAP2.7</italic> gene of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and expressed both in floral and vegetative tissues <xref rid="pone.0077454-Lin1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. Studies conducted in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, rice and grapevine confirmed the expression of the <italic>RAP2-7</italic>-like genes in floral and vegetative tissues <xref rid="pone.0077454-Okamuro1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Licausi1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0077454-Rashid1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. However, differential splicing has never been described for these genes. In <italic>O. italica</italic>, the expression pattern of both isoforms, <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic>, is restricted to the outer and inner tepals and lip and is absent in the fused reproductive organs (column). The different expression level of the two isoforms, in particular in the lip from the late inflorescence, where the highest expression of the <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic> isoform is detected, might reflect a possible functional partition of the two isoforms in the development and maintenance of the perianth organs. The expression profile detected in the ovary before pollination and in vegetative tissues seems to confirm non-redundant functions of <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and <italic>OitaAP2_ISO</italic>, with the latter specifically involved in ovary formation (but not in post-pollination processes) and in root- and stem-specific functions. However, further studies are needed to confirm this hypothesis and to verify the presence of two <italic>AP2</italic> isoforms in other orchid species.</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Comparative expression analysis of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> isoforms and miR172</title><p>
<italic>AP2</italic>-like genes are negatively regulated by the microRNA miR172. To evaluate the relationship existing between <italic>OitaAP2</italic> and mir172 in <italic>O. italica</italic>, their relative expression patterns in different floral tissues was compared (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g004">Figure 4</xref>).</p><p>In the tissues from early inflorescence, the expression profile of miR172 was clearly complementary to that observed for the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> isoforms. In particular, miR172 appears to be expressed mainly in the column from early inflorescence and is almost absent in the other tissues. This pattern fully agrees with the repressive action of mir172 on the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> isoforms. Surprisingly, in the floral tissues from late inflorescence, miR172 is expressed at very low levels in all tissues, including the column. This behavior suggests that in <italic>O. italica</italic> the inhibitory role of miR172 on the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> transcripts is exerted until the stages preceding the anthesis, whereas the absence of <italic>OitaAP2</italic> mRNA in the column after anthesis might be related to different regulatory mechanisms.</p><p>In the ovary tissue, miR172 is expressed from pre-pollinated ovary to 10 days after pollination, as observed in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0077454-Wollmann1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, showing its possible involvement in ovary development. However, in the ovary tissue of <italic>O. italica</italic>, the miR172 expression pattern is not complementary to that observed for the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> isoforms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0077454-g006">Figure 6</xref>). These results also suggest that during ovary maturation the inhibition of the <italic>OitaAP2</italic> isoforms might not be directly realized through miR172-mediated cleavage.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors are grateful to Mrs. Rosaria Terracciano and Mr. Enzo Iacueo for their technical support. The authors wish to thank Prof. Salvatore Cozzolino for supplying the plant material and performing the manual pollination of ovaries in <italic>O. italica</italic> and Dr. Maria Rosaria Barone Lumaga for the description of the ovary development stages.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0077454-Weigel1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The APETALA2 domain is related to a novel type of DNA binding domain</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>388</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>389</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7773013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Okamuro1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Okamuro</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caster</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Villarroel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Montagu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jofuku</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The AP2 domain of APETALA2 defines a large new family of DNA binding proteins in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>94</volume>: <fpage>7076</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7081</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9192694</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Kim1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Phylogeny and domain evolution in the APETALA2-like gene family</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>120</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16151182</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Jofuku1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jofuku</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>den Boer</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Montagu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okamuro</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Control of Arabidopsis flower and seed development by the homeotic gene APETALA2</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1211</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1225</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7919989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Klucher1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Klucher</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reiser</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The AINTEGUMENTA gene of Arabidopsis required for ovule and female gametophyte development is related to the floral homeotic gene APETALA2</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>153</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8742706</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Riechmann1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Riechmann</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The AP2/EREBP family of plant transcription factors</article-title>. <source>Biol Chem</source>
<volume>379</volume>: <fpage>633</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>646</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9687012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Boutilier1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Boutilier</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Offringa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kieft</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ouellet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Ectopic expression of BABY BOOM triggers a conversion from vegetative to embryonic growth</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1737</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1749</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12172019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Liu1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kasuga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sakuma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Two transcription factors, DREB1 and DREB2, with an EREBP/AP2 DNA binding domain separate two cellular signal transduction pathways in drought- and low-temperature-responsive gene expression, respectively, in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1406</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9707537</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Haake1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Haake</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riechmann</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pineda</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomashow</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Transcription factor CBF4 is a regulator of drought adaptation in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>130</volume>: <fpage>639</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>648</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12376631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Dubouzet1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dubouzet</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sakuma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kasuga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dubouzet</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>OsDREB genes in rice, Oryza sativa L., encode transcription activators that function in drought-, high-salt- and cold-responsive gene expression</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>751</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>763</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12609047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Gutterson1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gutterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reuber</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Regulation of disease resistance pathways by AP2/ERF transcription factors</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>465</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>471</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15231271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Kagaya1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kagaya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ohmiya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>RAV1, a novel DNA-binding protein, binds to bipartite recognition sequence through two distinct DNA-binding domains uniquely found in higher plants</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>470</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>478</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9862967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Rhoades1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rhoades</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reinhart</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Prediction of plant microRNA targets</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>110</volume>: <fpage>513</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>520</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12202040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Aukerman1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Aukerman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Regulation of flowering time and floral organ identity by a MicroRNA and its APETALA2-like target genes</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>2730</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2741</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14555699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Chen1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A microRNA as a translational repressor of APETALA2 in Arabidopsis flower development</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>303</volume>: <fpage>2022</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2025</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12893888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Chuck1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chuck</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meeley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Floral meristem initiation and meristem cell fate are regulated by the maize AP2 genes ids1 and sid1</article-title>. <source>Development</source>
<volume>135</volume>: <fpage>3013</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3019</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18701544</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-GilHumanes1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gil-Humanes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Piston</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Comparative genomic analysis and expression of the APETALA2-like genes from barley, wheat, and barley-wheat amphiploids</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>66</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19480686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Sharoni1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sharoni</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nuruzzaman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Satoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kondoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Gene structures, classification and expression models of the AP2/EREBP transcription factor family in rice</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>344</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>360</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21169347</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Vahala1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Vahala</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oxelman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>von Arnold</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Two APETALA2-like genes of Picea abies are differentially expressed during development</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>1111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1115</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11432927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Nilsson1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carlsbecker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sundas-Larsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vahala</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>APETALA2 like genes from Picea abies show functional similarities to their Arabidopsis homologues</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>
<volume>225</volume>: <fpage>589</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>602</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16953432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Shigyo1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shigyo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Analysis of gymnosperm two-AP2-domain-containing genes</article-title>. <source>Dev Genes Evol</source>
<volume>214</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>114</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14986134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Bowman1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Genetic interactions among floral homeotic genes of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Development</source>
<volume>112</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1685111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Coen1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Coen</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>The War of the Whorls - Genetic Interactions Controlling Flower Development</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>353</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1715520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Pelaz1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pelaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ditta</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baumann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wisman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yanofsky</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>B and C floral organ identity functions require SEPALLATA MADS-box genes</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>405</volume>: <fpage>200</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>203</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10821278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Pinyopich1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pinyopich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ditta</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Savidge</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liljegren</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baumann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Assessing the redundancy of MADS-box genes during carpel and ovule development</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>424</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12840762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Kunst1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kunst</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klenz</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martinez-Zapater</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haughn</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>AP2 Gene Determines the Identity of Perianth Organs in Flowers of Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>1195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1208</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12359889</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Wollmann1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wollmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mica</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Todesco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>On reconciling the interactions between APETALA2, miR172 and AGAMOUS with the ABC model of flower development</article-title>. <source>Development</source>
<volume>137</volume>: <fpage>3633</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3642</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20876650</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Yant1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yant</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mathieu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dinh</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lanz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Orchestration of the floral transition and floral development in Arabidopsis by the bifunctional transcription factor APETALA2</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>2156</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2170</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20675573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Jofuku2"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jofuku</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Omidyar</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gee</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okamuro</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Control of seed mass and seed yield by the floral homeotic gene APETALA2</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>102</volume>: <fpage>3117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3122</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15708974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Ohto1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ohto</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Control of seed mass by APETALA2</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>102</volume>: <fpage>3123</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3128</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15708976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Wurschum1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wurschum</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gross-Hardt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>APETALA2 regulates the stem cell niche in the Arabidopsis shoot meristem</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>307</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16387832</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Guillaumot1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Guillaumot</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lelu-Walter</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Germot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meytraud</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gastinel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Expression patterns of LmAP2L1 and LmAP2L2 encoding two-APETALA2 domain proteins during somatic embryogenesis and germination of hybrid larch (Larix x marschlinsii)</article-title>. <source>J Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>165</volume>: <fpage>1003</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1010</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18160178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Dinh1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dinh</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Girke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yant</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The floral homeotic protein APETALA2 recognizes and acts through an AT-rich sequence element</article-title>. <source>Development</source>
<volume>139</volume>: <fpage>1978</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1986</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22513376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Licausi1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Licausi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giorgi</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zenoni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Osti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pezzotti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genomic and transcriptomic analysis of the AP2/ERF superfamily in Vitis vinifera</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>719</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21171999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Rashid1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guangyuan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guangxiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>AP2/ERF Transcription Factor in Rice: Genome-Wide Canvas and Syntenic Relationships between Monocots and Eudicots</article-title>. <source>Evol Bioinform Online</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>355</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22807623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Zahn1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zahn</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leebens-Mack</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DePamphilis</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Theissen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>To B or Not to B a flower: the role of DEFICIENS and GLOBOSA orthologs in the evolution of the angiosperms</article-title>. <source>J Hered</source>
<volume>96</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>240</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15695551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-MondragonPalomino1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mondragon-Palomino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Theissen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Conserved differential expression of paralogous DEFICIENS- and GLOBOSA-like MADS-box genes in the flowers of Orchidaceae: refining the &#x02018;orchid code&#x02019;</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>1008</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1019</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21435045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Salemme1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Salemme</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sica</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaudio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aceto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Expression pattern of two paralogs of the PI/GLO-like locus during Orchis italica (Orchidaceae, Orchidinae) flower development</article-title>. <source>Dev Genes Evol</source>
<volume>221</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>246</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21892737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Salemme2"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Salemme</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sica</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaudio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aceto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The OitaAG and OitaSTK genes of the orchid Orchis italica: a comparative analysis with other C- and D-class MADS-box genes</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Rep</source>
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>3523</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3535</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23277396</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Xu1"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Floral organ identity genes in the orchid Dendrobium crumenatum</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>46</volume>: <fpage>54</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16553895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Lin1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Catalog of Erycina pusilla miRNA and categorization of reproductive phase-related miRNAs and their target gene families</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
<volume>82</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>204</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23575662</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-An1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>An</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Sequencing-based approaches reveal low ambient temperature-responsive and tissue-specific microRNAs in phalaenopsis orchid</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e18937</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21573107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Hall1"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NT</article-title>. <source>Nucl Acids Symp Ser</source>
<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Tamura1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>MEGA5: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>2731</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2739</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21546353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Doyle1"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>A rapid DNA isolation procedure for small amounts of leaf tissue</article-title>. <source>Phytochem Bull</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Llave1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Llave</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kasschau</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Cleavage of Scarecrow-like mRNA targets directed by a class of Arabidopsis miRNA</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>297</volume>: <fpage>2053</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2056</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Shi1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Poly(T) adaptor RT-PCR</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>
<volume>822</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22144191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Zhao1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fernald</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Comprehensive algorithm for quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction</article-title>. <source>J Comput Biol</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1047</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1064</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16241897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Schefe1"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Schefe</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buschmann</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Unger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Funke-Kaiser</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Quantitative real-time RT-PCR data analysis: current concepts and the novel &#x0201c;gene expression's CT difference&#x0201d; formula</article-title>. <source>J Mol Med</source>
<volume>84</volume>: <fpage>901</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>910</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16972087</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Javelle1"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Javelle M, Marco CF, Timmermans M (2011) In situ hybridization for the precise localization of transcripts in plants. J Vis Exp: e3328.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Schwab1"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palatnik</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riester</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schommer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Specific effects of microRNAs on the plant transcriptome</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>517</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>527</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15809034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Lauter1"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lauter</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kampani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goebel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moose</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>microRNA172 down-regulates glossy15 to promote vegetative phase change in maize</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>102</volume>: <fpage>9412</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9417</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15958531</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Chuck2"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chuck</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meeley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Irish</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The maize tasselseed4 microRNA controls sex determination and meristem cell fate by targeting Tasselseed6/indeterminate spikelet1</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>
<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1517</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1521</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18026103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-VarkonyiGasic1"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Varkonyi-Gasic</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lough</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hellens</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Kiwifruit floral gene APETALA2 is alternatively spliced and accumulates in aberrant indeterminate flowers in the absence of miR172</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
<volume>78</volume>: <fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>429</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22290408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Velasco1"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Velasco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zharkikh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Troggio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cartwright</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cestaro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A high quality draft consensus sequence of the genome of a heterozygous grapevine variety</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>e1326</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18094749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0077454-Velasco2"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Velasco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zharkikh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Affourtit</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dhingra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cestaro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The genome of the domesticated apple (Malus x domestica Borkh.)</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>
<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>833</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>839</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20802477</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>