<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3499474</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23166814</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-26332</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0050025</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Protein Chemistry</subject><subject>Protein Structure</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biophysics</subject><subj-group><subject>Protein Chemistry</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Macromolecular Structure Analysis</subject><subj-group><subject>Protein Structure</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Model Organisms</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Proteomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Analytical Chemistry</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Diagnostic Medicine</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Non-Clinical Medicine</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Pulmonology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>A Rapid Screening Assay to Search for Phosphorylated Proteins in Tissue Extracts </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Phosphorproteomics in Tissue Extracts</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garaguso</surname><given-names>Ignazio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Borlak</surname><given-names>Juergen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>Centre for Pharmacology and Toxicology, Hannover Medical School, Hannover, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Addison</surname><given-names>Christina Lynn</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute, Canada</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>Borlak.Juergen@mh-hannover.de</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: IG JB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: IG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: IG JB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: IG JB. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e50025</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2012 Garaguso, Borlak</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Garaguso, Borlak</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Reversible protein phosphorylation is an essential mechanism in the regulation of diverse biological processes, nonetheless is frequently altered in disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>As most phosphoproteome studies are based on optimized in-vitro cell culture studies new methods are in need to improve de novo identification and characterization of phosphoproteins in extracts from tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Here, we describe a rapid and reliable method for the detection of phosphoproteins in tissue extract based on an experimental strategy that employs 1D and 2D SDS PAGE, Western immunoblotting of phosphoproteins, in-gel protease digestion and enrichment of phosphorpeptides using metal oxide affinity chromatography (MOAC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, phosphoproteins are identified by MALDI-TOF-MS/MS with the CHCA-TL or DHB ML sample matrix preparation method and further characterized by various bioinformatic software tools to search for candidate kinases and phosphorylation-dependent binding motifs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The method was applied to mouse lung tissue extracts and resulted in an identification of 160 unique phosphoproteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Notably, TiO2 enrichment of pulmonary protein extracts resulted in an identification of additional 17 phosphoproteins and 20 phosphorylation sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>By use of MOAC, new phosphorylation sites were identified as evidenced for the advanced glycosylation end product-specific receptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>So far this protein was unknown to be phosphorylated in lung tissue of mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Overall the developed methodology allowed efficient and rapid screening of phosphorylated proteins and can be employed as a general experimental strategy for an identification of phosphoproteins in tissue extracts. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The authors gratefully acknowledge support from The Virtual Liver Network (grant 031 6154) of the German Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF). Part of this work was also funded by the Lower Saxony Ministry of Culture and Sciences and the Volkswagen foundation, Germany to JB. Grant number: 25A.5-7251-99-3/00. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. The charge for this publication was covered by the German Research Foundation (DFG) sponsorship “open access publication.”</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Reversible protein phosphorylation is a major cellular mechanism in the regulation of protein function and activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Such post-translational modifications of proteins are accomplished by the activities of protein kinases and reversed by phosphatases in a highly dynamic manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Approximately 500 protein kinases are encoded by the human genome to possibly phosphorylate more than 100 000 sites [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The predominant class of protein phosphorylation in eukaryotic cells is O-phosphates, and modifications occur on serine (S), threonine (T) and tyrosine (Y) residues at a stoichiometric ratio of 86.4%, 11.8% and 1.8%, respectively [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Phosphorylation of proteins changes their activities and is associated with translocation and modulation of protein–protein interaction to influence cellular processes including signal transduction, cell differentiation, proliferation, metabolic maintenance, cell division, as well as programmed cell death [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Importantly, an imbalance between phosphorylation and de-phosphorylation results in a wide range of pathological conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Thus, inhibiting kinases is the subject of molecular targeted therapies, particularly in the treatment of cancers where hyperactivity of kinases is frequently observed [4]–[7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>While it is highly desirable to study entire phosphoproteomes, an identification of low abundance phosphoproteins and an assessment of the stoichiometry of protein phosphorylation is challenging, especially when current protocols are applied to small amounts of tissues such as that of lung of mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>As a result of this only a small number of investigators reported studies on the pulmonary proteome and these are based primarily on cell lines [8]–[10] or nasal/bronchoalveolar lavage [11]–[13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>However, in biomedical research diverse mouse models are employed to study disease mechanisms, yet the mapping of components, regulatory events and substrates in signaling pathways remains challenging and is impaired by the lack of an easy method to study more comprehensively entire proteomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, in recent years, research on phosphoproteins benefitted from the availability of antibodies that selectively recognize phosphorylated amino acid residues [14]–[17], thus enabling a more broad search of phosphoproteins [18] even though some may prove to be ineffective in the recognition of phosphoproteins [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Thus, a variety of experimental strategies for the enrichment and detection of phosphorylated proteins has been developed but none of these approaches can be regarded as universally applicable with the mapping and characterization of phosphoproteins requiring a combination of different methods and experimental strategies [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Specifically, metal oxide affinity chromatography (MOAC) with titanium dioxide (TiO2) has been employed for the selective enrichment of phosphopeptides prior to MS [20], [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>This technique is based on the selective interaction of phosphopeptides with porous TiO2 microspheres (titanspheres) via bidentate binding at the TiO2 surface and in combination with MALDI-MS to allow the detection of phosphopeptides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Likewise, separation of complex protein mixtures by two-dimensional electrophoresis (2-DE) and the combination of 2-DE with MALDI-MS for proteome and phosphoproteome mapping studies have been reported as a successful strategy [22]–[24] while other investigators used HPLC- coupled with ESI-MS/MS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0050025-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0050025.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Description of the combined 2-DE-WB approach. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>200 µg of tissue lysate protein extracts were separated on 2-DE, stained with Colloidal Coomassie G-250 and acquired as an image (2-DE-cCBB). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In parallel 40 µg of total protein extract was separated by 2-DE and subsequently transferred onto PVDF membrane for incubation with antibodies directed against phosphorylated proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>With a marker pen, landmarks points (crosses in Figure) were set around the membrane and the image of phosphorylated proteins was acquired (WB-pAb). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, the total proteins on the same membrane were revealed by cCCB-post staining and the image was recorded (WB-CBB). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Using the marker added landmarks the two images were superimposed and combined by the image analysis software to create a virtual image showing the phosphoproteins and the total proteins together (WB-virtual). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Several protein spots from this image, which are in common with the cCBB-2-DE image, were selected as additional landmarks and used to superimpose the WB-CCB image to the 2-DE-cCBB image. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>This allowed deciphering of phosphorylated proteins on the gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Highlighted spots were then excised from the gel using a spot cutter, followed by in-gel digestion using trypsin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The proteins were identified using MALDI-TOF MS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0050025.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>To overcome current limitations in phosphoproteomic analyses of tissue extracts a simple and fast method was developed consisting of 1D or 2D SDS-PAGE, Western immunoblotting (WB) of phosphoproteins, in-gel protease digestion and in the case of 1D gel electrophoresis enrichment of phosphopeptides using TiO2-MOAC micro columns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, proteins were analyzed by MALDI-TOF-MS/MS and further characterized using various bioinformatic software tools to search for candidate kinases and phosphorylation-dependent binding motifs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Finally, phosphoproteins were classified with respect to their Gene Ontology (GO). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0050025-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0050025.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>2-DE maps. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>200 µg of tissue lysate protein extracts were separated on 2-DE and stained with Colloidal Coomassie G-250 and acquired as an image (2-DE-cCBB). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>In parallel 40 µg of total protein extract was separated by 2-DE and subsequently transferred onto PVDF membrane for incubation with antibodies directed against phosphorylated proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>With a marker pen, landmarks points (some are highlighted by arrows in the Figure) were set around the membrane to be used for computer assisted merging and matching of images of phosphorylated proteins as acquired with the Abs WB-Yset, WB-pSset, WB-4G10, WB-MPM-2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, protein spots on the same membrane were revealed by cCCB-post staining and the image was recorded (not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Using the marker added landmarks, the images were superimposed and combined by the image analysis software to create a virtual image showing the phosphoproteins and the total proteins together (WB-virtual). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0050025.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Ethics Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>All animal work followed strictly the Public Health Service (PHS) Policy on Humane Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Formal approval to carry out animal studies was granted by the institutional board and the ethical review board of the city of Hannover, Germany. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The approval ID is Az: 33.9-42502-04-06/1204. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0050025-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0050025.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Identification of phosphoproteins with the pSset of MAbs and by MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry using two different matrix layer sample preparation methods. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Two different MALDI sample preparation methods in combination enabled reliable identification of proteins. Panel A: In 2-DE-cCBB stained gels spot 7409 and 7411 are not well separated but WB with the pSset MAbs resolved three distinct spots. Panel B: With the CHCA TL sample matrix preparation the heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoproteins A2/B1 (O88569) was identified by MALDI-MS and confirmed by MS/MS (Panel B, right spectra). Panel C: When the same spots were analyzed with the DHB ML sample preparation method glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (P16858) was additionally identified by MALDI-MS (upper panel C, left spectra marked as MS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Then, single protonated peptides were selected from the spectrum as precursor ions for MALDI-MS/MS analysis, i.e. 1013.451, 1779,797 and 1570, 813 m/z. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Depicted are three individual MS/MS spectra of the selected precursor ions to confirm the identity of the protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0050025.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Animal Care </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Mice C57BL/6 were maintained under specific pathogen free conditions in the facilities of the center and housed in Makrolon® Type III cages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Drinking water and food (V1124-000, SSNIFF, The Netherlands) were given ad libitum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The temperature and relative humidity were 22±2°C and 40–70%, respectively and a 12-h day and night cycle was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Mice were anesthetized with CO2 and sacrificed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>After surgical removal the lung was washed with PBS containing protease and phosphatases inhibitors until free of blood. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0050025-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0050025.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Distribution of identified proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Identified proteins were assigned on the basis of information provided by GO lists downloaded from PIR (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pir.georgetown.edu/">http://pir.georgetown.edu/</ext-link>).to (a) cellular component or (b) molecular function. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0050025.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The following materials were obtained from Bruker Daltonics (Bremen, Germany): α-cyano-4-hydroxycinnamic acid (CHCA), 2,5-dihydroxybenzoic acid (DHB) and MALDI pre-structured sample support (AnchorChip™ 384/600). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Sequencing grade modified trypsin was bought from Promega Co. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>(Madison, WI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Protease inhibitor kit III and Phosphatase inhibitor kit II were purchased from Merck (Darmstadt, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The 4G10 and MPM-2 monoclonal antibodies were from Millipore (Billerica, MA), all other antibodies were obtained from ALEXIS (Enzo, Lörrach, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The IPG pH 3-11 strips and buffer solution were obtained from GE Healthcare (München, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>All chemicals and reagents were of the highest grade available. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0050025-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0050025.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Identified phosphopeptide by MALDI tandem MS using DHB ML sample preparation. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0050025-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0050025.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Protein Entry Name </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Accession </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Sequence </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Start end </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Meas. mass </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Ion Score </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Miss </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>MW </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Angiotensin-converting enzyme </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>P09470 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>R.GPQFGSEVELR.H </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>1300–1310 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>1298.57765 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>63 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>151.888 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Calnexin precursor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>P35564 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>K.AEEDEILNRSPR.N </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>573–584 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>1508.67402 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>39 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>67.733 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Advanced glycosylation end product-specific receptor </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Q62151 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>R.KAPESQEDEEER.A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>373–384 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>1526.60058 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>60 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>43.068 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Nascent polypeptide-associated complex alpha subunit </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>P70670 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>R.SVTDPAMAPRTAK.N </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>588–600 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>1600.58786 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>221.603 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Matrix-remodeling-associated protein 7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Q9CZH7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>R.VAEPEESEAEEPAAEGR.Q </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>73–89 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>1879.75921 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>82 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>19.516 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Tensin </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>gi|226437589 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>R.SQSFPDVEPQLPQAPTR.G </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>790–806 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>1976.91134 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>56 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>203.317 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Arginase-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Q61176 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>-.MSSKPKSLEIIGAPFSK.G </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>1–17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>2075.89248 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>35 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>34.999 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>60S acidic ribosomal protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>P99027 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>K.KEESEESDDDMGFGLFD.- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>99–115 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>2125.68687 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>40 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>11.651 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>60S acidic ribosomal protein P1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>P47955 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>K.KEESEESEDDMGFGLFD.- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>98–114 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>2139.70251 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>40 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>11.610 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Myosin phosphatase Rho-interacting protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>P97434 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>R.AEEQLPPLLSPPSPSTPHSR.R </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>280–299 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>2220.06959 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>27 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>117.357 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Alpha-1 catenin </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>P26231 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>R.TPEELDDSDFETEDFDVR.S </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>634–651 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>2238.85983 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>127 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>100.896 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Membrane-associated progesterone receptor component </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>O55022 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>K.EGEEPTVYSDDEEPKDETAR.K </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>173–192 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>2375.93983 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>112 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>21.692 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>60S acidic ribosomal protein P0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>P14869 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>K.AEAKEESEESDEDMGFGLFD.- </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>298–317 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>2410.81924 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>45 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>34.408 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Septin-2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>P42208 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>K.IYHLPDAESDEDEDFKEQTR.L </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>210–229 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>2517.04527 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>115 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>41.783 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>EH domain-containing protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Q8BH64 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>R.GPDEAIEDGEEGSEDDAEWVVTK.D </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>426–448 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>2557.01375 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>112 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>50.135 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Elongation factor 1-delta </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>P57776 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>K.GATPAEDDEDKDIDLFGSDEEEEDKEAAR.L </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>145–173 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>3276.32225 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>144 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>31.916 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Serum deprivation-response protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Q63918 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>R.GNNSAVGSNADLTIEEDEEEEPVALQQAQQVR.Y </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>356–387 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>3520.57109 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>135 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>46.806 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>R.RGNNSAVGSNADLTIEEDEEEEPVALQQAQQVR.Y </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>355–387 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>3676.67219 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>105 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>K.SSPFKVSPLSFGR.K </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>287–299 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>1488.72465 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>53 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Phosphopeptides identified by MALDI-TOF-MS/MS from 50 µg of protein extracted from mouse lung and separated by SDS-PAGE. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt102"><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>S = phosphorylated serine determined by MALDI TOF-MS/MS. M = oxidized methionine. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0050025-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0050025.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>MALDI-TOF MS/MS of phosphopeptides. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Characterization of phosphorylation sites of phosphorylated peptides by MALDI-TOF-MS/MS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0050025.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Proteins Extraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Whole lung tissue explants were washed twice with wash buffer (20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.4) containing phosphatase inhibitors and protease inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The tissue was disrupted with an ultrasound sonicator in lysis buffer (0,5% SDS, 100 mM DTT in 20 mMTris-HCl, pH 7.4) containing phosphatase inhibitors (diluted 1∶100) and protease inhibitors (diluted 1∶100). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Then, proteins were precipitated with TCA/Acetone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>After centrifugation at 20,000×g for 20 min at 4°C, the pellet was re-suspended in a buffer solution of 8 M Urea, 2 M Thiourea, 2% CHAPS, 2% ASB 14, 65 mM DTT, 5% IPG Buffer pH 3-11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The protein concentration was determined by the Bradford reagent (Sigma-Aldrich, Germany). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0050025-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0050025.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Specificity of the anti-phosphoproteins antibodies. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>The phosphoserine specific antibodies pSset recognized aldehyde dehydrogenase (P47738) and selenium-binding protein 1 (P17563), whereas the MPM-2, sYset and 4G10 identified the former only. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>O = spots identified as selenium-binding protein 1 (P17563); X = spots identified as aldehyde dehydrogenase (P47738). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>On the right side are depicted the same membrane after cCCB post staining. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0050025.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>High-resolution 2-DE </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>250 µg of total tissue protein extracts were separated with 2-DE and gels were stained by colloidal Coomassie Brilliant Blue G-250 (cCBB) as described previously [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Phosphoproteins were detected by Western immunoblotting as described below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>1D SDS-PAGE </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Proteins were loaded onto polyacrylamide gels [stacking: 4%T, 2.6%C (Bis); resolving gel 12%T, 2.6%C (Bis), 2% SDS] and ran in a Mini-PROTEAN III, (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA) according to the manufacturer recommendations and stained with colloidal Coomassie Brilliant Blue (cCBB). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Then, visible bands were excised and after in-gel protein digestion phophoproteins were enriched by metal oxide affinity chromatography as detailed below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>In-gel Digestion of Proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>CCB-stained protein-bands were removed from SDS-PAGE gels with a scalpel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Protein-spots from 2-DE gel were cut using EXQuest™ spot cutter (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>In-gel digestion was performed according to standard protocols [26] with minor modifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>The protein-bands and protein-spots were rehydrated in 30 µl and 16 µl of a digestion buffer, respectively containing 50 mM NH4HCO3 and 10 ng/µl of trypsin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>The digestion was allowed to proceed at 37°C for 4 hours and was subsequently stopped finally with a 0.5% TFA solution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>TiO2 Enrichment of Phosphopeptides </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Enrichment of phosphorylated peptides was accomplished by metal oxide affinity chromatography (MOAC) with TiO2 beads on self-assembled disposable micro column (µ-MOAC-TiO2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>For each sample to be purified, a micro purification column was packed into a 2–200 µl pipette tip (Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany) using a small plug of glass microfiber filter (Whatman, Dassel, Germany) as a frit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>The column consisted of a very small volume bed (∼1.5 mm thick bed stationary phase) of TiO2 beads (5µm; GL Sciences, Tokio, Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>The µ-MOAC TiO2 were conditioned/activated with 2×30 µl of acetonitril, equilibrated with 2×30 µl of loading/wash (L/W) solution (50% acetonitrile, 1% TFA solution). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Typically, 30 µl of tryptic digest solution were loaded onto the column and washed with 3×30 µl of LW solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>The phosphopeptides were eluted from the column with 3×10 µl of elution solution (5% NH4OH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>The elutes were reduced to dryness in a rotor concentrator (Christ, Germany) and resuspended in a solution of 5% acetonitrile, 0.1% TFA suitable for MALDI-MS analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>MALDI Matrix Sample Preparation Protocols </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>A CHCA thin-layer (TL) matrix was prepared and deposited on the AnchorChip™ (Bruker Daltonics) sample support as described previously [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Once dry, 1 µl of in-gel tryptic digest was deposited and thereafter re-crystallized “on-target” using 0.5 µl of re-crystallization solution (ethanol: acetone: TFA 0.1%, 6∶3:1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>In addition, a DHB matrix layer (ML) was prepared and deposited on the AnchorChip™ sample support (Bruker Daltonics) using the conditions detailed in [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Without further modifications either 1 µl of in-gel tryptic digest or TiO2-MOAC enriched phosphopeptide extracts, were deposited to await MALDI-MS analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Mass Spectrometric Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>MALDI-MS experiments were carried out with an Ultraflex II MALDI-TOF/TOF mass spectrometer equipped with a SmartBeam™ laser and a LIFT-MS/MS facility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The instrument was operated in positive ion reflectron mode and an acceleration voltage of 25 keV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Typically, 400 spectra over a 600–4000 m/z mass range, acquired at 100Hz, were summed and externally calibrated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The MS/MS-CID spectra were obtained by use of the LIFT device for selection and fragmentation of the ions, acceleration voltage in the ion source was 8 kV, the Timed Ion Selector was set to 0.4% (relative to parent mass), and argon was used as collision gas (∼4–6×10–6 mbar). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Resulting fragments were further accelerated in a second source by 19 kV and analyzed by a two-stage gridless reflectron. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Typically, 600 shots were accumulated for the parent ion signal and 1000–2500 shots for the fragments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>FlexControl™ 3.0, and FlexAnalysis™ 3.0 were used as instrument control and processing software (instrumentation and software from Bruker Daltonics, Bremen, Germany). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2k"><title><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Calibration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Spectra were externally calibrated using a peptide calibration standard that is a mixture of seven peptides (cod. # 22570, Bruker Daltonics). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>The mixture was spotted onto positions adjacent to the samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Additional internal mass calibration of peptide mass maps was performed using trypsin autolysis products (m/z 842.51 and m/z 2211.10). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2l"><title><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Protein Identification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Automated MALDI-MS spectra acquisition, tandem MS/MS spectra selection and acquisition as well as protein identification were carried out with the Proteinscape software (Bruker Daltronics), using the SwissProt protein database and Mascot searches for variable modifications (v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>2.0, Matrix sciences; UK) software [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Sequence database searches were done using the following search parameters for MS and MS/MS data: all entries; mass tolerance: 100 ppm for parent ion; 0.9 Da for fragments, one missed cleavage site; cysteine residues modified with acrylamide and methionine oxidation as partial modification. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2m"><title><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Western Blot Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>After 2-DE separation, the proteins were electro-blotted onto PVDF membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>The blotted membranes were rinsed with TBS buffer (100 mM NaCl, 10 mM Tris-HCl ph 7.5) and blocked with 3% BSA in TBS buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Thereafter, membranes were rinsed with TBS-T solution (0,1% Tween in TBS buffer) to remove excess of BSA and incubated with different anti-phosphoprotein specific monoclonal antibody (MAb) solutions (see Table S1) diluted as 1∶1000 with 3% BSA in TBS-T buffer for a minimum of 90 min to over night at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Then the membrane were washed 4 times with TBS-T solution, and incubated with horseradish peroxidase-goat anti-mouse conjugate polyclonal anti-IgG or anti-IgM antibodies, diluted as 1∶1000 in TBS-T containing 1% BSA for about 90 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>The protein-antibody complexes were visualized with an OPTI-4-CN kit (Biorad), air dried. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, reference points were added and images acquired. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Finally, dry membranes were immersed in cCCB-post-staining solution [5% Al2(SO4)3 2% H3PO4, 25% ethanol, 0.02% Coomassie G-250] for 15 minutes, then washed with water, and new images were acquired. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Each sample was run in triplicate, reprehensive results are presented. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2n"><title><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Image Acquisition and Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>The images of cCCB stained gel, immuno-developed and cCCB-post-stained PVDF membranes were acquired with an Expression 10000 XL scanner (Epson, Germany) at 16 bit and 50 µm/pixel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Prior to image acquisition of the immuno-developed PVDF membranes, 8–12 dots as reference point were added manually on the boundary region and in the middle of membrane with a marker pen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Image analysis was done with the software PDQuest v 8.0.1 (Bio-Rad), and the alignment and matching process was supervised. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2o"><title><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Prediction and Classification of Phosphoproteins and Phosphorylation Sites </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>The NetPhos 2.0 server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/NetPhos/">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/NetPhos/</ext-link>) [29] was used to predict the number and position of potential protein phosphorylation sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Database searches within PhosphoSitePlus® (PSP) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phosphosite.org/">http://www.phosphosite.org/</ext-link>) [30], Phospho.ELM 9.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://phospho.elm.eu.org/">http://phospho.elm.eu.org/</ext-link>) [31] and UniProt (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uniprot.org/">http://www.uniprot.org/</ext-link>) [32] were additionally carried out to gain information about the exact position of known phosphorylated sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Scansite 2.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scansite.mit.edu">http://scansite.mit.edu</ext-link>) [33] was used to predict candidate Ser/Thr- or Tyr-kinases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Here, motive searches of specific amino acid sequence of phosphorylated protein helped to identify candidate kinases responsible for the phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Finally, gene ontology (GO) lists were downloaded using the protein information resource (PIR) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pir.georgetown.edu/">http://pir.georgetown.edu/</ext-link>) [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Each protein was classified with respect to its cellular component and molecular function using GO annotation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2p"><title><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>A Combined 2-DE-Western Blotting Approach </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>To screen for phosphorylated proteins a combination of different techniques and technologies were employed, i.e. (1) 2-DE, (2) 2-DE-Western blotting with antibodies recognising phosphorylated proteins, (3) computer assisted image analysis and processing, (4) MALDI-TOF tandem mass spectrometry (MS) with automated spectra acquisition and analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>These technologies have been put together as depicted in Figure 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>A detailed description of the procedure is given below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Mice were sacrified and lungs were removed and washed free of blood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Then the lung tissue was disrupted with a sonicator and the proteins extracted in the presence of detergents (SDS), reducing agents (DTT), protease and phosphatase inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Preparative gels were loaded with 250 µg of tissue lysate proteins and separated by 2-DE, then stained with Colloidal Coomassie G-250 (cCCB) and the image acquired to generate a reference image of the total protein extract (2-DE-cCBB). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, analytical gels were prepared by loading 40 µg of proteins that were subsequently separated by 2-DE, transferred onto PVDF membrane followed by immuno-detection using anti-phosphorylated proteins specific monoclonal antibodies (WB-pAb). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>With a marker pen (rapidograph®, rotring, Germany) several dots were added on the PVDF membrane and used as landmarks for membrane images that were superimposed (see below) and the image was acquired. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Thereafter, the membrane was post-stained using cCCB, to visualize total proteins blotted, and a new image was acquired (WB-cCCB). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Using the dots as landmarks the WB-pAb and the WB-cCCB images were merged by the image analysis software as superimposed and matched by creating an image showing the phosphoproteins and the total proteins together (WB-Virtual). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Eventually, the 2-DE-CBB image was superimposed and matched to the WB-Virtual image using the CCB post-stained protein spot on the membrane as landmarks, to unravel phosphorylated proteins on the 2-DE-cCBB gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Protein spot landmarks were selected in such a way to be evenly distribution through the gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>This allowed the software algorithm to compensate local gel distortions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Protein spots on the 2-DE-cCBB gel showed the same electrophoretic mobility as the immunodetected proteins in the membrane were excised from the gel, subjected to in-gel tryptic digestion and identified by MALDI-TOF/TOF-MS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Each immunoblot was run in parallel with one or more 2-DE-cCBB gels, in order to be matched with. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>At the same time, the protein spots used as landmark for the matching process were also excised and identified on every different 2-DE-cCBB gel to confirm the accuracy of the matching procedure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Results and Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>De-novo phosphoproteomic analysis from limited sample material is challenging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>To demonstrate the utility of the developed method lung tissue of mice was analyzed and protein extracts were separated by 2-D PAGE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Representative 2-DE maps of tissue lysates and immunoblots are shown in Figure 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>On average 450±30 protein spots per gel were visualized by colloidal CCB staining (cCCB) at a pI range of 3–11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>The identified proteins and other relevant information are given in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>2-DE Phosphoprotein Analysis of Tissue Lysates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Successful research into protein phosphorylation requires both a selective separation and enrichment procedure and a reliable method for the detection, identification and characterization of phosphoproteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>When phosphorylated proteins are detected by antibodies, it is important to realise that each antibody (Ab) has its own unique properties regarding sensitivity and specificity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>In addition, factors such as background from contaminating proteins and nonspecific reactivity of the antibodies toward unrelated proteins could influence the performance as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>In the present study, the employed monoclonal antibodies (MAbs) were validated previously for their usefulness in the enrichment of phosphorylated proteins and were confirmed by MS identification, therefore demonstrating specificity and selectivity [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Table S2 informs on the properties and the combination of antibodies used for the search of pulmonary phosphoproteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Notably, the various MAb were produced with slightly different antigens, which might influence the specificity and binding behavior of the Ab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Alongside the immunoblotting of phosphoproteins their identification by MS and the subsequent submission of identified sequences to software predictor and database searches of already known literature information confirmed the reliability of the identified data as phoshorylated proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Consequently, detection of phosphoproteins with specific Ab and their identification by high performance MALDI-TOF-MS/MS was a simple and fast method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Moreover, to increase the sequence coverage and for comprehensive analysis, the trypsin digested protein spots were analyzed by two different sample preparations, i.e. the CHCA thin layer (TL) and DHB matrix layer (ML). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Then, MS/MS data were used to confirm identified proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Once identified, bioinformatics was used to predict the potential protein phosphorylation sites, and database searches provided information about the exact position of known phosphorylated sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>In addition to the immunoblotting of phosphoproteins, extracted proteins of lung tissue were also separated by one dimensional SDS-PAGE, and after in-gel digestion of individual bands phosphopeptides were enriched with self-made TiO2 micro column. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>The phosphorylation sites were then identified and characterized by MALDI-TOF-MS/MS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Detection and Identification of Phosphorylated Proteins with Anti-phosphoserine Antibodies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>For the detection of serine phosphorylated proteins, a set of 5 different anti-phosphoserines (pSset) and the MPM-2 MAbs were used (Supplementary Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>After development on PVDF membranes (Figure 2) with the pSset of monoclonal antibodies, the corresponding spots were excised from the 2-DE cCBB stained gel, in-gel digested with trypsin to overall yield 149 unique proteins (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>In Figure 3 an example of the specificity of the pSset of MAbs is given. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Three distinct spots detected in the WB with the pSset MAbs had two corresponding spots in the 2-DE-cCBB stained gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Importantly, with the CHCA TL sample matrix preparation the heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoproteins A2/B1 (O88569) was identified and confirmed by MS/MS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>However, when the digests of the same spots were analyzed by the DHB ML sample preparation Glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (P16858) was additionally identified and confirmed by MS/MS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Therefore, a careful comparison of the spot in the developed immunoblot of the 2-DE-cCBB gel and the visual inspection of regions in which the spots appeared needed to be confirmed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Likewise co-migrated and adjacent spots were examined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Specifically, the use of two different MALDI sample preparation methods and the acquisition of MS/MS spectra in an automated mode enabled reliable identification of phosphoproteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>The pSset of MAbs facilitated the MS identification of a large number of kinases including the SRC kinase (P05480), inhibitor of nuclear factor kappa-B kinase subunit beta (O88351), integrin-linked protein kinase (O55222) and serine-protein kinase ATM (Q62388) mitogen-activated protein kinase 3 (Q63844). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>For spots commonly identified by immunoblotting and by 2-DE MALDI MS/MS experiments were additionally performed (Table S1) With the MPM-2 MAb 43 unique proteins were detected by WB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Despite the overall reduced number of proteins detected with the this MAb unique proteins (n = 6) were identified and had not been detected by the pSmix Abs most likely as a result of differences in specificity of epitop recognition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>One of these proteins is the heat shock protein HSP 90-alpha (HS90A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>This chaperone is essential for proper protein folding, stabilization and trafficking of an expanding list of proteins, but appears to be critical for a variety of signal transduction pathways as well through an interaction with a wide range of transcription factors and protein kinases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Moreover, inhibition of HS90A activity is pursued for the treatment of various kinds of cancer including lung cancer [35], [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Of note, the use of the software Scansite predicted HS90A as a substrate for Fgr Kinase, Src Kinase, Lck Kinase, Akt Kinase, Casein Kinase 2 and the Erk D-domain and database search as with Phospho.ELM and PhosphoSitePlus confirmed the phosphorylation of serine, threonine and tyrosine in mouse and humans based on other experimental data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Detection and Identification of Phosphorylated Proteins with Anti-phosphotyrosine Antibodies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>For the detection of tyrosine phosphorylated proteins a set of 4 different monoclonal anti phosphotyrosine (pYset) and the 4G10 MAb were used (Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>With the pYmix MAbs (Figure 2) 54 unique proteins were detected and the corresponding spots on 2-DE-cCBB stained gels were excised. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Thereafter trypic digestes were prepared and analysed by MALDI-MS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>With the 4G10 MAb 40 phosphoproteins were detected, however 6 were unique when compared with the immunoblots obtained with the pYmix of MAbs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>(Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatic Analysis of Phosphoproteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Functional annotation of identified phosphoproteins was achieved by categorizing the proteins using GO terms. Figure 4A and B depicts a pie-chart distribution of the identified proteins catalogued according to the cellular component or molecular function (Supplementary Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Out of the 160 phosphoproteins identified their distribution was assigned to 21.2% into cytoplasm, 17.9% in the nucleus, 11.9% in the mitochondria, 16.6% in the cytoskeleton, 15.2% in the plasma membrane and 7.3% as extracellular. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Such a distribution of proteins provided further evidence of the versatile character of the developed assay in the search for novel phosphoproteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>The molecular functions of the annotated proteins are consistent with the activity of phosphoproteins in biological processes including protein binding (22.2%), nucleotide binding (15.7%), catalytic activity (9.8%), enzyme regulation (8.5%), enzyme binding (5.9%) and signal transduction (6.5%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Since lung served as a source of tissue material, it is not surprising that the functions of most identified phosphoproteins are related to respiratory biology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>The PhosphoSitePlus®, Phospho.ELM 9.0 and the UniProt database were used to search for the exact position of known phosphorylation sites based on the available literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, putative phosphorylation sites were searched with different software packages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>With Netphos 2.0, an output score of 0.5 was employed as cutoff to ensure that the obtained result is a bona fide phosphorylation site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Notably, for all of the 160 identified proteins several phosphorylation sites were predicted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Each phosphoprotein is further analyzed with Scansite 2.0 with high and medium stringency to predict the kinase and phosphorylation-dependent binding motifs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Potential binding sites for the Erk D-domain, PDK1 Binding, DNA PK, ATM kinase and casein kinase are most commonly predicted; casein kinase 1 and 2, PKC epsilon and zeta sites are also found frequently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Thus, out of 160 proteins analyzed 106 (66.2%) are already validated phosphoproteins based on the available literature, 26 proteins (16.2%) were predicted in mouse but validated as phosphoproteins either in humans or in rats, and 30 (18.8%) are only predicted to be phosphorylated but enharbour a kinase docking domain (Supplementary Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>In all, a total of 130 phosphoproteins (81.25%) are validated; this documents the usefulness of the developed assay. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Enrichment of Phosphoproteins by MOAC and de novo Identification of Phosphoryation Sites by MALDI-TOF-MS/MS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Several reports describe the use of titanium in metal oxide affinity chromatography (MOAC-TiO2) for the successful enrichment of phosphorylated peptides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>We found most of these protocols not useful for our sample preparation due to the elevated concentration of DHB in the elution solution and the increased backpressure obtained [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we developed a disposable micro-column (µ-MOAC-TiO2) in which inert glass microfiber was used as a frit and the composition of the elution solution was modified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>To further characterize the position of the phosphorylation site, trypsin digests of immunoreactive spots were enriched by µ-MOAC-TiO2 and subsequently applied to the pre-structured sample support for MS analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>The obtained MALDI-TOF-MS spectra were analyzed for the presence of phosphorylated peptide signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>None of the digested proteins gave acceptable signals of phosphorylated peptides (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Considering the low stoichiometry of phosphoporylation the total amount of peptides in the 2-DE spots digests was simply insufficient for an identification of phosphopeptides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Tissue extracted proteins were therefore separated by one-dimensional SDS-PAGE and enriched as follows: 50 µg of lung extracted proteins were loaded on SDS-PAGE; the lane was cut into 15 regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>The digested proteins from each region were enriched using µ-MOAC-TiO2 and analyzed by MALDI-TOF-MS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Each peptide signal presented in the MS spectrum was subjected to MS/MS fragmentation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>With this approach additional 17 proteins and 19 phosphorylated peptides were identified and characterized by MALDI-TOF-MS/MS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Specifically, 14 peptides contained a single pSer residue, 3 peptides contained two and 1 peptide contained three pSer residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Moreover, one protein with a single pSer residue also contained pThre residues as reported in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>The yielded spectra contained the characteristic neutral loss of ions at -98 and -80 from the molecular ion as result of β-elimination of H3PO4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>The high quality of spectra enabled detection of copious signal from the peptide back bone (y- and b- series) leading to an unambiguous characterization of the phosphorylation site(s), and in some cases the complete peptide sequence was observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>In addition, peptide ions of masses of&gt;2000 Da were detected to yield highly informative and structurally relevant fragment ions as shown in Figure 5A for the peptide R.TPEELDDSDFETEDFDVR.S of alpha-1 catenin (P26231). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>In Figure 5B the MALDI-TOF-MS/MS spectra of peptide m/z 1526.5210 that corresponds to the peptide R.KAPESQEDEEER.A of the advanced glycosylation end product-specific receptor protein (RAGE_MOUSE) is depicted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>The fragmentation pattern allowed not only an unambiguous identification of the peptide through the main fragmentation signal but the identification of the Ser 377 as the definitive phosphorylation site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Noteworthy, this protein is described as phosphorylated on threonine 271 but not as phosphorylated on serine (377) in mouse lung. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>While TiO2 has been widely used for the enrichment of phosphorylated peptides, none of the presented works demonstrated the feasibility of such enrichment for MALDI-MS for the specific characterization of phosphorylation sites in tissue extracts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Importantly, the copious neutral loss in MS/MS spectra shadows the signal of the backbone peptide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>With the CHCA TL sample preparation method a reduced number of phosphorylated peptides, copious matrix clusters, and increased fragmentation rendered data analysis impossible (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>However, the DHB ML sample preparation method delivered an improved homogeneity and increased backbone peptide fragments signal in MS/MS experiments when the matrix was doped with diammonium hydrogen phosphate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the ML sample preparation in combination with µ-MOAC-TiO2 enrichment allowed the successful fragmentation and characterization of novel phosphorylation sites. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>Taken collectively, the experimental strategy consisted of two approaches in the search of phosphoproteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>The first approach is based on immunoblots with anti-phosphorylated protein MAbs, while the second approach is based on enrichment of phosphopetides from tissue extracts with TiO2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>The immunoblot procedure does not always define all the possible residues subjected to posttranslational modifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 6, the phosphoserine specific MAbs pSset recognized aldehyde dehydrogenase (P47738) and selenium-binding protein 1 (P17563), but with the MAbs 4G10, MPM-2 and pYset only one of these proteins were detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>These two proteins are phosphorylated at different sites as reported elsewhere. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Thus, by use of several anti-phosphoprotein Abs with different specificity in the recognition of epitopes a more comprehensive characterization of phosphoproteins can be achieved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the identified proteins enharbour kinases binding motifs as suggested by various bioinformatic sequence analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Moreover, 66% of all the detected proteins have been reported to be phosphorylated at sites identified in the present study and appeared to be conserved in human, rat and mouse. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3f"><title><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>An antibody based rapid screening method for detection and de novo identification of phosphoproteins was developed and applied to lung tissue for an identification of pulmonary phosphoproteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>The facile use of MALDI-TOF-MS/MS for the characterization of phosphopeptides is therefore demonstrated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>The assay can readily be applied to any tissue in the search for phosphoproteins and to obtain information about on/off states with regard to protein phosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>In the same way it would be possible to study the effects of drug treatment with kinase inhibitors on the phosphoproteome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>The proposed assay provided the capability to qualify protein phosphorylation status on a systematic scale and therefore can be employed in biomedical research. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0050025.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Summary of sequence specific phosphoresidues of identified proteins and bioinformatic prediction of kinases involved. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>(XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0050025.s001.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0050025.s002"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Monoclonal antibodies and their properties. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>(DOC) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0050025.s002.doc"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0050025.s003"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>GO annotations of identified proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>(XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0050025.s003.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>We wish to thank Ines Voepel and Ute Sanger for the technical help and Dr. Maria Stella Ritorto for constructive discussions. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0050025-Manning1"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>1 ManningG, WhyteDB, MartinezR, HunterT, SudarsanamS (2002) The protein kinase complement of the human genome. Science 298: 1912–1934.12471243 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Olsen1"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>2 OlsenJV, BlagoevB, GnadF, MacekB, KumarC, et al (2006) Global, in vivo, and site-specific phosphorylation dynamics in signaling networks. Cell 127: 635–648.17081983 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Zhang1"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>3 ZhangX, JinQK, CarrSA, AnnanRS (2002) N-terminal peptide labeling strategy for incorporation of isotopic tags: A method for the determination of site-specific absolute phosphorylation stoichiometry. Rapid Commun Mass Spectrom 16: 2325–2332.12478578 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-BlumeJensen1"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>4 Blume-JensenP, HunterT (2001) Oncogenic kinase signalling. Nature 411: 355–365.11357143 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Zheng1"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>5 ZhengX, WangJ, HaerryTE, WuAY, MartinJ, et al (2003) TGF-beta signaling activates steroid hormone receptor expression during neuronal remodeling in the drosophila brain. Cell 112: 303–315.12581521 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Gazdar1"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>6 GazdarAF, ShigematsuH, HerzJ, MinnaJD (2004) Mutations and addiction to EGFR: The achilles ‘heal’ of lung cancers? Trends Mol Med 10: 481–486.15464447 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Lim1"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>7 LimYP (2005) Mining the tumor phosphoproteome for cancer markers. Clin Cancer Res 11: 3163–3169.15867208 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Leung1"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>8 LeungKY, WaitR, WelsonSY, YanJX, AbrahamDJ, et al (2001) A reference map of human lung MRC-5 fibroblast proteins using immobilized pH gradient-isoelectric focusing-based two-dimensional electrophoresis. Proteomics 1: 787–794.11677786 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Predic1"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>9 PredicJ, SoskicV, BradleyD, Godovac-ZimmermannJ (2002) Monitoring of gene expression by functional proteomics: Response of human lung fibroblast cells to stimulation by endothelin-1. Biochemistry 41: 1070–1078.11790131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Linthicum1"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>10 LinthicumDS (2001) Ultrastructural effects of silicic acid on primary lung fibroblasts in tissue culture. Tissue Cell 33: 514–523.11949787 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Ghafouri1"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>11 GhafouriB, StahlbomB, TagessonC, LindahlM (2002) Newly identified proteins in human nasal lavage fluid from non-smokers and smokers using two-dimensional gel electrophoresis and peptide mass fingerprinting. Proteomics 2: 112–120.11788998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-NoelGeoris1"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>12 Noel-GeorisI, BernardA, FalmagneP, WattiezR (2001) Proteomics as the tool to search for lung disease markers in bronchoalveolar lavage. Dis Markers 17: 271–284.11790894 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Stripp1"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>13 StrippBR, ReynoldsSD, BoeIM, LundJ, PowerJH, et al (2002) Clara cell secretory protein deficiency alters clara cell secretory apparatus and the protein composition of airway lining fluid. Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol 27: 170–178.12151308 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Gronborg1"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>14 GronborgM, KristiansenTZ, StensballeA, AndersenJS, OharaO, et al (2002) A mass spectrometry-based proteomic approach for identification of serine/threonine-phosphorylated proteins by enrichment with phospho-specific antibodies: Identification of a novel protein, frigg, as a protein kinase A substrate. Mol Cell Proteomics 1: 517–527.12239280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Rush1"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>15 RushJ, MoritzA, LeeKA, GuoA, GossVL, et al (2005) Immunoaffinity profiling of tyrosine phosphorylation in cancer cells. Nat Biotechnol 23: 94–101.15592455 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Davis1"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>16 DavisFM, TsaoTY, FowlerSK, RaoPN (1983) Monoclonal antibodies to mitotic cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 80: 2926–2930.6574461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Cohen1"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>17 CohenB, YoakimM, Piwnica-WormsH, RobertsTM, SchaffhausenBS (1990) Tyrosine phosphorylation is a signal for the trafficking of pp85, an 85-kDa phosphorylated polypeptide associated with phosphatidylinositol kinase activity. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 87: 4458–4462.1693771 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Oda1"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>18 OdaY, HuangK, CrossFR, CowburnD, ChaitBT (1999) Accurate quantitation of protein expression and site-specific phosphorylation. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 96: 6591–6596.10359756 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Delom1"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>19 DelomF, ChevetE (2006) Phosphoprotein analysis: From proteins to proteomes. Proteome Sci 4: 15.16854217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Larsen1"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>20 LarsenMR, ThingholmTE, JensenON, RoepstorffP, JorgensenTJ (2005) Highly selective enrichment of phosphorylated peptides from peptide mixtures using titanium dioxide microcolumns. Mol Cell Proteomics 4: 873–886.15858219 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Pinkse1"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>21 PinkseMW, UittoPM, HilhorstMJ, OomsB, HeckAJ (2004) Selective isolation at the femtomole level of phosphopeptides from proteolytic digests using 2D-NanoLC-ESI-MS/MS and titanium oxide precolumns. Anal Chem 76: 3935–3943.15253627 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Kristensen1"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>22 KristensenDB, KawadaN, ImamuraK, MiyamotoY, TatenoC, et al (2000) Proteome analysis of rat hepatic stellate cells. Hepatology 32: 268–277.10915733 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Yamagata1"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>23 YamagataA, KristensenDB, TakedaY, MiyamotoY, OkadaK, et al (2002) Mapping of phosphorylated proteins on two-dimensional polyacrylamide gels using protein phosphatase. Proteomics 2: 1267–1276.12362345 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Guy1"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>24 GuyGR, PhilipR, TanYH (1994) Analysis of cellular phosphoproteins by two-dimensional gel electrophoresis: Applications for cell signaling in normal and cancer cells. Electrophoresis 15: 417–440.8055870 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Ferrari1"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>25 FerrariG, GaragusoI, Adu-BobieJ, DoroF, TaddeiAR, et al (2006) Outer membrane vesicles from group B neisseria meningitidis delta gna33 mutant: Proteomic and immunological comparison with detergent-derived outer membrane vesicles. Proteomics 6: 1856–1866.16456881 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Jensen1"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>26 JensenON, WilmM, ShevchenkoA, MannM (1999) Sample preparation methods for mass spectrometric peptide mapping directly from 2-DE gels. Methods Mol Biol 112: 513–530.10027274 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Garaguso1"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>27 GaragusoI, BorlakJ (2008) Matrix layer sample preparation: An improved MALDI-MS peptide analysis method for proteomic studies. Proteomics 8: 2583–2595.18546159 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Perkins1"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>28 PerkinsDN, PappinDJ, CreasyDM, CottrellJS (1999) Probability-based protein identification by searching sequence databases using mass spectrometry data. Electrophoresis 20: 3551–3567.10612281 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Blom1"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>29 BlomN, GammeltoftS, BrunakS (1999) Sequence and structure-based prediction of eukaryotic protein phosphorylation sites. J Mol Biol 294: 1351–1362.10600390 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Hornbeck1"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>30 HornbeckPV, ChabraI, KornhauserJM, SkrzypekE, ZhangB (2004) PhosphoSite: A bioinformatics resource dedicated to physiological protein phosphorylation. Proteomics 4: 1551–1561.15174125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Diella1"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>31 DiellaF, CameronS, GemundC, LindingR, ViaA, et al (2004) Phospho.ELM: A database of experimentally verified phosphorylation sites in eukaryotic proteins. BMC Bioinformatics 5: 79.15212693 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Jain1"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>32 JainE, BairochA, DuvaudS, PhanI, RedaschiN, et al (2009) Infrastructure for the life sciences: Design and implementation of the UniProt website. BMC Bioinformatics 10: 136.19426475 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Obenauer1"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>33 ObenauerJC, CantleyLC, YaffeMB (2003) Scansite 2.0: Proteome-wide prediction of cell signaling interactions using short sequence motifs. Nucleic Acids Res 31: 3635–3641.12824383 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Wu1"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>34 WuCH, HuangH, ArminskiL, Castro-AlvearJ, ChenY, et al (2002) The protein information resource: An integrated public resource of functional annotation of proteins. Nucleic Acids Res 30: 35–37.11752247 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Shimamura1"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>35 ShimamuraT, ShapiroGI (2008) Heat shock protein 90 inhibition in lung cancer. J Thorac Oncol 3: S152–9.18520302 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0050025-Pratt1"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>36 PrattWB (1998) The hsp90-based chaperone system: Involvement in signal transduction from a variety of hormone and growth factor receptors. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 217: 420–434.9521088 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
