<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genomics Inf</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genomics Inf</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GNI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Genomics &amp; Informatics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1598-866X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2234-0742</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korea Genome Organization</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3480684</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5808/GI.2012.10.2.99</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Effect of Genetic Predisposition on Blood Lipid Traits Using Cumulative Risk Assessment in the Korean Population </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Go</surname><given-names>Min Jin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>Joo-Yeon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Dong-Joon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Hye-Ja</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>Han Byul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Kyung-Hee</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Jihyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Jong-Young</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Center for Genome Science, National Institute of Health, Osong Health Technology Administration Complex, Cheongwon 363-951, Korea.</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Division of Metabolic Diseases, Center for Biomedical Sciences, Korea National Institute of Health, Cheongwon 363-951, Korea.</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Family Medicine, Hallym University Sacred Heart Hospital, Hallym University College of Medicine, Anyang 431-796, Korea.</aff><author-notes><corresp>Corresponding author: Tel: +82-43-719-8870, Fax: +82-43-719-8908, <email>leejy63@nih.go.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>6</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>4</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 by The Korea Genome Organization</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0"><license-p>It is identical to the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Dyslipidemia, mainly characterized by high triglyceride (TG) and low high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C) levels, is an important etiological factor in the development of cardiovascular disease (CVD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Considering the relationship between childhood obesity and CVD risk, it would be worthwhile to evaluate whether previously identified lipid-related variants in adult subjects are associated with lipid variations in a childhood obesity study (n = 482). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>In an association analysis for 16 genome-wide association study (GWAS)-based candidate loci, we confirmed significant associations of a genetic predisposition to lipoprotein concentrations in a childhood obesity study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Having two loci (rs10503669 at LPL and rs16940212 at LIPC) that showed the strongest association with blood levels of TG and HDL-C, we calculated a genetic risk score (GRS), representing the sum of the risk alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>It has been observed that increasing GRS is significantly associated with decreased HDL-C (effect size, -1.13 ± 0.07) compared to single nucleotide polymorphism combinations without two risk variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>In addition, a positive correlation was observed between allelic dosage score and risk allele (rs10503669 at LPL) on high TG levels (effect size, 10.89 ± 0.84). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>These two loci yielded consistent associations in our previous meta-analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Taken together, our findings demonstrate that the genetic architecture of circulating lipid levels (TG and HDL-C) overlap to a large extent in childhood as well as in adulthood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Post-GWAS functional characterization of these variants is further required to elucidate their pathophysiological roles and biological mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>childhood obesity</kwd><kwd>dyslipidemias</kwd><kwd>genetic risk score</kwd><kwd>genome-wide association study</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Dyslipidemia is an important etiological factor in the development of cardiovascular disease (CVD), which is the leading cause of deaths for adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Dyslipidemia is mainly characterized by elevated levels of triglycerides (TGs), increased low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C), and reduced high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C) [1]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>In the past few years, genome-wide association studies (GWASs) and meta-analyses have identified common genetic variants that contribute to blood lipid phenotypes in Caucasian-based populations [2-8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>In addition, we have convincingly mapped 16 loci for major lipoprotein concentrations (TG, HDL-C, and LDL-C) in a two-stage association study in individuals of East Asian ancestry [9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Given the growing global epidemic of metabolic syndrome, including obesity and type 2 diabetes (T2D), lipoprotein metabolism disorders have become an important health problem in adulthood but also have emerged as an increasingly prevalent risk factor in childhood [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Although many GWASs and meta-analyses have provided susceptibility genes or loci for lipid-related traits from multiple large population-based cohorts of adults, it is of great importance to evaluate genetic predisposition at an early age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>However, little is known about their genetic effects in a younger population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Moreover, most identified variants have shown modest effects and have explained only a small proportion of heritable components for disease risk [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, when multiple genetic markers are considered together, literature-based genetic risk scores might be useful in improving the identification of the genetic contribution in those at high risk of disease [12-14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the aim of this study was to consolidate the associations of GWAS-based candidate variants with blood lipid concentrations in a childhood obesity study and to evaluate genetic risk scores (GRS) for lipid-related risk phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Study subjects </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Korean Association Resource (KARE) study was collected through the Korean Genome Epidemiologic Study project - in total, 10,038 people, 40-69 years old, living in Ansung and Ansan, from 2001-2002. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>For more information, the study has already been reported [9, 15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The Health Examinee cohort (HEXA) shared project is a community-based epidemiological cohort of 1,200,000 subjects (aged, 40-69) who were recruited for baseline examination from 2004 to 2009. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>To share the controls, 4,302 subjects were randomly selected to participate between 2006 and 2007. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The BioBank Japan study was approved by the ethical committees in the Institute of Medical Science, the University of Tokyo, and the Center for Genomic Medicine, RIKEN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Subjects for the Health2 cohorts for the replication study were selected from another community-based cohort sample provided by the Health2 study, as described previously [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>We examined 7,861 selected from the 8,500 participants (aged, 40-69). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The students aged 9 and 12 years were recruited from Gwacheon City and Gyeonggi Province between April and June 2010. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>This study was conducted as part of the Korean Children-Adolescents Study (KoCAS), which has been monitored yearly since their entry into elementary school at age 7 in Gwacheon City or fourth grade at age 10 in Seoul and Gyeonggi Province, Korea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Subjects who were enrolled in a specific diet program or were taking any medications known to affect appetite were excluded from the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The study protocol was approved by the institutional review board of Seoul-Paik Hospital, Inje University, and the Korea Center for Disease Control and Prevention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Informed consent was obtained from the children's parents. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Genotyping </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>KARE samples were genotyped using Affymetrix Genome-Wide Human SNP array 5.0 (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA, USA) and processed by Bayesian Robust Linear Modeling using the Mahalanobis Distance (BRLMM) genotyping algorithm [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The HEXA shared sample was genotyped using Affymetrix Genome-Wide Human SNP array 6.0 and processed with the Birdseed Genotyping Algorithm [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The BioBank Japan study was genotyped using the Illumina Human610-Quad BeadChip (Illumina Inc., San Diego, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>A childhood obesity study was genotyped using the Illumina Omni1-Quad BeadChip. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Individuals were excluded as follows: genotyping call rate, sex inconsistency, heterozygosity, identity-by-state value, and any kinds of tumor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>For more information, the study has been reported [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>For the replication study in Health2 (7,861), we performed a genotype assay using the TaqMan reaction for four single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) (rs2074356, rs16940212, rs12708980, rs599839) and the GoldenGate assay (Illumina Inc.) for nine SNPs (rs780092, rs10503669, rs2001945, rs603446, rs12686004, rs11216126, rs12229654, rs519113, rs12654264, rs2738446). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>To analyze the quality control, we conducted duplicate genotyping using 1-2.5% of samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>For further association analyses, concordance rates were satisfied with duplicates of over 99% and a genotype success rate of over 98%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>SNP imputation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>In each GWAS data point, imputation analysis was performed using the IMPUTE reference HapMap Asian (Japanese [JPT]/Han Chinese [CHB]) population panel, based on NCBI build 36 and dbSNP build 129. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Of these, in each cohort, we dropped SNPs with a posterior probability score &lt; 0.90, high genotype information content (info &lt; 0.5), Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) (p &lt; 1 × 10-7), SNP missing rate &gt; 0.1, and minor allele frequency (MAF) &lt; 0.01. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>In the former analysis, only imputed SNPs that satisfied the genomewide SNP quality control criteria were considered. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Association analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>In performing the association tests, SNPs were analyzed with PLINK (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pngu.mgh.harvard.edu/~purcell/plink/">http://pngu.mgh.harvard.edu/~purcell/plink/</ext-link>) and SAS version 9.1 (SAS institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Individuals who were on lipid-lowering therapy and hypertensive medications were excluded for dyslipidemia-related phenotypes, such as TG, HDL-C, and LDL-C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>LDL-C concentrations were calculated with Friedewald's formula [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Missing values were assigned for individuals with TG over 400 mg/dL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The dyslipidemia-related phenotypes were tested by multivariate linear regression analysis in an additive genetic model (1-d.f.), including age, sex, and recruitment area as covariates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>TG and HDL-C were transformed prior to analysis using natural log transformation to remove skewing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>LDL-C was normally distributed, and no transformations were required. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>A GRS was examined using multivariate linear regression analysis, adjusting for age, sex, and recruitment area. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The clinical characteristics and statistics of the variables for each study sample are described in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Our previous large-scale GWAS identified 9 novel and 24 known genetic loci influencing metabolic traits in East Asians [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>In an attempt to determine whether well-established lipid-related variants contribute to significant and reproducible genetic factors for susceptibility to blood lipid concentrations in a childhood obesity study, we first examined the associations between individual genetic variants and lipid-related phenotypes using linear regression analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Of these 16 SNPs for blood lipid traits, rs10503669 in LPL (genotyped SNP in a childhood obesity study) was significantly associated with TG and HDL-C, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>In addition, rs16940212 in LIPC (linkage disequilibrium-based proxy SNP) was associated with HDL-C (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The direction of these associations was consistent with our previous GWAS [9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Having two loci (rs10503669 at LPL and rs16940212 at LIPC) showing the strongest association with TG and HDL-C, we next investigated whether the cumulative allelic dosage of risk alleles contributes to the quantitative variation of lipoprotein concentrations in the KARE study using a method of calculating a GRS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>We evaluated the joint effects of the best-associated SNPs at the two loci showing evidence of association with HDL-C (rs10503669 at LPL and rs16940212 at LIPC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>We calculated a GRS, representing the sum of the risk alleles, and observed that increasing GRS was significantly associated with decreased HDL-C (effect size, -1.13 ± 0.07) compared to SNP combinations without two risk variants (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>In addition, a positive correlation was observed between allelic dosage score and risk allele (rs10503669 at LPL) for high TG levels (effect size, 10.89 ± 0.84) (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Blood lipid levels are an important etiological contributor to CVD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>CVD is the leading cause of death among individuals with T2D, in which lipid abnormalities are characterized by hypertriglyceridemia, reduced levels of HDL-C, and elevated levels of LDL-C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>These lipid-related traits, including ~14-54% for TG, ~34-42% for HDL-C, and ~28-50% for LDL-C, are highly heritable in familial T2D or diabetic patients [19, 20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>These estimates indicate that genetic variants play important roles in explaining inter-individual variations in blood lipid levels. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Although systematic reviews have reported relationships between childhood obesity and adult CVD risk [21, 22], there is not a shred of evidence that blood lipid status in adults is an independent or dependent risk factor in a childhood obesity group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Early childhood obesity might be the best time for dyslipidemia intervention, including screening, early detection, and management. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The aim of this study was to consolidate the associations of 16 GWAS-based candidate variants with blood lipid concentrations across the lifespan. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>In GWAS-based candidate approaches, the well-known LPL gene was significantly associated with low TG and high HDL-C levels in a childhood obesity study, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>This finding is well matched to the negative correlation between blood TG and HDL-C concentrations [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>In addition, the LIPC gene was further observed in decreased HDL-C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>In analyses of the joint effects of these variants, we found that GRSs on the two risk alleles (rs10503669 at LPL and rs16940212 at LIPC) were associated with a cumulative effect of TG and HDL-C levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>However, these facts indicate that currently identified risk variants might have low discriminatory ability and modest genetic contribution to disease prediction [24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Lipoprotein lipase (LPL) plays an important role in lipid metabolism by hydrolyzing TGs of circulating chylomicrons and very low-density lipoproteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>In addition, LPL is expressed in the brain regions that are functionally relevant to learning, memory, and other cognitive functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Many GWASs and meta-analyses have shown that variations in the well-known LPL gene for multiple lipid-related traits are implicated in multiethnic populations [2, 3, 9, 25-28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>An increasing number of studies have suggested an association of LPL gene variants with the risk of cerebrovascular as well as CVD [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Recent genome-wide investigations identified schizophrenia-associated loci in the chromosome 8p22 region, including LPL [30-32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>It was suggested that LPL is an attractive candidate gene that might be involved in the potential role of lipid metabolism in schizophrenia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Stages of early childhood development can be taken into account when considering a diagnosis of mental illness [33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Hepatic lipase (LIPC) gene encodes hepatic triglyceride lipase, which is expressed in liver. LIPC has a dual function as a triglyceride hydrolase and ligand/bridging factor for receptor-mediated lipoprotein uptake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>A GWAS has identified a possible role of LIPC in advanced age-related macular degeneration (AMD) [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>AMD is an eye condition affecting the central part of the retina. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Although a condition that is commonly associated with the elderly, macular degeneration affects younger people through a rare inherited condition [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Based on a lack of direct relationships between HDL-C and AMD risk, the LIPC association may not be the result of an effect on HDL-C levels, but it could represent a pleiotropic effect as a functional component, such as a lipoprotein transporter, underlying the biological mechanisms involving the cholesterol pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Taken together, our findings demonstrate that the genetic architecture of circulating lipid levels (TG and HDL-C) overlap to a large extent in childhood as well as in adulthood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>A genetic risk assessment by incorporating two risk alleles suggests encouraging evidence that identified genetic risk variants for lipid phenotypes have cumulative effects on lipid concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Post-GWAS functional characterization of these variants is further required to elucidate the pathophysiological role and biological mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by grants from the Korea Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (4845-301, 4851-302, 4851-307) and an intramural grant from the Korea National Institute of Health (2011-N73005-00). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>1MeagherEAAddressing cardiovascular disease in women: focus on dyslipidemiaJ Am Board Fam Pract20041742443715575034 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>2KristianssonKPerolaMTikkanenEKettunenJSurakkaIHavulinnaASGenome-wide screen for metabolic syndrome susceptibility Loci reveals strong lipid gene contribution but no evidence for common genetic basis for clustering of metabolic syndrome traitsCirc Cardiovasc Genet2012524224922399527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>3TanASunJXiaNQinXHuYZhangSA genome-wide association and gene-environment interaction study for serum triglycerides levels in a healthy Chinese male populationHum Mol Genet2012211658166422171074 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>4AulchenkoYSRipattiSLindqvistIBoomsmaDHeidIMPramstallerPPLoci influencing lipid levels and coronary heart disease risk in 16 European population cohortsNat Genet200941475519060911 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>5KathiresanSMelanderOGuiducciCSurtiABurttNPRiederMJSix new loci associated with blood low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol or triglycerides in humansNat Genet20084018919718193044 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>6KathiresanSWillerCJPelosoGMDemissieSMusunuruKSchadtEECommon variants at 30 loci contribute to polygenic dyslipidemiaNat Genet200941566519060906 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>7WillerCJSannaSJacksonAUScuteriABonnycastleLLClarkeRNewly identified loci that influence lipid concentrations and risk of coronary artery diseaseNat Genet20084016116918193043 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>8Diabetes Genetics Initiative of Broad Institute of Harvard and MIT, Lund University, and Novartis Institutes of BioMedical ResearchSaxenaRVoightBFLyssenkoVBurttNPde BakkerPIGenome-wide association analysis identifies loci for type 2 diabetes and triglyceride levelsScience20073161331133617463246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>9KimYJGoMJHuCHongCBKimYKLeeJYLarge-scale genome-wide association studies in East Asians identify new genetic loci influencing metabolic traitsNat Genet20114399099521909109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>10BradfieldJPTaalHRTimpsonNJScheragALecoeurCWarringtonNMA genome-wide association meta-analysis identifies new childhood obesity lociNat Genet20124452653122484627 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>11ZukOHechterESunyaevSRLanderESThe mystery of missing heritability: genetic interactions create phantom heritabilityProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20121091193119822223662 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>12LiuSSongYBuilding genetic scores to predict risk of complex diseases in humans: is it possible?Diabetes2010592729273120980472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>13QiLMaJQiQHartialaJAllayeeHCamposHGenetic risk score and risk of myocardial infarction in HispanicsCirculation201112337438021242481 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>14VaarhorstAALuYHeijmansBTDolléMEBöhringerSPutterHLiterature-based genetic risk scores for coronary heart disease: the Cardiovascular Registry Maastricht (CAREMA) prospective cohort studyCirc Cardiovasc Genet2012520220922373668 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>15ChoYSGoMJKimYJHeoJYOhJHBanHJA large-scale genome-wide association study of Asian populations uncovers genetic factors influencing eight quantitative traitsNat Genet20094152753419396169 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>16RabbeeNSpeedTPA genotype calling algorithm for affymetrix SNP arraysBioinformatics20062271216267090 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>17YeungJMShamPCChanASChernySSOpenADAM: an open source genome-wide association data management system for Affymetrix SNP arraysBMC Genomics2008963619117518 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>18JohnsonRMcNuttPMacMahonSRobsonRUse of the Friedewald formula to estimate LDL-cholesterol in patients with chronic renal failure on dialysisClin Chem199743218321849365406 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>19MalhotraAWolfordJKAmerican Diabetes Association GENNID Study GroupAnalysis of quantitative lipid traits in the genetics of NIDDM (GENNID) studyDiabetes2005543007301416186406 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>20ElbeinSCHasstedtSJQuantitative trait linkage analysis of lipid-related traits in familial type 2 diabetes: evidence for linkage of triglyceride levels to chromosome 19qDiabetes20025152853511812765 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>21LloydLJLangley-EvansSCMcMullenSChildhood obesity and adult cardiovascular disease risk: a systematic reviewInt J Obes (Lond)201034182819434067 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>22BeilinLHuangRCChildhood obesity, hypertension, the metabolic syndrome and adult cardiovascular diseaseClin Exp Pharmacol Physiol20083540941118307730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>23GawAHDL-C and triglyceride levels: relationship to coronary heart disease and treatment with statinsCardiovasc Drugs Ther200317536212843687 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>24CornelisMCQiLZhangCKraftPMansonJCaiTJoint effects of common genetic variants on the risk for type 2 diabetes in U.S. men and women of European ancestryAnn Intern Med200915054155019380854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>25FranceschiniNCartyCBůzkovaPReinerAPGarrettTLinYAssociation of genetic variants and incident coronary heart disease in multiethnic cohorts: the PAGE studyCirc Cardiovasc Genet2011466167222042884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>26SarzynskiMAJacobsonPRankinenTCarlssonBSjöströmLCarlssonLMAssociation of GWAS-based candidate genes with HDL-cholesterol levels before and after bariatric surgery in the Swedish obese subjects studyJ Clin Endocrinol Metab201196E953E95721430028 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>27LettreGPalmerCDYoungTEjebeKGAllayeeHBenjaminEJGenome-wide association study of coronary heart disease and its risk factors in 8,090 African Americans: the NHLBI CARe ProjectPLoS Genet20117e100130021347282 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>28WaterworthDMRickettsSLSongKChenLZhaoJHRipattiSGenetic variants influencing circulating lipid levels and risk of coronary artery diseaseArterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol2010302264227620864672 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>29MunshiABabuMSKaulSRajeshwarKBalakrishnaNJyothyAAssociation of LPL gene variant and LDL, HDL, VLDL cholesterol and triglyceride levels with ischemic stroke and its subtypesJ Neurol Sci2012318515422541364 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>30NeedACGeDWealeMEMaiaJFengSHeinzenELA genome-wide investigation of SNPs and CNVs in schizophreniaPLoS Genet20095e100037319197363 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>31MaXDengWLiuXLiMChenZHeZA genome-wide association study for quantitative traits in schizophrenia in ChinaGenes Brain Behav20111073473921679298 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>32LewisCMLevinsonDFWiseLHDeLisiLEStraubREHovattaIGenome scan meta-analysis of schizophrenia and bipolar disorder, part II: SchizophreniaAm J Hum Genet200373344812802786 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>33XieCWangZCLiuXFWangLYangMSAssociation between schizophrenia and single nucleotide polymorphisms in lipoprotein lipase gene in a Han Chinese populationPsychiatr Genet20112130731421862952 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>34NealeBMFagernessJReynoldsRSobrinLParkerMRaychaudhuriSGenome-wide association study of advanced age-related macular degeneration identifies a role of the hepatic lipase gene (LIPC)Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A20101077395740020385826 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>35HarkewiczRDuHTongZAlkurayaHBedellMSunWEssential role of ELOVL4 in very long chain fatty acid synthesis and retinal functionJ Biol Chem20111224[Epub]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M111.256073">http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M111.256073</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Combined effects of risk alleles on high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Allelic dosage scores are plotted on the X axis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The histogram (Y axis on left, grey bars) represents the percentage of individuals in each risk allele category. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The histogram (Y axis on right, black bars) represents mean HDL-C concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>(A) Eight single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) including the risk alleles (rs10503669 at LPL and rs16940212 at LIPC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>(B) Six SNPs without the risk alleles (rs10503669 at LPL and rs16940212 at LIPC). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gni-10-99-g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Combined effects of risk alleles on triglyceride (TG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Allelic dosage scores are plotted on the X axis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The histogram (Y axis on left, grey bars) represents the percentage of individuals in each risk allele category. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The histogram (Y axis on right, black bars) represents mean TG concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>(A) Five single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) including the risk allele (rs10503669 at LPL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>(B) Four SNPs without the risk allele (rs10503669 at LPL). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gni-10-99-g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Descriptive statistics of variables for each study cohort </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gni-10-99-i001"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>KARE, Korea Association Resource study; HEXA, Health Examinee cohort; BBJ, BioBank Japan study; TG, triglyceride; HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; LDL-C, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol.</p><p><sup>a</sup>LDL-C is calculated using the Friedewald's formula.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Association between SNPs and lipid-related traits in the population with discovery sets and replication study </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gni-10-99-i002"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>A bold indicates significant result.</p><p>SNP, single nucleotide polymorphism; CHR, chromosome; TG, triglyceride; HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; LDL-C, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol.</p><p><sup>a</sup>rsID, LD based SNP; <sup>b</sup>rsID, genetic distant based SNP.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
