<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Toxins (Basel)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Toxins (Basel)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">toxins</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Toxins</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2072-6651</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3509713</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins4111367</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">toxins-04-01367</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Short Toxin-like Proteins Abound in Cnidaria Genomes </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tirosh</surname><given-names>Yitshak</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-toxins-04-01367">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Linial</surname><given-names>Itai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-toxins-04-01367">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Askenazi</surname><given-names>Manor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-toxins-04-01367">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Linial</surname><given-names>Michal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-toxins-04-01367">1</xref><xref rid="c1-toxins-04-01367" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-toxins-04-01367"><label>1 </label>Department of Biological Chemistry, Silberman Institute of Life Sciences, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Jerusalem 91904, Israel; Email: <email>yitshak.tirosh@mail.huji.ac.il</email> (Y.T.); <email>manoras@cs.huji.ac.il</email> (M.A.)</aff><aff id="af2-toxins-04-01367"><label>2 </label>The Racah Institute of Physics, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Jerusalem 91904, Israel; Email: <email>itai.linial@mail.huji.ac.il</email></aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-toxins-04-01367"><label>*</label> Author to whom correspondence should be addressed; Email: <email>michall@cc.huji.ac.il</email>; Tel.: +972-2-658-5425; Fax: +972-2-658-6448.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1367</fpage><lpage>1384</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>9</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>08</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2012 by the authors; licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This article is an open-access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Cnidaria is a rich phylum that includes thousands of marine species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In this study, we focused on Anthozoa and Hydrozoa that are represented by the Nematostella vectensis (Sea anemone) and Hydra magnipapillata genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>We present a method for ranking the toxin-like candidates from complete proteomes of Cnidaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Toxin-like functions were revealed using ClanTox, a statistical machine-learning predictor trained on ion channel inhibitors from venomous animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Fundamental features that were emphasized in training ClanTox include cysteines and their spacing along the sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Among the 83,000 proteins derived from Cnidaria representatives, we found 170 candidates that fulfill the properties of toxin-like-proteins, the vast majority of which were previously unrecognized as toxins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>An additional 394 short proteins exhibit characteristics of toxin-like proteins at a moderate degree of confidence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, only 11% of the predicted toxin-like proteins were previously classified as toxins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Based on our prediction methodology and manual annotation, we inferred functions for over 400 of these proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Such functions include protease inhibitors, membrane pore formation, ion channel blockers and metal binding proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Many of the proteins belong to small families of paralogs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>We conclude that the evolutionary expansion of toxin-like proteins in Cnidaria contributes to their fitness in the complex environment of the aquatic ecosystem. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>hydra</kwd><kwd>nematostella</kwd><kwd>neurotoxin</kwd><kwd>protein families</kwd><kwd>disulfide bonds</kwd><kwd>antimicrobial peptide</kwd><kwd>ion channel inhibitor</kwd><kwd>ClanTox</kwd><kwd>complete proteome</kwd><kwd>comparative proteomics</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>To date, most multicellular model organisms that have been studied come from Bilateria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>A glimpse of our metazoan origin can nevertheless be seen from the recently sequenced genome of the choanoflagellate Monosiga brevicollis [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The genomic information from Porifera (sponges) has contributed to the reconstruction of the relative evolutionary position of Metazoa with respect to unicellular fungi [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>It is now clear that a more recent branch along the evolution of metazoa links the Cnidaria and the Bilateria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>This separation is dated to 650–750 million years ago [3,4,5] though, some inconsistency remains in the positioning of Cnidaria in the phylogenetic tree of the ctenophores, bilaterians and sponges [6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Cnidaria is a phylum including thousands of species that live in aquatic environments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>They include the following groups: (i) Anthozoa such as sea anemones, corals and sea pens; (ii) Scyphozoa such as the jellyfish; (iii) Cubozoa such as the box jellies, and (iv) Hydrozoa, such as the Hydra [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Cnidarians are distinguished from other phyla by their cnidocytes, which they use to capture prey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In most Cnidarians, a “nettle” has evolved for effective injection of venom into the prey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Such a device is found in jellyfish and cubozoans [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Cnidaria feed on a variety of organisms from plankton to large animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The survival success of Cnidarians over millions of years is linked to the evolution of their toxins, many of which have yet to be discovered. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The goal of this study is the identification of toxin and toxin-like proteins (collectively termed TOLIPs) in Cnidaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The two completed genomes that were included in this study are the Sea anemone Nematostella vectensis [9] from the Atlantic coasts and the Hydra magnipapillata. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The Sea anemone is a model for the underlying developmental program of the body plan [10] and the Hydra is the first sequenced representative of the Hydrozoa that includes the fire corals, siphonophores and hydrocorals [11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Animal toxins and other short proteins share a compact, cysteine rich scaffold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>An increasing number of proteins resembling animal-toxins have been identified in non-venomous contexts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>These proteins often act as natural cell modulators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>They include pore forming proteins, proteases, protease inhibitors, as well as secreted proteins that resemble cell antigens and growth factors [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Several predictors were developed for identifying toxin related proteins from animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>However, each such predictor focuses on only one type or property such as the conotoxins family [13], peptidases [14] or cysteine-rich proteins [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>A strong evolutionary relationship exists between animal toxins and ancestral cysteine cross-linked proteins [16,17,18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The most striking examples are proteins from rodents and humans that resemble snake α-neurotoxins and act as modulators in brain [19] and skin [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The exponential growth rate of raw protein sequence has driven the field to acknowledge the need for automated, robust functional inference on a genomic scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>However, routinely used genome annotation tools often overlook the weak signal of short proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, mass spectrometry (MS) methods only provide partial coverage of short proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The lack of transcriptomic evidence and the realization that many toxins (especially from marine animals) include non-classical post-translational modifications limit the knowledge of these short proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Consequently, EST collections, RNA-Seq and full-length cDNA remain the preferred source in seeking out novel short bioactive proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>We have developed a machine-learning based classifier called ClanTox (CLssifier of ANimal TOXins) for ranking protein sequences according to their toxin-like properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The short proteins that carry toxin activity and those that share toxin-like compact structures are collectively called TOLIPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>ClanTox creates a robust characterization of proteins that exhibit features of compact proteins, many of which resemble animal toxins [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>We have identified novel TOLIPs in the honeybee brain [21], in viruses and in rodents [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Recently, a TOLIP candidate expressed in the brain of the honeybee and other insects was validated as a non-coding brain specific expressed RNA [23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>We applied ClanTox to the entire available Cnidaria proteome and have identified hundreds of novel candidates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>We then prioritized the predicted TOLIPs in view of their key biological functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>We found 564 TOLIPs among the 17,000 short proteins from Nematostella and Hydra. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The top TOLIPS (159 and 30 candidates from Nematostella and Hydra, respectively) were carefully analyzed and we were able to infer functions for most of these proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>We conclude this analysis with a discussion of the evolutionary and functional insights achieved through the expansion of TOLIP genes in Cnidaria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The Cnidarian Short Proteome </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Currently, there are over 83,000 known proteins for the different branches of Cnidaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Most of these sequences originate from the recently completed proteomes from the genomes of the sea anemones Nematostella vectensis and Hydra magnipapillata. Figure 1 shows the number of proteins associated with Cnidaria and the branch of the sponges. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The latter are represented by Amphimedon queenslandica and will not be further discussed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Short proteins are under-represented in all organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>We have shown that a rather small number of functions populate this subset of the proteome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Notably, many of the short proteins archived in the main databases (e.g., UniProtKB [24] and NCBI Proteins) are incomplete. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>These databases also include fragmented sequences from incomplete mRNA sequence (i.e., sequences that lack initiating Methionines or stop codons). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Only a negligible percentage is attributable to processed peptides that carry a distinct biological function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The fraction of short proteins (&lt;150 amino acids) in all eukaryotes (total 6.3 million sequences) is close to 20%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>This ratio is consistent across all major branches of metazoa (e.g., Insects 19%; Echinodermata 18%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>However, the proportion of short proteins in Cnidaria is significantly higher (27.5%) even relative to Porifera (Sponges, 24%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The rest of the analysis will focus exclusively on this fraction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>There are two resources for the complete proteomes from Nematostella vectensis and Hydra magnipapillata that differ in their level of redundancy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The UniProtKB reports on a total of 33,000 proteins from Cnidaria among which 9050 are short. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The protein section from NCBI, on the other hand, appears to be a more complete (but somewhat redundant) resource. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>NCBI reports 82,400 Cnidarian sequences (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>There are 68,000 protein sequences originating from the two complete sequenced genomes of Nematostella and Hydra, 16,900 of which are short proteins (&lt;150 amino acids, 25%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>We combine these sources and focus exclusively on the short proteins (13,586 and 3314 from Nematostella and Hydra, respectively) to ensure a maximal discovery rate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="toxins-04-01367-f001" position="anchor"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic tree of the metazoa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The number of protein sequences for each branch is indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Data are retrieved from the NCBI taxonomy database. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="toxins-04-01367-g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="toxins-04-01367-f002" position="anchor"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Complete proteome annotations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The fraction of the proteins annotated as predicted, hypothetical or putative are shown for Apis mellifera, Hydra magnipapillata and Nematostella vectensis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="toxins-04-01367-g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Cnidarian Proteomes Are Partial and Poorly Annotated </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The annotations of protein sequences from Cnidaria (Namatostella and Hydra) lags by comparison to the model organisms curated by the NCBI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>This state of affairs is particularly extreme for the Nematostella genome where only 1.5% of the proteome has informative protein titles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The rest is indicated as “predicted” or “hypothetical” (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>For the Hydra proteome, about 50% of the sequences are associated with informative annotations and the rest are marked “predicted” or “hypothetical”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Proteomes that belong to the class of Cubozoa (sea wasps) and Scyphozoa (jellyfishes) are only partially sequenced, with less than 200 and 1000 known ORFs, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>By comparison, we present the annotation coverage of the Apis mellifera completed proteome. A. mellifera (honeybee), curation provides informative annotations for 75% of the proteome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>For other species (e.g., popular model organisms), the annotation assignment of the complete proteome is higher than 75% and may reach 98% (e.g., in the case of the human proteome). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Note that due to the difficulty in assigning function to short proteins, the fraction of annotated short proteins from Hydra and Nematostella is effectively negligible. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Discovery of Toxin-like Proteins (TOLIPs) in Hydra </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>While most Hydrae are non-toxic, a few species, such as the fire coral Millepora and the Portugese Man-O-War Physalia are highly venomous animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>A bioinformatics approach for detecting bioactive peptides with toxin-like activities was conducted [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, Hydra lacks classical ion channel blockers that are found in almost all venomous organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>However, some proteins act as Ryanodine receptor Ca2+ channel blockers [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Manual inspection reveals the complexity and richness of bioactive peptides in Hydra [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Among them are proteins that belong to the phospholipase family PLA2, pore forming sequences and non-classical ion channel blockers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="toxins-04-01367-f003" position="anchor"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Scheme of toxin-like proteins (TOLIPs) discovery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The three major steps in TOLIPs discovery and functional inference are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The schematic representation of the histogram of the ClanTox prediction for short proteins is shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The high confidence predictions are indicated as P2 and P3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="toxins-04-01367-g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Figure 3 illustrates the schematic steps in the discovery of Cnidarian TOLIPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The steps include the input set of short sequences, the training protocol for ClanTox, the prediction results and the semi-manual functional inference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>We demonstrate the entire protocol for the Hydra short proteome whose annotation coverage is superior relative to the Nematostella proteome (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>ClanTox tends to identify proteins containing multiple cysteines distributed along the entire sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Multiple cysteines and their spacing are the hallmark of many animal secreted ion channel inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Activating ClanTox on the 17,580 proteins from the Hydra proteome revealed 110 sequences that are positively predicted to be toxin-like (marked P1–P3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Figure 4 lists the inferred functions for the 30 highest confidence sequences (P3 and P2, Figure 3) from Hydra. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>We note that four of the proteins are composed of tandem repeats (TRs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>For such cases, ClanTox wrongly predicts these proteins as TOLIPs (Figure 3, stars). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>A protein that has even one (or more) cysteine in its repeated unit is prone to being mistakenly characterized as TOLIP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>For the rest of the Hydra TOLIPs, evidence of their function can be exposed based on a homology search for domains and structural resemblance (Figure 4, arrowheads). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="toxins-04-01367-f004" position="anchor"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Functional inference for the predictions of TOLIPs from Hydra. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>TOLIPs that are listed are predicted as P2 and P3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Tandem Repeat (TR) proteins are marked by a star. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>All other functions are marked by colored arrowheads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>XP_002156558.1 carries two functional domains. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="toxins-04-01367-g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Figure 4 summarizes the 10 major functions associated with high-confidence predictions from Hydra. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>These functions include antimicrobial peptides, metal binding, protease inhibitors and domains that participate in protein interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Of special interest are TOLIPs that act in the Wnt signaling pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Reports on Wnt pathway in Cnidaria are in accord with our previously reported finding [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Ultimately, for about 2/3 of the predicted TOLIPs, some function can be inferred (based on Hidden Markov Models comparisons, see Experimental Section). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, for a subset of these findings, a mode of action for the toxic effect of the protein can be envisioned. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>A salient example in our findings is the identification as TOLIPs of short proteins (XP_002166541.1 and XP_002161753.1) that structurally resemble the porcine spasmolytic proteins (pSP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The latter appears in extracellular eukaryotic proteins that are stabilized by three disulphide bonds to form a trefoil motif [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Possibly, the Hydra pSP-like proteins comprise unknown receptor binding or a growth factor-like domain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Expansion of Cell Modulatory Functions among TOLIPs from Hydra </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Most of the Hydra TOLIPs can be considered secreted with extracellular functions (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>For example, XP_002156558.1 (135 amino acids) is a secretory protein with two regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The N-terminus resembles the single insulin-like growth factor binding domain protein (SIBD-1) and the C-terminus resembles a Protease inhibitor of the Kunitz superfamily. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>An architecture that is based on this combination of domains is found in additional toxins such as the β-bungarotoxin [29]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Beta-bungarotoxin is a heterodimeric neurotoxin consisting of a phospholipase subunit linked by a disulfide bond to a K+ channel binding subunit (belonging to the Kunitz protease inhibitor superfamily). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Thus, toxicity is achieved by a phospholipase that is targeted to the presynaptic membrane by way of a paired Kunitz module [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>In the case of the Hydra, we anticipate a mode in which the Kunitz protease inhibitor domain presents the SIBD-1 to produce an effective binding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Among the 3D-solved structures (from the PDB), The Hydra Kunitz domain is similar to that of several potent toxins: β-bungarotoxin (PDB: 1BUN_B), Huwentoxin-11 (PDB: 2JOT_A), Anntoxin from the tree frog Hyla annectans (PDB: 2KCR_A), the snake venom of the Bungarus fasciatus (PDB: 1JC6_A) and the green Mamba Dendroaspis angusticeps (PDB: 1DTK_A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>We now focus on a predicted TOLIP that represents a short, secreted protein with a modulatory function. Figure 5A compares a statistical model (HMM, Hidden Markov Model) that was based on the sequence XP_002164320.1 (105 amino acids) with a library of HMM models from all 3D solved structures that are archived in the PDB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The resulting model was based on PDB accession 3ZXC from the Central America hunting spider Cupiennius salei. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>This sequence is a single insulin-like growth factor binding domain protein (SIBD-1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>SIBD-1 was proposed to act in the spider’s immune system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>This domain appears in 10 additional remote paralogs (the closest paralog XP_002156854.1 was scored by ClanTox at a moderate P1 confidence level). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>An expansion of TOLIP genes is a general trend among the Hydra. Figure 5B shows such instance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>All paralogs of XP_002154511.1 maintain the cysteine positions (Figure 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>While the Signal peptide segment (green font) is less conserved, the 10 cysteines in addition to a number of charged amino acids are fully conserved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>It is likely that these conserved amino acids participate in the folding or binding properties of these proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Modulation of adhesion through the activation of the integrin signaling pathways was identified among the proposed TOLIPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>XP_002157505.1 (and five additional paralogs) resembles the vascular apoptosis-inducing protein (VAP) from Crotalus atrox venom (Western diamond back rattlesnake). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The similarity covers the disintegrin domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Disintegrin is a short metalloproteinase domain that appears in viper venoms and functions as potent inhibitors of platelet aggregation and integrin-dependent cell adhesion [31]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="toxins-04-01367-f005" position="anchor"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Cell modulators from Hydra. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>(A) The sequence XP_002164320.1 is shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The segments of the sequence that were excluded from the HHPred comparative models are colored gray. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>HHPred representation of SIBD domain from Hydra and a structural homologue PDB: 3ZXC_A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The domain of 3ZXC includes a Single Insulin-like Growth Factor-Binding Domain Protein (SIBD-1) from the Central American Hunting Spider Cupiennius salei; (B) Set of secreted proteins and their paralogs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The function of these proteins is unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>However, the spacing and the number of cysteines along the sequences are conserved (marked red). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="toxins-04-01367-g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>2.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The Number of Tolips Is Exceptionally High among Short Proteins from Nematostella </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Table 1 summarizes the prediction results from ClanTox for Nematostella and Hydra proteomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>We divided the results according to the significance of the predictions: P3 (Very High), P2 (High) and P1 (Moderate). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>We also indicated the number of negatives predictions (N). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>It is evident that the fraction of positively identified TOLIPs in Nematostella is exceptionally high (4 fold higher relative to the Hydra). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>As expected, the fraction of TOLIPs among the proteins that are shorter than 100 amino acids is very high (17% for P1–P3), the fraction of TOLIPs is somewhat smaller (11%) for proteins of length 101–150. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>However, in both cases, the fraction appears significantly larger than the equivalent Hydra. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Hydra’s TOLIPs occupy 3.1% and 3.4% of the proteins for length &lt;100 and 101–150 amino acids, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>We therefore investigated the origin of TOLIPs’ expansion in the sea anemone proteome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="toxins-04-01367-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">toxins-04-01367-t001_Table 1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Results of ClanTox predictions on short proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr align="center"><th valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Species </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Range (aa) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>P3 (Very high) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>P2 (High) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>P1 (Moderate) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>% P2–P3 predictions </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Negative predictions </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Total </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr align="center"><td rowspan="3" valign="middle" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>N. vectensis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>10–100 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>133 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>253 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>657 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>6.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>5083 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>6126 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>101–150 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>26 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>122 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>704 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>1.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>6608 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>7460 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>10–150 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>159 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>375 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>1361 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>3.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>11691 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>13586 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td rowspan="3" valign="middle" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>H. magnipapillata </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>10–100 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>19 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>1.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>1038 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>1073 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>101–150 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>61 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>0.6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>2164 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>2241 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>10–150 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>19 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>80 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>0.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>3202 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>3314 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>2.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>False Detection of TOLIPs Is Associated with Tandem Repeats Sequences </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>It has been noted that the Nematosella proteome is enriched in tandem repeats (TRs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The properties of TRs have been thoroughly studied [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>We found that the fraction of TRs among the most highly significant TOLIPs (P3, see Experimental Section) reaches 25% of the sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>It is substantially higher than the fraction of TR appearance in the overall proteome (16%). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="toxins-04-01367-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">toxins-04-01367-t002_Table 2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Tandem Repeats (TR) proteins among the top predictions from Nematostella. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Each repeat was identified in two proteins (total 40 proteins) due to redundancy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr align="center"><th valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Consensus error </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Copy number </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Period </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Repeat </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>0.02 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>3.03 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>38 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>0.11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>2.09 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>35 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>0.12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>29 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>0.03 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>3.05 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>0.07 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>5.26 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>19 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>0.08 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>2.17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>0.04 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>4.58 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>0.03 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>5.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>0.04 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>9.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>0.04 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>7.78 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>0.06 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>8.75 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>0.18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>5.38 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>0.07 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>13.25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>14 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>0.03 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>8.71 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>0.06 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>15.71 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>16 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>0.08 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>9.14 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>0.07 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>8.71 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>0.04 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>11.17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>19 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr align="center"><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>0.07 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>7.67 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>The properties of the repeats, the repeated unit length and the copy number of the periodicity are summarized in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>There are 20 types of TR units in 40 of the top 159 TOLIP predictions (Very high, P3, Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>We anticipate that these 40 TR proteins are false positives and do not play a role as Toxins or Toxin-like proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>The TR proteome is prone to false identification of TOLIPs due to the pattern of repeats that include at least one cysteine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Importantly, the length of the repeated segment (i.e., Number of TR units × Unit length) occupies most of the protein length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Many of the TR proteins lack an initiator Methionine and constitute of partial sequences with no evidence for their expression (see discussion in [32]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>2.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Functional Assignment of Most TOLIPs from Nematostella </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Among the 119 predicted TOLIPs from Nematostella (Table 1, excluding TR proteins), 19 were already annotated as Neurotoxins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>For the 100 remaining proteins, no annotations are available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>These proteins are named predicted/hypothetical proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>To assign function to these 100 proteins, we first removed the most obviously redundant proteins (i.e., 100% identity in amino acids, identical length). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>This step led to 80 non-redundant proteins (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Among them 20 were TR proteins (Table 2) and 12 were named Neurotoxins (Figure 6, marked yellow). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Each sequence was tested for its most likely 3D structure using the HHpred algorithm (see Experimental Section). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>From this analysis we were able to annotate an additional 8 TOLIPs based on similarities to neurotoxin structural models (Figure 6, marked blue; 22 redundant proteins). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>These proteins can be partitioned into two main classes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>The major group (5 proteins, 14 redundant proteins) shares a strong similarity to the Navs fold [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>The Nav polypeptides (e.g., Nv1, N. vectensis toxin 1) inhibit the inactivation of voltage-gated sodium channels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>These proteins occupy an expanded chromosomal region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Notably, changes in the expression and maturation of Nv1 transcripts are known to occur throughout the development and the life cycle of the sea anemone [33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>The other class of predicted neurotoxins is longer (range from 105–125 amino acids) with homologues from a wide array of venoms that block K+ channels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>An example is EDO49171.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>The closest homologue of EDO49171.1 is the human EDO45628.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>The shared segment matches the MMP23 (matrix metalloproteinase 23) that is evolutionarily related to the Sea anemones peptides ShK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>The ShK is a short peptide (35 amino acids) stabilized by three disulfide bridges. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>There are three such sequences that form a paralogous group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Additional functions that dominated the Nematostella’s TOLIPs belong to ligand-cell surface modulators (including Adhesion, Wnt signaling) and the Kunitz protease inhibitors (Figure 6, marked brown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>These functions are shared with the Hydra TOLIPS (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>TOLIPs that resemble adhesion domains may participate in cell-cell interaction networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Many adhesion proteins are composed of a series of EGF-like domains that also bind calcium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>For example, the protein EDO26015.1 share this domain that is found in several calcium-binding cell adhesion regulators (modeled on PDB: 2Bo2_A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Cell interaction by calcium regulation is an attractive extension of TOLIP functionality that calls for further investigation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>In a few cases we identified TOLIPs as fragments that eventually belong to long proteins (Figure 6, F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Such cases are propagated from a failure in the genome annotation phase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>From the 80 non-redundant high confidence TOLIPs, only 3% resisted functional characterization. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="toxins-04-01367-f006" position="anchor"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>High confidence predictions from Nematostella. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>A list of 80 TOLIPs that were predicted by ClanTox as P3 are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Major functions are indicated by the colored bar next to the Cysteine pattern scheme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Neurotoxins (NTx, marked yellow) include proteins that were previously annotated as such. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Predicted overlooked neurotoxins are marked blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>The other functions are colored as detailed: Gray, Tandem repeats (TR) proteins; Orange, Extracellular regulation and ligand binding; Brown, Protease inhibitors, mainly represented by the Kunitz domain; Green, homologue to specialized domains from Pfam; Light blue, Calciun modulating domains of adhesion and EGF like; M, metaloprotein; Proteins with exceptionally high number of paralogs are assigned by their number; F marks a fragment that apparently belongs to a long protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>These sequences reflect mistakes in the database assignments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>The redundant list includes 159 sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Most proteins appear in Refseq and GeneBank and thus appear redundant by the NCBI protein database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Only the non-redundant set is shown. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="toxins-04-01367-g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>The proteomes of Hydra and Nematostella are representatives of the Anthozoa and Hydrozoa that have diverged &gt;540 million year ago [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>These two genomes differ in their genome sizes, the GC nucleotide content, the number of transposomal elements among other features. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>We found that the spectrum of functions which were predicted for TOLIPs in Hydra and Nematostella proteomes overlap (compare Figure 4 and Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the basis for the drastic difference in the number of toxin-like candidate in each of these genomes (Table 1) is not evident. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>We show that 25% of the Nematostella TOLIPs are actually tandem repeat (TR) proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>We postulate that in addition to the organism’s unique proteome, a permissive gene annotation contributes to wrongly identified sequences as TOLIP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Lack of Knowledge Regarding the Cnidaria Secretome </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>It is expected that toxins (and TOLIPs) have a Signal peptide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>However, the Cnidaria genomes are mostly un-annotated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Thus, only 11 proteins were indicated as containing a Signal peptide (SwissProt based annotation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Among the analyzed Nematostella’s predictions (P3, excluding TR proteins), we identified 34% as having a Signal peptide using SignalP 4.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Recall that Signal peptide information was not included in the training of ClanTox. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>We attribute such relatively low fraction to the missing segments at the N-terminal of the proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Actually, only 32% of the analyzed short proteins from Nematostella contain an initiator Methionine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>It is expected that transcriptomic data will be needed to improve the completeness of the Cnidaria sequences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Most Nematostella proteins (98.5%) are unannotated (Figure 2), thus the functions of their predicted TOLIPs remain elusive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Sequence search of the predicted TOLIPs highlights homologues among marine metagenomics sequences with unknown origin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>For example, sequence XP_001624064.1 (130 amino acids, P3), resembles several uncharacterized sequences from metagenomic experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>The potential for active genetic material exchange through viruses and pathogen of Cnidaria cannot be excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>A genetic exchange from viruses to their metazoan hosts was demonstrated among short proteins [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>However, for a number of sequences the apparent relatedness to metagenomic sequences is clearly spurious (e.g., EDO31964.1, 130 amino acids). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>The Cnidaria TOLIPs—A Source for New Drugs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>We propose that the top Toxin-like protein predictions may lead to an expansion of known toxins, toxin-like and antibacterial proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>Further analysis of homologs and paralogs presented in this study will lead to the identification of amino acids critical to binding and specificity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Such analysis is beyond the scope of this research. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>The therapeutic potential of TOLIPs has led to the development of toxin-based drugs [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Some small peptides from the conotoxin family are already in clinical use for managing chronic pain [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Some toxins from Nematostella act by forming pores in the targeted membranes [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>From the mesoglea of a scyphoid jellyfish (Aurelia aurita) a novel antimicrobial peptide was biochemically identified with weak similarity to ion channel blockers or defensins [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the Defensin-fold carries an antimicrobial activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>As such, Defensins were proposed as attractive vaccines and as potential drugs [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>A Defensin-like fold is missing in Cnidaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Most likely, the expansion of Defensins occurred in recently evolved phylogenetic branches prior to the speciation of Chordata. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>Evolution Dynamics—Expansion and Deletion of TOLIP Sequences </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>Representative genomes from Porifera (sponges) have provided molecular explanation for the increase in gene number due to a burst of gene duplication events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>This process gave rise to the evolution of new domains (i.e., adhesion molecules, lectin, proteases) [2] in Cnidaria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Our results support local expansion events of genes encoding for short proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>The ability of a duplication burst to increase functional diversity was illustrated in yeast [40] and humans [41]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>The analysis of neurotoxin (Nav1) evolution exposed extensive genomic expansion of this region [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Gene expansion has shaped many domain families mainly for the immune system, signaling (e.g., leucine-rich repeats) and adhesion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Several venom components evolved via convergent evolution [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Our study confirms that the phenomenon of genetic expansion and convergent evolution is not limited to vertebrates (e.g., reptiles, platypus) [44] but already dominates in the Cnidaria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>Experimental Section </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>4.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Data Collection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Protein sequences from Cnidaria were collected from UniProtKB [24] and sequences marked as “fragments” were excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>UniProtKB was used as an annotation source for “Signal peptide” and “cell localization”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Only 1% of the Cnidaria proteins are curated and represented in the SwissProt collection (391/32,934 proteins). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>The proteome of Nematostella vectensis (Starlet sea anemone) includes 24,435 proteins in UniProtKB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>The original data set was extracted from the N. vectensis JGI complete genome 1.0 (2007) [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>In the case of Nematostella proteome, protein redundancy originates from accessions obtained from RefSeq and GeneBank databases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Analysis was performed on protein shorter than 150 amino acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>The FASTA file from the NCBI protein collection [46] was used as input for ClanTox prediction [47]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>4.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatics Analysis Tools </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>SignalP 4.0 was applied for prediction of signal peptides [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>ClustalW and alignment viewer tools were used from EBI’s (ClustalW2) server and the NCBI (Cobalt multiple sequence alignment). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Multiple sequence alignment was applied using the default parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>HHpred was used to identify remote homologues [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>HHpred is a sensitive algorithm that is based on HMM-HMM-comparisons for proposing the most likely structure of domain family assignments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>We applied HHpred to build an HMM from the query sequence and compared it with a library of HMMs representing all known 3D-structures from the PDB. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>4.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>ClanTox Scoring </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>The typical performance of ClanTox as assessed by cross-validation testing is exceptionally high with a Receiver operating characteristic (ROC curve) and mean area under the curve (AUC) of &gt;0.99% accuracy (for details see [22]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>The classifier returns one of four labels: N for negative predictions and P1–P3, reflecting three levels of positive predictions for TOLIPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>The most significant set of predictions is labeled P3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>The labeling P1 to P3 reflects the mean score (the higher the score, the higher is the prediction confidence), and the robustness of the score [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>The robustness is calculated from 10 independent runs of the predictor on different negative sets and calculating the standard deviation (SD) of the prediction results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>P3 comprises proteins with a mean score &gt; 0.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>The negative predictions (i.e., predicted as non-toxin) result from proteins with a mean score &lt; −0.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>We separate the confidence of positive predictions to 3 levels: P3 are predictions with a mean score &gt; 0.2 or mean score &gt; 2 * SD; P2 are predictions with a mean score &gt; 0.2 or mean score between SD and 2 * SD; P1 are predictions with a mean score &gt; −0.2 or mean score &lt; SD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>ClanTox is accessible as an interactive web server [50]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>4.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Discovery of Tandem Repeats (TRs) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>The presence of tandem repeats (TRs) in proteins and transcripts was determined using the Xstream web tool [51] with the following parameters: (i) TRs are &gt;70% identical in their sequence; (ii) The minimal length of the repeated unit is 3 amino acids; (iii) The minimal domain length (defined as the total length of the repeated units) is 10 amino acids; (iv) The repeated unit appears at least twice; (v) Each repeat unit shares &gt;80% identity to the consensus sequence; (vi) There are at most three gaps in the repeats. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>We present here a systematic analysis for predicting Cnidarian toxin-like proteins (TOLIPs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>We showed that even with poorly annotated genomes, identifying new TOLIPs candidates and inference of their possible functions is feasible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>Over 95% of TOLIP candidates can be confidently annotated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>For many of these predictions, experimental evidence is still lacking. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>From a functional perspective, we identified candidates that are predicted to function as protease inhibitors, components of a membrane pore, ion channel blockers, metal binding proteins and signaling molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>Importantly, many of the short compact neurotoxin folds exhibit similarity to adhesion domains (signaling and extracellular modulators). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>We postulate that the basic elements of adhesion in Cnidaria resemble toxin-like proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Lastly, the TOLIPs in Cnidaria belong to small families of paralogs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>The identified TOLIPs from Nematostella and Hydra genomes exposed an abundance of genes that code for short templates of venom molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, cysteine-rich templates account for a rich spectrum of related functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>Gene expansion dynamics is fundamental to increase the repertoire of functions with a broad range of specificity and potency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>We conclude that the reported evolutionary expansion of toxin-like proteins contribute to the fitness in the complex environment of the aquatic ecosystem. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>This study is supported by grants from the ISF 592/07 and the BSF 2007/219. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>N.R. and M.A. are student fellows of the SCCB, the Sudarsky Center of Computational Biology. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><notes><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>1. KingN.WestbrookM.J.YoungS.L.KuoA.AbedinM.ChapmanJ.FaircloughS.HellstenU.IsogaiY.LetunicI. The genome of the choanoflagellate Monosiga brevicollis and the origin of metazoans Nature 2008 451 783 788 18273011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>2. MullerW.E.SchroderH.C.SkorokhodA.BunzC.MullerI.M.GrebenjukV.A. Contribution of sponge genes to unravel the genome of the hypothetical ancestor of Metazoa (Urmetazoa) Gene 2001 276 161 173 10.1016/S0378-1119(01)00669-2 11591483 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>3. HemmrichG.AnokhinB.ZachariasH.BoschT.C. Molecular phylogenetics in Hydra, a classical model in evolutionary developmental biology Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>Phylogenet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>Evol. 2007 44 281 290 10.1016/j.ympev.2006.10.031 17174108 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>4. PhilippeH.DerelleR.LopezP.PickK.BorchielliniC.Boury-EsnaultN.VaceletJ.RenardE.HoulistonE.QuéinnecE. Phylogenomics revives traditional views on deep animal relationships Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2009 19 706 712 10.1016/j.cub.2009.02.052 19345102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>5. BridgeD.CunninghamC.W.DeSalleR.BussL.W. Class-level relationships in the phylum Cnidaria: Molecular and morphological evidence Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>Evol. 1995 12 679 689 7659022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>6. SeipelK.SchmidV. Evolution of striated muscle: Jellyfish and the origin of triploblasty Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2005 282 14 26 10.1016/j.ydbio.2005.03.032 15936326 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>7. EvansN.M.LindnerA.RaikovaE.V.CollinsA.G.CartwrightP. Phylogenetic placement of the enigmatic parasite, Polypodium hydriforme, within the Phylum Cnidaria BMC Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2008 8 139 18471296 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>8. CartwrightP.NawrockiA.M. Character evolution in Hydrozoa (phylum Cnidaria) Integr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>Comp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2011 50 456 472 10.1093/icb/icq089 21558215 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>9. PutnamN.H.SrivastavaM.HellstenU.DirksB.ChapmanJ.SalamovA.TerryA.ShapiroH.LindquistE.KapitonovV.V. Sea anemone genome reveals ancestral eumetazoan gene repertoire and genomic organization Science 2007 317 86 94 10.1126/science.1139158 17615350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>10. MartindaleM.Q.FinnertyJ.R.HenryJ.Q. The Radiata and the evolutionary origins of the bilaterian body plan Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>Phylogenet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>Evol. 2002 24 358 365 10.1016/S1055-7903(02)00208-7 12220977 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>11. ChapmanJ.A.KirknessE.F.SimakovO.HampsonS.E.MitrosT.WeinmaierT.RatteiT.BalasubramanianP.G.BormanJ.BusamD. The dynamic genome of Hydra Nature 2010 464 592 596 10.1038/nature08830 20228792 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>12. WhittingtonC.M.PapenfussA.T.BansalP.TorresA.M.WongE.S.DeakinJ.E.GravesT.AlsopA.SchatzkamerK.KremitzkiC. Defensins and the convergent evolution of platypus and reptile venom genes Genome Res. 2008 18 986 994 10.1101/gr.7149808 18463304 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>13. KouaD.BrauerA.LahtS.KaplinskiL.FavreauP.RemmM.LisacekF.StocklinR. ConoDictor: A tool for prediction of conopeptide superfamilies Nucleic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>Acids Res. 2012 40 W238 W241 10.1093/nar/gks337 22661581 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>14. XuX.YuD.FangW.ChengY.QianZ.LuW.CaiY.FengK. Prediction of peptidase category based on functional domain composition J. Proteome Res. 2008 7 4521 4524 10.1021/pr800292w 18763822 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>15. LenfferJ.LaiP.el MejaberW.KhanA.M.KohJ.L.TanP.T.SeahS.H.BrusicV. CysView: Protein classification based on cysteine pairing patterns Nucleic Acids Res. 2004 32 W350 W355 10.1093/nar/gkh475 15215409 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>16. FryB.G. From genome to “venome”: Molecular origin and evolution of the snake venom proteome inferred from phylogenetic analysis of toxin sequences and related body proteins Genome Res. 2005 15 403 420 10.1101/gr.3228405 15741511 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>17. FryB.G.VidalN.NormanJ.A.VonkF.J.ScheibH.RamjanS.F.R.KuruppuS.FungK.HedgesS.B.RichardsonM.K. Early evolution of the venom system in lizards and snakes Nature 2006 439 584 588 16292255 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>18. KiniR.M. Molecular moulds with multiple missions: Functional sites in three-finger toxins Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>Pharmacol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>Physiol. 2002 29 815 822 10.1046/j.1440-1681.2002.03725.x 12165048 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>19. MiwaJ.M.Ibanez-TallonI.CrabtreeG.W.SanchezR.SaliA.RoleL.W.HeintzN. lynx1, an endogenous toxin-like modulator of nicotinic acetylcholine receptors in the mammalian CNS Neuron 1999 23 105 114 10.1016/S0896-6273(00)80757-6 10402197 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>20. TjiuJ.W.LinP.J.WuW.H.ChengY.P.ChiuH.C.ThongH.Y.ChiangB.L.YangW.S.JeeS.H. SLURP1 mutation-impaired T-cell activation in a family with mal de Meleda Br. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>Dermatol. 2011 164 47 53 10.1111/j.1365-2133.2010.10059.x 20854438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>21. KaplanN.MorpurgoN.LinialM. Novel families of toxin-like peptides in insects and mammals: A computational approach J. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2007 369 553 566 10.1016/j.jmb.2007.02.106 17433819 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>22. NaamatiG.AskenaziM.LinialM. A predictor for toxin-like proteins exposes cell modulator candidates within viral genomes Bioinformatics 2010 26 i482 i488 10.1093/bioinformatics/btq375 20823311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>23. TiroshY.MorpurgoN.CohenM.LinialM.BlochG. Raalin, a transcript enriched in the honey bee brain, is a remnant of genomic rearrangement in Hymenoptera Insect Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2012 21 305 318 10.1111/j.1365-2583.2012.01138.x 22404450 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>24. BoutetE.LieberherrD.TognolliM.SchneiderM.BairochA. UniProtKB/Swiss-Prot Methods Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2007 406 89 112 18287689 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>25. SherD.KnebelA.BsorT.NesherN.TalT.MorgensternD.CohenE.FishmanY.ZlotkinE. Toxic polypeptides of the hydra—A bioinformatic approach to cnidarian allomones Toxicon 2005 45 865 879 10.1016/j.toxicon.2005.02.004 15904682 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>26. BrownR.L.HaleyT.L.WestK.A.CrabbJ.W. Pseudechetoxin: A peptide blocker of cyclic nucleotide-gated ion channels Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>USA 1999 96 754 759 10.1073/pnas.96.2.754 9892706 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>27. KusserowA.PangK.SturmC.HroudaM.LentferJ.SchmidtH.A.TechnauU.von HaeselerA.HobmayerB.MartindaleM.Q.HolsteinT.W. Unexpected complexity of the Wnt gene family in a sea anemone Nature 2005 433 156 160 10.1038/nature03158 15650739 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>28. GajhedeM.PetersenT.N.HenriksenA.PetersenJ.F.DauterZ.WilsonK.S.ThimL. Pancreatic spasmolytic polypeptide: First three-dimensional structure of a member of the mammalian trefoil family of peptides Structure 1993 1 253 262 10.1016/0969-2126(93)90014-8 8081739 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>29. AbeT.LimbrickA.R.MilediR. Acute muscle denervation induced by beta-bungarotoxin Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>Lond. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>B 1976 194 545 553 10.1098/rspb.1976.0093 12515 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>30. KwongP.D.McDonaldN.Q.SiglerP.B.HendricksonW.A. Structure of beta 2-bungarotoxin: Potassium channel binding by Kunitz modules and targeted phospholipase action Structure 1995 3 1109 1119 10.1016/S0969-2126(01)00246-5 8590005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>31. CalveteJ.J.MarcinkiewiczC.MonleonD.EsteveV.CeldaB.JuarezP.SanzL. Snake venom disintegrins: Evolution of structure and function Toxicon 2005 45 1063 1074 10.1016/j.toxicon.2005.02.024 15922775 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>32. NaamatiG.FromerM.LinialM. Expansion of tandem repeats in sea anemone Nematostella vectensis proteome: A source for gene novelty? BMC Genomics 2009 10 593 10.1186/1471-2164-10-593 20003297 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>33. MoranY.WeinbergerH.ReitzelA.M.SullivanJ.C.KahnR.GordonD.FinnertyJ.R.GurevitzM. Intron retention as a posttranscriptional regulatory mechanism of neurotoxin expression at early life stages of the starlet anemone Nematostella vectensis J. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2008 380 437 443 10.1016/j.jmb.2008.05.011 18538344 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>34. RappoportN.LinialM. Viral proteins acquired from a host converge to simplified domain architectures PLoS Comput. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2012 8 e1002364 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002364 22319434 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>35. CraikD.J.DalyN.L.WaineC. The cystine knot motif in toxins and implications for drug design Toxicon 2001 39 43 60 10.1016/S0041-0101(00)00160-4 10936622 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>36. ArmishawC.J. Synthetic alpha-conotoxin mutants as probes for studying nicotinic acetylcholine receptors and in the development of novel drug leads Toxins 2010 2 1471 1499 10.3390/toxins2061471 22069647 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>37. KristanK.C.VieroG.dalla SerraM.MacekP.AnderluhG. Molecular mechanism of pore formation by actinoporins Toxicon 2009 54 1125 1134 10.1016/j.toxicon.2009.02.026 19268680 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>38. OvchinnikovaT.V.BalandinS.V.AleshinaG.M.TagaevA.A.LeonovaY.F.KrasnodembskyE.D.Men’sheninA.V.KokryakovV.N. Aurelin, a novel antimicrobial peptide from jellyfish Aurelia aurita with structural features of defensins and channel-blocking toxins Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>Commun. 2006 348 514 523 10.1016/j.bbrc.2006.07.078 16890198 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>39. BiragynA. Defensins-non-antibiotic use for vaccine development Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>Protein Pept. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>Sci. 2005 6 53 60 10.2174/1389203053027601 15638768 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>40. VerstrepenK.J.JansenA.LewitterF.FinkG.R. Intragenic tandem repeats generate functional variability Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>Genet. 2005 37 986 990 10.1038/ng1618 16086015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>41. ZhangP.GuZ.LiW.H. Different evolutionary patterns between young duplicate genes in the human genome Genome Biol. 2003 4 R56 10.1186/gb-2003-4-9-r56 12952535 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>42. WankeE.ZaharenkoA.J.RedaelliE.SchiavonE. Actions of sea anemone type 1 neurotoxins on voltage-gated sodium channel isoforms Toxicon 2009 54 1102 1111 10.1016/j.toxicon.2009.04.018 19393679 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>43. BrodieE.D.III. Convergent evolution: pick your poison carefully Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2010 20 R152 R154 10.1016/j.cub.2009.12.029 20178758 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>44. WhittingtonC.M.KohJ.M.WarrenW.C.PapenfussA.T.TorresA.M.KuchelP.W.BelovK. Understanding and utilising mammalian venom via a platypus venom transcriptome J. Proteomics 2009 72 155 164 10.1016/j.jprot.2008.12.004 19152842 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>45. JOE Joint Genome Institute. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>Nematostella vectensis genome assembly 1.0 (accessed on 2 March 2012) Available online:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.jgi.doe.gov/Nemve1">http://genome.jgi.doe.gov/Nemve1</ext-link>  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>46. NCBI Protein database from NCBI including translations from GenBank, RefSeq, TPA, SwissProt, PIR, PRF, and PDB (accessed on 12 May 2010) Available online:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein</ext-link>  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>47. NaamatiG.AskenaziM.LinialM. ClanTox: A classifier of short animal toxins Nucleic Acids Res 2009 37 W363 W368 10.1093/nar/gkp299 19429697 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>48. PetersenT.N.BrunakS.von HeijneG.NielsenH. SignalP 4.0: Discriminating signal peptides from transmembrane regions Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>Methods 2011 8 785 786 10.1038/nmeth.1701 21959131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>49. HildebrandA.RemmertM.BiegertA.SodingJ. Fast and accurate automatic structure prediction with HHpred Proteins 2009 77 128 132 10.1002/prot.22499 19626712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>50. ClanTox Predictor for Toxin-like proteins (accessed on 31 December 2008) Available online:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.clantox.cs.huji.ac.il">www.clantox.cs.huji.ac.il</ext-link>  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51-toxins-04-01367"><text><SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>51. NewmanA.M.CooperJ.B. XSTREAM: A practical algorithm for identification and architecture modeling of tandem repeats in protein sequences BMC Bioinformatics 2007 8 382 10.1186/1471-2105-8-382 17931424 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
