<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mem. Inst. Oswaldo Cruz</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Memórias do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0074-0276</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1678-8060</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Instituto Oswaldo Cruz, Ministério da Saúde</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4660618</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26560979</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0074-02760150175</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Identification of the nicotinamide mononucleotide adenylyltransferase ofTrypanosoma cruzi </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Niño</surname><given-names>Carlos H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Forero-Baena</surname><given-names>Nicolás</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Contreras</surname><given-names>Luis E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sánchez-Lancheros</surname><given-names>Diana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Figarella</surname><given-names>Katherine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ramírez</surname><given-names>María H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01">
<sup>+</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Universidad Nacional de Colombia, Facultad de Ciencias, Laboratorio de
Investigaciones Básicas en Bioquímica, Bogotá, Colombia</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Fundación Instituto de Estudios Avanzados, Caracas, Venezuela</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c01"><label>+</label> Corresponding author: <email>mhramirezh@unal.edu.co</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>110</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>890</fpage><lpage>897</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>5</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>8</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly
cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The intracellular parasite Trypanosoma cruzi is the aetiological agent of Chagas disease, a public health concern with an increasing incidence rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>This increase is due, among other reasons, to the parasite's drug resistance mechanisms, which require nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NAD+). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, this molecule is involved in metabolic and intracellular signalling processes necessary for the survival of T. cruzi throughout its life cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>NAD+ biosynthesis is performed by de novo and salvage pathways, which converge on the step that is catalysed by the enzyme nicotinamide mononucleotide adenylyltransferase (NMNAT) (enzyme commission number: 2.7.7.1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The identification of the NMNAT of T. cruzi is important for the development of future therapeutic strategies to treat Chagas disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>In this study, a hypothetical open reading frame (ORF) for NMNAT was identified in the genome of T. cruzi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The corresponding putative protein was analysed by simulating structural models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The ORF was amplified from genomic DNA by polymerase chain reaction and was further used for the construction of a corresponding recombinant expression vector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The expressed recombinant protein was partially purified and its activity was evaluated using enzymatic assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>These results comprise the first identification of an NMNAT in T. cruzi using bioinformatics and experimental tools and hence represent the first step to understanding NAD+ metabolism in these parasites. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide</kwd><kwd>nicotinic acid mononucleotide</kwd><kwd>nicotinamide mononucleotide</kwd><kwd>nicotinamide mononucleotide adenylyltransferase</kwd><kwd><italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic></kwd><kwd>Chagas disease</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><counts><fig-count count="7"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="35"/><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NAD+) and its phosphorylated form (NADP+) are vital coenzymes for cellular physiology in all organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>These dinucleotides perform important functions in cellular basal metabolism and cellular antioxidant mechanisms (Kirsch &amp; De Groot 2001, Ghosh et al. 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>NAD+ has an equally important function as a substrate and is involved in multiple cellular signalling processes (Berger et al. 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Because of this role, NAD+ is continuously consumed and thus, its synthesis is essential to maintain cellular homeostasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>NAD+ synthesis occurs via two pathways: de novo synthesis and salvage pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In both cases, nicotinic acid mononucleotide (NAMN) and nicotinamide mononucleotide (NMN) are synthesised, with the subsequent synthesis of NAD+ from these precursors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In the final stage, both synthetic pathways must converge on the reaction catalysed by NMN adenylyltransferase (NMNAT) [enzyme commission number (EC): 2.7.7.1], which transfers the adenylate from adenosine triphosphate (ATP) to any of the mononucleotides (NMN or NAMN), producing NAD+ or nicotinic acid adenine dinucleotide (NAAD) along with pyrophosphate (Jayaram et al. 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>NMNAT has been identified in archaebacteria, eubacteria and eukaryotes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, despite their ubiquity, large differences exist between these enzymes in terms of substrate specificity, oligomerisation capabilities and sensitivity to divalent cationic cofactors (Lau et al. 2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Trypanosoma cruzi is a trypanosomatid that causes Chagas disease, an important public health concern in Latin American countries given its high prevalence and its high morbidity and mortality rates (Rassi Jr et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The increase in diseases caused by trypanosomatids is largely due to the development of resistance to commonly used drugs against these parasites (Borges et al. 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Redox systems are fundamental for the survival and drug resistance of intracellular parasites (Krauth-Siegel et al. 2003, Müller et al. 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>All known resistance mechanisms require NAD+ for their operation (Müller et al. 2003, Turrens 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Moreover, NAD(P) biosynthetic pathways can be considered a generous source of enzymatic targets for drug development (Magni et al. 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The study of NAD+ metabolism in T. cruzi would allow for the design of strategies for the treatment of Chagas disease given the importance of this nucleotide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Consequently, the identification of NMNAT enzymes in this parasite would represent an increase in knowledge of NAD+synthesis and aid in the search for new drug targets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>This paper presents, for the first time, the in silico identification of an NMNAT of T. cruzi (TcNMNAT) using cloning and the heterologous expression of a candidate gene to confirm its identity using direct enzymatic assays. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatic identification of TcNMNAT - Initially, to obtain candidate sequences, a multiple alignment was performed of 16 amino acid (aa) sequences corresponding to several NMNATs of various organisms with varying degrees of phylogenetic divergence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Such sequences were indexed and manually annotated in the UniProtKB protein database (UniProt Consortium 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>To perform the alignment, the Multiple Sequence Comparison by Log-Expectation algorithm (Edgar 2004) embedded as a plugin in the software CLC Sequence Viewer v.6.9 (CLC bio,Denmark) was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The resulting consensus sequence was used to search the genomes of the available T. cruzi strains using the BLASTP algorithm in the trypanosomatid TriTrypDB database (Aslett et al. 2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatic analysis of the TcNMNAT putative protein structure - The primary, secondary and tertiary structures of the TcNMNAT protein encoded in theT. cruzi CL Brener Esmeraldo-like genome were analysed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The web-based tool ProtParam from the ExPASy server (Gasteiger et al. 2003) was used for the analysis of the primary structure and provided predictions of different physicochemical aspects of the protein, such as length and molecular mass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The secondary structure patterns were predicted using three different algorithms that were located on the web-based server NPS@ for network protein sequence analysis (Combet et al. 2000): the GORIV algorithm (Garnier et al. 1996), the third-generation algorithm PHD (Rost &amp; Sander 1993) and the PREDATOR algorithm (Frishman &amp; Argos 1996). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>For the prediction of the tertiary structure and for the assignment of a hypothetical function, a tridimensional model of the putative sequence was performed using the I-TASSER server (Zhang 2008, Roy et al. 2010, 2012), 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The parameters that were chosen from this server were the best tridimensional model that was generated, the prediction of the Enzyme Commission Number EC number and the gene ontology (GO) terms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The tridimensional model that was generated was used for a structural alignment with the HsNMNAT-1 model (PDB ID: 1KQO) (Zhou et al. 2002), which was generated from the X-Ray Diffraction (XRD) database and registered on the PDB database (Bernstein et al. 1978). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>This process was performed using UCSF Chimera v.1.8 software (Pettersen et al. 2004). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>T. cruzi culture and DNA extraction - T. cruziepimastigotes were cultured at 27ºC in Schneider medium (Sigma S9895) that was supplemented with 10% (v/v) foetal bovine serum (Gibco) (Baker &amp; Price 1973, Miralles et al. 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>DNA was extracted from 1 x 107 epimastigotes using the phenol chloroform method (Pereira et al. 2000). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Amplification of the coding fragment of TcNMNAT - The amplification was performed by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using the primers 5'-CACCATGAGCGATGACACA-3´ and 5'-TCAACAATTTTGAGTATTGTTTG-3' (Dieffenbach et al. 1993). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Amplification was performed using two systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The fragment's initial amplification was achieved with a Platinum® PCR SuperMix High Fidelity (Invitrogen) system using 200 ng of genomic DNA as a template. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>An initial denaturation step of 5 min at 94ºC was used, followed by 30 cycles of denaturation at 94ºC for 30 s, annealing at 50ºC for 30 s and extension at 72ºC for 1 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The final extension step was 10 min at 72ºC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>A second amplification was subsequently performed using 1 μL of the previous PCR product as template; in this case, a Pfu DNA Polymerase system (Fermentas, USA) was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The initial denaturation was 5 min at 95ºC, followed by 30 cycles of denaturation at 95ºC for 30 s, annealing at 50ºC for 30 s and extension at 72ºC for 2 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The final extension step was 10 min at 72ºC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Cloning and expression of TcNMNAT - Using the amplified fragment and the pET100 D-TOPO Vector (Invitrogen), the construct pET100 D-TOPO-TcNMNAT was designed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The insertion of the PCR fragment was verified using digestion with the restriction enzyme EcoRV (Fermentas). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Using this construct, Escherichia coli BL21 (DE3) cells were transformed by thermal shock. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The transformed clones were inoculated into liquid Luria broth (LB) that was supplemented with 100 μg/mL ampicillin and incubated overnight at 37ºC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The cultures were diluted (1:50) in the same medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>When the cultures reached an optical density at 600nm of 0.6, the recombinant protein was induced overnight at 37ºC using isopropyl β-D-1-thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG) at a final concentration of 1 mM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The recombinant protein was expressed with a histidine tag (6xHis) on its N-terminus to allow for its detection and further purification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The expression of the recombinant protein was confirmed using sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) and western blotting (WB) (Fra et al. 1995, Ramprasad et al. 1996). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Purification of 6xHis-TcNMNAT - The induced BL21 (DE3) cell cultures were centrifuged at 4,000 g for 15 min at 4ºC and resuspended in lysis buffer (300 mM NaCl; 50 mM NaH2PO4; 10 mM imidazole, pH 8.0/NaOH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Lysozyme (1 mg/mL) and protease inhibitors (P8340; Sigma) were then added. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The mixture was incubated for 30 min at 4ºC with constant agitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>After incubation, the sample was macerated with liquid nitrogen and centrifuged at 19,000g for 15 min at 4ºC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The soluble protein fraction (supernatant) was collected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The obtained soluble extracts were partially purified using nickel affinity chromatography with a staggered elution scheme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>For this scheme, a nickel resin with nitrilotriacetic acid (Ni-NTA) was used as the stationary phase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>As the mobile phase, lysis buffer (50 mM NaH2PO4, 300 mM NaCl pH 8.0/NaOH) was used with varying imidazole concentrations according to both the manufacturer's instructions (Qiagen) and the purification step. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The resin was equilibrated with lysis buffer with 10 mM imidazole before the protein lysate was added and the same 10 mM imidazole concentration was used for the washes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Finally, several consecutive elutions were performed with increasing imidazole concentrations in lysis buffer as follows: first, three elutions with 50 mM imidazole were performed; then, two elutions with 75 mM imidazole and, finally, four elutions with 250 mM imidazole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The proteins that did not bind to the resin, the eluates and the washes were analysed by SDS-PAGE and WB (Fra et al. 1995, Ramprasad et al. 1996). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Detection of recombinant proteins using WB - The samples were separated by SDS-PAGE and then transferred to a polyvinylidene fluoride (Thermo-Scientific) membrane using a 200 mA current for 2 h in transfer buffer [0.2 M glycine, 10 mM Tris/HCl pH 8.0, 10% (v/v) methanol]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The membrane was blocked overnight with a 5% (w/v) nonfat milk solution in tris-buffered saline with Tween 20 (TBS-T) [150 mM NaCl, 20 mM Tris/HCl pH 7.0, 0.1% (v/v) Tween-20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The recombinant protein was detected using the primary antibody anti-6xHis (1:3,000), the secondary antibody biotinylated anti-mouse IgG (1:2,000) and streptavidin-alkaline phosphatase (1:3,000) in TBS-T for the final detection with nitro blue tetrazolium (S380C; Promega) and 5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indolyl-phosphate (S381C; Promega) substrates (Ramprasad et al. 1996). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Direct enzymatic assays - The enzymatic activity of the partially purified recombinant proteins was determined by direct enzymatic assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The reaction mix contained 25 mM HEPES/KOH pH 7.4, 10 mM MgCl2, 1 mM ATP (Sigma) and 1 mM NMN (Sigma) or 1 mM NAMN (Sigma). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>This mix was incubated at 37ºC for 5 min and the enzymatic reaction was initiated by the addition of 5 μg of the samples: the partially purified protein 6xHis-TcNMNAT and the recombinant form of the human isozyme 6xHis-HsNMNAT3 that was expressed from the vector pQE-30/hsnmnat3 as a positive control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The assays were performed in 100 μL at 37ºC for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>To stop and neutralise the reactions, 1.2 M HClO4 and 1 M K2CO3 were used, respectively (Emanuelli et al. 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The analyte separation (50 μL) was performed by reverse phase high-performance liquid chromatographic (RP-HPLC) using a C18 column, 25 cm long x 4.6 mm internal diameter, with a particle size of 5 μm (Phenomenex). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>An elution gradient was used with phosphate buffer (0.1 mM potassium phosphate, pH 6.0) and methanol-phosphate buffer [0.1 mM potassium phosphate pH 6.0 and 20% (v/v) methanol]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The separations were performed at room temperature with a flow of 1.5 mL/min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The analyte detection was performed at 254 nm, considering the elution area under the peak and compared with the appropriate pattern (NAD+ or NAAD). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Protein quantification - The protein concentration was determined by densitometry analysis and/or the Bradford method using bovine serum albumin (BSA) as a standard (Bradford 1976). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Identification of NMNAT candidate sequences in the genome of T. cruzi - Based on a multiple sequence alignment of NMNAT isozymes (Fig. 1), a consensus sequence of 244 residues was obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>This sequence was composed of residues that were highly conserved among the initial sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Using this sequence, a search was performed on the genomes of four T. cruzi strains using the BLASTP algorithm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>A candidate sequence was found for each genome, producing a total of four sequences with scores and significant p-values as shown in Table I; each of these genes encodes a protein of 289 aa and 32 kDa from a coding region of 870 nucleotides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>For all four genes, a biosynthetic function (predicted GO process) and a nucleotidyltransferase activity were predicted (predicted GO function). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Fig. 1:multiple alignments of 16 nicotinamide mononucleotide adenylyltransferase isozymes from phylogenetically divergent organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Sequences used were indexed and annotated in the UniProtKB database and are shown with their corresponding identification code and the degree of conservation of the residues along the sequences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>TABLE IBLASTP search results for NMNAT in genomes of Trypanosoma cruzi strainsGenScorep (n)Gene IDOrganismGenomic locationPredicted gene ontology function12385.3E-021TcCLB.507047.170 T. cruzi CL Brener Esmeraldo-likeTcChr17-S: 188,592-189,461 (-)Nucleotidyltransferase activity22376.8E-021TCSYLVIO_008891 T. cruzi Sylvio X10/1ADWP02020923: 12,533-13,402 (-)Nucleotidyltransferase activity32322.3E-020Tc_MARK_7577 T. cruzi marinkellei strain B7TcMARK_CONTIG_420: 29,693-30,562 (-)Nucleotidyltransferase activity42277.8E-020TcCLB.509179.80 T. cruzi CL Brener non-Esmeraldo-likeTcChr17-P: 188,641-189,510 (-)Nucleotidyltransferase activity </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatics analysis of the putative TcNMNAT - Using the sequence from the genome of CL Brener Esmeraldo-like (TcCLB.507047.170), a structural analysis of the putative TcNMNAT was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The primary structure showed that the putative protein is 289 aa and has a molecular mass of 32,031.4 Da. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The modelling of the secondary structure pattern was performed using three different algorithms (Table II). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The GORIV algorithm (precision ~64%) is based on the propensity of each aa and its neighbours to form a determined secondary structure using a dynamic window of a determined length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The third-generation algorithm PDH (precision &gt;70%) is based on adaptive neural networks and the PREDATOR algorithm (precision ~68-75%) is based on the recognition of aa that are potentially linked by hydrogen bonds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>All three bioinformatics methods showed similar results, with a mean of 43.90% residues located in α-helices, 12.57% in β-sheets and 44.52% in random regions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>TABLE IISecondary structure prediction for a nicotinamide mononucleotide adenylyltransferase of Trypanosoma cruzi candidate </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>For the modelling of the tertiary structure and the assignation of a putative function, a tridimensional model was constructed for the sequence using the I-TASSER server. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The first of five models that were constructed by the server which had the best quality parameters (RMSD, C-score and TM-score) is shown in Fig. 2A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>This figure shows a Rossmann fold, which is typical of proteins that bind to nucleotides (βαβαβ motif). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The three-dimensional model confirmed the secondary structure models that were predicted by the GORIV, PDH and PREDATOR algorithms. Fig. 2B shows a tridimensional alignment with the tertiary structure of the HsNMNAT (1KQO) as generated from XRD data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Clear structural coincidences were evident in several α-helices and β-sheets of the overlapping proteins, which had an RMSD of 0.897 Å between 170 atom pairs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Fig. 2A:tertiary structure model of the nicotinamide mononucleotide adenylyltransferase of Trypanosoma cruzi (TcNMNAT) hypothetical sequence using the I-TASSER server. α-helices are shown in blue and β-sheets are shown in red. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The N-terminal methionine and C-terminal tyrosine residues are shown in black (C-score: -5 &lt; -0.70 &lt; 2, TM-score: 0.62 ± 0.14 &gt; 0.5, RMSD: 7.6 ± 4.3 Å); B: overlap of the TcNMNAT model with the tertiary structure of the HsNMNAT (1KQO) protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>HsNMNAT is shown in yellow and TcNMNAT is shown in red and blue (RMSD between 170 atom pairs: 0.897 Å). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the I-TASSER server predicted the function of the protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The EC number, which was predicted from comparisons with protein structures that were registered in databases, was 2.7.7.1/18, which is consistent with an adenylyltransferase function of the NMNAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Likewise, the predicted GO terms for the function of the protein are consistent with the functional characteristics that are known for NMNAT proteins: GO:0005524, ATP binding (94% confidence), GO:0004515, nicotinate-nucleotide adenylyltransferase activity (94% confidence) and GO:0000309, nicotinamide-nucleotide adenylyltransferase activity (75% confidence). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>TcNMNAT cloning - Taking into account the sequence of theTcCLB.507047.170 gene from the genome of CL Brener Esmeraldo-like, primers for the subsequent PCR amplification were designed.T. cruzi strain CL Brener genomic DNA was used as a template. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>A single fragment with an approximate size of 870 bp was amplified according to the electrophoresis analysis (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Two annealing temperatures below the hypothetical value for the primers were used to observe which condition would render more specific amplification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>This fragment was directly ligated into the expression vector pET100 D-TOPO, followed by transformation into the maintenance E. coli strain TOP10. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Fig. 3:open reading frame amplification of nicotinamide mononucleotide adenylyltransferase of Trypanosoma cruzi from genomic DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Electrophoresis on a 1% agarose gel in Tris/borate/ethylenediamine tetraacetic acid of the amplified fragment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Lanes correspond to molecular marker (100 bp ladder), amplicons from genomic DNA using annealing temperatures of 50°C and 52ºC, followed by the negative control (polymerase chain reaction with no template). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>For subsequent experiments, a temperature of 50ºC was used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Expression and purification of 6xHis-TcNMNAT - The cloned plasmids were extracted and used to transform E. coli BL21 DE3 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The expression of the recombinant protein, termed 6xHis-TcNMNAT, was induced at 37ºC overnight with 1 mM IPTG (Fermentas). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Expression was monitored using SDS-PAGE and WB against the histidine tag that was added to the insert sequence during the cloning step in the pET-100 D-TOPO vector (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The SDS-PAGE in Fig. 4A shows that only one of the TcNMNAT-BL21 DE3 clones that were analysed overexpressed a 35-kDa band, which corresponded to the expected molecular weight for the original aa sequence (32 kDa) with the histidine tag added (3 kDa). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The identity of this recombinant protein was confirmed using an anti-histidine antibody (Fig. 4B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Fig. 4:induction of the 6xHis-nicotinamide mononucleotide adenylyltransferase of Trypanosoma cruzi (TcNMNAT) in total cellular extracts from transformed BL21 DE3 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>A: sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis on a 10% gel stained with Coomassie dye; B: western blot with alkaline phosphatase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The lanes include the molecular weight marker (kDa), induced negative control with a nontransformed strain (-) and different inductions of transformed cells with the expression vector pET100 D-TOPO-6xHis-TcNMNAT (BL21 clones I, II, III and IV). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The recombinant protein was purified from the soluble fraction of the induced cells, although the majority of the 6xHis-TcNMNAT was found in the insoluble fraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>This process was performed by nickel affinity chromatography using Ni-NTA with a staggered elution scheme (using imidazole), as shown in Fig. 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>A partial purification and an enrichment of the recombinant protein were obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The bands with a lower molecular weight correspond to possible degradation products according to the recognition of the antibody. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Fig. 5:nickel affinity chromatography using Ni-NTA with staggered elutions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>A: sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis on a 12% gel stained with Coomassie dye; B: western blot with alkaline phosphatase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The lanes correspond to the molecular weight marker, the insoluble fraction of induced Escherichia coli BL21 DE3 cells, the soluble fraction of induced E. coli BL21 DE3 cells, proteins that did not bind to the Ni-NTA resin, the first wash fraction (L1), the final wash fraction (L31), the third elution at 50 mM imidazole and elutions using 75 mM and 250 mM imidazole. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Confirmation of the NMNAT identity using enzymatic assays - The functional identity of the recombinant protein was verified with direct enzymatic assays using the 250 mM imidazole elution fraction from the affinity chromatography. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>In these assays, the presence of substrates and products was detected using RP-HPLC (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The chromatographic profiles showed that the hypothetical protein 6xHis-TcNMNAT is an NMNAT, which was confirmed by the presence of the corresponding products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>This enzyme showed activity for both NAMN and NMN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>NAMN and NMN are the substrates that are used by NMNAT in the presence of ATP to form NAD+ and NAAD, respectively (Berger et al. 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Therefore, this result confirms that 6xHis-TcNMNAT effectively belongs to the NMNAT family. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Fig. 6:determination of the enzymatic activity of 6xHis-nicotinamide mononucleotide adenylyltransferase of Trypanosoma cruzi(TcNMNAT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>A: assays performed with nicotinic acid mononucleotide (NAMN); B: assays performed with nicotinamide mononucleotide (NMN). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>From the top down, the graphs correspond to positive controls (6xHis-HsNMNAT3, the recombinant form of the human NMNAT isozyme), assays with the 6xHis-TcNMNAT and the negative controls (reactions with no enzyme); ATP: adenosine triphosphate; NAD: nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide; NaMN: nicotinic acid mononucleotide; OD: optical density. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>NAD+ synthesising routes in T. cruzi have been previously reported, including the NMNAT gene (Klein et al. 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>However, in the present study, a TcNMNAT was identified by means of different bioinformatic and experimental strategies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>This finding represents important progress towards the understanding of the biosynthesis of pyridine nucleotides in parasitic protozoa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>In addition, this study establishes a first approach to understanding NAD+ metabolism in T. cruzi by providing information about NAD+ synthesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The performed sequence analysis allowed for the identification of a single gene encoding NMNAT in the different genomes that are available for T. cruzistrains (Table I). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The structural analysis of the putative protein, which is encoded by a gene from the strain CL Brener Esmeraldo-like, suggests that it belongs to the NMNAT family (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Based on this gene, a sequence was amplified from the genomic DNA of T. cruzi CL Brener (Fig. 3) and the approximately 35 kDa recombinant protein 6xHis-TcNMNAT was successfully expressed (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>In addition, partial purification of the protein was achieved (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The purified recombinant protein was capable of synthesising NAD+ and NAAD from NAMN and NMN (Fig. 6), respectively, which are substrates that used by the NMNAT family of enzymes (Jayaram et al. 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that the hypothetical sequence analysedin silico and in vitro corresponds to that of the TcNMNAT. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>All of the known pathways leading to the synthesis of NAD+ require NMNAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>This enzyme is of great importance for metabolism, energy supply and signal transduction (Berger et al. 2004, Jayaram et al. 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>This enzyme also plays an important role in oxidative stress control and drug resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the TcNMNAT represents a potential target for the development of future drugs and other therapeutic strategies, as has been proposed in other intracellular parasites (Sorci et al. 2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>As no other NMNAT structurally related enzymes were found, it is tempting to suggest that the NAD+ levels in this organism may depend exclusively on the expression of the NMNAT that was identified in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Likewise, the production of NAD+ could be explained by the use of precursors from the host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>However, the existence of additional isozymes in T. cruzi should not be excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>It is necessary to use other search strategies to identify new candidates that do not meet the current prediction parameters (e.g., gene finding through hidden Markov models). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>This is the first NMNAT to be identified in the genus Trypanosoma, which includes several pathogens that infect humans and other economically important mammals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Thus, TcNMNAT emerges as a starting point in the understanding of the NAD+ synthetic pathway in this parasite. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Financial support: COLCIENCIAS, DIB-UNAL (566-2012/ 15715,19148), Venezuelan Ministry of Higher Education, Science and Technology (IDEA Foundation, POA-2012/2013), FONDEN-Venezuela </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>AslettMAurrecoecheaCBerrimanMBrestelliJBrunkBPCarringtonMDepledgeDPFischerSGajriaBGaoXGardnerMJGingleAGrantGHarbOSHeigesMHertz-FowlerCHoustonRInnamoratoFIodiceJKissingerJCKraemerELiWLoganFJMillerJAMitraSMylerPJNayakVPenningtonCPhanIPinneyDFRamasamyGRogersMBRoosDSRossCSivamDSmithDFSrinivasamoorthyGStoeckertCJJrSubramanianSThibodeauRTiveyATreatmanCVelardeGWangH2010TriTrypDB: a functional genomic resource for the TrypanosomatidaeNucleic Acids Res38D457D46219843604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>BakerJRPriceJ1973Growth in vitro of Trypanosoma cruzi as amastigotes at temperatures below 37ºCInt J Parasitol35495514580045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>BergerFRamírez-HernándezMZieglerM2004The new life of a centenarian: signalling functions of NAD(P)Trends Biochem Sci2911111815003268 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>BernsteinFCKoetzleTFWilliamsGJBMeyerEFJr1978The protein data bank: a computer-based archival file for macromolecular structuresArch Biochem Biophys185584591626512 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>BorgesVMLopesUGde SouzaWVannier-SantosMA2005Cell structure and cytokinesis alterations in multidrug-resistant Leishmania (Leishmania) amazonensisParasitol Res95909615592939 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>BradfordMM1976A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye bindingAnal Biochem72248254942051 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>CombetCBlanchetCGeourjonCDeléageG2000NPS@: Network Protein Sequence analysisTrends Biochem Sci2514715010694887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>DieffenbachCWLoweTMDvekslerGS1993General concepts for PCR primer designPCR Methods Appl3S30S378118394 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>EdgarRC2004MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughputNucleic Acids Res321792179715034147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>EmanuelliMCarnevaliFLorenziMRaffaelliNAmiciARuggieriSMagniG1999Identification and characterization of YLR328W, the Saccharomyces cerevisiae structural gene encoding NMN adenylyltransferase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Expression and characterization of the recombinant enzymeFEBS Lett455131710428462 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>FraAMWilliamsonESimonsKPartonRG1995 De novo formation of caveolae in lymphocytes by expression of VIP21-caveolinProc Natl Acad Sci USA92865586597567992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>FrishmanDArgosP1996Incorporation of non-local interactions in protein secondary structure prediction from the amino acid sequenceProtein Eng91331429005434 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>GarnierJGibratJFRobsonBDoolittleR1996GOR secondary structure prediction method version IVMethods Enzymol2665405538743705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>GasteigerEGattikerAHooglandCIvanyiIAppelRDBairochA2003ExPASy: the proteomics server for in-depth protein knowledge and analysisNucleic Acids Res313784378812824418 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>GhoshSGeorgeSRoyURamachandranDKolthur-SeetharamU2010NAD: a master regulator of transcriptionBiochim Biophys Acta179968169320713194 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>JayaramHNKusumanchiPYalowitzJA2011NMNAT expression and its relation to NAD metabolismCurr Med Chem181962197221517776 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>KirschMGrootH2001NAD(P)H, a directly operating antioxidant?FASEB J151569157411427489 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>KleinCCAlvesJMSerranoMGBuckGAVasconcelosATSagotMFTeixeiraMMCamargoEPMottaMC2013Biosynthesis of vitamins and cofactors in bacterium-harbouring trypanosomatids depends on the symbiotic association as revealed by genomic analysesPLoS ONE8 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Krauth-SiegelRLMeieringSKSchmidtH2003The parasite-specific trypanothione metabolism of Trypanosoma and LeishmaniaBiol Chem38453954912751784 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>LauCNiereMZieglerM2009The NMN/NaMN adenylyltransferase (NMNAT) protein familyFront Biosci14410431 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>MagniGDi StefanoMOrsomandoGRaffaelliNRuggieriS2009NAD(P) biosynthesis enzymes as potential targets for selective drug designCurr Med Chem161372139019355893 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>MirallesDMMarínCMagánRFernández-RamosCEntralaECordovaOVargasFSánchez-MorenoM2002In vitro culture and biochemical characterization of six trypanosome isolates from Peru and BrazilExp Parasitol102232912615163 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>MüllerSLiebauEWalterRDKrauth-SiegelRL2003Thiol-based redox metabolism of protozoan parasitesTrends Parasitol1932032812855383 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>PereiraCAAlonsoGDPavetoMCIribarrenACabanasMLTorresHNFlawiáMM2000Trypanosoma cruzi arginine kinase characterization and cloning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>A novel energetic pathway in protozoan parasitesJ Biol Chem2751495150110625703 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>PettersenEFGoddardTDHuangCCCouchGSGreenblattDMMengECFerrinTE2004UCSF Chimera - a visualization system for exploratory research and analysisJ Comput Chem251605161215264254 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>RamprasadMPTerpstraVKondratenkoNQuehenbergerOSteinbergD1996Cell surface expression of mouse macrosialin and human CD68 and their role as macrophage receptors for oxidized low density lipoproteinProc Natl Acad Sci USA9314833148388962141 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>RassiAJrRassiAde RezendeJM2012American trypanosomiasis (Chagas disease)Infect Dis Clin N Am26275291 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>RostBSanderC1993Prediction of protein secondary structure at better than 70% accuracyJ Mol Biol2325845998345525 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>RoyAKucukuralAZhangY2010I-TASSER: a unified platform for automated protein structure and function predictionNat Protoc572573820360767 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>RoyAYangJZhangY2012COFACTOR: an accurate comparative algorithm for structure-based protein function annotationNucleic Acids Res40W471W47722570420 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>SorciLPanYEyoboYRodionovaIHuangNKurnasovOZhongSMacKerellADJrZhangHOstermanAL2009Targeting NAD biosynthesis in bacterial pathogens: structure-based development of inhibitors of nicotinate mononucleotide adenylyltransferase NadDChem Biol1684986119716475 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>TurrensJF2004Oxidative stress and antioxidant defenses: a target for the treatment of diseases caused by parasitic protozoaMol Aspects Med2521122015051329 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>UniProt Consortium2014Activities at the Universal Protein Resource (UniProt)Nucleic Acids Res42D191D19824253303 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>ZhangY2008I-TASSER server for protein 3D structure predictionBMC Bioinformatics9 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>ZhouTKurnasovOTomchickDRBinnsDDGrishinNVMarquezVEOstermanALZhangH2002Structure of human nicotinamide/nicotinic acid mononucleotide adenylyltransferase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Basis for the dual substrate specificity and activation of the oncolytic agent tiazofurinJ Biol Chem277131481315411788603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
