<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4564166</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26352270</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135927</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-04993</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Whole-Exome Sequencing in a South American Cohort Links ALDH1A3, FOXN1 and Retinoic Acid Regulation Pathways to Autism Spectrum Disorders </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Whole Exome Sequencing in Colombian ASD Trios</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moreno-Ramos</surname><given-names>Oscar A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Olivares</surname><given-names>Ana María</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Haider</surname><given-names>Neena B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Autismo</surname><given-names>Liga Colombiana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001">
<sup>¶</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lattig</surname><given-names>María Claudia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Departamento de Ciencias Biológicas, Facultad de Ciencias, Universidad de los Andes, Bogotá D.C., Colombia</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Schepens Eye Research Institute, Massachusetts Eye and Ear Infirmary, Department of Ophthalmology, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff003">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Liga Colombiana de Autismo (LICA), Bogotá D.C., Colombia</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Laboratoire de Biologie du Développement de Villefranche-sur-Mer, FRANCE</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors declare funding from a commercial source: Bank of America. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>This does not alter their adherence to all the PLOS ONE policies on sharing data and materials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: MCL OAM NBH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: OAM AMO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: OAM MCL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: NBH MCL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: OAM MCL NBH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Patient referral, clinical and psychological evaluation: Liga Colombiana de Autismo. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>¶ Membership of the Liga Colombiana de Autismo is listed in the Acknowledgments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>mlattig@uniandes.edu.co</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e0135927</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 Moreno-Ramos et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Moreno-Ramos et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0135927.pdf"/><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Autism spectrum disorders (ASDs) are a range of complex neurodevelopmental conditions principally characterized by dysfunctions linked to mental development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown that there are more than 1000 genes likely involved in ASD, expressed mainly in brain and highly interconnected among them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>We applied whole exome sequencing in Colombian—South American trios. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Two missense novel SNVs were found in the same child: ALDH1A3 (RefSeq NM_000693: c.1514T&gt;C (p.I505T)) and FOXN1 (RefSeq NM_003593: c.146C&gt;T (p.S49L)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Gene expression studies reveal that Aldh1a3 and Foxn1 are expressed in ~E13.5 mouse embryonic brain, as well as in adult piriform cortex (PC; ~P30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Conserved Retinoic Acid Response Elements (RAREs) upstream of human ALDH1A3 and FOXN1 and in mouse Aldh1a3 and Foxn1 genes were revealed using bioinformatic approximation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) assay using Retinoid Acid Receptor B (Rarb) as the immunoprecipitation target suggests RA regulation of Aldh1a3 and Foxn1 in mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Our results frame a possible link of RA regulation in brain to ASD etiology, and a feasible non-additive effect of two apparently unrelated variants in ALDH1A3 and FOXN1 recognizing that every result given by next generation sequencing should be cautiously analyzed, as it might be an incidental finding. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>Support for sequencing was provided by proyecto semilla 2013-1, Facultad de ciencias, Universidad de los Andes (OAM) and Vicerrectoria de investigaciones, Universidad de los Andes (MCL). Support for molecular and animal studies was provided by the Chase Fund (NBH) and Edward N. &amp; Della L. Thome Memorial Foundation, Bank Of America, N.A., Trustee (NBH). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="3"/><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Autism spectrum disorders (ASD) are a range of complex neurodevelopmental conditions characterized by dysfunctions in mental development [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>At the same time, it has been hypothesized that ASD are a group of continuous disorders instead of a single discrete disorder [2], explaining why ASD patient symptomatology is so variable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Although prevalence of ASD has increased worldwide [3], in Colombia there are no official reports regarding its prevalence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>A recent study has shown that ASD heritability is calculated closely to 50% [4] (lower than the ~90% previously estimated [2,5]) leading to higher environmental factor’s impact on the occurrence of the disorder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In fact, no clear environmental factors that have been unfolded since the recurrence of ASD does not change statistically between dizygotic twins and complete siblings [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Most of our understanding of the molecular basis of ASD comes from reports of rare copy number variants (CNVs) [6–8] and the discovery of de novo single nucleotide variants (SNVs) using Whole Exome Sequencing (WES) [9–13] or Whole Genome Sequencing (WGS) [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>More than a 1000 genes are thought to be involved in ASD [15], most of them located in genes of known function and involved in pathways related to cell and neuronal development, projection, motility and proliferation; also in genes involved in spine and dendrite plasticity regulation, and gene regulation [8,15,16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Additionally, variants affecting recurrent genes have been associated to ASD by their single impact ignoring a possible synergic impact between two or more de novo events in the same individual. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, all this information has been derived mostly from Caucasian individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Thus, novel genes and even novel pathways involved in ASD pathogenesis might be found in understudied populations such as Colombian. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>WES was applied in search of de novo variants that might be causative of ASD in four family trios from Colombia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Two de novo non-synonymous mutations affecting ALDH1A3 (RefSeq NM_000693, MIM:600463) and FOXN1 (RefSeq NM_003593.2, MIM:600838) genes were uncovered in the same child (FAM07). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Recently, retinoic acid (RA) pathways mediated by Retinoid Orphan Receptor Alpha (RORA) have been implicated in ASD [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, homozygous ALDH1A3 missense and nonsense mutations in humans have been linked to anophthalmia and microphthalmia (MIM: 615113; A/M) with some affected individuals also exhibiting autistic traits [18–23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Though no clear evidence supports a link between variants in ALDH1A3 with autism, mouse studies show that lack of Aldh1a3 (Gene NC_000073.6) results in abnormal GABAergic neuronal differentiation in the forebrain basal ganglia [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Malfunctions in this inhibitory system have been found to be associated to mental disorders like ASD, schizophrenia and bipolar disorder [25,26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Moreover, failures of this enzyme in the striatum are related to elimination of dopamine receptor D2 in the nucleus accumbens [27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Although little is known about FOXN1, it is essential for proper immune system function, especially in thymus development and maintenance during adulthood [28–30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Foxn1 (Gene NC_000077.6) knockout mice (commonly known as NUDE mouse) overexpress pro-inflammatory cytokines (Specially TH1) [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>This overexpression has also been reported in ASD children [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Besides T-cell immunodeficiency, mutations in FOXN1 have also been observed together with congenital alopecia and nail dystrophy (MIM: 601705). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>A homozygote mutation in FOXN1 was reported in a 15-week-old fetus with anencephaly and severe neural tube defect (MIM: 601705) [33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>As ALDH1A3 is an enzyme responsible for Retinoic Acid (RA) synthesis, and FOXN1 has been found to regulated by RORA (gene involved in RA cascade) [17], together with RA’s major role in gene expression regulation during brain development [34], it was questioned if RA might possibly regulate ALDH1A3 and FOXN1 through RA receptors (RARs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Predicted RA Response Elements (RAREs) in the promoter regions of both genes where evaluated to be recognized by RARs, using C57BL/6J (B6) mice, in two developmental stages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Rarb (Gene NC_000080.6) was selected as the chromatin association target protein since it is known to regulate dorsal and ventral telencephalon development, hippocampal plasticity and brain barrier development [35–38]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Results indicate that Rarb regulates Aldh1a3 and Foxn1 (NC_000077.6) in adult (~P30) mice PC and in embryo (~E13.5) whole brain, as demonstrated by ChIP essay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>We suspect that both variants in genes ALDH1A3 and FOXN1 interact in a non-additive manner, where an epistatic interaction effect can be expected, possibly explaining the etiology in the affected child. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec003"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Ethics statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The study presented here involves human participation and informed consent and assent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The study and consent procedure was approved by the ethical committee of Universidad de los Andes (Acta 11, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Informed consent and assent was given and explained to all participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>All participants provided a written informed consent to participate in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Each consent was marked with a family and individual unique identifier, names and identifying information are kept securely stored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Only the principal investigator is able to recognize personal data with unique identifiers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Animal procedures were approved by Schepens Eye Research Institute Animal Care and Use Committee (Permit number: S-309–0714) in compliance with the Animal Welfare Act Regulations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Cohort selection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Four family trios (family ID: Fam02, Fam07, Fam09 and Fam10) referred by Liga Colombiana de Autismo (LICA) were selected to participate in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>All individuals are from Bogotá D.C.—Colombia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Affected individuals were engaged in a series of tests-tasks to evaluate patterns and maturity of the child, interaction with parents and family patterns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Inclusion in the present study required meeting criteria for autism on the ADOS [39] and ADI-R [40] and subject were confirmed to meet DSM-V (APA, 2012) criteria for autism by trained professionals who observed and interacted with them over several visits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>After psychological examination, a genetic counselor physician discarded any comorbidity with other ASD related syndrome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>DNA sample preparation, exome sequencing and analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>DNA extraction was carried out using FlexiGene DNA kit (Qiagen, Gaithersburg, MD, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The extraction was carried out parting from 300uL of leucocytes following manufacturer instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>A mean of 8.7ug of DNA per individual was sent to Otogenetics Corporation in Atlanta GA, USA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>We applied WES using Agilent Sureselect All Exon V4 platform and PE100 Illumina HiSeq2000 platform to the four family trios selected (all family trios DNA samples met the quality criteria for WES by Otogenetics Corporation, Atlanta, GA—USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Sequence reads were cleaned using the latest version of FASTX-Toolkit (V 0.0.13.2) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hannonlab.cshl.edu/fastx_toolkit/index.html">http://hannonlab.cshl.edu/fastx_toolkit/index.html</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Sequence mapping and variant calling was carried first by mapping the short sequences using Burrows-Wheeler aligner (BWA) (from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bio-bwa.sourceforge.net/">http://bio-bwa.sourceforge.net</ext-link>) [41] on the latest version of the human genome available at UCSC Genome Browser (HG19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>SAM tools (from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://samtools.sourceforge.net/">http://samtools.sourceforge.net</ext-link>) [42] and PicardTools (from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://picard.sourceforge.net/">http://picard.sourceforge.net</ext-link>) were used to manipulate and mark sequence duplicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>SNPs and small indel calling was achieved using HaplotypeCaller walker of Genome Analysis Toolkit (GATK, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/gatk/">http://www.broadinstitute.org/gatk/</ext-link>) [43,44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Best practices of GATK were followed in order to guarantee an efficient variant calling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Annotation was performed using snpEff (Human genome reference 37.5) [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Putative de novo variants were identified using AWK language. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Variant prioritization and validation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>After identifying all the non-inherited variants, minor allele frequency (MAF) was revised from dbSNP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Those variants that presented a MAF &gt; 5% were discarded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Different sets of primers were manually designed to flank the variants position obtained during calling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>PCR amplification protocol described in Perea, C.S. et al., 2012 was used [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Sanger sequencing at Macrogen, Seul—Korea; and at Universidad de los Andes’ Sanger sequencing facility (3500 Genetic Analyzer; Applied Biosystems, USA) was used to corroborate the presence of each of the variants unveiled. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>After validation of each of the variants was performed, depending on the predicted impact, different bioinformatic tools were used to predict their impact. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The possible effect of the synonymous variant on mRNA stability was analyzed using SilVA [47], and ESEfinder for possible de novo splicing regions [48,49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Non-synonymous variants were analyzed using SIFT [50], PolyPhen [51] and PROVEAN [52]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Retinoic acid regulation pattern discovery </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Searching for the relaxed Retinoic Acid Response Element [RARE; 5’-(A/G)G(G/T)(G/T)(G/C)A-3’ motif separated by one, two or five nucleotides, which interacts with heterodimers of RARs and retinoid X receptors (RXRs)] [34,53,54], was achieved using the online interface of Patser (online site: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://stormo.wustl.edu/consensus/html/Html/main.html">http://stormo.wustl.edu/consensus/html/Html/main.html</ext-link>) [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Genomic region spanning 30000bp upstream to 1000bp downstream from the initial transcription site for humans and mice (Human genome build NCBI 37.5 and Mouse genome build GRCm38.p2) in both negative and positive strands was analyzed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Pregnant females and adults were obtained under standard conditions from Jackson Laboratory and housed in vivariums at Schepens Eye Research Institute. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The study was carried out in strict accordance with the recommendations in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of the National Institute of Health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Tissues were collected from C57BL/6J (B6) postnatal (~P30) and from B6 embryonic (~E13.5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Aldh1a3 and Foxn1 expression study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Transcription was observed after total RNA extraction from piriform cortex (PC) from both lobules of adult C57BL/6J (B6) brain mice (~P30), and B6 embryonic whole brain (~E13.5) using Trizol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>PC was chosen since Aldh1a3 expression has been reported in this region in postnatal stages [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>A total of 2μg of total RNA was reversed using random decamers, in independent biological triplicates using Retroscript (Ambion). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>PCR, using primers flanking the conserved splice regions of both genes (S2 Table), was used to check Foxn1 and Aldh1a3 transcription. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>PCR products were run on agarose (2%) ethidium bromide stained gel. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Chromatin immunoprecipitation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Chromatin immunoprecipitacion assay (ChIP) against RARs-RARE interaction was used to validate the bioinformatic predictions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>ChIP, followed by PCR against the interaction of Rarb with the predicted RAREs, was performed as described in Haider, N.B. et al., 2009 with modifications [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Briefly, three adult (~P30) mice PC and three embryo (~E13.5) mouse whole brain were collected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Each sample was sonicated using three cycles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>First cycle: 1s pulse*1s wait between pulses; total of 20 pulses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Second cycle: 19 steps of ten pulses, 1s pulse*1s wait between pulses, 30 seconds wait between steps; total of 190 pulses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Third cycle: 10s pulse*20s wait between pulses; total of three pulses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Average DNA fragment size obtained was ~300bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Aliquots for Input (Positive control), Rarb antibody (SC-552, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.) immunoprecipitation and rabbit IgG (2027, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.) (Negative control) were taken and incubated overnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>PCR was performed using primers flanking each RARE sequence found in mice (S3 Table), to amplify approximately 200 base pair amplicon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>PCR conditions used are previously described in Haider, N.B. et al., 2001 where an annealing temperature of 58°C and 35 cycles were applied, and a dilution of 1:10 for the Input sample was used [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>PCR products were visualized by ethidium bromide staining. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="sec011"><title><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec012"><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Exome sequencing, technical outcomes, variant calling and de novo variant discovery </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>After applying WES, a ~69.1X coverage was yielded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>In average, ~228,116.1 variants per family trio were obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>A total of three SNVs and one Indel were validated by PCR amplification followed by Sanger sequencing (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>We observed a transvertion-transition ratio of 1:2 and non-coding SNV or Indel were found in two of the families studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>None of the genes found in this study have been reported in the 982 WES studies [9–13], or in any of the ten WGS family trios [14] performed to date. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>All other NGS data is stored at the Universidad de los Andes bioinformatic facility and it is freely available upon request. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec016"><title><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Most ASD studies highlight a strong genetic heterogeneity where both de novo germline and rare inherited variants are distributed across numerous genes yet, interconnected in similar biological processes such as chromatin remodeling and transcription regulation [8,10–13,16] or target of fragile X mental retardation protein (FMRP) [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, previous WES studies associate genes to ASD only if two or more disrupting variants are observed in the same gene in different individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Variant and gene association depends uniquely on the effect the affected gene has [6,10–13,15,59], though it is also important to examine how two or more de novo variants in the same individual might play a synergic role on ASD phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Moreover, every result given by WES or WGS trio studies should be carefully analyzed, as it might be an incidental finding unless function studies are performed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The findings of RAREs sequences in the promoter regions, in humans as in mice, made us consider that RARs family might regulate FOXN1 and ALDH1A3 genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Thus, we aimed to determine if any of those RAREs predicted might be functional using mice as models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>We first confirm expression of Aldh1a3 in PC during in adult (~P30) mouse brain as previously shown [56] and evaluated co-expression of Foxn1 in the same region and stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Moreover, we demonstrate that both genes are also expressed in embryo (~E13.5) mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>ChIP-PCR results suggest that Foxn1 and Aldh1a3 expression is promoted by Rarb binding to different RARES in both tissues (adult PC and embryo whole brain; Fig 2B, Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Since ChIP was only carried out to analyze Rarb-RARE interaction, we could not assure that any other members of the Rar family or other transcription factors might contribute to Foxn1 or Aldh1a3 regulation during the stages analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is possible that gene RA regulation is exerted by other proteins in both tissues at both stages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Based on known functions of RARs/RXRs, these results predict a possible positive regulation by Rarb for both genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>The RA regulation model predicts that in RA presence, RARs/RXRs release co-repressor proteins and recruit co-activation complexes [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>In fact, it has been demonstrated that RA promotes Rars binding to putative RAREs in mouse embryonic stem cells working as transcription enhancers [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>As Rarb and the other RAR family members regulate many genes at different stages and tissues at time-specific periods, lack of RA might contribute to a transcriptional deregulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Recently, non functional ALDH1A3 alleles have been reported as responsible for ophthalmologic diseases as A/M in which four of the six reports mention that some affected individuals also have ASD like features or intellectual disability in different degrees, even though these findings are generally considered as incidental [18,19,21,23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>However, it is not possible to discard the idea that mutations in ALDH1A3 might alter brain development since it has been described that RA is essential for brain cortex development facilitating transcription of essential genetic markers [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Additionally, FAM07 child carries a non-synonymous variant, predicted to be pathogenic in ALDH1A3 (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>One would thus predict that RA synthesis and concentration in basal ganglia, nucleus accumbens, striatum, and PC would be lower than normal levels. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Since RA mediates transcription of different genes, variants in ALDH1A3 in conjunction with other inherited rare variants or de novo variants potentially act synergistically causing ASD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>This might also be the case in the A/M phenotype where some of the affected individuals also have ASD or intellectual disability [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Yet, if another pathogenic variant is present on a gene that is regulated by retinoic acid, the altered concentrations levels of RA together with a deficient function of a second gene might end up in a phenotype such as ASD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>As no clear data of FOXN1 regulation of brain development is clear, we cannot predict a direct effect of the non-synonymous variant observed in this child. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Since this nuclear receptor is apparently regulated by RA via Rarb, the lack of this metabolite due to the mutation in ALDH1A3 might cause a lower transcription of FOXN1, leading to a dysregulation of genes and pathways not yet described. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Moreover, nude affected humans by mutations or truncations in the FOXN1 gene do not present gross central nervous system alterations [62], but they however present changes in the corpus callosum, neural tube and choroid plexus [33,62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>This suggest that FOXN1 has similar functions as other member of the FOX family like FOXP1 and FOXP2 [63,64], which have been already associated to ASD [6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, the results indicate that next generation sequencing from under-studied cohorts provide new genetic data that might conduct to new perspectives and hypothesis to explain genetic basis of ASD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Our results are in concordance with previous studies demonstrating that transcription factors play significant roles in ASD [8,10–13,16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>A previous study of our group reported that genes involved in transcription regulation are essential to serotoninergic pathway stability in depression [65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Moreover, even though ASD is highly heritable, a multitude of environmental influences play a fundamental role on ASD incidence [4], which might interact with the proband’s genetic variants causing the disorder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Though carrying a variant in one allele of ALDH1A3 might not cause a defined phenotype such as A/M, this can act as a risk allele to ASD since lower levels of RA might contribute to a poor transcription of several genes, one of them being FOXN1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the second gene variant present in FOXN1, might affect this transcription factor´s function by not properly regulating yet uncovered pathways in brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Finally, when attributing causation to de novo variants prudence needs to be exercised. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec017"><title><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0135927.s001"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Retinoic Acid Response Elements (RAREs) found 30000bp upstream and 1000bp downstream from the initial transcription site in both DNA strands for ALDH1A3 and FOXN1 genes in humans, and Aldh1a3 and Foxn1 genes in mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Relative positions are given from the initial transcription site of each gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0135927.s001.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0135927.s002"><label>S2 Table</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Primer sequences flanking conserved regions of Aldh1a3 and Foxn1 transcripts in mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Sequences are given 5’࢐3’ direction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0135927.s002.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0135927.s003"><label>S3 Table</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Primer sequences used to amplify each flanking RARE bioinformatically predicted sequences for Aldh1a3 and Foxn1 genes in mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Sequences are given 5’→3’ direction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0135927.s003.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>We thank the children, their families for deciding to be part of this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Liga Colombiana de Autismo participant’s member list is as follows: Edith B. Roncancio, Camilo O. Vargas, Francisco J. Paredes, Sandra M. Grisales, Anyela M. Peña, Miguel A. Robayo, María E. Rodriguez and María E. Reyes. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0135927.ref001"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>1 AbrahamsBS, GeschwindDH. Advances in autism genetics: on the threshold of a new neurobiology. Nat Rev Genet. 2008;9:341–55. 10.1038/nrg2346 <?supplied-pmid 18414403?>18414403 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref002"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>2 ConstantinoJN, ToddRD. Autistic traits in the general population: a twin study. Arch Gen Psychiatry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>American Medical Association; 2003 5 1;60(5):524–30. <?supplied-pmid 12742874?>12742874 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref003"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>3 ZaroffCM, UhmSY. Prevalence of autism spectrum disorders and influence of country of measurement and ethnicity. Soc Psychiatry Psychiatr Epidemiol. 2012 3;47(3):395–8. 10.1007/s00127-011-0350-3 <?supplied-pmid 21293843?>21293843 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref004"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>4 SandinS, LichtensteinP, Kuja-HalkolaR, LarssonH, HultmanCM, ReichenbergA. The familial risk of autism. JAMA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>American Medical Association; 2014 5 7;311(17):1770–7. 10.1001/jama.2014.4144 <?supplied-pmid 24794370?>24794370 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref005"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>5 OzonoffS, YoungGS, CarterA, MessingerD, YirmiyaN, ZwaigenbaumL, et al Recurrence risk for autism spectrum disorders: a Baby Siblings Research Consortium study. Pediatrics. 2011 9;128(3):e488–95. 10.1542/peds.2010-2825 <?supplied-pmid 21844053?>21844053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref006"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>6 SandersSJ, Ercan-SencicekAG, HusV, LuoR, MurthaMT, Moreno-De-LucaD, et al Multiple recurrent de novo CNVs, including duplications of the 7q11.23 Williams syndrome region, are strongly associated with autism. Neuron. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Elsevier; 2011 6 9;70(5):863–85. 10.1016/j.neuron.2011.05.002 <?supplied-pmid 21658581?>21658581 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref007"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>7 VorstmanJAS, van DaalenE, JalaliGR, SchmidtERE, PasterkampRJ, de JongeM, et al A double hit implicates DIAPH3 as an autism risk gene. Mol Psychiatry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Macmillan Publishers Limited; 2011 4;16(4):442–51. 10.1038/mp.2010.26 <?supplied-pmid 20308993?>20308993 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref008"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>8 PintoD, DelabyE, MericoD, BarbosaM, MerikangasA, KleiL, et al Convergence of Genes and Cellular Pathways Dysregulated in Autism Spectrum Disorders. Am J Hum Genet. 2014 4 1;94(5):677–94. 10.1016/j.ajhg.2014.03.018 <?supplied-pmid 24768552?>24768552 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref009"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>9 O’RoakBJ, DeriziotisP, LeeC, VivesL, SchwartzJJ, GirirajanS, et al Exome sequencing in sporadic autism spectrum disorders identifies severe de novo mutations. Nat Genet. Nature Publishing Group, a division of Macmillan Publishers Limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>All Rights Reserved.; 2011 6;43(6):585–9. 10.1038/ng.835 <?supplied-pmid 21572417?>21572417 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref010"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>10 O’RoakBJ, VivesL, GirirajanS, KarakocE, KrummN, CoeBP, et al Sporadic autism exomes reveal a highly interconnected protein network of de novo mutations. Nature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Nature Publishing Group, a division of Macmillan Publishers Limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>All Rights Reserved.; 2012 5 10;485(7397):246–50. 10.1038/nature10989 <?supplied-pmid 22495309?>22495309 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref011"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>11 NealeBM, KouY, LiuL, Ma’ayanA, SamochaKE, SaboA, et al Patterns and rates of exonic de novo mutations in autism spectrum disorders. Nature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Nature Publishing Group, a division of Macmillan Publishers Limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>All Rights Reserved.; 2012 5 10;485(7397):242–5. 10.1038/nature11011 <?supplied-pmid 22495311?>22495311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref012"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>12 SandersSJ, MurthaMT, GuptaAR, MurdochJD, RaubesonMJ, WillseyAJ, et al De novo mutations revealed by whole-exome sequencing are strongly associated with autism. Nature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Nature Publishing Group, a division of Macmillan Publishers Limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>All Rights Reserved.; 2012 5 10;485(7397):237–41. 10.1038/nature10945 <?supplied-pmid 22495306?>22495306 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref013"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>13 IossifovI, RonemusM, LevyD, WangZ, HakkerI, RosenbaumJ, et al De novo gene disruptions in children on the autistic spectrum. Neuron. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Elsevier; 2012 4 26;74(2):285–99. 10.1016/j.neuron.2012.04.009 <?supplied-pmid 22542183?>22542183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref014"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>14 MichaelsonJJ, ShiY, GujralM, ZhengH, MalhotraD, JinX, et al Whole-genome sequencing in autism identifies hot spots for de novo germline mutation. Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Elsevier; 2012 12 21;151(7):1431–42. 10.1016/j.cell.2012.11.019 <?supplied-pmid 23260136?>23260136 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref015"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>15 De RubeisS, HeX, GoldbergAP, PoultneyCS, SamochaK, ErcumentCicek A, et al Synaptic, transcriptional and chromatin genes disrupted in autism. Nature. 2014 10 29;515(7526):209–15. 10.1038/nature13772 <?supplied-pmid 25363760?>25363760 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref016"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>16 BuxbaumJD, DalyMJ, DevlinB, LehnerT, RoederK, StateMW. The autism sequencing consortium: large-scale, high-throughput sequencing in autism spectrum disorders. Neuron. 2012 12 20;76(6):1052–6. 10.1016/j.neuron.2012.12.008 <?supplied-pmid 23259942?>23259942 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref017"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>17 SarachanaT, HuVW. Genome-wide identification of transcriptional targets of RORA reveals direct regulation of multiple genes associated with autism spectrum disorder. Mol Autism. 2013 1;4(1):14 10.1186/2040-2392-4-14 <?supplied-pmid 23697635?>23697635 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref018"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>18 Fares-TaieL, GerberS, ChassaingN, Clayton-SmithJ, HaneinS, SilvaE, et al ALDH1A3 mutations cause recessive anophthalmia and microphthalmia. Am J Hum Genet. 2013 2 7;92(2):265–70. 10.1016/j.ajhg.2012.12.003 <?supplied-pmid 23312594?>23312594 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref019"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>19 RoosL, FangM, DaliC, JensenH, ChristoffersenN, WuB, et al A homozygous mutation in a consanguineous family consolidates the role of ALDH1A3 in autosomal recessive microphthalmia. Clin Genet. 2013 9 11; </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref020"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>20 YahyaviM, AbouzeidH, GawdatG, de Preux A-S, XiaoT, BardakjianT, et al ALDH1A3 loss of function causes bilateral anophthalmia/microphthalmia and hypoplasia of the optic nerve and optic chiasm. Hum Mol Genet. 2013 8 15;22(16):3250–8. 10.1093/hmg/ddt179 <?supplied-pmid 23591992?>23591992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref021"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>21 AldahmeshMA, KhanAO, HijaziH, AlkurayaFS. Mutations in ALDH1A3 cause microphthalmia. Clin Genet. 2013 8;84(2):128–31. 10.1111/cge.12184 <?supplied-pmid 23646827?>23646827 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref022"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>22 MoryA, RuizFX, DaganE, YakovtsevaEA, KurolapA, ParésX, et al A missense mutation in ALDH1A3 causes isolated microphthalmia/anophthalmia in nine individuals from an inbred Muslim kindred. Eur J Hum Genet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Macmillan Publishers Limited; 2014 3;22(3):419–22. 10.1038/ejhg.2013.157 <?supplied-pmid 23881059?>23881059 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref023"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>23 SemerciCN, KalayE, YıldırımC, DinçerT, OlmezA, ToramanB, et al Novel splice-site and missense mutations in the ALDH1A3 gene underlying autosomal recessive anophthalmia/microphthalmia. Br J Ophthalmol. 2014 6;98(6):832–40. 10.1136/bjophthalmol-2013-304058 <?supplied-pmid 24568872?>24568872 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref024"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>24 ChatziC, BradeT, DuesterG. Retinoic acid functions as a key GABAergic differentiation signal in the basal ganglia. PLoS Biol. 2011 4;9(4):e1000609 10.1371/journal.pbio.1000609 <?supplied-pmid 21532733?>21532733 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref025"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>25 BenesFM, BerrettaS. GABAergic interneurons: implications for understanding schizophrenia and bipolar disorder. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2001 7;25(1):1–27. <?supplied-pmid 11377916?>11377916 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref026"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>26 RubensteinJLR, MerzenichMM. Model of autism: increased ratio of excitation/inhibition in key neural systems. Genes Brain Behav. 2003 10;2(5):255–67. <?supplied-pmid 14606691?>14606691 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref027"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>27 MolotkovaN, MolotkovA, DuesterG. Role of retinoic acid during forebrain development begins late when Raldh3 generates retinoic acid in the ventral subventricular zone. Dev Biol. 2007 3 15;303(2):601–10. <?supplied-pmid 17207476?>17207476 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref028"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>28 BredenkampN, NowellCS, BlackburnCC. Regeneration of the aged thymus by a single transcription factor. Development. 2014 4;141(8):1627–37. 10.1242/dev.103614 <?supplied-pmid 24715454?>24715454 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref029"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>29 ChenL, XiaoS, ManleyNR. Foxn1 is required to maintain the postnatal thymic microenvironment in a dosage-sensitive manner. Blood. 2009 1 15;113(3):567–74. 10.1182/blood-2008-05-156265 <?supplied-pmid 18978204?>18978204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref030"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>30 NowellCS, BredenkampN, TetélinS, JinX, TischnerC, VaidyaH, et al Foxn1 regulates lineage progression in cortical and medullary thymic epithelial cells but is dispensable for medullary sublineage divergence. PLoS Genet. 2011 11;7(11):e1002348 10.1371/journal.pgen.1002348 <?supplied-pmid 22072979?>22072979 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref031"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>31 SuckowMA, RosenED, WolterWR, SailesV, JeffreyR, TenniswoodM. Prevention of human PC-346C prostate cancer growth in mice by a xenogeneic tissue vaccine. Cancer Immunol Immunother. 2007 8;56(8):1275–83. <?supplied-pmid 17242926?>17242926 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref032"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>32 OnoreC, CareagaM, AshwoodP. The role of immune dysfunction in the pathophysiology of autism. Brain Behav Immun. 2012 3;26(3):383–92. 10.1016/j.bbi.2011.08.007 <?supplied-pmid 21906670?>21906670 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref033"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>33 AmorosiS, D’ArmientoM, CalcagnoG, RussoI, AdrianiM, ChristianoAM, et al FOXN1 homozygous mutation associated with anencephaly and severe neural tube defect in human athymic Nude/SCID fetus. Clin Genet. 2008 4;73(4):380–4. 10.1111/j.1399-0004.2008.00977.x <?supplied-pmid 18339010?>18339010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref034"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>34 RhinnM, DolléP. Retinoic acid signalling during development. Development. 2012 3;139(5):843–58. 10.1242/dev.065938 <?supplied-pmid 22318625?>22318625 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref035"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>35 LiaoW-L, WangH-F, TsaiH-C, ChambonP, WagnerM, KakizukaA, et al Retinoid signaling competence and RARbeta-mediated gene regulation in the developing mammalian telencephalon. Dev Dyn. 2005 4;232(4):887–900. <?supplied-pmid 15736225?>15736225 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref036"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>36 LiaoW-L, LiuF-C. RARbeta isoform-specific regulation of DARPP-32 gene expression: an ectopic expression study in the developing rat telencephalon. Eur J Neurosci. 2005 6;21(12):3262–8. <?supplied-pmid 16026464?>16026464 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref037"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>37 BonhommeD, PalletV, DominguezG, ServantL, HenkousN, LafenêtreP, et al Retinoic acid modulates intrahippocampal levels of corticosterone in middle-aged mice: consequences on hippocampal plasticity and contextual memory. Front Aging Neurosci. 2014 1;6:6 10.3389/fnagi.2014.00006 <?supplied-pmid 24570662?>24570662 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref038"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>38 MizeeMR, WooldrikD, LakemanKAM, van het HofB, DrexhageJAR, GeertsD, et al Retinoic acid induces blood-brain barrier development. J Neurosci. 2013 1 23;33(4):1660–71. 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1338-12.2013 <?supplied-pmid 23345238?>23345238 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref039"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>39 LordC, RisiS, LambrechtL, CookEH, LeventhalBL, DiLavorePC, et al The autism diagnostic observation schedule-generic: a standard measure of social and communication deficits associated with the spectrum of autism. J Autism Dev Disord. 2000 6;30(3):205–23. <?supplied-pmid 11055457?>11055457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref040"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>40 LordC, RutterM, Le CouteurA. Autism Diagnostic Interview-Revised: a revised version of a diagnostic interview for caregivers of individuals with possible pervasive developmental disorders. J Autism Dev Disord. 1994 10;24(5):659–85. <?supplied-pmid 7814313?>7814313 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref041"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>41 LiH, DurbinR. Fast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transform. Bioinformatics. 2009 7 15;25(14):1754–60. 10.1093/bioinformatics/btp324 <?supplied-pmid 19451168?>19451168 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref042"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>42 LiH, HandsakerB, WysokerA, FennellT, RuanJ, HomerN, et al The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools. Bioinformatics. 2009 8 15;25(16):2078–9. 10.1093/bioinformatics/btp352 <?supplied-pmid 19505943?>19505943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref043"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>43 McKennaA, HannaM, BanksE, SivachenkoA, CibulskisK, KernytskyA, et al The Genome Analysis Toolkit: a MapReduce framework for analyzing next-generation DNA sequencing data. Genome Res. 2010 9;20(9):1297–303. 10.1101/gr.107524.110 <?supplied-pmid 20644199?>20644199 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref044"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>44 DePristoMA, BanksE, PoplinR, GarimellaK V, MaguireJR, HartlC, et al A framework for variation discovery and genotyping using next-generation DNA sequencing data. Nat Genet. 2011 5;43(5):491–8. 10.1038/ng.806 <?supplied-pmid 21478889?>21478889 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref045"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>45 CingolaniP, PlattsA, WangLL, CoonM, NguyenT, WangL, et al A program for annotating and predicting the effects of single nucleotide polymorphisms, SnpEff: SNPs in the genome of Drosophila melanogaster strain w1118; iso-2; iso-3. Fly (Austin). 2012;6(2):80–92.22728672 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref046"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>46 PereaCS, PaterninaAC, GomezY, LattigMC. Negative affectivity moderated by BDNF and stress response. J Affect Disord. 2012 2;136(3):767–74. 10.1016/j.jad.2011.09.043 <?supplied-pmid 22044630?>22044630 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref047"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>47 BuskeOJ, ManickarajA, MitalS, RayPN, BrudnoM. Identification of deleterious synonymous variants in human genomes. Bioinformatics. 2013 8 1;29(15):1843–50. 10.1093/bioinformatics/btt308 <?supplied-pmid 23736532?>23736532 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref048"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>48 SmithPJ, ZhangC, WangJ, ChewSL, ZhangMQ, KrainerAR. An increased specificity score matrix for the prediction of SF2/ASF-specific exonic splicing enhancers. Hum Mol Genet. 2006 8 15;15(16):2490–508. <?supplied-pmid 16825284?>16825284 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref049"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>49 CartegniL, WangJ, ZhuZ, ZhangMQ, KrainerAR. ESEfinder: A web resource to identify exonic splicing enhancers. Nucleic Acids Res. 2003 7 1;31(13):3568–71. <?supplied-pmid 12824367?>12824367 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref050"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>50 KumarP, HenikoffS, NgPC. Predicting the effects of coding non-synonymous variants on protein function using the SIFT algorithm. Nat Protoc. 2009 1;4(7):1073–81. 10.1038/nprot.2009.86 <?supplied-pmid 19561590?>19561590 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref051"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>51 AdzhubeiIA, SchmidtS, PeshkinL, RamenskyVE, GerasimovaA, BorkP, et al A method and server for predicting damaging missense mutations. Nat Methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Nature Publishing Group; 2010 4;7(4):248–9. 10.1038/nmeth0410-248 <?supplied-pmid 20354512?>20354512 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref052"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>52 ChoiY, SimsGE, MurphyS, MillerJR, ChanAP. Predicting the functional effect of amino acid substitutions and indels. PLoS One. 2012 1;7(10):e46688 10.1371/journal.pone.0046688 <?supplied-pmid 23056405?>23056405 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref053"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>53 BalmerJE, BlomhoffR. Gene expression regulation by retinoic acid. J Lipid Res. 2002 11;43(11):1773–808. <?supplied-pmid 12401878?>12401878 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref054"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>54 BalmerJE, BlomhoffR. A robust characterization of retinoic acid response elements based on a comparison of sites in three species. J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol. 2005 9;96(5):347–54. <?supplied-pmid 16081280?>16081280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref055"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>55 HertzGZ, StormoGD. Identifying DNA and protein patterns with statistically significant alignments of multiple sequences. Bioinformatics. 1999;15(7–8):563–77. <?supplied-pmid 10487864?>10487864 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref056"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>56 WagnerE, LuoT, DrägerUC. Retinoic acid synthesis in the postnatal mouse brain marks distinct developmental stages and functional systems. Cereb Cortex. 2002 12;12(12):1244–53. <?supplied-pmid 12427676?>12427676 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref057"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>57 HaiderNB, MollemaN, GauleM, YuanY, SachsAJ, NystuenAM, et al Nr2e3-directed transcriptional regulation of genes involved in photoreceptor development and cell-type specific phototransduction. Exp Eye Res. 2009 9;89(3):365–72. 10.1016/j.exer.2009.04.006 <?supplied-pmid 19379737?>19379737 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref058"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>58 HaiderNB, NaggertJK, NishinaPM. Excess cone cell proliferation due to lack of a functional NR2E3 causes retinal dysplasia and degeneration in rd7/rd7 mice. Hum Mol Genet. 2001 8 1;10(16):1619–26. <?supplied-pmid 11487564?>11487564 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref059"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>59 IossifovI, O’RoakBJ, SandersSJ, RonemusM, KrummN, LevyD, et al The contribution of de novo coding mutations to autism spectrum disorder. Nature. 2014 10 29;515(7526):216–21. 10.1038/nature13908 <?supplied-pmid 25363768?>25363768 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref060"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>60 MahonyS, MazzoniEO, McCuineS, YoungRA, WichterleH, GiffordDK. Ligand-dependent dynamics of retinoic acid receptor binding during early neurogenesis. Genome Biol. 2011 1;12(1):R2 10.1186/gb-2011-12-1-r2 <?supplied-pmid 21232103?>21232103 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref061"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>61 SiegenthalerJA, AshiqueAM, ZarbalisK, PattersonKP, HechtJH, KaneMA, et al Retinoic acid from the meninges regulates cortical neuron generation. Cell. 2009 10 30;139(3):597–609. 10.1016/j.cell.2009.10.004 <?supplied-pmid 19879845?>19879845 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref062"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>62 AmorosiS, ViglianoI, Del GiudiceE, PanicoL, MaruottiGM, FuscoA, et al Brain alteration in a Nude/SCID fetus carrying FOXN1 homozygous mutation. J Neurol Sci. 2010 11 15;298(1–2):121–3. 10.1016/j.jns.2010.08.066 <?supplied-pmid 20864124?>20864124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref063"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>63 RoussoDL, GaberZB, WellikD, MorriseyEE, NovitchBG. Coordinated actions of the forkhead protein Foxp1 and Hox proteins in the columnar organization of spinal motor neurons. Neuron. 2008 7 31;59(2):226–40. 10.1016/j.neuron.2008.06.025 <?supplied-pmid 18667151?>18667151 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref064"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>64 LaiCS, FisherSE, HurstJA, Vargha-KhademF, MonacoAP. A forkhead-domain gene is mutated in a severe speech and language disorder. Nature. 2001 10 4;413(6855):519–23. <?supplied-pmid 11586359?>11586359 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0135927.ref065"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>65 Moreno-RamosOA, LattigMC, González BarriosAF. Modeling of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis-mediated interaction between the serotonin regulation pathway and the stress response using a Boolean approximation: a novel study of depression. Theor Biol Med Model. 2013 1;10:59 10.1186/1742-4682-10-59 <?supplied-pmid 24093582?>24093582 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
