<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4654818</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1989</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-015-1989-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Transcriptomic profiling of host-parasite interactions in the microsporidian Trachipleistophora hominis </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>Andrew K.</given-names></name><address><email>a.k.watson@ncl.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Tom A.</given-names></name><address><email>tom.williams2@ncl.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Bryony A. P.</given-names></name><address><email>B.A.P.Williams@exeter.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>Karen A.</given-names></name><address><email>K.A.Moore@exeter.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hirt</surname><given-names>Robert P.</given-names></name><address><email>robert.hirt@ncl.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Embley</surname><given-names>T. Martin</given-names></name><address><email>martin.embley@ncl.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Institute for Cell and Molecular Biosciences, Newcastle University, Newcastle upon Tyne, NE2 4HH UK </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Biosciences, College of Life and Environmental Sciences, University of Exeter, Devon, UK </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>983</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Watson et al. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Trachipleistophora hominis was isolated from an HIV/AIDS patient and is a member of a highly successful group of obligate intracellular parasites. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Here we have investigated the evolution of the parasite and the interplay between host and parasite gene expression using transcriptomics of T. hominis-infected rabbit kidney cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>T. hominis has about 30 % more genes than small-genome microsporidians. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Highly expressed genes include those involved in growth, replication, defence against oxidative stress, and a large fraction of uncharacterised genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Chaperones are also highly expressed and may buffer the deleterious effects of the large number of non-synonymous mutations observed in essential T. hominis genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Host expression suggests a general cellular shutdown upon infection, but ATP, amino sugar and nucleotide sugar production appear enhanced, potentially providing the parasite with substrates it cannot make itself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Expression divergence of duplicated genes, including transporters used to acquire host metabolites, demonstrates ongoing functional diversification during microsporidian evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>We identified overlapping transcription at more than 100 loci in the sparse T. hominis genome, demonstrating that this feature is not caused by genome compaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The detection of additional transposons of insect origin strongly suggests that the natural host for T. hominis is an insect. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Our results reveal that the evolution of contemporary microsporidian genomes is highly dynamic and innovative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Moreover, highly expressed T. hominis genes of unknown function include a cohort that are shared among all microsporidians, indicating that some strongly conserved features of the biology of these enormously successful parasites remain uncharacterised. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12864-015-1989-z) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Host-parasite interactions</kwd><kwd>Microsporidia</kwd><kwd>Gene expression</kwd><kwd>Transcriptomics</kwd><kwd>Evolution</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Microsporidia are a group of obligate endoparasitic fungi [1, 2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>They are highly successful pathogens that are able to infect a diverse range of hosts, including species of economic significance, and can also cause disease in immunocompromised humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Microsporidia were first characterised as the causative agent of pébrine, the disease that contributed to the fall of the European silkworm industry in the 19th century [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>More recently, the microsporidian Nosema ceranae has been implicated in colony collapse disorder affecting bee populations world wide [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Documented cases of human microsporidiosis have risen sharply since the onset of the AIDS pandemic, and 14 species of Microsporidia have been described as causing opportunistic infection in immunocompromised humans [5], including Trachipleistophora hominis, the focus of the present study, which was isolated from an HIV/AIDS patient in 1996 [6, 7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Microsporidians are obligate intracellular pathogens, and their genomes have become highly reduced in terms of protein coding content as a result [8–11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Recent analyses suggest that most gene loss occurred in the common ancestor of microsporidians, leaving a small core of genes that carry out functions that are essential for all eukaryotic cells, embellished by an additional conserved core of genes common to most microsporidians [10, 11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>This novel, Microsporidia-specific core includes genes for a variety of different proteins, many of unknown function, and some of which form expanded gene families in contrast to the general trend of microsporidian genome reduction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Included among the latter are genes for nucleotide transport proteins (NTT) that are present in multiple copies on all but one of the microsporidian genomes sequenced to date [8, 10, 11, 12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In the absence of ATP production capabilities these proteins, which are among the very few proteins to be functionally characterised for microsporidians, play a key role in the import of ATP and other nucleotides from infected host cells, without which the parasite cannot complete its life cycle [13, 14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The observation that other proteins, including additional transporters, show similar patterns of retention and expansion [11] suggests that they may also play conserved roles in the microsporidian intracellular lifestyle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The advent of RNA-Seq provides the opportunity to investigate microsporidian gene expression during the intracellular stages of infection on a genome-wide scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Gene expression analyses of Encephalitozoon cuniculi [15], Nematocida parisii [16], Spraguea lophii [17], and Nosema bombycis [18] have already shown that this technology can be used for microsporidians, highlighting the potential of this technique for studying a group of parasites that cannot be genetically manipulated in the laboratory. They have also highlighted strategies by which host cells respond to microsporidian infections, including defence responses mediated by ubiquitation [19], the production of antimicrobial peptides [18], and the perturbation of metabolic pathways [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In the present study we have used RNA sequencing to investigate gene expression by Trachipleistophora hominis infecting a mammalian (rabbit kidney) cell line, and we compare host expression under infected and non-infected conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Our expression analyses confirm the large coding capacity – 3153 genes – of T. hominis refuting a recent suggestion [20] that the large number of genes initially reported might be an artefact of genome annotation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Although our analyses did identify some false gene models, this was balanced by the identification of genes previously missed during the genome annotation, including some that expand the metabolic capacities of T. hominis in interesting ways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Parasite gene expression was extremely heterogeneous with 5 % of genes accounting for over 50 % of total gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>This includes a strong signature for genes involved in replication and growth, but also a cohort of highly expressed genes that are conserved among microsporidians but are of so far unknown function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>We detect strong evidence of functional divergence within gene families including transport proteins that, counter to the prevailing mode of gene loss, have undergone expansion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>These data support classical ideas of functional divergence after gene duplication with the most conserved paralogue being the most highly expressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Analysis of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and their allele frequency spectrum strongly suggest that T. hominis, like other unikaryotic Microsporidia [16, 21, 22], is diploid and raises the possibility of a sexual stage in its lifecycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The detection of active insect-derived transposons suggests that T. hominis – which is an opportunistic pathogen of humans – has an insect host in nature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Transcriptional profiling of the host is consistent with a generalised cellular shutdown upon infection with T. hominis, with the upregulation of host pathways for ATP production, amino sugar and nucleotide sugar metabolism: these pathways potentially complement gaps in parasite biosynthesis predicted by in silico analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Results and discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Reproducibility of host-parasite transcriptomics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>T. hominis is an obligate intracellular parasite grown in laboratory co-culture within rabbit kidney (RK) cells [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>We harvested total RNA from three biological replicates of infected RK cells seven days post inoculation, at which point ~60 % of RK cells in each flask were infected with T. hominis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>At this stage the community of T. hominis cells was a mixture of different life cycle stages including thick walled spores and pre-spore stages (sporonts and sporoblasts) as well as the intracellular sporoplasm (newly geminated parasite inside the host cell) and replicative or meront stage (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Although we used a bead beating method similar to one previously shown [10] to lyse T. hominis spores in our RNA extractions, the resistant nature of the spore-forming stages of the parasite lifecycle may make lysis less efficient, which could lead to an enrichment of transcripts from replicative stages in the total RNA pool; possible implications of this bias are discussed in more detail below. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>In parallel we also isolated total RNA from three biological replicates of uninfected RK cells, in order to compare patterns of host expression under the two conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>We obtained 2.3 × 107 sequencing reads from the infected cells, with 7.7 % of these reads mapping to the T. hominis genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The reproducibility between biological and technical replicates was very high, both for pairwise comparisons of the expression of individual genes between replicates and the overall distribution of expression levels across all transcripts (Fig. 2 (T. hominis); Additional file 1: Figure S1 (rabbit)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that our analysis of the T. hominis and host transcriptomes was highly reproducible; thus, the potential biological implications can be explored in a meaningful way.Fig. 1A schematic lifecycle of Trachipleistophora hominis with phase contrast images of representative intracellular stages. In stage 1, the T. hominis spore injects its contents into the host cell via a proteinaceous polar tube. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>This uninucleate sporoplasm is the earliest stage of infection of the host cell [119]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Following injection, the parasite – now called the meront - grows and begins to proliferate in the host cell (merogony, the second stage of the parasite lifecycle) [6, 7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>It is unknown how many cycles of proliferation meronts undergo in the host cell before stage three of the lifecycle begins, the transition from meronts to spore-forming sporonts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>In Microsporidia this is marked by the deposition of an electron-dense material on the surface of the parasite, and in T. hominis may represent the timing of formation of the parasitophorous vacuole, an additional membrane surrounding the parasite within the host cell [6, 7, 119]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>During spore formation (sporogony) the microsporidian spore wall is assembled, and T. hominis undergoes a further round of proliferation [6, 7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Eventually mature spores form inside the host cell (stage 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>These spores may either eject their polar tubes from within their host cell and infect neighbouring cells, or else be released from the cell in stage 6 of the parasite lifecycle, allowing dissemination of the infection to new cells or new organisms [119]Fig. 2Robustness and reproducibility of transcriptomic analysis for T. hominis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>In this figure, each sample is an individual biological replicate of T. hominis infected RK-13 cells from which total RNA was purified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>All of these samples were sequenced on two different lanes of the Illumina sequencing chip to provide technical replication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The strong positive correlation of transcript abundance, as measured by Fragments Per Kilobase per Million mapped reads (FPKM) between replicates in all cases is indicative of high levels of reproducibility between both biological and technical replicates. a Pairwise comparisons of T. hominis transcript log10 FPKM values between biological replicates (samples) and technical replicates (sequencing lanes); density plots generated in cummeRbund [109] represent the distribution of log10 FPKM values for that replicate. b FPKM density plot overlay comparing the distribution of T. hominis transcript FPKM values between individual biological replicates (samples) from a single sequencing lane. c FPKM density plot overlay comparing the distribution of T. hominis transcript FPKM values between technical replicates (different sequencing lanes) from a single sample (Sample 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The levels of reproducibility between replicates for the expression of host genes were equally very high, this data is summarised in Additional file 1, Figure S1 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>T. hominis has more genes than small-genome microsporidians </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The T. hominis genome (~11.6 Mbp haploid genome size) was initially reported to contain 3266 predicted open reading frames (ORFs), which is over 1000 more genes than the ~2000 open reading frames predicted for the best studied small genome (~2.3–2.5 Mbp haploid genome size) species of Encephalitozoon [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>It has been suggested that the predicted number of T. hominis genes may be an overestimate due to over-prediction of small genes [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Indeed, some ORFs (113) appear to be unique to T. hominis, with no homologues identified in its closest sequenced relative Vavraia culicis [23, 24], or any other microsporidian [10, 11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Additionally, T. hominis encodes a large family of novel leucine rich repeat proteins (117 ORFs) that includes many fragmented ORFs, indicative of ongoing pseudogenisation [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>It is therefore possible that the estimated coding capacity of T. hominis includes some false positives, particularly given the highly derived nature of most microsporidian gene sequences [10, 20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>We obtained evidence for the expression of 2958 (90 %) of the 3266 annotated T. hominis ORFs (Additional file 2: Table S1), including 85 % of the leucine-rich repeat genes, suggesting that most are genuine ORFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>However, we detected expression for fewer (73 %: 83 of 113) T. hominis-specific genes, consistent with the idea that some of these are false-positive calls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Balancing this reduction in the predicted gene count based on transcription, we obtained evidence for an additional 292 transcripts that were not predicted as ORFs in the original genome project. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>One hundred and fifty-five (80 %) of these transcripts are located within regions of ambiguous genomic sequence or near the ends of scaffolds; the difficulty in annotating these regions may explain their absence from the original T. hominis genome annotation [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Ninety seven of the 292 novel transcripts lacked an ORF suggesting that they might be T. hominis noncoding RNAs, although they did not give significant matches to the noncoding RNAs already included in the Rfam database [25, 26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>They also appear to be missing from other microsporidian genomes as searched using BLASTN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Despite this, one of the transcripts, XLOC_000764, was in the upper 95th percentile of overall expression levels; that is, its expression level was higher than 95 % of detected transcripts, suggesting that it plays a physiologically relevant role. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The remaining 195 transcripts are predicted to contain ORFs of which 89 had significant hits to the nr protein database at a BLASTX E-value cutoff of 0.01. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The two most highly expressed of the 89 shared significant similarity to partial ORFs (VCUG_01670 and VCUG_016701) annotated in the Vavraia culicis genome [24], the closest sequenced relative of T. hominis [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The putative T. hominis protein is 564 amino acids in length and contains a series of 12 tandem glycine-asparagine repeats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>A search using HHPred [27, 28] suggests that these are similar to a class of repeats present in over 30 % of Plasmodium falciparum genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Their function in Plasmodium falciparum is unknown, but it has been suggested that they may interact with host proteins [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this idea, the T. hominis gene has an N-terminal signal peptide [30], suggesting that it might be secreted or localised on the surface of the parasite. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Twenty-five of the newly identified transcripts show significant similarity to genes outside of the microsporidian clade, including several broadly-distributed eukaryotic genes previously thought to be absent from the genome of T. hominis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>These include exportin, a component of the nuclear export machinery, as well as homologues of deoxyhypusine hydroxylase [31], the Rea1 AAA-ATPase [32], and the 60S ribosomal protein L29 [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>We found transcript evidence for three new transport proteins, including an amino acid/auxin permease of the AAAP family, a putative cation transporting P-type ATPase, and a member of the DMT superfamily of drug and metabolite transporters that includes a UAA transporter family domain (pfam:08449) associated with UDP-N-acetyl-glucosamine:UMP antiporter activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Published data demonstrate that microsporidians can import purine nucleotides using nucleotide transport (NTT) proteins [11, 13, 14] but as yet there is no evidence for the transport of pyrimidine nucleotides by these transporters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Based upon in silico predictions it appears that microsporidians cannot make pyrimidines de novo so there is a transport gap that needs to be filled [11, 13, 14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>UDP-N-acetylglucosamine is the direct monomeric precursor for chitin synthesis, an integral component of the microsporidian spore wall [34], but it is also biosynthesised by the mammalian host cell in which it plays roles as a co-enzyme, signalling molecule, and precursor for glycosylation [35, 36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The pyrimidine UDP is liberated from UDP-N-acetylglucosamine during chitin polymerisation by chitin synthase and during glycosylation, so as well as providing chitin precursors this novel transporter could potentially provide the starting substrate to make pyrimidines needed for T. hominis DNA and RNA biosynthesis (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Genes within the chitin biosynthesis pathway in T. hominis are generally expressed at similar levels in our analysis (600–900 fpkm), however expression of the terminal components of the pathway, chitinase and chitin synthases, were much lower (20–30fpkm) (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>These observations suggest that in the proliferative stages of the microsporidian lifecycle, UDP-N-acetylglucosamine is either being used primarily for UDP-liberating glycosylation reactions, or being accumulated for chitin production during sporogony. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>We also obtained transcriptomic evidence for a previously unannotated T. hominis homologue of a UDP-N-acetylglucosamine pyrophosphorylase, an enzyme also encoded on the genomes of Vavraia, Encephalitozoon, Anncalia, Edhazardia and Vittaforma. This enzyme catalyses the conversion of UTP and N-acetyl-alpha-D-glucosamine 1-phosphate to UDP-N-acetylglucosamine and diphosphate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>This means that, in addition to potential acquisition of UDP-N-acetylglucosamine from the host, T. hominis encodes a complete pathway for its biosynthesis (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The potential importance of this enzyme for spore wall formation in Microsporidia makes it a potential target for therapeutic intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Thus, recent studies have shown that UDP-N-acetylglucosamine pyrophosphorylase is essential for the survival of Trypanosoma brucei in its bloodform lifecycle stage [37], and chemicals that can selectively inhibit the Trypanosoma brucei UDP-N-acetyl pyrophosphorylase have been identified [38].Fig. 3A potential route for pyrimidine and chitin precursor acquisition by T. hominis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>De novo routes for pyrimidine biosynthesis are not present in Microsporidia, but scavenger pathways allow conversion between different pyrimidines [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The import of only one pyrimidine from the host cell would, in principle, enable the biosynthesis of other pyrimidines via scavenger pathways, because interconversions between bases are possible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>NupG-like transport proteins have been hypothesised to transport nucleosides and thus act as a source of pyrimidine precursors [16], but the specificity and subcellular localisation of these genes are currently unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>A putative UDP-N-acetyl glucosamine transporter provides another potential source of pyrimidines in T. hominis and V. culicis: the imported metabolite can feed into chitin synthase and glycosylation pathways, both of which may liberate free pyrimidineFig. 4A drive for UDP-N-acetylglucosamine biosynthesis with low-level spore wall production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The heatmap shows the levels of expression of genes within the chitin biosynthesis pathway, with blue representing low levels of expression and red as high. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>GFA1, glutamine-fructose-6-phosphate aminotransferase; GNA1, glucosamine-6-phosphate N-acetyltransferase 1; UGP1, UDP-N-acetylglucosamine pyrophosphorylase; PCM, phosphoacetylglucosamine mutase; CHS, chitin synthase; CDA, chitin deacetylase; ACS, acetyl-CoA synthetase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The significantly lower expression levels of chitin synthases compared to the rest of the pathway leading to UDP-N-acetylglucosamine production suggest that chitin synthesis is not very active in this sample, consistent with the low expression of other enzymes involved in spore wall formation </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, the transcript data from our experiments appear to be very reproducible for both host and T. hominis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The data validate the majority of gene models originally predicted from the T. hominis genome sequence and identify some previously missed genes, providing evidence for a total of 3153 transcribed genes and making the T. hominis gene complement one of the largest identified for microsporidians so far [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Overlapping transcription in a gene-sparse microsporidian genome </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>We detected 140 T. hominis transcripts encoding more than one ORF, of which 113 overlap on the genome assembly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The remaining 27 do not overlap on the genome, but the intergenic region between them was spanned by RNA-Seq reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>This suggests that overlapping transcription occurs in T. hominis, as previously reported for the small genome species E. cuniculi and A. locustae, where a similar number of multi-ORF transcripts (144) was identified [39, 40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, our data suggests that overlapping transcription is not necessarily linked [40, 41] with genome compaction, because gene density in T. hominis is actually lower than for yeast [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>One possibility is that overlapping transcription provides a mechanism for co-regulating the expression of particular genes [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>If so, then this mode of regulation is poorly conserved over evolutionary time, because transcriptional overlap is conserved for only one gene pair across E. cuniculi, A. locustae, and T. hominis [40]: ribosomal protein L6 (THOM_0162) and RNA polymerase III transcription factor IIIC subunit 5 (THOM_0163), which overlap in the 3′ UTR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Low levels of splicing in T. hominis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>A total of 85 introns were predicted in T. hominis based upon the presence of conserved E. cuniculi intron motifs [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, we obtained transcriptomic evidence for the splicing of only a single gene – 40S ribosomal protein S23 – at this conserved intron motif (JUNC00000002 in Additional file 3: Table S2); this gene was spliced efficiently, with 93 % of detected transcripts being spliced, higher than the splicing efficiency detected for any spliced gene in the E. cuniculi transcriptome [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>This gene was also one of only two genes for which splicing was detected in transcripts from the microsporidian Spraguea lophii, and the intron has a similar length [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Splicing in general in Microsporidia appears to be inefficient for short introns [17], with splicing rates of less than 15 % identified for several E. cuniculi transcripts [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>This potentially explains our inability to detect splicing at the great majority of characterised intron motifs in the T. hominis transcriptome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>By contrast, we obtained evidence for 13 introns where RNA sequencing reads suggest a spliced exon boundary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>One of these novel junctions (JUNC00000048 in Additional file 3: Table S2) is found in the third most highly expressed transcript in our dataset, and its presence is supported by a greater number of reads than the originally predicted 40S ribosomal protein S23. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, the remaining new experimentally identified introns lack the classical intron motif previously described in E. cuniculi [43], and an alignment revealed no unique novel motif common to the group (Additional file 4: Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Highly expressed T. hominis genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The top 5 % (170 genes) of genes accounted for over half (58 %) of all detected transcription in T. hominis (Additional file 5: Figure S3). Fifty three percent of these highly transcribed ORFs belong to a core conserved set of microsporidian genes defined by Nakjang et al. [11] as those encoded by 9 of the analysed 11 sequenced microsporidian genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Of these highly expressed core genes 32 % encode rRNA or ribosomal proteins, and 31 % encode other essential elements of eukaryotic cell biology including cytoskeletal proteins, transcription and translation factors, cell division proteins (e.g., NudC), histones, and molecular chaprones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Similar functional gene groups (E.g. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Ribosome biogenesis and protein translation factors) were significantly enriched in highly expressed genes during proliferative growth of fission yeast (Schizosaccharomyces pombe) [44], suggesting the pattern of expression observed in T. hominis may reflect the signatures of its rapid growth and replication in the host cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The highly expressed core microsporidian genes also include a large number of microsporidian hypothetical proteins of unknown function (37 %). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>In fission yeast, groups of functionally related genes tend to be expressed at similar levels [44], suggesting that if the same pattern applies to Microsporidia these uncharacterised proteins may also play important and as yet unknown roles in core parasite biology and proliferation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The inclusion of molecular chaperones of the HSP40/DNAJ and HSP70 families and protein disulfide isomerase among highly expressed core T. hominis genes is intriguing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>High expression of HSP70 has been identified in several different microsporidian clades [41], suggesting it is a common feature of the group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Chaperones have been identified as important virulence factors in bacterial and eukaryotic pathogens, including intracellular bacteria [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Published work has demonstrated that intracellular bacteria and bacteria cultured under conditions that introduce a population bottleneck often over-express chaperones to maintain functionality under an increased mutational load [46–50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The high levels of chaperonin expression in several microsporidians, which also experience bottlenecks during transmission and show high rates of sequence evolution [6, 10], suggest that these intracellular eukaryotes are behaving in the same way [41]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Replication and biosynthesis are energy-requiring processes and hence T. hominis must either make or acquire ATP and GTP during proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Genome analyses suggest that T. hominis has a complete glycolytic pathway [10] and we detected expression of all of the relevant enzymes in the transcriptome, but only glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase was in the top 5 % of transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The most highly expressed glycolytic enzymes are PBA, GAPDH and PGK, with GAPDH and PGK respectively providing NAD+ reduction and ATP synthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that T. hominis is potentially making some of the ATP it needs, but the cell stage where this occurs is not resolved by our data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Quantitative immuno-localisation of PGK protein, the first ATP-generating step of glycolysis, suggests that the protein is mainly, but not exclusively, inside T. hominis spores rather than vegetative cells [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>It has also been previously suggested that glycolysis occurs mainly in the spores of another microsporidian, Paranosema grylli [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, transcripts for the most abundant protein identified in spores, Polar Tube Protein 3, were detected at only modest levels in the RNA sequencing data, with an average of 18.1 FPKM ±12.3 SD (within the 30th percentile for expressed genes in the dataset). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Indeed, no genes known to be associated with spore wall formation (spore wall proteins, polar tube proteins and chitin synthases) were found in the top 5 % of highly transcribed genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>One possibility is that the lysis procedure used to extract total RNA may not lyse T. hominis sporonts, sporoblasts and spores very efficiently; if so, then the extracted RNA would be enriched for transcripts from replicative stages of the parasite lifecycle despite the mixed infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, these more quiescent stages of the parasite lifecycle might show an overall reduction in levels of gene expression, as observed in the nonreplicating stages of the fission yeast cell cycle [44], so that they will naturally be represented at lower levels in the total RNA pool Conversely, high levels of expression were observed for a number of genes involved in DNA replication and proliferation, consistent with an enrichment of transcripts from the actively proliferating stages of the parasite, and suggesting that some ATP production by glycolysis may occur in these stages of the parasite lifecycle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Few metabolic enzymes appeared in the top 5 % of expressed transcripts, consistent with genomic predictions that T. hominis must import many of the substrates it needs for biosynthesis directly from the infected host cell [10, 11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>One highly expressed enzyme is nucleotide diphosphate kinase (YNK) [52], which was also highly abundant in proteomic analyses of highly purified spores [10], YNK is predicted to play a key role in supporting T. hominis intracellular proliferation by converting nucleotides or nucleoside diphosphates to their triphosphate forms, the precursors for both RNA and DNA synthesis and sources of cellular energy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>High levels of expression were also observed for dUTPase, another enzyme predicted to be involved in nucleotide biosynthesis [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The most highly transcribed metabolic enzyme was an asparagine synthetase A (asnA, THOM_2136, InterPro ID: IPR004618). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Among Microsporidia, coding sequences for this protein are found on the genomes of T. hominis, V. culicis, Enterocytozoon bienieusi, N. ceranae and Nosema pernyi, and were likely acquired by lateral gene transfer from bacteria [10, 11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Among eukaryotes, AsnA is almost exclusively found in parasites [10] including Typanosoma brucei and Leishmania donovani, where it is essential for survival [54, 55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>In bacteria, AsnA is responsible for the reversible transamination of aspartate to asparagine in the presence of ATP and ammonia. Leishmania and Trypanosoma AsnA, the only characterised eukaryotic homologues, have a broader specificity, and are able to use glutamine as a nitrogen donor to generate glutamate [55, 56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>One possibility is that microsporidian AsnA may play important roles in interconversion between essential amino acids, including glutamine, an important precursor to both chitin biosynthesis for spore wall formation and glutathione (GSH) biosynthesis required in parasite detoxification systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>This ORF contains an aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase (class II) domain (InterPro ID: IPR004364) suggesting that it may also function to add asparagine to its cognate tRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Its specificity to parasitic eukaryotes, coupled with its functional importance, high expression level, and the availability of an AsnA crystal structure make the protein a promising potential drug target [55]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Maintaining supplies of glutamine is important for the generation of GSH, a detoxifying molecule required for the prevention of damage by reactive oxygen species [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The T. hominis detoxification system also includes thioredoxin reductases, peroxidases, glutathione reductases and superoxide dismutase [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>While all identified components of this pathway are expressed in T. hominis, the highest expressed in our dataset, and only component in the 95th percentile of overall expression levels, was iron/manganese superoxide dismutase (SOD), which reduces and detoxifies superoxide molecules (O2−) [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The largest biological source of superoxide species is as a by-product in the production of ATP by oxidative phosphorylation, which T. hominis does not carry out but which we show is upregulated in host cells during infection by T. hominis (see below). T. hominis SOD may protect against oxidative stress generated by the host cell as it supports both its own survival and parasite proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Previous work [58–60] has indicated that oxidative stress in the host cell is elevated during infection; therefore, a robust detoxification system is likely to be important for parasite survival, as observed in some bacterial infections [61]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>One metabolic pathway known to be essential and that has been functionally characterised in Microsporidia is iron-sulphur cluster biogenesis [62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Iron-sulphur clusters are required for the activity of key proteins needed for microsporidian replication, including DNA polymerase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The metabolic pathway for the biogenesis of iron-sulphur clusters is compartmentalised, starting in the microsporidian mitosome (remnant mitochondrion) and ending in the cytosol [62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>This allows us to examine the variability in levels of transcript abundance between different compartments in a single linked pathway that should be required throughout the parasite lifecycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The only highly expressed gene in the pathway (in the top 5 % of expressed transcripts) was Dre2, a cytosolic component of iron-sulphur cluster biogenesis [63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, Dre2 also plays a role in inhibiting free radical-induced apoptosis [63]; given that other detoxifying enzymes are also highly expressed in T. hominis, it may be this function of Dre2 that drives its high expression level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this idea, the other components of iron-sulphur cluster biogenesis are expressed at significantly lower and similar levels, suggesting that genes in the same pathway may be generally expressed at similar levels in T. hominis, as observed in fission yeast [44]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Surface-located transport proteins are predicted by genome analyses to be fundamental for supporting the replication of T. hominis and other microsporidians by importing substrates from infected host cells [3, 10, 11, 13, 14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The expression of T. hominis proteins related to known transporters, or annotated as potential transporters, is very heterogeneous within structural types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Only three predicted transport proteins are found in the top 5 % (&gt;2210 FKPM) of expressed genes and these do not include any of the T. hominis nucleotide (NTT1-4) transporters for which functional data is available [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The most highly expressed of these – NTT4 – appears in the 92nd percentile of expression levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>NTT4 is one of four paralogous nucleotide transporters that are expressed on the surface of replicating parasites [14], where they function to transport purine nucleotides including ATP and GTP, for energy and/or biosynthesis [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Of the three highly expressed transporters, the first and third in terms of expression are hypothetical transporters of unknown specificity while the second is a putative inorganic phosphate transport protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Given the potential importance of the NTT transporters it seems possible that these more highly transcribed transporters also support important, albeit currently uncharacterised, cellular functions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The most highly transcribed of the three membrane proteins (THOM_1886) appears to be specific to T. hominis and its closest sequenced relative, V. culicis, as determined by sensitive PSI-BLAST [64] and HMMER [65] based searches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The THOM_1886 protein is predicted to include 7 transmembrane domains and was annotated as a putative transport protein [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Its expression level is more than 1500x that of the average transporter in our study (22209 FPKM ± 5483 SD) suggesting that, in addition to the conserved common core of microsporidian genes, lineage-specific innovation is also important for parasite biology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Levels of T. hominis gene expression are correlated with gene history and conservation among microsporidians </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Comparative analyses of the genome of T. hominis with other microsporidian genomes have demonstrated that genome evolution has been a dynamic process, in which the loss of ancestral gene families has been partially offset by the gain of new microsporidia-specific genes [8–11, 16, 17, 66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>In this broader evolutionary context, T. hominis genes can be classified into three major groups: core eukaryotic genes – that is, core microsporidian genes defined in Nakjang at al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>[11] that were also found in most or all eukaryotes; ancestral microsporidian innovations, or core microsporidian genes that evolved in the common ancestor of all microsporidia (and thus are not identified in other eukaryotes); and recent innovations (for example THOM_1886) that are only found in T. hominis, or that are shared between T. hominis and its close relative V. culicis. To evaluate the relationship between evolutionary conservation and expression level in T. hominis, we compared the expression levels of the genes in these three classes using a linear mixed-effects model (Fig. 5).Fig. 5Levels of T. hominis gene expression are correlated with gene history and conservation among microsporidians. T. hominis genes can be classified according to the period in evolutionary history when they first arose: core eukaryotic genes, shared with most or all other eukaryotes and encoding fundamental features of eukaryotic cell biology; ancestral microsporidian innovations, found only in T. hominis and other microsporidians; and recent innovations, genes found only in T. hominis and its close relative V. culicis. This density plot shows the distribution of expression levels (as log10FPKM) for T. hominis genes in each of these three categories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Mixed-effects modelling indicates that core eukaryotic genes and ancestral microsporidian innovations are expressed at significantly higher levels than recently-evolved T. hominis genes (P = 0), but that there is no significant difference in expression patterns between the former two classes (P = 0.166); the recently-evolved genes also show a much broader range of expression than the older gene classes, perhaps reflecting greater variation in functional constraints within this group </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Our analysis indicated that core eukaryotic genes and ancestral microsporidian innovations were both expressed at significantly higher levels than recently-evolved genes specific to the T. hominis/V. culicis lineage (P = 0), but that there was no significant difference in expression levels between the two more highly-expressed classes (P = 0.166). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The consistently high expression levels for core eukaryotic genes are not, in themselves, particularly surprising: this category includes genes involved in basic cellular processes such as DNA replication and repair, mitochondrial iron-sulphur cluster assembly, intracellular trafficking and in some metabolic pathways such as glycolysis and the pentose phosphate pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>However, the equally high level of expression observed for ancestral microsporidian innovations is interesting because it implies that genes which first evolved in the common ancestor of microsporidia, and which were then conserved across the group, are as important to microsporidians – by the measure of transcript abundance - as genes encoding the fundamental eukaryotic cellular componentry. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>By contrast, genes specific to the T. hominis/V. culicis lineage are expressed at significantly lower levels than other genes in the parasite (P = 0); we focused on genes shared between these close relatives to minimise the impact of false ORF calls on our analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Most of these genes are expressed (735 out of 862, or 85 %), but not necessarily at high levels; as can be seen from Fig. 5, this class of recently evolved genes displays a broad range of expression levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The more heterogeneous distribution of expression levels for recently evolved genes is consistent with a recently proposed model [67] for the gradual emergence of proto-genes from previously non-coding sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Under this model, some new, fortuitously expressed genes acquire important functions and are maintained by selection, while others do not and will eventually be lost to drift and pseudogenisation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>It is possible that this process of genomic innovation underpins recently evolved host-parasite interactions for these two species, both of which are thought to infect insects as their natural hosts [10, 68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this hypothesis, the T. hominis/V. culicis-specific families are enriched for signal peptides (P = 1.2 x 10−10, Fisher’s exact test) [11], suggesting that the proteins in these families may be localised to the parasite cell surface, part of the infective polar tube, or secreted into the host cell. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Expression divergence in expanded T. hominis gene families </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the general trend of reductive evolution among microsporidians, a number of T. hominis gene families have expanded through gene duplication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Gene duplication is important in the evolution of gene family function, because duplication events can relax selective constraints allowing the functions of one or both paralogues to change [69, 70]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Consistent with a role for duplication and functional divergence in microsporidian evolution, Nakjang et al. [11] and Heinz et al. [14] found evidence of sequence divergence at conserved amino acid residues following microsporidia-specific duplications in the Hsp90 chaperone, Ste24 metalloprotease, NTT nucleotide transporter, ZiP zinc ion permease, SulP sulphate permease and NupG nucleoside transporter families. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Intriguingly, members of these expanded gene families tend to be expressed at above-average levels in T. hominis (P = 3 x 10−4, linear mixed-effects model). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Figure 6 summarises expression levels for the functionally characterised T. hominis nucleotide (NTT) transport proteins [14] and T. hominis members of the microsporidian gene families investigated by Nakjang et al. [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>The variation in expression level is clearly correlated with the evolutionary history of the gene family: in all of these cases, the most highly conserved family member, in terms of conservation of critical residues or branch length in gene family trees [11, 14], is also the most highly expressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>These data are consistent with a model of functional divergence whereby one conserved, highly-expressed paralogue continues to carry out the ancestral function, while other duplicates experiencing reduced selective constraint can gain new functions [71–73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Any new functions, which could include stage-specific expression, different cellular location or substrate affinity or specificity, will need to be identified through experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>For example, proteomics data already suggest that NTT4, the most highly expressed member of the gene family (Fig. 6), is the main NTT transporter located within the T. hominis spore [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>In Encephalitozoon cuniculi the NTT transporter family has undergone an independent expansion [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>This expansion was followed by divergence in both sequence and localisation, with one family member (EcNTT3) localised to the mitosome while the other three are located on the surface of replicating parasites [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The correlation between sequence divergence and transcript abundance we observe in T. hominis is maintained in E. cuniculi [15], with divergent family members (EcNTT3 and EcNTT4) expressed at lower levels (mean FPKM 139 for EcNTT3, 96 for EcNTT4) than the more highly conserved family members (EcNTT1 and EcNTT2 – 402 and 977 FPKM respectively).Fig. 6Members of gene families with evidence of sequence divergence also show variable levels of gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Expression levels (log10 FPKM) for the members of gene families in which functional divergence was previously detected at the sequence level [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>In each case, the most highly expressed paralogue is also the most highly conserved based on single gene trees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>H, the heterogeneity index calculated for each gene family, is also shown (see Materials and Methods). a Nucleotide transport proteins (NTTs). b NupG-related nucleoside permeases. c Zinc iron permase (Zip) family. d Sulphate permease (SulP) family. e Ste24 metalloprotease family. f Heat shock protein 90 (HSP90) family </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>To evaluate variation in expression among microsporidian gene duplicates more systematically, we analysed expression for all duplicate families identified by Nakjang et al. [11] containing at least two paralogues in T. hominis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>We calculated the standard deviation of FPKM values within each family, and normalised by the per-family mean (see Materials and Methods) (Additional file 6: Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Expanded T. hominis families were then ranked by this metric to identify the families showing the most extreme expression divergence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Plotting these scores revealed an inflection point in the distribution of the metric, above which we considered within-family expression to be highly heterogeneous (Additional file 7: Figure S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The most heterogeneous family identified by this approach included a family of retrotransposon-encoded reverse transcriptases; some family members had no detectable expression, suggesting ongoing pseudogenization as might be expected for transposable elements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The group of T. hominis families showing the greatest expression divergence also includes the hexokinase gene family, whose paralogues in the microsporidian N. parisii have been suggested to manipulate host metabolism following secretion into the host cell [16]. T. hominis encodes four hexokinases of which two include predicted signal peptides [11], consistent with the hypothesis that they may be secreted into the host cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>One of the remaining copies (XLOC_001491) is the most highly expressed member of the family, again consistent with the idea that the most highly conserved member of a duplicated family continues to perform the ancestral function. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Parallel horizontal transfers of transposons implicate an insect host in the lifecycle of T. hominis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>T. hominis is one of several microsporidians that retain elements of the RNA interference machinery [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The core components of this machinery, Dicer and Argonaute, are both expressed by T. hominis during infection but are not in the top 5 % of expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The RNAi machinery is hypothesised to play a role in defence against transposon activity in Microsporidia [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this hypothesis, we obtained evidence for the expression of 58 of the 110 annotated transposons in the T. hominis genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Combined with evidence for transcription of transposons in Edhazardia aedis [41], these data suggest that active transposons pose an ongoing threat to genome integrity in microsporidians more generally. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Although T. hominis is an opportunistic parasite of immunocompromised humans, its natural host remains unknown. T. hominis can proliferate within artificially infected mosquitoes under experimental conditions, but these infections have not been observed in nature [74]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>One of the novel transcripts identified in this study showed similarity to a PiggyBac transposase [75]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>This transcript maps to a previously unannotated portion of the T. hominis genome, and is therefore distinct from the PiggyBac element reported in the original genome annotation [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The best BLAST hits to the novel PiggyBac element include transposable elements from insects but not other Microsporidia, raising the possibility that T. hominis gained the element in a recent horizontal transfer that occurred after the divergence of T. hominis from its close relative V. culicis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>A PiggyBac element identified as recently acquired in bats has been demonstrated to retain activity when inserted into both human and yeast cells, highlighting the capacity of this particular family of transposons for inter-species transfer [76]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis of the novel T. hominis element strongly suggests that it was recently acquired from an insect, and probably a member of the Hymenoptera (ants, bees and wasps; Fig. 7 and Additional file 8: Figure S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The T. hominis sequence forms a strongly supported clade with PiggyBac elements from bees (Bombus impatiens and Megachile rotundata) and the ant Harpegnathos saltator (Fig. 7, Clade B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, this transfer appears to have occurred independently of the previously identified PiggyBac acquisition from insects in T. hominis, which branches in a separate insect clade with maximal posterior support (1.0 posterior probability; Fig. 7, Clade A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>In both cases, the most closely related sequence is from Jerdon’s jumping ant (Harpegnathos saltator), although the posterior support for this relationship is variable (0.99 in Clade A, and 0.77 in Clade B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The phylogeny of the two separate T. hominis PiggyBac elements provides consistent support for the hypothesis that T. hominis infections of humans may represent opportunistic zoonoses from a natural hymenopteran host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we also identified a separate novel horizontal transfer from insects into the microsporidian Nosema apis, a honeybee parasite [77], providing further support for the horizontal transfer of host-derived transposable elements into Microsporidia (Fig. 7, Clade C) [78–80].Fig. 7Phylogenetic analysis of PiggyBac transposons suggests a natural insect host for T. hominis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>A Bayesian phylogeny of T. hominis PiggyBac transposases inferred under the C20 model [117] in PhyloBayes [118]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Support values are Bayesian posterior probabilities, and branch lengths are proportional to the expected number of substitutions per site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>The tree topology supports two recent, independent transfers of PiggyBac elements from hymenopteran insects into T. hominis. In both cases, the ant Harpegnathos saltator is recovered as the closest relative of the T. hominis sequence, although with variable posterior support. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>We also identify a transfer from insects into the microsporidian Nosema apis, a honeybee parasite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Clade A – An insect clade including two T. hominis PiggyBac elements, as identified in [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Clade B – A distinct clade of insect elements, including the newly discovered T. hominis PiggyBac element. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Clade C – Clade including Nosema apis and insect PiggyBac elements </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Patterns of single nucleotide polymorphism reveal that T. hominis is diploid </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Microsporidia replicate inside their host cell, and can only exist outside it as a resistant and infectious spore [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>This would be a barrier to sex between two different parasite cells, which would require multiple independent infections of a single host cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, limited evidence for a sexual reproduction cycle has been identified in several microsporidians [81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The early morphological characterisation of Ambylospora identified a meiosis-like stage of division including karyogamy, the fusion of two haploid nuclei to form a single diploid nucleus [82]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Recent studies of the Nosema/Vairimorpha lineage have also provided some evidence for sex and recombination [81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Although proliferating T. hominis cells can contain multiple nuclei, nuclear fusion has never been observed [6, 7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Our RNA-Seq data presents an opportunity to investigate the ploidy of T. hominis and to test whether sexual reproduction may be possible. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>We identified 7596 variant sites (polymorphisms) in the T. hominis transcriptome, with a total of 7654 possible variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>These included 7120 single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs), 314 insertions and 220 deletions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Plotting the allele frequency spectrum of the variations reveals a clear peak at a frequency of 0.5 (50 % reference genome allele, 50 % alternative allele) (Fig. 8a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Our T. hominis populations are likely to be clonal, both because their obligate intracellular lifecycle results in a population bottleneck in each generation, and also because our experimental isolate has been passaged repeatedly in cell culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>In addition, population-level variation would not be expected to give rise to a peak at 0.5, unless two distinct populations had somehow been maintained in a 50:50 ratio. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Given these considerations, the simplest interpretation of the observed allele frequency spectrum is that the genome of T. hominis is diploid in at least some stage of its lifecycle and that, at least in the majority of cases, both alleles are expressed. T. hominis is unikaryotic – that is, it has one nucleus per spore – and so our results are consistent with analyses suggesting that other unikaryotic microsporidians are also diploid [16, 21, 22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>The diploidy of T. hominis and other unikaryotic Microsporidia supports the notion that diplokaryotic Microsporidia are likely to be tetraploid [83], containing two diploid nuclei as observed in the diplomonad Giardia lamblia [84]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The diploidy of T. hominis raises the possibility that it occasionally has sex, although the density of SNPs in our dataset was not sufficiently high to evaluate the possibility of recombination or linkage disequilibrium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Although the T. hominis spore is unikaryotic, the intracellular stages of its lifecycle divide by a combination of binary division and plasmotomy, the division of a single cell producing multinucleate progeny [6, 7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>This raises the possibility that meiosis could still be triggered in multinuclear intracellular stages of the parasite lifecycle.Fig. 8The allele frequency spectrum of SNPs in expressed T. hominis transcripts suggests a diploid phase to the parasite lifecycle. a The allele frequency spectrum (reference and alternative alleles) for T. hominis SNPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>The clear peak at an allele frequency of 0.5 suggests that T. hominis is diploid. b Allele frequency spectra with synonymous and non-synonymous SNPs plotted separately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The distributions are similar, providing no evidence for reduced expression of non-synonymous alleles </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>A total of 5496 SNPs were identified within annotated T. hominis ORFs, with 2175 non-synonymous and 2933 synonymous changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>SNPs were identified in 1551 ORFs in total, with 1071 of these ORFs including non-synonymous changes, leading to possible protein variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Although we cannot exclude the possibility that some non-synonymous mutations might be beneficial, we expect the majority to be deleterious, particularly given the frequent genetic bottlenecks experienced by our artificially maintained experimental population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>388 changes were more severe in nature, either including frameshifts or alterations to start and stop codons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>In principle, the deleterious effects of these mutations could be suppressed in a diploid organism by preferential expression of the reference allele. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>However, the peak at 0.5 is still observed in the frequency spectrum for non-synonymous alleles (Fig. 8b), implying that synonymous, non-synonymous and reference alleles are all expressed at similar levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>34 % of all SNPs occurred in “core” microsporidian genes – those shared among at least 9 of 11 sequenced Microsporidia and predicted to play an important role in the parasite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>The expression of these variants is perhaps surprising due to their potential impact on protein function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>However, it is important to remember that this study examines a single population of T. hominis, and that many of these SNPs may be en route to elimination by negative selection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Another possibility is that the high levels of expression we observed for key molecular chaperones may help to suppress the phenotypic effect of these deleterious mutations, as has previously been reported for intracellular bacteria [46]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Response of the RK-13 cell line to infection with T. hominis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Recent studies have begun to shed light on the mechanisms by which microsporidians exploit their hosts [13, 14, 85, 86], but we still know almost nothing about the host response to infection at the molecular level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>We quantified host gene expression to identify genes and pathways that were differentially expressed in RK-13 cells during infection with T. hominis compared to uninfected cells (Additional file 9: Table S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>These analyses provide a first snapshot of the impact of T. hominis infection on the host cell transcriptome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>We identified 1734 transcripts that showed significant changes in expression in the RK-13 cell line during infection with T. hominis (Additional file 10: Table S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>KEGG categories [87] were assigned to these transcripts using the KOBAS annotation pipeline [88]; nine KEGG categories were enriched for differentially expressed transcripts (Additional file 11: Table S6); that is, these categories contained more genes whose expression levels changed in response to infection than would be expected by chance, allowing us to explore the general effects of infection on the host cell. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Our analysis suggests that the host experiences a generalised cellular shutdown in response to T. hominis infection, with the down-regulation of the great majority of genes involved in the KEGG pathways for the cell cycle, meiosis, DNA replication, and ribosome biogenesis (Additional file 12: Figure S6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Several other host cell pathways contained a mixture of both up-regulated and down-regulated genes relative to the uninfected control; these pathways are clearly disrupted during T. hominis infection, but the overall effect on the host is difficult to predict from changes in transcript abundance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>The pathways included those involved in focal adhesion, extracellular matrix-receptor interactions, renal cell carcinoma, oxidative phosphorylation, and pyrimidine biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Although these patterns are complex and difficult to interpret, they were also consistent across our three biological replicates, and therefore represent reproducible perturbations of host cell pathways. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>The only host cell pathways in which the majority of changes were up-regulations relative to the control were amino sugar and nucleotide sugar metabolism (Additional file 12: Figure S6), potentially leading to increased production of nucleotide sugars by the host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Similar changes to silkworm metabolism were observed during infection with Nosema bombycis, suggesting that this may be common feature of microsporidian infection [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Candidate nucleotide sugar importers have been identified in T. hominis [10] and other Microsporidia, consistent with the idea that microsporidians might manipulate host metabolism to increase production of required substrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>One potential mechanism for the manipulation of host metabolism that has already been proposed is the secretion of hexokinase into the host cell [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>As in mammalian cancer cells [89], Microsporidia infected RK-13 cells had a modulated hexokinase expression profile compared to healthy cells, possibly to the benefit of the intracellular parasite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>The two hexokinase isozymes (HKI and HKII) with the highest affinity for glucose in mammals [90] were significantly differentially expressed in the host during infection, with an increase in HKI and a decrease in HKII. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>HKI is believed to have a primarily catabolic function, driving glycolysis and ATP production [90] – an essential molecule for T. hominis growth and replication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>These changes in gene expression draw striking parallels to other host-parasite systems, where complex changes in host energy metabolism [91, 92] and pyrimidine biosynthesis [93] are associated with infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>A number of pathway regulators were also differentially expressed in RK-13 cells during T. hominis infection, providing insights into the potential mechanisms that might underpin some of the observed changes in transcript levels of metabolic genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>We observed significant up-regulation of host 5′-AMP-activated protein kinase catalytic subunit alpha-2 (PRKAA2) and peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma co-activator 1-alpha (PPARGC1A) during T. hominis infection, both of which are reported to promote energy metabolism and mitochondrial biogenesis [94, 95]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>PRKAA2 is additionally implicated in shutting down ATP-consuming pathways including cell proliferation [94], consistent with our observation of decreased expression of genes in this pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Linked to the above inference of increased host ATP production coupled with reduced consumption, we also observed a significant decrease in the expression of host pyruvate dehydrogenase lipoamide kinase isozyme 4 (PDK4) during infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>This kinase represses metabolism through the phosphorylation and inactivation of pyruvate dehydrogenase, the enzyme that converts pyruvate to acetyl-coA, thereby linking glycolysis and the citric acid cycle [96]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Decreased expression of PDK4 would lead to increased activity of pyruvate dehydrogenase, promoting citric acid cycle-based metabolism and, under normal oxygen conditions, increased ATP production [96, 97]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>The increased glucose required to support the elevated metabolic demand might be acquired by increased import since the glucose transporter GLUT9 [98] is highly up-regulated transporter during infection by T. hominis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Changes in expression in the ubiquitination pathway have been recently implicated in the immune response of C. elegans to N. parisii infection [19], raising the possibility that the ubiquitin system may be part of a common host response to microsporidian infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Although the expression levels of several host ubiquitination genes were altered upon T. hominis infection, the pathway as a whole was not enriched in differentially expressed genes in our analysis, suggesting that this does not represent a major component of the host cell response to infection by T. hominis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Our transcriptomics data was highly reproducible for parasite and host, and confirmed that T. hominis, with ~3150 genes, has one of the largest coding capacities among microsporidians [10, 20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Although our data rejected some of the shortest predicted gene models, this was compensated by the identification of genes that were previously missed by the genome annotation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Some of these, including transporters that may acquire pyrimidines and enzymes that function in chitin biosynthesis, may plug what were previously considered to be gaps in the metabolic capacity of the parasite. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Gene expression for the parasite was highly biased towards growth and replication, consistent with published microscopic data [6, 7] demonstrating rapid parasite proliferation after infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Intriguingly, a proportion of the highly expressed transcripts are encoded by conserved microsporidian genes of unknown function, suggesting there is much still to discover about the core biology of these highly successful parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Expression within expanded gene families, including key transport proteins, was highly variable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>In most cases the most highly conserved members of gene families were also the most highly expressed, consistent with evolutionary models in which duplication can free individual paralogues to diversify in function while preserving the ancestral function in the conserved copy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>The expression of genes confined to T. hominis and its close relative Vavraia culicus was also more heterogeneous than was observed for core genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Some of this lineage-specific innovation was highly expressed – in particular a membrane protein of unknown function - but much of it was not. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>This class of genes is also enriched for signal peptides [11] suggesting that some may be secreted or exposed on the surface of the parasite where they can interact with host targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Our results contribute to a growing body of work supporting the idea that the evolution of contemporary microsporidian genomes is highly dynamic and innovative, and that while the initial transition to intracellular parasitism catalysed a drastic reduction in genome size and coding capacity shared by all microsporidians, important lineage-specific differences continue to evolve. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Our data strongly suggest that T. hominis is diploid and demonstrate the presence of a large number of non-synonymous SNPs, many of which are expected to be deleterious, that are equally distributed between alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Many of these SNPs may eventually be eliminated by negative selection but, as already suggested for intracellular bacteria [46–49], the high levels of chaperonin expression that we observed may also suppress the phenotypic effects of these deleterious mutations in Microsporidia [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>It has been demonstrated that artificially infected mosquitoes can support the replication of T. hominis [74], but the natural host of this opportunistic pathogen of humans is currently unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>We identified transcripts from a novel PiggyBac element that, together with a previously identified element of insect origin [10], strongly suggest that the natural host for T. hominis belongs to the hymenoptera. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>The response of eukaryotic host cells to microsporidian infection is only just beginning to be investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Our data, which were highly reproducible between biological and technical replicates, suggest a generalized cellular shutdown by infected cells compared to uninfected rabbit kidney cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Several other host pathways displayed a reproducible mixture of up-regulated and down-regulated genes relative to the uninfected control; these pathways are clearly disrupted but the overall effect on the host and its relationship to the activities of the parasite are difficult to predict based solely upon these data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>We did observe an up-regulation of host amino and nucleotide sugar metabolism: this has also been reported for silkworms infected with Nosema bombycis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>These are among substrates predicted to be imported by microsporidians to plug gaps in their reduced metabolism [11, 16], so it is possible that these changes are to the benefit of the parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>There is some evidence that host ATP production might be increased in combination with reduced host energy consumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>This could potentially benefit a parasite that is dependent on the host cell for most of its ATP and purine nucleotides for DNA and RNA biosynthesis [14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Culture of T. hominis infected RK-13 cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>T. hominis was grown in co-culture with RK-13 cells [6] grown in minimal essential medium (MEM) containing 10 % heat inactivated foetal calf serum and antibiotics (Penicillin/Streptomycin (0.1 mg/ml), Ampicillin B (1 μg/ml) and Kanamycin sulphate (0.1 mg/ml)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>A single 175 cm2 flask of RK-13 cells was grown to confluence (defined as a continuous cell monolayer) and split into three separate flasks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>These flasks were raised in parallel until confluence, when each was again split into two centrifuge tubes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Samples were spun at 400 g and trypsin removed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>The cells were resuspended in 5 ml MEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Spores were freshly harvested from 20 flasks of T. hominis-infected RK-13 cells and resuspended in 400 μl PBS (~2.3x107 spores/ml). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>100 μl of this spore suspension was added to one of the two centrifuge tubes containing RK-13 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Cells were incubated for 10 min before seeding to a new 175 cm2 flask containing 40 ml MEM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Flasks of uninfected and T. hominis infected RK-13 cells were raised in parallel for 7 days post inoculation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>During this time they were trypsinised and split twice in order to boost levels of infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Two days after the final trypsinisation the cells were harvested in RNAprotect cell reagent and immediately frozen at −20 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>At this stage, approximately 60 % of cells in flasks to which spores had been added exhibited signs of infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Preparation of RNA for sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Cells suspended in RNAprotect (Qiagen) were thawed and pelleted by centrifugation at 400 g. Total RNA was purified from each sample using the standard TRIzol (Invitrogen) extraction protocol, with the addition of a bead beating step (three times for 20 s at 5 m/s, with 10 mins incubation on ice between beating). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>An additional cleanup step using the GeneJet RNA purification kit (Thermo Scientific) was added to remove residual organic solvents from the purified total RNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>The RNA integrity and concentration was assessed using the Agilent RNA 6000 Nano Kit on the Agilent 2100 BioAnalyser. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>PolyA RNA was isolated from 5 μg of purified total RNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Libraries were prepared using the ScriptSeq™ v2 RNA-Seq Library Preparation Kit (Epicentre Biotechnologies) and sequenced on the Illumina HiSeq 2500 in Rapid-Run mode, producing non-strand-specific 100 bp single-ended reads, with each library sequenced on two different lanes of the sequencer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Processing and analysis of RNA-seq data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>The Trachipleistophora hominis genome and annotation [10] were obtained from NCBI, whilst the genome and annotation of the European rabbit (Oryctolagus cuniculus: GCA_000003625.1) were obtained from the Ensembl database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Bowtie2 [99] was used to separately index the genomes of T. hominis and O. cuniculus. Quality control on the raw RNA sequencing reads was performed using FastQC [100] and Illumina sequencing adapters and low quality bases were trimmed using fastq-mcf [101]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>In order to quantify the expression levels of T. hominis transcripts, and for novel transcript discovery, TopHat2 [102] was used to map quality-filtered reads from each infected sample to the T. hominis genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Transcripts were assembled using cufflinks [103]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>The final transcriptome assembly was generated using cuffmerge [103]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>All sequence data associated with this project has been deposited at NCBI under the BioProject ID PRJNA 278775. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Linear mixed-effect models were used to assess differential expression between different categories of genes within the parasite transcriptome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>We fit functional category as a fixed effect, with random effects for gene, technical replicate, and biological replicate, and used log FPKM values as the response variable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Transcripts that mapped to unannotated regions of the T. hominis genome were screened for potential ORFs by using BLASTx to search against the nr database with an E-value threshold of 0.01. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>SNPs were identified using SamTools mpileup and bcftools [104]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Vcfutils.pl varFilter was applied under default settings to remove low quality SNPs, with the addition of a minimum read depth of 10 [105]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>An additional filter was applied to remove bases with low mapping quality scores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Values of 20, 40, 60 and 80 were tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>In all cases application of the filter reduced non-peak (0.5 frequency) signals while retaining the overall distribution of the allele frequency spectrum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>We used a 60 as a balance between stringently filtering out low quality mapping and retaining data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>The location of SNPs relative to annotated T. hominis genes and the impact of SNPs on protein-coding sequences were assessed using SNPeff [106] and processed using SNPsift [107]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>To maximise the data available for intron detection, reads from all samples including T. hominis-infected cells were pooled and mapped onto the T. hominis reference genome using TopHat2 [102]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>The intron junctions identified from this mapping were manually filtered so as to retain only those junctions covered by more than one read. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Overlapping junctions were merged. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>For quantification of O. cuniculus transcripts, TopHat2 [102] was used to map reads from all samples from one lane of the sequencer to the O. cuniculus genome, and transcripts were assembled and quantified using cufflinks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>The abundance of transcripts in the three flasks of uninfected RK-13 cells was compared to that in the three flasks of T. hominis infected RK-13 cells using cuffdiff [108]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>All RNA sequencing results were analysed in R using the cummeRbund package [109]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>KEGG pathway [87] assignment for significantly differentially expressed genes and pathway enrichment analysis was carried out using KOBAS 2.0 [88]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis of PiggyBac elements </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>We BLASTed T. hominis PiggyBac elements THOM_1159, THOM_1429 and the additional family member newly identified in our transcriptome against the nr database, retrieving the top 100 significant hits with an E-value of less than 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Duplicate hits were manually removed before sequences were aligned using M-Coffee [110], combining the results of alignments using Muscle [111], Mafft [112], ProbCons [113], PCMA [114], and Fsa [115]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Poorly-aligning regions were identified and removed using trimAl [116]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Our phylogeny was inferred using the C20 model [117] implemented in PhyloBayes 3.3 [118]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Assessing heterogeneous expression in duplicated gene families </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>The expanded gene families in T. hominis and other Microsporidia identified by Nakjang et al. [11] where T. hominis had at least two duplicate copies were investigated to compare the expression of individual genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>To identify the T. hominis gene families showing the greatest level of between-paralogue expression level divergence, we normalised the expression level of each gene by the average level of expression for the family to which it belonged, then took the standard deviation of these values for each family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>We then ranked families by this score to identify the families with the greatest within-family divergence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Microscopy of T. hominis infected RK-13 cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>For phase contrast microscopy cells were fixed in a 50 % methonal 50 % acetone solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>After washing in water slides were mounted in Mowiol containing p-Phenylenediamine (0.01 %) which was allowed to set overnight at room temperature. and mounted in the same way. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Microscopy was performed using the Zeiss Axio Imager II (Upright) in structured illumination (apotome) mode at the Newcastle University Bio-Imaging unit. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Ethical approval </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>T. hominis was maintained in the RK-13 cell line so no ethical approval was required for this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec id="Sec22"><title><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Availability of supporting data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>All sequence data associated with this project has been deposited at NCBI under the BioProject ID PRJNA 278775, and the Trachipleistophora hominis genome assembly (GCA_000316135.1) has been updated with the new gene models identified here. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></body><back><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec23"><title>Additional files</title><p><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2015_1989_MOESM1_ESM.tiff" id="MOESM1"><label>Additional file 1: Figure S1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Robustness and reproducibility of transcriptomic analysis for RK-13 cells during intracellular infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Pairwise comparison of log10 FPKM values in rabbit kidney cell transcript quantification, as outlined in Fig. 2a for parasite transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>In this case biological replicates of uninfected RK-13 cells (samples labelled RK) are compared to those for T. hominis infected RK-13 cells (samples labelled TH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>(TIFF 6369 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2015_1989_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx" id="MOESM2"><label>Additional file 2: Table S1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Expression levels of T. hominis transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>These include novel transcripts identified in this study (Locus tag labelled as “NA”). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Genes annotated in the T. hominis genome but not detected during this study are also included for reference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>In some cases multiple locus tags map to a single transcript, as discussed in the main text. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>(XLSX 486 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2015_1989_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx" id="MOESM3"><label>Additional file 3: Table S2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Predicted T. hominis intron junctions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>The genomic location and sequencing depth of all intron junctions identified in the T. hominis genome by TopHat (see Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>(XLSX 11 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2015_1989_MOESM4_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM4"><label>Additional file 4: Figure S2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Alignment of a selection of identified intron sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>An alignment of novel T. hominis intron sequences predicted from our transcriptome, suggesting no conserved intron motif. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>The alignment was generated using MUSCLE [111] and visualised using SeaView [120]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>(PDF 62 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2015_1989_MOESM5_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM5"><label>Additional file 5: Figure S3.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Overall expression profile of the T. hominis transcriptome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Distribution of ranked FPKM values for the T. hominis transcriptome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>The 95th percentile (2240 FPKM) is marked by a blue line and the mean expression value (705 FPKM) is marked by a red line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>(PDF 30 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2015_1989_MOESM6_ESM.xlsx" id="MOESM6"><label>Additional file 6: Table S3.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>Heterogeneity in expression of duplicated gene families. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>All duplicated gene families [11] containing at least two paralogues in T. hominis ranked according to their expression heterogeneity index (see Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>(XLSX 25 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2015_1989_MOESM7_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM7"><label>Additional file 7: Figure S4.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Heterogeneous expression in expanded microsporidian gene families. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Distribution of ranked heterogeneity index (see Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>The red line denotes the inflection point above which we considered gene families to show high levels of expression heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>(PDF 18 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2015_1989_MOESM8_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM8"><label>Additional file 8: Figure S5.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis of PiggyBac transposons suggests a natural insect host for T. hominis– full tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>An expanded version of the tree from Figure 4 including GI accessions for all included sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>The accession number of the newly identified T. hominis sequence (Clade B) is XLOC_002128. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>(PDF 22 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2015_1989_MOESM9_ESM.xlsx" id="MOESM9"><label>Additional file 9: Table S4.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Expression levels of RK-13 transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Where possible these were annotated with Ensembl gene names. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>For unannotated transcripts identified in this study Ensembl Gene IDs are labelled as “NA”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Genes annotated in the O. cuniculus genome with no detectable expression during this study are also included for reference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Due to overlapping genes and alternative splicing, some transcriptome gene IDs are associated with multiple Ensembl gene IDs and/or multiple Ensembl Protein IDs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>(XLSX 8052 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2015_1989_MOESM10_ESM.xlsx" id="MOESM10"><label>Additional file 10: Table S5.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>RK-13 transcripts identified as significantly differentially expressed during infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Genes identified by cuffdiff [108] as significantly differentially expressed in the RK-13 host cell during T. hominis infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Q-values are P-values that have been corrected for multiple testing using the false discovery rate method [108]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>(XLSX 345 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2015_1989_MOESM11_ESM.xlsx" id="MOESM11"><label>Additional file 11: Table S6.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Testing for enrichment of differentially expressed genes in KEGG pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Fischer’s exact test with Benjamini and Hochberg correction [121] for the enrichment of genes identified as significantly differentially expressed in KEGG pathways in the RK-13 cell line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>(XLSX 70 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2015_1989_MOESM12_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM12"><label>Additional file 12: Figure S6.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Host cell gene expression changes in KEGG pathways enriched for differentially expressed genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Genes highlighted in cyan are significantly up-regulated upon infection with T. hominis, genes in red are down-regulated, and the expression of genes in purple does not significantly change. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Genes were assigned to KEGG pathways [87] using the KOBAS annotation pipeline [88], and colours representing differential expression were assigned using the KEGG web server [122]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>(PDF 613 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></p></sec></app></app-group></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>FPKM</term><def><p>Fragments per kilobase of transcript per million mapped reads</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NTT</term><def><p>Nucleotide transport protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ORF</term><def><p>Open reading frame</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RK</term><def><p>Rabbit kidney</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SNP</term><def><p>Single nucleotide polymorphism</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UTR</term><def><p>Untranslated region</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>AKW, TAW, RPH, and TME designed the experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>AKW carried out the experiments and analysed the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>BAPW and KAM provided help and guidance with sample preparation and the transcriptomic analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>All authors contributed to the interpretation of the results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>AKW and TAW wrote the paper, with editing from RPH and TME. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>All authors have read and approved the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by a BBSRC studentship to A.K.W., a Marie Curie Intra-European postdoctoral fellowship to T.A.W., and the European Research Council Advanced Investigator Programme (ERC- 2010-AdG-268701) and the Wellcome Trust (grant number 045404) to T.M.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>K.A.M. was supported by a Wellcome Trust Institutional Strategic Support Award (WT097835MF) We thank M. E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Geggie and E. Kozhevnikova for assistance with cell culture and lab reagents, Dr. S. E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>Campbell for assistance in RNA purification and sample preparation, Dr. K. Moore and A. Farbos at the Exeter Sequencing Service for assistance in Illumina sequencing and library preparation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>Dr T. A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Booth for microscopy training and K. Sendra, A. Farbos, and Dr. S. E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>Heaps for helpful discussions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>We also thank the two anonymous reviewers for their insightful comments. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>Bibliography</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>1.HirtRPLogsdonJMHealyBDoreyMWDoolittleWFEmbleyTMMicrosporidia are related to Fungi: Evidence from the largest subunit of RNA polymerase II and other proteinsProc Natl Acad Sci1999965805<?supplied-pmid 9892676?>9892676 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>2.JamesTYPelinABonenLAhrendtSSainDCorradiNStajichJEShared signatures of parasitism and phylogenomics unite Cryptomycota and microsporidiaCurr Biol201323154853<?supplied-pmid 23932404?>23932404 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>3.VávraJLukešJMicrosporidia and “the art of living together”Adv Parasitol201382253319<?supplied-pmid 23548087?>23548087 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>4.VidauCDiogonMAufauvreJFontbonneRViguèsBBrunetJ-LTexierCBironDGBlotNEl AlaouiHBelzuncesLPDelbacFExposure to sublethal doses of fipronil and thiacloprid highly increases mortality of honeybees previously infected by Nosema ceranaePLoS One20116e21550<?supplied-pmid 21738706?>21738706 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>5.DidierESWeissLMMicrosporidiosis: not just in AIDS patientsCurr Opin Infect Dis2011244905<?supplied-pmid 21844802?>21844802 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>6.HollisterWSCanningEUWeidnerEFieldASKenchJMarriottDJDevelopment and ultrastructure of Trachipleistophora hominis n.g., n.sp. after in vitro isolation from an AIDS patient and inoculation into athymic miceParasitology1996112Pt 114354<?supplied-pmid 8587798?>8587798 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>7.FieldASMarriottDJMillikenSTBrewBJCanningEUKenchJGDarvenizaPHarknessJLMyositis associated with a newly described microsporidian, Trachipleistophora hominis, in a patient with AIDSJ Clin Microbiol199634280311<?supplied-pmid 8897186?>8897186 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>8.KatinkaMDDupratSCornillotEMéténierGThomaratFPrensierGBarbeVPeyretailladeEBrottierPWinckerPDelbacFEl AlaouiHPeyretPSaurinWGouyMWeissenbachJVivarèsCPGenome sequence and gene compaction of the eukaryote parasite Encephalitozoon cuniculiNature20014144503<?supplied-pmid 11719806?>11719806 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>9.CorradiNPombertJ-FFarinelliLDidierESKeelingPJThe complete sequence of the smallest known nuclear genome from the microsporidian Encephalitozoon intestinalisNat Commun2010177<?supplied-pmid 20865802?>20865802 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>10.HeinzEWilliamsTANakjangSNoëlCJSwanDCGoldbergAVHarrisSRWeinmaierTMarkertSBecherDBernhardtJDaganTHackerCLucocqJMSchwederTRatteiTHallNHirtRPEmbleyTMThe genome of the obligate intracellular parasite Trachipleistophora hominis: new insights into microsporidian genome dynamics and reductive evolutionPLoS Pathog20128e1002979<?supplied-pmid 23133373?>23133373 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>11.NakjangSWilliamsTAHeinzEWatsonAKFosterPGSendraKMHeapsSEHirtRPMartin EmbleyTReduction and expansion in microsporidian genome evolution: new insights from comparative genomicsGenome Biol Evol201352285303<?supplied-pmid 24259309?>24259309 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>12.HaagKLJamesTYPombertJ-FLarssonRSchaerTMMRefardtDEbertDEvolution of a morphological novelty occurred before genome compaction in a lineage of extreme parasitesProc Natl Acad Sci201411143154805<?supplied-pmid 25313038?>25313038 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>13.TsaousisADKunjiERSGoldbergAVLucocqJMHirtRPEmbleyTMA novel route for ATP acquisition by the remnant mitochondria of Encephalitozoon cuniculiNature20084535536<?supplied-pmid 18449191?>18449191 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>14.HeinzEHackerCDeanPMifsudJGoldbergAVWilliamsTANakjangSGregoryAHirtRPLucocqJMKunjiERSEmbleyTMPlasma Membrane-Located Purine Nucleotide Transport Proteins Are Key Components for Host Exploitation by Microsporidian Intracellular ParasitesPLoS Pathog201410e1004547<?supplied-pmid 25474405?>25474405 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>15.GrisdaleCJBowersLCDidierESFastNMTranscriptome analysis of the parasite Encephalitozoon cuniculi: an in-depth examination of pre-mRNA splicing in a reduced eukaryoteBMC Genomics201314207<?supplied-pmid 23537046?>23537046 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>16.CuomoCADesjardinsCABakowskiMAGoldbergJMaATBecnelJJDidierESFanLHeimanDILevinJZYoungSZengQTroemelERMicrosporidian genome analysis reveals evolutionary strategies for obligate intracellular growthGenome Res201222247888<?supplied-pmid 22813931?>22813931 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>17.CampbellSEWilliamsTAYousufASoanesDMPaszkiewiczKHWilliamsBAPThe genome of Spraguea lophii and the basis of host-microsporidian interactionsPLoS Genet20139e1003676<?supplied-pmid 23990793?>23990793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>18.MaZLiCPanGLiZHanBXuJLanXChenJYangDChenQSangQJiXLiTLongMZhouZGenome-wide transcriptional response of silkworm (Bombyx mori) to infection by the microsporidian Nosema bombycisPLoS One20138e84137<?supplied-pmid 24386341?>24386341 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>19.BakowskiMADesjardinsCASmelkinsonMGDunbarTALopez-MoyadoIFRifkinSACuomo CATroemel ER: Ubiquitin-Mediated Response to Microsporidia and Virus Infection in C. elegans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>PLoS Pathog201410e1004200 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>20.Peyretaillade E, Boucher D, Parisot N, Gasc C, Butler R, Pombert J-F, Lerat E, Peyret P: Exploiting the architecture and the features of the microsporidian genomes to investigate diversity and impact of these parasites on ecosystems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>Heredity (Edinb) 2014, ePub. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>21.HaagKLTrauneckerEEbertDSingle-nucleotide polymorphisms of two closely related microsporidian parasites suggest a clonal population expansion after the last glaciationMol Ecol20132231426<?supplied-pmid 23163569?>23163569 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>22.SelmanMSakBKváčMFarinelliLWeissLMCorradiNExtremely reduced levels of heterozygosity in the vertebrate pathogen Encephalitozoon cuniculiEukaryot Cell201312496502<?supplied-pmid 23376943?>23376943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>23.VávraJBecnelJJVavraia culicis (Weiser, 1947) Weiser, 1977 revisited: cytological characterisation of a Vavraia culicis-like microsporidium isolated from mosquitoes in Florida and the establishment of Vavraia culicis floridensis subsp. nFolia Parasitol (Praha)2007542597118303767 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>24.Desjardins CA, Sanscrainte ND, Goldberg JM, Heiman D, Young S, Zeng Q, et al. Contrasting host-pathogen interactions and genome evolution in two generalist and specialist microsporidian pathogens of mosquitoes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>Nat Commun. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>2015;6: 7121. doi: 10.1038/ncomms8121. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>25.NawrockiEPKolbeDLEddySRInfernal 1.0: inference of RNA alignmentsBioinformatics20092513357<?supplied-pmid 19307242?>19307242 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>26.BurgeSWDaubJEberhardtRTateJBarquistLNawrockiEPEddySRGardnerPPBatemanARfam 11.0: 10 years of RNA familiesNucleic Acids Res201341Database issueD22632<?supplied-pmid 23125362?>23125362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>27.SödingJProtein homology detection by HMM-HMM comparisonBioinformatics20052195160<?supplied-pmid 15531603?>15531603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>28.SödingJBiegertALupasANThe HHpred interactive server for protein homology detection and structure predictionNucleic Acids Res200533Web Server issueW2448<?supplied-pmid 15980461?>15980461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>29.MuralidharanVGoldbergDEAsparagine repeats in Plasmodium falciparum proteins: good for nothing?PLoS Pathog20139e1003488<?supplied-pmid 23990777?>23990777 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>30.PetersenTNBrunakSvon HeijneGNielsenHSignalP 4.0: discriminating signal peptides from transmembrane regionsNat Methods201187856<?supplied-pmid 21959131?>21959131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>31.ParkMHWolffECFolkJEHypusine: its post-translational formation in eukaryotic initiation factor 5A and its potential role in cellular regulationBiofactors1993495104<?supplied-pmid 8347280?>8347280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>32.BasslerJKallasMPertschyBUlbrichCThomsMHurtEThe AAA-ATPase Rea1 drives removal of biogenesis factors during multiple stages of 60S ribosome assemblyMol Cell20103871221<?supplied-pmid 20542003?>20542003 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>33.DeLabreMLKesslJKaramanouSTrumpowerBLRPL29 codes for a non-essential protein of the 60S ribosomal subunit in Saccharomyces cerevisiae and exhibits synthetic lethality with mutations in genes for proteins required for subunit couplingBiochim Biophys Acta2002157425561<?supplied-pmid 11997090?>11997090 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>34.WeissLMDelbacFHaymanJRPanGDangXZhouZWeissLMBecnelJJThe Microsporidian Polar Tube and Spore WallMicrosporidia Pathog Oppor20141IowaJohn Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc170 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>35.ZacharaNEHartGWO-GlcNAc a sensor of cellular state: the role of nucleocytoplasmic glycosylation in modulating cellular function in response to nutrition and stressBiochim Biophys Acta200416731328<?supplied-pmid 15238246?>15238246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>36.SlawsonCHousleyMPHartGWO-GlcNAc cycling: how a single sugar post-translational modification is changing the way we think about signaling networksJ Cell Biochem2006977183<?supplied-pmid 16237703?>16237703 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>37.StokesMJGütherMLSTurnockDCPrescottARMartinKLAlpheyMSFergusonMAJThe synthesis of UDP-N-acetylglucosamine is essential for bloodstream form trypanosoma brucei in vitro and in vivo and UDP-N-acetylglucosamine starvation reveals a hierarchy in parasite protein glycosylationJ Biol Chem20082831614761<?supplied-pmid 18381290?>18381290 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>38.UrbaniakMDCollieITFangWAristotelousTEskilssonSRaimiOGHarrisonJNavratilovaIHFrearsonJAvan AaltenDMFFergusonMAJA novel allosteric inhibitor of the uridine diphosphate N-acetylglucosamine pyrophosphorylase from Trypanosoma bruceiACS Chem Biol2013819817<?supplied-pmid 23834437?>23834437 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>39.WilliamsBAPSlamovitsCHPatronNJFastNMKeelingPJA high frequency of overlapping gene expression in compacted eukaryotic genomesProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20051021093641<?supplied-pmid 16037215?>16037215 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>40.CorradiNGangaevaAKeelingPJComparative profiling of overlapping transcription in the compacted genomes of microsporidia Antonospora locustae and Encephalitozoon cuniculiGenomics20089138893<?supplied-pmid 18280697?>18280697 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>41.GillEEBecnelJJFastNMESTs from the microsporidian Edhazardia aedisBMC Genomics20089296<?supplied-pmid 18570666?>18570666 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>42.ZorioDAChengNNBlumenthalTSpiethJOperons as a common form of chromosomal organization in C. elegansNature19943722702<?supplied-pmid 7969472?>7969472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>43.LeeRCHGillEERoySWFastNMConstrained intron structures in a microsporidianMol Biol Evol201027197982<?supplied-pmid 20360213?>20360213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>44.MargueratSSchmidtACodlinSChenWAebersoldRBählerJQuantitative Analysis of Fission Yeast Transcriptomes and Proteomes in Proliferating and Quiescent CellsCell201215167183<?supplied-pmid 23101633?>23101633 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>45.HendersonBAllanECoatesARMStress wars: the direct role of host and bacterial molecular chaperones in bacterial infectionInfect Immun2006743693706<?supplied-pmid 16790742?>16790742 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>46.FaresMARuiz-GonzálezMXMoyaAElenaSFBarrioEEndosymbiotic bacteria: groEL buffers against deleterious mutationsNature2002417398<?supplied-pmid 12024205?>12024205 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>47.WilliamsTAFaresMAThe effect of chaperonin buffering on protein evolutionGenome Biol Evol2010260919<?supplied-pmid 20660109?>20660109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>48.McCutcheonJPMoranNAExtreme genome reduction in symbiotic bacteriaNat Rev Microbiol201210132622064560 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>49.BogumilDDaganTCumulative impact of chaperone-mediated folding on genome evolutionBiochemistry201251994153<?supplied-pmid 23167595?>23167595 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>50.LiberekKLewandowskaAZietkiewiczSChaperones in control of protein disaggregationEMBO J20082732835<?supplied-pmid 18216875?>18216875 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>51.DolgikhVVSokolovaJJIssiIVActivities of enzymes of carbohydrate and energy metabolism of the spores of the microsporidian, Nosema grylliJ Eukaryot Microbiol1997442469<?supplied-pmid 9183713?>9183713 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>52.TsunehiroFJunichiNNarimichiKKazutadaWIsolation, overexpression and disruption of a Saccharomyces cerevisiae YNK gene encoding nucleoside diphosphate kinaseGene199312914168392963 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>53.VértessyBGTóthJKeeping uracil out of DNA: physiological role, structure and catalytic mechanism of dUTPasesAcc Chem Res20094297106<?supplied-pmid 18837522?>18837522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>54.Gowri VS, Ghosh I, Sharma A, Madhubala R. Unusual domain architecture of aminoacyl tRNA synthetases and their paralogs from Leishmania major. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>BMC Genomics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>2012;13:621. doi: 10.1186/1471-2164-13-621. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>55.ManhasRTripathiPKhanSSethu LakshmiBLalSKGowriVSSharmaAMadhubalaRIdentification and functional characterization of a novel bacterial type asparagine synthetase A: a tRNA synthetase paralog from Leishmania donovaniJ Biol Chem201428912096108<?supplied-pmid 24610810?>24610810 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>56.LoureiroIFariaJClaytonCRibeiroSMRoyNSantarémNTavaresJCordeiro-da-SilvaAKnockdown of Asparagine Synthetase A Renders Trypanosoma brucei Auxotrophic to AsparaginePLoS Negl Trop Dis20137e2578<?supplied-pmid 24340117?>24340117 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>57.Lu SC: Regulation of glutathione synthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>Mol Aspects Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>2009;30:42–59. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>58.BironDGAgnewPMarchéLRenaultLSidobreCMichalakisYProteome of Aedes aegypti larvae in response to infection by the intracellular parasite Vavraia culicisInt J Parasitol200535138597<?supplied-pmid 16102770?>16102770 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>59.DuncanABAgnewPNoelVDemettreESevenoMBrizardJ-PMichalakisYProteome of Aedes aegypti in response to infection and coinfection with microsporidian parasitesEcol Evol2012268194<?supplied-pmid 22837817?>22837817 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>60.PanekJEl AlaouiHMoneAUrbachSDemettreETexierCBrunCZanzoniAPeyretailladeEParisotNLeratEPeyretPDelbacFBironDGHijacking of Host Cellular Functions by an Intracellular Parasite, the Microsporidian Anncaliia algeraePLoS One20149e100791<?supplied-pmid 24967735?>24967735 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>61.VanapornMWandMMichellSLSarkar-TysonMIrelandPGoldmanSKewcharoenwongCRinchaiDLertmemongkolchaiGTitballRWSuperoxide dismutase C is required for intracellular survival and virulence of Burkholderia pseudomalleiMicrobiology2011157Pt 82392400<?supplied-pmid 21659326?>21659326 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>62.GoldbergAVMolikSTsaousisADNeumannKKuhnkeGDelbacFVivaresCPHirtRPLillREmbleyTMLocalization and functionality of microsporidian iron-sulphur cluster assembly proteinsNature20084526248<?supplied-pmid 18311129?>18311129 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>63.ZhangYLyverERNakamaru-OgisoEYoonHAmuthaBLeeD-WBiEOhnishiTDaldalFPainDDancisADre2, a Conserved Eukaryotic Fe/S Cluster Protein, Functions in Cytosolic Fe/S Protein BiogenesisMol Cell Biol200828556982<?supplied-pmid 18625724?>18625724 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>64.AltschulSGapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programsNucleic Acids Res1997253389402<?supplied-pmid 9254694?>9254694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>65.FinnRDClementsJEddySRHMMER web server: interactive sequence similarity searchingNucleic Acids Res201139Web Server issueW2937<?supplied-pmid 21593126?>21593126 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>66.CornmanRSChenYPSchatzMCStreetCZhaoYDesanyBEgholmMHutchisonSPettisJSLipkinWIEvansJDGenomic analyses of the microsporidian Nosema ceranae, an emergent pathogen of honey beesPLoS Pathog20095e1000466<?supplied-pmid 19503607?>19503607 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>67.CarvunisA-RRollandTWapinskiICalderwoodMAYildirimMASimonisNCharloteauxBHidalgoCABarbetteJSanthanamBBrarGAWeissmanJSRegevAThierry-MiegNCusickMEVidalMProto-genes and de novo gene birthNature20124873704<?supplied-pmid 22722833?>22722833 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>68.BecnelJJAndreadisTJWeissLMBecnelJJMicrosporidia in InsectsMicrosporidia Pathog Oppor2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>69.OhnoSEvolution by Gene Duplication1970New YorkSpringer </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>70.ForceALynchMPickettFBAmoresAYanYLPostlethwaitJPreservation of duplicate genes by complementary, degenerative mutationsGenetics1999151153145<?supplied-pmid 10101175?>10101175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>71.KellisMBirrenBWLanderESProof and evolutionary analysis of ancient genome duplication in the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiaeNature200442861724<?supplied-pmid 15004568?>15004568 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>72.ConantGCWagnerAAsymmetric sequence divergence of duplicate genesGenome Res20031320528<?supplied-pmid 12952876?>12952876 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>73.ConantGCWolfeKHTurning a hobby into a job: how duplicated genes find new functionsNat Rev Genet2008993850<?supplied-pmid 19015656?>19015656 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>74.WeidnerECanningEURutledgeCRMeekCLMosquito (Diptera: Culicidae) Host Compatibility and Vector Competency for the Human Myositic Parasite Trachipleistophora hominis (Phylum Microspora)J Med Entomol1999365225<?supplied-pmid 10467783?>10467783 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>75.CaryLCGoebelMCorsaroBGWangH-GRosenEFraserMJTransposon mutagenesis of baculoviruses: Analysis of Trichoplusia ni transposon IFP2 insertions within the FP-locus of nuclear polyhedrosis virusesVirology198917215669<?supplied-pmid 2549707?>2549707 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>76.MitraRLiXKapustaAMayhewDMitraRDFeschotteCCraigNLFunctional characterization of piggyBat from the bat Myotis lucifugus unveils an active mammalian DNA transposonProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20131102349<?supplied-pmid 23248290?>23248290 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>77.ZanderETierische Parasiten als Krankenheitserreger bei der BieneMünchener Bienenzeitung190931196204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>78.PanGXuJLiTXiaQLiuS-LZhangGLiSLiCLiuHYangLLiuTZhangXWuZFanWDangXXiangHTaoMLiYHuJLiZLinLLuoJGengLWangLLongMWanYHeNZhangZLuCKeelingPJComparative genomics of parasitic silkworm microsporidia reveal an association between genome expansion and host adaptationBMC Genomics201314186<?supplied-pmid 23496955?>23496955 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR79"><text><SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>79.GuoXGaoJLiFWangJEvidence of horizontal transfer of non-autonomous Lep1 Helitrons facilitated by host-parasite interactionsSci Rep201445119<?supplied-pmid 24874102?>24874102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR80"><text><SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>80.ParisotNPelinAGascCPolonaisVBelkorchiaAPanekJEl AlaouiHBironDGBrassetEVauryCPeyretPCorradiNPeyretailladeÉLeratEMicrosporidian genomes harbor a diverse array of transposable elements that demonstrate an ancestry of horizontal exchange with metazoansGenome Biol Evol201462289300<?supplied-pmid 25172905?>25172905 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR81"><text><SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>81.IronsideJEMultiple losses of sex within a single genus of MicrosporidiaBMC Evol Biol2007748<?supplied-pmid 17394631?>17394631 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR82"><text><SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>82.HazardEIBrookbankJWKaryogamy and meiosis in an Amblyospora sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>(Microspora) in the mosquito Culex salinariusJ Invertebr Pathol198444311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR83"><text><SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>83.PelinASelmanMAris-BrosouSFarinelliLCorradiNGenome analyses suggest the presence of polyploidy and recent human-driven expansions in eight global populations of the honeybee pathogen Nosema ceranaeEnviron Microbiol2015<?supplied-pmid 25914091?>25914091 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR84"><text><SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>84.BernanderRPalmJEDSvardSGGenome ploidy in different stages of the Giardia lamblia life cycleCell Microbiol200135562<?supplied-pmid 11207620?>11207620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR85"><text><SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>85.TroemelERFélixM-AWhitemanNKBarrièreAAusubelFMMicrosporidia are natural intracellular parasites of the nematode Caenorhabditis elegansPLoS Biol20086273652<?supplied-pmid 19071962?>19071962 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR86"><text><SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>86.EstesKASzumowskiSCTroemelERNon-LyticActin-Based Exit of Intracellular Parasites from C. elegans Intestinal Cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>PLoS Pathog20117e1002227 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR87"><text><SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain>87.KanehisaMGotoSKEGG: kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomesNucleic Acids Res2000282730<?supplied-pmid 10592173?>10592173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR88"><text><SENT sid="550" pm="."><plain>88.XieCMaoXHuangJDingYWuJDongSKongLGaoGLiC-YWeiLKOBAS 2.0: a web server for annotation and identification of enriched pathways and diseasesNucleic Acids Res201139Web Server issueW31622<?supplied-pmid 21715386?>21715386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR89"><text><SENT sid="551" pm="."><plain>89.MathupalaSPKoYHPedersenPLThe pivotal roles of mitochondria in cancer: Warburg and beyond and encouraging prospects for effective therapiesBiochim Biophys Acta20101797122530<?supplied-pmid 20381449?>20381449 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR90"><text><SENT sid="552" pm="."><plain>90.WilsonJEIsozymes of mammalian hexokinase: structure, subcellular localization and metabolic functionJ Exp Biol2003206204957<?supplied-pmid 12756287?>12756287 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR91"><text><SENT sid="553" pm="."><plain>91.MartinF-PJVerduEFWangYDumasM-EYapIKSCloarecOBergonzelliGECorthesy-TheulazIKochharSHolmesELindonJCCollinsSMNicholsonJKTransgenomic metabolic interactions in a mouse disease model: interactions of Trichinella spiralis infection with dietary Lactobacillus paracasei supplementationJ Proteome Res20065218593<?supplied-pmid 16944930?>16944930 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR92"><text><SENT sid="554" pm="."><plain>92.WangYHolmesENicholsonJKCloarecOCholletJTannerMSingerBHUtzingerJMetabonomic investigations in mice infected with Schistosoma mansoni: an approach for biomarker identificationProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20041011267681<?supplied-pmid 15314235?>15314235 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR93"><text><SENT sid="555" pm="."><plain>93.MungerJBajadSUCollerHAShenkTRabinowitzJDDynamics of the cellular metabolome during human cytomegalovirus infectionPLoS Pathog20062e132<?supplied-pmid 17173481?>17173481 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR94"><text><SENT sid="556" pm="."><plain>94.TowlerMCHardieDGAMP-activated protein kinase in metabolic control and insulin signalingCirc Res200710032841<?supplied-pmid 17307971?>17307971 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR95"><text><SENT sid="557" pm="."><plain>95.LinJHandschinCSpiegelmanBMMetabolic control through the PGC-1 family of transcription coactivatorsCell Metab2005136170<?supplied-pmid 16054085?>16054085 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR96"><text><SENT sid="558" pm="."><plain>96.KimJTchernyshyovISemenzaGLDangCVHIF-1-mediated expression of pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase: a metabolic switch required for cellular adaptation to hypoxiaCell Metab2006317785<?supplied-pmid 16517405?>16517405 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR97"><text><SENT sid="559" pm="."><plain>97.HolnessMJSugdenMCRegulation of pyruvate dehydrogenase complex activity by reversible phosphorylationBiochem Soc Trans200331Pt 6114351<?supplied-pmid 14641014?>14641014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR98"><text><SENT sid="560" pm="."><plain>98.DobladoMMoleyKHFacilitative glucose transporter 9, a unique hexose and urate transporterAm J Physiol Endocrinol Metab2009297E8315<?supplied-pmid 19797240?>19797240 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR99"><text><SENT sid="561" pm="."><plain>99.LangmeadBSalzbergSLFast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2Nat Methods201293579<?supplied-pmid 22388286?>22388286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR100"><text><SENT sid="562" pm="."><plain>100.Andrews S: FastQC: A quality control tool for high throughput sequence data. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/">http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/</ext-link> 2010. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="563" pm="."><plain>Access 14 October 2015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR101"><text><SENT sid="564" pm="."><plain>101.Aronesty E: Command-line tools for processing biological sequencing data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="565" pm="."><plain>ea-utils 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR102"><text><SENT sid="566" pm="."><plain>102.KimDPerteaGTrapnellCPimentelHKelleyRSalzbergSLTopHat2: accurate alignment of transcriptomes in the presence of insertions, deletions and gene fusionsGenome Biol201314R36<?supplied-pmid 23618408?>23618408 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR103"><text><SENT sid="567" pm="."><plain>103.TrapnellCWilliamsBAPerteaGMortazaviAKwanGvan BarenMJSalzbergSLWoldBJPachterLTranscript assembly and quantification by RNA-Seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiationNat Biotechnol2010285115<?supplied-pmid 20436464?>20436464 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR104"><text><SENT sid="568" pm="."><plain>104.LiHHandsakerBWysokerAFennellTRuanJHomerNMarthGAbecasisGDurbinRThe Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtoolsBioinformatics20092520789<?supplied-pmid 19505943?>19505943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR105"><text><SENT sid="569" pm="."><plain>105.DanecekPAutonAAbecasisGAlbersCABanksEDePristoMAHandsakerRELunterGMarthGTSherrySTMcVeanGDurbinRThe variant call format and VCFtoolsBioinformatics20112721568<?supplied-pmid 21653522?>21653522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR106"><text><SENT sid="570" pm="."><plain>106.CingolaniPPlattsAWangLLLCoonMNguyenTWangLLLLandSJLuXRudenDMA program for annotating and predicting the effects of single nucleotide polymorphisms, SnpEff: SNPs in the genome of Drosophila melanogaster strain w(1118); iso-2; iso-3Fly (Austin)20126809222728672 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR107"><text><SENT sid="571" pm="."><plain>107.CingolaniPPatelVMCoonMNguyenTLandSJRudenDMLuXUsing Drosophila melanogaster as a Model for Genotoxic Chemical Mutational Studies with a New ProgramSnpSift. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="572" pm="."><plain>Front Genet2012335<?supplied-pmid 22435069?>22435069 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR108"><text><SENT sid="573" pm="."><plain>108.TrapnellCHendricksonDGSauvageauMGoffLRinnJLPachterLDifferential analysis of gene regulation at transcript resolution with RNA-seqNat Biotechnol2013314653<?supplied-pmid 23222703?>23222703 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR109"><text><SENT sid="574" pm="."><plain>109.TrapnellCRobertsAGoffLPerteaGKimDKelleyDRPimentelHSalzbergSLRinnJLPachterLDifferential gene and transcript expression analysis of RNA-seq experiments with TopHat and CufflinksNat Protoc2012756278<?supplied-pmid 22383036?>22383036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR110"><text><SENT sid="575" pm="."><plain>110.WallaceIMO’SullivanOHigginsDGNotredameCM-Coffee: combining multiple sequence alignment methods with T-CoffeeNucleic Acids Res20063416929<?supplied-pmid 16556910?>16556910 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR111"><text><SENT sid="576" pm="."><plain>111.EdgarRCMUSCLE: a multiple sequence alignment method with reduced time and space complexityBMC Bioinformatics20045113<?supplied-pmid 15318951?>15318951 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR112"><text><SENT sid="577" pm="."><plain>112.KatohKMAFFT: a novel method for rapid multiple sequence alignment based on fast Fourier transformNucleic Acids Res200230305966<?supplied-pmid 12136088?>12136088 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR113"><text><SENT sid="578" pm="."><plain>113.DoCBMahabhashyamMSPBrudnoMBatzoglouSProbCons: Probabilistic consistency-based multiple sequence alignmentGenome Res20051533040<?supplied-pmid 15687296?>15687296 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR114"><text><SENT sid="579" pm="."><plain>114.PeiJSadreyevRGrishinNVPCMA: fast and accurate multiple sequence alignment based on profile consistencyBioinformatics2003194278<?supplied-pmid 12584134?>12584134 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR115"><text><SENT sid="580" pm="."><plain>115.BradleyRKRobertsASmootMJuvekarSDoJDeweyCHolmesIPachterLFast statistical alignmentPLoS Comput Biol20095e1000392<?supplied-pmid 19478997?>19478997 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR116"><text><SENT sid="581" pm="."><plain>116.Capella-GutiérrezSSilla-MartínezJMGabaldónTtrimAl: a tool for automated alignment trimming in large-scale phylogenetic analysesBioinformatics20092519723<?supplied-pmid 19505945?>19505945 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR117"><text><SENT sid="582" pm="."><plain>117.Quang LS, Gascuel O, Lartillot N, Lirmm B, Cedex M: Empirical profile mixture models for phylogenetic reconstruction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="583" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatics 2008;24(20):2317–3. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR118"><text><SENT sid="584" pm="."><plain>118.LartillotNLepageTBlanquartSPhyloBayes 3: a Bayesian software package for phylogenetic reconstruction and molecular datingBioinformatics20092522868<?supplied-pmid 19535536?>19535536 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR119"><text><SENT sid="585" pm="."><plain>119.CaliATakvorianPMWeissLMBecnelJJDevelopmental Morphology and Life Cycles of MicrosporidiaMicrosporidia Pathog Oppor2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR120"><text><SENT sid="586" pm="."><plain>120.GouyMGuindonSGascuelOSeaView version 4: A multiplatform graphical user interface for sequence alignment and phylogenetic tree buildingMol Biol Evol2010272214<?supplied-pmid 19854763?>19854763 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR121"><text><SENT sid="587" pm="."><plain>121.BenjaminiYHochbergYControlling the False Discovery Rate: A Practical and Powerful Approach to Multiple TestingJ R Stat Soc Ser B199557289300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR122"><text><SENT sid="588" pm="."><plain>122.KanehisaMGotoSSatoYKawashimaMFurumichiMTanabeMData, information, knowledge and principle: back to metabolism in KEGGNucleic Acids Res201442Database issueD199205<?supplied-pmid 24214961?>24214961 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
