<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4460013</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26053695</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128887</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-02547</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The Characteristics and Function of S100A7 Induction in Squamous Cell Carcinoma: Heterogeneity, Promotion of Cell Proliferation and Suppression of Differentiation </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">The Characteristics of S100A7 in SCC</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Zhi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Ting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>Fei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yunguang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Rui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Junhao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Qianqian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Weiqing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Suozhu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Dacheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Xueyuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Key laboratory of Cell Proliferation and Regulation of Ministry of Education, Beijing Normal University, Beijing, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Universities’ Confederated Institute of Proteomics, Beijing, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff003">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Pathology, General Hospital of the Second Artillery, Beijing, China</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>Karl X</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Central Florida, UNITED STATES</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: XX ZQ DH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: ZQ TL FK YL RW JW QX WZ SS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: ZQ TL FK YL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: XX ZQ FK YL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>xyxiao@bnu.edu.cn</email> (XX); <email>dhe@bnu.edu.cn</email> (DH)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e0128887</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>5</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 Qi et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Qi et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0128887.pdf"/><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>S100A7 is highly expressed in squamous cell carcinomas (SCC) and is related to the terminal differentiation of keratinocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>However, its characteristic and function in SCC is not very known. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>In this present study, we used immunohistochemistry to examine the expression of S100A7 in 452 SCC specimens, including the lung, esophagus, oral cavity, skin, cervix, bladder, and three SCC cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>We found that S100A7-positive staining showed significant heterogeneity in six types of SCC specimen and three SCC cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Further examination found that S100A7-positive cells and its expression at mRNA and protein levels could be induced in HCC94, FaDu, and A-431 cells both in vitro and in vivo using immunohistochemistry, real-time PCR, and Western blotting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Notably, the upregulation of squamous differentiation markers, including keratin-4, keratin-13, TG-1, and involucrin, also accompanied S100A7 induction, and a similar staining pattern of S100A7 and keratin-13 was found in HCC94 cells both in vitro and in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Further study revealed that the overexpression of S100A7 significantly increased proliferation and inhibited squamous differentiation in A-431 cells both in vitro and in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Conversely, silencing S100A7 inhibited cell growth and survival and increased the expression of keratin-4, keratin-13, TG-1, and involucrin in HCC94 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Therefore, these results demonstrate that S100A7 displays heterogeneous and inducible characteristic in SCC and also provide novel evidence that S100A7 acts as a dual regulator in promoting proliferation and suppressing squamous differentiation of SCC. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Ministry of Science and Technology of China (2011CB915504), of the National Natural Science Foundation of China (81172216, 81272604). The funder's website is <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nsfc.gov.cn">www.nsfc.gov.cn</ext-link>. X.Y. Xiao and D.C.He are the authors who received the funding. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="8"/><table-count count="1"/><page-count count="16"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Squamous cell carcinomas (SCCs) are the most common cancer and can be very aggressive and metastatic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>SCC shows deregulation and defects in cell differentiation [1–2], and these defects are hypothesized to help squamous cells survive and escape terminal differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Despite operation, radiotherapy, and chemotherapy, SCC lesions often recur and spread to other body sites, such as the lungs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is important to identify the molecules that inhibit the aberrant proliferation of SCC and simultaneously reinstate a normal differentiation program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>This strategy may be an additional useful strategy for the clinical treatment of SCCs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>S100A7 (psoriasin) belongs to the S100 multigenic family of calcium-modulated proteins of the EF-hand type and was originally identified in psoriatic keratinocytes [3–4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In addition to its antibacterial effects [5], S100A7 expression is up-regulated in breast cancer and many types of squamous cell carcinomas, including lung, oral cavity, bladder, and skin, and also plays an important role in carcinogenesis and metastasis [6–18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Several studies report that the high level of S100A7 expression is always observed in highly differentiated SCCs, and weak or loss of expression is observed in moderately or poorly-differentiated SCCs [7,11,12,18], suggesting a specific association of S100A7 expression with SCC proliferation and differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The involvement of S100A7 in the differentiation process is also suggested by the fact that S100A7 is located within a gene cluster in chromosome 1q21, the epidermal differentiation complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>This cluster also contains epidermal differentiation markers, such as several cytokeratins and involucrin [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Intriguingly, the level of S100A7 expression in SCC tissues is inconsistent with that in SCC cell line cultured in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Because S100A7 expression is relatively low or undetected in SCC cells in vitro; however, it has been reported that S100A7 is induced in keratinocytes by certain stimuli, such as suspension and confluent culture [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="?"><plain>Thinking along the connection between S100A7 expression in vivo, in vitro, and induction, we asked: can S100A7 be induced in SCC cell lines similar as keratinocytes? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="?"><plain>If so, what is the function of S100A7 in SCC cells? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we found that S100A7-positive staining showed significant heterogeneity in six types of SCC specimen and three SCC cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Further examination found that S100A7-positive cells could be induced in HCC94, FaDu, and A-431 cells both in vitro and in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Notably, the upregulation of squamous differentiation markers, including keratin-4, keratin-13, TG-1, and involucrin, also accompanied S100A7 induction, and a similar staining pattern of S100A7 and keratin-13 was found in HCC94 cells both in vitro and in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Further study revealed that the overexpression of S100A7 significantly increased proliferation and inhibited squamous differentiation in A-431 cells both in vitro and in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Conversely, knockdown S100A7 inhibited cell growth and survival and increased the expression of keratin-4, keratin-13, TG-1, and involucrin in HCC94 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Overall, our findings provide novel evidence that S100A7 acts as a dual regulator in promoting proliferation and suppressing squamous differentiation of SCC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec003"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Cell lines and culture conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The human carcinoma cell lines A-431, HCC94, and FaDu were purchased from the Chinese Academy of Sciences Committee Type Culture Collection Cell Bank and the cell lines were authenticated by short tandem repeat analysis at HK Gene Science Technology Co (Beijing, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>All cells were cultured in accordance with the corresponding culture method of the ATCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Cultured cells that reached∼60% density were defined as pre-confluent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>For the confluent induction experiment, the cells were maintained at confluence for different numbers of days and the medium was routinely changed each day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Suspension culture was achieved by plating the cells in Poly-HEMA coated (12mg/ml dissolved in 95% ethanol) 6-well and 96-well plates in medium with 10% fetal bovine serum for different numbers of days. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Tissue specimens </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Four hundred and fifty-two SCC tissue specimens were obtained from thirteen cancer tissue arrays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>One lung SCC tissue array (No Hlug-squ150CS-01), one esophageal SCC tissue array (No HEso-squ172Sur-01), and one bladder cancer tissue array (No OD-CT-UrBla03-003) were purchased from Shanghai Outdo Biotech Co., Ltd,. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>One oral cavity SCC tissue array (OR601a), three skin cancer tissue arrays (SK801b array, SK802a and SK483), one cervical SCC tissue array (CR803), and six cancer tissue arrays (No CC04-01-001, T271a,T022c, T124b, CR803 and SK483) including normal tissues of lung, tong, esophagus, bladder, cervix and skin were purchased from Xi An Alenabio Co. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>All cancer tissues were obtained from surgically treated patients who gave informed consent and the Ethics Committee of the General Hospital of the Second Artillery (No. KY2013024) approved this protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>All participants provide their written informed consent to participate in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>All methods were carried out in accordance with the approved protocol by above Ethics Committee. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>All cancer patients received a pathological diagnosis, and none had received prior therapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Reverse transcription and Real-time PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was extracted from the cells for the generation of single-stranded cDNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The real-time PCR was performed using an ABI 7300 Real-time PCR System with the Power SYBR Green PCR Master Mix in a final volume of 20 μL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The PCR primers were designed using Primer Premier 5.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The thermal cycle conditions were as follows: 2 min at 50°C and then 95°C for 10 min, followed by 40 cycles of 95°C for 15 s and 60°C for 1 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The uniform amplification of the products was confirmed by analyzing the melting curves of the amplified products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>GAPDH was used as an endogenous control for each sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The primers used for each of the genes are listed in S1 Table. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Western blotting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Western blot was performed as previously described [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The anti-S100A7 monoclonal antibody was purchased from Abcam (No. ab13680). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The target proteins were detected using either a chemiluminescent substrate or DAB. β-Actin was used as an internal control for equal protein loading. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemistry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemical staining for S100A7 in the tissue arrays was performed as previously described [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Keratin-13 tissue staining was performed as for S100A7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Cell immunostaining of S100A7 and keratin-13 was performed as follows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>First, the cells were plated on cover-glass and cultured for different numbers of days and fixed with 4% buffered paraformaldehyde after washing with PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The cells were then permeabilized with 0.5% Triton X-100 for 10 min at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The subsequent steps were performed as previously described [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Isotype IgG was used as a negative control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Two pathologists evaluated all tissue immunostaining for S100A7 independently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Any staining in the cytoplasm, nucleus, or cytoplasmic membrane was considered positive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The cancers were scored using our previously reported scale [20]: 0, no positive cells; 1, &lt;10% cancer cells positive; 2, &gt;10% and &lt;50% cancer cells positive; 3, &gt;50% and &lt;75% cancer cells positive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Grade 1: well-differentiated; Grade 2: moderately-differentiated; Grade 3: poorly differentiated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>To calculate S100A7-positive cells in suspension, cells were cultured in suspension for 48 hours and then reseeded on the glass-cover slides and cultured for 12 hours,and finally examined by immunohistochemistry with specific anti-S100A7 antibody and control antibody, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>S100A7-positive and–negative cells were counted in each clump of cells under a microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The average value of S100A7-positve in 20 clumps of cells for each cell lines were used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Double immunofluorescence staining </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Double immunofluorescence labeling of S100A7 and keratin-13 was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>First, the cells were plated, fixed, and permeabilized as for the cell immunostaining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The cells were then blocked with 3% BSA-PBS solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>S100A7 antibody was applied for 1 h at 37°C followed by washing and subsequent incubation with TRITC-labeled goat anti-rabbit IgG for 1 h at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The cells were blocked again and incubated with keratin-13 antibody (mouse monoclonal IgG), and FITC-labeled goat anti-mouse IgG was used to detect keratin-13 expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Finally, the nuclei were stained using DAPI, and S100A7 and keratin-13 expression was detected using a fluorescence microscope. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>siRNA interference </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>To knockdown the expression of S100A7, small interfering RNAs were purchased from Gene Pharma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The targeted sequences were as follows: CCAGACGUGAUGACAAGAUTT and AUCUUGUCAUCACGUCUGGTT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The siRNA was designed according to the sequence provided under GenBank accession number NM_002963.3 S100A7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Scrambled siRNA was used as the control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>HCC94 cells were transfected with S100A7-siRNA and scrambled siRNA using the Lipofectamine 2000 Transfection Reagent according to the manufacturer's protocol. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>S100A7 over-expression vector construction and transfection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>To construct the expression plasmid for the S100A7 protein, the S100A7 cDNA fragment was amplified using the primers5’-CCGCTCGAGATGAGCAACACTCAAGCTGA-3’ and 5’-CGGAATTCTCACTGGCTGCCCCCGGAAC-3’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The amplified cDNA was inserted into the pcDNA3.1+ vector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The cells were transfected with the plasmids using the Lipofectamine 2000 Transfection Reagent, and empty vector was used as the control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>For the generation of stable transfectants, A-431 cells were transfected with pcDNA3.1/S100A7, and pcDNA3.1 empty plasmids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>After 2 weeks G418 (400μg/mL) treatment, G418-resistant clones were selected, and those clones were then expanded for further studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Tumorigenicity in nude mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Viable cells (5×106) cells were mixed with HBSS and inoculated subcutaneously in six-week-old female nude mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>BALB/C nude (nu/nu) mice were bought from the Peking University Laboratory Animal Center (Beijing, PR China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Tumor growth was monitored as described in our previous study [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The tumors were washed with PBS and fixed with 4% buffered paraformaldehyde. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>All animal work was approved by Ethics Committee of College of Life Science, Beijing Normal University (CLS-EAW-2013-08). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>All methods were carried out in accordance with relevant guidelines by above Ethics Committee. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec012"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Cell proliferation and survival rate in suspension </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Cell proliferation and survival rate were evaluated by MTT and XTT [23–24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The survival rates are expressed as a percentage of the absorbance reading of the control cells (% survival), and each condition was tested in six replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec013"><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The statistical significance was evaluated using Student’s t-test (two-tailed) for comparisons between the experimental groups and the corresponding control groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The differences were considered statistically significant at p less than 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="sec014"><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec015"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>S100A7 is heterogeneously expressed in both squamous cell carcinoma tissues and cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>In our previous study, we reported that S100A7 was selectively expressed in lung SCC tissue specimens [20–21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>To determine whether a similar expression of S100A7 is present in the other SCCs, six types of SCCs tissue arrays with 452 cases of SCCs were examined for S100A7 expressions using immunohistochemistry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The results showed that 41% of lung SCCs, 76.6% of esophageal SCCs, 50.6% of cervical SCCs, 80.4% of oral SCCs, 84.8% of skin SCCs and 66.7% of bladder SCCs were positive for S100A7 (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Importantly, we found that S100A7 expression was heterogeneous and displayed a patchy or a scattered distribution in all positively stained tissues, and the staining intensity of S100A7 was inversely associated with degree of differentiation in all tested SCC tissues Representative immunoreactivity results are shown in Fig 1A–1F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>In addition, S100A7 expression was also found in the normal tissues including cervix and oral cavity, but was absent from normal lung, bladder, esophagus tissues, and skin (Fig 1M–1R). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Tissue section using nonspecific IgG as negative control showed no positive staining (Fig 1G–1L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Based on the characteristics of S100A7 expression in SCC tissues, we hypothesized that S100A7 heterogeneity may exist in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>To test our hypothesis, three squamous carcinoma cell lines, including HCC94, FaDu, and A-431 cells, were selected and the S100A7 expression was examined by immunohistochemistry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Unlike with HCC94 cells, less than 1% S100A7-positive cells were detected in FaDu and A-431 cells in the normal culture conditions (Fig 2A–2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Cultured cells using nonspecific IgG as negative control showed no positive staining (Fig 2D–2F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that the heterogeneity of S100A7 is a common feature in both SCC tissues and cultured SCC cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0128887.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128887.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The expression of S100A7 in SCC tissues. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>SCC and normal tissues were examined by immunohistochemistry with specific anti-S100A7 antibody in lung (A, M); esophagus (B, N); cervix (C, O); bladder (D, P); oral cavity (E, Q); skin (F, R). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The corresponding types of SCC tissues were also examined by immunohistochemistry with nonspecific IgG (G-L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Arrowheads indicate the positive staining of S100A7 and the asterisks indicate the keratinizing areas. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0128887.g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0128887.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128887.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The expression of S100A7 in SCC cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Cancer cells were examined by immunohistochemistry with specific anti-S100A7 antibody (A-C) and nonspecific IgG (D-F). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0128887.g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"></SecTag></sec><sec id="sec016"><title><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>S100A7-negative cells become positive in confluent culture </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>The inconsistent proportions of S100A7-positive cells in vitro and in vivo in SCCs suggest that there is a factor that triggers this difference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that S100A7 expression could be induced in HEKn cells under confluent culture [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>To investigate whether confluent culture also induces S100A7 expression in SCC cells, HCC94, A-431, and FaDu cells were cultured under confluent conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, A-431 and FaDu cells were easily detached in confluent culture, only HCC94 cells were successfully to culture under the confluence for 6 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Notably, the percentage of S100A7-positive cells was increased from about 10% under the normal culture condition to above 80% under confluence conditions, and then significantly decreased after the confluent cells were reseeded at the pre-confluent density and returned to the original ratio after three cell passages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Although the percentage of S100A7-positive cells was significantly different before and after the confluent culture, the subcellular localization and intensity of the S100A7 immunostaining were the same (Fig 3A, 3C and 3E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>In contrast, cultured cells using nonspecific IgG as negative control showed no positive staining (Fig 3B, 3D and 3F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>As expected, the expression of both S100A7 mRNA and proteins also changed based on the increased or decreased percentage of S100A7-positive cells (Fig 3G and 3H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Collectively, these results indicate that S100A7-positive cells could be inducible in HCC94 in the confluent culture and S100A7-negative and–positive cells bi-directionally convert to each other, depending on the cell density. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0128887.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128887.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>The induction of S100A7 expression in HCC94 cells in confluent culture. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>S100A7 expression was examined by immunohistochemistry (A, C, E), real-time PCR (G) and Western blotting (H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Cells were also examined by immunohistochemistry with nonspecific IgG (B, D, F).*, p&lt;0.05, and **, p&lt;0.01 versus the experimental groups and the pre-confluent groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The results represent the average values from three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>N: pre-confluence; C6: cells were cultured at confluence for 6 days; C6-R3P: cells that were cultured at confluence for six days and then reseeded at sub-confluence for 3 cell passages. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0128887.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="sec017"><title><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>S100A7-negative cells convert into positive cells in suspension culture </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Suspension culture is another inducer of S100A7 expression in keratinocytes [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>To explore whether S100A7 may also be induced by suspension in SCC cells, HCC94, FaDu, and A-431 cells were cultured in suspension for two days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Similar to the results of the confluence experiment, the expression of S100A7 was induced by suspension in all three SCC cells (Fig 4A–4F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>To further confirm whether the elevated levels of S100A7 expression resulted from an increased percentage of S100A7-positive cells, the suspension cells were reattached to a slide for 12 h and then examined by immunohistochemistry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>As expected, the percentage of S100A7-positive cells was raised from less than 1% in FaDu and A-431 cells, and about 10% in HCC94 cells in the normal culture to above 30%, 50% and 80% after suspension treatment, respectively; the induced-positive cells also displayed heterogeneous expression (Fig 4G–4I), indicating that the S100A7-positive cells are also inducible by suspension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Cultured cells using nonspecific IgG as negative control showed no positive staining (Fig 4J–4L). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0128887.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128887.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>The induction of S100A7 expression in FaDu, A-431, and HCC94 cells in suspension culture. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>The expression of S100A7 was determined by real-time PCR (A-C) and Western blotting (D-F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>FaDu, HCC94 and A-431cells in suspension for two days were reattached for 12h and examined using immunohistochemistry with specific anti-S100A7 antibody (G-I) and nonspecific IgG (J-L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>S48h: suspension 48h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>N: pre-suspension.*, p&lt;0.05, and **, p&lt;0.01 versus the suspension groups and the pre-suspension groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>The results represent the average values from three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0128887.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="sec018"><title><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>S100A7-positive cells are inducible in vivo </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>To determine whether S100A7 induction in SCC cells occurs in vivo, we examined S100A7 expression in xenografts derived from FaDu, A-431, and HCC94 cells using immunohistochemistry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Similar to the distribution of S100A7 staining in specimens from SCC patients, S100A7-positive cells displayed patchy or scattered pattern, and marked heterogeneity of S100A7 staining existed in all tested xenografts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Importantly, the percentage of S100A7-positive cells was dramatically raised in their corresponding xenografts, respectively (Fig 5A–5C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>In contrast, tissue sections using nonspecific IgG as negative control showed no positive staining (Fig 5D–5F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>These results directly support the hypothesis that S100A7 induction in SCC cells also occurs in vivo. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0128887.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128887.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemical analysis of S100A7 protein expression in xenografts. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>S100A7 expression was examined in FaDu xenografts, A-431 xenografts, and HCC94 xenografts by immunohistochemistry with specific anti-S100A7 antibody (A-C) and nonspecific IgG (D-E). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0128887.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="sec019"><title><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Squamous differentiation markers are induced in SCC cells both in vitro and in vivo </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that SCCs could express the keratins pattern shown by their normal epithelium, such as K4/K13 in non-keratinizing epithelia and K1/K10 in keratinizing epithelia [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Our novel findings were that the expression of differentiation markers including keratin-1, keratin-4, keratin-13, TG-1 and involucrin was also significantly increased in A-431, FaDu, and HCC94 cells after suspension and/or the confluent culture, respectively (Fig 6A–6F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>However, no expression of keratin-10 and keratin-4 was detected in A-431 cells and no difference expression of keratin-13 was observed in A-431 cells cultured in the normal condition and suspension (S1 Fig). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Given that S100A7 and differentiation-specific markers were induced in vitro by same stimuli in the above mentioned SCC cell lines, we wished to know the expression pattern of these proteins in vitro and in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Based on the aforementioned results, we selected keratin-13 to as representative differentiation markers among others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>For one reason, keratin-13 could be detected in both HCC94 cells and FaDu cells, whereas, keratin-1 only in A-431 cells but not in HCC94 and FaDu cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>The other reason is that HCC94 xenografts display a distinct squamous differentiation phenotype due to its being a well-differentiated cervical squamous carcinoma cell line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>The results revealed that some S100A7-positive cells displayed co-localization with keratin-13-positive cells, but others were not (Fig 7A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>In HCC94 xenograft, a distinct squamous differentiation phenotype, with clear stratum basale, stratum spinosum and stratum granulosum was found because HCC94 is a well-differentiated cervical squamous carcinoma cell line and becomes well-differentiated in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Notably, S100A7-positive staining in the stratum spinosum and stratum granulosum was distributed in the both cytoplasm and/or nucleus, but in the stratum basale, staining occurred only in the nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Keratin-13 demonstrated a similar staining pattern in the suprabasal layer where S100A7-positive staining was found in both the cytoplasm and the nucleus, whereas keratin-13 was only detected in the cytoplasm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Importantly, some S100A7-positive cells with only nuclear staining co-expressed with Ki67 in the basal layer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>In contrast, tissue sections using nonspecific IgG as negative control showed no positive staining (Fig 7). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0128887.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128887.g006</object-id><label>Fig 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Squamous differentiation markers were also induced by suspension and confluent treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>The expression of keratin-1, keratin-13, keratin-4, TG-1 and involucrin was determined by real-time PCR for the FaDu (A); A-431(B) and HCC94 (C, F) cells after suspension or confluent culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>The protein level of keratin-13 was confirmed by Western blotting for the FaDu (D) and HCC94 (E) cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>S48h: suspension 48h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>N: pre-suspension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>C6: cells were cultured at confluence for six days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>C6-R3P: cells were cultured at confluence for six days and then reseeded at sub-confluence for 3 cell passages. *, p&lt;0.05, and **, p&lt;0.01 versus the S100A7 experiential groups and the control groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>The results represent the average values from three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0128887.g006"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0128887.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128887.g007</object-id><label>Fig 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>The relationship of S100A7 and keratin-13 expression was examined by immunofluorescence and by immunohistochemistry. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>The expression of keratin-13 and S100A7 in HCC94 cells was examined by immunofluorescence (A) and in HCC94 xenografts (B) by immunohistochemistry with specific antibody (B, Top panel) in the consecutive sections, and nonspecific IgG (B, Bottom panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Box areas indicate the positive staining of keratin 13, S100A7 and Ki67 in the basal and suprabasal layers of xenograft. ‘B’ indicates stratum basale; ‘S’ indicates stratum spinosum; ‘G’ indicates stratum granulosum. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0128887.g007"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="sec020"><title><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>S100A7 promotes squamous cell carcinoma proliferation and survival and inhibits squamous cell differentiation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>The above findings that the expression of S100A7 can be induced in SCC cells by suspension and confluent culture seem to imply that S100A7 upregulation may involve in SCC cell differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>To explore the roles of S100A7 in SCCs, S100A7 knockdown or overexpression was performed in HCC94, FaDu, and A-431 cells, depending on the endogenous levels of S100A7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>We found that the cell proliferation and survival rate of the FaDu and A-431 cells were significantly increased in the S100A7 overexpressed group compared to the control group (Fig 8A, 8B and 8D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Converse results were obtained in the HCC94 cells with silencing of S100A7 (Fig 8C and 8E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>In parallel, the expression of the differentiation-specific markers keratin-4, keratin-13, TG-1, and involucrin were significantly increased by S100A7 knockdown and decreased by S100A7 overexpression (Fig 7F–7L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Silencing or overexpression of S100A7 and the expression of keratin-13 were also confirmed by Western blot (Fig 8M, 8N and 8O). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>To gain further insight into the function of S100A7 in vivo, the stable-overexpressing S100A7-A431 cells and control cells were implanted into the left and right flank areas of nude mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Similar results were also obtained in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>The overexpression of S100A7 significantly promoted tumor growth and decreased the expression of cytokeratin-1, TG-1, and involucrin in A-431 xenografts compared with the control animals (Fig 8P–8S). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Taken together the above results indicate that S100A7 expression promotes SCC cell proliferation and inhibits cell differentiation in the tested cell lines. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone.0128887.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128887.g008</object-id><label>Fig 8</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>S100A7 promotes squamous carcinoma cell growth and inhibits squamous cells differentiation both in vitro and in vivo. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>The proliferation and the survival rate of SCC cells were evaluated by MTT (A, B, C) and XTT (D, E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>The expression of differentiation markers was determined by real-time PCR (F-L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>The expressions of S100A7 and keratin-13 after overexpression or knockdown S100A7 in SCC cells were confirmed by Western blotting (M, N, O). ‘NC’ stands for mock-transfected cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>The volumes of tumor xenografts derived from the stable-overexpressing S100A7-A431 cells and the control cells (P). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>The expression of differentiation markers in xenografts was examined by real-time PCR (Q-S). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>The stable-overexpressing S100A7 in A-431 cells was confirmed by Western blotting (T). *, p&lt;0.05, and **, p&lt;0.01 versus the S100A7 experiential groups and the control groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>The results represent the average values from six independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0128887.g008"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec021"><title><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we examined the expression of S100A7 in 452 SCC specimens, including the lung, esophagus, bladder, cervix, oral cavity, and skin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>The results demonstrated that S100A7 expression occurred in the majority of SCC tissues, with stronger staining in well-differentiated tissues or well-differentiated areas within one section. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>In addition, this is the first report that S100A7 is also expressed in SCCs of the esophagus and cervix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>These results strongly suggest that S100A7 may be a common marker of SCCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Further examination found that the heterogeneity of S100A7 existed in all S100A7-positive specimens, and S100A7 appeared in a patchy or scattered distribution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the heterogeneity of S100A7 was also detected in cultured A-431, FaDu, and HCC94 cells and in their corresponding xenografts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>The heterogeneity of the S100A7 in the SCC cells and SCC tissues may be because of the origin of the SCCs, which arise from multilayered epithelia that undergo continuous self-renewal in a basal layer and differentiate to a superficial direction under normal conditions [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the heterogeneity of S100A7 may be caused by the cellular heterogeneity within SCC tissues or cultured cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we found that the expression of S100A7 was dramatically induced in all tested SCC cell lines both in vitro and in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>We suggest two reasons for this difference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>First, is the proliferation of S100A7-positive cells in vivo, and second, is S100A7 induction in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>In support of this hypothesis are our results showing that S100A7-positive cells are significantly induced by confluent and suspension cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, S100A7-positive cells also become negative cells when the inducer is removed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that S100A7-negative and–positive cells might directionally convert to each other depending on the microenvironment, such as cell density or suspension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>In addition, we also found that S100A7-positive cells could generate the same positive cells only for limited cell passages in vitro (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Taken together, our results indicate that S100A7-positive cells are induced both in vitro and in vivo, either by proliferation or induction or both. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Although S100A7 and differentiation-specific markers both were inducible expression by confluent and suspension cultures, even in vivo, we found that cell proliferation, survival rate, and/or tumor growth were significantly increased in S100A7 overexpressing cells, whereas the expression differentiation-specific markers was markedly decreased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Conversely, inhibition of cell proliferation and upregulation of differentiation markers were detected by silencing of S100A7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that both endogenous and ectopic expression of S100A7 plays the similar role in promoting the growth and inhibiting the differentiation of squamous cancer cells, at least for our tested SCC cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>In addition, overexpressing S100A7 in A-431 cells could dramatically inhibit the induction of differentiation markers by suspension (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Our unpublished results demonstrated that S100A7 acts as a dual regulator in promoting proliferation and suppressing squamous differentiation through the GATA-3/caspase-14 pathway in A-431 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, S100A8 and S100A9, two members of the S100 family, display the similar expression and function in SCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that the expression of S100A8/A9 was positively correlated with differentiation in clinical SCC tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>However, in SCC12 cells, overexpressing S100A8 and/or S100A9 had increased proliferation and cell migration capacity in vitro and also showed increased tumor growth in vivo in SCID mice [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we conclude that the expression and function of S100A7 are highly cell-type-specific and its functions range from regulating cell proliferation and differentiation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we have demonstrated that S100A7 is a common marker of squamous cell carcinomas and displays the cellular heterogeneity in SCC tissues and cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>In addition, S100A7-positive cells could be inducible in SCC cell lines both in vitro and in vivo depending on the microenvironments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>S100A7 acts as a dual regulator in promoting cell growth and inhibiting cell differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Further elucidation of the molecular mechanisms of S100A7 induction and its exact role in cell differentiation are ongoing in our laboratory. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>No potential conflicts of interest were disclosed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec022"><title><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0128887.s001"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>The expression of keratin-4 and keratin-13 in A-431 cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0128887.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0128887.s002"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Primers used for each of the genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>(DOC) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0128887.s002.doc"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0128887.ref001"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>1 RheinwaldJG, BeckettMA. Defective terminal differentiation in culture as a consistent and selectable character of malignant human keratinocytes. Cell 1980;22:629–32. <?supplied-pmid 6160916?>6160916 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref002"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>2 ScottRE, WilkeMS, WilleJJJr, PittelkowMR, HsuBM, KasperbauerJL. Human Squamous Carcinoma Cells Express Complex Defects in the Control of Proliferation and Differentiation. Am J Pathol 1988;133:374–80. <?supplied-pmid 3056022?>3056022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref003"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>3 KulshiJK, LimCP, DunnDS, BellqardM. Genomic and phylogenetic analysis of the S100A7 (psoriasin) gene duplications within the region of the S100 gene cluster on human chromosome 1q21. J Mol Evol 2003;56:397–406. <?supplied-pmid 12664160?>12664160 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref004"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>4 MadsenP, RasmussenHH, LeffersH, HonoreB, DejqaardK, OlsenE, et al Molecular cloning, occurrence, and expression of a novel partially secreted protein "psoriasin" that is highly up-regulated in psoriatic skin. J Invest Dermatol 1991;97:701–712. <?supplied-pmid 1940442?>1940442 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref005"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>5 LeeKC, EckertRL. S100A7 (psoriasin) mechanism of antibacterial action in wounds. J Invest Dermatol 2007;127:945–957. <?supplied-pmid 17159909?>17159909 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref006"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>6 NasserMW, QamriZ, DeolYS, RaviJ, PowellCA, TrikhaP, et al S100A7 enhances mammary tumorigenesis through upregulation of inflammatory pathways. Cancer Res 2012;72:604–15. 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-11-0669 <?supplied-pmid 22158945?>22158945 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref007"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>7 CelisJE, RasmussenHH, VorumH, MadsenP, HonoreB, WolfH, et al Bladder squamous cell carcinomas express psoriasin and externalize it to the urine. J Urol 1996;155:2105–2112. <?supplied-pmid 8618345?>8618345 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref008"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>8 MoubayedN, WeichenthalM, HarderJ, WandelE, SticherlingM, GlaserR, et al Psoriasin (S100A7) is significantly up-regulated in human epithelial skin tumours. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 2007;133:253–261. <?supplied-pmid 17136347?>17136347 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref009"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>9 EmberleyED, MurphyLC, WatsonPH. S100A7 and the progression of breast cancer. Breast Cancer Res 2004;6:153–159. <?supplied-pmid 15217486?>15217486 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref010"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>10 Al-HaddadS, ZhangZ, LeyqueE, SnellL, HuangA, NiuY, et al Psoriasin (S100A7) expression and invasive breast cancer. Am J Pathol 1999;155:2057–2066. <?supplied-pmid 10595935?>10595935 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref011"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>11 AlowamiS, QingG, EmberleyE, SnellL, WatsonPH. Psoriasin (S100A7) expression is altered during skin tumorigenesis. BMC Dermatol 2003;3:1 <?supplied-pmid 12600274?>12600274 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref012"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>12 KestingMR, SudhoffH, HaslerRJ, NieberlerM, PautkeC, WolffKD, et al Psoriasin (S100A7) up-regulation in oral squamous cell carcinoma and its relation to clinicopathologic features. Oral Oncol 2009;45:731–736. 10.1016/j.oraloncology.2008.11.012 <?supplied-pmid 19147391?>19147391 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref013"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>13 TripathiSC, MattaA, KaurJ, GriqullJ, ChauhanSS, ThakarA, et al Nuclear S100A7 is associated with poor prognosis in head and neck cancer. PLos ONE 2010;5:8. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref014"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>14 BarbieriMR, AndradeCD, SilvaWAJr, MarquesAA, LeopoldinoAM, MontesMB, et al Expression of human protein S100A7 (psoriasin), preparation of antibody and application to human larynx squamous cell carcinoma. BMC Res 2011; 4:494 10.1186/1756-0500-4-494 <?supplied-pmid 22082027?>22082027 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref015"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>15 LeygueE, SnellL, HillerT, DotzlawH, HoleK, MurphyLC, et al Differential expression of psoriasin messenger RNA between in situ and invasive human breast carcinoma. Cancer Res 1996;56:4606–4609. <?supplied-pmid 8840971?>8840971 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref016"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>16 EmberleyED, AlowamiS, SnellL, MurphyLC, WatsonPH. S100A7 (psoriasin) expression is associated with aggressive features and alteration of Jab1 in ductal carcinoma in situ of the breast. Breast Cancer Res 2004;6:308–315. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref017"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>17 KaurJ, MattaA, KakI, SrivastavaG, AssiJ, LeongI, et al S100A7 overexpression is a predictive marker for high risk of malignant transformation in oral dysplasia. Int J Cancer 2014;15:1379–1388. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref018"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>18 OstergaardM, RasmussenHH, NielsenHV, VorumH, PrntoftTF, WolfH, et al Proteome profiling of bladder squamous cell carcinomas: identification of markers that define their degree of differentiation. Cancer Res 1997; 57:4111–4117. <?supplied-pmid 9307301?>9307301 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref019"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>19 MartinssonH, YhrM, EnerbäckC. Expression patterns of S100A7 (psoriasin) and S100A9 (calgranulin-B) in keratinocyte differentiation. Exp Dermatol 2005; 14:161–168. <?supplied-pmid 15740587?>15740587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref020"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>20 ZhangH, ZhaoQ, ChenY, WangY, GaoS, MaoY, et al Selective expression of S100A7 in lung squamous cell carcinomas and large cell carcinomas but not in adenocarcinomas and small cell carcinomas. Thorax 2008;63:352–359. 10.1136/thx.2007.087015 <?supplied-pmid 18364444?>18364444 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref021"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>21 ZhangH, WangY, ChenY, SunS, LiN, LvD, et al Identification and validation of S100A7 associated with lung squamous cell carcinoma metastasis to brain. Lung Cancer 2007;57:37–45. <?supplied-pmid 17418446?>17418446 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref022"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>22 QianZ, LiM, WangR, XiaoQ, WangJ, LiM, et al Knockdown of CABYR-a/b Increases Chemosensitivity of Human Non–Small Cell Lung Cancer Cells through Inactivation of Akt. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Cancer Res 2014;12:335–347. 10.1158/1541-7786.MCR-13-0391 <?supplied-pmid 24362251?>24362251 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref023"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>23 XuA, HaoJ, ZhangZ, TianT, JiangS, HaoJ, et al 14-kDa phosphohistidine phosphatase and its role its role in human lung cancer cell migration and invasion. Lung Cancer 2010;67:48–56. 10.1016/j.lungcan.2009.03.005 <?supplied-pmid 19344975?>19344975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref024"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>24 ChanvorachoteP, NimmannitU, LuY, TalbottS, JiangBH, RojanasakulY. Nitric Oxide Regulates Lung Carcinoma Cell Anoikis through Inhibition of Ubiquitin-Proteasomal Degradation of Caveolin-1. J Biol Chem 2009;284: 28476–28484. 10.1074/jbc.M109.050864 <?supplied-pmid 19706615?>19706615 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref025"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>25 BloorBK, SeddonSV, MorganPR. Gene expression of differentiation-specifc keratins in oral epithelial dysplasia and squamous cell carcinoma. Oral Oncology 2001;37:251–261 <?supplied-pmid 11287279?>11287279 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref026"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>26 WikramanayakeTC, StojadinovicO, Tomic-CanicM. Epidermal Differentiation in Barrier Maintenance and Wound Healing. Adv Wound Care (New Rochelle) 2014;1: 272–280. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0128887.ref027"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>27 ChoiDK, LiZJ, ChangIK, YeoMK, KimJM, SohnKC, et al Clinicopathological roles of S100A8 and S100A9 in cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma in vivo and in vitro. Arch Dermatol Res 2014;306:489–496. 10.1007/s00403-014-1453-y <?supplied-pmid 24550082?>24550082 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
