<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Neuroeng Rehabil</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Neuroeng Rehabil</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of NeuroEngineering and Rehabilitation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1743-0003</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4802889</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">138</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12984-016-0138-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Sequencing bilateral robot-assisted arm therapy and constraint-induced therapy improves reach to press and trunk kinematics in patients with stroke </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>Yu-wei</given-names></name><address><email>ywhsieh@mail.cgu.edu.tw</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liing</surname><given-names>Rong-jiuan</given-names></name><address><email>ronliing0101@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Keh-chung</given-names></name><address><email>kehchunglin@ntu.edu.tw</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4726-2916</contrib-id><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Ching-yi</given-names></name><address><phone>886-3-211-8800</phone><email>cywu@mail.cgu.edu.tw</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liou</surname><given-names>Tsan-hon</given-names></name><address><email>peter_liou@tmu.edu.tw</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Jui-chi</given-names></name><address><email>08175@s.tmu.edu.tw</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>Jen-wen</given-names></name><address><email>hung0702@adm.cgmh.org.tw</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Occupational Therapy and Graduate Institute of Behavioral Sciences, College of Medicine, and Healthy Aging Research Center, Chang Gung University, 259 Wenhua 1st Rd, Taoyuan, Taiwan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>School of Occupational Therapy, College of Medicine, National Taiwan University, Taipei, Taiwan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Division of Occupational Therapy, Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, National Taiwan University Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, Shuang Ho Hospital, Taipei Medical University, Taipei, Taiwan </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label/>Department of Rehabilitation, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital-Kaohsiung Medical Center, Kaohsiung, Taiwan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>31</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Hsieh et al. 2016</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The combination of robot-assisted therapy (RT) and a modified form of constraint-induced therapy (mCIT) shows promise for improving motor function of patients with stroke. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>However, whether the changes of motor control strategies are concomitant with the improvements in motor function after combination of RT and mCIT (RT + mCIT) is unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>This study investigated the effects of the sequential combination of RT + mCIT compared with RT alone on the strategies of motor control measured by kinematic analysis and on motor function and daily performance measured by clinical scales. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The study enrolled 34 patients with chronic stroke. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The data were derived from part of a single-blinded randomized controlled trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Participants in the RT + mCIT and RT groups received 20 therapy sessions (90 to 105 min/day, 5 days for 4 weeks). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Patients in the RT + mCIT group received 10 RT sessions for first 2 weeks and 10 mCIT sessions for the next 2 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The Bi-Manu-Track was used in RT sessions to provide bilateral practice of wrist and forearm movements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The primary outcome was kinematic variables in a task of reaching to press a desk bell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Secondary outcomes included scores on the Wolf Motor Function Test, Functional Independence Measure, and Nottingham Extended Activities of Daily Living. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>All outcome measures were administered before and after intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>RT + mCIT and RT demonstrated different benefits on motor control strategies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>RT + mCIT uniquely improved motor control strategies by reducing shoulder abduction, increasing elbow extension, and decreasing trunk compensatory movement during the reaching task. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Motor function and quality of the affected limb was improved, and patients achieved greater independence in instrumental activities of daily living. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Force generation at movement initiation was improved in the patients who received RT. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>A combination of RT and mCIT could be an effective approach to improve stroke rehabilitation outcomes, achieving better motor control strategies, motor function, and functional independence of instrumental activities of daily living. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Trial registration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>ClinicalTrials.gov. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01727648">NCT01727648</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Stroke</kwd><kwd>Sequential combination therapy</kwd><kwd>Robotic rehabilitation</kwd><kwd>Constraint-induced</kwd><kwd>Upper extremity</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100004663</institution-id><institution>Ministry of Science and Technology, Taiwan</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>103-2314-B-182-002</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>Yu-wei</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100004663</institution-id><institution>Ministry of Science and Technology, Taiwan</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>102-2628-B-182-005-MY3</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Ching-yi</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100004737</institution-id><institution>National Health Research Institutes</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NHRI-EX104-10403PI</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Keh-chung</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Healthy Ageing Research Center at Chang Gung University</institution></funding-source><award-id>EMRPD1E1711</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Ching-yi</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100005795</institution-id><institution>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Linkou</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>CMRPD1B0332 and CMRPD1C0403</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Ching-yi</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100004663</institution-id><institution>Ministry of Science and Technology, Taiwan</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>102-2314-B-002-154-MY2</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Keh-chung</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Stroke remains a leading cause of permanent motor disability worldwide [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Persistent impairment of the upper extremity (UE) occurs in up to two-thirds of patients after stroke [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>UE paresis can lead to deficits in motor control [3], motor dysfunction [4], and participation in activities of daily living (ADL) [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Developing and providing effective therapeutic techniques to improve UE motor control and recovery is crucial. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Robot-assisted therapy (RT) is an emerging intervention approach that provides high-intensity, high-repetition, and task-specific training to enhance motor learning and control in patients with stroke [6, 7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Systemic reviews have indicated that RT improves UE muscle strength and motor function of patients with moderate to severe motor impairment after stroke [8, 9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>A recent review suggested that the assessment of movement kinematics should be included in RT studies to identify modulation in motor control strategies [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Previous studies found that RT can improve motor control strategies in patients with stroke, including greater movement efficacy [11–13], better movement smoothness of the affected UE [13], and more use of the preplanned control strategy [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>However, no consistent findings on patients’ participation in ADL were observed after RT [8, 14–17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>How to optimize or transfer the treatment benefits of RT on motor function and motor control strategies into participation in ADL warrants further investigation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>An approach using RT monotherapy may not optimally address this need. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Constraint-induced therapy (CIT), one most investigated approaches to rehabilitation, was developed to overcome the learned nonuse phenomenon and enhance functional use of the affected arm after stroke [18, 19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Treatment components of CIT include repetitive and intensive task practice, behavioral shaping techniques, restraint of the unaffected UE, and transfer package [20, 21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Modified and distributed CIT, which are not as intensive as the original CIT, have been developed and validated [20, 22, 23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The benefits of the original CIT and its modified versions have been well demonstrated to improve motor function, arm-hand activities, and daily performance of patients with stroke [19, 24, 25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Therapies that combine RT with other rehabilitation approaches have been developed to optimize the treatment effects of RT [26–29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The combination of RT and conventional therapy led to significant gains in arm function of patients, but different combination sequences showed benefits in different outcomes [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>In addition, RT combined with repetitive task practice was effective in enhancing hand function and stroke recovery of patients [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>To the best of our knowledge, only one study has investigated the treatment effects of sequencing the combination of RT and a modified form of CIT (mCIT) in patients with stroke [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The results indicated that the sequential combination of RT and mCIT led to better motor and functional ability measured by clinical scales compared with RT alone or conventional rehabilitation [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>However, whether the changes in motor control strategies are responsible for the improvements in motor function after the sequential combination therapy remains unclear. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Kinematic analysis has been recommended as a sound measure to provide objective and sensitive evaluations on spatial and temporal characteristics of UE movements [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>More importantly, kinematics can capture motor control strategies that cannot be detected by clinical scales [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Thus, kinematic analysis enables us to understand whether the behavioral improvement is due to a true change in the end point control and joint motion or is a result of compensation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Kinematic measures, along with clinical assessments, can better clarify the motor control strategies underlying the motor improvements of stroke patients [31, 32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>This study investigated the effects of the sequential combination of RT and mCIT (RT + mCIT), compared with RT alone, focusing on motor control strategies measured by kinematic analysis and on motor and ADL functions using clinical measures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that (1) RT + mCIT would lead to different benefits on the motor control strategies compared with and RT alone and that (2) RT + mCIT would contribute to better performances in ADL than RT alone. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The data of the current study were derived from part of a single-blinded, randomized controlled trial designed to comprehensively examine the effects of RT alone and the combination of RT and mCIT in patients with stroke. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>According to previous findings, the estimated sample size required at least 15 patients in each intervention group [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The Institutional Review Board of the National Taiwan University Hospital (IRB#201112104RIB) and Chang Gung Memorial Hospital (IRB#99-0832B) approved the study, and all participants signed an informed consent. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The study included 34 patients with stroke. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The inclusion criteria were chronic unilateral stroke (&gt;6 months poststroke), an initial Fugl-Meyer Assessment (FMA) score between 20 and 50 [33], able to perform ≥10° of wrist extension with extension of at least two fingers &gt;0° and &lt;10° and with thumb abduction ≥10° [34], without excessive spasticity in any of the UE joint (modified Ashworth scale ≤3), without UE fracture within 3 months or painful arthritis, and Mini-Mental State Examination score ≥22. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Randomization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>When a new eligible participant was registered, the participant was stratified into four strata based on the lesion side and the motor impairment level (the cutoff point was 35 in the initial core of the FMA) [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>An investigator who was not involved in the evaluation and treatment managed the randomization procedure by using a random-number table. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Sequentially numbered, sealed, and opaque envelopes containing the group sheets were prepared before the study began. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Interventions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Participants in RT + mCIT and RT groups received a similar amount of therapy time (an average of 90 to 105 min/day, 5 days for 4 consecutive weeks). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>RT group </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Participants in the RT group used the Bi-Manu-Track (Reha-Stim Co., Berlin, Germany) to perform movements of forearm pronation-supination and wrist flexion-extension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>There were three computer-controlled modes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>In the passive–passive mode, the device passively moves both arms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>In the active–passive mode, the unaffected arm actively drives the affected arm to move passively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>In the active–active mode, the affected arm has to overcome the initial resistance to allow the arm movements [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Before RT, participants had 5 to 10 min of mobilization as a warm-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Then, the RT protocol included 600 to 800 repetitions of the passive–passive and active–passive modes for 15 to 20 min and 150 to 200 repetitions of the active-active mode for 3 to 5 min [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>While the patient’s affected arm can actively perform the movements or as the patient improved, the active-passive mode was adjusted to the affected arm actively driving the unaffected arm to encourage more active movements of the affected arm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>After RT training protocol, participants practiced functional-based activities for 15 to 20 min, such as picking up coins, opening a jar, turning pages of newspaper, carrying objects, and twisting a towel, which were selected by the patient and the therapist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>RT + mCIT group </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>For the first 2 weeks, participants in RT + mCIT group received RT, using the same treatment principles as those in the RT group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>RT was followed by 2 weeks of a form of mCIT with reduced training and restraint time compared with the original CIT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Treatment components included repetitive training of the affected UE in functional tasks with behavior shaping [29, 37, 38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>A mitt was used to restrict the unaffected hand for 6 h each day [37, 38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Some strategies of transfer package applied to facilitate the use of the affected UE included behavioral contract, home diary, and problem solving mentoring [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The functional tasks included, for example, reaching to move a cup, picking up a utensil to get food, flipping pages of magazines, pouring water, wiping a table, and using a cellphone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The shaping techniques involved individualized task selection, graded task difficulty, verbal feedback, prompting, physical assistance with movements, and modeling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The level of challenge was adapted according to the patient’s ability and progress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Outcome measures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The outcome measures were administered before and after intervention by the same blinded assessor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The primary outcomes were kinematic parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>For the secondary outcomes, the Wolf Motor Function Test (WMFT), Functional Independence Measure (FIM), and Nottingham Extended Activities of Daily Living (NEADL) were used to measure the activity and participation levels [40]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Kinematic evaluation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>A task of reaching to press a desk bell was used to obtain reaching kinematic performance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The bell was placed along the participant’s midsagittal plane at a distance measured from the media border of axilla to the distal wrist crease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The participant sat on a chair in front of a table with the seat height adjusted to the lower leg’s length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The initial position of the hand was on the table edge with elbow flexed at 90°. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The participant was asked to use the index finger of the affected arm to press the bell as quickly as possible [41]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>A total of 13 markers were placed on the affected side to model arm and trunk movements, including the spinal processes of the 7th cervical vertebra (C7) and 4th thoracic vertebra (T4), midsternum, bilateral clavicular heads and acromions, the anterior aspect of the upper arm midway between the acromion and the lateral epicondyle, lateral epicondyle, styloid processes of ulna and radius, thumb nail, and the index nail. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The marker positions in 3-dimensional space were measured with a sampling rate of 120 Hz by a 7-camera motion capture system (VICON MX, Oxford Metrics Inc, Oxford, UK) and low-pass filtered at 5 Hz using a second-order Butterworth filter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>LabVIEW software (National Instruments Inc, Austin, TX) was used to process the kinematic data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Movement onset was defined as the time at which the tangential velocity rose above 5 % of the peak tangential velocity of the markers on the index nail or sternum, and movement offset was defined as the time at which the tangential velocity fell and remained below 5 % of the peak tangential velocity [31]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Clinical assessment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>We used the WMFT to quantify UE motor function of participants through 15 function-based tasks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>WMFT tasks 1 to 6 are timed joint-segment movements, and tasks 7 to 15 are timed integrative functional movements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Participants were scored based on the performance time (WMFT-TIME) and quality of movements (WMFT-Functional Ability Scale [FAS]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Reliability and validity of the WMFT-TIME and WMFT-FAS have been well established [42, 43]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The FIM was used to measure functional independence of basic ADL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>It consists six subscales, including self-care, sphincter control, transfer, locomotion, communication, and social ability [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The FIM has good inter-rater reliability, construct validity [45, 46], and discriminate validity [47] in patients with stroke. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The NEADL measures instrumental ADL function in patients with stroke [48], which may relate to quality of life after stroke [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The NEADL incorporates 22 activities contained in four subscales: mobility, domestic, leisure, and kitchen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The NEADL is a valid measure for evaluating rehabilitation efficacy [50, 51]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Data reduction for kinematic variables </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The kinematic variables used in this study were categorized into three motor control strategies: endpoint coordinate strategy, joint angle coordinate strategy, and trunk compensatory movement [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The variables to measure endpoint coordinate strategy include index movement time (Index MT), movement distance (Index Dist), peak velocity (Index PV), and the percentage of movement time at which index peak velocity occurs (Index PPV). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>These variables were computed according to the marker placed on the index nail. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Index MT was defined as the time between the onset and offset of the index movement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The direct distance of the markers placed on the index nail, calculated from index movement onset to offset during the reaching task, was termed Index Dist [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The highest instantaneous velocity during the task was defined as Index PV [38, 54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The percentage of the Index MT at which the index PV occurs represented the Index PPV [55]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The shoulder joint angle coordinate strategies can be described by the maximal angle of shoulder flexion (MaxShFlex) and the maximal shoulder abduction (MaxShAbd). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The elbow joint angle coordinate strategy can be described by the maximal angle of elbow extension (MaxElbExt). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Shoulder flexion was defined as the angle between vectors of the ipsilateral acromion-lateral epicondyle markers and the C7-T4 trunk markers on the sagittal plane (Fig. 1a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Shoulder abduction was calculated as the angle between the vectors of the ipsilateral acromion-lateral epicondyle markers and the C7-T4 trunk markers on the frontal plane (Fig. 1b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The angle between the vector defined by the lateral epicondyle and the styloid process of the ulna and the vector formed by the ipsilateral acromion-lateral epicondyle markers was defined as the elbow angle (Fig. 1a).Fig. 1Graphic representation of the angular strategy variables: (a) shoulder flexion (ShFlex) in the sagittal plane and elbow extension (ElbExt) in the sagittal plane; (b) shoulder abduction (ShAbd) in the frontal plane; and (c) trunk flexion in sagittal (TrunkFlex) plane </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Trunk compensatory movement was described by trunk MT (Trunk MT), trunk Dist (Trunk Dist), trunk PV (Trunk PV), and maximal angle of trunk flexion (MaxTrunkFlex) in the sagittal plane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>These variables were defined by the marker placed on the sternum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The time between the onset and offset of the trunk movement was defined as Trunk MT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The direct distance of the marker placed on the sternum from trunk movement onset to offset during the reaching task was defined as Trunk Dist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The highest instantaneous velocity during the reaching task was defined as Trunk PV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The angle between the vectors joining the C7-T4 markers at the trunk movement onset and offset was defined as the trunk angle (Fig. 1c). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>To compare treatment effect between the two groups, we used analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) for each variable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The baseline performance was treated as the covariate for controlling pretreatment differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>An effect size of partial η2 was calculated [56] to index the magnitude of group differences in kinematic performance and clinical scales. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The level of statistical significance was set at .05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>A total of 34 patients participated in this study, and each intervention group had 17 participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>No significant differences between the two groups were found in baseline characteristics (Table 1).Table 1Demographic and Clinical Features of the Participants for the two GroupsVariablesRT + mCITRT P Value(n = 17)(n = 17)Age (years)55.1 ± 9.452.6 ± 13.6.53Time after stroke (months)20.2 ± 13.624.8 ± 14.4.35Gender.45 Male11 (64.7)13 (76.5) Female6 (35.3)4 (23.5)Side of lesion.72 Right6 (35.3)7 (41.2) Left11 (64.7)10 (58.8)Stroke subtype.08 Ischemic8 (47.1)13 (76.5) Hemorrhagic9 (52.9)4 (23.5)Stroke site.31 Cortical10 (58.8)10 (58.8) Subcortical5 (29.4)7 (41.2) Pons2 (11.8)0 (0)Initial FMA score31.6 ± 7.535.9 ± 9.5.15NOTE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Values are mean ± SD or n (%) Abbreviations FMA Fugl-Meyer Assessment, mCIT a modified form of constraint-induced therapy, RT robot-assisted therapy, SD standard deviation </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Kinematic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Table 2 summarizes the descriptive statistics and results of the ANCOVA that tested the effects of RT + mCIT relative to RT on the kinematic variables.Table 2Descriptive and Inferential Statistics for Kinematic variablesKinematic variablesPretreatmentPosttreatmentANCOVART + mCITRTRT + mCITRT F  P Partial η 2 (n = 17)(n = 17)(n = 17)(n = 17)Endpoint coordinate strategy variables Index MT (ms)2.53 ± 1.222.17 ± 1.592.32 ± 1.281.84 ± 0.990.89.350.03 Index Dist (mm)252.28 ± 54.84241.68 ± 49.17264 ± 48.06242.61 ± 59.740.94.340.03 Index PV (mm/ms)705.7 ± 279.54724 ± 201.91700.42 ± 231.40847.84 ± 224.965.63.02*0.15 Index PPV (%)26.7 ± 18.4622.12 ± 12.9325.87 ± 13.7722.34 ± 14.620.35.560.01Angular coordinate strategy variables MaxShFlex (degree)33.22 ± 25.0227.16 ± 15.8432.36 ± 19.5229 ± 18.310.01.91&lt;0.001 MaxShAbd (degree)44.98 ± 18.2940.19 ± 14.3939.6 ± 16.4545.4 ± 13.396.10.02*0.16 MaxElbExt (degree)87.43 ± 17.9888.54 ± 17.294.01 ± 18.4384.5 ± 14.734.48.04*0.13Trunk compensatory variables Trunk MT (ms)2.66 ± 1.272.21 ± 1.632.54 ± 1.441.86 ± 1.071.58.220.05 Trunk Dist (mm)95.6 ± 51.2283.12 ± 34.1582.76 ± 30.0991.02 ± 30.985.23.03*0.14 Trunk PV (mm/ms)129.01 ± 64.14122.98 ± 41.89126.48 ± 49.91147.01 ± 43.964.51.04*0.13 MaxTrunkFlex (degree)10.72 ± 6.6910.38 ± 5.779.54 ± 5.2713.03 ± 5.397.13.01*0.19NOTE: Values are mean ± standard deviation. *P &lt; 0.05 Abbreviations Dist distance, MaxElbExt maximal angle of elbow extension, MaxShAbd maximal angle of shoulder abduction, MaxShFlex maximal angle of shoulder flexion, MaxTrunkFlex maximal angle of trunk flexion, mCIT a modified form of constraint-induced therapy, MT movement time, PPV percentage of movement time where peak velocity occurs, PV peak velocity, RT robot-assisted therapy </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The results for endpoint coordinate strategy variables showed that the Index PV in the RT + mCIT group was significantly smaller than in the RT group (P = .02). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Nonsignificant and small effects were found for the Index MT, Index Dist, and Index PPV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The RT + mCIT group showed lower movement impulse for movement initiation during the task of reaching to press the desk bell after treatment than the RT group, but the difference in relative time for online error correction was not significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The results for joint angle coordinate strategy variables showed that the MaxShAbd in RT + mCIT group was significantly smaller than in the RT group (P = .02), whereas the MaxElbExt in the RT + mCIT group was significantly greater than in the RT group (P = .04). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>For trunk compensatory movement, the results showed that the Trunk Dist, Trunk PV, and MaxTrunkFlex of the RT + mCIT group were significantly less than in the RT group (P = .03, P = .04, and P = .01, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>After treatment, the RT + mCIT group used less trunk movement and had lower trunk movement impulse for movement initiation than the RT group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>No significant difference between groups was found for Trunk MT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Compared with the RT group, patients in the RT + mCIT group extended their elbow more and recruited less trunk movements to perform the reaching task after treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>No significant group difference was found in the MaxShFlex. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Clinical assessment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The intervention effects of RT + mCIT and RT on the WMFT, NEADL, and FIM are presented in Table 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The RT + mCIT group demonstrated significantly greater improvements on WMFT-FAS and the NEADL total score than the RT group (P = .01 and P = .02, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The differences in the WMFT-TIME and the FIM total score between the two groups were not significant.Table 3Descriptive and Inferential Statistics for Clinical AssessmentsOutcomePretreatmentPosttreatmentANCOVART + mCITRTRT + mCITRT(n = 17)(n = 17)(n = 17)(n = 17) F  P Partial η 2 WMFT-FAS2.21 ± 0.42.74 ± 0.682.59 ± 0.462.89 ± 0.686.78.01*0.18WMFT-TIME6.28 ± 2.226.81 ± 5.224.84 ± 1.457.19 ± 6.662.67.110.08NEADL20.15 ± 11.2432.9 ± 14.2226.44 ± 11.8233.89 ± 15.316.35.02*0.17FIM119.47 ± 3.99116.18 ± 7.08122 ± 2.78117.53 ± 7.133.61.070.10NOTE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Values are mean ± standard deviation. *P &lt; 0.05 Abbreviations FAS functional ability score, FIM Functional Independence Measure, mCIT a modified form of constraint-induced therapy, NEADL Nottingham Extended Activities of Daily Living, RT robot-assisted therapy, SD standard deviation, WMFT Wolf Motor Function Test </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>This study is the first to investigate the changes in motor control strategies along with motor function and ADLs after RT + mCIT in patients with stroke. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Patients who received RT + mCIT or RT alone demonstrated different benefits on motor control strategies after treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Compared with the RT group, the RT + mCIT group used less shoulder abduction, more elbow extension, and less trunk compensation movement, representing restoration of better motor control strategies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the RT group showed significantly improved force generation at movement initiation than the RT + mCIT group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The RT + mCIT group achieved greater improvements than the RT group on movement quality of the affected limb (measured by the WMFT-FAS) and independence of instrumental ADL (measured by the NEADL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Better UE motor control strategies may contribute to the improvement of UE movement quality and participation in ADLs after RT + mCIT. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Benefits of RT + mCIT in kinematics relative to RT </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>RT + mCIT led to better motor control strategies by reducing shoulder abduction, increasing elbow extension, and decreasing trunk compensatory movement during the reaching task than RT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Excessive shoulder abduction and trunk movement during reaching are common compensatory movements after stroke [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Our findings suggest that RT + mCIT may promote normalized movement at the shoulder, elbow, and trunk, which may decrease compensatory movement during the reaching task. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The kinematics improvement may be associated with the improvement in endpoint coordinate control after RT, and the improvement became a preparation for subsequent mCIT, which continuously strengthen the joint angle coordinate through massed practice of the affected arm with purposeful functional activities training. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>RT provides distal movement training with a constant velocity and a high repetition of passive or active movement, which may also help prevent inappropriate compensatory strategies [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Moreover, RT + mCIT induced significant improvement on the maximal angle of elbow extension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Previous studies of RT and CIT monotherapy demonstrated beneficial effects on motor control strategy based on kinematic data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Ellis et al. also found that reaching range of motion (including elbow extension) was improved after the intervention with the ACT3D robotic device in stroke patients [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>They indicated that increased reaching ability may be attributed to the improvements in shoulder-elbow coordination or joint control after RT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>In addition, previous CIT studies found that CIT induced feedforward control strategy (more preprogrammed movement) and better spatiotemporal control of movement resulting in improvements in shorter reaction and movement time, smoother trajectories, and better joint coordination [38, 57, 59, 60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>However, CIT did not significantly improve the angle of elbow extension during reaching movements [57, 59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Extending the affected elbow when reaching outward is difficult for patients with stroke due to the strong synergistic joint torque coupling of shoulder abduction and elbow flexion [61, 62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Encouragingly, our results showed that RT + mCIT increased elbow extension and reduced shoulder abduction and trunk compensatory movement during the reaching task. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>An interaction between RT and mCIT likely led to synergistic effects on joint angle coordinate strategies and trunk compensatory movement. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Benefits of RT in kinematics relative to RT + mCIT </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Our results showed that RT led to gains on endpoint coordinate strategy, as reflected by the Index PV variable during the reaching task, suggesting that RT generated more force at movement initiation than RT + mCIT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The results agree with previous studies that showed distal upper-limb RT had significant benefits on increasing muscle strength of patients [35, 63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest that RT is crucial for enhancing force generation, which may lead to the superior effect on endpoint coordinate strategy of RT group in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Benefits of RT + mCIT in motor function and ADL as measured by clinical scales relative to RT </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The RT + mCIT group improved more on motor function measured by the WMFT-FAS than the RT group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>This finding was similar to the results of a previous study that found greater motor improvement after RT in sequential combination with mCIT than a control therapy [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The RT + mCIT group had greater improvement than the RT group in instrumental ADL function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The mean change score of the NEADL was 6.29 points, which exceeded the minimal clinically important difference (6.1 points) [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The possible explanation is that the 2-week mCIT program the patients received focused on the repeated practice of functional tasks, which facilitated transferring the gains in motor performance to instrumental ADL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Further, the improvement of instrumental ADL after RT + mCIT may also transfer to the functional use of the affected arm in executing daily activities that can be detected by the Motor Activity Log [65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Further research to incorporate the use of the Motor Activity Log to more comprehensively measure daily function of patients is suggested. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>No significant group differences were noted in basic ADL function, possibly because there may be an approaching ceiling effect on the total score of FIM in the current study, which did not leave much room for improvement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Our participants were also in the chronic phase of stroke, a phase in which basic ADL functions tend to be stable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>In addition, some strategies of CIT transfer package, such as home skill assignment and home practice, were not applied in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Transfer package is a set of strategies to facilitate the transfer of CIT treatment gains to real-life activities [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Studies showed that larger improvements with long-term effects occurred in the CIT groups that received transfer package compared with groups that did not [21, 66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Further investigation that includes whole strategies of transfer package [39] may demonstrate greater differences in daily performance between groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Study limitations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>One potential confounding factor was that the baseline NEADL score in the RT + mCIT group was significantly lower than in the RT group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Although the improved score of the RT + mCIT group on the NEADL was significantly higher than the RT group, caution is needed in interpreting the results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Secondly, the lack of a follow-up assessment might limit the understanding of potential long-term effects of combined rehabilitation therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Future research should examine the retention effects of therapeutic gains on motor control mechanisms in patients with stroke after combined interventions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Third, further research with a larger sample size is suggested to apply principal component analysis to help identify the critical components that can represent various kinematic variables and to avoid multiple comparisons of kinematic variables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Use of the ISB standards [67] is suggested for defining joint coordinate systems when reporting kinematic data, which can enhance communication among clinicians and researchers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>In addition, the robot-assisted device used in this study provided training of wrist and forearm movements only. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Further studies to investigate the effects of RT focus on the proximal versus distal portion of the UE on motor control strategies are suggested. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec22"><title><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>This study demonstrated that patients who received RT + mCIT and RT alone had different aspects of benefits on motor control strategies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>RT + mCIT uniquely improved motor control strategies of the affected limb and enhanced independence in instrumental ADL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>RT improved force generation at movement initiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>A combination of RT and mCIT contributes to improve motor control strategies, motor function, and functional independence of instrumental ADL for patients with stroke. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ADL</term><def><p>activities of daily living</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Dist</term><def><p>movement distance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FAS</term><def><p>functional ability score</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FIM</term><def><p>Functional Independence Measure</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FMA</term><def><p>Fugl-Meyer Assessment</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MaxElbExt</term><def><p>the maximal angle of elbow extension</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MaxShAbd</term><def><p>the maximal shoulder abduction in the frontal plane</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MaxShFlex</term><def><p>the maximal angle of shoulder flexion in the sagittal plane</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>mCIT</term><def><p>a modified form of constraint-induced therapy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MT</term><def><p>movement time</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NEADL</term><def><p>Nottingham Extended Activities of Daily Living</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PPV</term><def><p>percentage of movement time at which peak velocity occurs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PV</term><def><p>peak velocity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RT</term><def><p>robot-assisted therapy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RT + mCIT</term><def><p>sequential combination of robot-assisted therapy and a modified form of constraint-induced therapy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UE</term><def><p>upper extremity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WMFT</term><def><p>Wolf Motor Function Test</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The authors declare no competing interests related to this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>YWH, CYW, and KCL contributed to the study design, coordination, and project management. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>YWH interpreted data and drafted and revised the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>RJL performed the data analyses and helped to draft the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>THL and JCL participated in subject recruitment and provided consultation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>JWH conceived of the study and provided medical consultation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>All authors have read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>ᅟ </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>This project was in part supported by the National Health Research Institutes (NHRI-EX105-10403PI), the Ministry of Science and Technology (102-2628-B-182-005-MY3, 102-2314-B-002-154-MY2, 103-2314-B-182-002, and 104-2314-B-002-019-MY3), Healthy Aging Research Center at Chang Gung University (EMRPD1F0321), and Chang Gung Memorial Hospital (CMRPD1E0281, CMRPD1C0403, BMRP553, and BMRP25) in Taiwan. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>1.RogerVLGoASLloyd-JonesDMAdamsRJBerryJDBrownTMHeart disease and stroke statistics--2011 update: a report from the American Heart AssociationCirculation.2011123e1820910.1161/CIR.0b013e3182009701<?supplied-pmid 21160056?>21160056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>2.KwakkelGKollenBJWagenaarRCTherapy impact on functional recovery in stroke rehabilitation: a critical review of the literaturePhysiotherapy.1999853779110.1016/S0031-9406(05)67198-2 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>3.Alt MurphyMWillenCSunnerhagenKSKinematic variables quantifying upper-extremity performance after stroke during reaching and drinking from a glassNeurorehabil Neural Repair.201125718010.1177/1545968310370748<?supplied-pmid 20829411?>20829411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>4.BroeksJGLankhorstGJRumpingKPrevoAJThe long-term outcome of arm function after stroke: results of a follow-up studyDisabil Rehabil.1999213576410.1080/096382899297459<?supplied-pmid 10503976?>10503976 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>5.LaiSMStudenskiSDuncanPWPereraSPersisting consequences of stroke measured by the Stroke Impact ScaleStroke.2002331840410.1161/01.STR.0000019289.15440.F2<?supplied-pmid 12105363?>12105363 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>6.FasoliSEKrebsHISteinJFronteraWRHoganNEffects of robotic therapy on motor impairment and recovery in chronic strokeArch Phys Med Rehabil.2003844778210.1053/apmr.2003.50110<?supplied-pmid 12690583?>12690583 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>7.BrewerBRMcDowellSKWorthen-ChaudhariLCPoststroke upper extremity rehabilitation: a review of robotic systems and clinical resultsTop Stroke Rehabil.200714224410.1310/tsr1406-22<?supplied-pmid 18174114?>18174114 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>8.KwakkelGKollenBJKrebsHIEffects of robot-assisted therapy on upper limb recovery after stroke: a systematic reviewNeurorehabil Neural Repair.2008221112110.1177/1545968307305457<?supplied-pmid 17876068?>17876068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>9.LanghornePCouparFPollockAMotor recovery after stroke: a systematic reviewLancet Neurol.200987415410.1016/S1474-4422(09)70150-4<?supplied-pmid 19608100?>19608100 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>10.NordinNXieSQWunscheBAssessment of movement quality in robot- assisted upper limb rehabilitation after stroke: a reviewJ Neuroeng Rehabil.20141113710.1186/1743-0003-11-137<?supplied-pmid 25217124?>25217124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>11.WuCYYangCLChuangLLLinKCChenHCChenMDEffect of therapist-based versus robot-assisted bilateral arm training on motor control, functional performance, and quality of life after chronic stroke: a clinical trialPhys Ther.20129210061610.2522/ptj.20110282<?supplied-pmid 22517782?>22517782 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>12.KahnLEZygmanMLRymerWZReinkensmeyerDJRobot-assisted reaching exercise promotes arm movement recovery in chronic hemiparetic stroke: a randomized controlled pilot studyJ Neuroeng Rehabil.200631210.1186/1743-0003-3-12<?supplied-pmid 16790067?>16790067 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>13.ChangJJTungWLWuWLHuangMHSuFCEffects of robot-aided bilateral force-induced isokinetic arm training combined with conventional rehabilitation on arm motor function in patients with chronic strokeArch Phys Med Rehabil.2007881332810.1016/j.apmr.2007.07.016<?supplied-pmid 17908578?>17908578 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>14.Norouzi-GheidariNArchambaultPSFungJEffects of robot-assisted therapy on stroke rehabilitation in upper limbs: systematic review and meta-analysis of the literatureJ Rehabil Res Dev.2012494799610.1682/JRRD.2010.10.0210<?supplied-pmid 22773253?>22773253 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>15.MehrholzJHadrichAPlatzTKuglerJPohlMElectromechanical and robot-assisted arm training for improving generic activities of daily living, arm function, and arm muscle strength after strokeCochrane Database Syst Rev.20126<?supplied-pmid 22696362?>22696362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>16.ChangWHKimYHRobot-assisted therapy in stroke rehabilitationJ Stroke.2013151748110.5853/jos.2013.15.3.174<?supplied-pmid 24396811?>24396811 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>17.MehrholzJPohlMPlatzTKuglerJElsnerBElectromechanical and robot-assisted arm training for improving activities of daily living, arm function, and arm muscle strength after strokeCochrane Database Syst Rev.201511<?supplied-pmid 26559225?>26559225 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>18.TaubEMillerNENovackTACookEW3rdFlemingWCNepomucenoCSTechnique to improve chronic motor deficit after strokeArch Phys Med Rehabil.19937434754<?supplied-pmid 8466415?>8466415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>19.KwakkelGVeerbeekJMvan WegenEEWolfSLConstraint-induced movement therapy after strokeLancet Neurol.2015142243410.1016/S1474-4422(14)70160-7<?supplied-pmid 25772900?>25772900 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>20.FleetAPageSJMacKay-LyonsMBoeSGModified constraint-induced movement therapy for upper extremity recovery post stroke: what is the evidence?Top Stroke Rehabil.2014213193110.1310/tsr2104-319<?supplied-pmid 25150664?>25150664 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>21.TaubEUswatteGMarkVWMorrisDMBarmanJBowmanMHMethod for enhancing real-world use of a more affected arm in chronic stroke: transfer package of constraint-induced movement therapyStroke.2013441383810.1161/STROKEAHA.111.000559<?supplied-pmid 23520237?>23520237 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>22.DettmersCTeskeUHamzeiFUswatteGTaubEWeillerCDistributed form of constraint-induced movement therapy improves functional outcome and quality of life after strokeArch Phys Med Rehabil.200586204910.1016/j.apmr.2004.05.007<?supplied-pmid 15706544?>15706544 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>23.PageSJLevinePLeonardASzaflarskiJPKisselaBMModified constraint-induced therapy in chronic stroke: results of a single-blinded randomized controlled trialPhys Ther.2008883334010.2522/ptj.20060029<?supplied-pmid 18174447?>18174447 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>24.StevensonTThalmanLChristieHPoluhaWConstraint-induced movement therapy compared to dose-matched interventions for upper-limb dysfunction in adult survivors of stroke: a systematic review with meta-analysisPhysiother Can.20126439741310.3138/ptc.2011-24<?supplied-pmid 23997396?>23997396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>25.ThraneGFriborgOAnkeAIndredavikBA meta-analysis of constraint-induced movement therapy after strokeJ Rehabil Med.2014468334210.2340/16501977-1859<?supplied-pmid 25182341?>25182341 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>26.HesseSWaldnerAMehrholzJTomelleriCPohlMWernerCCombined transcranial direct current stimulation and robot-assisted arm training in subacute stroke patients: an exploratory, randomized multicenter trialNeurorehabil Neural Repair.2011258384610.1177/1545968311413906<?supplied-pmid 21825004?>21825004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>27.BrokawEBNicholsDHolleyRJLumPSRobotic therapy provides a stimulus for upper limb motor recovery after stroke that is complementary to and distinct from conventional therapyNeurorehabil Neural Repair.2014283677610.1177/1545968313510974<?supplied-pmid 24297763?>24297763 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>28.KutnerNGZhangRButlerAJWolfSLAlbertsJLQuality-of-life change associated with robotic-assisted therapy to improve hand motor function in patients with subacute stroke: a randomized clinical trialPhys Ther.20109049350410.2522/ptj.20090160<?supplied-pmid 20185616?>20185616 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>29.HsiehYWLinKCHorngYSWuCYWuTCKuFLSequential combination of robot-assisted therapy and constraint-induced therapy in stroke rehabilitation: a randomized controlled trialJ Neurol.201426110374510.1007/s00415-014-7345-4<?supplied-pmid 24748465?>24748465 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>30.NowakDAThe impact of stroke on the performance of grasping: usefulness of kinetic and kinematic motion analysisNeurosci Biobehav Rev.20083214395010.1016/j.neubiorev.2008.05.021<?supplied-pmid 18582943?>18582943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>31.LevinMFKleimJAWolfSLWhat do motor "recovery" and "compensation" mean in patients following stroke?Neurorehabil Neural Repair.200923313910.1177/1545968308328727<?supplied-pmid 19118128?>19118128 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>32.van DokkumLHauretIMottetDFrogerJMetrotJLaffontIThe contribution of kinematics in the assessment of upper limb motor recovery early after strokeNeurorehabil Neural Repair.20142841210.1177/1545968313498514<?supplied-pmid 23911973?>23911973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>33.Fugl-MeyerARJaaskoLLeymanIOlssonSSteglindSThe post-stroke hemiplegic patient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>1. a method for evaluation of physical performanceScand J Rehabil Med197571331<?supplied-pmid 1135616?>1135616 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>34.TaubEUswatteGBowmanMHMarkVWDelgadoABrysonCConstraint-induced movement therapy combined with conventional neurorehabilitation techniques in chronic stroke patients with plegic hands: a case seriesArch Phys Med Rehabil.201394869410.1016/j.apmr.2012.07.029<?supplied-pmid 22922823?>22922823 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>35.HesseSWernerCPohlMRueckriemSMehrholzJLingnauMLComputerized arm training improves the motor control of the severely affected arm after stroke: a single-blinded randomized trial in two centersStroke.2005361960610.1161/01.STR.0000177865.37334.ce<?supplied-pmid 16109908?>16109908 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>36.HsiehYWWuCYLinKCYaoGWuKYChangYJDose–response relationship of robot-assisted stroke motor rehabilitation: the impact of initial motor statusStroke.20124327293410.1161/STROKEAHA.112.658807<?supplied-pmid 22895994?>22895994 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>37.LinKCWuCYLiuJSChenYTHsuCJConstraint-induced therapy versus dose-matched control intervention to improve motor ability, basic/extended daily functions, and quality of life in strokeNeurorehabil Neural Repair.200923160510.1177/1545968308320642<?supplied-pmid 18981188?>18981188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>38.WuCYChenCLTangSFLinKCHuangYYKinematic and clinical analyses of upper-extremity movements after constraint-induced movement therapy in patients with stroke: a randomized controlled trialArch Phys Med Rehabil.2007889647010.1016/j.apmr.2007.05.012<?supplied-pmid 17678656?>17678656 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>39.MorrisDMTaubEMarkVWConstraint-induced movement therapy: characterizing the intervention protocolEura Medicophys.20064225768<?supplied-pmid 17039224?>17039224 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>40.World Health OrganizationInternational classification of functioning, disability and health: ICF2001GenevaWorld Health Organization </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>41.DeJongSLSchaeferSYLangCENeed for speed: better movement quality during faster task performance after strokeNeurorehabil Neural Repair.2012263627310.1177/1545968311425926<?supplied-pmid 22140198?>22140198 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>42.WolfSLCatlinPAEllisMArcherALMorganBPiacentinoAAssessing Wolf motor function test as outcome measure for research in patients after strokeStroke.2001321635910.1161/01.STR.32.7.1635<?supplied-pmid 11441212?>11441212 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>43.MorrisDMUswatteGCragoJECookEW3rdTaubEThe reliability of the Wolf motor function test for assessing upper extremity function after strokeArch Phys Med Rehabil.200182750510.1053/apmr.2001.23183<?supplied-pmid 11387578?>11387578 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>44. Hamilton BB, Granger, CV, Sherwin FS, Zielezny M, Tashman JS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Rehabilitation outcomes: analysis and measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>In: Fuhrer MJ, editor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>A uniform national data system for medical rehabilitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Baltimore, MD: Brookes; 1987. p. 137–47. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>45.ChauNDalerSAndreJMPatrisAInter-rater agreement of two functional independence scales: the Functional Independence Measure (FIM) and a subjective uniform continuous scaleDisabil Rehabil.199416637110.3109/09638289409166014<?supplied-pmid 8043886?>8043886 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>46.HamiltonBBLaughlinJAFiedlerRCGrangerCVInterrater reliability of the 7-level functional independence measure (FIM)Scand J Rehabil Med.1994261159<?supplied-pmid 7801060?>7801060 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>47.Gosman-HedstromGSvenssonEParallel reliability of the functional independence measure and the Barthel ADL indexDisabil Rehabil.2000227021510.1080/09638280050191972<?supplied-pmid 11117590?>11117590 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>48.NouriFMLincolnNBAn extended activities of daily living scale for stroke patientsClin Rehabil.19871301510.1177/026921558700100409 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>49.SveenUThommessenBBautz-HolterEWyllerTBLakkeKWell-being and instrumental activities of daily living after strokeClin Rehabil.2004182677410.1191/0269215504cr719oa<?supplied-pmid 15137558?>15137558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>50.HsuehIPHuangSLChenMHJushSDHsiehCLEvaluation of stroke patients with the extended activities of daily living scale in TaiwanDisabil Rehabil.20002249550010.1080/096382800413989<?supplied-pmid 10972353?>10972353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>51.WuCYChuangLLLinKCHorngYSResponsiveness and validity of two outcome measures of instrumental activities of daily living in stroke survivors receiving rehabilitative therapiesClin Rehabil.2011251758310.1177/0269215510385482<?supplied-pmid 21059664?>21059664 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>52.Shumway-cookAWoollacottMHLupashENormal reach, grasp, and manipulationMotor control: translating research into clnical practice20124PhiladelphiaLippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins55294 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>53.WuCYLinKCChenHCChenIHHongWHEffects of modified constraint-induced movement therapy on movement kinematics and daily function in patients with stroke: a kinematic study of motor control mechanismsNeurorehabil Neural Repair.200721460610.1177/1545968307303411<?supplied-pmid 17601803?>17601803 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>54.FlashTHoganNThe coordination of arm movements: an experimentally confirmed mathematical modelJ Neurosci.198551688703<?supplied-pmid 4020415?>4020415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>55.HaalandKYPrestopnikJLKnightRTLeeRRHemispheric asymmetries for kinematic and positional aspects of reachingBrain.200412711455810.1093/brain/awh133<?supplied-pmid 15033898?>15033898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>56.CohenJStatistical power analysis for the behavior sciences19882Hillsdale, NJErlbaum </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>57.MassieCMalcolmMPGreeneDThautMThe effects of constraint-induced therapy on kinematic outcomes and compensatory movement patterns: an exploratory studyArch Phys Med Rehabil.200990571910.1016/j.apmr.2008.09.574<?supplied-pmid 19345771?>19345771 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>58.EllisMDSukal-MoultonTDewaldJPProgressive shoulder abduction loading is a crucial element of arm rehabilitation in chronic strokeNeurorehabil Neural Repair.200923862910.1177/1545968309332927<?supplied-pmid 19454622?>19454622 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>59.CaimmiMCardaSGiovanzanaCMainiESSabatiniAMSmaniaNUsing kinematic analysis to evaluate constraint-induced movement therapy in chronic stroke patientsNeurorehabil Neural Repair.20082231910.1177/1545968307302923<?supplied-pmid 17595381?>17595381 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>60.LinKCWuCYWeiTHLeeCYLiuJSEffects of modified constraint-induced movement therapy on reach-to-grasp movements and functional performance after chronic stroke: a randomized controlled studyClin Rehabil.20072110758610.1177/0269215507079843<?supplied-pmid 18042603?>18042603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>61.BeerRFGivenJDDewaldJPTask-dependent weakness at the elbow in patients with hemiparesisArch Phys Med Rehabil.1999807667210.1016/S0003-9993(99)90225-3<?supplied-pmid 10414760?>10414760 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>62.EllisMDAcostaAMYaoJDewaldJPPosition-dependent torque coupling and associated muscle activation in the hemiparetic upper extremityExp Brain Res.200717659460210.1007/s00221-006-0637-x<?supplied-pmid 16924488?>16924488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>63.LumPSBurgarCGShorPCMajmundarMVan der LoosMRobot-assisted movement training compared with conventional therapy techniques for the rehabilitation of upper-limb motor function after strokeArch Phys Med Rehabil.200283952910.1053/apmr.2001.33101<?supplied-pmid 12098155?>12098155 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>64.WuCYChuangLLLinKCLeeSDHongWHResponsiveness, minimal detectable change, and minimal clinically important difference of the Nottingham Extended Activities of Daily Living Scale in patients with improved performance after stroke rehabilitationArch Phys Med Rehabil.2011921281710.1016/j.apmr.2011.03.008<?supplied-pmid 21807147?>21807147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>65.UswatteGTaubEMorrisDLightKThompsonPAThe Motor Activity Log-28: assessing daily use of the hemiparetic arm after strokeNeurology.20066711899410.1212/01.wnl.0000238164.90657.c2<?supplied-pmid 17030751?>17030751 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>66.TakebayashiTKoyamaTAmanoSHanadaKTabusadaniMHosomiMA 6-month follow-up after constraint-induced movement therapy with and without transfer package for patients with hemiparesis after stroke: a pilot quasi-randomized controlled trialClin Rehabil.2013274182610.1177/0269215512460779<?supplied-pmid 23036841?>23036841 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>67.WuGvan der HelmFCVeegerHEMakhsousMVan RoyPAnglinCISB recommendation on definitions of joint coordinate systems of various joints for the reporting of human joint motion--Part II: shoulder, elbow, wrist and handJ Biomech.2005389819210.1016/j.jbiomech.2004.05.042<?supplied-pmid 15844264?>15844264 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
