<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ImpactJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Oncotarget</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1949-2553</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Impact Journals LLC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4480729</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25762645</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Tetraspanin CD9 determines invasiveness and tumorigenicity of human breast cancer cells </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Rappa</surname><given-names>Germana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>Toni M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Karbanová</surname><given-names>Jana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Corbeil</surname><given-names>Denis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lorico</surname><given-names>Aurelio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><sup>1</sup> Cancer Research Center, Roseman University of Health Sciences with Roseman University College of Medicine, Las Vegas, NV, USA</aff><aff id="A2"><sup>2</sup> Tissue Engineering Laboratories (BIOTEC) and DFG Research Center and Cluster of Excellence for Regenerative Therapies Dresden, Technische Universität Dresden, Tatzberg, Dresden, Germany</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold><italic>Correspondence to:</italic></bold><italic>Aurelio Lorico,</italic><email>alorico@roseman.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>10</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>7970</fpage><lpage>7991</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2015 Rappa et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Interaction of breast cancer cells (BCCs) with stromal components is critical for tumor growth and metastasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Here, we assessed the role of CD9 in adhesion, migration and invasiveness of BCCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>We used co-cultures of BCCs and bone marrow-derived multipotent mesenchymal stromal cells (MSCs), and analyzed their behavior and morphology by dynamic total internal reflection fluorescence, confocal and scanning electron microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>83, 16 and 10% of contacts between MDA-MB-231 (MDA), MA-11 or MCF-7 cells and MSCs, respectively, resulted in MSC invasion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>MDA cells developed long magnupodia, lamellipodia and dorsal microvilli, whereas long microvilli emerged from MA-11 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>MCF-7 cells displayed large dorsal ruffles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>CD9 knockdown and antibody blockage in MDA cells inhibited MSC invasion by 95 and 70%, respectively, suggesting that CD9 is required for this process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, CD9-deficient MDA cells displayed significant alteration of their plasma membrane, harboring numerous peripheral and dorsal membrane ruffles instead of intact magnupodium/lamellipodium and microvillus, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Such modification might explain the delayed adhesion, and hence MSC invasion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In agreement with this hypothesis, CD9-knockdown suppressed the metastatic capacity of MDA cells in mouse xenografts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Our data indicate that CD9 is implicated in BCC invasiveness and metastases by cellular mechanisms that involve specific CD9+ plasma membrane protrusions of BCCs. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>breast cancer</kwd><kwd>CD9</kwd><kwd>cell invasion</kwd><kwd>plasma membrane protrusions</kwd><kwd>tetraspanin</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The formation of breast cancer metastases requires an interaction in the tumor microenvironment between malignant epithelia and local stroma [1, 2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>In order to adhere to, communicate with, and transfer materials to/from stromal cells, breast cancer cells (BCCs) often employ different types of plasma membrane protrusions (PMPs), including filopodia and lamellipodia [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Some of these PMPs are also instrumental for BCCs to spread and reach distant sites, helping them to move between, and invade, stromal cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>In addition to passing through intercellular gap junctions, BCCs can use a transcellular route for intra/extra-vasation, essential steps of the metastatic process [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Cancer cell invasion is also at the basis of entosis, cell-in-cell structures observed in a variety of tumors [5], and of the formation of hybrid cancer cells by cell-cell fusion, which contributes to aneuploidy and aberrant gene expression patterns [6-11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Tetraspanin-29 (CD9, motility-related protein-1) is involved in the metastatic process and depending on the context as a metastasis suppressor or promoter [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Physiologically, it is involved in cell fusion, adhesion, motility, proliferation, and signaling [13] and is required for egg-sperm fusion leading to fertilization [14, 15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>CD9 has also an important role in muscle cell fusion [16] and in canine distemper virus and HIV-1-induced cell-cell fusion [17, 18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Based on its physiological importance and its putative involvement in cancer metastasis, we sought to investigate whether CD9 has a role in the cellular interaction between human BCCs and bone marrow-derived multipotent mesenchymal stromal cells (MSCs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>We found that CD9 is expressed on diverse types of PMPs of BCCs, and is required for MSC invasion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>CD9 disruption resulted in profound alterations of plasma membrane of BCCs in vitro, including the impaired formation of magnupodium, lamellipodium and microvillus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Upon transplantation of CD9-deficient cells in a murine model, an inhibition of tumor growth was observed after one week as well as a partial loss of metastatic capacity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>These novel CD9 functions could be exploited to develop innovative breast cancer therapeutic strategies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2_1"><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Differential expression of CD9 among BCC lines </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In this study, we used three distinct cell lines to investigate the implication of CD9 in BCC invasiveness and tumorigenicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Its cell surface expression was monitored by flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>MDA-MB-231 and MCF-7 BCCs displayed a heterogeneous expression of CD9 which comprised 74, 19 and 59% of total cells, respectively (Fig. 1A, blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The differential CD9 expression among cell lines is also observed at mRNA levels (Fig. 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Although the underlying cause of such heterogeneous expression is unknown, we observed conversion in culture of CD9+ into CD9− cells and vice versa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Indeed, upon sorting of CD9+ and CD9− MDA cell fraction (&gt;99.8 % pure) from an exponential culture growth and their subsequent culture for 6 or 12 days, both cell fractions reformed mixed population with a ratio similar to parental MDA cells (Fig. 1C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Expression and functions of CD9 in BCCs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>A. Flow cytometric analysis of MDA, MA-11, MCF-7 (blue) and CD9shRNA (red) cells labeled with PE-conjugated anti-CD9 mAb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Black, parental cells labeled with PE-conjugated isotype. B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>RNA sequencing data for CD9 in MDA, MA-11 (MA), MCF-7 cells and MSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Data are expressed as gene-specific CD9 mRNA reads per 100,000 total reads. C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>MDA cells were labeled with PE-conjugated anti-CD9 Ab and sorted by FACS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>CD9-positive and negative cell fractions were cultured for 6 and 12 days, and the cell surface CD9 expression was re-assessed using another anti-CD9 Ab against a distinct CD9 epitope. D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The CD9 knockdown in MDA cells causes a delay in the adhesion to plastic substratum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Cells (2.5 × 104) were plated in tissue culture-treated plastic dish and the number of adherent cells was evaluated after 30 min, 2 h and 24 h. *p&lt;0.05. E. Growth curves of MDA and MDA CD9shRNA (MDA-CD9sh) cells for a period of three days. F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Parental (lane1) and CD9 shRNA (lane 2) MDA cells were probed by immunoblotting for different proteins as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Actin was used as a loading control. G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>DsRed-transduced MDA cells were co-cultured with GFP-transduced MSCs for 5 days and dual fluorescent cells were sorted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Occasional phenomena of entosis were observed 24 h after plating. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Scale bars, 20 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-06-7970-g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2_2"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>CD9 is required for invasion of BCCs into MSCs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>To investigate the CD9 role in BCC invasiveness, we co-cultured BCC lines with MSCs and monitored their migratory behavior by time-lapse total internal reflection fluorescence (TIRF) and confocal imaging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>MSCs were derived from pooled bone marrow samples of healthy adult donors, and cultured on poly-L-lysine as a substratum [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>To visualize them, BCCs and MSCs were transduced with DsRed- and GFP-based retroviral vectors, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>In 1:1 ratio co-cultures of DsRed-expressing MDA, MA-11 or MCF-7 cells with MSCs-GFP, we observed that 83% of direct contacts between MDA-MSC resulted in MSC invasion, whereas only 16 and 10% of MA-11-MSC and MCF-7-MSC contacts lead to an invasion (Fig. 2A, D, F, H; Supplementary Video S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Since the evanescent TIRF wave penetrates only 100-150 nm into the sample [20], overlapping fluorescence (green and red) signal did not derive from cell stacking, but from cell-cell invasion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Under same conditions, no invasion of human mammary epithelial cells (HuMECs) into MSCs was observed (Fig. 2G). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Next, we targeted the expression of CD9 by lentiviral-mediated short-hairpin RNA (shRNA) transduction using a pool of three distinct anti-CD9 shRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Its expression was abrogated in MDA, MA-11 and MCF-7 cell lines as observed by flow cytometry (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Upon CD9 knockdown, we found a 10-fold increase in the expression of CD81, a tetraspanin protein-interacting partner of CD9, in MDA CD9shRNA cells (Fig. 1F) [21, 22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>CD81 could potentially compensate for the lack of CD9 as reported in other cellular systems including knockout models, and consequently attempt to rescue the CD9 deficient phenotype [23, 24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>5- and 3-fold decreases in the expression of tetraspanin CD63 and ADAM10, respectively, were observed (Fig. 1F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>ADAM10 is a sheddase that cleaves Her2 (CD340), of which the latter oncogene plays a role in the development and progression of aggressive breast cancers [25, 26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The abrogation of CD9 expression neither affects the growth rate (Fig. 1E) nor the clonogenic ability of MDA cells (clonogenicity of 41.5 +/− 1.3% and 42.1 +/− 2.2% for MDA and MDA CD9 shRNA cells, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, MSC invasion rates of CD9-deficient MDA cells were significantly inhibited (Fig. 2C; Supplementary Video S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Such phenomenon was not a consequence of the reduction of BCC-MSC contacts, since CD9-deficient cells showed more contacts with MSCs than parental cells (Fig. 2I). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Finally, the invasiveness of MDA or MA-11 cells was evaluated using anti-CD9 blocking antibody (Ab). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Again, MDA and MA-11 invasiveness were significantly inhibited (Fig. 2B, E, H), although the interactions of BCCs and MSCs were unchanged (Fig. 2J). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>CD9-dependent invasion of MDA or MA-11 cells into MSCs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>A. Representative TIRF time-lapse images showing the partial/complete invasion, egress and trans-cell migration of MDA-DsRed cells into GFP-transduced MSCs over 12 h period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>MDA-DsRed cell A fully invaded MSC C by 8 h (arrow), and remained within the next four hours; MDA-DsRed cell D transiently entered the observation field at 3.5 h; MDA-DsRed cell E (outlined in white) entered the observation field between 10 and 12 h, and was seen within the same MSC at 12 h. B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>An anti-CD9 Ab was added to the MDA-DsRed/MSCs-GFP cells, which were recorded as described in panel A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Contacts and partial entry of MDA cells into MSCs were observed, but not invasion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>MDA-DsRed cell D entered the observation field between 10 and 12 h. C MDA CD9 shRNA cells plated with MSCs-GFP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Contacts and partial entries of DsRed-labeled CD9-deficient MDA cells were observed, but not invasion. D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Representative TIRF time-lapse images showing the entry of MA-11-Ds-Red into MSCs-GFP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>At 4 h, a MA-11 cell (A) invaded a MSC (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Between 8 and 12 h, a second MA-11 cell (D) invaded and passed through MSC E. E. An anti-CD9 Ab was added to the MA-11-Ds-Red/MSCs-GFP cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Only cell contacts were observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Note that MSC-GFP cell observed at 4 hours is leaving transiently the field of observation at 8 hours. F. G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>MCF-7-DsRed (F) or HuMEC-DsRed (G) cells were cultured with MSCs-GFP and TIRF images were recorded at indicated time points over 12 h period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>No full cell invasions were observed. H Quantification of the invasion events of BCCs into MSCs per cell contact measured by TIRF in the absence (parental) or presence (CD9 Ab) of anti-CD9 mAb in the cultured medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Inset, invasions per contact of MDA control shRNA (controlsh) and MDA CD9shRNA (CD9sh) cells. * p &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>I Average number of contacts between parental or CD9-deficient MDA cells and MSCs. * p &lt; 0.05. J. Addition of anti-CD9 Ab did not change the frequency of intercellular contacts between BCCs and MSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>B-E, Red, DsRed; green, GFP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Scale bars, 25 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-06-7970-g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2_3"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Implication of CD9 in BCC morphology and adhesion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>To gain more insight into the morphology of BCCs and the impact of CD9 on their structures, we analyzed them by scanning electron microscopy (SEM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The characteristics of different types of PMPs generated by MDA, MDA CD9 shRNA, MCF-7 and MA-11 cells are summarized in Table 1. while parental MDA cells were spread and created lamellipodia and filopodia close to the poly-L-lysine substratum, or interestingly, above the neighboring cells (Fig. 3A-C, white asterisks and black arrows, respectively; Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>S1), CD9-deficient cells displayed a certain impairment in adhesion, particularly at their cell border where numerous membrane ruffles were observed (Fig. 3E, F, arcs; Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>S1, arcs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>As a consequence, the knockdown of CD9 resulted in delayed adhesion of MDA cells as well as MA-11 and MCF-7 to poly-L-lysine (not shown) or tissue culture-treated plastic substratum (Fig. 1D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>In addition, the knockdown of CD9 caused severe modifications of the plasmalemma of MDA cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>While microvillus-like structures covered the apex of parental MDA cells (Fig. 3D, black arrowheads; Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>S1), they were rarely observed in an intact form in MDA CD9 shRNA cells, suggesting the implication of CD9 in their proper morphogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>In contrast, many dorsal ruffles were present (Fig. 3G, green asterisks; Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, MDA cells developed very long, and often thick (0.5-1.2 μm) PMPs (referred to as magnupodia), which extended for up to 100 micrometers away from the cell body and adhered either to the substratum or to another cell (Fig. 4A-C, dashed arrows). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Frequently, a lamellipodium was found at their tip (Fig. 4A-C, white asterisks). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Sometimes, the magnupodium seemed not to interact directly with the substratum with the exception of its ending lamellipodium (Fig. 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Generally, the MDA cells harboring a magnupodium had fibroblast-like structure (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Magnupodia were detected less often in MDA CD9 shRNA cells (Table 1), suggesting that CD9 is somehow involved in their formation and/or stabilization (see below for the localization of CD9 in these PMPs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Finally, both parental and CD9-deficient MDA cells exhibited numerous small and thin processes emerging from their dorsal part, which were able to link two neighboring cells or to establish a contact with the substratum (Fig. 3, Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>S1, white arrows; Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>A similar analysis was performed on MCF-7 and MA-11 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>MCF-7 cells were spread and created lamellipodia/filopodia as observed for MDA cells (Fig. 5A, B, white asterisks and black arrows, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>No magnupodium was observed in MCF-7 cells or very rarely with MA-11 cells (Fig. 5F, G, dashed arrows). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Likewise, no or rare thin processes emerging from their dorsal part could be detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>In contrast, MCF-7 cells harbored large dorsal ruffles (Fig. 5B-E, black asterisks). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>MA-11 cells also produced lamellipodia/filopodia (Fig. 5F-H, white asterisks and black arrows, respectively) and developed peripheral ruffles similar to CD9-deficient MDA cells (Fig. 5F-H, arcs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, MA-11 cells were often covered with numerous long microvillus-like structures (3.013 ± 0.948 μm by comparison to 1.069 ± 0.146 in MDA cells, n &gt; 100; Fig. 5F-J, black arrowheads). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The latter structures are particularly interesting since they seem to link adjacent cells (Fig. 5K). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Distinctive morphological traits and common features of different breast cancer cell lines </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>MDA </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>CD9shRNA(MDA) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>MA-11 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>MCF-7 </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Shape and growing profile </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Spindle, and sometimes growing above each other </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Polygonal, cell cluster </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Polygonal, cell cluster </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Polygonal, cell cluster </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Morphology at the cell border </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Lamellipodia and filopodia </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Lamellipodia and filopodia </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Lamellipodia and filopodia </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Peripheral ruffles </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Peripheral ruffles </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>magnupodium(length 73 ± 27 μm; thickness 0.5-1.2 μm)(n = 9) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Very rare magnupodia </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Rare magnupodia </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>No magnupodium </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Morphology at the cell surface </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Microvillus-like structures(length 1.1 ± 0.1 μm; thickness 0.11 ± 0.01μm)(n = 96) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Small dorsal ruffles(height 1.1 ± 0.3μm; width 1.6 ± 0.3 μm) and/or altered microvillus-like structures(n = 30) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Long microvillus-like structures(length 3.0 ± 1 μm; thickness 0.14±0.02 μm)and thin ruffles(n = 138) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Small microvillus-like structures(length 1.1 ± 0.2 μm; thickness 0.11 ± 0.01μm)and ruffles(n = 31) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Thin (0.08 ± 0.02 μm) and long (47 ± 12 μm) processes with small membranous bulges(n = 21) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Thin (0.08± 0.01 μm) and long (48 ± 18 μm) processes with small membranous bulges(n = 14) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Sparse and large dorsal ruffles(height 5.6 ± 1.6 μm; width 6.1 ± 1.7 μm)(n = 42) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Cell-cell contact </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Lamellipodia that grow above the neighboring cells </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Long microvillus-like structures and thin ruffles emerge from the cell border and make contacts with adjacent cells </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Large dorsal ruffles are touching neighboring cells </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Thin and long processes emerging from the apex (or side) of cell are connecting adjacent cells </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Thin and long processes emerging from the apex (or side) of cell are connecting adjacent cells </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Frequent magnupodia that links cells over a long-distance </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The data are mean ± standard deviation of indicated number (n) of measurements </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>CD9 influences BCC morphology </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>A-G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>MDA cells (A-D) and their CD9-shRNA-transduced counterpart (E-G) grown on poly-L-lysine-coated coverslips were analyzed by SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Various types of PMPs such as lamellipodium (A-C, white asterisks), filopodium (A-B, black arrows), and dorsal microvillus-like structures (D, black arrowheads) were identified on MDA cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Membrane ruffles were detected at the edge (E, F, arcs) or dorsal part (G, green asterisks) of CD9-deficient cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Thin membrane processes emerged from the dorsal side of parental and CD9-deficient cells (A, C, E, F, white arrows). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The distinct shapes of microvillus-like structures or membrane ruffles/altered microvillus-like structures observed at the apex of cells are depicted in the insets (D, G, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are indicated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-06-7970-g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>MDA cells display magnupodia </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>A-C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>MDA cells grown on poly-L-lysine-coated coverslips were analyzed by SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>MDA cells develop long and thick magnupodia (dashed arrows) where a lamellipodium often emerges from their ending point (white asterisk). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are indicated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-06-7970-g004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>MCF-7 and MA-11 BCC lines are morphologically distinct to MDA cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>A-K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>MCF-7 (A-E) and MA-11 (F-K) cells grown on poly-L-lysine-coated coverslips were analyzed by SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>MCF-7 cells developed various types of PMPs such as lamellipodia (A, B, white asterisks), filopodia (D, black arrows) and large dorsal ruffles (C-E, black asterisks), the latter structure being absent in MDA cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>In contrast, MA-11 cells are very often covered by long microvillus-like structures (F-K, black arrowheads). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Rare magnupodia also contain them (F, G, dashed arrow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Although infrequent at the dorsal portion of the cells (G, black asterisk), membrane ruffles were observed at the cell periphery (G-I, arcs), which also contained filopodia (F, H, black arrows). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Microvillus-like structures seem often to link two neighboring cells (K, 1 and 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Broken membranes during the SEM preparation are indicated with #. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are indicated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-06-7970-g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2_4"><title><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>CD9 is present in several types of BCC PMPs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>TIRF and confocal live cell-imaging of MDA cells revealed an extensive array of CD9+ PMPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>CD9 was observed either by immunolabeling or upon the ectopic expression of CD9-GFP fusion protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Both approaches gave similar data indicating that fusion protein is properly targeted to PMPs (Fig. 6A-E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>CD9 is detected in (i) microvilli; (ii) branched web-like filopodia, which are morphologically similar to the described nanopodia that play a role in cell adhesion [27]; (iii) unbranched filopodia bundles, associated with directional movement (see below); (iv) short filopodia; (v) magnupodia; and (vi) lamellipodia (Fig. 6C, arrow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The different CD9+ PMPs were present either when MDA cells were cultured alone (Fig. 6B, C) or with DiD-labeled MSCs (Fig. 6A, H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>As observed by SEM, MDA cells deployed a long magnupodium away from the cell body towards a neighboring one (Fig. 6B, white asterisk). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Magnupodia tended to float in the medium and, with fluid motion, to extend downstream, whereas the cell remained adherent to the substratum (Fig. 6B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The morphology of magnupodia suggests that they may play sensory and mechanical roles during cell migration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>During retraction, the extended materials often pooled into a bulb located on the pod (Fig. 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Both MDA and MDA-CD9-GFP cells contained CD9+ PMPs between them that could play a role in cell-cell adhesion (Fig. 6C, I, J, arrowheads). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>We then evaluated the number of CD9+ PMPs emerging from MDA, MA-11 and MCF-7 cells transfected with CD9-GFP fusion plasmid by confocal microscopy (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>In both MA-11 and MCF-7 cells, shorter and less frequent CD9-GFP+ PMPs than MDA cells were observed as suggested by SEM analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The calculated area of PMPs for MDA cells was 4200.0 +/− 732.1 μm2, 1583.3 +/− 215.0 μm2 for MA-11 cells, and 716.7 +/− 269.7 μm2 for MCF-7 cells (for technical details see Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The numbers of CD9-GFP+ PMPs is significantly higher in MDA cells by comparison to MA-11 (p = 0.02) and MCF-7 (p = 0.01) cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>MA-11 cells did have a greater frequency of CD9-GFP+ PMPs than MCF-7 cells (p = 0.047). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, CD9+ filopodia and thin PMPs were negative (or below the detectable level) for α-tubulin (acetylated and non-acetylated) and β1 integrin (Fig. 6I-K). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>IgSF8, a binding partner of CD9, was located along CD9+ filopodia (Fig. 6L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>CD44, which is known to associate with CD9, was observed in CD9+ PMPs including microvilli (Fig. 6D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>CD9 and CD44 showed a strong co-localization with a Pearson's co-localization coefficient of 0.87 +/− 0.02. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Similarly, CD9 co-localized with CD81 on the plasma membrane and PMPs thereof (Pearson's R value 0.82 +/− 0.04) (Fig. 7A, B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>A co-localization of CD9 and CD81 was also observed in filopodia and cell footprints (Fig. 7A, B, respectively), the latter being fragments of PMPs that remain attached to the substratum when cells are migrating further [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>These footprints were degraded over time (Fig. 6A, white arrows). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>CD81 was also detected at the apex of parental MDA/MDA control shRNA and MDA-CD9 shRNA cells where microvillus-like structures and small dorsal ruffles are found, respectively, (Fig. 7C, F; Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Likewise, numerous thin membrane processes with small membranous bulges that establish a contact with the substratum (Fig. 7D, G) or with either neighboring MDA cells (Fig. 7D, G, Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>S2, arrowheads) or MSCs-GFP (Fig. 7E, H, Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>S2) were positive for CD81. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Given the localization of CD81 and CD9 in various types of PMPs this alternative marker allows us to quantify the number of PMPs in CD9-deficient MDA cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Fluorescence measurements of CD81+ PMPs were not significantly different between MDA (272.3 +/− 41.9), MDA CD9shRNA (372.6 +/− 41.9) and MDA control shRNA (354.1 +/− 26.5) cells, suggesting that the knockdown of CD9 did not reduce them with the notable exception of magnupodia (see above; Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Although the total expression level of CD81 was increased upon CD9 knockdown as observed by immunoblotting (Fig. 1F), the lack of intensified immunofluorescence signal in MDA CD9shRNA cells might be explained by its oligomerization or other protein-protein interactions where certain CD81 epitopes will be masked. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Neither the morphology of MDA cells nor the number of CD9+ PMPs derived therefrom were affected when they were transduced with control shRNA (Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>MDA-CD9-GFP cells were transfected with a β-actin-mCherry fusion plasmid to determine the relationship between the dynamics of filopodia and cell movement, and the presence of actin in CD9+ PMPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>When MDA-CD9-GFP-β-actin-mCherry cells were co-cultured with DiD-labeled MSCs, unbranched filopodia bundles containing CD9 appeared at a 163o +/− 14o (s.d.) angle from the direction of MDA cell movement (Fig. 7I, top panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The average ratio of unbranched filopodia expansion/distance traveled by the cell was 0.82 +/− 0.089 (s.d.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>This indicated that as a MDA cell migrated, the distance traveled was almost equal to the length of the growing filopodia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The actin was located solely at the base of the filopodia bundles during cell migration, and consequently did not extend through the length of the CD9+ PMPs (Fig. 7I, bottom panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Together, these observations suggest that trailing filopodia could influence the speed and direction of the cancer cell migration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Thus, they might guide the invasion cells in a 3-dimensional (3D) microenvironment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Magnupodia with lamellipodia at their leading edge containing both CD9 and CD81 were observed in MDA cells as well as MDA-CD9-GFP cells (Fig. 8A, C, Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>S2D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>These lamellipodia were involved in MDA cell invasion into MSCs, as shown in co-cultures of MDA/MDA-CD9-GFP cells with MSC-GFP/MSCs, the latter ones being either labeled with DiI or transiently transfected with β-actin-mCherry (Fig. 8A-C; Supplementary Video S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Live-cell TIRF imaging of co-cultures of MDA-CD9-GFP with MSC-β-actin-mCherry cells showed the formation of a CD9+ magnupodium extending from an MDA cell (Fig. 8C), similar to those observed by SEM (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Upon its initial contact with the MSC, a cell invasion occurred. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Given that the CD9 deficiency dramatically reduced the number of MSC invasions and no magnupodia was observed in MDA CD9shRNA cells, these observations suggest that CD9-dependent magnupodia is the main PMPs of MDA cells involved in the invasion of MSCs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, TIRF imaging revealed a progressive transfer of materials from MSCs-β-actin-mCherry to MDA-CD9-GFP cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Thus we could observe a large portion of an MSC being taken up by an MDA-CD9-GFP cell (Fig. 8D, E and Supplementary Video S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Although such phenomenon is rare (~1-2 events/50,000 cells) under our experimental setting, it is nonetheless observable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>CD9+ PMPs on BCCs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>A. Confocal images were taken every 25 min of live CD9-GFP-transfected MDA cells cultured with DiD-labeled MSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Retraction of magnupodium (asterisk) occurs on a 1 h-time scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Arrows, branched CD9+ filopodia detached from cells and degraded over time. B. C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Fixed, permeabilized MDA cells were stained with anti-CD9 Ab followed by Cy5-conjugated secondary Ab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Images are maximum intensity projections (MIPs) of confocal z-stacks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Representative z-optical sections taken at different heights from the coverslip shown to the right of the MIP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Arrow, branched CD9+ filopodia; white asterisk, lamellipodium at the tip of magnupodium (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>CD9+ PMPs such as a lamellipodium (arrow) at the tip of magnupodium and short filopodia (arrowheads) promote the intercellular interaction between two MDA cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>High power views of images of outlined areas are shown (C). D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>CD9-GFP-transfected MDA cells stained with anti-CD44 Ab followed by Cy5-conjugated secondary Ab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Image is representative z-optical section of microvilli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Insets show GFP and Cy5 channels. E-G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>CD9+ PMPs on MDA-CD9-GFP, MA-11-CD9-GFP, and MCF-7-CD9-GFP cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Branched CD9+ filopodia (arrowhead) are emerging from MDA cells over long distance (see magnification of the outlined area) (E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Short CD9+ filopodia (arrowhead) are emerging from MA-11 (F) and MCF-7 (G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Note numerous CD9+ long microvilli in MA-11 cells and large dorsal ruffles (intense green areas) in MCF-7 cells (F, G, respectively, see insets where magnifications of indicated areas are shown). H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Live-cell image of CD9-GFP and β-actin-mCherry-transfected MDA cells co-cultured with DiD-labeled MSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>CD9+ long and branched filopodia (arrows) and thin membrane processes (arrowhead) are either spreading over the long distance or link adjacent cells. I-L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>CD9-GFP-transfected MDA cells were labeled with anti-β1 integrin (I), anti-α-tubulin (J), anti-acetylated-α-tubulin (K), or anti-IgSF8 (L) Abs followed by Cy5- or TRITC-conjugated secondary Ab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>CD9+ filopodia are indicated with arrowheads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>High power views of CD9+IgSF8+ PMPs of outlined areas are shown (L, GFP and TRITC channels). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>MIPs of confocal z-stacks (A-C, E-K). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>All scale bars, 50 μm, except for D, 25 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-06-7970-g006"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>CD9+ PMPs contain CD81 and actin </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>A. B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>CD9-GFP-transfected MDA cells were fixed, permeabilized and labeled with anti-CD81 Ab followed by Cy5-conjugated secondary Ab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>A co-localization of CD9 with CD81 was observed on PMPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Short (A) and long (B) CD9+CD81+ filopodia and cell footprints (B, inset) are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Individual GFP and Cy5 channels are shown (right panels). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Images are MIPs of z-stacks. C-H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>MDA (C-E) or MDA-CD9shRNA (F-H) cells were plated alone (C, D, F, G) or with MSCs-GFP (E, H) prior to labeling with anti-CD81 Ab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Arrows indicate BCC-derived thin filopodia interacting with a MSC (E, H), while arrowheads point to short and thin processes connecting cells (D, G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Magnified images of outlined regions are shown (C, D, F, G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Images are MIPs (D, E, G, H) or representative optical sections of z-stacks (C, F). I. MDA-CD9-GFP-β-actin-mCherry cells cultured with DiD-labeled MSCs were imaged every 30 min for a 12 h period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Arrows indicate CD9+ filopodia approximately 180o opposite to the direction of cell movement (top panels) or actin at the base of these filopodia (bottom panels). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Images are MIPs of z-stacks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 50 μm, except for A, E, H, 25 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-06-7970-g007"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>The invasion of MSCs by MDA cells involves CD9+ lamellipodia </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>A. MDA cells were cultured with GFP-transduced MSCs prior to their staining with anti-CD81 Ab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Inset shows a representative z-optical section of MIP of z-stack. B. Live-cell confocal images of CD9-GFP-transfected MDA cells (B, C, D, F) co-cultured with DiI-labeled MSCs (A, E, G, H, I) were taken every 30 min for at least 8 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>A lamellipodium-driven invasion of MDA-CD9-GFP cell (cell F) into DiI-labeled MSC (cell H). C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Live-cell TIRF images of MDA-CD9-GFP cells cultured with β-actin-mCherry-transfected MSCs were taken every 30 min for at least 10 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>A CD9+ lamellipodium (arrow) emerging from a MDA cell interacts with MSC prior to invasion. D. E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Live-cell TIRF images of MDA-CD9-GFP cells co-cultured with β-actin-mCherry-transfected MSCs were acquired every 15 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>The indicated time points are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Note a large piece of MSC phagocytosed by MDA cell (D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Two distinct MDA-CD9-GFP cells contain fragments of β-actin-mCherry+ MSC (E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Scale bars, A, C-E, 25 μm; B, 50 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-06-7970-g008"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2_5"><title><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>CD9 is required for generation of heterotypic hybrids </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Next, we investigated the formation of BCC/MSC hybrids by culturing them together for 6 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, cellular invasion was associated with spontaneous fusion of MDA or MA-11 cells with MSCs, which amounted to 0.68 and 0.12% according to initial number of plated BCCs, respectively (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>The pre-incubation with two different CD9 blocking Abs caused a decrease of fusion between MDA cells and MSCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The knockdown of CD9 in both cell lines totally abrogated the heterologous fusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>No fusion events were observed between the less aggressive MCF-7 cells or HuMECs with MSCs (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Clearly, most invasion events did not result in heterologous fusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>To investigate the relationship between invasion and cell fusion, we sorted and re-plated dual (red-green) fluorescent cells originated from mixed BCC/MSC co-cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>When analyzed within 60 min from sorting, cells showed different morphological stages of invasion and presence of dual fluorescent cells (about 30%) (Fig. 9A, B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>However, 24 hours later, about 1% of the double-positive cells were present (Fig. 9C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>As shown in Table 2 and Fig. 9D, the latter fraction of cells included viable hybrids, i.e. able to divide and form dual fluorescent progeny with mesenchymal morphology, as previously described [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Disappearance of dual fluorescent cells could not be attributed to selective cell death of the hybrids, since trypan blue dye exclusion revealed that was over 99% of cell viability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the majority of sorted dual-color cells was confirmed not to be stable hybrids, four days after sorting, by a single broad DNA peak with a DNA index of 1.2 including both diploid MSCs (DNA index 1.0) and MDA cells (1.25). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that the double-fluorescent cells observed by flow cytometry represented for the most part transient stages of invasion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>We observed occasional occurrence of entosis, with presence of Ds-Red in the cytoplasm of MSCs, evidenced by yellow fluorescence (Fig. 1G, mix of red and green). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Effect of anti-CD9 antibodies and CD9 knockdown on formation of breast cancer/MSC hybrids </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>MDA/MSC </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>% hybrids ± S.D.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>P value </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Control </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>0.68 ± 0.16 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Anti-CD9 (MEM-61) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>0.15 ± 0.10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>0.007 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Anti-CD9 (M-L 13) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>0.184 ± 0.16 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>0.016 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Anti-CD9 (P1/33/2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>0.5 ± 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>0.11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>CD9 knockdown </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>0.0018 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>MA-11/MSC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Control </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>0.12 ± 0.05 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>CD9 knockdown </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>0.022 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>MCF-7/MSC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Control </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>CD9 knockdown </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>HuMEC/MSC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Control </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn_001"><label>1</label><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>2000 BCCs and 8000 MSCs were plated together (24-well plate) and dual fluorescence of heterotypic hybrids was counted after 6 days of co-cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>The percentage of hybrids was calculated relative to the initial number of BCCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Data are the mean of five independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Anti-CD9 Ab clone is indicated in bracket. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F9" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>CD9-dependent fusogenicity, tumorigenicity and metastatic capacity of MDA cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>A-D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>The great majority of dual-fluorescent MDA-MSC hybrids from 5-days co-cultures of DsRed-transduced MDA and GFP-transduced MSCs represents a transient stage of invasion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Representative MDA-MSC hybrid observed 1 h (A, B) or 24 h (C, arrow) post-sorting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Groups of proliferating hybrids observed 96 h post-sorting (D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Scale bars, 30 μm; E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Fluorescence imaging over time of two representative tumors in the mammary fat pad, upon injection of 6 × 106 MDA-DsRed (upper panels) and MDA-DsRed-CD9shRNA (lower panels) cells in nu/nu mice. F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Analysis of primary tumor growth by live-animal fluorescence imaging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Tumor volumes were evaluated weekly over 1 month period and analyzed by two-way ANOVA (p&lt;0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Error bars, s.e.m. from the mean volume of ten xenografts per group. G. H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Representative fluorescent images of lung (G) and axillary lymph node (H) metastases in nu/nu mice six weeks after injection of MDA-DsRed cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-06-7970-g009"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2_6"><title><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>CD9 knockdown inhibits tumor growth and metastases in immune-deficient hosts </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the effects of CD9 knockdown on MDA cells in vivo, we compared primary tumor growth and metastasis after implantation of either MDA-Ds-Red or MDA-Ds-Red-CD9sh cells into the mammary fat pad of nu/nu mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>The tumor progression was monitored weekly by orthotopic tumor fluorescence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>The CD9-deficient cells could initiate the growth of tumor until 7th day post-injection in agreement with in vitro data (Fig. 1E), however, the cancer progression was afterward stopped and in several cases a complete regression was observed (Fig. 9E, F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>In mice implanted with MDA-Ds-Red cells, macroscopic fluorescent axillary lymph node, lung and brain metastases were detected in 70, 60 and 40% of the animals at autopsy, respectively, by comparison these numbers drastically dropped to 30, 40 and 0% of mice implanted with MDA-Ds-Red-CD9sh cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Representative fluorescent images of lung and lymph node metastases of nu/nu mice implanted with MDA-DsRed cells are shown in Fig. 9G, H. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Breast cancer progression into overt metastatic phenotype requires migration of tumor cells through extracellular matrix and across host cell layers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we characterized CD9+ PMPs of BCCs as pro-invasive and fusogenic, found a direct correlation between the extent of CD9+ PMPs and BCC invasiveness and established CD9 as a molecule required for the correct formation of certain types of PMPs, notably the long magnupodium. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>In MDA cells, migration, invasiveness and subsequent heterologous fusion were achieved by CD9-dependent lamellipodia including those found at the tip of magnupodia (see Figs 4, 10), which in in vivo 3D-microenvironment could appear as invadopodia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>The absence of CD9 impaired their formation and/or destabilized them, which resulted in numerous membrane ruffles at the edge of MDA CD9shRNA cells, and hence the lack of firm adhesion therein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, while CD9 knockdown and blocking Abs severely hindered invasion and cell fusion, the overall adhesion properties of MDA CD9shRNA cells to MSCs were nonetheless preserved or seemingly increased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>These data are in agreement with earlier results showing that the lack of fusion in Cd9 null eggs was not accompanied by loss of sperm–egg adhesion [24, 29], but rather by an increase in sperm binding sites [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Such observation suggests that CD9 deficiency lead to a compensatory mechanism responsible for the maintenance of cellular adhesion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>The increased expression of CD9-interacting partner CD81 observed in CD9-deficient cells might explain it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>CD81 was constantly associated with CD9+ PMPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>We are currently using atomic force microscopy-based single-cell force spectroscopy to quantify the adhesive BCC-MSC interaction(s) and decipher further these issues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, the up regulation of CD81 did not compensate the MSC invasion in vitro or cancer progression and metastasis capacity of CD9-deficient MDA cells in vivo in agreement with previous studies (see below; reviewed in Ref [12]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>It is worth to mention that thin CD9+ PMPs, which often interact with those emerging from neighboring cells (Fig. 3, white arrows), are reminiscent to long and thin nanopodia recently described in endothelial cells [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Like those described here, they contain a tetraspanin protein, namely transmembrane-4-L-six-family (TM4SF1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>The function of such TM4SF1/CD9+ membrane projections is not yet clear but they might play a role in intercellular communication or sensing the microenvironment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>In addition, the implication of CD9+ filopodia in keratinocyte wound healing migration or lymphocyte trans-endothelial migration has been previously reported [28, 31, 32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Obviously, further efforts are urged to determine their implication in cancer progression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Magnupodia and thin PMPs are rarely observed in MA-11 cells, and their invasiveness and fusogenicity might be related to the long microvillus-like structures (~3 μm in length) that originate from the cell border, and collectively form a “microvilli zipper” between adjacent BCCs (Fig. 10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>The formation of CD9-dependent microvilli zippers is not unique to cancer cells since similar structures have been demonstrated to regulate virus-induced cell fusion [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Thus, CD9+ microvillus-like structures could act as a platform to concentrate adhesion and/or fusion proteins such as CD44. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="?"><plain>Is CD9 directly involved in the microvillar architecture? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>A hint of its direct structural role was already provided in Cd9 null oocytes, where numerous alterations (length, thickness and density) in microvillus-like structures were noted [32, 34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Similarly, we observed that CD9 knockdown causes alterations of microvillus-like structures at the dorsal part of MDA cells, which resulted in the appearance of tiny dorsal ruffles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>CD9 proteins together with the tetraspanin web could provide the appropriate shape of PMPs including a low radius of curvature necessary for membrane fusion [32, 35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Finally, we could not exclude that dorsal microvillus-like structures of MDA cells participate as well in cellular interaction/fusion in vivo given that they might be in direct contact with adjacent cells in a native microenvironment in contrast to 2D cell cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Besides the components of PMPs (i.e. lamellipodia/magnupodia in MDA cells and microvillus-like structures in MA-11 cells), other actors may be involved in bridging adjacent membranous structures in vivo, such as soluble factors and/or microvesicles [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, CD9 is a major constituent of exosomes released by MDA cells (Green et al., unpublished data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Since inflammation is often associated with tumor microenvironment, adhesion-promoting factors released by hematopoietic cells could also play a role [37]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>The impairment of BCCs invasion into MSCs, caused either by CD9 deficiency or Ab interference, led to decrease of heterotypic cell-cell fusion – potential source of genomic instability, aneuploidy and cancer heterogeneity – hallmarks of cancer progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>A direct relation between invasiveness and fusogenicity is nonetheless not surprising, in view of previous findings showing that in high-density homotypic cultures, MDA cells were 11- and 7.2-fold more fusogenic and capable of invading Matrigel matrix, respectively, than MA-11 cells [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Although only a minority of invasion events resulted in formation of hybrid cells (e.g., MDA/MA-11–MSC), our previous study demonstrated that after 5 days of drug selection 80% of cells in mixed cultures were hybrids, capable of forming metastatic tumors in immune-deficient hosts, suggesting that the current phenomenon is biologically pertinent [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>In addition, we occasionally observed in our co-cultures a phenomenon entosis, which is implicated in cancer aneuploidy and progression [39], our adherent BCCs and MSCs were not favorable to its occurrence since the entosis mainly happens in suspension cultures [39-41]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>It might not be more a coincidence that MCF-7 a much less aggressive and poorly metastatic BCC line [42], displays less CD9+ PMPs than MDA cells and has poor invasive and fusogenic capacities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>These observations strongly suggest that local cellular interactions in the microenvironment, presumably mediated by CD9+ PMPs, play an important role in the breast cancer metastatic phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>While MDA cells are triple negative (estrogen receptor (ER), progesterone receptor (PR), Her-2), and belong to Basal-like subtype of breast carcinomas, MCF-7 cells are ER+/PR+/Her-2− and fell within Luminal-A subtype [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Tumors of Basal-like subtype are aggressive, poorly differentiated and often occur on younger patients with a poor prognosis by comparison to those of Luminal-A subtype, which are more differentiated and observed in older patients with the best prognosis contrasted to other subtypes [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Thus, the presence and/or absence of certain types of PMPs (e.g., magnupodium, long microvilli, membrane ruffles) can contribute, in addition to the molecular signature, to the classification of breast carcinomas. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>The requirement of CD9 for orthotopic tumor growth suggests that membrane extension-driven cell communication and/or reduced cell adhesiveness to stromal components are responsible for the absence of local tumor growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>We should also keep in mind that CD9-deficiency leads to decreased expression of ADAM10, a metalloproteinase that could play a role in breast cancer progression [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, the formation of metastases, although reduced, was not fully abrogated by CD9 knockdown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>This may reflect the capacity of BCCs of intra/extravasating in vivo through tight endothelial junctions rather than trans-cellular route and/or to decreased adhesiveness caused by CD9 deficiency that could facilitate metastatic dissemination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Recent findings that the CD9/CD81 tetraspanin complex regulates α3β1 integrin-dependent tumor cell behavior [45] and that integrin α3β1 promotes breast carcinoma metastases [46] suggests that the anti-metastatic effect observed upon CD9 knockdown could depend on the CD9 regulation of α3β1-integrin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>However, we did not detect association between CD9 and β1-integrin in MDA cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Our findings are intriguing in the context of the “push and pull” role of tetraspanins in metastases [12]: while an inverse correlation between CD9 expression and metastatic potential was observed in some studies [12, 47], a pro-metastatic role of CD9 was observed in others [48-52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, while melanoma cells had reduced CD9 expression relative to normal melanocytes, forced increase in CD9 expression stimulated their invasiveness [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Similarly, CD9 was down regulated in primary sites of cervical cancers, but re-expressed at sites of trans-endothelial invasion to promote malignant expansion at metastatic sites [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Collectively, our data indicate that CD9 is implicated in BCC invasiveness and tumor growth by mechanisms that involve specific and dynamics protruding structures of BCC plasma membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Investigation of CD9-targeted breast cancer therapeutic strategies is warranted. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F10" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Two distinct potential mechanisms involved in cancer cell invasion and fusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>A-F. MDA (A-C) and MA-11 (D-F) cells grown on poly-L-lysine-coated coverslips were analyzed by SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>In MDA cells, a lamellipodium emerging from one or two cells simultaneously seems to link them closely (red box). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Note that in certain cases it is highly difficult to delimitate the cell border suggesting membrane fusion (B, C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Cells were pseudocolored in cyan or yellow in order to help their visualization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>In MA-11 cells, microvillus-like structures (E, black arrowhead) and thin membrane ruffles (F, asterisk) emerging from cell borders (red box) might play a role in cell-cell contacts, invasion and eventually cell fusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Note that rare MA-11 cells with an elongated morphology (F) can generate a microvilli zipper between their entire length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are indicated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-06-7970-g010"/></fig></SecTag></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4_1"><title><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Error bars in graphical data represent means ± s.e.m., unless stated otherwise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Mouse experiments were performed in duplicate, using at least 5 mice per treatment group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>To determine how many mice were required for the data to be statistically significant, we used a Fisher's Exact test at 80% power and 95% confidence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://calculators.stat.ucla.edu/powercalc/binomial/fishers/index.php">"http://calculators.stat.ucla.edu/powercalc/binomial/fishers/index.php</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>For tumor growth analyses, we performed two-way ANOVA statistical analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>All in vitro experiments were performed at least in triplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Statistical significance was determined using a two-tailed Student's t-test, and p-values of p &lt; 0.05 were considered statistically significant by ANOVA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>For total internal reflection fluorescence (TIRF) analysis, F-tests were performed to compare variance between groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Those that were determined to have equal variance were compared using an unpaired Student's t-test, and those that had unequal variances were compared using a Welch's t-test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>The first BCC line studied was evaluated using a two-tailed Student's t-test, and subsequent BCC lines were evaluated using a one-tailed Student's t-test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>The Manual Tracking Plugin of Fiji was used to track MDA-CD9-GFP cell movement as well as the position of the CD9+ unbranched bundles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>The angle of cell at the base of the extension compared to the tip of the extension was measured for the duration of cell movement using Fiji. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>Averages of at least 3 independent experiments are reported +/– s.d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>The same Manual Tracking Plugin was used to measure the initial length of the CD9+ PMPs, the distance traveled by the cell, and the final length of the PMPs (measured using the last time frame of cell migration). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>The growth of the PMPs, i.e. difference between final and initial extension length, was divided by the distance traveled by the cell in order to calculate the ratio of unbranched filopodia growth: distance traveled by the cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Averages of at least 3 independent experiments are reported +/− s.e.m. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_2"><title><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Cell Lines </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Human MDA (i.e. MDA-MB-231) and MCF-7 BCCs were obtained from the American Type Culture Collection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>The human MA-11 BCC line, which was established from bone marrow micrometastases of a breast cancer patient, was obtained from Dr. Fodstad (Norwegian Radium Hospital) [55, 56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Human MSCs were isolated from 1–4 ml bone marrow aspirates taken from the iliac crest of normal adult donors after informed consent, as described [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>They were obtained from Dr. Prockop (Texas A&amp;M) and prepared under a protocol approved by the Texas A&amp;M Institutional Review Board. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>MSCs were cultured in complete culture medium [α-minimal essential medium (Gibco, Carlsbad, CA), 17% fetal bovine serum (lot selected for rapid growth of MSC; Atlanta Biologicals, Inc., Norcross, GA), 100 units/ml penicillin, 100 μg/ml streptomycin, and 2 mM L-glutamine] as described [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Their multipotency was regularly monitored by their differentiation into adipocytes, osteoblasts and chondrocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>All cell lines were kept in culture for less than 3 months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>They were tested for mycoplasma contamination and authenticated by morphology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_3"><title><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Antibodies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>The following primary Abs were employed throughout this study: anti-CD9 clone P1/33/2 (Santa Cruz, Dallas, TX), anti-CD9 clone MEM-61 (Abcam, San Francisco, CA), anti-CD9 clone M-L13 (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA), anti-CD9 clone HI9a (BioLegend, San Diego, CA), anti-CD81 (cat. #349502, BioLegend), anti-CD63 (cat. #sc-15363, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Dallas, TX), anti-ADAM-10 (cat. #sc-25578, Santa Cruz Biotechnology), anti-β-actin (cat. #sc-47778, Santa Cruz Biotechnology), anti-IgSF8 (cat. #103561, Santa Cruz Biotechnology), anti-β1 integrin (cat #4706S, Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, MA), anti-α-tubulin (cat. #sc-8035, Santa Cruz Biotechnology), anti-acetylated-α-tubulin (cat. #T7451, Sigma), anti-CD44 (cat. #MA5-13890, ThermoScientific, Waltham, MA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>The following secondary Abs were employed: TRITC-conjugated anti-rabbit IgG (Jackson ImmunoResearch), TRITC-conjugated anti-goat IgG (Sigma), and Cy5-conjugated anti-mouse IgG (Jackson ImmunoResearch). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>For inhibition experiments, sodium azide was removed by desalting through Sephadex G-25 spin columns. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_4"><title><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Labeling of MSCs with Membrane Dyes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>MSCs were enzymatically detached, centrifuged at 200 x g for 5 min, and resuspended in serum-free media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Cells were labeled for 10-20 min at 37oC by the addition of DiI (or DiD; Invitrogen, Grand Island, NY) at a final concentration of 5 μM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed twice in complete medium, and plated in a 35-mm dish containing 0.17 mm coverslip. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Labeled MSCs were co-cultured with MDA-CD9-GFP cells (ratio 1:1; 5 × 104 cells) overnight prior to the beginning of the experiment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_5"><title><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Retroviral and Lentiviral Vectors </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>The EGFP and DsRed-expressing retroviral vectors used are based on pSF91 (GenBank accession no. AJ224005) with the 3′ LTR of spleen focus-forming virus and the leader of the murine embryonic stem cell virus [58, 59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>To generate retroviral producers, the Phoenix-gp packaging cell line was transfected with pSF91/eGFP or pSF91/DsRed, and a plasmid expressing the vesicular stomatitis virus glycoprotein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>Culture supernatants containing viral particles were collected at 24-48 h after transfection, passed through 0.22-μm Millex GP filters (Millipore Co., Bedford, MA) and stored at –80oC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>To inhibit the expression of CD9, shRNA lentiviral particles (Santa Cruz Biotechnologies, cat. #sc-35032-V) were employed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>They consist of a pool of transduction-ready lentiviral vectors containing 3 target-specific constructs encoding 19-25 nucleotides (plus hairpin) shRNA designed to knockdown CD9 gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>shRNA lentiviral particles containing an shRNA construct encoding a scrambled sequence (cat. #sc-108080) were employed as negative control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_6"><title><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>Viral Transduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>For transduction of MSCs and BCCs, retroviral supernatants or transduction-ready lentiviral particles were preloaded onto recombinant fibronectin (Retronectin, Takara Shuzo, Japan)-coated plates and centrifuged at 950 x g for 30 min at 4oC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>The operation was repeated a second time with fresh supernatant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was then removed and plates washed with PBS before addition of cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>After transduction, stable cell lines were selected by introducing 2 μg/ml puromycin in the culture medium. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_7"><title><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>Transfection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>MDA, MA-11 and MCF-7 cells were transfected by electroporation with 10 μg PrecisionShuttle mammalian plasmid encoding CD9 with GFP tag at its C-terminus under the control of the cytomegalovirus promoter (PS100010 vector; OriGene Tech., Rockville, MD) using a Gene Pulser X-cell electroporator according to the supplier's instructions (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>Cells expressing the neomycin resistance gene were selected by introducing 400 μg/ml of G418 (Life Technologies) into culture medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>At least one week before the experiments, G418 was omitted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>Under these conditions, &gt;99% of neomycin-resistant cells expressed the recombinant CD9-GFP fusion protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>MDA-CD9-GFP cells and MSCs were transiently transfected with pLVX-mCherry-Actin vector (0.8 μg DNA, Clontech, Mountain View, CA) using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen) in a 1:3 ratio of DNA:lipofectamine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Cells were plated in a 35-mm dish with 0.17 mm coverslip on the bottom and incubated for at least 16 h prior their use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_8"><title><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>Cell Sorting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>Fluorescent cells were sorted using an SH800 cell sorter (Sony Global, Champaign, IL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>To exclude doublets from the sorted sub-population of dual fluorescence hybrids, gating was performed sequentially on the basis of forward and back light scatter first, and then on the basis of forward scatter height vs. width. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_9"><title><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>Deep RNA Sequencing (RNA-seq) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>The RNA-seq-based mRNA profiling was performed by Ocean Ridge Biosciences (Palm Beach Gardens, FL) as previously described [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>To normalize the data, the raw nucleotides mapped for each gene X sample were converted to reads per 100,000 total reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>Missing data points, where no reads were mapped for a specific sample X gene, were replaced with a value of 0.08 reads/100,000 total reads. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_10"><title><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>Immunoblotting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>Detergent cell lysates were prepared using lysing buffer (1% Triton X-100, 100 mM NaCl, 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5) supplemented with a protease inhibitor cocktail (Calbiochem, Billerica, MA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>The lysates were incubated on ice for 30 min, centrifuged at 20,000 x g for 5 min, and Laemmli sample buffer (reducing condition) was added to the supernatants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>Proteins were separated by a 4-12% Bis-Tris precast gel (Invitrogen) along with a pre-stained protein molecular weight ladder (Genetex, Irvine, CA), and transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane (Thermo, Waltham, MA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>Membranes were incubated for 40 min in a blocking buffer (PBS + 1% BSA) at room temperature, and then probed with a given primary Ab overnight at 4oC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>After 3 washing steps for 10 min each with PBS + 0.1% Tween 20, membranes were incubated with an IRdye secondary Ab (Licor, Lincoln, NE) for 30 min at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>Finally, membranes were washed 3 times (10 min each) in PBS + 0.1% Tween 20, rinsed in ddH2O and antigen-Ab complexes were visualized using an Odyssey CLx system (Licor). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_11"><title><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>Total Internal Reflection Fluorescence Microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>MSCs-GFP and BCCs were co-plated (6 × 104 cells each) into 35-mm microscopy dishes containing coverslips (0.17 mm in diameter) (MatTek, Ashland, MA), and incubated overnight at 37oC prior the beginning of the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>Nikon Eclipse Ti inverted microscope equipped with a Nikon TI-TIRF Illuminator unit (Melville, NY) and a 60X Apo-TIRF oil-immersion objective (NA 1.49) was used to capture images. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>Cells were kept in a humid, live-cell chamber set at 37oC and 5% CO2 throughout the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>A 40 mW Argon ion laser tuned to 488 nm and a solid-state 561 nm laser were used to excite GFP and DsRed or β-actin-mCherry, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>Images were recorded using a Nikon Digital Sight DS-U3 CCD camera and processed using Nikon NIS Elements AR 3.22 software and Fiji. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>When indicated, 3 μg/μl anti-CD9 Ab (Abcam clone MEM-61) was added to the dish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>Since the TIRF microscope excites fluorophores only ~100 nm from the coverslip, overlapping green and red fluorescence signified entry of the BCC into the MSC rather than cell stacking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>Entries of BCCs were considered invasions if ≥50% of the cell was inside of, or passed through, a MSC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_12"><title><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>Confocal Microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>Cells (1 × 106) of the indicated cell lines were plated into 35-mm microscopy dishes containing 0.17 mm coverslips on the bottom (MatTek) and incubated overnight at 37oC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed with PBS, fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) and permeabilized with 0.2% Tween 20 in PBS for 15 min at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>Afterward, they were labeled with 25 μg/ml anti-CD9 Ab (clone HI9a, BioLegend), 2 μg/ml anti-β1 integrin Ab, 2 μg/ml anti-tubulin Ab, 10 μg/ml anti-acetylated tubulin Ab, 10 μg /ml anti-CD81 Ab, 4 μg/ml anti-CD44 Ab, or 4 μg/ml anti-IgSF8 Ab diluted in permeabilization buffer for 1 h at room temperature followed by TRITC-conjugated anti-rabbit (1:50) or anti-goat (1:100) IgG or 1:50 dilution Cy5-conjugated anti-mouse secondary Ab (Jackson ImmunoResearch or Sigma) for 30 min at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>Cells stained with fluorescent secondary Ab alone were employed as a control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed in PBS and, where indicated, stained with 1 μg/ml DAPI (MP Biomedicals, Santa Ana, CA) prior to imaging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>Cells stained with TRITC- or Cy5-conjugated anti-mouse secondary Ab alone were used as a control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>Live cell imaging was performed in an incubation chamber at 37oC under 5% CO2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>Cells were imaged using confocal laser-scanning microscopy on a Nikon A1R+ using a galvano or resonant scanner and a 60X Apo-TIRF oil-immersion objective with a numerical aperture of 1.49 at either 512 × 512 or 1024 × 1024 pixel resolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>405 nm, 488 nm, 561 nm, and 638 nm solid-state lasers were used to excite DAPI, GFP, TRITC, and Cy5, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>DAPI, GFP, TRITC, and Cy5 fluorescence emissions were collected using 425-475 nm, 500-550 nm, 570-620, and 662-737 nm longpass filters, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>GFP and TRITC emissions were collected using higher-sensitivity GaAsP detectors on the A1R+ microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>Images were recorded using NIS Elements software (Nikon) Raw images were processed using Fiji [60]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_13"><title><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>Co-localization Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>MDA-CD9-GFP cells plated in 35-mm dishes with 0.17 mm coverslips on the bottom were fixed with 4% PFA for 20 min at 4oC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>The cells were permeabilized with 0.2% Tween 20 in PBS for 15-30 min at RT, then stained with 4 μg/ml anti-CD44 or anti-CD81 Abs for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>The cells were washed and stained with a 1:50 dilution of Cy5-conjugated anti-mouse secondary Ab (Jackson ImmunoResearch) for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>Cells stained with Cy5-conjugated anti-mouse secondary Ab alone were employed as a control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>The cells were washed with PBS prior to viewing on a Nikon A1R+ confocal microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>The Coloc 2 plugin of Fiji was used to determine Pearson's coefficients of ROIs within background-subtracted images. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>Averages are reported +/− s.e.m. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_14"><title><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>Cell Fluorescence and Membrane Protrusion Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>Images of MDA lines were acquired under the same microscope settings for calculations of mean protrusion fluorescence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>All analysis was performed using Fiji. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>Maximum intensity projections of CD9 or CD81 z-stacks were thresholded until all cells were visible, and ROI outlines of cells created using the “analyze particles” function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>Mean fluorescence and integrated density were measured within cell outlines that were overlayed onto original z-stacks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>Mean protrusion fluorescence was calculated by subtracting the integrated density (mean fluorescence x area) of the cell body from the entire cell (which included protrusions), then dividing by the area difference: Mean protrusion fluorescence = (Int Dens total - Int Dens cell body)/(Area total – Area cell body). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>The z-slice containing the maximum fluorescence and its two surrounding z-slices were averaged for at least 4 XY positions to calculate mean protrusion and total fluorescence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>ROI outlines of MDA-CD9-GFP, MA-11-CD9-GFP, and MCF-7-CD9-GFP lines were created as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>Areas of protrusions were quantified by subtracting the area of the cell body from the total cell area for at least 3 XY positions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>One-way ANOVA and Tukey post-hoc analysis were used to determine if there were statistically significant differences between BCC lines in terms of protrusion area and fluorescence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>A minimum of 100 cells was evaluated for each condition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_15"><title><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>Scanning Electron Microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>BCCs and MDA CD9shRNA cells were plated and grown on coverslips coated with 0.01% poly-L-lysine (#P4707, Sigma, Darmstadt, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>After 2 days, they were fixed in 2% glutaraldehyde for 1 h at room temperature and then overnight at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>Following 2-h post-fixation in 1% osmium tetroxide at 4°C, they were subjected to dehydration in an acetone gradient (25–100%) and critical point-dried in a CO2 system (Critical Point Dryer, Leica Microsystems, EM CPD 300, Wetzlar, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>Samples were then sputter-coated with gold (sputter coating device SCD 050; BAL-TEC GmbH, Witten, Germany) and examined at 5-kV accelerating voltage in field emission scanning electron microscope (Jeol JSM 7500F, Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>The dimension (length and thickness) of various PMPs was quantified using ImageJ [60]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4_16"><title><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>In Vivo Studies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>In vivo studies were performed by AntiCancer, Inc. upon approval by the AntiCancer Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) and conducted in accordance with the principles and procedures outlined in the National Institutes of Health Guide for the Care and Use of Animals under Assurance No. A3873-01. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>NU/NU nude mice from Charles River (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.criver.com/products-services/basic-research/find-a-model/nu-nu-nude-mouse">http://www.criver.com/products-services/basic-research/find-a-model/nu-nu-nude-mouse</ext-link>) were kept within a barrier under HEPA filtration. and fed autoclaved laboratory rodent diet (Tecklad LM-485, Western Research Products, Orange, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>Viable MDA-DsRed and MDA-DsRed-CD9shRNA cells (6 × 106) were resuspended in 100 μl 50% growth factor-reduced Matrigel and injected orthotopically into the second thoracic gland of 5-6 weeks old female nu/nu mice (10 animals/group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>Mice were randomized based on age and weight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>No blinding was done. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>Tumor size was measured by live-animal fluorescence imaging (FluorVivo) once per week and at study termination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>Open imaging was performed to check metastases using the Olympus OV-100 imaging system (Olympus) at study termination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>Mice were euthanized when the tumor burden exceeded 10 mm. in greater diameter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>Euthanasia was achieved by 100% carbon dioxide inhalation, followed by cervical dislocation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL, FIGURES, TABLES </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="avi" xlink:href="oncotarget-06-7970-s001.avi" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e1663" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="avi" xlink:href="oncotarget-06-7970-s002.avi" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e1665" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="avi" xlink:href="oncotarget-06-7970-s003.avi" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e1667" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD4"><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="avi" xlink:href="oncotarget-06-7970-s004.avi" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e1669" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD5"><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="oncotarget-06-7970-s005.pdf" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e1671" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>The authors thank Harry Rosenberg and Renee Coffman for their constant support; Fabio Anzanello for invaluable technical assistance; Giuseppe Pizzorno for critical reading of the manuscript; and Darwin Prockop for human MSCs through grant # P40RR017447 from NCRR of the NIH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by US NIH R01CA133797 (Rappa), and Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft through SFB655 (Corbeil). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Cancer Institute or the National Institutes of Health. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>BCCs</term><def><p>breast cancer cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MSCs</term><def><p>multipotent mesenchymal stromal cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MDA</term><def><p>MDA-MB-231</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PMPs</term><def><p>plasma membrane protrusions</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HuMECs</term><def><p>human mammary epithelial cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SEM</term><def><p>scanning electron microscopy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TIRF</term><def><p>total internal reflection fluorescence</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MIP</term><def><p>maximum intensity projections</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><text><SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>1TakebeNWarrenRQIvySPBreast cancer growth and metastasis: interplay between cancer stem cells, embryonic signaling pathways and epithelial-to-mesenchymal transitionBreast Cancer Res201113211 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R2"><text><SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>2QuailDFJoyceJAMicroenvironmental regulation of tumor progression and metastasisNat Med2013191423143724202395 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R3"><text><SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>3MacheskyLMLamellipodia and filopodia in metastasis and invasionFEBS Lett20085822102211118396168 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R4"><text><SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>4KhuonSLiangLDettmanRWSpornPHWysolmerskiRBChewTLMyosin light chain kinase mediates transcellular intravasation of breast cancer cells through the underlying endothelial cells: a three-dimensional FRET studyJ Cell Sci201012343144020067998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R5"><text><SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>5OverholtzerMBruggeJSThe cell biology of cell-in-cell structuresNat Rev Mol Cell Biol2008979680918784728 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R6"><text><SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>6PawelekJMChakrabortyAKFusion of tumour cells with bone marrow-derived cells: a unifying explanation for metastasisNat Rev Cancer2008837738618385683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R7"><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>7DuelliDLazebnikYCell fusion: a hidden enemy?Cancer Cell2003344544812781362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R8"><text><SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>8LuXKangYCell fusion as a hidden force in tumor progressionCancer Res2009698536853919887616 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R9"><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>9PowellAEAndersonECDaviesPSSilkADPelzCImpeySWongMHFusion between Intestinal epithelial cells and macrophages in a cancer context results in nuclear reprogrammingCancer Res2011711497150521303980 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R10"><text><SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>10JacobsenBMHarrellJCJedlickaPBorgesVFVarella-GarciaMHorwitzKBSpontaneous fusion with, and transformation of mouse stroma by, malignant human breast cancer epitheliumCancer Res2006668274827916912208 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R11"><text><SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>11RappaGMercapideJLoricoASpontaneous formation of tumorigenic hybrids between breast cancer and multipotent stromal cells is a source of tumor heterogeneityAm J Pathol20121802504251522542847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R12"><text><SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>12ZöllerMTetraspanins: push and pull in suppressing and promoting metastasisNat Rev Cancer20099405519078974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R13"><text><SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>13HemlerMETetraspanin proteins mediate cellular penetration, invasion, and fusion events and define a novel type of membrane microdomainAnnu Rev Cell Dev Biol20031939742214570575 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R14"><text><SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>14Le NaourFRubinsteinEJasminCPrenantMBoucheixCSeverely reduced female fertility in CD9-deficient miceScience200028731932110634790 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R15"><text><SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>15ChenMSTungKSCoonrodSATakahashiYBiglerDChangAYamashitaYKincadePWHerrJCWhiteJMRole of the integrin-associated protein CD9 in binding between sperm ADAM 2 and the egg integrin alpha6beta1: implications for murine fertilizationProc Natl Acad Sci U S A199996118301183510518536 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R16"><text><SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>16TachibanaIHemlerMERole of transmembrane 4 superfamily (TM4SF) proteins CD9 and CD81 in muscle cell fusion and myotube maintenanceJ Biol Chem1999146893904 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R17"><text><SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>17SchmidEZurbriggenAGassenURimaBter MeulenVSchneider-SchauliesJAntibodies to CD9, a tetraspan transmembrane protein, inhibit canine distemper virus-induced cell-cell fusion but not virus-cell fusionJ Virol2000747554756110906209 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R18"><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>18Gordon-AlonsoMYanez-MoMBarreiroOAlvarezSMunoz-FernandezMAValenzuela-FernandezASanchez-MadridFTetraspanins CD9 and CD81 modulate HIV-1-induced membrane fusionJ Immunol20061775129513717015697 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R19"><text><SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>19SekiyaILarsonBLSmithJRPochampallyRCuiJGProckopDJExpansion of human adult stem cells from bone marrow stroma: conditions that maximize the yields of early progenitors and evaluate their qualityStem Cells20022053054112456961 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R20"><text><SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>20MattheysesALSimonSMRappoportJZImaging with total internal reflection fluorescence microscopy for the cell biologistJ Cell Sci20101233621362820971701 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R21"><text><SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>21RadfordKJThorneRFHerseyPCD63 associates with transmembrane 4 superfamily members, CD9 and CD81, and with beta 1 integrins in human melanomaBiochem Biophys Res Commun199622213188630057 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R22"><text><SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>22HorvathGSerruVClayDBillardMBoucheixCRubinsteinECD19 is linked to the integrin-associated tetraspans CD9, CD81, and CD82J Biol Chem199827330537305439804823 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R23"><text><SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>23TakedaYHePTachibanaIZhouBMiyadoKKanekoHSuzukiMMinamiSIwasakiTGoyaSDouble deficiency of tetraspanins CD9 and CD81 alters cell motility and protease production of macrophages and causes chronic obstructive pulmonary disease-like phenotype in miceJ Biol Chem2008283260892609718662991 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R24"><text><SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>24KajiKOdaSShikanoTOhnukiTUematsuYSakagamiJTadaNMiyazakiSKudoAThe gamete fusion process is defective in eggs of Cd9-deficient miceNat Genet20002427928210700183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R25"><text><SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>25ArduiseCAbacheTLiLBillardMChabanonALudwigAMauduitPBoucheixCRubinsteinELe NaourFTetraspanins regulate ADAM10-mediated cleavage of TNF-alpha and epidermal growth factorJ Immunol20081817002701318981120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R26"><text><SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>26LiuPCLiuXLiYCovingtonMWynnRHuberRHillmanMYangGEllisDMarandoCIdentification of ADAM10 as a major source of HER2 ectodomain sheddase activity in HER2 overexpressing breast cancer cellsCancer Biol Ther2006565766416627989 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R27"><text><SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>27ZukauskasAMerleyALiDAngLHSciutoTESalmanSDvorakAMDvorakHFJaminetSCTM4SF1: a tetraspanin-like protein necessary for nanopodia formation and endothelial cell migrationAngiogenesis20111434535421626280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R28"><text><SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>28PenasPFGarcia-DiezASanchez-MadridFYanez-MoMTetraspanins are localized at motility-related structures and involved in normal human keratinocyte wound healing migrationThe Journal of investigative dermatology20001141126113510844555 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R29"><text><SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain>29PolanskaUMOrimoACarcinoma-associated fibroblasts: non-neoplastic tumour-promoting mesenchymal cellsJ Cell Physiol20132281651165723460038 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R30"><text><SENT sid="550" pm="."><plain>30JegouAZiyyatABarraud-LangeVPerezEWolfJPPincetFGourierCCD9 tetraspanin generates fusion competent sites on the egg membrane for mammalian fertilizationProc Natl Acad Sci U S A2011108109461095121690351 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R31"><text><SENT sid="551" pm="."><plain>31BarreiroOYanez-MoMSala-ValdesMGutierrez-LopezMDOvalleSHigginbottomAMonkPNCabanasCSanchez-MadridFEndothelial tetraspanin microdomains regulate leukocyte firm adhesion during extravasationBlood20051052852286115591117 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R32"><text><SENT sid="552" pm="."><plain>32RungeKEEvansJEHeZYGuptaSMcDonaldKLStahlbergHPrimakoffPMylesDGOocyte CD9 is enriched on the microvillar membrane and required for normal microvillar shape and distributionDev Biol200730431732517239847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R33"><text><SENT sid="553" pm="."><plain>33SingethanKMullerNSchubertSLuttgeDKrementsovDNKhuranaSRKrohneGSchneider-SchauliesSThaliMSchneider-SchauliesJCD9 clustering and formation of microvilli zippers between contacting cells regulates virus-induced cell fusionTraffic2008992493518363777 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R34"><text><SENT sid="554" pm="."><plain>34ZylkiewiczENowakowskaJMaleszewskiMDecrease in CD9 content and reorganization of microvilli may contribute to the oolemma block to sperm penetration during fertilization of mouse oocyteZygote20101819520119939329 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R35"><text><SENT sid="555" pm="."><plain>35EspenelCMargeatEDossetPArduiseCLe GrimellecCRoyerCABoucheixCRubinsteinEMilhietPESingle-molecule analysis of CD9 dynamics and partitioning reveals multiple modes of interaction in the tetraspanin webJ Cell Biol200818276577618710926 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R36"><text><SENT sid="556" pm="."><plain>36KinoshitaYKinoshitaCHeuerJGBothwellMBasic fibroblast growth factor promotes adhesive interactions of neuroepithelial cells from chick neural tube with extracellular matrix proteins in cultureDevelopment19931199439568187649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R37"><text><SENT sid="557" pm="."><plain>37BauerNWilsch-BräuningerMKarbanováJFonsecaAVStraussDFreundDThieleCHuttnerWBBornhäuserMCorbeilDHaematopoietic stem cell differentiation promotes the release of prominin-1/CD133-containing membrane vesicles--a role of the endocytic-exocytic pathwayEMBO Mol Med2011339840921591261 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R38"><text><SENT sid="558" pm="."><plain>38MercapideJAnzanelloFRappaGLoricoARelationship between tumor cell invasiveness and polyploidizationPLoS One20137e5336423300919 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R39"><text><SENT sid="559" pm="."><plain>39KrajcovicMJohnsonNBSunQNormandGHooverNYaoERichardsonALKingRWCibasESSchnittSJA non-genetic route to aneuploidy in human cancersNat Cell Biol20111332433021336303 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R40"><text><SENT sid="560" pm="."><plain>40OverholtzerMMailleuxAAMouneimneGNormandGSchnittSJKingRWCibasESBruggeJSA nonapoptotic cell death process, entosis, that occurs by cell-in-cell invasionCell200713196697918045538 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R41"><text><SENT sid="561" pm="."><plain>41JanssenAMedemaRHEntosis: aneuploidy by invasionNat Cell Biol20111319920121364569 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R42"><text><SENT sid="562" pm="."><plain>42WinnardPTJrPathakAPDharaSChoSYRamanVPomperMGMolecular imaging of metastatic potentialJ Nucl Med200849 Suppl296S112S18523068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R43"><text><SENT sid="563" pm="."><plain>43SubikKLeeJFBaxterLStrzepekTCostelloDCrowleyPXingLHungMCBonfiglioTHicksDGTangPThe Expression Patterns of ER, PR, HER2, CK5/6, EGFR, Ki-67 and AR by Immunohistochemical Analysis in Breast Cancer Cell LinesBreast cancer: Breast Cancer (Auckl)201043541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R44"><text><SENT sid="564" pm="."><plain>44DuffyMJMulloolyMO'DonovanNSukorSCrownJPierceAMcGowan PM: The ADAMs family of proteases: new biomarkers and therapeutic targets for cancer?Clin Proteomics201189 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R45"><text><SENT sid="565" pm="."><plain>45Gustafson-WagnerEStippCSThe CD9/CD81 tetraspanin complex and tetraspanin CD151 regulate alpha3beta1 integrin-dependent tumor cell behaviors by overlapping but distinct mechanismsPLoS One20138e6183423613949 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R46"><text><SENT sid="566" pm="."><plain>46ZhouBGibson-CorleyKNHerndonMESunYGustafson-WagnerETeoh-FitzgeraldMDomannFEHenryMDStippCSIntegrin alpha3beta1 can function to promote spontaneous metastasis and lung colonization of invasive breast carcinomaMol Cancer Res20141214315424002891 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R47"><text><SENT sid="567" pm="."><plain>47MischiatiCNataliPGSereniASibilioLGiordaECappellacciSNicotraMRMarianiGDi FilippoFCatricalaCcDNA-array profiling of melanomas and paired melanocyte culturesJ Cell Physiol200620769770516523488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R48"><text><SENT sid="568" pm="."><plain>48LongoNYanez-MoMMittelbrunnMde la RosaGMunozMLSanchez-MadridFSanchez-MateosPRegulatory role of tetraspanin CD9 in tumor-endothelial cell interaction during transendothelial invasion of melanoma cellsBlood2001983717372611739177 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R49"><text><SENT sid="569" pm="."><plain>49KischelPBellahceneADeuxBLamourVDobsonREDEPClezardinPCastronovoVOverexpression of CD9 in human breast cancer cells promotes the development of bone metastasesAnticancer Res2012325211522023225418 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R50"><text><SENT sid="570" pm="."><plain>50Castro-SanchezLSoto-GuzmanANavarro-TitoNMartinez-OrozcoRSalazarEPNative type IV collagen induces cell migration through a CD9 and DDR1-dependent pathway in MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cellsEur J Cell Biol20108984385220709424 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R51"><text><SENT sid="571" pm="."><plain>51HwangJRJoKLeeYSungBJParkYWLeeJHUpregulation of CD9 in ovarian cancer is related to the induction of TNF-alpha gene expression and constitutive NF-kappaB activationCarcinogenesis201233778322095071 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R52"><text><SENT sid="572" pm="."><plain>52HerrMJKothaJHagedornNSmithBJenningsLKTetraspanin CD9 promotes the invasive phenotype of human fibrosarcoma cells via upregulation of matrix metalloproteinase-9PLoS One20138e6776623840773 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R53"><text><SENT sid="573" pm="."><plain>53FanJZhuGZNilesRMExpression and function of CD9 in melanoma cellsMol Carcinog201049859319777564 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R54"><text><SENT sid="574" pm="."><plain>54SauerGWindischJKurzederCHeilmannVKreienbergRDeisslerHProgression of cervical carcinomas is associated with down-regulation of CD9 but strong local re-expression at sites of transendothelial invasionClin Cancer Res200396426643114695144 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R55"><text><SENT sid="575" pm="."><plain>55RyePDNorumLOlsenDRGarman-VikSKaulSFodstadOBrain metastasis model in athymic nude mice using a novel MUC1-secreting human breast-cancer cell line, MA11Int J Cancer1996686826878938153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R56"><text><SENT sid="576" pm="."><plain>56RappaGLoricoAPhenotypic characterization of mammosphere-forming cells from the human MA-11 breast carcinoma cell lineExp Cell Res20103161576158620074564 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R57"><text><SENT sid="577" pm="."><plain>57LarsonBLYlostaloJProckopDJHuman multipotent stromal cells undergo sharp transition from division to development in cultureStem Cells20082619320117916801 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R58"><text><SENT sid="578" pm="."><plain>58HildingerMAbelKLOstertagWBaumCDesign of 5′ untranslated sequences in retroviral vectors developed for medical useJ Virol1999734083408910196304 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R59"><text><SENT sid="579" pm="."><plain>59RappaGKunkeDHolterJDiepDBMeyerJBaumCFodstadOKraussSLoricoAEfficient expansion and gene transduction of mouse neural stem/progenitor cells on recombinant fibronectinNeuroscience200412482383015026123 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R60"><text><SENT sid="580" pm="."><plain>60SchneiderCARasbandWSEliceiriKWNIH Image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysisNat Methods2012967167522930834 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
