<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4190355</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25295591</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-31817</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110061</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genomic Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic Testing</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic Diseases</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cancer Risk Factors</subject><subject>Carcinogenesis</subject><subject>Carcinogens</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Role of <italic>IL-4</italic> Gene Polymorphisms in HBV-Related Hepatocellular Carcinoma in a Chinese Population</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>IL-4</italic> Gene Polymorphisms and HBV-Related Hepatocellular Carcinoma Risk</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Yu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Zhitong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Qiliu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Liping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xiaolian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Jiangyang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Xue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Shan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Clinical Laboratory, First Affiliated Hospital of Guangxi Medical University, Nanning, Guangxi, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Guigang People&#x02019;s Hospital, Guigang, Guangxi, China</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>William B.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of North Carolina School of Medicine, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>qinxue919@126.com</email> (XQ); <email>lis8858@126.com</email> (SL)</corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: XQ SL. Performed the experiments: YL ZTW. Analyzed the data: QLP LPM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: XLZ JYZ. Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: YL.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e110061</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2014 Lu et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Lu et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Interleukin-4 (IL-4) is best known as an important mediator and modulator of immune and inflammatory responses. Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is a typical inflammation-related cancer, and genetic variations in the <italic>IL-4</italic> gene may be associated with the risk of hepatitis B virus (HBV)-related HCC. However, few studies have been conducted on their association.</p></sec><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>To clarify the effects of <italic>IL-4</italic> gene polymorphisms on the risk of HBV-related HCC, two common variants, &#x02212;590C/T (rs2243250) and &#x02212;33C/T (rs2070874), and their relationship with HBV-related disease risk were investigated in a Chinese population.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>
<italic>IL-4</italic> &#x02212;590C/T and &#x02212;33C/T polymorphisms were examined in 154 patients with HBV-related HCC, 62 patients with HBV-induced liver cirrhosis (LC), 129 patients with chronic hepatitis B (CHB), and 94 healthy controls, using the polymerase chain reaction-restriction fragment length polymorphism method and DNA sequencing.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Overall, no significant differences were observed regarding the <italic>IL-4</italic> &#x02212;590C/T and &#x02212;33C/T polymorphism genotypes, alleles, or haplotypes between the patient groups and the healthy controls. However, the CC genotypes of <italic>IL-4</italic> &#x02212;590C/T and &#x02212;33C/T polymorphisms were observed to be significantly associated with CHB in subgroup analysis in males [CC versus TT (OR: 4.193, 95% CI: 1.094&#x02013;16.071, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.037; and OR: 3.438, 95% CI: 1.032&#x02013;11.458, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.044) and CC versus TT+CT (OR: 4.09, 95% CI: 1.08&#x02013;15.49, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.038; and OR: 3.43, 95% CI: 1.04&#x02013;11.28, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.042)].</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>These findings suggest that genetic variants in <italic>IL-4</italic> &#x02212;590C/T and &#x02212;33C/T polymorphisms may be a risk factor for CHB in Chinese males but not for HBV-related LC or HCC.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This research was supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 81260302) and Youth Science Foundation of Guangxi Medical University (GXMUYSF201334). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection is one of the leading causes of liver disease, with more than 2 billion people infected worldwide <xref rid="pone.0110061-Liaw1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0110061-Lavanchy1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Among them, approximately 350 million individuals persistently infected with HBV develop chronic hepatitis, which results in liver cirrhosis (LC) in one third of all cases, more than three quarters of which progress to hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) <xref rid="pone.0110061-Perz1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. It is widely accepted that chronic hepatitis B (CHB), LC, and HCC are progressive stages of chronic HBV infection <xref rid="pone.0110061-Yin1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Nevertheless, the mechanisms underlying such progression are not yet well understood, although immune system-mediated chronic inflammation is believed to play a pivotal role in HCC development. HBV clearance depends on an effective host immune response <xref rid="pone.0110061-Chisari1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref> and, thus, ineffective host immunity may create a hepatocarcinogenic microenvironment in the presence of HBV infection <xref rid="pone.0110061-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0110061-Han1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>.</p><p>Interleukin-4 (IL-4), a multifunctional pleiotropic cytokine mainly produced by activated T helper 2 (Th2) cells, plays important roles as a mediator and modulator of immune and inflammatory responses <xref rid="pone.0110061-Durie1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>; it is not only involved in humoral and cell-mediated immunity, but also an essential regulator in the immune response of B cells, T cells, and macrophages to fight against infections and malignant cells <xref rid="pone.0110061-Landi1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>; Th2 diseases are, in their majority, driven by IL-4 <xref rid="pone.0110061-Luzina1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. In addition, IL-4 and IL-13 are the archetypal inducers of M2 <xref rid="pone.0110061-Gordon1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>- an alternatively activated macrophage <xref rid="pone.0110061-Stein1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> that has been proved to promote HCC development <xref rid="pone.0110061-Capece1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Any alterations that influence the expression and function of IL-4 can lead to weakened immune responses, and thus increase the susceptibility to infections and inflammation-related diseases <xref rid="pone.0110061-Jiang1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Due to their highly polymorphic nature, genetic mutations in this gene might be the major contributor.</p><p>The human <italic>IL-4</italic> gene is located on chromosome 5q31 and consists of 25 kbps <xref rid="pone.0110061-Marsh1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. So far, more than 50 allelic variant polymorphisms have been found (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/</ext-link>), including &#x02212;590C/T (rs2243250), &#x02212;33C/T (rs2070874), +3437C/G (rs2227282), and 2979G/T (rs2227284) <xref rid="pone.0110061-Naslednikova1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. The impact of <italic>IL-4</italic> gene polymorphisms in the pathogenesis of HBV infection has been investigated, and numerous studies have suggested that <italic>IL-4</italic> variants play pivotal roles in hepatitis B vaccine response and HBV infection risk <xref rid="pone.0110061-Aithal1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0110061-Cui1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. However, to date, few studies have been conducted to investigate the role of these polymorphisms in HCC development <xref rid="pone.0110061-Ognjanovic1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. In the present study, the two most common promoter polymorphisms of <italic>IL-4</italic>, &#x02212;590C/T (rs2243250) and &#x02212;33C/T (rs2070874), were evaluated in four Chinese patient groups &#x02013; patients with CHB, LC, and HBV-related HCC, and a healthy control group &#x02013; to determine whether these <italic>IL-4</italic> gene polymorphisms contribute to the susceptibility of HBV-related HCC.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Study population</title><p>A hospital-based series of 345 unrelated patients were recruited from the First Affiliated Hospital of Guangxi Medical University (Guangxi, China) between June and November 2013, including 154 patients with HBV-related HCC, 62 patients with HBV-induced LC, and 129 patients with CHB. To confirm that all patients had a chronic HBV infection for a period of at least 6 months, hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), hepatitis B virus core antibody, and hepatitis Be antigen or hepatitis Be antibody were confirmed as seropositive. CHB was further diagnosed with serum HBV-DNA levels &#x0003e;1,000 copies/mL, as well as elevated alanine aminotransferase or aspartate aminotransferase (&#x0003e;2 times the upper limit of normal) <xref rid="pone.0110061-Lok1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. LC was diagnosed by histologic analysis of liver biopsy specimens or typical morphologic findings from computed tomography or ultrasonography, together with laboratory features. For the HCC group, the patients enrolled fulfilled the following criteria: i) positive cytologic or pathologic findings or ii) elevated &#x003b1;-fetoprotein levels (&#x02265;400 ng/mL) combined with a positive image on computed tomography or ultrasonography; iii) were newly diagnosed HCC patients without a prior medical history of HCC; and iv) not diagnosed with other cancers <xref rid="pone.0110061-Peng1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. For comparison, 170 HBV free healthy controls were randomly selected from the Health Examination Center of the First Affiliated Hospital of Guangxi Medical University during the same period. The selection criteria for controls were absence of any malignancy or other serious illness, as well as other inflammatory status such as autoimmune hepatitis which may generate possible bais. All subjects were Chinese from the Guangxi District. Written informed consent was obtained from each participant, and the study was approved by the ethics committee of the First Affiliated Hospital of Guangxi Medical University, Nanning, Guangxi, China.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>DNA extraction and single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) genotyping</title><p>By using the standard phenol-chloroform method, genomic DNA was extracted from 2 mL peripheral white blood cells. The &#x02212;589C/T and &#x02212;33C/T SNPs in <italic>IL-4</italic> were detected by polymerase chain reaction-restriction fragment length polymorphism (PCR-RFLP). Primers and probes were designed by Sangon Biotech Company (Shanghai, China). The primer sequences, annealing temperature, length of the PCR products, and corresponding restriction enzyme used for genotyping are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0110061.s001">Table S1</xref>. After amplification, the PCR product was digested by restriction enzyme, visualized on a 2.5% agarose gel, and stained with ethidium bromide (Promega Corporation, Madison, WI, USA) for genotyping (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0110061-g001">Figure 1</xref>). The genotyping was performed for all participants under blinded conditions. For quality control, 50% of samples were repeated and direct sequencing was also performed by Sangon Biotech Company using 10% randomly selected samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0110061-g002">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0110061-g003">3</xref>); a 100% concordance rate was achieved.</p><fig id="pone-0110061-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110061.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>PCR-RFLP assay for analyzing the IL-4&#x02212;589C/T and &#x02212;33C/T polymorphisms of the IL-4 gene.</title><p>PCR product was digested by restriction enzyme and visualized on a 2.5% agarose gel. a &#x02212;589C/T polymorphism. Lanes 1 and 2 show CC genotype; lanes 3, 4 and 5 show TT genotype; lanes 6 and 7 show CT genotype. b &#x02212;33C/T polymorphism. Lanes 1, 2 and 3 show TT genotype; lanes 4 and 5 show CC genotype; lanes 6 and 7 show CT genotype. M, marker.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0110061.g001"/></fig><fig id="pone-0110061-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110061.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Sequencing map of the genotype for the IL-4&#x02212;589C/T polymorphism.</title><p>Arrow in parts a&#x02212;c indicates CC, TT and C/T genotypes, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0110061.g002"/></fig><fig id="pone-0110061-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110061.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Sequencing map of the genotype for the IL-4&#x02212;33C/T polymorphisms.</title><p>Arrow in parts a&#x02212;c indicates CC, TT and C/T genotypes, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0110061.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The statistical analyses were performed using the statistical software package SPSS 16.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). The Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) was firstly tested with a goodness-of-fit &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> test. General characteristics among the four groups were determined via Analysis of Variance (ANOVA) and the allele frequency and genotype distribution of <italic>IL-4</italic> gene polymorphisms were compared using the &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> test and Fisher&#x02019;s exact test, when appropriate. Binary logistic regression was used to calculate the odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) after age and gender status adjustments. Globally, HCC rates are more than twice as high in males as in females <xref rid="pone.0110061-Jemal1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> and, therefore, gender may be a possible confounder. Thus, a stratification of the study population into males and females was further performed to evaluate the association within each stratum. Considering the possible linkage disequilibrium between the polymorphisms, Shi&#x02019;s standardized coefficient D&#x02019; was used for quantification <xref rid="pone.0110061-Shi1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>; using the Phase program <xref rid="pone.0110061-Li1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0110061-Stephens1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, haplotypes and their frequencies were also estimated based on a Bayesian algorithm. All significance tests were two-sided, and <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 was considered a statistically significant difference.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Characteristics of the study participants</title><p>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0110061-t001">Table 1</xref> summarizes the basic characteristics of the 170 healthy controls and the 129 CHB, 62 LC, and 154 HCC patients. Briefly, the LC and HCC patients were, on average, 10 years older than CHB patients and healthy controls, with the difference being statistically significant (both <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001). As for gender distribution, there were no significant differences between the case and control groups (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.488, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.618, and <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.751, respectively).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0110061-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110061.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Basic characteristic of the study population.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0110061-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0110061.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HealthyControls(n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;170)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHB patients(n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;129)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>-value</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LC patients(n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;62)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>-value</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCC patients(n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;154)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>-value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age(year, mean&#x000b1;SD)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.68&#x000b1;11.76</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.67&#x000b1;7.78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.994</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.38&#x000b1;9.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.19&#x000b1;11.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender, N(%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147(86.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115(89.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.488</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52(83.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.618</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135(87.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.751</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23(13.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(10.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(16.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19(12.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Genotype polymorphisms and the risk of HBV-related diseases</title><p>The genotype and allele frequencies of the &#x02212;589C/T and &#x02212;33C/T <italic>IL-4</italic> gene polymorphisms for patients with HBV-related diseases and healthy controls are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0110061-t002">Table 2</xref>. According to the HWE test, the genotype distribution of the two SNPs in the patient groups and healthy controls were all agreed with HWE (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003e;0.05 for all). However, no significant differences between the genotype and allele frequencies of the &#x02212;589C/T and &#x02212;33C/T <italic>IL-4</italic> gene polymorphisms and CHB risk were observed. Binary logistic regression analyses adjusted for age and gender also failed to reveal any significant difference between them. Further, when considering LC and HCC patients, similar non-significant results were also found.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0110061-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110061.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Genotype and allele frequencies of &#x02212;589C/T and &#x02212;33C/T polymorphisms between HBV-related patients and healthy controls.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0110061-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0110061.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polymorphisms</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthycontrols,N&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;170(%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHBpatientsN&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;129(%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LCpatients,N&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;62(%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCCpatients,N&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;154(%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHB patientsvs. Healthycontrols</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LC patients vs.Healthy controls</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCC patientsvs. Healthycontrols</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">OR (95%CI)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;589C/T</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115(67.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77(59.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37(59.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111(72.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51(30.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43(33.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22(35.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39(25.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28(0.78&#x02013;2.12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58(0.80&#x02013;3.10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90(0.52&#x02013;1.56)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(2.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9(7.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(4.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(2.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.35(0.99&#x02013;11.28)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10(0.39&#x02013;11.34)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13(0.26&#x02013;5.06)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dominant model<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55(32.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52(40.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25(40.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43(27.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44(0.89&#x02013;2.33)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56(0.81&#x02013;2.99)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.921(0.54&#x02013;1.56)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recessive model<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">c</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166(97.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120(93.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59(95.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150(97.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.08(0.93&#x02013;10.25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92(0.87&#x02013;7.36)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17(0.27&#x02013;5.13)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T allele</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">281(82.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197(76.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96(77.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261(84.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C allele</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59(17.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61(23.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28(22.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47(15.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49(0.99&#x02013;2.23)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51(0.87&#x02013;2.61)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95(0.60&#x02013;1.51)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-<sub>HWE</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.550</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.383</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.907</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.796</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;33C/T</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113(66.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77(59.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36(58.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97(63.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52(30.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42(32.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22(35.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49(31.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21(0.73&#x02013;2.00)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59(0.81&#x02013;3.13)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29(0.76&#x02013;2.20)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5(2.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(7.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(6.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8(5.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92(0.96&#x02013;8.92)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33(0.52&#x02013;10.56)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.24(0.65&#x02013;7.74)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dominant model<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57(33.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52(40.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26(41.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57(47.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36(0.84&#x02013;2.20)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67(0.87&#x02013;3.19)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38(0.83&#x02013;2.30)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recessive model<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">c</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165(97.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119(92.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58(93.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146(94.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74(0.91&#x02013;8.25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98(0.25&#x02013;8.74)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06(0.60&#x02013;7.01)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T allele</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">278(81.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">196(76.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94(75.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">263(78.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C allele</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62(18.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62(24.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30(24.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65(21.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43(0.96&#x02013;2.13)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56(0.91&#x02013;2.66)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38(0.90&#x02013;2.12)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-<sub>HWE</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.737</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.219</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.797</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.581</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>a</label><p>Adjusted by age and gender;</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>b</label><p>Dominant model: CT+CC versus TT;</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>c</label><p>Recessive model: CC versus TT+CT.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Nevertheless, when subgroup analyses between males and females were conducted, significant differences were found in males in the CC genotype in co-dominant genetic model CC versus TT and recessive genetic model CC versus TT+CT. Both 589C/T CC and &#x02212;33C/T CC genotypes in males were associated with a significantly increased risk of CHB compared with the TT genotype (OR: 4.193, 95% CI: 1.094&#x02013;16.071, and <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.037; and OR: 3.438, 95% CI: 1.032&#x02013;11.458, and <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.044); similar situation was also found in the recessive model (OR: 4.09, 95% CI: 1.08&#x02013;15.49, and <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.038; and OR: 3.43, 95% CI: 1.04&#x02013;11.28, and <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.042) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0110061-t003">Table 3</xref>). On the other hand, significant differences between case and control groups were not observed for any genotype in females (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0110061.s002">Table S2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0110061-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110061.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Genotype and allele frequencies of &#x02212;589C/T and &#x02212;33C/T polymorphisms between HBV-related patients and healthy controls in males.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0110061-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0110061.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polymorphisms</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthycontrols,N&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;147(%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHBpatientsN&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;115(%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LCpatients,N&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;52(%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCCpatients,N&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;135(%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHB patients vs.Healthy controls,OR(95%CI)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LC patients vs.Healthycontrols, OR(95%CI)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCC patientsvs. Healthycontrols, OR(95%CI)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">a</xref>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;589C/T</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotypes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100(68.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72(62.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31(59.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95(70.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44(30.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34(29.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19(36.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36(26.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08(0.63&#x02013;1.86)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92(0.92&#x02013;4.01)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01(0.57&#x02013;1.81)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(2.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9(7.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(3.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(3.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4.19(1.09&#x02013;16.07)</bold>
<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83(0.42&#x02013;18.88)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59(0.32&#x02013;7.98)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dominant modelb</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47(32.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43(37.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21(40.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40(29.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28(0.76&#x02013;2.15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98(0.99&#x02013;4.08)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05(0.60&#x02013;1.85)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recessive modelc</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144(98.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106(92.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50(96.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131(97.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4.09(1.08&#x02013;15.49)</bold>
<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23(0.35&#x02013;14.43)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58(0.32&#x02013;7.88)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T allele</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">244(83.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178(77.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81(77.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226(83.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C allele</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50(17.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52(22.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23(22.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44(16.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43(0.93&#x02013;2.06)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76(0.97&#x02013;3.18)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.085(0.67&#x02013;1.77)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;33C/T</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotypes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98(66.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72(62.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30(57.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84(62.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45(30.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33(28.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19(36.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43(31.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01(0.58&#x02013;1.74)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84(0.89&#x02013;3.82)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37(0.78&#x02013;2.43)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(2.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(8.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(5.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8(5.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3.44(1.03&#x02013;11.46)</bold>
<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.76(0.51&#x02013;14.96)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.96(0.78&#x02013;11.22)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dominant modelb</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49(33.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43(37.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22(42.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51(37.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20(0.72&#x02013;2.01)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92(0.95&#x02013;3.89)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51(0.87&#x02013;2.61)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recessive modelc</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143(97.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105(91.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49(94.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127(94.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3.43(1.04&#x02013;11.28)</bold>
<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.22(0.43&#x02013;11.54)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.65(0.71&#x02013;9.90)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T allele</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241(82.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177(77.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79(76.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211(78.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C allele</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53(18.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53(23.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24(24.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59(21.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37(0.89&#x02013;2.10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73(0.97&#x02013;3.07)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52(0.96&#x02013;2.41)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label>a</label><p>Adjusted by age and gender;</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>b</label><p>Dominant model: CT+CC versus TT;</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label>c</label><p>Recessive model: CC versus TT+CT;</p></fn><fn id="nt107"><label/><p>*p&#x0003c;0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Considering that the <italic>IL-4</italic> genetic background may be distinct between different populations, the genotype and allele frequencies of the two SNPs in our control group were further compared with those in different races from the Haplotype Map (HapMap) project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih</ext-link>. gov/snp/) as well as in previous reports <xref rid="pone.0110061-TangZY1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. The data shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0110061-t004">Table 4</xref> suggests that the distribution of the two SNPs in the present study is significantly different from that in JPT (Japanese in Tokyo) and CEU (Utah residents with northern and western European ancestry) populations. For the 589C/T polymorphism, the frequencies of genotype TT and allele T in JPT and CEU populations are significantly lower, and the rate of CC genotype and C allele are significantly higher. With respect to the &#x02212;33C/T polymorphism, significant genotype differences between the present study and YRI (Yoruba in Ibadan) were also found. Further, there were significantly lower detection rates of the TT genotype and T allele and higher detection rates of the CC genotype and C allele in the JPT, CEU, and YRI populations when compared with our data.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0110061-t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110061.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Comparison of genotype and allele frequencies in the healthy control subjects of our study and that from the HapMap project.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0110061-t004-4" xlink:href="pone.0110061.t004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polymorphisms</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Samples, N</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Genotype frequency, n(%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Alleles frequency, n(%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P values</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P values</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;589C/T</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present study</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115(67.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51(30.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(2.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">281(82.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59(17.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCB<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50(58.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34(39.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(2.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.307</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134(77.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38(22.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.196</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JPT<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90(52.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66(38.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(8.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">246(72.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94(27.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CEU<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(1.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54(23.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168(74.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62(13.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">390(86.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YRI<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140(61.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76(33.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(4.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.356</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">356(78.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96(21.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.172</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chinese<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">&#x02020;</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92(60.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50(33.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9(6.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.185</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">234(77.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68(22.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;33C/T</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present study</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113(66.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52(30.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5(2.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">278(81.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62(18.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCB<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50(58.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34(39.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(2.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.357</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134(77.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38(22.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.298</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JPT<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">172</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90(52.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68(39.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(8.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248(72.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96(27.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CEU<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(1.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54(23.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168(74.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62(13.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">390(86.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YRI<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44(19.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126(55.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56(24.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214(47.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">238(52.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCH<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">&#x02020;</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">159</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104(65.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51(32.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(2.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.939</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">259(81.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59(18.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.916</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt108"><label/><p>*Data from HapMap Project;</p></fn><fn id="nt109"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Data from previous reports; HCB, Han Chinese in Beijing, China; JPT, Japanese in Tokyo, Japan; CEU, Utah residents with northern and western European ancestry; YRI, Yoruba in Ibadan, Nigeria; HCH, Han Chinese in Hunan province, China.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Estimated haplotype frequencies and the risk of HBV-related diseases</title><p>Haplotype analyses were performed for all patient groups and healthy controls using the SHEsis software, and the four possible haplotype frequencies of the two SNPs are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0110061-t005">Table 5</xref>. According to the results, the T<sup>&#x02212;589</sup> T<sup>&#x02212;33</sup> haplotype is the most common haplotype and represents &#x0003e;50% in all groups, whereas the C<sup>&#x02212;589</sup> C<sup>&#x02212;33</sup> haplotype accounts for 14.9% to 23.3% among the four groups and represents the second highest haplotype. After haplotype analyses, however, no significant differences in these haplotype frequencies were found in any group. Finally, C<sup>&#x02212;589</sup> T<sup>&#x02212;33</sup> and T<sup>&#x02212;589</sup> C<sup>&#x02212;33</sup> are rare haplotypes that account for less than 2% in the control subjects and therefore further analyses were not conducted for these.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0110061-t005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110061.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Frequencies of the haplotypes formed by &#x02212;589C/T and &#x02212;33C/T polymorphisms in HBV-related patients and healthy controls.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0110061-t005-5" xlink:href="pone.0110061.t005"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haplotype</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthycontrol(%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHBPatients(%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR(95%CI)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LCPatients(%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR(95%CI)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCCPatients(%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR(95%CI)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47(0.98&#x02013;2.20)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96(0.55&#x02013;1.66)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.878</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85(0.56&#x02013;1.30)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.459</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68(0.45&#x02013;1.02)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52(0.33&#x02013;0.84)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83(0.57&#x02013;1.23)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.356</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>China, a region with 94 million HBsAg carriers, accounts for 50% of the total HCC cases worldwide <xref rid="pone.0110061-Yin2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0110061-Siegel1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. The predominant mode of HBV transmission in this hyperendemic region is vertical transmission from infected mothers during or shortly after birth <xref rid="pone.0110061-Yu1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. However, only 5% to 10% of perinatally-infected infants become persistent carriers as adults, despite the approximately 90% risk; further, from these persistent infectors, 10% to 30% will progress to LC and HCC <xref rid="pone.0110061-Zeng1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Such highly variable disease outcomes cannot be fully explained by differences in immunological, viral, or environmental factors. Thus, differences in host genetic factors may play essential roles in these processes.</p><p>IL-4, a typical pleiotropic Th2 cytokine <xref rid="pone.0110061-Durie1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, is best known for defining the Th2 phenotype of lymphocytes, as well as being involved in regulating cell proliferation, apoptosis, and expression of numerous genes in lymphocytes, macrophages, and fibroblasts, among others <xref rid="pone.0110061-Nelms1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0110061-Iseki1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. Functional variations in this gene may contribute to viral clearance as well as HBV-associated HCC in high-risk Chinese patients. However, in the present study, we did not observe any association of <italic>IL-4</italic> genotypes, alleles, and haplotypes with the overall CHB, LC, and HCC patients. Nevertheless, in subgroup analysis, CC genotypes of the <italic>IL-4</italic> &#x02212;589C/T and &#x02212;33C/T polymorphisms were observed to be significantly associated with CHB in males as compared with the TT genotypes and TT+CT genotypes. In females, a similar trend towards an increased risk effect of CC genotypes in CHB was also observed, but the difference was not significant. These results indicate that <italic>IL-4</italic> gene polymorphisms may be a risk factor for CHB in the Chinese male population only.</p><p>Data from previous epidemiological studies was consistent with our results. In a meta-analysis conducted by Zheng et al. <xref rid="pone.0110061-Zheng1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> exploring the <italic>IL-4</italic> 590C/T polymorphism and its susceptibility to liver disease (including HBV infection, HCV infection, liver cirrhosis, etc.), significant associations between the <italic>IL-4</italic> 590T polymorphism and increased risk of liver diseases was found in Caucasian populations, but not in Asian populations. Another meta-analysis investigating the association of <italic>IL-4</italic> polymorphisms with response to HBV vaccine and susceptibility to HBV infection, also found no evidence indicating a correlation between <italic>IL-4</italic> polymorphisms (rs2243250 C&#x0003e;T) and susceptibility to HBV infection <xref rid="pone.0110061-Cui1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. It is noted that all &#x0201c;Asian population&#x0201d; studies included in the two meta-analyses mentioned above were conducted in China <xref rid="pone.0110061-Chen2" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0110061-Gao2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>.</p><p>It is noteworthy that, in the present study, the significant association between CHB in males was found in the CC genotypes of &#x02212;589C/T and &#x02212;33C/T polymorphisms, as opposed to the T allele in the Caucasian populations studied in the meta-analysis of Zheng et al. <xref rid="pone.0110061-Zheng1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. The fact that the same polymorphism site has distinct genotype frequencies which play different roles in the same disease may be principally explained by differences in the <italic>IL-4</italic> genetic background among ethnicities; results from the comparison of genotype and allele frequencies in the healthy control subjects in the present study and those from the HapMap project provide evidence to this effect. In the current study, the <italic>IL-4</italic> &#x02212;590T and &#x02212;33T allele frequencies among healthy controls were 82.6% and 81.8%, respectively, which were significantly higher than those observed in healthy Caucasians (both were 13.7%), while the C allele frequencies accounted for 17.4% in &#x02212;590C/T mutations and 18.2% in &#x02212;33C/T mutations, which were significantly lower than in Caucasians (both were 86.3%). Thus, the T allele may be the major allele in &#x02212;589C/T and &#x02212;33C/T SNPs in the Chinese population, and the C allele is the variant responsible for various diseases, while the opposite is true for Caucasians.</p><p>With respect to HCC, only two studies were found regarding the <italic>IL-4</italic> &#x02212;590 C/T polymorphism and HCC risk in a high-risk Chinese population <xref rid="pone.0110061-Nieters1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref> and in low-risk non-Asians in the USA <xref rid="pone.0110061-Ognjanovic1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, both conducted by Ognjanovic et al. <xref rid="pone.0110061-Ognjanovic1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0110061-Nieters1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. Contrary to our results, the authors noted a substantial decrease in HCC risk associated with the <italic>IL-4</italic> &#x02212;590 CC genotype in Guangxi, China, and a non-significant result in Los Angeles non-Asians. However, in the present study, no association was found for either <italic>IL-4</italic> &#x02212;590C/T or &#x02212;33C/T polymorphisms and HCC risk in the Chinese population. Drinking status may be a possible factor in the disparate associations between our study and theirs. According to their results <xref rid="pone.0110061-Nieters1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, the <italic>IL-4</italic> &#x02212;590 CC genotype was not associated with a lower risk of HCC when initially adjusted for age, gender, and ethnicity (CC vs. CT/TT, OR: 0.46, 95% CI: 0.16&#x02013;1.31); however, after further adjustment for HBsAg seropositivity and the number of alcoholic drinks per day (0, &#x0003c;3, or &#x0003e;3), the CC genotype was found to be negatively associated with HCC risk (CC vs. CT/TT, OR: 0.05, 95% CI: 0.01&#x02013;0.40); in contrast, individuals included in our study were all HBsAg seropositive. In addition, the difference in study design and sample size may also be possible confounders.</p><p>For <italic>IL-4</italic> polymorphism haplotypes, previous experimental data has demonstrated some to be associated with respiratory syncytial virus <xref rid="pone.0110061-Puthothu1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, multiple sclerosis <xref rid="pone.0110061-Suppiah1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, oral cancer <xref rid="pone.0110061-Tsai1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, and systemic lupus erythematosus <xref rid="pone.0110061-Wu1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, suggesting that certain important polymorphisms could affect the regulation of this cytokine. In addition, the T allele of the <italic>IL-4</italic> &#x02212;590C/T polymorphism has been reported to be in linkage disequilibrium with &#x02212;33T <xref rid="pone.0110061-Takabayashi1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, and was associated with an increased expression of IL-4 <xref rid="pone.0110061-Wierenga1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. However, we did not find an association between any of the estimated haplotype frequencies and the risk of HBV-related diseases, indicating that the <italic>IL-4</italic> gene haplotypes may not play any facilitative role in the development of HCC.</p><p>In conclusion, we could not detect an effect of genetic variants between <italic>IL-4</italic> and HBV-related HCC in a Chinese population. Interestingly, in subgroup analysis, the CC genotype of <italic>IL-4</italic> &#x02212;589C/T and &#x02212;33C/T polymorphisms were observed to be significantly correlated with the risk of CHB in the Chinese male population. However, considering the relatively small sample size of this study, more studies with a larger sample size are warranted in an attempt to confirm the observed association.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0110061.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>The sequences of forward and backward primers and restriction enzymes for genotyping IL-4 polymorphisms.</bold>
</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0110061.s001.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0110061.s002"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Genotype and allele frequencies of &#x02212;589C/T and &#x02212;33C/T polymorphisms between HBV-related patients and healthy controls in females.</bold>
</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0110061.s002.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0110061-Liaw1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Liaw</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Hepatitis B virus infection</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>373</volume>: <fpage>582</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>592</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19217993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Lavanchy1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lavanchy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Worldwide epidemiology of HBV infection, disease burden, and vaccine prevention</article-title>. <source>J Clin Virol</source>
<volume>34</volume>
<issue>Suppl 1</issue>
<fpage>S1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Perz1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Perz</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Farrington</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hutin</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The contributions of hepatitis B virus and hepatitis C virus infections to cirrhosis and primary liver cancer worldwide</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source>
<volume>45</volume>: <fpage>529</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>538</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16879891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Yin1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Association between the various mutations in viral core promoter region to different stages of hepatitis B, ranging of asymptomatic carrier state to hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source>
<volume>106</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20959817</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Chisari1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chisari</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Hepatitis B virus immunopathogenesis</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Immunol</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7612225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Chen1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Viral and host inflammation-related factors that can predict the prognosis of hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer</source>
<volume>48</volume>: <fpage>1977</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1987</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22325840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Chemin1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chemin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zoulim</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Hepatitis B virus induced hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett</source>
<volume>286</volume>: <fpage>52</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19147276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Han1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Factors predicting occurrence and prognosis of hepatitis-B-virus-related hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>World J Gastroenterol</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>4258</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4270</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22090781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Durie1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Durie</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Foy</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Masters</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laman</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Noelle</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The role of CD40 in the regulation of humoral and cell-mediated immunity</article-title>. <source>Immunol Today</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>406</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>411</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7524518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Landi1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Landi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bottari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gemignani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gioia-Patricola</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guino</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Interleukin-4 and interleukin-4 receptor polymorphisms and colorectal cancer risk</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer</source>
<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>762</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>768</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17258448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Luzina1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Luzina</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keegan</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rook</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shea-Donohue</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Regulation of inflammation by interleukin-4: a review of &#x0201c;alternatives&#x0201d;</article-title>. <source>J Leukoc Biol</source>
<volume>92</volume>: <fpage>753</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>764</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22782966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Gordon1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Alternative activation of macrophages</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Immunol</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12511873</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Stein1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keshav</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Interleukin 4 potently enhances murine macrophage mannose receptor activity: a marker of alternative immunologic macrophage activation</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>176</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>292</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1613462</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Capece1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Capece</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fischietti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verzella</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaggiano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cicciarelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The inflammatory microenvironment in hepatocellular carcinoma: a pivotal role for tumor-associated macrophages</article-title>. <source>Biomed Res Int</source>
<volume>2013</volume>: <fpage>187204</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23533994</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Jiang1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rothman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>IL-4/IL-13 signaling beyond JAK/STAT</article-title>. <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source>
<volume>105</volume>: <fpage>1063</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1070</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10856136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Marsh1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neely</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Breazeale</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freidhoff</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Linkage analysis of IL4 and other chromosome 5q31.1 markers and total serum immunoglobulin E concentrations</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>264</volume>: <fpage>1152</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1156</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8178175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Naslednikova1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Naslednikova</surname><given-names>IO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Konenkov</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ryazantseva</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Novitskii</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tkachenko</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Role of genetically determined production of immunoregulatory cytokines in immunopathogenesis of chronic viral hepatitides</article-title>. <source>Bull Exp Biol Med</source>
<volume>143</volume>: <fpage>706</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>712</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18239807</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Aithal1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Aithal</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramsay</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sonchit</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leathart</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Hepatic adducts, circulating antibodies, and cytokine polymorphisms in patients with diclofenac hepatotoxicity</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>
<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1430</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1440</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15122773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Zhu1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>QR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Relationship between cytokines gene polymorphism and susceptibility to hepatitis B virus intrauterine infection</article-title>. <source>Chin Med J (Engl)</source>
<volume>118</volume>: <fpage>1604</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1609</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16232344</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Zheng1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>IL-4 -590C/T polymorphism and susceptibility to liver disease: a meta-analysis and meta-regression</article-title>. <source>DNA Cell Biol</source>
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>450</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23768103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Cui1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Association of polymorphisms in the interleukin-4 gene with response to hepatitis B vaccine and susceptibility to hepatitis B virus infection: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>
<volume>525</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23651591</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Ognjanovic1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ognjanovic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chaptman</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Genetic polymorphisms in the cytokine genes and risk of hepatocellular carcinoma in low-risk non-Asians of USA</article-title>. <source>Carcinogenesis</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>758</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>762</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19126646</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Lok1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lok</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Chronic hepatitis B. Hepatology</article-title>. <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>507</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>539</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Peng1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Association of IL27 gene polymorphisms and HBV-related hepatocellular carcinoma risk in a Chinese population</article-title>. <source>Infect Genet Evol</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23395794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Jemal1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <collab>Center MM, Ferlay J, Ward E, et al</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Global cancer statistics</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source>
<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21296855</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Shi1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>SHEsis, a powerful software platform for analyses of linkage disequilibrium, haplotype construction, and genetic association at polymorphism loci</article-title>. <source>Cell Res</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15740637</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Li1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) A partition-ligation-combination-subdivision EM algorithm for haplotype inference with multiallelic markers: update of the SHEsis (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://analysis.bio-x.cn">http://analysis.bio-x.cn</ext-link>). <article-title>Cell Res</article-title>. <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>519</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>523</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Stephens1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A new statistical method for haplotype reconstruction from population data</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
<volume>68</volume>: <fpage>978</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>989</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11254454</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-TangZY1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tang ZY</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Association between IL-4 C+33T and serum levels of IL-4 and atherothrombotic cerebral infarction in Chinese Han</article-title>. <source>Stroke and nevous diseases</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Yin2"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Distribution and hepatocellular carcinoma-related viral properties of hepatitis B virus genotypes in Mainland China: a community-based study</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>777</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>786</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20160279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Siegel1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Naishadham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Cancer statistics, 2012</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source>
<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22237781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Yu1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Environmental factors and risk for hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>
<volume>127</volume>: <fpage>S72</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15508106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Zeng1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Human genes involved in hepatitis B virus infection</article-title>. <source>World J Gastroenterol</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>7696</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7706</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24976707</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Nelms1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nelms</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keegan</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zamorano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The IL-4 receptor: signaling mechanisms and biologic functions</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Immunol</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>701</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>738</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10358772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-KellyWelch1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kelly-Welch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keegan</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Interleukin-13 (IL-13) pathway</article-title>. <source>Sci STKE</source>
<volume>2005</volume>: <fpage>cm8</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16030286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Chomarat1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chomarat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Banchereau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Interleukin-4 and interleukin-13: their similarities and discrepancies</article-title>. <source>Int Rev Immunol</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9914942</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-KellyWelch2"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kelly-Welch</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boothby</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keegan</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Interleukin-4 and interleukin-13 signaling connections maps</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>300</volume>: <fpage>1527</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1528</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12791978</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-LaPorte1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>LaPorte</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Juo</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vaclavikova</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colf</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Molecular and structural basis of cytokine receptor pleiotropy in the interleukin-4/13 system</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>132</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>272</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18243101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Iseki1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Iseki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Omori-Miyake</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Thymic stromal lymphopoietin (TSLP)-induced polyclonal B-cell activation and autoimmunity are mediated by CD4+ T cells and IL-4</article-title>. <source>Int Immunol</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>195</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22281511</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Chen2"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Impact of serum levels and gene polymorphism of cytokines on chronic hepatitis C infection</article-title>. <source>Transl Res</source>
<volume>150</volume>: <fpage>116</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>121</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17656331</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Gao1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>QJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Polymorphisms of some cytokines and chronic hepatitis B and C virus infection</article-title>. <source>World J Gastroenterol</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>5610</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5619</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19938203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Liu1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Relationship between genetic polymorphisms of interleukin-4 (IL-4), interleukin-4 receptor a chain with susceptibility to HBVinduced liver cirrhosis</article-title>. <source>Chin J Integr Tradit West Med Liver Dis</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>213</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Zhu2"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>QR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Relationship between cytokines gene polymorphism and susceptibility to hepatitis B virus intrauterine infection</article-title>. <source>Chin Med J</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1604</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1069</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Wang1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The association of IL-2 and IL-4 polymorphisms and hepatitis B in population of north China</article-title>. <source>Chin J Curr Adv Gen Surg</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>176</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Gao2"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>QJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>DX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Association of IL-4-589 polymorphisms with chronic hepatitis B and hepatitis C virus infection</article-title>. <source>Med Pharm J Chin People&#x02019;s Liberation Army</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>8</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Nieters1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nieters</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stoehlmacher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Effect of cytokine genotypes on the hepatitis B virus-hepatocellular carcinoma association</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source>
<volume>103</volume>: <fpage>740</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>748</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15643599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Puthothu1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Puthothu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heinzmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Association between severe respiratory syncytial virus infection and IL13/IL4 haplotypes</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source>
<volume>193</volume>: <fpage>438</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>441</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16388492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Suppiah1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Suppiah</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alloza</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heggarty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Polymorphisms in the interleukin-4 and IL-4 receptor genes and multiple sclerosis: a study in Spanish-Basque, Northern Irish and Belgian populations</article-title>. <source>Int J Immunogenet</source>
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>383</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>388</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16313303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Tsai1"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hang</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Interleukin-4 gene, but not the interleukin-1 beta gene polymorphism, is associated with oral cancer</article-title>. <source>J Clin Lab Anal</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15900573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Wu1"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Polymorphisms of the interleukin-4 gene in chinese patients with systemic lupus erythematosus in Taiwan</article-title>. <source>Lupus</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12587822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Takabayashi1"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Takabayashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kusuhara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nishima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Novel polymorphism in the 5&#x02032;-untranslated region of the interleukin-4 gene</article-title>. <source>J Hum Genet</source>
<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>352</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>353</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10496083</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0110061-Wierenga1"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wierenga</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Messer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Regulation of interleukin 4 gene transcription: alterations in atopic disease?</article-title>
<source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
<volume>162</volume>: <fpage>S81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10988157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>