<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Virol J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Virol. J</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Virology Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1743-422X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4351832</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">242</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12985-015-0242-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Association of human papillomavirus 16 E6 variants with cervical carcinoma and precursor lesions in women from Southern Mexico </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ortiz-Ortiz</surname><given-names>Julio</given-names></name><address><email>julioortiz771210@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alarcón-Romero</surname><given-names>Luz del Carmen</given-names></name><address><email>luzdelcarmen14@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiménez-López</surname><given-names>Marco Antonio</given-names></name><address><email>marcoajl16@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garzón-Barrientos</surname><given-names>Víctor Hugo</given-names></name><address><email>victhorgarzon@hotmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Calleja-Macías</surname><given-names>Itzel</given-names></name><address><email>itzel14@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barrera-Saldaña</surname><given-names>Hugo Alberto</given-names></name><address><email>habarrera@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leyva-Vázquez</surname><given-names>Marco Antonio</given-names></name><address><email>leyvamarco13@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Illades-Aguiar</surname><given-names>Berenice</given-names></name><address><email>b.illadesaguiar@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Laboratorio de Biomedicina Molecular, Unidad Académica de Ciencias Químico Biológicas, Universidad Autónoma de Guerrero, Chilpancingo, Guerrero México </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Laboratorio de Citopatología, Unidad Académica de Ciencias Químico Biológicas, Universidad Autónoma de Guerrero, Chilpancingo, Guerrero México </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Instituto Estatal de Cancerología “Dr. Arturo Beltrán Ortega”, Acapulco, Guerrero México </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Molecular Biology and Biochemistry, School of Biological Sciences, University of California Irvine, Irvine, CA USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label/>Departamento de Bioquímica y Medicina Molecular, Facultad de Medicina, Universidad Autónoma de Nuevo León, Monterrey, Nuevo León México </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>22</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>29</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Ortiz-Ortiz et al.; licensee BioMed Central. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>HPV 16 is the cause of cervical carcinoma, but only a small fraction of women with HPV infection progress to this pathology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Besides persistent infection and HPV integration, several studies have suggested that HPV intratype variants may contribute to the development of cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The purpose of this study was to investigate the nucleotide variability and phylogenetically classify HPV 16 E6 variants circulating over a period of 16 years in women from Southern Mexico, and to analyze its association with precursor lesions and cervical carcinoma. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>This study was conducted in 330 cervical DNA samples with HPV 16 from women who were residents of the State of Guerrero, located in Southern Mexico. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>According of cytological and/or histological diagnosis, samples were divided into the following four groups: no intraepithelial lesion (n = 97), low-grade squamous intraepithelial lesion (n = 123), high-grade squamous intraepithelial lesion (n = 19) and cervical carcinoma (n = 91). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>HPV 16 E6 gene was amplified, sequenced and aligned with reference sequence (HPV 16R) and a phylogenetic tree was constructed to identify and classify HPV 16 variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Chi squared was used and data analysis and statistics were done with SPSS Statistics and STATA softwares. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Twenty seven HPV 16 E6 variants were detected in women from Southern Mexico, 82.12% belonged to the EUR, 17.58% to AA1 and 0.3% to Afr2a sublineages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The most common was E-G350 (40%), followed by E-prototype (13.03%), E-C188/G350 (11.82%), AA-a (10.61%), AA-c (6.07%) and E-A176/G350 (5.15%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Eight new E6 variants were found and 2 of them lead to amino acid change: E-C183/G350 (I27T) and E-C306/G350 (K68T). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The HPV 16 variant that showed the greatest risk of leading to the development of CC was AA-a (OR = 69.01, CI = 7.57-628.96), followed by E-A176/G350 (OR = 39.82, CI = 4.11-386.04), AA-c (OR = 21.16, CI 2.59-172.56), E-G350 (OR = 13.25, CI = 2.02-87.12) and E-C188/G350 (OR = 10.48, CI = 1.39-78.92). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The variants more frequently found in women with cervical carcinoma are E-G350, AA-a, AA-c, E-C188/G350 and E-A176/G350. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>All of them are associated with the development of cervical carcinoma, however, AA-a showed the highest association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>This study reinforces the proposal that HPV 16 AA-a is an oncogenic risk for cervical carcinoma progression in Mexico. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12985-015-0242-3) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>HPV 16 variants</kwd><kwd>Cervical cancer</kwd><kwd>Precursor lesions</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Infection by high risk human papillomavirus (HR-HPV) is necessary for the development of cervical carcinoma (CC) [1] and HPV 16 is the cause of more than half of CC worldwide [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Only a small fraction of women with HPV infection may progress to cervical carcinoma; however, the factors that favor this progression are still poorly understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Besides persistent infection and HPV integration [3,4], several studies have suggested that HPV intratype variants may contribute to cancer development [4-7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Like other HR-HPV, HPV 16 has well preserved distinctive intratypic variants by geographical origin [8], their global distribution and risk of cervical carcinoma appears to be dependent on the population [9,10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Its phylogeny reflects evolutionary divergence associated with human migration patterns, suggesting that they may have co-diversified as human populations expanded worldwide [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>HPV 16 variants have been classified into 4 major lineages and 9 sublineages based on common LCR and E6 single polymorphisms: (1) European-Asian (EAS), including European (EUR) and Asian (As) sublineages; (2) African 1 (AFR1), including Afr1a and Afr1b sublineages; (3) African 2 (AFR2), including Afr2a and Afr2b sublineages; and (4) Asian American/North American (AA/NA), including Asian American 1 (AA1), Asian American 2 (AA2) and North American (NA) sublineages [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Several reports have shown the presence of common polymorphisms that generate amino acid changes in the E6 oncoprotein, one of them is T350G, and is present in the four lineages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>T350G causes a leucine to valine change (L83V), that leads to the split of the EUR sublineage into three classes, 350 T (prototype sequence), 350C and 350G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Other polymorphisms including A131G, G132C, C143G, G145T, G176A, T178G and C335T generate the amino acid changes R10G/I, Q14H/D, D25E/N, I27R and H78Y, respectively [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>It has been suggested that these polymorphisms and the subsequent amino acid changes in E6 HPV 16 variants may influence the persistence of HPV infection and its progression to cervical carcinoma [4,14-18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Epidemiologic data shows that regions with high incidence of cervical carcinoma like Latin America, Africa and Asia, also have a high prevalence of sublineages AA and Af [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Studies in Mexico have reported that persistent infection and risk of progression to cervical carcinoma is higher when HPV infection is caused by AA sub-lineages compared with EUR sublineages [5,19-21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Social disparities like access to social security health care services, ethnic groups, residence and socioeconomic level are factors associated with cervical carcinoma development [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The State of Guerrero, located in Southern Mexico, is the second poorest state in Mexico and a majority of inhabitants have a very low socioeconomic level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In this region, cervical carcinoma is the most common type of cancer in women and has the fourth highest mortality rate in the country with 12.5 deaths per 100,000 women, compared to the national mortality rate of 9.1 per 100,000 in 2008 [23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>We have previously shown that HPV 16 was the most commonly identified HPV genotype in cervical carcinoma and high grade squamous intraepithelial lesions in women from the State of Guerrero. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>We studied a sample of HPV 16 positive women and found E and AA variants [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>It has been proposed that variants AA of HPV 16 are more oncogenic than E variants [5,25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Knowing the regional variants of HPV 16 is of great value for evolutionary, phylogenetic, epidemiological and biological analysis [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>To further analyze the regional variants of HPV 16, the aim of this study was to investigate the nucleotide variability and phylogenetically classify HPV 16 E6 variants circulating over a period of 16 years in the Southern Mexican population, and to analyze its association with the whole spectrum of disease from no intraepithelial lesion in cervical epithelium to cervical carcinoma. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The most dominant HPV variants were detected in low and high-grade squamous intraepithelial lesion, cervical carcinoma and no intraepithelial lesion, and 8 novel HPV 16 variants were found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>An association between E-G350, E-A176/G350, E-C188/G350, AA-a and AA-c variants and the risk of developing cervical carcinoma was shown in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>HPV 16 E6 variants and phylogenetic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The variant analysis for the E6 gene was carried out in 330 HPV16 samples from all study groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Using the HPV 16 R (Los Alamos National Laboratory, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NC_001526.2">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NC_001526.2</ext-link>) as a reference sequence, a total of 27 variants were detected, 8 of them were new. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Sequence analysis showed substitution in 29 nucleotides located between positions 104 and 559 in the E6 sequence with a predicted amino acid change (Table 1).Table 1Phylogenetic classification, nucleotide sequence variations and frequency of HPV-16 E6 variants identified in women from Southern Mexico  Variants  HPV 16 E6 nucleotide position  Predicted amino acid change E6 protein (151 aa form)  Frequency  109  110  131  132  143  145  176  182  183  185  188  189  256  257  271  286  289  306  310  335  350  403  424  442  532  535  N=330  % HPV 16RTCAGCGGATTGACATTAACCTAAAAALineage EAS/Sublineage EURClass E-T350 51  15.45% E-Prototype--------------------------No change4313.03%E-G131--G-----------------------R10G82.42%Class E-G350 220  66.67% E-G350--------------------G-----L83V13240.00%E-C109/G350c-------------------G-----L83V61.82%E-G110/G350-G------------------G-----Q3E/L83V20.61%E-G131/G350--G-----------------G-----R10G/L83V20.61%E-G131/C188/G350--G-------C---------G-----R10G/E29Q/L83V20.61%E-A176/G350------A-------------G-----D25N/L83V175.15%**E-A176/G424/G350------A-------------G-g---D25N/L83V10.30%E-T182/G350-------T------------G-----I27L/L83V41.21%E-C182/G350-------C------------G-----I27L/L83V20.61%**E-C183/G350-------- C -----------G-----I27T/L83V30.91%E-G185/G350---------G----------G-----L28V/L83V20.61%E-A188/G350----------A---------G-----E29K/L83V10.30%E-C188/G350----------C---------G-----E29Q/L83V3911.82%**E-C188/G310/G350----------C-------G-G-----E29Q/F69L/L83V20.61%**E-G189/T256/G350-----------Gt-------G-----E29G/L83V10.30%E-G257/G350-------------G------G-----I52L/L83V10.30%**E-C306/G350----------------- C --G-----K68T/L83V10.30%E-C442/G350--------------------G--C--L83V/E113D10.30%**G535/G350--------------------G---- g L83V10.30%Lineage AA/NA/Sublineage AA1Class AA-a 36  10.91% AA-a-----T---------ag--TG---g-Q14H/H78Y/L83V3510.61%**AA-a/C188-----T----C----ag--TG---g-Q14H/E29Q/H78Y/L83V10.30%Class AA-c 22  6.67% AA-c-----T--G------ag--TG---g-Q14H/I27R/H78Y/L83V206.07%**AA-c/G185-----T--GG-----aa--TG---g-Q14H/I27R/L28V/H78Y/L83V10.30%AA-c/C271-----T--G-----cag--TG---g-Q14H/I27R/H78Y/L83V10.30%Lineage AFR2/Sublineage Afr2aClass Af2-a 1  0.30% Af2-a/C109/G403c--TGT---------ag--T-g----R10I/Q14D/H78Y10.30%HPV 16 R: reference sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Predicted amino acid change: the amino acid numeration was done using the 151 amino acid E6 oncoprotein form as reference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Capital letters indicate polymorphisms that produce amino acid change. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Lower-case letters indicate silent mutations. – Indicate no polymorphism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Italic letters indicate new polymorphisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Italic capital letters indicate amino acid change. **Indicate new variants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic analysis showed that the E6 variants found belong to EUR, AA1 and Afr2a sublineages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Six of the 8 novel variants were related to variants of the EUR sublineages, and 2 to variants of the AA1 sublineage (Figure 1).Figure 1 Phylogenetic tree based in E6 variations of HPV 16. To classify the newly identified variants, their phylogenetic relationship with previously reported variants were determined, by constructing a phylogenetic tree based on E6 sequences found in Southern Mexico. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The new variants are underlined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The tree is drawn to scale with branch lengths measured in the number of substitutions per site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The analysis involved 27 nucleotide sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>All positions containing gaps and missing data were eliminated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>There were a total of 456 positions in the final dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Analyses were conducted in MEGA5.2 [43]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic classification of the E6 variants showed that the majority (82.12%) belonged to the EUR sublineage, followed by AA1 (17.58%) and Afr2a (0.3%) sublineages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>From sublineage EUR, 15.45% was class E-T350 which includes E-Prototype (13.03%), and 66.67% was class E-G350 finding 19 subclasses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>From sublineage AA1, AA-a class was the most frequent (10.91%) followed by AA-c class (6.67%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>From the 27 variants found in this study, the most common E6 variant was E-G350 (40%), followed by E-prototype (13.03%), E-C188/G350 (11.82%), AA-a (10.61%), AA-c (6.07%) and E-A176/G350 (5.15%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The 8 novel variants are subclasses, 6 are subclasses of class G-350, one is subclass of class AA-a and the last one is subclass of class AA-c (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>E-C183/G350, E-C306/G350 and E-G535/G350 show polymorphisms that so far have not been reported, E-C183/G350 leads to the amino acid change I27T, E-C306/G350 changes K68T and E-G535/G350 does not lead to any amino acid change (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>HPV 16 E6 variants in cervical carcinoma and precursor lesions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>A total of 330 samples with HPV16 were analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The histology of the 91 cervical carcinoma identified 76 (83.5%) as squamous cell carcinoma (SCC), 13 (14.3%) as adenocarcinoma (ADC) and 2 (2.2%) as other epithelial tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The majority of cases of cervical carcinomas were found in the FIGO stage IIB (34%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Additionally, 19 samples were HSIL, 123 LSIL and 97 with non-IL (11 with inflammation and 86 with normal Pap smears). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>HPV 16 AA variants were more common in ADC (46.15%) than in SCC (30.27%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>AA-a variants increased their frequency according to the degree of evolution of cervical lesion: 38.46% in ADC, 15.79% in SCC, 15.79% in HSIL, 8.94% in LSIL and 3.09% in non-IL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>HPV 16 E variants were the most common in SCC (69.75%), HSIL (78.94%), LSIL (87.79%) and non-IL (89.69%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>HPV 16 E-G350 class was the most frequent in all groups, E-Prototype, on the other hand, was not detected in ADC and other epithelial tumors, and only 2.63% of SCC, 5.26% of HSIL, 18.7% of LSIL and 17.53% of non-IL (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The Af variants were not found in any cervical carcinoma.Table 2 Distribution of HPV 16 E6 variants for diagnostic category  Variant  Non-IL N=97  LSIL N=123  HSIL N=19  SCC N=76  ADC N=13  Other Epithelial Tumor N=2  Cervical carcinoma N=91  Total N=330 E variants 87 (89.69%)  108 (87.79%)  15 (78.94%)  53 (69.75%)  7 (53.84%)  1 (50.0%)  61 (67.05%)  271 (82.12%) Class E-T350 23 (23.72%)  23 (18.7%)  1 (5.26%)  4 (5.26%)  -  -  4 (4.4%)  51 (15.45%) E-Prototype17 (17.53%)23 (18.7%)1 (5.26%)2 (2.63%)--2 (2.2%)43 (13.03%)E-G1316 (6.19%)--2 (2.63%)--2 (2.2%)8 (2.42%)Class E-G350 64 (65.97%)  85 (69.09%)  14 (73.68%)  49 (64.49%)  7 (53.84%)  1 (50.0%)  57 (62.65%)  220 (66.67%) E-G35039 (40.21%)56 (45.53%)6 (31.58%)28 (36. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>84%)3 (23.08%)-31 (34.07%)132 (40.00%)E-C109/G350-3 (2.44%)1 (5.26%)2 (2.63%)--2 (2.2%)6 (1.82%)E-G110/G3501 (1.03%)1 (0.81%)-----2 (0.61%)E-G131/G3501 (1.03%)--1 (1.32%)--1 (1.1%)2 (0.61%)E-G131/C188/G3501 (1.03%)1 (0.81%)-----2 (0.61%)E-A176/G3503 (3.09%)5 (4.07%)1 (5.26%)5 (6.58%)2 (15.38%)1 (50.0%)8 (8.79%)17 (5.15%)**E-A176/G424/G350---1 (1.32%)--1 (1.1%)1 (0.30%)E-T182/G350-1 (0.81%)1 (5.26%)2 (2.63%)--2 (2.2%)4 (1.21%)E-C182/G3501 (1.03%)1 (0.81%)-----2 (0.61%)**E-C183/G3503 (3.09%)------3 (0.91%)E-G185/G3501 (1.03%)--1 (1.32%)--1 (1.1%)2 (0.61%)E-A188/G350---1 (1.32%)--1 (1.1%)1 (0.30%)E-C188/G35011 (11.34%)13 (10.57%)5 (26.32%)8 (10.53%)2 (15.38%)-10 (10.99%)39 (11.82%)**E-C188/G310/G3501 (1.03%)1 (0.81%)-----2 (0.61%)**E-G189/T256/G350-1 (0.81%)-----1 (0.30%)E-G257/G350-1 (0.81%)-----1 (0.30%)**E-C306/G3501 (1.03%)------1 (0.30%)E-C442/G3501 (1.03%)------1 (0.30%)**G535/G350-1 (0.81%)-----1 (0.30%)AA variants 10 (10.31%)  14 (11.38%)  4 (21.05%)  23 (30.27%)  6 (46.15%)  1 (50.0%)  30 (32.97%)  58 (17.58%) Class AA-a 4 (4.12%)  11 (8.94%)  3 (15.79%)  12 (15.79%)  5 (38.46%)  1 (50.0%)  18 (19.78%)  36 (10.91%) AA-a3 (3.09%)11 (8.94%)3 (15.79%)12 (15.79%)5 (38.46 %)1 (50.0%)18 (19.78%)35 (10.61%)**AA-a/C1881 (1.03%)------1 (0.30%)Class AA-c 6 (6.19%)  3 (2.44%)  1 (5.26%)  11 (14.48%)  1 (7.69%)  -  12 (13.19%)  22 (6.67%) AA-c6 (6.19%)3 (2.44%)1 (5.26%)9 (11.84%)1 (7.69%)-10 (10.99%)20 (6.07%)**AA-c/G185---1 (1.32%)--1 (1.1%)1 (0.30%)AA-c/C271---1 (1.32%)--1 (1.1%)1 (0.30%)Af variants -  1 (0.81%)  -  -  -  -  -  1 (0.30%) Class Af2-a -  1 (0.81%)  -  -  -  - - 1 (0.30%) Af2-a/C109/G403-1 (0.81%)-----1 (0.30%)-,Indicate that the variant was not found. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Associations between the five most frequent HPV 16 E6 variants and LSIL, HSIL and cervical carcinoma were assessed (Table 3), using the HPV 16 E-Prototype as a reference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The 5 variants analyzed showed significant association with CC, but only AA-a variant showed significant association with HSIL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The HPV 16 variant that showed the most risk of developing CC was AA-a (OR = 69.01, CI = 7.57-628.96), followed by E-A176/G350 (OR = 39.82, CI = 4.11-386.04), AA-c (OR = 21.16, CI 2.59-172.56), E-G350 (OR = 13.25, CI = 2.02-87.12) and E-C188/G350 (OR = 10.48, CI = 1.39-78.92).Table 3 The most common HPV 16 E6 variants in women from Southern Mexico and risk of cervical carcinoma  Variants  Non-IL N (%)  LSIL N (%)  OR (CI 95%) P  HSIL N (%)  OR (CI 95%) P  SCC N (%)  OR (CI 95%) p  ADC N (%)  OR (CI 95%) P  Other epithelial tumor N (%)  Cervical carcinoma N (%)  OR (CI 95%) P Class E-T350a  23 (23.71%)  23 (18.7%)  -  1 (5.26%)  -  4 (5.26%)  -  0 (0%) b  -  0 (0.0%)  4 (4.40%)  - E-Prototype17 (17.53%)23 (18.7%)1*1 (5.26%)1*2 (2.63%)1*0 (0%)b 1*-2 (2.2%)1*Class E-G350 64 (65.98%)  85 (69.11%)  0.97  3.73  12.66  2.42  14.12  0.47-1.99  14 (73.68%)  0.46-30.44  49 (64.47%)  1.89-84.92  7 (53.85%)  0.25-∞ 1 (50.0%)  57 (62.65%)  2.19-90.97  0.94  0.22  0.009  0.44  0.005 E-G35039 (40.21%)56 (45.53%)1.012.5812.561.7413.250.47-2.176 (31.58%)0.29-23.1728 (36.84%)1.84-85.863 (23.08%)0.15-∞-31 (34.07%)2.02-87.120.980.390.0100.650.007E-A176/G3503 (3.09%)5 (4.07%)1.495.8224.7912.6239.820.31-7.231 (5.26%)0.28-121.375 (6.58%)2.33-263.352 (15.38%)0.79-∞1 (50.0%)8 (8.79%)4.11-386.040.620.260.0080.070.001E-C188/G35011 (11.34%)13 (10.57%)1.07.918.563.0510.480.35-2.845 (26.32%)0.81-77.588 (10.53%)1.07-68.262 (15.38%)0.23-∞-10 (10.99%)1.39-78.920.990.080.0430.400.023Class AA-a 4 (4.12%)  11 (8.94%)  2.18  12.65  35.21  21.24  54.51  0.58-8.17  3 (15.79%)  1.02-156.20  12 (15.79%)  3.87-320.39  5 (38.46%)  1.75-∞ 1 (50.0%)  18 (19.78%)  6.36-467.62  0.25  0.048  0.002  0.016  0.000 AA-a3 (3.09%)11 (8.94%)3.0817.4043.7326.6969.010.73-13.043 (15.79%)1.32-229.6012 (15.79%)4.55-420.565 (38.46%)2.10-∞1 (50.0%)18 (19.78%)7.57-628.960.130.030.0010.010.000Class AA-c 6 (6.19%)  3 (2.44%)  0.44  2.79  24.46  3.01  25.28  0.10-2.06  1 (5.26%)  0.15-52.20  11 (14.47%)  2.89-207.12  1 (7.69%)  0.15-∞ -  12 (13.19%)  3.12-204.74  0.30  0.49  0.003  0.47  0.002 AA-c6 (6.19%)3 (2.44%)0.462.9319.972.9921.160.10-2.151 (5.26%)0.16-54.909 (11.84%)2.34-170.251 (7.69%)0.15-∞-10 (10.99%)2.59-172.560.320.470.0060.470.004Class Af2-a 0 (0%)  1 (0.81%)  -  0 (0%)  -  0 (0%)  -  0 (0%)  -  0 (0%)  0 (0%)  - *,Indicate reference category (E-Prototype). a ,OR was not calculated for E-T350 class because it includes reference category (E-Prototype). b,To calculate OR and CI in ADC an artificial case was created.OR: Odds ratio adjusted for age. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The novel HPV 16 E6 variants were found in 11 women, 6 from the center of the State of Guerrero, 2 from the coast and 3 from Northern Guerrero. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>These variants were found in samples taken from 1997 to 2012. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The AA-a/C188 HPV 16 variant was found in non-IL cervical sample taken in 1997, AA-c/G185 variant was found in a cervical carcinoma sample taken in 1998, E-A176/G424/G350 was found in a cervical carcinoma sample taken in 2003, E-C183/G350 was found in a non-IL cervical samples taken in 2002 and 2006, E-C306/G350 was found in non-IL a cervical sample taken in 2003, E-C188/G310/G350 was found in a non-IL cervical sample taken in 2004 and an LSIL taken in 2009, E-G535/G350 was found in an LSIL cervical sample taken in 2006 and E-G189/T256/G350 variant was found in an LSIL cervical sample taken in 2008. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Six novel variants were found with non-IL, 3 with LSIL and 2 with cervical carcinoma (E-A176/G350/G424 and AA-c/G185). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Data from a follow up cytological diagnosis of 5 women with HPV 16 E6 novel variants were collected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Follow up information shows that two with the variant E-C183/G350 evolved from non-IL to LSIL, whereas those with E-C188/G310/G350 and E-G189/T256/G350 maintain LSIL status (Table 4).Table 4 Novel HPV16 E6 variants, regional distribution, collection year and lesion in cervical epithelium  Patient  HPV 16 E6 Novel variant  Accession number GenBank  Nucleotide change  Amino acid change (not previously reported)  Women residence (City/State region)  Diagnosis/Sampling year  Follow up Diagnosis/Year 1E-A176/G424/G350KJ465994G424-Atoyac/CoastCervical carcinoma 2003-2E-C183/G350KJ465995C183I27TChilpancingo/CenterNon-IL 2002LSIL 20063E-C183/G350KJ465995C183I27TChilpancingo/CenterNon-IL 2006LSIL 20094E-C183/G350KJ465995C183I27TChilpancingo/CenterNon-IL 2002-5E-C188/G310/G350KJ465996G310-Chilpancingo/CenterNon-IL 2004Non-IL 20056E-C188/G310/G350KJ465996G310-Chilpancingo/CenterLSIL 2009LSIL 20127E-G189/T256/G350KJ465998G189 and T256-Chilpancingo/CenterLSIL 2008LSIL 20098E-C306/G350KJ465997C306K68TAcapulco CoastNon-IL 2003-9E-G535/G350KJ465999G535-Tepecoacuilco/NorthLSIL 2006-10AA-a/C188KJ465992C188-Iguala/NorthNon-IL 1997-11AA-c/G185KJ465993G185-Juchitan/NorthCervical carcinoma 1998- </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Sequence Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The 8 novel variant sequences described in this report have been deposited in GenBank under designated accession numbers KJ465992, KJ465993, KJ465994, KJ465995, KJ465996, KJ465997, KJ465998 and KJ465999. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The objective of this study was to document HPV 16 E6 variants circulating over a period of 16 years in women from Southern Mexico and to analyze its association with cervical carcinoma and precursor lesions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>According to sequence analysis, nucleotide polymorphisms were detected and used to investigate the intratypic heterogeneity of HPV 16 in the Southern Mexican population. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>It is known that the genomes of HPV 16 variants differ geographically worldwide due to evolution linked to ethnic groups and that the risk for cervical carcinoma seems to be population-dependent [5,6,8,10,26-28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Mexico is a country with diverse ethnic origins because European immigrants mixed with various indigenous populations, in consequence current population carries HPV variant from various ethnic group [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>In the present study of 330 women with HPV 16 sampled over a period of 16 years, 27 variants were found; E variants were the most common, followed by AA variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Studies worldwide have found that E variants are the most prevalent worldwide (94% in Oceania, 84% in Eastern Asia, 83% in North America, 82% in Europe, 78% in Western Asia and 71% in Central and South America) with exception of Africa (36%) [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Tornesello, et al. (2011) showed that globally, the most prevalent variant in Central and South America (including Mexico) is E-G350 (43%) followed by AA (30%) and E-Prototype (27%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>In North America it is E-Prototype and E-G350 (49% each one) followed by AA (11%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>In Europe it is E-G350 (44%) followed by E-Prototype (38%) and AA (6%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>In Western Asia it is E-G350 (51%) followed by E-Prototype (25%) and AA (9%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>In Eastern Asia it is As (42%) followed by E-Prototype (37%) and E-G350 (9%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>In Oceania it is E-Prototype (38%) followed by E-G350 (29%) and As (12%) and in Africa it is Afr1 and Afr2 (62%) followed by E-Prototype (34%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>In the present study, the most frequently identified HPV 16 variant was E-G350 (40%), following the E-Prototype (13.03%), E-C188/G350 (11.82%), AA-a (10.61%), AA-c (6.07%) and E-A176/G350 (5.15%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>However, unlike other regions, it was found that E-Prototype frequency in Southern Mexico is lower than the rest of the world, while E-G350, considering all its subclasses together, is more frequent than in the rest of the world. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The AA variants of HPV 16 were 15-fold more prevalent than E-prototype in cervical carcinoma. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Studies on HPV 16 variants in Mexico have shown that even in the same country its distribution is different depending on the region analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of HPV 16 variants, stratified by histological groups, from five geographical regions of Mexico (Central, North-Central, Northeastern, Southeastern and Southern) is presented in Table 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The E variants are the most prevalent in all geographical regions in women, E-prototype in the Southeastern region and E-G350 in Central and Southern Mexico. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>AA variants are present in the five regions, but its prevalence is higher in the Northeastern region than in the rest of the country, although it is inhabited mostly by Europeans descendants, Mestizo and very few indigenous ethnic groups [5,8,20,21,23,29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The State of Guerrero, located in Southern Mexico, is inhabited by Mestizo, Nahuas, Mixtecs, Amuzgos, Tlapanecos and Afro-Mexicans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>In this study, which is larger than our previous study [24], we found that HPV 16 E-G350 was the most common variant in all histological grades, although in ADC, the prevalence of E-G350 and AA is close. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>In all regions of Mexico, the prevalence of AA in ADC tends to increase in comparison to the other histological grades. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Moreover, among AA variants, AA-a is more common than AA-c.Table 5 Published data on HPV 16 variants distribution in cervical epithelium lesions in regions of Mexico  Region of Mexico  State/City  Genome region  Samples  Histology  HPV 16 E  HPV 16 E-Prototype  HPV 16 E-G350  AA  AA-a  AA-c  Reference CentralMexico CityE6, L180SCC56%4%52%44%--Berumen, et al., 20016ADC0%0%0%100%--20Non-IL90%5%85%10%--CentralMexico CityE650SCC30%--40%32%8%Lizano, et al., 200611ADC55%--45%27%18%23HSIL74%--26%26%0%13LSIL54%--46%46%0%16Non-IL56%--44%44%0%North-CentralSan Luis PotosíE62ICC100%50%50%0%0%0%López-Revilla, et al., 20099HSIL89%33%56%11%11%0%27LSIL96%85%11%4%4%0%NortheasternNuevo LeónLCR112Undefined13%--87%--Calleja-Macias, et al., 2004SoutheasternYucatanE625IIC52%28%24%44%--González-Losa, et al. 200415LSIL100%66%33%0%0%0%SouthernGuerreroE645ICC67%--33%--Illades-Aguiar, et al., 201010HSIL90%--10%--18LSIL67%--33%--5Non-IL60%--40%--SouthernGuerreroE676SCC70%3%64%30%16%14%13ADC54%-54%46%38%8%19HSIL79%5%74%21%16%5%Present study123LSIL88%19%69%11%9%2%97Non-IL90%18%66%10%4%6% </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Of the 27 HPV 16 variants found in Southern Mexico in 16 years, 8 of them were new and may be considered to be variants specific to this Mexican region. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Previous data suggests that HPV 16 variants with E6 sequence variation are biologically distinct and may confer different pathological risks for development of squamous intraepithelial lesions and invasive cervical carcinoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>E6 specific sequence variations may modify its linkage to cellular targets changing its ability for p53 degradation, inhibiting keratynocyte differentiation, modifying signal transduction [30-34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>It was proposed that there might be a strong relation between AA variant and cervical carcinoma development [9,16,25,35,36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Using a comparative analysis, it was found in this study that HPV 16 AA-a detection rate increased according to the severity of the cervical lesion, with a large increase in ADC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The results show that HPV 16 AA-a infection has a strong association with a high risk of CC development compared to E-Prototype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>This study reinforces the proposal that HPV 16 AA-a is an oncogenic risk for cervical carcinoma progression in Mexico [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Similar behavior was observed in HPV 16 E-A176/G350 variant, the rate increased according severity of the cervical lesion, although frequency was less than for AA-a, and the infection is associated with a risk for development of CC compared with E-Prototype, but less than for AA-a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>AA-c, E-G350 and E-C188/G350, also show association with risk for CC compared with E-Prototype, although lower than the aforementioned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The results of this study highlight the importance of identifying HPV 16 variants in the screening of clinical samples and of conducting follow up test for women with the HPV 16 AA-a variant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>According to the HPV variants found in this study, the amino acid substitutions circulating in Southern Mexico are: Q3E, R10G, Q14H, D25N, I27L, I27R I27T, L28V, E29K, E29Q, E29G, I52L, K68T, F69L, H78Y, L83V (the most frequent) and E113D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The amino acid substitutions present in the HPV 16 E6 variants in descending order of association with CC were: Q14R/H78Y/L83V (AA-a variant), D25N/L83V (E-A176/G350 variant), Q14R/I27/H78Y/L83V (AA-c variant), L83V (E-G350 variant) and E29Q/L83V (E-C188/G350 variant). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Q14R/H78Y/L83V amino acid changes gender AA variants with increased oncogenic potential and more efficient evasion of the host’s immune surveillance [25,37,38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>L83V amino acid change display more efficient degradation of Bax and binding to E6AP, induces ubiquitination and degradation of p53, NFX1-91 and PDZ proteins [14,33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>D25N, I27R and E29Q amino acid changes affect E6 T cell epitope [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Two of the 8 novel variants found in this study had amino acid changes not previously reported: I27T in E-C183/G350 variant and K68T in E-C306/G350 variant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>I27T amino acid change is located at the N-terminal domain of the E6 oncoprotein; K68T is located between zinc fingers of E6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The E-C183/G350 variant was found in women with non-IL who progressed to LSIL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The finding of this new variant could be potentially important. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>It was not possible to analyze the association of novel E6 variants for the risk of developing cervical carcinoma because of the low number of positive samples; however, by having nucleotide changes may also be associated with the development of cervical carcinoma. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Current findings show that in 16 years, at least 27 HPV 16 E6 variants were present in Southern Mexico and 8 novel variants were found, which may be considered to be variants specific to this Mexican region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The variants more frequently found in women with cervical carcinoma are E-G350, AA-a, AA-c, E-C188/G350 and E-A176/G350. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>All of them are associated with the development of cervical carcinoma, however, AA-a showed the highest association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>This study reinforces the proposal that HPV 16 AA-a is an oncogenic risk for cervical carcinoma progression in Mexico. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>This represents the largest study carried out in Mexico analyzing all classes of European and non-European variants in the whole spectrum of disease, from intraepithelial lesion-free cytology to cervical carcinoma including squamous cell carcinoma and adenocarcinoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Further studies are needed to clarify the pathogenicity of HPV 16 E6 variants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The database and biobank, with 7,480 cervical DNA samples collected from 1997 to 2012, of the Molecular Biomedicine and Cytopathology Laboratories at the School of Chemistry and Biology of the Autonomous University of Guerrero in Chilpancingo Guerrero, Mexico, was searched for all cervical DNA samples with HPV 16 and 330 were found in appropriate conditions for analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The samples were studied to investigate circulating HPV 16 variants in Southern Mexico and to do a comparative analysis between these variants and the different grades of cervical lesion. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Cervical samples came from women who were residents of State of Guerrero, seeking cytological screening or for other gynecological complaints, which attended public health centers of Acapulco, Chilpancingo, and Iguala, the three biggest cities in this state of Southern Mexico. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Based on the diagnosis, samples were divided into: (1) no intraepithelial lesion (non-IL) (n = 97), (2) low-grade squamous intraepithelial lesion (LSIL) (n = 123), high-grade squamous intraepithelial lesion (HSIL) (n = 19) and (4) cervical carcinoma (CC) (n = 91). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Non-IL and LSIL samples have cytological diagnosis; HSIL and CC samples have histological diagnosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Cytological diagnosis was done according to the Bethesda System [39] and histological diagnosis according to the classification system of the International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics (FIGO) [40]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>This study was approved by the Bioethical Committee the Autonomous University of Guerrero. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Informed consent was obtained from women participants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>HPV DNA was detected and identified by three methods depending on the year of in which the sample was taken and analyzed: (1) from 1997 to 2010, HPV detection was done by the MY09/11 system and typing by restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLPs); (2) from 2005 to 2010, detection was done by general GP5+/6+ PCR system and typing by sequencing analysis [24] when samples analyzed with MY09/11 PCR were negative; (3) from 2010 to 2012 HPV was detected and typed with INNO Lipa genotyping Extra (Innogenetics) [41]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>HPV variants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The HPV 16 E6 gene was amplified using type-specific primers E6-F048 (5′GAACCGAAACCGGTTAGTAT3′) and E6-R622 (5′CAGTTGTCTCTGGTTGCAAA3′) that amplify a 575-bp region [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>PCR amplification was carried out in a 50 μl reaction containing 1 μM of each primer, 4 mM of MgCl2, and 1.25 U of Platinum Taq DNA Polymerase (Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The DNA amplification was done in a DNA Eppendorf AG 22331 Hamburg [24] as follows: initial denaturation at 95°C for 10 min, followed by 40 cycles of 95°C for 45 s, 57°C for 30 s, 72°C for 1.15 min, and a final extension al 72°C for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>PCR products were purified with 75% isopropanol (2–34 protocol of user manual of Applied Biosystems) and ZR DNA Sequencing Clean-up Kit™ (ZYMO RESEARCH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>These were sequenced using Big Dye Terminator Chemistry v3.1 Ready Reaction Kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA) in an automated sequencer DNA ABI Prism 310 Genetic Analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA) using primers previously described [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Sequences were analyzed with EMBOSS Stretcher of the European Institute of Bioinformatics, LALING GENESTREAM network server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/psa/emboss_stretcher/nucleotide.html">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/psa/emboss_stretcher/nucleotide.html</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://embnet.vital-it.ch/software/LALIGN_form.html">http://embnet.vital-it.ch/software/LALIGN_form.html</ext-link>) and the Finch TV program respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Sequences were aligned with reference sequence (HPV 16R) [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Using the E6 sequence, HPV 16 variants were classified into lineages with their respective sublineages [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The sublineages were stratified in classes and subclasses [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>When new polymorphisms were found, independent PCRs were carried out under the described conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The products obtained were sequenced on both strands to exclude PCR artifacts and to validate the polymorphism found and accept them as new variants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>HPV 16 E6 sequences were compared by multiple sequence alignments using the CLUSTAL W method [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>A phylogenetic tree was constructed by neighbor-joining analysis executed by MEGA 5.2 program [43]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The Chi squared test was used to compare HPV 16 variant frequencies and cervical lesion grade. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Differences were considered to be statistically significant when p values were less than 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Age-adjusted odds ratios and 95% confidence intervals were used to estimate associations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Data analysis and statistics were done using IBM SPSS Statistics V.22.0 and STATA V.11 softwares. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>BIA and MALV designed and supervised research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>JOO identified HPV 16, analyzed HPV 16 E6 variants, and did sequence alignment and statistical analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>JOO, ICM did phylogenetic analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>LCAR, MAJL and VHGB collected the samples and did cytological and histological diagnosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>JOO and BIA drafted the manuscript, HABS revised the manuscript and all authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>We thank José Guadalupe Muñoz Camacho and all of the Instituto Estatal de Cancerología “Dr. Arturo Beltán Ortega” who helped with this study at the clinic sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>We thank Miguel Angel Rodríguez Barrera for his help in the registration of new variants in GenBank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>We thank Dinorah N. Martínez-Carrillo for contributing in statistical analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>We also thank Juan Francisco Leyva and Travis Ashworth for reviewing the English style of the article. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>This study was supported by grant from CONACYT, México. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>1.Zur HausenHPapillomaviruses and cancer: from basic studies to clinical applicationNat Rev Cancer2002234235010.1038/nrc798<?supplied-pmid 12044010?>12044010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>2.GuanPHowell-JonesRLiNBruniLde SanjoseSFranceschiSCliffordGMHuman papillomavirus types in 115,789 HPV-positive women: a meta-analysis from cervical infection to cancerInt J Cancer20121312349235910.1002/ijc.27485<?supplied-pmid 22323075?>22323075 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>3.PeitsaroPJohanssonBSyrjänenSIntegrated human papillomavirus type 16 is frequently found in cervical cancer precursors as demonstrated by a novel quantitative real-time PCR techniqueJ Clin Microbiol200240388689110.1128/JCM.40.3.886-891.2002<?supplied-pmid 11880410?>11880410 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>4.GheitTCornetICliffordGMIftnerTMunkCTommasinoMKjaerSKRisks for persistence and progression by human papillomavirus type 16 variant lineages among a population-based sample of Danish womenCancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev2011201315132110.1158/1055-9965.EPI-10-1187<?supplied-pmid 21527576?>21527576 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>5.BerumenJOrdoñezRMLazcanoESalmerónJGalvánSCEstradaRAYunesEGarcía-CarrancaAGonzalez-LiraGMadrigal-de la CampaAAsian-American variants of human papillomavirus 16 and risk for cervical cancer: a case–control studyJ Natl Cancer Inst200193171325133010.1093/jnci/93.17.1325<?supplied-pmid 11535707?>11535707 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>6.ZunaREMooreWEShanesmithRPDunnSTWangSSSchiffmanMBlakeyGITeelTAssociation of HPV16 E6 variants with diagnostic severity in cervical cytology samples of 354 women in a US populationInt J Cancer20091252609261310.1002/ijc.24706<?supplied-pmid 19569178?>19569178 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>7.SchiffmanMRodríguezACChenZWacholderSHerreroRHildesheimADesalleRBefanoBYuKSafaeianMShermanMEMoralesJGuillenDAlfaroMHutchinsonMSolomonDCastlePEBurkRDA Population-Based Prospective Study of Carcinogenic Human Papillomavirus Variant Lineages, Viral Persistence, and Cervical NeoplasiaCancer Res20107083159316910.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-4179<?supplied-pmid 20354192?>20354192 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>8.Calleja-MacíasIEKalantariMHuhJOrtiz-LópezRRojas-MartínezAGonzalez-GuerreroJFWilliamsonALHagmarBWileyDJVillarrealLBernardHUBarrera-SaldañaHAGenomic diversity of human papilomavirus- 16, 18, 31 and 35 isolates in a Mexican population and relationship to European, African, and Native American variantsVirol200431931532310.1016/j.virol.2003.11.009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>9.TorneselloMLLositoSBenincasaGFulcinitiFBottiGGreggiSBuonaguroLBuonaguroFMHuman papillomavirus (HPV) genotypes and HPV16 variants and risk of adenocarcinoma and squamous cell carcinoma of the cervixGynecol Oncol20111211324210.1016/j.ygyno.2010.12.005<?supplied-pmid 21211829?>21211829 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>10.CornetIGheitTLannaconeMRVignatJSyllaBSDel MistroAFranceschiSTommasinoMCliffordGMIARCHPVVariant Study GroupHPV16 genetic variation and the development of cervical cancer worldwideBr J Cancer201310824024410.1038/bjc.2012.508<?supplied-pmid 23169278?>23169278 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>11.ChenZSchiffmanMHerreroRDe SalleRAnastosKSegondyMSahasrabuddheVVGravittPEHsingAWBurkRDEvolution and Taxonomic Classification of Human Papillomavirus 16 (HPV16)-Related Variant Genomes: HPV31, HPV33, HPV35, HPV52, HPV58 and HPV67Plos One201165e2018310.1371/journal.pone.0020183<?supplied-pmid 21673791?>21673791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>12.CornetIGheitTFranceschiSVignatJBurkRDSyllaBSTommasinoMCliffordGMIARC HPV Variant Study GroupHuman Papillomavirus Type 16 Genetic Variants: Phylogeny and Classification Based on E6 and LCRJ Virol201286126855686110.1128/JVI.00483-12<?supplied-pmid 22491459?>22491459 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>13.Huertas-SalgadoAMartín-GámezDCMorenoPMurilloRBravoMMVillaLMolanoME6 molecular variants of human papillomavirus (HPV) type 16: An updated and unified criterion for clustering and nomenclatureVirol2011410120121510.1016/j.virol.2010.10.039 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>14.LichtigHAlgrisiMBotzerLEAbadiTVerbitzkyYJackmanATommasinoMZehbeIShermanLHPV16 E6 natural variants exhibit different activities in functional assays relevant to the carcinogenic potential of E6Virol200635021622710.1016/j.virol.2006.01.038 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>15.ZehbeIRichardCDecarloCAShaiALambertPFLichtigHTommasinoMShermanLHuman papillomavirus 16 E6 variants differ in their dysregulation of humankeratinocyte differentiation and apoptosisVirol2009383697710.1016/j.virol.2008.09.036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>16.ZehbeILichtigHWesterbackALambertPFTommasinoMShermanLRare human papillomavirus 16 E6 variants reveal significant oncogenic potentialMol Cancer 201120111077113 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>17.SmithBChenZReimersLDoorslaerKSchiffmanMDeSalleRHerreroRYuKWacholderSWangTBurkRDSequence Imputation of HPV16 Genomes for Genetic Association StudiesPLoS ONE201166e2137510.1371/journal.pone.0021375<?supplied-pmid 21731721?>21731721 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>18.JangMRheeJEJangDHKimSSGene Expression Profiles are Altered in Human Papillomavirus-16 E6 D25E-Expressing Cell LinesVirol J201184531621205327 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>19.CasasLGalvánSCOrdoñezRMLópezNGuidoMBerumenJAsian-american variants of human papillomavirus type 16 have extensive mutations in the E2 gene and are highly amplified in cervical carcinomasInt J Cancer199983444945510.1002/(SICI)1097-0215(19991112)83:4&lt;449::AID-IJC3&gt;3.0.CO;2-0<?supplied-pmid 10508478?>10508478 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>20.LizanoMBerumenJGarcía-CarrancaAHPV-related Carcinogenesis: Basic Concepts, Viral Types and VariantsArch Med Res200940642843410.1016/j.arcmed.2009.06.001<?supplied-pmid 19853182?>19853182 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>21.López-Revilla R, Pineda MA, Ortíz-Valdez J, Sánchez-Garza M, Riego L: Human papillomavirus type 16 variants in cervical intraepithelial neoplasia and invasive carcinoma in San Luis Potosi City, Mexico. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Infectious Agents and Cancer 2009, 4(3): <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.infectagentscancer.com/content/4/1/3">http://www.infectagentscancer.com/content/4/1/3</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>22.BradleyCJGivenCWRobertsCHealth Care Disparities and Cervical CancerAm J Public Health20049412209810310.2105/AJPH.94.12.2098<?supplied-pmid 15569960?>15569960 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>23.Secretaría de Salud. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Dirección General de Información en Salud. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Mexico, 2006. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Available from URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dgis.salud.gob.mx/descargas/xls/m_016.xls">http://www.dgis.salud.gob.mx/descargas/xls/m_016.xls</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Accessed March 27, 2009. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>24.Illades-AguiarBAlarcón-RomeroLCAntonio-VéjarVZamudio-LópezNSales-LinaresNFlores-AlfaroEFernández-TilapaGVences-VelázquezAMuñoz-ValleJFLeyva-VázquezMAPrevalence and distribution of human papillomavirus types in cervical cancer, squamous intraepithelial lesions, and with no intraepithelial lesions in women from Southern MexicoGynecol Oncol2010117229129610.1016/j.ygyno.2010.01.036<?supplied-pmid 20199804?>20199804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>25.RichardCLannerCNaryzhnySNShermanLLeeHLambertPFZehbeIThe immortalizing and transforming ability of two common human papillomavirus 16 E6 variants with different prevalences in cervical cancerOncogene201029233435344510.1038/onc.2010.93<?supplied-pmid 20383192?>20383192 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>26.YamadaTManosMMPetoJGreerCMuñozNBoshFXWheelerMHuman papillomavirus type 16 sequence variation in cervical cancers: a wordlwide perspectiveJ Virol199771324632472<?supplied-pmid 9032384?>9032384 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>27.VillaLLSicheroLRahalPCaballeroOFerenczyARohanTFrancoELMolecular variants of human papillomavirus types 16 and 18 preferentially associated with cervical neoplásicaJ Gen Virol20008129592968<?supplied-pmid 11086127?>11086127 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>28.TorneselloMLDuraturoMLSalatielloIBuonaguroLLositoSBottiGStellatoGGreggiSPiccoliRPilottiSStefanonBDe PaloGFranceschiSBuobaguroFMAnalysis of human papillomavirus type-16 variants in Italian women with cervical intraepithelial neoplasia and cervical cancerJ Med Virol200474111712610.1002/jmv.20154<?supplied-pmid 15258977?>15258977 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>29.González-LosaMDRLaviada Mier y TeranMAPuerto-SolísMGarcía-CarrancáAMolecular variants of HPV type 16 E6 among Mexican women with LSIL and invasive cancerJ Clin Virol200429959810.1016/S1386-6532(03)00094-514747027 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>30.ZehbeIVoglinoGWilanderEDeliusHMarongiuAEdlerLKlimekFAnderssonSTommasinoMp53 codon 72 polymorphism and various human papillomavirus 16 E6 genotypes are risk factors for cervical cancer developmentCancer Res2001612608611<?supplied-pmid 11212257?>11212257 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>31.XiLFKoutskyLAHildesheimAGallowayDAWheelerCMWinerRLHoJKiviatNBRisk for High-Grade Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia Associated with Variants of Human Papillomavirus Types 16 and 18Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev20071641010.1158/1055-9965.EPI-06-0670<?supplied-pmid 17220325?>17220325 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>32.ChopjittPEkalaksanananTPientongCKongyingyoesBKleebkaowPCharoensriNPrevalence of human papillomavirustype16 and its variants in abnormal squamous cervical cells in Northeast ThailandInt J Infect Dis2009132212910.1016/j.ijid.2008.06.017<?supplied-pmid 18838282?>18838282 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>33.PillaiMRHariharanRBabuJMLakshmiSChiplunkarSVPatkarMTongaonkarHDinshawKJayshreeRSReddyBKSiddiquiMRoychoudurySSahaBAbrahamPGnanamonyMPeedicayilASubhashiniJRamTSDeyBSharmaCJainSKSinghNMolecular variants of HPV-16 associated with cervical cancer in Indian populationInt J Cancer200912519110310.1002/ijc.24322<?supplied-pmid 19358280?>19358280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>34.Wise-DraperTMWellsSLPapillomavirus E6 and E7 proteins and their cellular targetsFront Biosci2008131003101710.2741/2739<?supplied-pmid 17981607?>17981607 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>35.Junes-GillKSicheroLMaciagPCMelloWNoronhaVVillaLLHuman papillomavirus type 16 variants in cervical cancer from an admixtured population in BrazilJ Med Virol2008801639164510.1002/jmv.21238<?supplied-pmid 18649325?>18649325 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>36.QuintKDde KoningMNvan DoornLJQuintWGPirogECHPV genotyping and HPV16 variant analysis in glandular and squamous neoplastic lesions of the uterine cervixGynecol Oncol2010117229730110.1016/j.ygyno.2010.02.003<?supplied-pmid 20207397?>20207397 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>37.ZehbeIMytilineosJWikströmIHenriksenREdlerLTommasinoMAssociation between human papillomavirus 16 E6 variants and human leukocyte antigen class I polymorphism in cervical cancer of swedish womenHum Immunol20036455384210.1016/S0198-8859(03)00033-8<?supplied-pmid 12691704?>12691704 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>38.SicheroLSobrinhoJSVillaLLOncogenic potential diverge among human papillomavirus type 16 natural variantsVirol201243212713210.1016/j.virol.2012.06.011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>39.SolomonDDaveyDKurmanRMoriartyAO'ConnorDPreyMRaabSShermanMWWrightTJYoungNThe 2001 Bethesda System: terminology for reporting results of cervical cytologyJAMA20022872114910.1001/jama.287.16.2114<?supplied-pmid 11966386?>11966386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>40.BenedetJLFIGO staging classifications and clinical practice guidelines of gynaecologic cancers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>FIGO Committee on Gynecologic OncologyInt J Gynecol Obstet2000702096210.1016/S0020-7292(00)90001-8 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>41.KleterBvan DoornLJSchrauwenLMolijnASastrowijotoSter ScheggetJLindemanJter HarmselBBurgerMQuintWDevelopment and clinical evaluation of a highly sensitive PCR-reverse hybridization line probe assay for detection and identification of anogenital human papillomavirusJ Clin Microbiol1999378250817<?supplied-pmid 10405393?>10405393 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>42.ThompsonJDGibsonTJPlewniakFJeanmouginFHigginsDGThe CLUSTAL_X windows interface: flexible strategies for multiple sequence alignment aided by quality analysis toolsNucleic Acids Res 1997199725244876488210.1093/nar/25.24.4876 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>43.TamuraKPetersonDPetersonNStecherGNeiMKumarSMEGA5: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis using Maximum Likelihood, Evolutionary Distance, and Maximum Parsimony MethodsMol Biol Evol201128102731273910.1093/molbev/msr121<?supplied-pmid 21546353?>21546353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
