<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Archaea</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Archaea</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ARCHAEA</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Archaea</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1472-3646</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1472-3654</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4325475</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2015/241608</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Adaptation, Ecology, and Evolution of the Halophilic Stromatolite Archaeon Halococcus hamelinensis Inferred through Genome Analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gudhka</surname><given-names>Reema K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Neilan</surname><given-names>Brett A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>Brendan P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>School of Biotechnology and Biomolecular Sciences, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW 2052, Australia</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Australian Centre for Astrobiology, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW 2052, Australia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Brendan P. Burns: <email>brendan.burns@unsw.edu.au</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editor: William B. Whitman </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>2015</volume><elocation-id>241608</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>4</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2015 Reema K. Gudhka et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Halococcus hamelinensis was the first archaeon isolated from stromatolites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>These geomicrobial ecosystems are thought to be some of the earliest known on Earth, yet, despite their evolutionary significance, the role of Archaea in these systems is still not well understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Detailed here is the genome sequencing and analysis of an archaeon isolated from stromatolites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The genome of H. hamelinensis consisted of 3,133,046 base pairs with an average G+C content of 60.08% and contained 3,150 predicted coding sequences or ORFs, 2,196 (68.67%) of which were protein-coding genes with functional assignments and 954 (29.83%) of which were of unknown function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Codon usage of the H. hamelinensis genome was consistent with a highly acidic proteome, a major adaptive mechanism towards high salinity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Amino acid transport and metabolism, inorganic ion transport and metabolism, energy production and conversion, ribosomal structure, and unknown function COG genes were overrepresented. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The genome of H. hamelinensis also revealed characteristics reflecting its survival in its extreme environment, including putative genes/pathways involved in osmoprotection, oxidative stress response, and UV damage repair. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Finally, genome analyses indicated the presence of putative transposases as well as positive matches of genes of H. hamelinensis against various genomes of Bacteria, Archaea, and viruses, suggesting the potential for horizontal gene transfer. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Stromatolites are defined as organosedimentary structures produced by the trapping and precipitation of carbonates and sediments as a result of microbial growth and metabolic activity [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The presence of stromatolites dates back some 3.5–3.8 billion years in Earth's history, a time period that witnessed the appearance of the first forms of life [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The microbial communities that constituted these complex structures also played a significant role in global biogeochemical cycles, including early oxygenation of the atmosphere [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Owing to their importance, stromatolites have formed the core of a growing area of microbial ecology and evolution-based research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The most extensive modern stromatolites to date reside in the open marine waters in Exuma Sound in the Bahamas [4] and the hypersaline marine environment of Shark Bay on the western coast of Australia [5, 6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Previous reports employing a combination of microbial isolation, culture-independent nucleic acid based analyses, and lipid profiling have shown that Shark Bay stromatolites support a significant range of metabolically and phylogenetically diverse microorganisms [5–7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Major functional groups were identified that are involved in cycling of key nutrients, including oxygenic and anoxygenic photosynthesisers, aerobic heterotrophs, and organisms involved in sulphur cycling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>For the first time, a diverse range of Archaea was also identified in the stromatolites of Shark Bay [5–7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Although most studies to date have focused on the function of cyanobacteria and heterotrophic bacteria in stromatolites, the physiological role and significance of Archaea in stromatolite systems still remains unexplored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Halophilic Archaea in particular may be an important component of the Shark Bay stromatolites vital to ecosystem function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Halophilic Archaea are very well adapted to hypersaline environments and thrive in many different areas, including the Dead Sea and solar salterns [8, 9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Previously, the first archaeon to be isolated from stromatolites, a Gram-negative, nonmotile, strictly aerobic Halococcus isolate (Halococcus hamelinensis) was also characterised [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>This archaeon grows optimally at 37°C in medium containing 15% NaCl, as opposed to 20–30% in other characterized Halococcus strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>It metabolizes many simple and complex carbohydrates including glucose, sucrose, xylose, maltose, trehalose, mannitol, galactose, and glycerol [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>It does not hydrolyze starch or produce indole and is negative for sulfide reduction, urease, and gelatin liquefication, in contrast to other Halococcus species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, it displays sensitivity to rifampicin, novobiocin, and bacitracin and resistance to kanamycin, tetracycline, streptomycin, neomycin, and penicillin. H. hamelinensis was also oxidase-negative, whereas all recognized Halococcus species are oxidase-positive, and most aerobic halophilic Archaea are also oxidase-positive [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Whole-cell protein profiles, enzyme composition, and carbon source utilization of this isolate were distinct from other characterized Halococcus species, rendering it a novel species of Halococcus [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Prior to the isolation of this organism, no archaeal species had been discovered at Shark Bay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>As no archaeal isolates were also identified in the surrounding water, despite samples being collected several years apart [5, 7], it may be that this organism has a significant role to play in stromatolite ecosystem function. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Recent studies have shown that H. hamelinensis displays a number of other novel characteristics, including lacking potassium accumulation as a primary osmoprotective strategy, in contrast to most known haloarchaea [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Instead, accumulation of glycine betaine as well as other solutes such as glutamate and trehalose was observed to be the primary mechanism of adaptation to salt stress in this organism [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In addition, a recent study examined the effects of UV stress/damage in H. hamelinensis [13], revealing that this archaeon is able to survive high germicidal UVC radiation dosages, as well as possessing several bacterial-like nucleotide excision repair genes [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Changes in the expression levels of these genes (uvrA, uvrB, and uvrC) were investigated by qRT-PCR, and all were upregulated during both light and dark repairs [13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>While these recent studies have provided useful insights into the physiological characteristics of this novel archaeon, what is lacking is a comprehensive whole genomic profile and related computational analyses of this organism, which would significantly enhance our understanding of its evolutionary and adaptive traits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Here we describe the sequence (by massively parallel 454 pyrosequencing technology), annotation, and analysis of the genome of H. hamelinensis, which provides insights into the ecology, evolution, and adaptation of this novel microorganism. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Genome Sequencing and Assembly </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Halococcus hamelinensis was grown as previously described until logarithmic phase [10], and DNA was extracted using a xanthogenate protocol previously optimised for this Archaea [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The genome of H. hamelinensis was sequenced at The Clive and Vera Ramaciotti Centre using 454 (Roche) sequencing technology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Sample quality and quantity were assessed prior to library preparation, as described in the GS FLX Titanium General Library Preparation Method Manual (Roche). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Briefly, 8 μg of gDNA was fragmented by nebulization, fragmented DNA run on a 0.8% agarose gel and fragments between ~500 and 800 bp excised, and purified using a QiaQuick Gel Extraction Kit (Qiagen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>DNA sample quality assessment, fragment end repair and adaptor ligation, small fragment removal, library immobilization, and single-stranded DNA library isolation were performed as per GS FLX Titanium Sequencing Method Manual (Roche). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The quality of the library was assessed on a Bioanalyzer RNA Pico 6000 Chip (Agilent Technologies) and quantified using the Quant-It RiboGreen assay (Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Finally emulsion PCR and sequencing were performed as described in the GS FLX Titanium Sequencing Method Manual. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>A total of 272,854 reads, counting up to 118,638,438 bases (32-fold coverage of the genome), were assembled using 454 Newbler GS de novo Assembler software, which generated 453 contigs ranging from 500 to 105,929 bp, with bases having quality scores of 40 and above. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Automated Sequence Annotation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Sequencing output was uploaded onto two different auto annotation servers, the Rapid Annotation using Subsystem Technology (RAST) [15] and Integrated Microbial Genomes/Expert Review (IMG/ER) [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>RAST uses a strategy based on comparison with manually curated subsystems and subsystem-based protein families, guaranteeing a high degree of consistency and accuracy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Putative coding sequences were identified by Glimmer software [17], and peptides shorter than 30 amino acids were eliminated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>tRNA genes and rRNA genes were predicted by tRNAScan-SE software and RNAmmer, respectively [18, 19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Functional annotation was performed by searching the NCBI nonredundant protein database and the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) protein database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Data from the genome were matched against data from external sources, including RefSeq, EBI Genome Reviews, GenBank/EMBL, JGI microbial genome data, LIGAND, GO, COG, Enzyme, InterPro, KEGG, KO, Pfam, TIGRFam, and GOLD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Pathways for modes of nutrition and transport system were acquired through the KEGG function analysis in IMG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>COG analysis was carried out using COG functions and abundance profile analysis within the IMG/ER. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatic Analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analyses were performed to elucidate evolutionary relationships. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The 16 S rRNA gene sequences were derived from various euryarchaeal genomes from the NCBI database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The sequences were then aligned using ClustalX [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>A BLOSUM series protein weight matrix was used with a Gap Opening of 10 and a Gap Extension of 0.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Using the ClustalX multiple sequence alignment, neighbor joining phylograms were constructed, bootstrapped, and displayed using the MEGA version 4 program [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Programs from the EMBOSS package, COMPSEQ (calculates the composition of unique words in a sequence) and CHIPS (calculates Nc codon usage statistics), were run to determine the number and frequency of occurrence of codon triplets of the predicted proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Over- or underrepresented codons were corrected based on the GC content (66.08%) of the H. hamelinensis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Predictions of amino acid usage were based on the codon frequency output for each amino acid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Radial graphs were created using IMG/ER Phylogenetic Distribution of genes software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The program Alien Hunter was used to detect potential horizontal transfer regions within the H. hamelinensis genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The Alien hunter output was read through the Artemis program and the data output was viewed using the DNA PLOTTER program. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>3.1. H. hamelinensis Genome Overview </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Whole genome sequencing by 454 pyrosequencing produced a greater than 32x coverage of the H. hamelinensis genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The genome sequence of H. hamelinensis is accessible at GenBank under accession number PRJNA80845. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>An overview of the genome features is given in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The genome of H. hamelinensis consisted of 3,133,046 base pairs (bp) with an average G+C content of 60.08%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The genome consisted of 223 DNA scaffolds and 48 RNA genes, 45 of which were tRNA genes and the remaining three were rRNA genes comprising of a single rRNA operon (16 S-23 S-5 S). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the genome contained 3,150 predicted coding sequences, 2,196 (68.67%) of which were protein-coding genes with functional assignments and 954 (29.83%) of which were of unknown function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Based on 16 S rDNA phylogenetic analyses, H. jeotgali was identified as the closest sequenced genome to H. hamelinensis with a BLAST identity score of 91%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Other related organisms were H. turkmenica, isolated in sulfate saline soil in Turkmenistan [22], N. Magadii, isolates from a Kenyan soda lake [23], and H. xanaduensis, isolated from a saline Lake Shangmatala in China [24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The results for codon frequency indicated a bias towards high GC content in the third position (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>From the three-letter codon prediction codons, the following amino acids were observed to have high frequency: alanine (GCC, GCG, and GCA), arginine (CGA, CGC, CGG, and CGT), aspartic acid (GAC), glutamic acid (GAA, GAG), glycine (GGC, GGG, and GGT), histidine (CAC), leucine (CTC), proline (CCC, CCG), serine (TCC, TCG), threonine (ACC, ACG), and valine (GTC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Frank Wright's NC statistic for the effective number of codons used was also calculated, where the Nc output can take values from 20, in the case of extreme bias where one codon is exclusively used for each aa, to 61 when the use of alternative synonymous codons is equally likely. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The Nc output value for the H. hamelinensis genome was calculated as 47.8, indicating very little bias between individual codon usage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Organisms high in GC% tend to have codons ending in C or G and this is also reflected in the H. hamelinensis genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Carbon Assimilation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Preliminary studies carried out on H. hamelinensis whole cells indicated that the organism utilizes glucose, sucrose, xylose, maltose, trehalose, and glycerol as both single and complex carbon sources, in addition to mannitol, galactose and ethanol as single carbon sources [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Detailed genome analyses conducted in the present study identified glucose catabolism to proceed via the Embden-Meyerhof pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Genes encoding enzymes from the Entner-Doudoroff pathway were not present in the H. hamelinensis genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Nitrogen Assimilation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Archaea can use ammonia as well as a large variety of nitrogen compounds as sole sources of nitrogen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>To assimilate ammonia, only one enzyme is required, glutamine synthetase that was identified here in the H. hamelinensis genome (gene ID: 2502298936). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Once converted to L-glutamine, the enzyme glutamate synthase (gene ID: 2502300824, 2502301225, and 2502301417) converts it to glutamate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>In cases of low ammonia H. hamelinensis can putatively convert nitrate to ammonia via nitrite using the enzymes nitrate reductase (catalytic subunit) (gene ID: 2502301552) and ferredoxin nitrite reductase (gene ID: 2502300324). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The organism also has the genetic potential to produce glycine and cyclic amidines, using the enzymes aminomethyltransferase/glycine cleavage system T protein (gene ID: 2502301667) and NAD+ synthetase (Gene ID: 2502298992, 2502299198, 2502299746). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>In addition to these enzymes, H. hamelinensis also possesses genes encoding three ABC transport proteins involving glutamine, namely, glutamine ABC transporter, periplasmic glutamine-binding protein (gene ID 2502298730), ABC-type glutamine/glutamate/polar amino acids transport system, permease protein (gene ID: 2502298731), and ABC-type glutamine/glutamate polar amino acids transport system, ATP-binding protein (gene ID: 2502298732). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>3.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Energy Acquisition </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Analyses here confirmed the presence of genes encoding: 3Na+/H+ antiporters, Na+/H+ antiporter NhaC, Na+/H+ antiporter MnhB subunit-related protein, multisubunit Na+/H+ antiporter, MnhF subunit, and two Na+ symporters, namely, Na+/solute symporter and pantothenate: Na+ symporter, suggesting a functioning pathway between H+ and osmotic metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Genome analysis also confirmed the presence of an ATP synthase gene cluster (V-type ATP synthase subunit A, B, C, E, F, H, I, and a ATP synthase subunit C) and putative regulatory, ligand-binding protein related to C-terminal domains of K+ channels, indicating complete pathways from H+ to K+ gradients and ATP production, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Respiratory chain enzymes, in halophilic organisms, require high salt concentration to be active [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Genome analyses indicated that H. hamelinensis contained a putative electron-transport flavoprotein (alpha and beta subunit) and two cytochrome B coding genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The halophilic Archaea possess light driven ion pumps [26], bacteriorhodopsin, and halorhodopsin that pump protons and chloride ions, respectively, across the membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The proton pump serves to create a proton potential that can be used to drive ATP synthesis [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Although this has been thought to be exclusively an archaeal protein, recently bacteriorhodopsin-like proteins, such as xanthorhodopsin and proteorhodopsin, have been discovered in bacteria [27, 28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, despite exhaustive genome analyses, no homologous genes encoding bacteriorhodopsin, halorhodopsin, or bacterioruberin were identified in the H. hamelinensis genome in the present study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>3.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Osmoadaptation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>H. hamelinensis is known to accumulate compatible solutes such as glycine betaine, trehalose, glutamate, and proline [12], which display a general stabilizing effect by preventing the unfolding and denaturation of proteins caused by heating, freezing, and drying. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Genome analyses here revealed several putative genes involved in glycine betaine accumulation processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The presence of three genes (designated betI, betII, and betIII) encoding for three putative glycine betaine transport proteins supports the previous findings showing glycine betaine accumulation as an osmoprotective strategy in this archeon [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Two ABC-type glycine betaine permease components and glycine betaine ABC transporter ATP-binding protein identified here (Table 2) also indicate the presence of a glycine betaine ABC-transport system used to accumulate glycine betaine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In addition, there are two further genes encoding a putative glycine betaine transporter (OpuD) present in the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis carried out on the three Bet proteins from H. hamelinensis that showed high similarity to putative glycine betaine secondary transporters of other halophilic Archaea as well as those of Desulfomicrobium baculatum, ButA of the halophilic bacterium, Tetragenococcus halophilus, and OpuD of the marine gamma-proteobacterium, Teredinibacter turnerae [29–31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Twelve transmembrane domains were present, a signature of the BCCT (betaine/carnitine/choline transporter) family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Trehalose is another compatible solute putatively synthesized in H. hamelinensis for osmoadaptation [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>A putative trehalose biosynthesis pathway was found to be complete in the H. hamelinensis genome here, where UPD-glucose is metabolised to trehalose-6-phosphate and then trehalose via trehalose 6-phosphate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Archaea are also known to maintain a constant K+ concentration intracellularly for essential functions such as maintenance of cell turgor and homeostasis, adaptation of cells to osmotic stress, and activation of cell cytoplasmic enzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>There are various mechanisms to accumulate K+ in the cell and the three best characterized systems are the Trk, Kdp, and Kup K+ transport systems [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Previous analyses screening for putative K+ uptake genes by degenerative PCR failed to detect two putative potassium transport proteins, namely, TrkH and KdpB, in H. hamelensis [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>While no homologs to the kdpB system were identified in the present study, other genes coding for K+ uptake proteins were identified which included two putative K+ uptake proteins: TrkH and TrkA (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>These form a part of the Trk system, which is a low affinity, rapid transport system mainly used at neutral or alkaline pH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The presence of homologs to TrkH in the present study is in contrast to PCR results reported recently [12] and illustrates the advantage of whole genome sequencing to complement targeted PCR approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Two Kef-type K+ transport proteins and multiple sodium-potassium/hydrogen antiporter subunits were also identified here, which comprise the K+ efflux system [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, genes encoding for the synthesis of archaeatidylglyercolmethyl phosphate, a typical lipid identified previously in H. hamelinensis [12] and known to contribute to osmotolerance, were not found here. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><title><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>3.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Strategies of DNA Repair and Heavy Metal Resistance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>A recent study revealed the presence of a UvrABC DNA repair system in H. hamelinensis, possessing three bacterial-like nucleotide repair genes, namely, excinuclease ABC subunit A, B, and C [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Three other putative DNA repair systems were identified in the present study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>These were a bacterial MutL-MutS system, consisting of mismatch repair proteins, DNA repair base excision system consisting endonucleases and ligases, and the 2-phosphoglycolate salvage system, consisting of phosphoglycolate phosphatase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>In addition there were also several DNA repair and recombination proteins detected within the H. hamelinensis genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Various Archaea are also known to possess mechanisms for heavy metal resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Analyses were conducted here to verify the presence of any toxic/heavy metal resistance coding genes in H. hamelinensis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Several putative genes were identified here and are shown in Table 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Two copper-translocating ATPases were detected, and there was also the presence of genes encoding arsenate reductase enzymes and copper-zinc-cadmium resistance proteins within the H. hamelinensis genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>There were four permease enzymes belonging to the drug/metabolite transporter super family, which are presumed to transport toxic metabolites out of the cell. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.7"><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>3.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Cluster of Orthologous Group (COG) Categories </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The H. hamelinensis genome has a total of 2,296 genes within COG categories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>A search was carried out to determine the overrepresented COG categories within H. hamelinensis, when compared to other sequenced archaeal genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>There were 8 overrepresented categories the general prediction category (16.90%), followed by the amino acid transport and metabolism (9.80%), unknown function (9.32%), inorganic ion transport and metabolism (7.62%), energy production and conversion (7.14%) and translation, and ribosomal structure and biogenesis (6.93%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Following these analyses, a search for both homolog and nonhomolog genes between H. hamelinensis and Archaea was conducted, and then for the Euryarchaeota. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Results indicate a higher number of homolog genes between both Archaea and Euryarchaeota and fewer nonhomolog genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Genome analysis reveals 165 genes from H. hamelinensis that have homologs in the 86 genomes of other Euryarchaeota, whereas there are only 95 genes from H. hamelinensis in total that have homologs after comparison with all other 120 Archaea genomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.8"><title><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>3.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Potential Horizontal Gene Transfer </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Nine putative transposase coding genes were detected in the H. hamelinensis genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>These were distributed amongst six different contigs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Two transposase DDE domains were found close to each other on contig 00141. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Neighbouring these transposase genes were three genes, two ABC transport protein coding genes and one putative cobalamin protein coding gene, from the inorganic ion transport and metabolism COG category. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Two putative transposase coding genes are found in close proximity to a glycine betaine transporter and a glycine cleavage T-protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Other genes neighbouring the transposases are genes belonging to the general function prediction COG category as well as the inorganic ion transport and metabolism COG category. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>A third putative transposase DDE domain was found isolated on contig 00142 with a hypothetical protein neighbouring it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>A phylogenetic distribution of genes was assessed by carrying out individual BLAST searches between each protein coding gene of H. hamelinensis and genes across all other phyla. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>This was conducted to analyze potential horizontally transferred genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>It was found that H. hamelinensis has 2,639 positive matches within the archaeal lineage, out of which 96.89% fall within the Euryarchaeota phylum and 117 hits within the bacterial lineage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Under the bacterial lineage, the highest numbers of genes with positive hits were against the following: the Actinobacteria phylum (22.%), Bacilli (15%), Gammaproteobacteria (11%), Clostridia (9%), Cyanobacteria (8%), and Bacteroidetes (7%). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>A radial phylogenetic tree comparison between H. hamelinensis and other bacteria and Archaea (Figure 2) also indicate potential evolutionary relationships and/or potential HGT that may have occurred. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>To further examine the importance of potential horizontal gene transfer to the H. hamelinensis genome, a gene-independent analysis of potential HGT using interpolated variable motif scores calculated from the program Alien Hunter was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Several putative regions were considered likely to have been acquired by HGT (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.9"><title><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>3.9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Screening for Restriction/Modification and CRISPR Systems in H. hamelinensis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Microbial defence systems against mobile elements/foreign DNA include restriction modification (RM) systems [34] and clustered, regularly interspaced, short palindromic repeat (CRISPR) systems [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>CRISPR systems have been recently identified as an adaptive microbial immune system that provides acquired immunity against viruses and plasmids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>This system represents a family of DNA repeats found in approximately 40% of bacterial genomes and most archaeal (~90%) genomes thus far screened [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, after analysis of the H. hamelinensis genome no putative CRISPR/Cas elements could be identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>RM systems were also examined by screening the H. hamelinensis annotated genome for genes involved in RM systems; no homologs to known host restriction modification systems were identified and only one homolog to a methylase putatively involved in methylating (and thus protecting) host DNA from host restriction enzymes (CTAG modification methylase) was identified. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The present study for the first time presents detailed bioinformatic analyses of the Halococcus hamelinensis genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>This microorganism was originally isolated from modern stromatolites in the hypersaline reaches of Shark Bay, Australia, and is known to exhibit several novel characteristics [10, 12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>However, few genomes of stromatolite organisms have been fully sequenced and are available for comparative genomics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, to date little is known in regards to the adaptive mechanisms employed by Archaea that reside in such ecosystems, and the exact role of Archaea in stromatolites remains clouded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>To better understand the basis of survival and potentially any role H. hamelinensis may play in its unique environment, the genome was sequenced, annotated, and detailed bioinformatics analyses conducted. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The environment where H. hamelinensis was isolated, Shark Bay, is prone to high salinity, exposed ultraviolet radiation and high temperatures leading to desiccation [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is likely that H. hamelinensis would need to possess various strategies to cope with such stresses, and recent studies have revealed several mechanisms this archaeon utilizes to cope with both high saline and UV stress [12, 13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>In terms of saline stress, most halophilic Archaea are known to import potassium ions as the primary osmoadaptive strategy [12, 37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, recent studies indicated that no potassium was taken up by H. hamelinensis, either after growth at both low and high salt concentrations [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Upon analysis of the genome of H. hamelinensis in the present study, however, it was found that a putative potassium uptake protein TrkH was present; however no homologs to KdpB were identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Other putative potassium uptake proteins, such as TrkA and several others from the potassium efflux system, were identified (Table 2), although no complete pathway for potassium uptake was detected within the H. hamelinensis genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>It is hypothesized that these putative proteins may be inactive due to the lack of K+ uptake seen previously [12]; however it is also possible they may be expressed under different conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Other research based on multidrug susceptibility suggested that resistance to antibiotics in microorganisms is associated with several factors, including efflux pumps [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Specifically, one study found that the disruption of the putative potassium uptake regulator, TrkA, leads to rifampicin resistance [39], as well as conferring resistance to other antibiotics such as novobiocin [40, 41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, H. hamelinensis displays sensitivity to both rifampicin and novobiocin [10]; however it remains to be determined whether the putative TrkA present in this organism plays any role in its observed antibiotic sensitivities. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Early studies have also shown that halophilic enzymes exhibit highly polar surfaces in order to remain in solution [41], and comparative studies have shown that in particular ribosomal proteins from moderate halophiles often have a higher content of acidic amino acids than did the comparable proteins from E. coli and other nonhalophiles [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Therefore cytoplasmic proteins of halophiles often reveal high ratios of acidic amino acids, particularly glutamate and aspartate residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>A presence of high ratios of acidic amino acids was also observed in the genome of H. hamelinensis in the present study through codon prediction analyses, suggesting this feature may correlate with its ability to tolerate a high saline environment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Glycine betaine accumulation has been shown to be the major adaptive response to osmotic stress in H. hamelinensis [12] and the presence of several glycine betaine uptake genes were confirmed in the present study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>In addition, other solutes involved in osmoadaptive strategies in this archaeon include trehalose, glutamate, and proline [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Levels of trehalose were found to oscillate depending on the levels of glycine betaine present in the cell [12]; therefore the organism is likely able to synthesize and degrade this sugar depending on the level of other compatible solutes present in the cell and/or microenvironment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The high frequency of abundance displayed for codons that code for proline, glycine, and glutamic acid discovered in the present study in the H. hamelinensis in the genome further supports osmotolerance. H. hamelinensis can potentially use glycine betaine not only as an osmotic stabilizer but also as a carbon and energy source. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>An early study was carried out on a number of haloalkaliphilic isolates from Mono Lake, California, which grew on glycine betaine by sequential demethylation via dimethylglycine to sarcosine, later excreting glycine betaine into the medium [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>At high salinities, glycine betaine catabolism was suppressed and the compound was taken up solely to serve as an osmotic solute, thereby allowing extension of the salt range, enabling growth in 2.5–3.5 M NaCl [12, 43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Another study carried out on the Shark Bay stromatolites reported the synthesis of glycine betaine as a compatible solute in cyanobacteria [44], and it has been suggested that Archaea and cyanobacteria coexist in these systems through aspects of metabolic cooperation involving compatible solutes [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>However further work is needed to clarify the exact role of glycine betaine in H. hamelinensis physiology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Bacteriorhodopsin, halorhodopsin, and bacterioruberin are unique energy transducers involved in energy acquisition [25, 45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>These energy transducers are signature to most halophiles; however there were no homologs to these systems detected here in H. hamelinensis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>This was intriguing, since cultures of this organism display a bright red-pink color [12], characteristic of these pigments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Furthermore earlier studies employing Raman spectroscopy confirmed the presence of bacterioruberin in H. hamelinensis [46], indicating further work is needed to deduce whether genes involved in the synthesis of these pigments are less conserved than expected or are present as genes encoding unknown or hypothetical proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>To further distinguish the H. hamelinensis from other organisms, analyses were conducted here to review the composition and representation of its COG categories. H. hamelinensis COG categories with the largest number of PCGs were surprisingly also the overrepresented COG categories within H. hamelinensis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The overrepresented COG categories consisted of amino acids transport and metabolism, carbohydrate transport and metabolism, and general function prediction only. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>These mostly consisted of PCGs relating to nutrient metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Other overrepresented COG categories were energy production/conversion and inorganic transport and metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>These categories consisted of PCGs of various enzymes such as ATP-synthases, dehydrogenases, and multiple ABC-transporter genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>These COG categories suggest potential adaptation of H. hamelinensis towards high nutrient uptake and synthesis, which would be beneficial as this archaeon is prone to a low nutrient environment [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The secondary metabolites biosynthesis, transport, and catabolism and signal transduction mechanism COG categories were also overrepresented in H. hamelinensis, when compared to other archaeal genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>These categories consisted of putative genes for synthesis of coenzyme A, antibiotics such as novobiocin and streptomycin, and presence of stress response proteins, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>These suggest putative defence mechanism that may be present in H. hamelinensis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>H. hamelinensis is associated witha highly diverse microbial community [7], and this organism displays potentially unique genome characteristics not present in many Archaea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>To test the importance of horizontal gene transfer on H. hamelinensis, various detailed bioinformatics analyses were conducted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Interestingly there was significant similarity between H. hamelinensis and the bacterial lineage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>There was 22.22% similarity between the H. hamelinensis genome and the phyla of Actinobacteria, which consists of many marine bacteria [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Additionally, there was 7.69% similarity between cyanobacteria and H. hamelinensis, which alludes to potential horizontal gene transfer between these organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Of further significance, four putative genes had &gt;30% similarity between H. hamelinensis and dsDNA viruses genomes, elucidating a possible function of viral DNA being involved in gene transfer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Most of the bacterial phyla indicated &lt;1% gene hits with the H. hamelinensis genes; therefore it is difficult to conclude based on this evidence that HGT was prevalent in the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Despite this, the apparent lack of CRISPR-associated genes in H. hamelinensis is consistent with a recent study indicating these predicted genes do not seem to be present in all haloarchaea [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Although it is possible other genes could be encoded for in some of the unknown/hypothetical genes of the H. hamelinensis genome, the apparent lack of these systems suggests this organism may be thus amenable to HGT, a trait which may be of critical importance in its specialized niche in the Shark Bay stromatolites. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>This study reports the detailed genome analyses of H. hamelinensis, a novel archaeon, first isolated from modern stromatolites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Early studies carried out indicated the putative presence of three distinct and unique glycine-betaine transporters BetI, BetII, and BetIII (unpublished data) and the presence of a bacterial-like nucleotide excision repair (NER) system, containing UvrA, UvrB, and UvrC genes, as well as a photolyase [12, 13] in the H. hamelinensis genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Postgenome analysis presented here revealed a range of other potential stress response mechanisms, and Figure 3 summarises some of the key adaptive responses identified through analyses in the current study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>It also highlights the advantages of high-throughput sequencing and comparative genomics to build on pregenome sequencing work. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>In addition to DNA repair mechanisms and osmotic response, there were selective putative genes for heavy metal resistance such as arsenic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>A recent study has suggested there may be a link between salinity and heavy metal uptake in some haloarchaea [50], and further work at the transcript and growth level may help elucidate the importance of these mechanisms in H. hamelinensis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>It is important to note that the genome analyses presented here describe the potential for a given function, and future detailed analyses at the gene and/or protein expression levels are required to definitively attribute the traits delineated in the this investigation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Such studies may ultimately help elucidate the role of this domain of life in these evolutionarily significant ecosystems. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>This work was funded by the Australian Research Council. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec sec-type="conflict"><title>Conflict of Interests</title><p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>1WalterM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>R.BuickR.DunlopJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>R.Stromatolites 3,400–3,500 Myr old from the North Pole area, Western AustraliaNature1980284575544344510.1038/284443a02-s2.0-0000622766 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>2SchopfJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>W.Fossil evidence of Archaean lifePhilosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences2006361147086988510.1098/rstb.2006.18342-s2.0-33747757566 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>3DuprazC.VisscherP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>T.Microbial lithification in marine stromatolites and hypersaline matsTrends in Microbiology200513942943810.1016/j.tim.2005.07.0082-s2.0-2394444370616087339 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>4ReidR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>P.VisscherP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>T.DechoA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>W.The role of microbes in accretion, lamination and early lithification of modern marine stromatolitesNature2000406679998999210.1038/350231582-s2.0-003473901610984051 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>5GohF.AllenM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>A.LeukoS.Determining the specific microbial populations and their spatial distribution within the stromatolite ecosystem of Shark BayThe ISME Journal20093438339610.1038/ismej.2008.1142-s2.0-6334909679319092864 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>6AllenM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>A.GohF.BurnsB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>P.NeilanB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>A.Bacterial, archaeal and eukaryotic diversity of smooth and pustular microbial mat communities in the hypersaline lagoon of Shark BayGeobiology200971829610.1111/j.1472-4669.2008.00187.x2-s2.0-6014908634919200148 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>7BurnsB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>P.GohF.AllenM.NeilanB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>A.Microbial diversity of extant stromatolites in the hypersaline marine environment of Shark Bay, AustraliaEnvironmental Microbiology20046101096110110.1111/j.1462-2920.2004.00651.x2-s2.0-464433542215344935 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>8OrenA.Population dynamics of halobacteria in the Dead Sea water columnLimnology and Oceanography19832861094110310.4319/lo.1983.28.6.10942-s2.0-0020924351 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>9BenllochS.AcinasS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>G.AntónJ.LuzS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>P.Rodríguez-ValeraF.Archaeal biodiversity in crystallizer ponds from a solar saltern: culture versus PCRMicrobial Ecology200141112192-s2.0-003500116111252160 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>10GohF.LeukoS.AllenM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>A. Halococcus hamelinensis sp. nov., a novel halophilic archaeon isolated from stromatolites in Shark Bay, AustraliaInternational Journal of Systematic and Evolutionary Microbiology20065661323132910.1099/ijs.0.64180-02-s2.0-3374529198316738110 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>11GrantW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>D.KamekuraM.McGenityT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>J.VentosaA.BooneD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>R.CastenholzR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>W.GarrityG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>M.The Archaea and the deeply branching and phototrophic BacteriaClass III. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Halobacteria class. nov In Bergey's Manual of Systematic Bacteriology200112ndNew York, NY, USASpringer </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>12GohF.JeonY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>J.BarrowK.NeilanB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>A.BurnsB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>P.Osmoadaptive strategies of the archaeon Halococcus hamelinensis isolated from a hypersaline stromatolite environmentAstrobiology20111165295362-s2.0-7996118511410.1089/ast.2010.059121810017 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>13LeukoS.NeilanB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>A.BurnsB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>P.WalterM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>R.RothschildL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>J.Molecular assessment of UVC radiation-induced DNA damage repair in the stromatolitic halophilic archaeon, Halococcus hamelinensis Journal of Photochemistry and Photobiology B: Biology2011102214014510.1016/j.jphotobiol.2010.10.0022-s2.0-78651440098 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>14LeukoS.GohF.Ibáñez-PeralR.BurnsB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>P.WalterM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>R.NeilanB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>A.Lysis efficiency of standard DNA extraction methods for Halococcus spp. in an organic rich environmentExtremophiles200812230130810.1007/s00792-007-0124-82-s2.0-4034910338318087671 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>15AzizR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>K.BartelsD.BestA.The RAST Server: rapid annotations using subsystems technologyBMC Genomics20089, article 752-s2.0-4054912059610.1186/1471-2164-9-75 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>16MarkowitzV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>M.KorzeniewskiF.PalaniappanK.The integrated microbial genomes (IMG) systemNucleic acids research.200634D344D34810.1093/nar/gkj0242-s2.0-3364487369716381883 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>17DelcherA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>L.BratkeK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>A.PowersE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>C.SalzbergS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>L.Identifying bacterial genes and endosymbiont DNA with GlimmerBioinformatics200723667367910.1093/bioinformatics/btm0092-s2.0-3414713282517237039 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>18LagesenK.HallinP.RødlandE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>A.StærfeldtH.-H.RognesT.UsseryD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>W.RNAmmer: consistent and rapid annotation of ribosomal RNA genesNucleic Acids Research20073593100310810.1093/nar/gkm1602-s2.0-3425066588817452365 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>19LoweT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>M.EddyS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>R.tRNAscan-SE: a program for improved detection of transfer RNA genes in genomic sequenceNucleic Acids Research199725595596410.1093/nar/25.5.9552-s2.0-00308547399023104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>20LarkinM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>A.BlackshieldsG.BrownN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>P.Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0Bioinformatics200723212947294810.1093/bioinformatics/btm4042-s2.0-3644899150017846036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>21TamuraK.DudleyJ.NeiM.KumarS.MEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0Molecular Biology and Evolution20072481596159910.1093/molbev/msm0922-s2.0-3454778175017488738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>22SaundersE.TindallB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>J.FähnrichR.Complete genome sequence of Haloterrigena turkmenica type strain (4kT)Standards in Genomic Sciences20102110711610.4056/sigs.6812722-s2.0-7814941951521304683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>23WitteA.BaranyiU.KleinR.Characterization of Natronobacterium magadii phage ϕCh1, a unique archaeal phage containing DNA and RNAMolecular Microbiology199723360361610.1046/j.1365-2958.1997.d01-1879.x9044293 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>24GutiérrezM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>C.CastilloA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>M.KamekuraM. Halopiger xanaduensis gen. nov., sp. nov., an extremely halophilic archaeon isolated from saline Lake Shangmatala in Inner Mongolia, ChinaInternational Journal of Systematic and Evolutionary Microbiology20075771402140710.1099/ijs.0.65001-02-s2.0-3454750020017625165 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>25OrenA.Molecular ecology of extremely halophilic Archaea and BacteriaFEMS Microbiology Ecology20023911710.1016/s0168-6496(01)00200-82-s2.0-003619226319709178 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>26PapkeR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>T.DouadyC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>J.DoolittleW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>F.Rodríguez-ValeraF.Diversity of bacteriorhodopsins in different hypersaline waters from a single Spanish salternEnvironmental Microbiology20035111039104510.1046/j.1462-2920.2003.00501.x2-s2.0-024267623014641583 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>27BalashovS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>P.ImashevaE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>S.BoichenkoV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>A.AntónJ.WangJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>M.LanyiJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>K.Xanthorhodopsin: a proton pump with a light-harvesting carotenoid antennaScience20053095743206120642-s2.0-2544446305810.1126/science.111804616179480 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>28DeLongE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>F.BéjàO.The light-driven proton pump proteorhodopsin enhances bacterial survival during tough timesPLoS Biology201084e100035910.1371/journal.pbio.10003592-s2.0-77951701764 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>29CopelandA.SpringS.GökerM.Complete genome sequence of Desulfomicrobium baculatum type strain (XT)Standards in Genomic Sciences200911293710.4056/sigs.131342-s2.0-7996073090521304634 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>30JustéA.LievensB.FransI.Genetic and physiological diversity of Tetragenococcus halophilus strains isolated from sugar- and salt-rich environmentsMicrobiology20081549260026102-s2.0-5344910244310.1099/mic.0.2008/018168-018757794 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>31YangJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>C.MadupuR.DurkinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>S.The complete genome of Teredinibacter turnerae T7901: an intracellular endosymbiont of marine wood-boring bivalves (shipworms)PLoS ONE200947e608510.1371/journal.pone.00060852-s2.0-67749097789 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>32VentosaA.NietoJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>J.OrenA.Biology of moderately halophilic aerobic bacteriaMicrobiology and Molecular Biology Reviews19986225045442-s2.0-00318105629618450 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>33LyngbergL.HealyJ.BartlettW.KefF, the regulatory subunit of the potassium efflux system KefC, shows quinone oxidoreductase activityJournal of Bacteriology2011193184925493210.1128/JB.05272-112-s2.0-8005251900621742892 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>34AllersT.MevarechM.Archaeal genetics—the third wayNature Reviews Genetics200561587310.1038/nrg15042-s2.0-10644271631 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>35HorvathP.BarrangouR.CRISPR/Cas, the immune system of bacteria and Archaea Science2010327596216717010.1126/science.11795552-s2.0-7424909551920056882 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>36BurnsB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>P.AnitoriR.ButterworthP.Modern analogues and the early history of microbial lifePrecambrian Research20091731–4101810.1016/j.precamres.2009.05.0062-s2.0-67650759093 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>37MartinD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>D.CiullaR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>A.RobertsM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>F.Osmoadaptation in Archaea Applied and Environmental Microbiology1999655181518252-s2.0-003294757710223964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>38WebberM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>A.PiddockL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>V.The importance of efflux pumps in bacterial antibiotic resistanceJournal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy20035119112-s2.0-003725732110.1093/jac/dkg05012493781 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>39Castañeda-GarcíaA.DoT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>T.BlázquezJ.The K+ uptake regulator trka controls membrane potential, pH homeostasis and multidrug susceptibility in Mycobacterium smegmatis Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy20116671489149810.1093/jac/dkr1652-s2.0-7995885604421613307 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>40SuJ.GongH.LaiJ.MainA.LuS.The potassium transporter Trk and external potassium modulate Salmonella enterica protein secretion and virulenceInfection and Immunity200977266767510.1128/iai.01027-082-s2.0-6054909973219001074 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>41KennedyS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>P.NgW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>V.SalzbergS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>L.HoodL.DasSarmaS.Understanding the adaptation of Halobacterium species NRC-1 to its extreme environment through computational analysis of its genome sequenceGenome Research200111101641165010.1101/gr.1902012-s2.0-003476749111591641 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>42StorzG.Hengge-AronisR.Bacterial Stress Responses2000Washington, DC, USAASM Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>43DiazM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>R.TaylorB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>F.Metabolism of methylated osmolytes by aerobic bacteria from Mono Lake, a moderately hypersaline, alkaline environmentFEMS Microbiology Ecology199619423924710.1016/0168-6496(96)00014-12-s2.0-0029973688 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>44GohF.BarrowK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>D.BurnsB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>P.NeilanB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>A.Identification and regulation of novel compatible solutes from hypersaline stromatolite-associated cyanobacteriaArchives of Microbiology2010192121031103810.1007/s00203-010-0634-02-s2.0-7864932519820936259 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>45KolbeM.BesirH.EssenL.-O.OesterheltD.Structure of the light-driven chloride pump halorhodopsin at 1.8 Å ResolutionScience20002885470139013962-s2.0-003471700710.1126/science.288.5470.139010827943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>46MarshallC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>P.LeukoS.CoyleC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>M.WalterM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>R.BurnsB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>P.NeilanB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>A.Carotenoid analysis of halophilic archaea by resonance Raman spectroscopyAstrobiology20077463164310.1089/ast.2006.00972-s2.0-3484882055217723094 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>47MortonB.The biology and functional morphology of Fragum erugatum (Bivalvia: Cardiidae) from Shark Bay, Western Australia: the significance of its relationship with entrained zooxanthellaeJournal of Zoology20002511395210.1017/s09528369000050692-s2.0-0034194612 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>48FiedlerH.-P.BruntnerC.BullA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>T.Marine actinomycetes as a source of novel secondary metabolitesAntonie van Leeuwenhoek2005871374210.1007/s10482-004-6538-82-s2.0-1474429273115726289 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>49LynchE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>A.LangilleG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>I.DarlingA.Sequencing of seven haloarchael genomes reveals patterns of genomci fluxPlos ONE20127113 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>50PopescuG.DumitruL.Biosorption of some heavy metals from media with high salt concentrations by halophilic Archaea Biotechnology &amp; Biotechnological Equipment201423supplement 179179510.1080/13102818.2009.10818542 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Radial graph displaying the three-letter codon frequency prediction of H. hamelinensis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Expected codon frequencies are indicated in the inner circle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Squares in the outer circle are indications are overrepresented codons. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ARCHAEA2015-241608.001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Radial phylogenetic tree comparison between H. hamelinensis and the bacterial and archaeal lineage within IMG/ER database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Genomes of Archaea, Bacteria, and Eukaryota are displayed clockwise on the circular plot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>The bar charts in between the circular plot and phylogenetic dendrograms are percentage representations of positive hits of genes between H. hamelinensis and respective genomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ARCHAEA2015-241608.002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Schematic representation of some of the putative adaptive traits present in H. hamelinensis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>The traits identified pregenome is indicated on the left, and those elucidated postgenome in the present study are indicated on the right. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ARCHAEA2015-241608.003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>General features of the H. hamelinensis genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>General features </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Number </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Size (bp) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>3133046 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>GC%1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>66.08 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>RNA genes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>48 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain> rRNA genes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>  5 S rRNA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>  16 S rRNA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>  23 S rRNA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain> tRNA genes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>45 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>DNA scaffolds </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>223 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>DNA coding bases </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>2529448 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Protein coding genes (PCG):  </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>3150 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>PCG with known and putative function (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>68.67 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>PCG with enzymes (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>22.39 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>PCG with COGs (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>65.13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>PCG with Pfam (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>65.98 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>PCG with TIGRfam (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>19.48 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>PCG with InterPro (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>87.12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>PCG coding signal peptides (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>10.07 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>PCG coding transmembrane proteins (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>22.48 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>PCG in paralog clusters (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>20.04 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Fused Protein coding genes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>219 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>COG clusters </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>1177 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>KOG clusters </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>635 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Pfam clusters </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>1207 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>TIGRfam clusters </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>539 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>
<sup>1</sup>GC percentage shown as count of G's and C's divided by a total number of G's, C's, A's, and T's. COGs—Clusters of Orthologous Groups of proteins; Pfam—protein family database; TIGRFAMs—resource consisting of curated multiple sequence alignments, Hidden Markov Models for protein sequence classification, and associated information designed to support automated annotation of proteins; KOG—euKaryotic Orthologous Groups.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>Putative osmoadaptive genes identified in H. hamelinensis genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>Gene name </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>Gene ID </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>Probable glycine betaine transporter protein (Bet III) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>2502299791 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>Glycine betaine transporters OpuD </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>2502299823 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>Glycine betaine transporter </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>2502299930 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>ABC-type proline/glycine betaine permease component </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>2502300305 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Glycine betaine ABC transporter, ATP-binding protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>2502300306 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>ABC-type proline/glycine betaine permease component </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>2502300307 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>Probable glycine betaine transport protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>2502301633 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>Potassium uptake protein TrkH </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.1799 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>TrkA system potassium uptake protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>ffig∣332168.3.peg.105 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>Potassiumchannel protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>2502299500 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>Kef-type K+ transport systems </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.334 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>Putative genes coding for heavy metal resistance in H. hamelinensis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>Gene name </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>Gene ID </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>Arsenical pump-driving ATPase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.1469 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>Arsenate reductase (EC 1.20.4.1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.2242 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>Arsenate reductase (EC 1.20.4.1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.3119 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>Arsenical-resistance protein ACR3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.3118 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>DNA gyrase subunit A (EC 5.99.1.3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.722 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>DNA gyrase subunit B (EC 5.99.1.3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.721 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>Aminoglycoside N6′-acetyltransferase (EC 2.3.1.82) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.687 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>Copper-translocating P-type ATPase (EC 3.6.3.4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.2377 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>Copper-translocating P-type ATPase (EC 3.6.3.4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.2190 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>Cobalt-zinc-cadmium resistance protein CzcD </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.2193 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>Cobalt-zinc-cadmium resistance protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.471 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>Permease of the drug/metabolite transporter (DMT) superfamily </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.1282 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>Permease of the drug/metabolite transporter (DMT) superfamily </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.2762 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>Permease of the drug/metabolite transporter (DMT) superfamily </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.2832 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>Permease of the drug/metabolite transporter (DMT) superfamily </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>fig∣332168.3.peg.2837 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
