<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName archivearticle3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ecol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ecol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2045-7758</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ECE3</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Ecology and Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-7758</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5723630</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.3530</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ECE33530</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Genetic implications of bottleneck effects of differing severities on genetic diversity in naturally recovering populations: An example from Hawaiian coot and Hawaiian gallinule </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">SONSTHAGEN et al.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="ece33530-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Sonsthagen</surname><given-names>Sarah A.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6215-5874</contrib-id><address><email>ssonsthagen@usgs.gov</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece33530-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="ece33530-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Robert E.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1800-0183</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece33530-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="ece33530-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Underwood</surname><given-names>Jared G.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8608-190X</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece33530-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="ece33530-aff-0001">
<label><sup>1</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Alaska Science Center</named-content>
<institution>U.S. Geological Survey</institution>
<named-content content-type="city">Anchorage</named-content>
<named-content content-type="country-part">AK</named-content>
<country country="US">USA</country>
</aff><aff id="ece33530-aff-0002">
<label><sup>2</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Pacific Reefs National Wildlife Refuge Complex</named-content>
<institution>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</institution>
<named-content content-type="city">Honolulu</named-content>
<named-content content-type="country-part">HI</named-content>
<country country="US">USA</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence</bold><break/>
Sarah A. Sonsthagen, Alaska Science Center, U.S. Geological Survey, Anchorage, AK, USA.<break/>
Email: <email>ssonsthagen@usgs.gov</email><break/></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>23</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.2017.7.issue-23</issue-id><fpage>9925</fpage><lpage>9934</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">© 2017 The Authors. <italic>Ecology and Evolution</italic> published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</copyright-statement><license license-type="creativeCommonsBy"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="file:ECE3-7-9925.pdf"/><abstract id="ece33530-abs-0001"><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Abstract </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The evolutionary trajectory of populations through time is influenced by the interplay of forces (biological, evolutionary, and anthropogenic) acting on the standing genetic variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>We used microsatellite and mitochondrial loci to examine the influence of population declines, of varying severity, on genetic diversity within two Hawaiian endemic waterbirds, the Hawaiian coot and Hawaiian gallinule, by comparing historical (samples collected in the late 1800s and early 1900s) and modern (collected in 2012–2013) populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Population declines simultaneously experienced by Hawaiian coots and Hawaiian gallinules differentially shaped the evolutionary trajectory of these two populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Within Hawaiian coot, large reductions (between −38.4% and −51.4%) in mitochondrial diversity were observed, although minimal differences were observed in the distribution of allelic and haplotypic frequencies between sampled time periods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Conversely, for Hawaiian gallinule, allelic frequencies were strongly differentiated between time periods, signatures of a genetic bottleneck were detected, and biases in means of the effective population size were observed at microsatellite loci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The strength of the decline appears to have had a greater influence on genetic diversity within Hawaiian gallinule than Hawaiian coot, coincident with the reduction in census size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>These species exhibit similar life history characteristics and generation times; therefore, we hypothesize that differences in behavior and colonization history are likely playing a large role in how allelic and haplotypic frequencies are being shaped through time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, differences in patterns of genetic diversity within Hawaiian coot and Hawaiian gallinule highlight the influence of demographic and evolutionary processes in shaping how species respond genetically to ecological stressors. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="ece33530-kwd-0001">bottleneck</kwd><kwd id="ece33530-kwd-0002">genetic diversity</kwd><kwd id="ece33530-kwd-0003">Hawaiian coot</kwd><kwd id="ece33530-kwd-0004">Hawaiian gallinule</kwd><kwd id="ece33530-kwd-0005">temporal genetic variation</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>Region One Inventory and Monitoring Program</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="7809"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>component-id</meta-name><meta-value>ece33530</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>December 2017</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_NLMPMC version:5.2.8 mode:remove_FC converted:10.12.2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><p content-type="self-citation">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece33530-cit-1001">
<string-name>
<surname>Sonsthagen</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Underwood</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Genetic implications of bottleneck effects of differing severities on genetic diversity in naturally recovering populations: An example from Hawaiian coot and Hawaiian gallinule </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title>. <source>Ecol Evol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>9925</fpage>–<lpage>9934</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/ece3.3530">https://doi.org/10.1002/ece3.3530</ext-link>
</mixed-citation>
</p></notes></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="ece33530-sec-0001"><label>1</label><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Genetic diversity is the basis for which evolutionary forces act upon and ultimately shape the trajectory of variation within populations through time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Standing genetic variation within populations is influenced by a variety of factors: biological characteristics of the species (e.g., dispersal propensity, distribution, mating system, and generation time), human disturbance (e.g., habitat fragmentation, introduced predators, and hunting), and evolutionary forces acting although stochastic (e.g., genetic drift), deterministic (e.g., mutation), and adaptive (e.g., natural selection) processes (Amos &amp; Hardwood, 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The strength at which evolutionary processes influence levels of genetic diversity is dependent, in part, on long‐term effective population sizes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Populations that are small and isolated, for example, may be predisposed to having low genetic diversity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Small populations are more likely to experience severe population fluctuations concomitant with environmental stochasticity (Melbourne &amp; Hastings, 2008) which reduces long‐term effective population sizes and ultimately the accumulation of genetic diversity (Habel &amp; Zachos, 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>None of these processes are the sole driver of change; it is the interaction between evolutionary and biological forces that affect the levels of diversity within populations and species over time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Populations occupying islands are often characterized as having reduced levels of genetic diversity relative to continental counterparts, a pattern often attributed to founder effects associated with island colonization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Among newly founded species, the genetic legacy of the founder effect may still be observed as insufficient time has passed for the species/population to overcome reductions in genetic diversity accompanying the bottleneck postcolonization (Habel &amp; Zachos, 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Many island endemics, however, colonized their respective islands millions of years ago; therefore, a genetic signature of the original founding event is likely not present, and more recent processes (e.g., habitat loss) are driving observed levels of genetic variation (Stuessy, Takayama, López‐Sepúlveda, &amp; Crawford, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Although the pattern of low genetic diversity of populations occupying islands may generally hold, processes (i.e., recent effects or legacy of colonization) promoting this pattern may differ among island taxa (Habel &amp; Zachos, 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The Hawaiian Archipelago is one of the most remote island groups in the world enabling it to function like a semiclosed system prior to human arrival (500 AD); the only vertebrates to colonize it were highly vagile species (birds and bats), and its diverse avifauna can be traced to as few as 20 colonizing species (James, 1991). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Similar to many Oceanic islands, however, many of the endemic species of Hawaii have gone extinct or experienced severe population declines as a result of anthropogenic influences (e.g., habitat loss/modification, introduced predators, invasive species, and disease; Blackburn, Cassey, Duncan, Evans, &amp; Gaston, 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the main Hawaiian Islands have the highest number of threatened, threatened endemic, and critical endemic restricted‐range species of the Pacific Endemic Bird Areas, many of which are likely close to extinction (BirdLife International, 2016a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Because islands were likely founded by just a few individuals, due to the remoteness of the archipelago, populations may generally harbor low levels of genetic diversity relative to mainland congeners (even prior to recent declines); this would be especially true for species that are recent colonizers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Potentially low levels of genetic diversity coupled with small population sizes may make Hawaiian endemics more susceptible to deleterious effects of environmental and demographic fluctuations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is important to determine standing levels of genetic variation within species that occupy the Hawaiian Islands to evaluate the impact of the population declines on genetic diversity as well as to gain insight into the ability of Hawaiian endemics to respond to stochastic processes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The Hawaiian coot (Fulica alai) and Hawaiian gallinule (Gallinula galeata sandvicensis) are endangered waterbirds endemic to the Hawaiian Archipelago (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Both species experienced severe population declines in the early 1900s attributed to wetland loss and modification, introduced plants and predators, disease, and altered hydrology (U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Fish and Wildlife Service, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Prior to the 1900s, both species were common and distributed across the main Hawaiian Islands (U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Fish and Wildlife Service, 2011), although no estimates (pre‐1900s) of population size are available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Surveys conducted in the 1950–1960s determined that census numbers were reduced to &lt;1,000 (Hawaiian coot) and ~60 (Hawaiian gallinule) individuals throughout Hawaii (U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Fish and Wildlife Service, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Populations started to increase in the late 1970s, likely attributable to the increase in aquaculture and the protection of wetland areas, including the establishment of several national refuges in Hawaii (U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Fish and Wildlife Service, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The current census population size for the Hawaiian coot is 1,777 ± 310 individuals (Underwood, Silbernagle, Nishimoto, &amp; Uyehara, 2013), and it occupies its historical range. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The Hawaiian gallinule's current distribution is restricted to the islands of Oahu and Kauai, and recent surveys recorded low numbers (~400 individuals range wide), although numbers are likely underestimated as Hawaiian gallinules are secretive (Underwood et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece33530-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Hawaiian coot (left; Fulica alai) and Hawaiian gallinule (right; Gallinula galeata sandvicensis) in James Campbell National Wildlife Refuge, Oahu, Hawaii, USA . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Photo credits: Sarah Sonsthagen (USGS) and Robert Wilson (USGS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-7-9925-g001"/></fig><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Hawaiian coot and Hawaiian gallinule are hypothesized to be relatively recent colonizers to the archipelago (Fleischer &amp; McIntosh, 2001); however, based on fossil evidence, the Hawaiian coot may have occupied the islands for a longer duration than the gallinule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>A Fulica sp. fossil was discovered at Ulupau Head, Oahu, a formation dated to 120,000 years before present (James, 1987), and on Kauai, F. alai bones were identified from stratigraphic units dating up to 6,760 years before present (Burney et al., 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Conversely, Gallinula chloropus (now G. galeata) bones have only been found in deposits postdating human colonization (~1,500 years before present; Barber's Point, Oahu; James, 1987), although the absence of detection does not necessarily equate to lack of presence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Many factors influence the maintenance and recovery of genetic diversity as species go through population declines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Therefore, some species within an area may be more adversely affected, while others may be more resilient in retaining genetic diversity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Here, we examine the influence of a population decline on genetic diversity simultaneously experienced by two species, the Hawaiian coot and the Hawaiian gallinule, using microsatellite genotype and mitochondrial sequence data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Specifically, we aim to examine how these species have responded genetically to recent ecological stressors (e.g., habitat loss, predation, disease). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Although these two species share many life history traits, a few potentially influential demographic differences exist, such as severity of decline, effective population sizes predecline, dispersal propensity, and longevity (Bannor &amp; Kiviat, 2002; Pratt &amp; Brisbin, 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Along with providing insights into the conservation genetics of Hawaiian waterbirds, the results of this study can inform conservation planning and management strategies, especially because both species are designated as “conservation reliant,” such that they will require active management into perpetuity (Underwood et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="ece33530-sec-0002"><label>2</label><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="ece33530-sec-0003"><label>2.1</label><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Specimens of Hawaiian coot (n = 14) and Hawaiian gallinule (n = 23) collected between 1893 and 1939 from Oahu, Hawaii, were obtained through museum tissue loans (Appendix 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>These samples represent the historical time period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Hawaiian coot (n = 34) and Hawaiian gallinule (n = 29) were trapped on James Campbell National Wildlife Refuge, Oahu, Hawaii, from 2012 to 2013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>These samples represent the modern time period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Blood samples were collected from the brachial vein and stored in preservation buffer (Longmire et al., 1988). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Hereafter, we will refer to each sampled temporal time period as a unique “population.” </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="ece33530-sec-0004"><label>2.2</label><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Laboratory techniques </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>DNA from historical samples was extracted using a phenol–chloroform protocol and recovered with a Microcon centrifugal filter (Millipore, Massachusetts). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA from contemporary samples was extracted using a “salting out” procedure described by Medrano, Aasen, and Sharrow (1990). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA concentrations were quantified using fluorometry and diluted to 50 ng/ml working solutions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Genotype data were collected at 13 loci for Hawaiian coot (Fal02, Fal04, Fal08, Fal10, Fal12, Fal14, Fal16, Fal19, Gch03, Gch07, Gch12, Gch14, Sonsthagen, Wilson, &amp; Underwood, 2014; and KiRa10, Brackett, Maley, Brumfield, &amp; McRae, 2013) and 10 loci for Hawaiian gallinule (Fal08, Fal10, Fal12, Fal14, Fal19, Gch06, Gch12, Gch13, Gch17, and Gch19, Sonsthagen et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) amplifications and thermocycler conditions followed Talbot et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>(2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>DNA extractions and PCR reactions for museum specimens were performed in a designated low‐copy laboratory to reduce the possibility of contamination from modern samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>DNA extractions and PCR reactions contained sample blanks, which were included through the data collection process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Sample blanks did not yield any product. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Because DNA extracted from museum specimens may be of low quality and quantity resulting in genotyping errors (i.e., allelic dropout, and null alleles), all DNA samples from museum specimens were amplified in duplicate at all microsatellite loci, and individuals that were homozygous at loci were amplified in triplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>In addition, 10% of the samples from James Campbell National Wildlife Refuge were extracted, amplified, and genotyped in duplicate for quality control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>No inconsistencies in genotype scores were observed between replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Microsatellite genotype data are accessioned at the USGS Alaska Science Center data repository ( <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5066/f74q7sxc">https://doi.org/10.5066/f74q7sxc</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Hawaiian coot and Hawaiian gallinule individuals were sequenced at two mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) loci: We amplified a 824 base pair (bp) and 826 bp fragment, respectively, of control region using primer pairs CR200L (5′‐TTCATGCATGCTTTAGGG‐3′) and CR1029H (5′‐CACCAATTTCCAGRAGTCC‐3′) as well as a 752 bp and 753 bp fragment, respectively, of NADH dehydrogenase (ND) two with primer pairs ND2_224L (5′‐CTMCTACTATTCTCCAGCAC‐3′) and ND2_1003H (5′‐GGGTGATAAGGGTAGGAG‐3′). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Smaller fragments of mtDNA were amplified for the historical samples using primer pairs CR200L and CR343H (5′‐GTGGRGGRGTATATTCGTG‐3′) for control region resulting in a 140 bp and 141 bp fragments in Hawaiian coot and Hawaiian gallinule, respectively, and ND2 primer pairs ND2_464L (5′‐GCCATCCTCTCAGCWGCC‐3′) and ND2_720H (5′‐GCCTGCTAGGGAKAG‐3′) resulting in a 172 bp fragment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>PCR amplifications, cycle‐sequencing protocols, and postsequencing processing followed Sonsthagen, Talbot, and McCracken (2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>For quality control purposes, we extracted, amplified, and sequenced 10% of the samples in duplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Data generated during this study are available at doi.org/10.5066/F74Q7SXC, and sequences are accessioned in GenBank (&gt;200 bp; <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MF673896">MF673896</ext-link>–<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MF673904">MF673904</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="ece33530-sec-0005"><label>2.3</label><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Analysis of genetic diversity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>We calculated allelic richness, observed and expected heterozygosities, Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium (HWE), and linkage disequilibrium at the microsatellite loci in FSTAT version 2.9.3 (Goudet, 1995). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Tests for null alleles and allelic dropout were implemented in MicroChecker (Van Oosterhout, Hutchinson, Wills, &amp; Shipley, 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>MtDNA sequences were trimmed to the same fragment length between historical and modern samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Haplotype (h) and nucleotide (π) diversity were calculated at mtDNA loci in ARLEQUIN version 2.0 (Schneider, Roessli, &amp; Excoffier, 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Fu's FS (Fu, 1997) and Tajima's D (Tajima, 1989) were calculated to test the hypothesis of selective neutrality for mtDNA loci and implemented in ARLEQUIN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>We applied critical significance values of 5%, which requires a p‐value of below .02 for Fu's FS (Fu, 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>An unrooted haplotype network for mtDNA loci was constructed in NETWORK version 4.613 (Fluxus Technology Ltd., 2015) using the reduced median method (Bandelt, Forster, Sykes, &amp; Richards, 1995), to illustrate possible reticulations in the gene tree because of homoplasy or recombination. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="ece33530-sec-0006"><label>2.4</label><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Analysis of genetic structure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The degree of population genetic structure within Hawaiian coot and Hawaiian gallinule sampled pre‐ and postdecline was assessed by calculating F ST and ΦST for microsatellite and sequence data, respectively, in ARLEQUIN, adjusting for multiple comparisons using Bonferroni correction (α = 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Tamura–Nei nucleotide substitution model (Tamura &amp; Nei, 1993) was used to calculate ΦST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Because samples were assayed over temporal scales and sizes varied among populations, population differentiation based on χ2 distributions of alleles and haplotypes was also determined using GENEPOP 3.1 (Raymond &amp; Rousett, 1995). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>We used the Bayesian clustering program, STRUCTURE 2.3.2 (Hubisz, Falush, Stephens, &amp; Pritchard, 2009; Pritchard, Stephens, &amp; Donnelly, 2000), to assign individuals to clusters based on their microsatellite allelic frequencies and infer the occurrence of genetic structure without a priori knowledge of putative temporal period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Data were analyzed using an admixture model assuming correlated frequencies and sample location information as a prior with a 50,000 burn‐in period, 500,000 Markov chain Monte Carlo iterations, and number of possible populations (K) ranging from one to five; the analysis was repeated 10 times to ensure consistency across runs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>We followed the method of Evanno, Regnaut, and Goudet (2005) to determine the most likely number of clusters given the data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="ece33530-sec-0007"><label>2.5</label><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Analysis of effective population size </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Contemporary effective population size (Ne) was estimated with NeESTIMATOR v2 (Do et al., 2014), using the linkage disequilibrium‐based and the molecular coancestry methods based on the microsatellite data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Molecular coancestry method examines the level of allele sharing among individuals; conversely, the linkage disequilibrium method tests for nonrandom associations formed among alleles at different loci that occur when Ne is low and genetic drift influences allelic frequencies (Luikart, Ryman, Tallmon, Schwartz, &amp; Allendorf, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Microsatellite data were analyzed using the random‐mating model, with 95% confidence limits determined by jackknifing over loci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>We evaluated the effects of low‐frequency alleles on Ne estimates by excluding rare alleles (Pcrit). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Variance in Ne estimates across a range of Pcrit values is suggestive of a history of gene flow and/or the presence of first‐generation dispersers, whereas stable Ne estimates across a range of Pcrit values are indicative of isolated populations (Waples &amp; England, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>We estimated Ne with Pcrit values for lowest allele frequency observed ranging from 0.02 and 0.10 and without a frequency restriction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="ece33530-sec-0008"><label>2.6</label><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Analysis of population demography </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Evidence for fluctuations in historical population demography was evaluated using BOTTLENECK 1.2.02 (Cornuet &amp; Luikart, 1996; Piry, Luikart, &amp; Cornuet, 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Fluctuations in population size inferred from microsatellite data were assessed using a Wilcoxon sign‐rank test using 5,000 permutations under three models: infinite allele model (IAM), stepwise mutation model (SMM), and two‐phased model of mutation (TPM; parameters: 70% SMM, variance 9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Heterozygote deficiency relative to the number of alleles indicates recent population growth, whereas heterozygote excess indicates a recent population bottleneck (Cornuet &amp; Luikart, 1996). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>It is important to note that BOTTLENECK compares heterozygote deficiency and excess relative to genetic diversity, not to HWE expectation (Cornuet &amp; Luikart, 1996). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Results were adjusted for multiple comparison using Bonferroni correction (α = 0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="ece33530-sec-0009"><label>3</label><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="ece33530-sec-0010"><label>3.1</label><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Genetic diversity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Null alleles and allelic dropout were not detected for any loci assayed for historical and contemporary Hawaiian gallinule populations and contemporary Hawaiian coot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Within the Hawaiian coot historical population, three loci (Fal10, Gch12, and KiRa10) had evidence of null alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Reamplification of these loci yielded consistent genotypes, and all loci and populations were in HWE and linkage equilibrium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we retained all loci in subsequent analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Indices of genetic diversity based on microsatellite loci were similar between time periods for both species (95% confidence limits overlapped), although fewer private alleles were observed within the contemporary Hawaiian gallinule (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="ece33530-tbl-0001" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Indices of genetic diversity along with the percent change for Hawaiian coot and Hawaiian gallinule on Oahu, Hawaii, sampled at two timescales </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Hawaiian coot </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Hawaiian gallinule </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Historical </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Contemporary </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>% change </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Historical </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Contemporary </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>% change </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Microsatellites </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>No. alleles </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>4.9 (1.9) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>5.0 (1.7) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>2.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>2.6 (1.6) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>2.3 (0.5) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>−11.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Allelic richness </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>4.6 (1.5) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>4.1 (1.1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>−10.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>2.6 (1.5) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>2.3 (0.4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>−11.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Private alleles </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>16 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>0.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>−75.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Ho </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>55.9 (3.9) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>58.9 (2.3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>5.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>42.2 (3.4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>41.0 (2.9) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>−2.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>He </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>64.9 (4.3) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>61.7 (3.2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>−4.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>40.4 (6.9) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>41.9 (3.7) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>3.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Ne </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>19.5 (0.5–71.8) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>19.0 (3.1–48.6) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>∞ (∞–∞) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>5.3 (1.8–10.5) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>n </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>34 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>23 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>29 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>mtDNA control region </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>No. haplotypes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>−40.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>−50.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Private haplotypes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>h </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>0.788 (0.089) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>0.383 (0.098) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>−51.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>0.100 (0.088) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>π </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>0.0146 (0.0099) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>0.0090 (0.0065) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>−38.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>0.0007 (0.0014) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Fu's Fs </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>−0.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>2.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>−0.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Tajima's D </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>1.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>0.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>−1.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>n </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>31 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>27 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>mtDNA ND2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>No. haplotypes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>0.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>0.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Private haplotypes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>h </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>0.400 (0.237) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>0.220 (0.087) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>−45.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>0.706 (0.042) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>0.689 (0.028) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>−2.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>π </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>0.0047 (0.0047) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>0.0026 (0.0026) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>−44.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>0.0055 (0.0044) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>0.0053 (0.0042) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>−3.6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Fu's Fs </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>1.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>1.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>0.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>1.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Tajima's D </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>−1.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>−0.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>1.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>1.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>n </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>33 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>17 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>26 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>— </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ece33530-note-0002"><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Descriptive statistics include the mean number of alleles and haplotypes, allelic richness, number of private alleles and haplotypes, observed and expected heterozygosity (Ho/He), effective population size (Ne) based on the molecular coancestry method, haplotype (h) and nucleotide diversity (π), Fu's Fs, Tajima's D, and sample size (n) based on 13 and 10 microsatellite loci, 140 bp of mtDNA control region, and 172 bp of mtDNA ND2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Single standard deviation is in parentheses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Within the mtDNA control region sequences, five haplotypes characterized by four variable sites were observed for Hawaiian coot, and two haplotypes characterized by a single variable site were observed for Hawaiian gallinule (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Greater variation at ND2 was observed for Hawaiian gallinule; three haplotypes were characterized by two variable sites, whereas only two haplotypes were observed within Hawaiian coot (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>All haplotypes were retained when sequences were trimmed to a common length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>A reduction in genetic diversity was observed at mtDNA for both species, although differences in indices of genetic diversity are greater for Hawaiian coot than Hawaiian gallinule (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Fewer haplotypes were observed within the mtDNA control region for the contemporary populations of Hawaiian coot and Hawaiian gallinule; further haplotype and nucleotide diversity were lower in the contemporary populations (Table 1); however, one of the two haplotypes observed in Hawaiian gallinule historical population was only found in a single individual (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Indices of genetic diversity appear similar between timescales for Hawaiian gallinule based on ND2, although similar reductions in variation were observed for Hawaiian coot (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Tests of selective neutrality were not significant (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece33530-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Parsimony networks illustrating relationships of mtDNA control region (a and c) and ND2 (b and d) haplotypes in Hawaiian coot and Hawaiian gallinule sampled at historical (white) and contemporary (black) timescales. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>The size of the circle node corresponds to the frequency of each haplotype </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="ECE3-7-9925-g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="ece33530-sec-0011"><label>3.2</label><title><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Genetic structure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Patterns of temporal variation at allelic and haplotypic frequencies varied between species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>A strong signature of genetic structure was observed within Hawaiian gallinule as frequency differences among microsatellite loci were detected across all three metrics (F ST, R ST, and χ2; Table 2) and was also uncovered in STRUCTURE (K = 2, ΔK = 162.4, r = .44; Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Conversely, only a weak signature of genetic structure was detected in Hawaiian coot based on microsatellite data; differences in allelic distributions (χ2) were observed; however, no structure was detected based on F ST and R ST (Table 2) nor was genetic partitioning uncovered in STRUCTURE (K = 1, LnP|K = −1548.9; K = 2, LnP|K = −1567.5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Frequency differences were detected in mtDNA control region haplotypic data based on F ST and χ2 distributions between historical and contemporary Hawaiian coot populations (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>No differences were observed at mtDNA control region within Hawaiian gallinule between time periods, as only two haplotypes were observed and one haplotype represented by a single individual (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="ece33530-tbl-0002" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Estimates of genetic differentiation (F ST, R ST, χ2, and ΦST) calculated from 13 and 10 microsatellite loci, respectively, 140 bp of mtDNA control region, and 172 bp of mtDNA ND2 between Hawaiian coot and Hawaiian gallinule sampled at two time periods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Significant comparisons (α = 0.05) are in bold text and marked with an asterisk </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Microsatellites </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>mtDNA control region </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>mtDNA ND2 </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>F ST </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>R ST </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>χ2 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>F ST </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>ΦST </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>χ2 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>F ST </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>ΦST </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>χ2 </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Hawaiian coot </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>0.014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>−0.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>68.7* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>0.095* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>0.096 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>11.3* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>−0.098 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>−0.098 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>1.0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Hawaiian gallinule </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>0.182* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>0.073* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>∞* </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>0.015 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>0.015 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>3.6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>−0.050 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>−0.050 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>0.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></SecTag><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece33530-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Average membership coefficient of Hawaiian gallinule individuals from sampled time periods into each of the two clusters inferred from ten microsatellite loci in STRUCTURE (Pritchard et al., 2000) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="ECE3-7-9925-g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="ece33530-sec-0012"><label>3.3</label><title><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Effective population size </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Genetic signatures of a reduction in Ne were not observed in either Hawaiian coot or Hawaiian gallinule based on the linkage disequilibrium method, as 95% confidence limits overlapped between sampling periods and the upper bound was infinity (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Variation in Ne estimates across Pcrit values was observed for contemporary Hawaiian coot individuals, indicative of past gene flow affecting Ne estimates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>In contrast, Ne estimates were similar across Pcrit values in Hawaiian gallinule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>While Ne estimates based on the molecular coancestry method overlapped for both Hawaiian coot and Hawaiian gallinule, the contemporary Hawaiian gallinule estimates were considerably smaller with narrow confidence intervals (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece33530-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Effective population size (Ne) estimates as a function of excluding of rare alleles (Pcrit) in Hawaiian coot and Hawaiian gallinule sampled at historical (shown in gray) and contemporary (shown in black) timescales, implemented in NeESTIMATOR v2 (Do et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>The solid line represents point estimates of Ne, and dash lines are associated lower 5% confidence limits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Upper 95% confidence limits and Ne for historical Hawaiian coot are ∞ for all estimates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Values of point estimates that exceed the range of the y‐axis are noted on the graph </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="ECE3-7-9925-g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="ece33530-sec-0013"><label>3.4</label><title><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Population demography </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Fluctuations in population demography were observed within the contemporary Hawaiian gallinule timeframe; significant heterozygote excess was detected at all mutation models (IAM, SMM, and TPM; p &lt; .001) suggestive of population decline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>The other timeframes were in mutation drift equilibrium. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="ece33530-sec-0014"><label>4</label><title><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>The evolutionary trajectories of the Hawaiian coot and Hawaiian gallinule were differentially shaped by the population declines of the early 1900s. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Within Hawaiian coots, large reductions (between −38.4% and −51.4%; Table 1) in mitochondrial diversity were observed, although minimal differences (χ2 = 68.7, p &lt; .001; F ST and R ST, p &gt; .05; Table 2) were observed in the distribution of allelic and haplotypic frequencies across timescales. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Conversely, for Hawaiian gallinules, allelic frequencies were strongly differentiated between time periods, signatures of a genetic bottleneck were detected, and biases in the means of the effective population size were observed at microsatellite loci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Researchers have invoked several hypotheses for the lack of observed temporal shifts in genetic diversity within species that have experienced declines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Generally, when reductions in genetic diversity are observed, those populations are often reduced to just a few individuals (e.g., Bouzat, Lewin, &amp; Paige, 1998; Groombridge, Jones, Bruford, &amp; Nichols, 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>However, long‐lived species can reduce the effective time spent experiencing a bottleneck thus enabling the retention of genetic diversity over short timescales (e.g., Hailer et al., 2006; Johnson, Gilbert, Virani, Asim, &amp; Mindell, 2008; White et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>It is important to note, our ability to detect a recent bottleneck is dependent on the level of genetic diversity pre‐ and postdecline as ancient reductions in genetic diversity may mask recent declines (e.g., Dussex, Rawlence, &amp; Robertson, 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>While the strength of the decline appears to be greater within Hawaiian gallinule than Hawaiian coot, coincident with the reduction in census size, these species exhibit similar life history characteristics and generation times (7 and 6 years, respectively; BirdLife International 2016b,c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we hypothesize that differences in behavior and colonization history are likely playing a large role in how allelic and haplotypic frequencies within these species are being shaped through time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Hawaiian coots and Hawaiian gallinules are capable of dispersing long distances, as evidenced by their successful colonization of the Hawaiian Archipelago. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Postcolonization, however, dispersal propensity appears to have changed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Current behavior for the Hawaiian gallinule is described as highly sedentary (Bannor &amp; Kiviat, 2002; JGU unpublished data), whereas mark/resight data for Hawaiian coot suggest there is some interisland movement (JGU unpublished data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>It is difficult to distinguish whether changes in dispersal behavior are an artifact of colonization or recent anthropogenic‐caused declines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Regardless, reduction in gene flow among remnant patches will lead to loss of genetic diversity through drift, as drift is inversely related to the effective population size (1/2Ne; Frankham, Ballou, &amp; Briscoe, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Movement of individuals among islands may provide an avenue for dispersal and in turn greater retention of genetic diversity through increased effective population size thereby reducing the effects of drift (Frankham et al., 2010; Jangjoo, Matter, Roland, &amp; Keyghobadi, 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Within the more sedentary Hawaiian gallinule, population recovery was likely the result of recruitment within remnant wetland patches, and therefore, the survivors of the decline changed the trajectory of neutral genetic variation as evidenced by significant structuring (Table 2, Figure 3) and reduction of Ne between sample periods (based on molecular coancestry; Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>The Hawaiian gallinule remains extirpated from islands in its former range in Hawaii, further supporting the hypothesis that dispersal remains restricted and recovery likely occurred through recruitment within patches rather than immigration among patches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Conversely, within Hawaiian coot, recovery was likely the result of recruitment within and dispersal among wetlands, which is supported by fluctuations in Ne estimates across Pcrit values (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Assuming interisland movement resulted in gene flow, immigration among islands likely counteracted the effects of genetic drift and homogenized neutral genetic variation while maintaining the predecline level genetic diversity through the demographic bottleneck (e.g., Jangjoo et al., 2016; Keller et al., 2001; McEachern, Van Vuren, Floyd, May, &amp; Eadie, 2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Levels of genetic diversity observed for Hawaiian gallinule are, at least in part, a legacy of the initial colonization event. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Across all measures of genetic diversity, Hawaiian coot is more diverse than the Hawaiian gallinule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>As noted earlier, both species are presumed to be recent colonizers to the Hawaiian Islands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>The presence of fossils for Hawaiian coot and lack of remains of Hawaiian gallinule in older deposits (&lt;1,500 years before present) provide anecdotal evidence that Hawaiian coot has occupied the Hawaiian Archipelago for a longer duration and therefore has had more time to overcome the initial reduction in genetic diversity in the wake of colonization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Among the same 48 microsatellite loci screened for variability, genetic diversity is ~48% less within Hawaiian gallinule (1.44 alleles/locus, 1–3 alleles observed, 31 loci monomorphic) than Hawaiian coot (2.75 alleles/locus, 1–7 alleles observed, 15 monomorphic, based on 10 individuals; Sonsthagen et al., 2014; SAS unpublished data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Ancient reductions in genetic diversity have been postulated to limit the signature of recent population declines (e.g., Dussex et al., 2015; Taylor &amp; Jamieson, 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Given that genetic diversity was likely already low prior to decline for Hawaiian gallinule, the observation of genetic structuring between sample time periods is even more noteworthy because genetic drift had little variation on which to act indicating that the individuals that survived the bottleneck had a strong influence on the evolutionary trajectory of the Oahu population. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>This study highlights the importance of species behavior and past evolutionary forces in shaping how species respond genetically to ecological stressors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Factors and time frame leading to the population decline were similar for the Hawaiian coot and Hawaiian gallinule: reduction in coastal wetlands, nonnative mammalian predators and plants, avian disease, and altered hydrology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Both were historically abundant with severe reductions in census size (&lt;1,000 Hawaiian coot and ~60 Hawaiian gallinule in the mid‐1900s) and have similar life history characteristics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, because these species cooccur where their distributions overlap, management strategies were implemented to conserve these species simultaneously. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Yet despite these similarities, allelic frequencies differed markedly pre‐ and postdecline within Hawaiian gallinule, and only minimal differences were observed within Hawaiian coot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>These findings illustrate the importance of considering how demographic (e.g., dispersal) and evolutionary processes (e.g., bottleneck effects) influence population recovery when planning and implementing conservation programs, especially for endemic species that likely harbor reduced levels of genetic variation relative to their mainland counterparts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>In light of these results, Hawaiian gallinule may be at increased risk of genetic endangerment relative to its ecological equivalent, the Hawaiian coot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Although indices of genetic diversity are not reduced (confidence intervals overlap), allelic frequencies have changed indicating genetic drift is strongly influencing genetic variation within the Hawaiian gallinule on Oahu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Continued persistence in isolation, coupled with low genetic diversity, could result in the continued reduction of genetic diversity through genetic drift making the Hawaiian gallinule more vulnerable to stochastic processes and ultimately extirpation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec id="ece33530-sec-0016"><title><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>All authors were involved with the concept and design; JGU collected the genetic samples; REW and SAS collected the genetic data and conducted the analyses; all authors were involved in interpretation of the results; SAS led the writing; and all authors were involved in the writing process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>All authors approved of the final draft of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec id="ece33530-sec-0017"><title><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>None declared. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack id="ece33530-sec-0015"><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>We thank J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Browning (USFWS), A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Nadig (USFWS), F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Healy (USFWS), and all other volunteers who helped us to capture birds as well as G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Sage (USGS) for laboratory support. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>The manuscript was improved by comments from T.L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Tibbitts and A.G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Vandergast (USGS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Funding was provided by U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Fish and Wildlife Service, Region One Inventory and Monitoring Program, and U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>The findings and conclusions in this article are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the views of the U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Fish and Wildlife Service. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Government. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="ece33530-bibl-0001"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ece33530-bib-0001"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>  Amos, W. , &amp;  Hardwood, J.  (1998). Factors affecting levels of genetic diversity in natural populations. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London Series B, 353, 177–186.9533122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0002"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>  Bandelt, H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>J. ,  Forster, P. ,  Sykes, B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>C. , &amp;  Richards, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>B.  (1995). Mitochondrial portraits of human populations. Genetics, 141, 743–753.8647407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0003"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>  Bannor, B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>K. , &amp;  Kiviat, E.  (2002). Common Gallinule (Gallinula galeata), The Birds of North America (P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Rodewald, Ed.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Ithaca: Cornell Lab of Ornithology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Retrieved from the Birds of North America: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://birdsna.org/Species-Account/bna/species/comgal1">https://birdsna.org/Species-Account/bna/species/comgal1</ext-link> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2173/bna.685">https://doi.org/10.2173/bna.685</ext-link>  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0004"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain> BirdLife International . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>(2016a). Endemic Bird Area factsheet: Central Hawaiian Islands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.birdlife.org">http://www.birdlife.org</ext-link>  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0005"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain> BirdLife International . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>(2016b). Fulica alai. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species 2016: e.T22692920A93374177. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2305/iucn.uk.2016-3.rlts.t22692920a93374177.en">https://doi.org/10.2305/iucn.uk.2016-3.rlts.t22692920a93374177.en</ext-link>  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0006"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain> BirdLife International . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>(2016c). Gallinula galeata. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species 2016: e.T62120280A95189182. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2305/iucn.uk.2016-3.rlts.t62120280a95189182.en">https://doi.org/10.2305/iucn.uk.2016-3.rlts.t62120280a95189182.en</ext-link>  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0007"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>  Blackburn, T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>M. ,  Cassey, P. ,  Duncan, R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>P. ,  Evans, K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>L. , &amp;  Gaston, K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>J.  (2004). Avian extinction and mammalian introductions on Oceanic islands. Science, 305, 1955–1958.15448269 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0008"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>  Bouzat, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>L. ,  Lewin, H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>A. , &amp;  Paige, K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>N.  (1998). The ghost of genetic diversity past: Historical DNA analysis of the greater prairie chicken. American Naturalist, 152, 1–6. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0009"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>  Brackett, C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>L. ,  Maley, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>M. ,  Brumfield, R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>T. , &amp;  McRae, S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>B.  (2013). Characterization of microsatellite loci for a threatened species, the King Rail, Rallus elegans, using a next‐generation sequencing protocol. Conservation Genetics Resources, 5, 1189–1191. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0010"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>  Burney, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>A. ,  James, H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>F. ,  Pigott Burney, L. ,  Olson, S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>L. ,  Kikuchi, W. ,  Wagner, W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>L. , …  Nishek, R.  (2001). Fossil evidence for a diverse biota from Kaua'i and its transformation since human arrival. Ecological Monographs, 71, 615–641. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0011"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>  Cornuet, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>M. , &amp;  Luikart, G.  (1996). Description and power analysis of two tests for detecting recent population bottlenecks from allele frequency data. Genetics, 144, 2001–2014.8978083 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0012"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>  Do, C. ,  Waples, R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>S. ,  Peel, D. ,  Macbeth, G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>M. ,  Tillett, B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>J. , &amp;  Ovenden, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>R.  (2014). NeEstimator v2: Re‐implementation of software for the estimation of contemporary effective population size (Ne) from genetic data. Molecular Ecology Resources, 14, 209–214.23992227 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0013"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>  Dussex, N. ,  Rawlence, N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>J. , &amp;  Robertson, B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>C.  (2015). Ancient and contemporary DNA reveal a pre‐human decline but no population bottleneck associated with recent human persecution in the Kea (Nestor notabilis). PLoS ONE, 1092, e0118522. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0014"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>  Evanno, G. ,  Regnaut, S. , &amp;  Goudet, J.  (2005). Detecting the number of clusters of individuals using the software STRUCTURE: A simulation study. Molecular Ecology, 14, 2611–2620.15969739 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0015"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>  Fleischer, R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>C. , &amp;  McIntosh, C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>E.  (2001). Molecular systematics and biogeography of the Hawaiian avifauna. Studies in Avian Biology, 22, 51–60. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0016"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain> Fluxus Technology Ltd . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>(2015). NETWORK 4.6.1.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fluxus">www.fluxus</ext-link>‐engineering.com </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0017"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>  Frankham, R. ,  Ballou, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>D. , &amp;  Briscoe, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>A.  (2010). Introduction to conservation genetics, 2nd ed. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0018"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>  Fu, Y. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>X.  (1997). Statistical tests of neutrality of mutations against population growth, hitchhiking and background selections. Genetics, 147, 915–925.9335623 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0019"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>  Goudet, J.  (1995). FSTAT (vers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>1.2): A computer program to calculate F‐statistics. Journal of Heredity, 86, 485–486. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0020"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>  Groombridge, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>J. ,  Jones, G. ,  Bruford, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>W. , &amp;  Nichols, R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>A.  (2000). Conservation biology – ‘Ghost’ alleles of the Mauritius kestrel. Nature, 403, 616.10688188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0021"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>  Habel, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>N. , &amp;  Zachos, F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>E.  (2013). Past population history versus recent population decline – Founder effects in island species and their genetic signatures. Journal of Biogeography, 40, 206–207. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0022"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>  Hailer, F. ,  Helander, B. ,  Folkestad, A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>O. ,  Ganusevich, S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>A. ,  Garstad, S. ,  Hauff, P. , …  Ellegren, H.  (2006). Bottlenecked but long‐lived: High genetic diversity retained in white‐tailed eagles upon recovery from population decline. Biology Letters, 2, 316–319.17148392 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0023"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>  Hubisz, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>A. ,  Falush, D. ,  Stephens, M. , &amp;  Pritchard, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>K.  (2009). Inferring weak population structure with the assistance of sample group information. Molecular Ecology Resources, 9, 1322–1332.21564903 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0024"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>  James, H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>F.  (1987). A late Pleistocene avifauna from the island of Oahu, Hawaiian Islands. Documents des Laboratoires de Geologie de Lyon, 99, 221–230. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0025"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>  James, H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>F.  (1991). The contribution of fossils to knowledge of Hawaiian birds. Acta XX Congressus Internationalis Ornithologici, 1, 420–424. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0026"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>  Jangjoo, M. ,  Matter, S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>F. ,  Roland, J. , &amp;  Keyghobadi, N.  (2016). Connectivity rescues genetic diversity after a demographic bottleneck in a butterfly population network. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 113, 10914–10919.27621433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0027"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>  Johnson, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>A. ,  Gilbert, M. ,  Virani, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>Z. ,  Asim, M. , &amp;  Mindell, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>P.  (2008). Temporal genetic analysis of the critically endangered oriental white‐backed vulture in Pakistan. Biological Conservation, 141, 2403–2409. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0028"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>  Keller, L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>F. ,  Jeffery, K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>J. ,  Arcese, P. ,  Beaumont, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>A. ,  Hochachka, W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>M. ,  Smith, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>M. , &amp;  Bruford, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>W.  (2001). Immigration and the ephemerality of a natural population bottleneck: Evidence from molecular markers. Proceedings of the Royal Society B, 268, 1387–1394.11429139 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0029"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>  Longmire, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>L. ,  Lewis, A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>K. ,  Brown, N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>C. ,  Buckingham, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>M. ,  Clark, L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>M. ,  Jones, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>D. , …  Moyzis, R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>K.  (1988). Isolation and molecular characterization of a highly polymorphic centromeric tandem repeat in the family Falconidae. Genomics, 2, 14–24.3384438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0030"><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>  Luikart, G. ,  Ryman, N. ,  Tallmon, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>A. ,  Schwartz, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>K. , &amp;  Allendorf, F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>W.  (2010). Estimation of census and effective population sizes: The increasing usefulness of DNA‐based approaches. Conservation Genetics, 11, 355–373. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0031"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>  McEachern, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>B. ,  Van Vuren, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>H. ,  Floyd, C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>H. ,  May, B. , &amp;  Eadie, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>M.  (2011). Bottlenecks and rescue effects in a fluctuating population of golden‐mantled ground squirrels (Spermophilus lateralis). Conservation Genetics, 12, 285–296. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0032"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>  Medrano, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>F. ,  Aasen, E. , &amp;  Sharrow, L.  (1990). DNA extraction from nucleated red blood cells. BioTechniques, 8, 43. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0033"><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>  Melbourne, B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>A. , &amp;  Hastings, A.  (2008). Extinction risk depends strongly on factors contributing to stochasticity. Nature, 454, 100–103.18596809 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0034"><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>  Piry, S. ,  Luikart, G. , &amp;  Cornuet, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>M.  (1999). BOTTLENECK: A computer program for detecting recent reductions in the effective population size using allele frequency data. Journal of Heredity, 90, 502–503. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0035"><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>  Pratt, H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>D. ,  Brisbin Jr, I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>L.  (2002). Hawaiian Coot (Fulica alai), The Birds of North America (P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>Rodewald, Ed.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>Ithaca: Cornell Lab of Ornithology; Retrieved from the Birds of North America: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://birdsna.org/Species-Account/bna/species/hawcoo">https://birdsna.org/Species-Account/bna/species/hawcoo</ext-link> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2173/bna.697b">https://doi.org/10.2173/bna.697b</ext-link>  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0036"><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>  Pritchard, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>K. ,  Stephens, M. , &amp;  Donnelly, P.  (2000). Inference of population structure from multilocus genotype data. Genetics, 155, 945–959.10835412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0037"><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>  Raymond, M. , &amp;  Rousett, F.  (1995). GENEPOP (version 1.2): Population genetics software for exact tests and ecumenicism. Journal of Heredity, 86, 248–249. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0038"><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>  Schneider, S. ,  Roessli, D. , &amp;  Excoffier, L.  (2000). ARLEQUIN version 2.0: A software for population genetic data analysis. Geneva: Genetics and Biometry Laboratory, University of Geneva. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0039"><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>  Sonsthagen, S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>A. ,  Talbot, S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>L. , &amp;  McCracken, K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>G.  (2007). Genetic characterization of common eiders (Somateria mollissima) breeding on the Yukon‐Kuskokwim Delta, Alaska. Condor, 109, 879–894. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0040"><text><SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>  Sonsthagen, S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>A. ,  Wilson, R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>E. , &amp;  Underwood, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>G.  (2014). Development and characterization of microsatellite markers for the Hawaiian coot, Fulica alai, and Hawaiian gallinule, Gallinula galeata sandvicensis, through next‐generation sequencing. Conservation Genetics Resources, 6, 765–767. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0041"><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>  Stuessy, T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>F. ,  Takayama, K. ,  López‐Sepúlveda, P. , &amp;  Crawford, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>J.  (2014). Interpretation of patterns of genetic variation in endemic plant species of oceanic islands. Botanical Journal of the Linnean Society, 174, 276–288.26074627 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0042"><text><SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>  Tajima, F.  (1989). The effect of change in population size on DNA polymorphism. Genetics, 123, 597–601.2599369 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0043"><text><SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>  Talbot, S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>L. ,  Palmer, A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>G. ,  Sage, G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>K. ,  Sonsthagen, S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>A. ,  Swem, T. ,  Brimm, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>J. , &amp;  White, C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>M.  (2011). Lack of genetic polymorphism among peregrine falcons Falco peregrinus of Fiji. Journal of Avian Biology, 42, 415–428. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0044"><text><SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>  Tamura, K. , &amp;  Nei, M.  (1993). Estimation of the number of nucleotide substitutions in the control region of mitochondrial DNA in humans and chimpanzees. Molecular Biology and Evolution, 10, 512–526.8336541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0045"><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>  Taylor, S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>S. , &amp;  Jamieson, I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>G.  (2008). No evidence for loss of genetic variation following sequencing translocations in extant populations of a genetically depauperate species. Molecular Ecology, 17, 545–556.17986194 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0046"><text><SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>  Underwood, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>G. ,  Silbernagle, M. ,  Nishimoto, M. , &amp;  Uyehara, K.  (2013). Managing conservation reliant species: Hawai'i's endangered endemic waterbirds. PLoS ONE, 8(6), e67872 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0067872">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0067872</ext-link> 23825687 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0047"><text><SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain> U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>Fish and Wildlife Service (2011). Recovery plan for Hawaiian waterbirds, second revision. Oregon: U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>Fish and Wildlife Service, Portland. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>Xx+233 pp. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0048"><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>  Van Oosterhout, C. ,  Hutchinson, W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>F. ,  Wills, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>M. , &amp;  Shipley, P.  (2004). Micro‐checker: Software for identifying and correcting genotyping errors in microsatellite data. Molecular Ecology Notes, 4, 535–538. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1471-8286.2004.00684.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1471-8286.2004.00684.x</ext-link>  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0049"><text><SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>  Waples, R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>S. , &amp;  England, P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>R.  (2011). Estimating contemporary effective population size on the basis of linkage disequilibrium in the face of migration. Genetics, 189, 633–644.21840864 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ece33530-bib-0050"><text><SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>  White, N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>E. ,  Bunce, M. ,  Mawson, P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>R. ,  Dawson, R. ,  Saunders, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>A. , &amp;  Allentoft, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain>E.  (2014). Identifying conservation units after large‐scale land clearing: A spatio‐temporal molecular survey of endangered white‐tailed black cockatoos (Calyptorhynchus spp.). Diversity and Distributions, 20, 1208–1220. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app id="ece33530-app-0001" content-type="APPENDIX"><label>APPENDIX 1</label><title>List of museum voucher specimens used in this study along with collection year</title><sec id="ece33530-sec-0018"><label>1.1</label><p>
<SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="nlm-table-wrap-1" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" colspan="2" valign="top" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="550" pm="."><plain>Hawaiian coot </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" colspan="2" valign="top" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="551" pm="."><plain>Hawaiian gallinule </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="552" pm="."><plain>Catalog no. </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="553" pm="."><plain>Collection year </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="554" pm="."><plain>Catalog no. </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="555" pm="."><plain>Collection year </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="556" pm="."><plain>AMNH 193232 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="557" pm="."><plain>1907 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="558" pm="."><plain>AMNH 546980 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="559" pm="."><plain>1893 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="560" pm="."><plain>AMNH 193233 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="561" pm="."><plain>1907 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="562" pm="."><plain>AMNH 546981 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="563" pm="."><plain>1893 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="564" pm="."><plain>ANSP 33672 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="565" pm="."><plain>1835 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="566" pm="."><plain>AMNH 546982 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="567" pm="."><plain>1893 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="568" pm="."><plain>BBM 4544 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="569" pm="."><plain>1907 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="570" pm="."><plain>AMNH 546983 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="571" pm="."><plain>1893 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="572" pm="."><plain>BBM 4545 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="573" pm="."><plain>1907 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="574" pm="."><plain>AMNH 546984 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="575" pm="."><plain>1893 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="576" pm="."><plain>BBM 4547 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="577" pm="."><plain>1907 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="578" pm="."><plain>AMNH 546985 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="579" pm="."><plain>1893 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="580" pm="."><plain>LSUMZ 81484 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="581" pm="."><plain>1939 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="582" pm="."><plain>AMNH 546986 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="583" pm="."><plain>1893 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="584" pm="."><plain>MCZ 55659 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="585" pm="."><plain>1895 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="586" pm="."><plain>BBM 4542 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="587" pm="."><plain>1907 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="588" pm="."><plain>MCZ 55660 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="589" pm="."><plain>1895 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="590" pm="."><plain>BBM 6307 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="591" pm="."><plain>1936 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="592" pm="."><plain>MCZ 80938 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="593" pm="."><plain>1895 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="594" pm="."><plain>BBM 6449 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="595" pm="."><plain>1938 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="596" pm="."><plain>MCZ 80939 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="597" pm="."><plain>1895 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="598" pm="."><plain>MCZ 39245 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="599" pm="."><plain>1894 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="600" pm="."><plain>MCZ 115018 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="601" pm="."><plain>1895 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="602" pm="."><plain>MCZ 55648 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="603" pm="."><plain>1895 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="604" pm="."><plain>MCZ 115019 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="605" pm="."><plain>1895 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="606" pm="."><plain>MCZ 55650 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="607" pm="."><plain>1895 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="608" pm="."><plain>MCZ 55651 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="609" pm="."><plain>1895 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="610" pm="."><plain>MCZ 55652 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="611" pm="."><plain>1895 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="612" pm="."><plain>MCZ 55654 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="613" pm="."><plain>1895 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="614" pm="."><plain>MCZ 55655 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="615" pm="."><plain>1895 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="616" pm="."><plain>MCZ 55656 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="617" pm="."><plain>1895 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="618" pm="."><plain>MCZ 55657 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="619" pm="."><plain>1895 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="620" pm="."><plain>MCZ 239942 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="621" pm="."><plain>1894 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="622" pm="."><plain>MVZ 7037 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="623" pm="."><plain>1903 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="624" pm="."><plain>MVZ 7040 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="625" pm="."><plain>1909 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="626" pm="."><plain>USNM 301112 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="627" pm="."><plain>1923 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ece33530-note-1001"><p><text><SENT sid="628" pm="."><plain>AMNH, American Museum of Natural History; ANSP, Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia; BBM, Bernice Pauahi Bishop Museum; LSUMZ, Louisiana State University Museum of Natural Science; MCZ, Harvard University Museum of Comparative Zoology; MVZ, University of California Berkeley Museum of Vertebrate Zoology; and USNM, National Museum of Natural History. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag>
</p></sec></app></app-group></SecTag></back></article>
