<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5753396</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkx936</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkx936</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Database Issue</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Xenbase: a genomic, epigenomic and transcriptomic model organism database </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>Kamran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fortriede</surname><given-names>Joshua D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lotay</surname><given-names>Vaneet S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>Kevin A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Dong Zhou</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>Malcom E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pells</surname><given-names>Troy J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>James-Zorn</surname><given-names>Christina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Ying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ponferrada</surname><given-names>V G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>Stanley</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chaturvedi</surname><given-names>Praneet</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zorn</surname><given-names>Aaron M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vize</surname><given-names>Peter D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1">Departments of Biological Sciences and Computer Science, University of Calgary, Calgary, Alberta T2N1N4, Canada</aff><aff id="AFF2">Cincinnati Children's Hospital, Division of Developmental Biology, 3333 Burnet Avenue, Cincinnati, OH 45229, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 403 210 8136; Email: <email>kkarimi@ucalgary.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>04</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date iso-8601-date="2017-10-20" pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>46</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><issue-title>Database issue</issue-title><fpage>D861</fpage><lpage>D868</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2017. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by-nc" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact <email>journals.permissions@oup.com</email></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="gkx936.pdf"/><abstract><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Abstract </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Xenbase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.xenbase.org">www.xenbase.org</ext-link>) is an online resource for researchers utilizing Xenopus laevis and Xenopus tropicalis, and for biomedical scientists seeking access to data generated with these model systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Content is aggregated from a variety of external resources and also generated by in-house curation of scientific literature and bioinformatic analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Over the past two years many new types of content have been added along with new tools and functionalities to reflect the impact of high-throughput sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>These include new genomes for both supported species (each with chromosome scale assemblies), new genome annotations, genome segmentation, dynamic and interactive visualization for RNA-Seq data, updated ChIP-Seq mapping, GO terms, protein interaction data, ORFeome support, and improved connectivity to other biomedical and bioinformatic resources. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="SEC1"><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The African frogs, Xenopus laevis and X. tropicalis, have been widely used in biomedical research for many decades. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>As a tetrapod vertebrate, amphibians occupy a powerful phylogenetic niche between mammalian systems and less complex vertebrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>As a model system, the large and robust eggs and embryos of these frogs are extremely well suited to microinjection, microdissection, and transplantation based experiments, while their external development in a simple saline solution makes observation of responses to experimental intervention vastly more straightforward than are equivalent tests performed in internally developing species, such as mammals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The dual goals of Xenbase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.xenbase.org">www.xenbase.org</ext-link>) are to enhance and support research using these model organisms, and to make the wealth of unique data generated through the many advantages of this system available to the larger biomedical research community. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>In the pre-genome era, Xenbase began with simple database modules supporting the Xenopus user community and papers describing research using Xenopus (1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>As more powerful resources became available, new expressed sequence tags and draft genomes were added to build gene-centric features such as ‘Gene Pages’ and these data were linked to the literature via our Xenopus Anatomical Ontology, or XAO (2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>With the addition of a manual data curation team in 2010 Xenbase expanded to manual annotation of literature published using Xenopus and began to capture gene expression and other content types such as morpholinos and antibodies and automatic systems that identify and link all of these elements (3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Most recently, we have added ORFeome, microRNA and human disease orthology content (4,5), and moved to a virtualized private cloud (6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>In this paper, we introduce a number of major new features and enhancements including chromosome scale genome assemblies, a new genome browser, novel genome analysis tracks, a University of California, Santa Cruz (UCSC) Genome Browser (7) track hub and massive amounts of Chromatin Immunoprecipitation Sequencing (ChIP-Seq) and RNA sequencing (RNA-Seq) content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>A novel RNA-Seq visualization system is also presented that allows users to load and view temporal, tissue, and experimental results from RNA-Seq data on-the-fly. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="SEC2"><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>NEW X. laevis AND X. tropicalis GENOMES </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>An international multi-team effort for sequencing, assembly and annotation of the X. laevis genome was undertaken and took several years to complete (8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The genome sequence revealed that this species is an allotetraploid which evolved from a hybridization event between two species ∼17–18 million years ago. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The two homeologous genes from each ancestor are still present for &gt;56% of all genes, though the level of expression is often very different. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>As each X. laevis gene now has two copies in most cases, it was necessary to restructure both the user interface and the underlying database to seamlessly integrate the two homoeologs and to match each gene pair to the single corresponding gene in X. tropicalis (9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The chromosomes of one of the X. laevis ancestral species are longer than those of the second species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>For this reason the Xenopus research community (10) chose to append gene symbols with a ‘.L’ (long) or a ‘.S’ (short) to indicate from which homoeologous chromosome they are derived, for example the pax8 homoeologs are pax8.L and pax8.S. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The X. laevis genome described by Session et al. (8) was released as version 9.1, and is viewable and searchable on Xenbase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The genome available at the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI), known as version 9.2 GCF, has some minor differences to this version and is also available at Xenbase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>A new chromosome-scale build of X. tropicalis was also released and is available for browsing, searching or download. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The NCBI version of the X. tropicalis genome also differs from the genome consortium version, and is known as X. tropicalis NCBI v9.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The official versions for future Xenbase annotation and Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) support are X. laevis version 9.2 GCF and X. tropicalis NCBI v9.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Annotations for both of these builds were generated by Xenbase by merging the genome consortium and NCBI machine generated annotations using the BEDTools (11) intersect program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In the most recent version, 22,329 out of 51,041 gene models are annotated in X. laevis v9.2 GCF and 18,335 out of 34,207 gene models are annotated in X. tropicalis v9.1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In addition to these latest genomes, Xenbase makes all previous genome versions available in genome browsers and source files accessible on its File Transfer Protocol (FTP) site (<ext-link ext-link-type="ftp" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.xenbase.org/pub/">ftp://ftp.xenbase.org/pub/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Other resources also host some current and legacy Xenopus genomes, for details on these please see Vize and Zorn (12). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC3"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>GENOME BROWSERS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>For many years Xenbase has used GBrowse (13) both as a genome browser and to generate genome snapshots on Gene Pages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>This browser uses the TopoView tool to stack High-throughput/NGS tracks—a powerful visualization methodology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In response to user requests, we also recently implemented a method to allow for Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLAST) searching from within GBrowse using a plugin written by Mark Wilkinson (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/GMOD/GBrowse">https://github.com/GMOD/GBrowse</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>To use this tool, select the ‘Configure’ button in the top right corner of a GBrowse window, paste the sequence of interest into the text field, select ‘Configure’ again, and when back on the browsing window select ‘Go’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Note that running BLAST in this manner does not reload the genome view window, so if the matched region is not in the active view, it will not be visible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Users can always also go directly to our BLAST pages from the main navigation bar, and select the genome of interest as the target. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The output will include hyperlinks to load and view the matched result directly in GBrowse. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>As GBrowse is no longer supported by a developer community, the current Generic Model Organism Database (GMOD) community supported browser known as JBrowse (14) is being adopted as our primary genome browsing tool. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>In addition to our extant GBrowse resources, we now support JBrowse versions of the most recent genome builds and will focus on importing current and legacy genomes and tracks over to this new browser. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>JBrowse has many performance and interface improvements, and supports a powerful faceted track selector. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In addition to viewing and searching the genomes, we used GBrowse to generate snapshots of a genomic region to enrich Gene Pages and provide a graphical overview of the architecture of the gene of interest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>JBrowse can render such views dynamically, but this method has a significant performance lag. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>As a step towards replacing GBrowse, we now use the data on gene coordinates and exon/intron boundaries already in our database to render a graphical representation of the genomic and chromosomal structure using Data-Driven Documents, JavaScript (D3.js; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://d3js.org/">https://d3js.org/</ext-link>), a tool that will be discussed in more detail below. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>This provides instant rendering and allows for greater customization. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC4"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>GENOME BROWSER TRACKS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>In the past, Xenbase posted tracks submitted by genome sequencing centers and research groups that made their output available to our resource. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>More recently, we initiated in-house data analysis and track generation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The first set of custom genome-based data contains chromatin segmentation predictions and transcription factor binding site maps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Chromatin segmentation utilizes a combination of different histone modification markers and distribution of bound proteins such as p300 and RNA polymerase 2 to predict chromatin states and features such as promoters, enhancers, transcribed regions, repressed regions and heterochromatin, similar to the chromatin states described by Hontelez et al. (15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>One aspect of Xenopus development that is intensively studied is how patterns of transcription change over time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>To capture such transitions, Xenbase chromatin segmentation maps are generated from data derived from the same developmental time stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Tracks are generated using ChromHMM (16) and Segway (17), similar to the UCSC genome browser. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Our color scheme also matches that of the UCSC browser for consistency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Currently, this feature is available only for X. tropicalis NCBI version 9.1 as sufficient ChIP-Seq data are not available for X. laevis at this time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Additional novel tracks include an 11-species conservation score track from an analysis by UCSC (unpublished) and a transcription factor binding site prediction track. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Transcription factor binding site predictions were generated using motifs from the CIS-BP website (18) and scanning motif instances using FIMO/MEME (19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Between 20% and 70% of our predicted binding sites were validated by association with ChIP-Seq peaks, depending on the transcription factors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>An ongoing issue with genomic resources is data migration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Published NGS tracks are most often aligned to older genome builds, as the research/publication cycle moves slowly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>In the past users needed to visit each legacy genome build and browse available tracks to view and evaluate all supporting content, and no single genome build had all available tracks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>To alleviate this problem, Xenbase also rebuilds NGS tracks originally aligned against older genome builds to the latest builds, X. tropicalis NCBI v9.1 and X. laevis NCBI GCF v9.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>This includes RNA-Seq, ChIP-Seq, methylation and other NGS content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>FASTQ files (20) obtained from NCBI are processed to generate BigWig (21) tracks for loading and viewing in JBrowse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>This will make over 350 NGS tracks available on the latest genomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC5"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>TRACK HUB </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>In addition to the GMOD browsers, we also support a UCSC browser track hub. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>This system uses the powerful resources at the UCSC to load and display content from the Xenbase remote site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Xenbase hosts a UCSC browser track hub, a collection of genomes and gene models plus over 350 NGS tracks, mostly ChIP- and RNA-Seq. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>All of this content can be loaded and displayed at UCSC, but tracks are only available against their original genome versions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>As only the requested view is loaded at any one time, this system is very fast and has minimal load and display times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>To access the hub visit Genomes/Xenbase UCSC Track Hub from the main navigation bar and follow the instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>A second Xenopus data hub is available at Radboud University (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://veenstra.science.ru.nl/trackhub.htm">http://veenstra.science.ru.nl/trackhub.htm</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC6"><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>INTERACTIVE CONTENT VISUALIZATION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Databases typically display content generated through hard-coded queries and visualization methods in their web application code. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Given the vast amount of NGS content available through resources such as NCBI GEO (22), and the enormous number of different potential unique uses by individual researchers, we developed a highly customizable method to view such data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The approach stores NGS data as a table in our core database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>In response to a query, Xenbase pulls matching data from this table, and then formats the output as a simple JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) file that can be rendered and displayed by D3.js, a JavaScript library widely used in data visualization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The output graphic is dynamic and elements can be added or removed by the user. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>When adding new content that changes the scale, the visualization changes accordingly, and users can also select between different scaling methods for rendering the data values, such as non-transformed (normalized), log2 or square root. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>On each Gene Page, tools for viewing temporal and spatial expression data are now embedded in the Expression tab, and render as soon as the page is selected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Graph color is selected randomly, and reloading the Expression tab using the browser reload button, will select a new color combination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>When a user clicks on one of the small icons, a larger version with new control tools opens, allowing new genes to be added, permanently removed, or temporarily hidden. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Mouse-overs display the read counts for individual data points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The data used in this context are derived from the work of Session et al. (8) for X. laevis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>For X. tropicalis genes, users have the option to view RNA-Seq data generated from different library protocols, or to view separate plots for different splice isoforms based on the data of Owens et al. (23). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>In the example shown in Figure 1, the temporal profile of the noggin gene (nog) is compared to that of chordin (chrd), two genes identified by research in Xenopus as playing key roles in head development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The noggin profile was generated by navigating to the noggin gene page, selecting the Expression tab, and then clicking on the icon to view the ‘Stage and Tissue Profiles’ for X. laevis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>This renders the X. laevis profile for both .L and .S homoeologs of noggin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The ‘Add’ feature was then selected, ‘chordin’ typed into the text field, and ‘Add’ clicked. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The nog.S and chrd1.L genes were then removed to declutter the lower expressed homoeologs, and the transformation set to log2 to provide a more direct comparison. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Users can also start from scratch by selecting Expression/RNA-Seq Viewers from the top horizontal navigation bar should they not wish to start with a Gene Page. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Interactive RNA-Seq visualization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>After selecting the central panel for X. laevis temporal data on a Gene Page ‘Expression’ tab, a larger window with additional controls opens as shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>A second gene, chordin, was added to further customize the view as described in the main text. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Note that the noggin profile (purple) has been rescaled on the Y axis to accommodate the higher level of transcription of the chordin gene (red). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkx936fig1"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Tissue distribution data (8) of RNA-Seq data are also available via this tool as a heat map. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>This tool allows for simple comparison of spatial expression differences between the L and S homoeologs in X. laevis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Custom color maps, data transformations and gene comparisons will be available in the near future. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Our data visualization interface also allows users to view changes in transcription of a gene in response to experimental manipulations, such as morpholino or mRNA microinjection, once again displayed as a heat map. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>This is available on Gene Pages in the Expression tab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Currently only one extensive dataset is available in this feature (24), but many more will be available in the near future. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>All D3.js views can be output to a Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) file, which can be edited in graphics programs (such as Adobe Illustrator) to generate figures for publications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The ‘Redraw’ button removes any custom text generated by mouse-overs to return to a clean rendering for download. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Xenbase is also in the process of building an RNA-Seq Transcripts Per Million (TPM) resource to enable users to rapidly evaluate and contrast datasets of interest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>This involves annotating all available RNA-Seq datasets at the NCBI and building a prioritized queue for alignment and standardized normalization to output TPM tables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>With further development, it is hoped that this content can be used to build global maps of how each gene behaves in all published Xenopus RNA-Seq datasets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC7"><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>DATA IMPORTS FROM THE EUROPEAN BIOINFORMATICS INSTITUTE (EBI) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>A number of data loaders now pull research data relevant to Xenopus from the EBI (25). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>This includes Gene Ontology (GO) terms for Xenopus proteins, Xenopus protein function descriptions, and human protein-protein interaction data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>This content is updated monthly and included in our weekly data reports, available on our FTP site (<ext-link ext-link-type="ftp" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.xenbase.org/pub/GenePageReports/">ftp://ftp.xenbase.org/pub/GenePageReports/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>GO terms are collected for both X. laevis and X. tropicalis proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>A non-redundant summary of these terms is available from the ‘GO Terms’ tab on every Gene Page as in Figure 2, and the full data, mapped to Xenbase identifiers (IDs), is placed on our FTP site on a weekly basis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>On the Gene Page/GO Terms tab, the species and/or homoeolog to which the GO term is attributed can be viewed by mousing over the information icon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>This new set of annotations is based on the UniProt GO annotation (UniProt-GOA) database, showing a filtered subset of manual and automated annotations meeting the criteria used by UniProtKB (25) for granularity, evidence code quality and excluding isoforms and annotations with certain qualifiers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>GO terms associated with an X. laevis and X. tropicalis gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkx936fig2"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The UniProtKB also provides descriptions of protein function, along with the sources of the annotation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Xenbase now imports and displays this information near the top of the summary tab of each Gene Page as ‘Protein Function’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Click on the ‘+’ to expand if the description display is truncated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Xenbase now also imports protein-protein interaction content derived from human experimental data, updated monthly, from IntAct (26). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>This approach was selected as the amount of human data available is considerably larger than data currently available from research on Xenopus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>We also display interactions predicted in-house from co-citation in the Xenopus literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>These are both available through the ‘Interactants’ tab on each Gene Page. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>D3.js is used to generate a dynamic view of the currently selected type of interactions, with edge thickness illustrating the number of evidence types or citations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Additional features will be added to allow further customization of the visualization by users, such as changing the number of root nodes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Figure 3 illustrates the top interactants for this new protein interaction data for AXIN1, compared to interactions predicted by co-citation of genes in the Xenbase literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>As predicted, there is often (but not always) considerable overlap in the two networks in terms of associated protein/gene identification, but the strength of evidence varies extensively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Comparison of Xenopus literature gene co-citation to human protein interaction data from IntAct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Genes co-cited with axin1 in Xenbase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Two key interactants, ctnnb1 (beta-catenin, 10 co-citations) and gsk3b (glycogen synthase kinase 3 beta, 8 co-citations) are circled in red. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>IntAct data on human proteins interacting with AXIN1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>CTNNB1 has 35 results and GSK3B has 41 results, ranging from co-immunoprecipitation and yeast two-hybrid interactions, to fluorescence polarization spectroscopy and protein kinase assays (click on interactions hyperlink on Xenbase to view evidence). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkx936fig3"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="SEC8"><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>ASSOCIATION WITH ADDITIONAL EXTERNAL RESOURCES </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>In addition to the already-existing human, mouse, and zebrafish links, Xenbase gene pages now have ortholog links to corresponding genes in fruit fly (27), chicken (28), and worm (29) MODs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The Genetic Phenotypes section has been augmented by links to OMIM (30), MalaCards (31), DECIPHER (32), KEGG (33) Disease and IMPC (34) mouse phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>In addition to matching OMIM IDs via gene symbols, Xenbase curators now also do manual annotation of Gene:OMIM associations from publications using Xenopus data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The Gene Expression section contains links to Ensembl (35) (multiple species), Protein Atlas (36), Eurexpress (37), Allen Brain Atlas for both human (38) and mouse (39) and MGI (40). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Functional Ontologies now include AmiGO (41), PANTHER (42), and KEGG (33) Pathways links. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>XenMine (43), a biological data mining tool set based on InterMine (44), has been available with Xenopus data since 2015. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Links to XenMine are available from multiple places throughout the site, including gene pages. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC9"><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>ORFeome </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>We now have full database support for the Xenopus ORFeome project (45). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>This project generated full length clones encoding the Open Reading Frame (ORF) of 8,633 Xenopus laevis cDNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>These include 2,724 genes for which the human ortholog has an OMIM disease association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>ORFeome cDNAs are cloned in Gateway vectors, and available from a number of commercial suppliers whose links are provided (they are not available directly from Xenbase). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Users can search for ORFeome clones using ORF names or symbols, Entrez IDs, or plate and well numbers for specific clones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Links to ORFeome resources are also provided in the Reagents section of each Gene Page. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The display for a typical ORFeome clone is shown in Figure 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The ORFeome project is ongoing and additional clones, including those encoding X. tropicalis proteins, will be added as the data become available. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>ORFeome page associated with an X. laevis gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkx936fig4"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="SEC10"><title><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>SMALL MOLECULES, microRNAs AND CRISPR/Cas </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Three new wiki sections are available to support the use of small molecules, to provide data on microRNAs (miRNAs) and their expression, and a CRISPR/TALEN (46) support module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The small molecules wiki (main menu; Reagents &amp; Protocols/Small Molecule Wiki) allows users to identify reagents that have been described in publications on Xenopus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Molecules are sorted by pathways (e.g. cAMP), by biological functions &amp; processes (e.g. apoptosis), and by effects of classes of genes (e.g. ion channels). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Each molecule has a wiki page that includes its description, known targets, suppliers, usage notes (if available), references, and molecular structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Registered Xenbase users can submit content to the discussion section of each molecule page. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The miRNA wiki (main menu; Expression/miRNA Catalog) incorporates data and images from Ahmed et al. (47) with miRBase content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>In addition, information on the sequence and mature product data images illustrating expression at multiple developmental stages are provided for each miRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>More tools useful for miRNA work are supported via links to external resources, such as target prediction software, miRNA papers in Xenbase, and miRNA nomenclature. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>We currently do not provide on-site CRISPR or TALEN target prediction or design tools. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>However, we do provide a summary and links to resources available at a number of specialized sites that do provide such services (main menu; Reagents &amp; Protocols/ CRISPR &amp; TALEN Support). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>This page summarizes which genome versions are available at each target prediction site, plus the sites input/output, aiding our users in selecting the best system for their experimental needs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>It also provides links to various resources, publications and an educational genome editing video. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC11"><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Xenbase HELP </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Every Xenbase web page has a ‘Contact Us’ link in the top right corner that will lead to an email to report problems or ask for help. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Throughout the resource, Information icons, a lower case ‘i’ in a green circle, provide additional data upon mouse-over. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>On the lower navigation bar on every page a ‘Need Help?’ button links to a suite of documentation on how to use various Xenbase features. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Tutorial videos on using Xenbase are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.xenbase.org/other/static/HowTo.jsp">http://www.xenbase.org/other/static/HowTo.jsp</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Finally, the Xenbase Wiki (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wiki.xenbase.org">wiki.xenbase.org</ext-link>) contains a wealth of helpful articles on Xenbase and Xenopus frogs and experimental protocols. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="SEC12"><title><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>THE FUTURE </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Our major targets for the immediate future are to expand and further improve the RNA-Seq visualization and analysis tools described above, and to add phenotype content including gene expression as a phenotype content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Numerous data-mining projects are also underway to identify synexpression sets within our extensive collection of gene expression data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>We also have several active genome track improvement projects, mapping NGS data from old genomes to the latest genomes and generating ChIP-peak calls and other data to make NGS data more accessible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Finally, genome improvement and annotation is a major and high priority community need that we are addressing using a combination of computational and manual methods. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>We would like to thank our NICHD program officer James Coulombe and our external advisory board for advice and guidance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Many members of our user community and external resources contributed greatly to the improvements described in this manuscript, including users who complete surveys and/or provide feedback, EBI/IntAct and Facebase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Research reported in this publication is supported by the Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development of the National Institutes of Health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institutes of Health. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec id="SEC13"><title>FUNDING</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Research reported in this publication is supported by Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development under Award Number P41HD064556. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Additional support was provided by the Wellcome Trust via the EXRC [RRID:SCR_007164]. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Conflict of interest statement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>None declared. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>1. BowesJ.B., SnyderK.A., SegerdellE., GibbR., JarabekC., NoumenE., PolletN., VizeP.D. Xenbase: a Xenopus biology and genomics resource. Nucleic Acids Res.2008; 36:D761–D767.17984085 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>2. SegerdellE., BowesJ.B., PolletN., VizeP.D. An ontology for Xenopus anatomy and development. BMC Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Biol.2008; 8:92.18817563 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>3. James-ZornC., PonferradaV.G., JarabekC.J., BurnsK.A., SegerdellE.J., LeeJ., SnyderK., BhattacharyyaB., KarpinkaJ.B., FortriedeJ. Xenbase: expansion and updates of the Xenopus model organism database. Nucleic Acids Res.2013; 41:D865–D870.23125366 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>4. James-ZornC., PonferradaV.G., BurnsK.A., FortriedeJ.D., LotayV.S., LiuY., KarpinkaB.J., KarimiK., ZornA.M., VizeP.D. Xenbase: Core features, data acquisition, and data processing. Genesis. 2015; 53:486–497.26150211 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>5. KarpinkaJ.B., FortriedeJ.D., BurnsK.A., James-ZornC., PonferradaV.G., LeeJ., KarimiK., ZornA.M., VizeP.D. Xenbase, the Xenopus model organism database; new virtualized system, data types and genomes. Nucleic Acids Res.2015; 43:D756–D763.25313157 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>6. KarimiK., VizeP.D. The Virtual Xenbase: transitioning an online bioinformatics resource to a private cloud. Database (Oxford). 2014; 2014:bau108.25380782 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>7. TynerC., BarberG.P., CasperJ., ClawsonH., DiekhansM., EisenhartC., FischerC.M., GibsonD., GonzalezJ.N., GuruvadooL. The UCSC Genome Browser database: 2017 update. Nucleic Acids Res.2017; 45:D626–D634.27899642 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>8. SessionA.M., UnoY.Kwon T., ChapmanJ.A., ToyodaA., TakahashiS., FukuiA., HikosakaA., SuzukiA., KondoM. Genome evolution in the allotetraploid frog Xenopus laevis. Nature. 2016; 538:336–343.27762356 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>9. VizeP.D., LiuY., KarimiK. Database and informatic challenges in representing both diploid and tetraploid Xenopus species in Xenbase. Cytogenet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Genome Res.2015; 145:278–282.26022975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>10. MatsudaY., UnoY., KondoM., GilchristM.J., ZornA.M., RokhsarD.S., SchmidM., TairaM. A new nomenclature of Xenopus laevis chromosomes based on the phylogenetic relationship to Silurana/Xenopus tropicalis. Cytogenet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Genome Res.2015; 145:187–189.25871511 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>11. QuinlanA.R., HallI.M. BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features. Bioinformatics. 2010; 26:841–842.20110278 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>12. VizeP.D., ZornA.M. Xenopus genomic data and browser resources. Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Biol.2017; 426:194–199.27039265 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>13. SteinL.D., MungallC., ShuS.Q., CaudyM., MangoneM., DayA., NickersonE., StajichJ.F., HarrisT.W., ArvaA. The generic genome browser: a building block for a model organism system database. Genome Res.2002; 12:1599–1610.12368253 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>14. SkinnerM.E., UzilovA.V., SteinL.D., MungallC.J., HolmesI.H. JBrowse: a next-generation genome browser. Genome Res.2009; 19:1630–1638.19570905 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>15. HontelezS., van KruijsbergenI., GeorgiouG., van HeeringenS.J., BogdanovicO., ListerR., VeenstraG.J. Embryonic transcription is controlled by maternally defined chromatin state. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Commun.2015; 6:10148.26679111 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>16. ErnstJ., KellisM. ChromHMM: automating chromatin-state discovery and characterization. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Methods. 2012; 9:215–216.22373907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>17. HoffmanM.M., BuskeO.J., WangJ., WengZ., BilmesJ., NobleW.S. Unsupervised pattern discovery in human chromatin structure through genomic segmentation. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Methods. 2012; 9:473–476.22426492 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>18. WeirauchM.T., YangA., AlbuM., CoteA.G., Montenegro-MonteroA., DreweP., NajafabadiH.S., LambertS.A., MannI., CookK. Determination and inference of eukaryotic transcription factor sequence specificity. Cell. 2014; 158:1431–1443.25215497 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>19. GrantC.E., BaileyT.L., NobleW.S. FIMO: scanning for occurrences of a given motif. Bioinformatics. 2011; 27:1017–1018.21330290 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>20. CockP.J.A., FieldsC.J., GotoN., HeuerM.L., RiceP.M. The Sanger FASTQ file format for sequences with quality scores, and the Solexa/Illumina FASTQ variants. Nucleic Acids Res.2010; 38:1767–1771.20015970 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>21. KentW.J., ZweigA.S., BarberG., HinrichsA.S., KarolchikD. BigWig and BigBed: enabling browsing of large distributed datasets. Bioinformatics. 2010; 26:2204–2207.20639541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>22. BarrettT., WilhiteS.E., LedouxP., EvangelistaC., KimI.F., TomashevskyM., MarshallK.A., PhillippyK.H., ShermanP.M., HolkoM. NCBI GEO: archive for functional genomics data sets–update. Nucleic Acids Res.2013; 41:D991–D995.23193258 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>23. OwensN.D., BlitzI.L., LaneM.A., PatrushevI., OvertonJ.D., GilchristM.J., ChoK.W., KhokhaM.K. Measuring absolute RNA copy numbers at high temporal resolution reveals transcriptome kinetics in development. Cell Rep.2016; 14:632–647.26774488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>24. DingY., PloperD., SosaE.A., ColozzaG., MoriyamaY., BenitezM.D., ZhangK., MerkurjevD., De RobertisE.M. Spemann organizer transcriptome induction by early beta-catenin, Wnt, Nodal, and Siamois signals in Xenopus laevis. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>U.S.A.2017; 114:E3081–E3090.28348214 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>25. The UniProt Consortium UniProt: a hub for protein information. Nucleic Acids Res.2015; 43:D204–D212.25348405 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>26. HermjakobH., Montecchi-PalazziL., LewingtonC., MudaliS., KerrienS., OrchardS., VingronM., RoechertB., RoepstorffP., Valencia IntAct: an open source molecular interaction database. Nucleic Acids Res.2004; 32:D452–D455.14681455 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>27. GramatesL.S., MarygoldS.J., dos SantosG., UrbanoJ.-M., AntonazzoG., MatthewsB.B., ReyA.J., TaboneC.J., CrosbyM.A., EmmertD.B. FlyBase at 25: looking to the future. Nucleic Acids Res.2017; 45:D663–D671.27799470 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>28. AntinP.B., YatskievychT.A., DaveyS., DarnellD.K. GEISHA: an evolving gene expression resource for the chicken embryo. Nucleic Acids Res.2014; 42:D933–D937.24150938 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>29. HoweK.L., BoltB.J., CainS., ChanJ., ChenW.J., DavisP., DoneJ., DownT., GaoS., GroveC. WormBase 2016: expanding to enable helminth genomic research. Nucleic Acids Res.2016; 44:D774–D780.26578572 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>30. AmbergerJ.S., BocchiniC.A., SchiettecatteF., ScottA.F., HamoshA. OMIM.org: Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man (OMIM), an online catalog of human genes and genetic disorders. Nucleic Acids Res.2015; 43:D789–D798.25428349 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>31. RappaportN., TwikM., NativN., StelzerG., BahirI., SteinT.I., SafranM., LancetD. MalaCards: a comprehensive automatically-mined database of human diseases. Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Protoc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatics. 2014; 47, doi:10.1002/0471250953.bi0124s47. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>32. FirthH.V., RichardsS.M., BevanA.P., ClaytonS., CorpasM., RajanD., Van VoorenS., MoreauY., PettettR.M., CarterN.P. DECIPHER: database of chromosomal imbalance and phenotype in humans using ensembl resources. Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Hum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Genet.2009; 84:524–533.19344873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>33. KanehisaM., FurumichiM., TanabeM., SatoY., MorishimaK. KEGG: new perspectives on genomes, pathways, diseases and drugs. Nucleic Acids Res.2017; 45:D353–D361.27899662 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>34. BrownS.D., MooreM.W. The International Mouse Phenotyping Consortium: past and future perspectives on mouse phenotyping. Mamm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Genome. 2012; 23:632–640.22940749 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>35. YatesA., AkanniW., AmodeM.R., BarrellD., BillisK., Carvalho-SilvaD., CumminsC., ClaphamP., FitzgeraldS., GilL. Ensembl 2016. Nucleic Acids Res.2016; 44:D710–D716.26687719 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>36. UhlénM., FagerbergL., HallströmB.M., LindskogC., OksvoldP., MardinogluA., SivertssonÅ., KampfC., SjöstedtE., AsplundA. Tissue-based map of the human proteome. Science. 2015; 347:1260419.25613900 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>37. Diez-RouxG., BanfiS., SultanM., GeffersL., AnandS., RozadoD., MagenA., CanidioE., PaganiM., PelusoI. A high-resolution anatomical atlas of the transcriptome in the mouse embryo. PLoS Biol. 2011; 9:e1000582.21267068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>38. HawrylyczM.J., LeinE.S., Guillozet-BongaartsA.L., ShenE.H., NgL., MillerJ.A., van de LagemaatL.N., SmithK.A., EbbertA., RileyZ.L. An anatomically comprehensive atlas of the adult human brain transcriptome. Nature. 2012; 489:391–399.22996553 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>39. OhS.W., HarrisJ.A., NgL., WinslowB., CainN., MihalasS., WangQ., LauC., KuanL., HenryA.M. A mesoscale connectome of the mouse brain. Nature. 2014; 508:207–214.24695228 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>40. BlakeJ.A., EppigJ.T., KadinJ.A., RichardsonJ.E., SmithC.L., BultC.J.the Mouse Genome Database Group Mouse Genome Database (MGD)-2017: community knowledge resource for the laboratory mouse. Nucleic Acids Res. 2017; 45:D723–D729.27899570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>41. CarbonS., IrelandA., MungallC.J., ShuS., MarshallB., LewisS. AmiGO Hub, Web Presence Working Group, AmiGO: online access to ontology and annotation data. Bioinformatics. 2009; 25:288–289.19033274 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>42. ThomasP.D., CampbellM.J., KejariwalA., MiH., KarlakB., DavermanR., DiemerK., MuruganujanA., NarechaniaA. PANTHER: a library of protein families and subfamilies indexed by function. Genome Res. 2003; 13:2129–2141.12952881 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>43. ReidC.D., KarraK., ChangJ., PiskolR., LiQ., LiJ.B., CherryJ.M., BakerJ.C. XenMine: a genomic interaction tool for the Xenopus community. Dev Biol. 2017; 426:155–164.27157655 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>44. KalderimisA., LyneR., ButanoD., ContrinoS., LyneM., HeimbachJ., HuF., SmithR., StěpánR., SullivanJ. InterMine: extensive web services for modern biology. Nucleic Acids Res.2014; 42:W468–W472.24753429 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>45. GrantI.M., BalchaD., HaoT., ShenY., TrivediP., PatrushevI., FortriedeJ.D., KarpinkaJ.B., LiuL., ZornA.M. The Xenopus ORFeome: a resource that enables functional genomics. Dev Biol. 2015; 408:345–357.26391338 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>46. NemudryiA.A., ValetdinovaK.R., MedvedevS.P., ZakianS.M. TALEN and CRISPR/Cas genome editing systems: tools of discovery. Acta Naturae. 2014; 6:19–40. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>47. AhmedA., WardN.J., MoxonS., Lopez-GomollonS., ViautC., TomlinsonM.L., PatrushevI., GilchristM.J., DalmayT., DotlicD. A database of microRNA expression patterns in Xenopus laevis. PLoS One. 2015; 10:e0138313.26506012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
