<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5382772</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep45254</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep45254</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Entomopathogenic nematodes in agricultural areas in Brazil </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Brida</surname><given-names>Andressa Lima</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>Juliana Magrinelli Osório</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>Cláudio Marcelo Gonçalves de</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>Bárbara Monteiro de Castro e</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Serrão</surname><given-names>José Eduardo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zanuncio</surname><given-names>José Cola</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leite</surname><given-names>Luis Garrigós</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wilcken</surname><given-names>Silvia Renata Siciliano</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Departamento de Proteção Vegetal, Universidade Estadual Paulista (UNESP/FCA)</institution>, Rua José Barbosa de Barros, 1780, CEP 18610-307, Botucatu, São Paulo, <country>Brasil</country></aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Laboratório de Nematologia (CEIB), Instituto Biológico</institution>, Alameda dos Vidoeiros, 1097, CEP 13101-680, Campinas, São Paulo, <country>Brasil</country></aff><aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>Departamento de Fitotecnia, Universidade Federal de Viçosa</institution>, 36570-900, Viçosa, Minas Gerais, <country>Brasil</country></aff><aff id="a4"><label>4</label><institution>Departamento de Biologia Geral, Universidade Federal de Viçosa</institution>, 36570-900, Viçosa, Minas Gerais, <country>Brasil</country></aff><aff id="a5"><label>5</label><institution>Departamento de Entomologia/BIOAGRO, Universidade Federal de Viçosa</institution>, 36570-900, Viçosa, Minas Gerais, <country>Brasil</country></aff><aff id="a6"><label>6</label><institution>Laboratório de Controle Biológico (CEIB), Instituto Biológico</institution>, Alameda dos Vidoeiros, 1097, CEP 13101-680 Campinas, São Paulo, <country>Brasil</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email>zanuncio@ufv.br</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>04</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>45254</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>07</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>02</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2017, The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Entomopathogenic nematodes (EPNs) (Steinernematidae and Heterorhabditidae) can control pests due to the mutualistic association with bacteria that kill the host by septicemia and make the environment favorable for EPNs development and reproduction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The diversity of EPNs in Brazilian soils requires further study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The identification of EPNs, adapted to environmental and climatic conditions of cultivated areas is important for sustainable pest suppression in integrated management programs in agricultural areas of Brazil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The objective was to identify EPNs isolated from agricultural soils with annual, fruit and forest crops in Brazil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Soil samples were collected and stored in 250 ml glass vials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The nematodes were isolated from these samples with live bait traps ([Galleria mellonella L. (Lepidoptera: Pyralidae) larvae]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Infective juveniles were collected with White traps and identified by DNA barcoding procedures by sequencing the D2/D3 expansion of the 28S rDNA region by PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>EPNs identified in agricultural areas in Brazil were Heterorhabditis amazonensis, Metarhabditis rainai, Oscheios tipulae and Steinernema rarum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>These species should be considered pest biocontrol agents in Brazilian agricultural areas. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Entomopathogenic nematodes (EPNs) Steinernematidae and Heterorhabditidae can control pests due to mutualistic association with bacteria of the genus Xenorhabdus (Thomas &amp; Poinar) and Photorhabdus (Boemare, Louis &amp; Kuhl), respectively12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>These nematodes penetrate the host through natural openings or through the cuticle transporting bacteria into the hemocele34 where they reproduce and kill the host from septicemia within 24 to 48 hours56, making the environment favorable for nematode development and reproduction7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Infective juveniles seek another host in the soil when the insect host resources run out8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Interest in these biological control agents is increasing9 due to the reduced efficiency of conventional chemical and cultural methods for insect soil management and the broad spectrum of EPN hosts10. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>EPNs are globally distributed, with different species and groups according to geographic regions1112. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Information on EPNs and their symbiotic bacteria is scarce in many countries, including in Brazil. Heterorhabditis amazonensis Andaló and Steinernema brasiliensis Nguyen were reported as native species in Brazil1314 and Heterorhabditids indica and H. baujardi were reported in Rondônia state, Brazil15. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Isolates of H. amazonensis, H. baujardi, H. indica and H. mexicana were found in Minas Gerais state, Brazil1617. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Nematode species can be identified by molecular characterization based on sequencing of rDNA subunit (28S)181920, because low morphological variation and similar characteristics within this group hamper identification15. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Infectivity, environmental tolerance and suitability for commercial formulations vary between EPN isolates and species2122 which can be used to control pests of various orders, such as Coleoptera232425, Hemiptera2627282930 and Lepidoptera313233. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>EPN identification, adapted to environmental and climatic conditions of cultivated areas is important for sustainable pest suppression in integrated management programs in agricultural areas of Brazil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The objective was to identify EPNs from agricultural soils with annual, fruit and perennial crops in Brazil. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Nematode collection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Soil samples were collected in agricultural areas in Barretos, Botucatu, Garça, São Manuel (São Paulo State), and Palotina (Paraná State), Brazil from 2010 to 2013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Thirty-seven samples were collected in areas with annual crops, [Glycine max (L.) Merrill, Zea mays (L.), Avena sativa (L.), Saccharum officinarum (L.) and irrigated Oryza sativa (L.)], 20 in areas with forest plantations [Anadenanthera falcata (Benth.) Speg.), Peltophorum dubium (Spreng.) Taub., Khaya ivorensis, Swietenia macrophylla, Hevea brasiliensis (L.), Eucalyptus spp., Cedrela odorata (L.), Acrocarpus fraxinifolius, Azadirachta indica (A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Juss.), Cordia ecalyculata (Vell), Calophyllum brasiliense (Cambess.) and Poecilanthe parviflora (Benth)], and 97 in areas with fruit [Litchi chinensis (Sonn.), Macadamia integrifolia (Maiden &amp; Betche), Citrus reticulata (L.), Prunus persica (L.), Prunus sp., Psidium guajava (L.), Mangifera indica (L.), Citrus sinensis (L.), Citrus sp., Rubus idaeus (L.), Musa spp. and Coffea arabica (L.)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In addition, four samples were collected in native forest, one in a pasture and 42 in plowed soil areas, totaling 201 samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>A zero to 25 cm deep soil sample was taken per sampling point and placed in 2L labeled plastic bags, stored in a Styrofoam box and transferred to the laboratory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The geographical coordinates of each sample were obtained with Garmin GPS device Etrex Vista H 2.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Nematodes were isolated in the laboratory using fifth instar Galleria mellonella Linnaeus (Lepidoptera: Pyralidae) larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Briefly, each soil sample was packed into a 250 mL a glass vial with five G. mellonella larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>These vials were covered and stored without light at 25 ± 2 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>After three to seven days, dead G. mellonella showing nematode infection symptoms were removed, rinsed in distilled water and transferred to White traps34. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The infective juveniles (IJs) were again inoculated in G. mellonella larvae for multiplication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Five G. mellonella larvae were used in a Petri dish (9 cm diameter) containing two moistened paper filters with 1.5 mL of solution with 100 JIs/larvae, for each nematode species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The samples were covered with PVC plastic and stored at 25 ± 2 °C and RH &gt; 80%35. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>After three days, dead larvae were transferred to a White trap34 at 25 ± 2 °C for seven and 15 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The IJs that left the G. mellonella carcasses were collected with distilled water every two days and stored at 18 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The nematode samples were named FCA 01 to 14 and stored in the Entomopathogenic Nematode Bank of the Nematology Laboratory at FCA/UNESP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Vials contained 1 M NaCl solution and were frozen at −80 °C until DNA extraction and EPN identification. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA was obtained for each population (FCA 01 to 14) from three individuals of each EPN, extracted using Lysis Buffer Holterman [(HLB) (800 μg proteinase K/ml, β-mercaptoethanol 1% (v/v), 0.2 M NaCl and 0.2 M Tris HCl pH 8)]36. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>A total of 25 μL of HLB was diluted in 25 μL of ultrapure water totaling 50 μL in a 0.2 mL Eppendorff tube. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>A drop of this solution (5 μL) was placed on a glass slide, where the nematodes were individually cut into three parts and placed in the same 0.2 mL tube. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The 45 μL of remaining solution was used to wash the slide and added to the tube with the sectioned nematode. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Samples were submitted to PCR at 65 °C for 2 h, 99 °C for five minutes and stored at −20 °C37. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The universal primers D2A (5′-CAAGTACCGTGAGGGAAAGTTG-3′) and D3B (5′TCGGAAGGAACCAGCTACT A-3′) were used to amplify the D2/D3 expansion segment of 28S rDNA by PCR38. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>A total of 12.5 μL of Gotaq Hot Start (Promega, São Paulo State, Brazil), with the reagents necessary for reaction: 5 U/μL Taq, 100 mM of each NTP and 25 mM MgCl2, 9.5 μL of nuclease free water (Promega), and 1 μL of each primer [10 mM] and 1 μL of cDNA from each representative population of target and non-target species, totaling 25 μL per reaction was submitted to pCR at 94 °C for seven minutes; followed by 35 cycles at 94 °C for 60 seconds, 55 °C for 60 seconds, 72 °C for 60 seconds; and 72 °C for 10 minutes39. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Five μL of PCR product was used for electrophoresis in TAE buffer40 on 1% agarose gel, stained with ethidium bromide (0.02 mg/mL), visualized and photographed under UV light. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The result of the amplification was compared to the molecular weight marker VIII. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The amplified fragments of D2/D3 expansion 28S rDNA were sequenced with the Big Dye Terminator kit (Applied Biosystems)41. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>A reagent mix containing 2 μL Big Dye, 3.2 mmol sense primers, 3.0 μL of amplified product containing 400 ng DNA and 2.0 mL of water was prepared for the product end of the PCR reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The reaction for sequencing was carried out according to manufacturer’s instructions (Applied Biosystems) with further purification of the amplified product by precipitation with isopropanol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Samples were denatured at 95 °C for three minutes and electrophoresis performed in an ABI Prism 377 DNA Sequencer unit (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The sequences were aligned and compared to nucleotide polymorphism identification with the aid of BioEdit Aligment Sequence Editor Program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The EPN population sequences were compared with other nematode species in the database (GenBank, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>) for identification based on genetic similarity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>For phylogenetic analysis, the multiple alignments between the sequences of the region D2/D3 of the different isolates were edited manually with BioEdit Sequence Aligment program when phylogenetically uninformative columns were excluded from the analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analyses were inferred using the Maximum Likelihood method based on the Kimura 2-parameter model42, considered the best fitting model for sequence evolution determined using the BIC scores (Bayesian Information Criterion) implemented in 6 MEGA program42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Initial trees for the heuristic search were obtained automatically by applying Neighbor-Join and BioNJ algorithms to a matrix of pairwise distances estimated using the Maximum Composite Likelihood (MCL) approach, and then selecting the topology with superior log likelihood value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>A discrete Gamma distribution was used to model evolutionary rate differences among sites (4 categories (+G, parameter = 2.3432)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The model variation rate allowed for some sites to be evolutionarily invariable ([+I], 19.1558% sites). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The tree was drawn to scale, with branch lengths measured in the number of substitutions per site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The analysis involved 48 nucleotide sequences, including 16 obtained in the present study (FCA01 to FCA16) and 32 from the GenBank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>All positions containing gaps and missing data were eliminated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>A total of 292 positions was obtained in the final dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Trees were sampled at intervals of 1000 generations and Caenorhabditis elegans (Brenner) was selected as outgroup. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Evolutionary analyses were conducted in 6 MEGA program42. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The nematodes obtained from White traps were inoculated in new G. mellonela larvae, which demonstrates parasitism by the isolated entomopathogen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>EPNs were found in 16 soil samples, corresponding to 8% of 201 samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Seven (35%) of 20 samples from forest plantation areas had nematodes (FCA 04, FCA 05, FCA 06, FCA 07, FCA 08, FCA 10 and FCA 15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>In annual crops, three (8.1%) out of 37 samples had nematodes: isolated FCA 11, detected in sandy soil in irrigated rice in Botucatu, São Paulo State, Brazil and isolates FCA 16 and FCA 03 in soybean crops in clay soils in Palotina, Paraná State, Brazil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Among 97 samples taken from orchards, six (6.2%) were positive for EPNs, FCA 12 isolates grown in sandy soils with wild raspberry, FCA 13 in citrus soil and FCA 14 in mango soil in São Manuel, São Paulo, Brazil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>FCA 01 and FCA 02 isolates were also found in clay soil with citrus in Botucatu, São Paulo State, Brazil (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>EPN samples were not found in plowed soil, native forest and pasture areas. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Amplification of D2/D3 expansion 28S rDNA gene of EPN isolates produced 590 bp fragments, whose sequences were deposited in the GenBank under the accession codes KRO11843 and KRO11858 (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The technique of DNA barcode sequences showed that the expansion D2/D3 28S rDNA gene of FCA 07 were identical to H. amazonensis (EU099036). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The sequences of isolates FCA 01, FCA 04, FCA 06, FCA 08, FCA 15 and FCA 16 were identical to the Metarhabditis rainai (EU195966). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The sequences of FCA 02, FCA 03 and FCA 05 isolates were identical to Oscheius tipulae (Lam &amp; Webster, 1971) (EU195969). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>FCA 09, FCA 10, FCA 11, FCA 12, FCA 13 and FCA 14 isolates were observed (99–100%) with Steinernema rarum (AF331905). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>However, these isolates formed two groups that had three polymorphisms between them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>One group with FCA 09, FCA 11 and FCA 12 isolates were similar to each other, but different in 3 bp from the group comprising FCA 10, FCA 13 and FCA 14 isolates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic tree (Fig. 2) obtained from the 48 aligned sequences of the D2/D3 expansion 28S rDNA genes in EPNs showed four distinct groups, H. amazonensis (FCA 07), S. rarum (FCA 09, FCA 10, FCA 11, FCA 12, FCA 13 and FCA 14), M. rainai (FCA 01, FCA 04, FCA 06, FCA 08, FCA 15 and FCA 16) and O. tipulae (FCA 02, FCA 03 and FCA 05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Heterorhabditis amazonensis was found in clay soil with P. parviflora in Garça, São Paulo State, Brazil; S. rarum in clay soil with Eucalyptus sp. and C. reticulata in Botucatu, São Paulo State, Brazil and in sandy soil with R. idaeus (FCA 12) and C. reticulata (FCA 13) and M. indica (FCA 14) in São Manuel, São Paulo State, Brazil. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Metarhabditis rainai was detected in clay soils cultivated with A. fraxinifolius, C. odorata, C. brasiliense and C. ecalyculata, in Garça, São Paulo State, Brazil and in those with C. reticulata, in Botucatu, São Paulo State, Brazil. Oscheius tipulae was found in soils with A. indica and C. reticulata in Botucatu, São Paulo State, Brazil and in clay soils cultivated with G. max, in Palotina, Paraná State. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Brazil (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Nematology surveys with G. mellonella baiting technique are useful to detect Steinernematidae and Heterorhabditidae species as well as other rhabditids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The molecular technique used was adequate to identify nematode isolates, enabling knowledge of its biodiversity and contributing to the detection of new isolates that may be used in biological control programs of insect pests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The sequence of D2/D3 expansion 28S rDNA gene analysis by DNA barcode technique was useful for the diagnosis of H. amazonensis, S. rarum, M. rainai and O. tipulae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic tree obtained from the 48 aligned sequences of the expansion D2/D3 EPNs with four distinct groups support the molecular identification of these nematodes isolated from soil samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>This technique has been used to diagnose plant and animal parasites and entomopathogenic nematodes with accurate and reliable results, such as one Pratylenchus penetrans (Cobb) specimen in potato41, Bursaphelenchus fungivorus (Franklin &amp; Hooper) in coconut fiber43, M. rainai (Carta &amp; Osbrink) in soil cultivated with soybean44 and Metarhabditis blumi (Sudhaus) parasitizing the ear canal of cattle45. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The finding of H. amazonensis and S. rarum in seven (3.5%) of the 201 soil samples, shows the reduced occurrence of these organisms in Brazil compared to surveys in Western Canada (20%)46, Argentina (13.2%)47 and Spain (23.3%)48. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>However, the prevalence of 3.5%, of these species, is similar to surveys in Turkey (2%, 9.1%)2549, Azores Archipelago, Portugal (3.9%)19 and Minas Gerais state, Brazil (9%)29. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The absence of EPNs in plowed soil areas suggests inadequate conditions for nematode survival, but zero EPN detection in the natural forest was unexpected and may be due the low soil samples collected in this area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>This result may also indicate the need for a higher number of samples taken at different soil depths. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The species habitat and soil type affected EPNs recovery2550. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Our samples with nematodes were obtained from, clay (75%) and sandy (25%) soils, indicating the mobility and survival of EPNs in soils rich in sand, but S. rarum occurred in clay (FCA 09 and FCA 10) and sandy (FCA, 11, 12, 13 and 14) soils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Many EPNs positive samples (89.65%) were obtained in acid soils in Nepal51. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Six EPNs were found in soils with PH &lt; 4, which is uncommon, but this has also been reported in Belgium52. Steinernema spp. are widespread in different regions and niches, whereas Heterorhabditis spp. are common in forest and river banks53. Heterorhabditis and Steinernema species were found in Sandy soils with pH &lt; 6, whereas representatives of Heterorhabditis, mainly in Sandy soils with pH &gt; 6 were found on nine islands of Açores19. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Steinernema rarum detection in sandy soil with Rubus edaeus, Mangifera indica and Oryza sativa crops and clay soils with Citrus sp. and Eucalyptus sp. demonstrates the habitat diversity of this nematode, which has been detected in Olea europea L. crops in Argentina54, Carya illinoinensis orchards (Wangenh.) in Mississippi and Louisiana State, USA28 and in sandy soils with annual and forest cultures in China55. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>In Brazil, this nematode was detected in soils with Nicotiana tabacum L., Triticum aestivum L., Glycine max and in native vegetation56. Steinernema rarum showed desiccation tolerance and freezing intolerance57, features that may be related to its adaptation to Brazilian soils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>This species has shown promise in biological control programs against Antonomus grandis Boheman (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) and Spodoptera frugiperda J.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Smith (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae)27. Metarhabditis rainai detection in fruit orchards, annual crops and forest areas shows the broad habitat diversity of this nematode. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>This species was reported in Glycine max crop in Araras, São Paulo State, Brazil44. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Other species, such as Metarhabditis blumi, are considered entomopathogenic and associated with the bacteria Alcaligenes faecalis Castellani &amp; Chalmers, Flavobacterium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>(Bernardet &amp; Grimont) and Providencia vermicola (Somvanshi), which killed G. mellonella larvae58. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Other genera, besides Heterorhabditis and Steinernema may feed on and kill insects44. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Rhabditidae nematodes are usually bacteriophages, found in insect carrions59. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>However, M. rainai was described from specimens isolated from the Oscheios tipulae termite gut60 detected in soil samples and may parasitize insects and was also found to be associated with Tipula paludosa Meigen (Diptera: Tipulidae) larvae61. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>This nematode has been frequently isolated in soil samples from around the world, enabling species population62. Oscheius genus (Rhabditidae) includes free-living, vertebrate and invertebrate parasitic species63, such as Oscheios chongmingensis (Zhang), considered a facultative entomopathogenic nematode64. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The bacteria symbiosis with this genus species is similar to that of Steinernematidae and Heterorhabditidae65. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>EPNs identified in agricultural areas in Brazil were Heterorhabditis amazonensis, Metarhabditis rainai, Oscheios tipulae and Steinernema rarum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>These species should be considered a pest biocontrol agent. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Additional Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>How to cite this article: de Brida, A. L. et al. Entomopathogenic nematodes in agricultural areas in Brazil. Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Rep. 7, 45254; doi: 10.1038/srep45254 (2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Publisher's note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>To “Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior (CAPES), Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico (CNPq)”, and “Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de Minas Gerais (FAPEMIG)”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Dr. Phillip John Villani (The University of Melbourne, Australia) revised and corrected the English language used in this manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="b1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>PoinarG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>O. &amp; GrewalP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>S. History of entomopathogenic nematology. J Nematol 44, 153–161 (2012).23482453 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Batalla-CarreraL., MortonA. &amp; Garcia-del-PinoF. Virulence of entomopathogenic nematodes and their symbiotic bacteria against the hazelnut weevil Curculio nucum. J Appl Entomol 140, 115–123 (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>LewisE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>E., CampbellJ., GriffinC., KayaH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>K. &amp; PetersA. Behavioral ecology of entomopathogenic nematodes. Biol Control 38, 66–79 (2006). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>FujimotoA., LewisE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>E., CobanogluG. &amp; Kaya1H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>K. Dispersal, infectivity and sex ratio of early- or late-emerging infective juveniles of the entomopathogenic nematode Steinernema carpocapsae. J Nematol 39, 333–337 (2007).19259508 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>CicheT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>A. &amp; EnsignJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>C. For the insect pathogen, Photorhabdus luminescens, which end of a nematode is out? Appl Environ Microb 69, 1890–1897 (2003). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>MeketeT., GauglerR., NguyenK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>B., MandefroW. &amp; TesseraM. Biogeography of entomopathogenic nematodes in Ethiopia. Nematropica 35, 31–36 (2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>KucharskaK., KucharskaD. &amp; ZajdelB. Bacteria Xenorhabdus and Photorhabdus, entomopathogenic nematodes and insects - Their role in the complex symbiont-parasite-host relationship. Postep Mikrobiol 54, 154–164 (2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>RiveraM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>J., Rodriguez-SaonaC., AlbornH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>T. &amp; KoppenhöferA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>M. Differential response of a local population of entomopathogenic nematodes to non-native herbivore induced plant volatiles (HIPV) in the laboratory and field. J Chem Ecol 42, 1259–1264 (2016).27848155 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>KayaH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>K. . Status of entomopathogenic nematodes and their symbiotic bacteria from selected countries or regions of the world. Biol Control 38, 134–155 (2006). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>GeorgisR. . Successes and failures in the use of parasitic nematodes for pest control. Biol Control 38, 103–123 (2006). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>TarascoE. . Biodiversity of entomopathogenic nematodes in Italy. J Helminthol 89, 359–366 (2015).24721783 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>TumialisD. . Occurrence of entomopathogenic nematodes in Polish soils. Cienc Rural 46, 1126–1129 (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>AndalóV., NguyenK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>B. &amp; MoinoA.Jr. Heterorhabditis amazonensis n. sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>(Rhabditida: Heterorhabditidae) from Amazonas, Brazil. Nematology 8, 853–867 (2006). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>NguyenK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>B., GinarteC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>A., LeiteL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>G., SantosJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>M. &amp; HarakavaR. Steinernema brazilense n. sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>(Rhabditida: Steinernematidae), a new entomopathogenic nematode from Mato Grosso, Brazil. J Invertebr Pathol 3, 8–20 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>DolinskiC., KamitaniF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>L., MachadoI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>R. &amp; WinterC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>E. Molecular and morphological characterization of heterorhabditid entomopathogenic nematodes from the tropical rainforest in Brazil. Mem I Oswaldo Cruz 103, 150–159 (2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>NguyenK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>B., Shapiro-IlanD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>I., FuxaJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>R., WoodB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>W., BertolottiM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>A. &amp; AdamsB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>J. Taxonomic and biological characterization of Steinernema rarum found in the Southeastern United States. J Nematol 38, 28–40 (2006).19259427 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>AndalóV., MoreiraG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>F. &amp; MoinoA.Jr. Studies of two new populations of Heteorhabditis amazonensis (Rhabditida: Heterorhabditidae). Nematropica 39, 199–211 (2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>ThanwisaiA. . Diversity of Xenorhabdus and Photorhabdus spp. and their symbiotic entomopathogenic nematodes from Thailand. PLoS ONE 7, e43835 (2012).22984446 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>KaraborkluaS., AyvazA., YilmazS., AzizogluU. &amp; AkbulutM. Native entomopathogenic nematodes isolated from Turkey and their effectiveness on pine processionary moth, Thaumetopoea wilkinsoni Tams. Int J Pest Manage 61, 3–8 (2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>CimenH., LeeM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>M., HattingJ., HazirS. &amp; StockS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>P. Steinernema tophus sp. n. (Nematoda: Steinernematidae), a new entomopathogenic nematode from South Africa. J Nematol 48, 148–158 (2016).27765988 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>HazirS., StockS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>P., KayaH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>K., KoppenhoferA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>M. &amp; KeskinN. Developmental temperature effects on five geographic isolates of the entomopathogenic nematode Steinernema feltiae (Steinernematidae). J Invertebr Pathol 77, 243–250 (2001).11437527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>KoppenhoferA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>M. &amp; FuzyE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>M. Ecological characterization of Steinernema scarabaei, a scarab-adapted entomopathogenic nematode from New Jersey. J Invertebr Pathol 83, 139–148 (2003).12788283 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Ramos-RodríguezO., CampbellJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>F. &amp; RamaswamyS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>B. Efficacy of the entomopathogenic nematode Steinernema riobrave against the stored-product insect pests Tribolium castaneum and Plodia interpunctella. Biol Control 40, 15–21 (2007). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>NageshM. . Comparative virulence of strains of entomopathogenic nematodes for management of eggplant Grey Weevil, Myllocerus subfasciatus Guerin (Coleoptera: Curculionidae). Indian J Exp Biol 54, 835–842 (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>LiX., LiuQ., LewisE. &amp; TarascoE. Activity changes of antioxidant and detoxifying enzymes in Tenebrio molitor (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae) larvae infected by the entomopathogenic nematode Heterorhabditis beicherriana (Rhabditida: Heterorhabditidae). Parasitol Res 115, 1–10 (2016).26462803 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>LeiteL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>G., MachadoL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>A., AguilleraM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>M., RodriguesR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>D. &amp; NegrisoliA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>S.Jr. Pathogenicity of Steinernema and Heterorhabditis (Nematoda: Rhabditidae) against sugarcane root spittlebug nymphs, Mahanarva fimbriolata (Hemiptera: Cercopidae). Revista da Agricultura 78, 139–148 (2002). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>LeiteL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>G., MachadoL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>A., GoulartR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>M., TavaresF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>M. &amp; Batista-FilhoA. Screening of entomopathogenic nematodes (Nemata: Rhabditida) and the efficiency of Heterorhabditis sp. against the sugar cane root spittlebug Mahanarva fimbriolata (Fabr.) (Hemiptera: Cercopidae). Neotrop Entomol 34, 785–790 (2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>BatistaE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>P., AuadA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>M., ResendeT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>T. &amp; MonteiroC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>O. Screening of entomopathogenic nematodes to control Mahanarva fimbriolata (Hemiptera: Cercopidae). Rev Colomb Entomol 37, 198–202 (2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>BatistaE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>P. &amp; AuadA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>M. Application methods of entomopathogenic nematodes for control of Mahanarva spectabilis (Hemiptera: Cercopidae). Biocontrol Sci Techn 20, 1079–1085 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>BatistaE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>P., AuadA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>M., AndalóV. &amp; MonteiroC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>O. Virulence of entomopathogenic nematodes (Rhabditida: Steinernematidae, Heterorhabditidae) to spittlebug Mahanarva spectabilis (Hemiptera: Cercopidae). Arquivos do Instituto Biológico 81, 145–149 (2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>OdendaalD., AddisonM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>F. &amp; MalanA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>P. Entomopathogenic nematodes for the control of the codling moth (Cydia pomonella L.) in field and laboratory trials. J Helminthol 90, 615–623 (2016).26484481 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>MalanA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>P. &amp; MooreS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>D. Evaluation of local entomopathogenic nematodes for the control of false codling moth, Thaumatotibia leucotreta (Meyrick, 1913), in a citrus orchard in South Africa. Afr Entomol 24, 489–501 (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Van DammeV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>M. . Efficacy of entomopathogenic nematodes against larvae of Tuta absoluta in the laboratory. Pest Manag Sci 72, 1702–1709 (2016).26620187 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>WhiteG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>F. A method for obtaining infective nematode larvae from cultures. Science 66, 302–303 (1927). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>WoodringL. &amp; KayaH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>K. Steinernematid and heterorhabditis nematodes: a handbook of techniques. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Southern Cooperative Series Bull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>331. Arkansas agric. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Statn., Fayetteville, AR, USA. 30p (1988). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>HoltermanM. . Phylum-wide analysis of SSU rDNA reveals deep phylogenetic relationships among nematode and accelerated evolution toward crown clades. Mol Biol Evol 23, 1792–1800 (2006).16790472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>ConsoliE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>A. . Desenvolvimento de diagnostico molecular para a identificação de Pratylenchus jaehni. Nematologia Brasileira 36, 62–70 (2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Al-BannaL. . Discrimination of six Pratylenchus species using PCR and species-specific primers. J Nematol 36, 142–146 (2004).19262799 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>MrácekZ. . Steinernema sichuanense n. sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>(Rhabditida, Steinernematidae) a new species of entomopathogenic nematode from the province of Sichuan, east Tibetan Mts., China. J Invertebr Pathol 93, 157–169 (2006).16934830 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>SambrookJ., FritschE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>F. &amp; ManiatisT. Composition of the electrophoresis buffer In Molecular cloning, a laboratory manual (ed. FordN. .) 66–67, Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, 1989. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b41"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>OliveiraC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>G. . Diagnose de Aphelenchoides fragariae e Pratylenchus spp. pela aplicação da tecnologia do código de barras do DNA. Nematologia Brasileira 33, 218–225 (2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b42"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>TamuraK. . MEGA6: Molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0. Mol Biol Evol 30, 2725–2729 (2013).24132122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b43"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>OliveiraC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>G. . Caracterizações morfológica e molecular de Bursaphelenchus fungivorus (Nematoda: Aphelenchida), detectado pela primeira vez no Brasil. Nematologia Brasileira 35, 3–4 (2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b44"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>TomaziniD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>M. . Análises biométrica e molecular de isolado brasileiro de Rhabditis rainai (Nematoda: Rhabditida). Nematologia Brasileira 37, 1–2 (2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b45"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>BossiP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>V. . Molecular identification and phylogenetic analysis of Metarhabditis blumi (Nematoda: Rhabditida). Vet Parasitol 214, 1–2 (2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b46"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>MrácekZ. &amp; WebsterJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>M. Survey of Heterorhabditidae and Steinernematidae (Rhabditida, Nematoda) in western Canada. J Nematol 25, 710–717 (1993).19279830 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b47"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>StockS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>P. Natural population of entomopathogenic nematodes in the Pampean region of Argentina. Nematropica 25, 143–148 (1995). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b48"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Garcia del PinoF. &amp; PalomoA. Natural occurrence of entomopathogenic nematodes (Rhabditida: Steinernematidae and Heterorhabditidae) in Spanish soils. J Invertebr Pathol 68, 84–90 (1996).8812576 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b49"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>ErbasZ. . Isolation and identification of entomopathogenic nematodes (Nematoda: Rhabditida) from the Eastern Black Sea region and their biocontrol potential against Melolontha melolontha (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae) larva. Turk J Agric For 38, 187–197 (2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b50"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>KaryN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>E., NiknamG., GriffinC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>T., MohammadiS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>A. &amp; MoghaddamM. A survey of entomopathogenic nematodes of the families Steinernematidae and Heterorhabditidae (Nematoda: Rhabditida) in the north-west of Iran. Nematology 11, 107–116 (2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b51"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Khatri-ChhetriH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>B., WaeyenbergeL., ManandharH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>K. &amp; MoensM. Natural occurrence and distribution of entomopathogenic nematodes (Steinernematidae and Heterorhabditidae) in Nepal. J Invertebr Pathol 103, 74–78 (2010).19836397 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b52"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>MiduritiJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>S., WaeyenbergeL. &amp; MoensM. Natural distribution of entomopathogenic nematode (Heterorhabditidae and Steinernematidae) in Belgian soils. Russ J Nematol 5, 55–65 (1997). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b53"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>GriffinC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>T., ChaeraniR., FallonD., ReidA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>P. &amp; DownesM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>J. Occurrence and distribution of entomopathogenic nematodes Steinernema spp. and Heterorhabditis indica in Indonesia. J Helminthol 74, 143–150 (2000).10881285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b54"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>DoucetA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>M. . Consideraciones acerca de nematodos entomófagos (Mermithidae, Heterorhabditidae, Steinernematidae) de la provincia de Córdoba. Boletin de la Academia Nacional de Ciencias 66, 75–85 (2001). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b55"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>WangH. . Natural occurrence of entomopathogenic nematodes in Liaoning (Northeast China). J Asia-Pac Entomol 17, 399–406 (2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b56"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>NegrisoliC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>B. . Survey of entomopathogenic nematodes (Rhabditida: Heterorhabditidae, Steinernematidae) in Rio Grande do Sul, State, Brazil. Nematologia Brasileira 34, 189–197 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b57"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Shapiro-IlanD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>I., BrownI. &amp; LewisE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>E. Freezing and desiccation tolerance in entomopathogenic nematodes: Diversity and correlation of traits. J Nematol 46, 27–34 (2014).24643501 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b58"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>ParkH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>W. . Effects of associated bacteria on the pathogenicity and reproduction of the insect-parasitic nematode Rhabditis blumi (Nematoda: Rhabditida). Can J Microbiol 57, 750–758 (2011).21867444 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b59"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>StockS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>P., CaicedoA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>M. &amp; CalatayudP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>A. Rhabditis (Oscheius) colombiana n. sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>(Nematoda: Rhabditidae), a necronemic associate of the subterranean burrower bug Cyrtomenus bergi (Hemiptera: Cydnidae) from the Cauca Valley, Colombia. Nematology 7, 363–373 (2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b60"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>CartaL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>K. &amp; OsbrinkW. Rhabditis rainai n. sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>(Nematoda: Rhabditida) associated with the Formosan subterranean termite, Coptotermes formosanus (Isoptera: Rhinotermitidae). Nematology 7, 863–879 (2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b61"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>BailleD., BarriereA. &amp; FelixM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>A. Oscheius tipulae, a widespread hermaphroditic soil nematode, displays a higher genetic diversity and geographical structure than Caenorhaditis elegans. Mol Ecol 17, 1523–1534 (2008).18284567 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b62"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>FelixM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>A. RNA interference in nematode and the chance that favored Sydney Brenner. Journal of Biology 7, 1–34 (2008).18226191 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b63"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>ParkinsonJ. . A transcriptomic analysis of the phylum nematode. Nat Genet 36, 1259–1267 (2004).15543149 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b64"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>JarosováA., PuzaV. &amp; ZurovcováM. The complete mitochondrial genome of the facultative entomopathogenic nematode Oscheius chongmingensis (Rhabditida: Rhabditidae). Mitochondrial DNA 11, 1–2 (2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b65"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>AnjusK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>M. . Purification and identification of an antibacterial protein from the symbiotic bacteria associated with novel entomopathogenic nematode, Rhabditis (Oscheius) sp. World J Microb Biot 31, 621–632 (2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>The authors declare no competing financial interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Author Contributions A.L.B., J.M.O.R., C.M.G.O., and B.M.C.C. performed experiments, and analyzed the data; J.E.S., and J.C.Z. analyzed the data; A.L.B., J.E.S., J.C.Z., L.G.L., C.M.G.O., and S.R.S.W. designed the experiments and wrote the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Geographical distribution of the sampling sites (x) in São Paulo and Paraná States, Brazil.</title><p><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>EPNs positive samples (.) (ESC.: 1: 10000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>AutoCAD SP2 (2015) [vJ.210.0.0]. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.Autodesk.com.br/products/autocad/overview">http://www.Autodesk.com.br/products/autocad/overview</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep45254-f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic tree showing the relationship between the entomopathogenic nematodes isolated (in bold) and their similarity with those from the GenBank based on expansion D2/D3 sequences 28S rDNA region.</title><p><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Caenorhabditis elegans was used as outgroup. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep45254-f2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap position="float" id="t1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Code (Code), species, sampling site (Site), soil type (S), crops, geographical coordinates (coordinates) and collection date (date) of entomopathogenic nematodes (species) in soils with annual, fruit and forest plantation crops in Brazil (2010 to 2013).</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Code </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Species </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Site </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>S </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Crops </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Coordinates </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Date </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>FCA01 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>M. rainai </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Bo (SP) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Citrus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>S773173; W7484343 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Oct/2011 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>FCA02 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>O. tipulae </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Bo (SP) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Citrus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>S773250; W7484319 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Oct/2011 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>FCA03 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>O. tipulae </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Pa (PR) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>G. max </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>S4172381; W3521906 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Jan/2013 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>FCA04 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>M. rainai </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Ga (SP) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>A. fraxinifolius </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>S763062; W77469943 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Jan/2013 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>FCA05 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>O. tipulae </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Ga (SP) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>A. indica </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>S640610; W7544268 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Jan/2013 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>FCA06 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>M. rainai </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Ga (SP) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>C. odorata </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>S640581; W7544259 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Jan/2013 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>FCA07 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>H. amazonensis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Ga (SP) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>P. parviflora </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>S640551; W7544214 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Jan/2013 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>FCA08 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>M. rainai </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Ga (SP) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>C. brasiliense </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>S640467; W7544384 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Jan/2013 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>FCA09 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>S. rarum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Bo (SP) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Citrus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>S766468; W7474631 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Sept/2012 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>FCA10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>S. rarum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Bo (SP) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Eucalyptus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>S764574; W7472130 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Sept/2012 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>FCA11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>S. rarum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>Bo (SP) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>S </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>O. sativa </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>S766897; W7474367 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Sept/2012 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>FCA12 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>S. rarum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>SM (SP) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>S </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>R. idaeus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>S749498; W7479197 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>Oct/2012 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>FCA13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>S. rarum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>SM (SP) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>S </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Citrus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>S749477; W7479125 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Oct/2012 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>FCA14 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>S. rarum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>SM (SP) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>S </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>M. indica </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>S749436; W7479022 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Oct/2012 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>FCA15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>M. rainai </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Ga (SP) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>C. ecalyculata </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>S640534; W7544537 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Jan/2013 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>FCA16 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>M. rainai </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Pa (PR) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>G. max </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>S4211166; W3491260 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Jan/2013 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t1-fn1"><p>Species: <italic>Metarhabditis (M.</italic>), <italic>Oscheius (O.</italic>), <italic>Heterorhabditis (H.</italic>), <italic>Steinernema (S.</italic>), Site: Botucatu (Bo), Palotina (Pa), Garça (Ga), São Manuel (SM), clay soil (C), Sandy soil (S). Date: Octuber (Oct), January (Jan), September (Sept).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
