<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?properties manuscript?><?origin nihpa?><?iso-abbr C. R. Biol.?><?submitter-system nihms?><?submitter-canonical-name Elsevier?><?submitter-canonical-id ELSEVIERAM?><?submitter-userid 8068823?><?submitter-authority myNCBI?><?submitter-login elsevieram?><?submitter-name Author support, Elsevier?><?domain nihpa?><?ppubseason Jul-Aug?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101140040</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">27041</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">C R Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">C. R. Biol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Comptes rendus biologies</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1631-0691</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1768-3238</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5393452</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27291506</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.crvi.2016.05.010</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">nihpa857889</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Vertebrate sex-determining genes play musical chairs </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Qiaowei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>Jennifer</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref rid="FN2" ref-type="author-notes">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bertho</surname><given-names>Sylvain</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Herpin</surname><given-names>Amaury</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Catherine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Postlethwait</surname><given-names>John H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schartl</surname><given-names>Manfred</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">d</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guiguen</surname><given-names>Yann</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>a</label>Inra, Fish Physiology and Genomics Laboratory, 35042 Rennes, France</aff><aff id="A2"><label>b</label>University of Wuerzburg, Physiological Chemistry, Biocenter, 97074 Würzburg, Germany</aff><aff id="A3"><label>c</label>University of Oregon, Institute of Neuroscience, Eugene, OR 97403, USA</aff><aff id="A4"><label>d</label>Comprehensive Cancer Center Mainfranken, University Hospital, 97080 Würzburg, Germany</aff><aff id="A5"><label>e</label>Texas Institute for Advanced Study and Department of Biology, Texas A&amp;M University, College Station, Texas 77843, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="FN1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. <email>yann.guiguen@rennes.inra.fr</email> (Y. Guiguen)</corresp><fn id="FN2" fn-type="present-address"><label>1</label><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Present address: Department of Systematic Biology, EBC, Uppsala University, Norbyägen 18D, 752 36 Uppsala, Sweden. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jul-Aug</season><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>339</volume><issue>7-8</issue><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><permissions><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Sexual reproduction is one of the most highly conserved processes in evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>However, the genetic and cellular mechanisms making the decision of whether the undifferentiated gonad of animal embryos develops either towards male or female are manifold and quite diverse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>In vertebrates, sex-determining mechanisms range from environmental to simple or complex genetic mechanisms and different mechanisms have evolved repeatedly and independently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>In species with simple genetic sex-determination, master sex-determining genes lying on sex chromosomes drive the gonadal differentiation process by switching on a developmental program, which ultimately leads to testicular or ovarian differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>So far, very few sex-determining genes have been identified in vertebrates and apart from mammals and birds, these genes are apparently not conserved over a larger number of related orders, families, genera, or even species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>To fill this knowledge gap and to better explore genetic sex-determination, we propose a strategy (RAD-Sex) that makes use of next-generation sequencing technology to identify genetic markers that define sex-specific segments of the male or female genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>Sex-determination</kwd><kwd>Evolution</kwd><kwd>Vertebrates</kwd><kwd>Fish</kwd><kwd>Next-generation sequencing</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="S1"><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P2"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Sex has been termed the “queen of problems in evolutionary biology”, and how sex is determined in the animal kingdom has always been a major question with “debates on the origin of the sexes that took place long before the beginning of the scientific era” [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Indeed, since the beginning of this “scientific era”, important knowledge has been acquired on this topic with, for instance within the quite recent “genetics era”, the important discovery of sex chromosomes, followed by the identification of the master gene governing the acquisition of the male sex in human and in mouse [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Despite huge efforts in the last decades, however, our knowledge of master genes controlling genetic sex-determination has remained limited [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The relative scarcity of information on sex-determination (SD) genes is mainly due to major scientific and technical barriers that hinder the precise identification of these SD genes in many species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Classical approaches for the characterization of SD genes have always relied on the intimate knowledge of a group of specialists working on very few species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Their success has often been guided either by educated guess and candidate gene approaches [4,5], or by tedious searches for sex-linked markers with various time-consuming methods [6–9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The relatively few species investigated now with regards to SD genes have been selected based on practical interests (for instance species easy to maintain in captivity [8–12]) or economical (for instance important aquaculture species [5,13–15]) and these species always had preexisting genetic and/or genomic information available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>There is then an urgent need to address the question of the evolution of SD genes using a large-scale, unbiased approach that would not rely on or need such previous knowledge. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="S2"><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>A glimpse into sex-determination and SD genes evolution in vertebrates with a focus on fish species </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P3"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The field of evolution of sex-determination and SD genes in vertebrates has long been shaped by knowledge gathered in mammals, because previously this was the only group for which the master SD gene, SRY, was known [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The generally accepted hypothesis for the mechanism by which an SD gene can evolve, namely by allelic diversification of an autosomal gene towards a male or female sex-promoting function, and subsequent maintenance of the male-specifying allele as a male dominant SD gene on the proto-Y chromosome, was satisfied by SRY and its supposed progenitor SOX3 [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In 1999, dmrt1 was found as a candidate gene for SD in chicken, which proposed a different mechanism, namely dosage sensitivity [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In 2002, the first fish SD gene was identified in the medaka, Oryzias latipes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Unexpectedly, this gene, called dmrt1bY or dmy [7,10], arose by a gene duplication event from the autosomal dmrt1a gene being transposed to the proto-Y, adding another evolutionary mechanism for the emergence of an SD gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Full sequencing of the male-specific region of the Y chromosome (MSY), the first to be known after the human Y, revealed that several additional predictions of the general theory of Y chromosome evolution were also not fulfilled, like stepwise diversification on an autosome, recombination suppression, degeneration of Y-linked genes, and accumulation of male-favoring genes [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>This finding raised doubts about a unifying concept for the evolution of SD genes and heterogametic sex chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P4"><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Fish are uniquely suited to study the evolution of sex-determination and SD genes (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Comprising about half of the 60,000 species of vertebrates, fish show also the greatest variety of sex-determination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Unisexuality, simultaneous and consecutive hermaphroditism, environmental, and genetic sex-determination are found in different, often closely related species and the distribution of various mechanisms follows no obvious phylogenetic pattern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>With respect to genetic SD, it became quickly clear after its first discovery that dmrt1bY of medaka is not the master SD gene of fish in general [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Despite huge efforts over more than a decade, SD genes of only a few more species have been added to this list, and all those species have strong monogenic sex-determination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In a sister species to medaka, O. luzonensis, and also in sablefish, Anoplopoma fimbria, allelic variations of a TGFβ member gene named gsdfY determines male development [8,13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>In Takifugu rubripes (pufferfish) as well, allelic variation at a single nucleotide position of the amh-receptor 2 gene, again a downstream component of the SD cascade in other vertebrates, controls phenotypic sex [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In the Patagonian pejerry, Odontesthes hatcheri, a Y-linked duplicate of the amh gene drives male sex-determination [5], a situation that mirrors the evolutionary scenario of the medaka SD gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The same SD gene is also found in the tilapia, Oreochromis niloticus, but in that species it is a Y chromosome missense SNP on a tandem duplication of amh that drives sex-determination [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, another TGFβ member, namely gdf6Y has also been found as a potential SD in the killifish Nothobranchius furzeri [11], suggesting that members from the TGFβ pathway are often recruited as SD genes in vertebrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>In rainbow trout, Oncorhynchus mykiss, gene duplication and neofunctionalization led to the emergence of the SD gene [14], but totally unexpected and contrary to the situation in all other vertebrates for which information on proven or candidate SD genes exists, the duplicated gene sdY is not derived from a previously known component of the SD cascade, but from the interferon regulatory factor 9, which normally functions in the context of immunity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P5"><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The current state of knowledge about the evolution of SD in vertebrates – last but not least influenced by the recent findings in fish – has resulted in a very unsatisfying situation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>With the examples of male-biasing SD genes identified to date, it is rather impossible to derive a comprehensive understanding of processes and mechanisms that lead to the evolution of new SD genes and to evaluate the prevalence and general relevance of different systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>We do not know whether dosage sensitivity of master SD genes is an enigmatic case that is restricted to the avian lineage or is used more generally. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Gene duplication and neofunctionalization is appearing now as a more frequent process to create novel SD genes, but the three fish species in which it has been found might be special in some way and bias our view by chance due to the low number of known SD genes in general. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>It can also be asked whether teleost fish that experienced in their evolutionary history whole-genome duplication and certain lineage-specific additional ones profit from this genomic situation with respect to the evolution of new SD genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Regarding female heterogamety, there is so far no example of a predicted dominant female-determining SD gene in fish that could add to the single case of Xenopus laevis, where dominant-negative action of a W-linked truncated dmrt1 gene is proposed to suppress a postulated default male development in WZ frogs [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>A totally unresolved complication comes from several reports where, even in cases that appear to be clear monogenic SD, polymorphic autosomal modifier genes or environmental influences can modify or override the sex-chromosomal mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>It can only be vaguely hypothesized that these findings indicate transition states between SD switches, and again the prevalence of such situations is absolutely unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>It is obvious that the first step towards a better understanding of SD mechanisms and how new SD genes evolve is to characterize SD genes in more species, study their inheritance, and eventually illuminate their mode of action. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S3"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The RAD-Sex approach: a Genome Wide Association Study (GWAS) screening for exploring the diversity of sex-determination systems in fish </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P6"><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Restriction Associated DNA tags (RAD-tags) are sequences adjacent to restriction enzyme cutting sites that can be assayed by a next-generation sequencing technique known as RAD sequencing method (RAD-seq) [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>RAD-seq has been shown to be an extremely powerful method for sampling the genomes of multiple individuals in a population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Because it does not require preliminary information on the genetics or the genome of the studied species, this approach is especially interesting for developing genetic analyses in the context of non-model organisms [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>This technique was recently applied with success to search for sex-specific sequences in Gecko lizards [20] and for a sex-determining locus in zebrafish, in which strain-specific sex-determination systems were characterized [21,22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>To serve as an additional proof of principle, we applied this approach to the medaka, Oryzias latipes, which has a strong well-characterized genetic SD system [7,10,17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The main idea was to investigate if RAD-seq was equally efficient in identifying sex-specific sequences close to dmrt1bY, the known SD gene in that species [7,10], using as starting biological material individuals from an outbred population of fish and not a genetic mapping family panel as was used in the case of the zebrafish [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>To that end, fin clips were sampled from 31 phenotypic males and 32 phenotypic females of the Carbio strain of medaka. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA was extracted from these samples and RAD library construction was carried out with each individual given a distinct barcode. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Samples were sequenced in two lanes of Illumina HiSeq2000 using single-end 100-bp reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>This dataset analysis allowed us to characterize more than 600 sex-polymorphic RAD-tag sequences among an overall total of 120,000 genetic markers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Most of these sex-polymorphic sequences map to the central portion of medaka linkage group LG1, the region that distinguishes the Y from the X chromosome (see Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Among these sex-polymorphic RAD-tag sequences, 58 were sex-specific, i.e. the sequences were only present in males and totally absent in all the females. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>When mapped onto the medaka genome, 22 of these sex-specific RAD-tags were found to be on the Y chromosome (LG1) and 30 on unordered scaffolds, probably due to an incomplete assembly of the medaka Y chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Among these sex-specific RAD-tag sequences, nine mapped to the Y non-recombinant sex-specific region (Gen-Bank ID: AP006153) including two sequences that were less than 1 kb downstream of the 5′ end of the dmrt1bY medaka sex-determining gene (GenBank ID: AY129241) [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>These results clearly demonstrate that the RAD-Sex approach is highly efficient because it enabled the identification of sex-specific sequences located very close to the previously known SD gene even in a GWAS that does not allow a simultaneous genetic mapping of the RAD-tags. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>It should be noted, that our analysis, although conducted on a species with a sequenced genome, did not use the genome sequence for the analysis of sex-associated RAD-tags: the genome sequence only provided validation of the proof of principle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>This comparatively inexpensive approach can thus be applied to multiple species in a relatively high throughput project, without the need for obtaining biological materials from controlled genetic crosses that could be difficult to obtain in some species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>This approach is also possible in species with no genetic or genomic information available, thus providing a special opportunity to develop an evolutionary-based project that can investigate the sex-determining system in a vast array of species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P7"><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Applying this approach to a large panel of species should provide a first evolutionary picture of SD genes answering simple but important questions like: how many evolutionary innovations can be characterized i.e., novel SD genes, how many “usual suspects”, i.e. duplications of genes already known for their implication in the sex differentiation cascade, and how prevalent are gene duplications as primary events generating novel SD genes and thus how relevant is this evolutionary scenario beside the classical hypothesis of allelic diversification and the so far enigmatic situation of SD by gene dosage to explain the diversity of SD mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>These questions on the evolution of SD genes have currently only been addressed for a narrow phylogenetic range, but never for a broad spectrum of taxa that represent a considerable fraction of the diversity and adaptations of a whole class of the chordate phylum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Such information will inform an essential question in evolutionary biology, foster genetics and developmental biology, and last but not least provide immediately useful information for better management of economically important fish species in fisheries and aquaculture. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="S4"><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P8"><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Sex-determination is a very basal and ubiquitous developmental process and the fact that it is so variable even between closely related organisms poses many fascinating questions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>A number of scenarios and hypotheses have been put forward to explain which evolutionary forces could favor such transitions and turnovers (for a review, see [23]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>They range from fitness advantages of a new sex-determination or its linkage to genes that are favorable to one sex or antagonistic to the other sex, over mutational load on the old, disappearing sex-determination gene to scenarios that consider that neutral or non-adaptive processes of genetic drift, mutation and recombination can be instrumental in creating new sex-determination systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>For all these hypotheses, which appear to a certain extent opposing or even contradictory, examples to support them can be found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>A single one obviously cannot explain all the different cases of sex-determination systems and the many instances of turnovers and transitions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Rather than being alternatives, they may be complementary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>To further our understanding of the trajectories that lead to the evolution of diverse sex-determination mechanisms and sex chromosomes we need more detailed molecular knowledge about the molecular biology of these various mechanisms and about the ecology and population genetics under which they occur. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack id="S5"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>This project is supported by funds from the “Agence nationale de la recherche” (France) and the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (ANR/DFG, PhyloSex project, 2014–2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Funding: FACAD. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN3"><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Disclosure of interest </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="R1"><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>1MittwochUSex-determination in mythology and historyArq Bras Endocrinol Metabol49200571316544030 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R2"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>2KoopmanPThe molecular biology of SRY and its role in sex-determination in mammalsReprod Fertil Dev719957137228711208 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R3"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>3GravesJAMHow to evolve new vertebrate sex-determining genesDev Dyn Off Publ Am Assoc Anat2422013354359 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R4"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>4YoshimotoSIkedaNIzutsuYShibaTTakamatsuNItoMOpposite roles of DMRT1 and its W-linked paralogue, DM-W, in sexual dimorphism of Xenopus laevis: implications of a ZZ/ZW-type sex-determining systemDevelopment13720102519252620573695 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R5"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>5HattoriRSMuraiYOuraMMasudaSMajhiSKSakamotoTA Y-linked anti-Müllerian hormone duplication takes over a critical role in sex-determinationProc Natl Acad Sci U S A10920122955295922323585 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R6"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>6KamiyaTKaiWTasumiSOkaAMatsunagaTMizunoNA trans-species missense SNP in Amhr2 is associated with sex-determination in the tiger pufferfish, Takifugu rubripes (fugu)PLoS Genet82012e100279822807687 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R7"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>7MatsudaMNagahamaYShinomiyaASatoTMatsudaCKobayashiTDMY is a Y-specific DM-domain gene required for male development in the medaka fishNature417200255956312037570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R8"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>8MyoshoTOtakeHMasuyamaHMatsudaMKurokiYFujiyamaATracing the emergence of a novel sex-determining gene in medaka, Oryzias luzonensisGenetics191201216317022367037 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R9"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>9TakehanaYMatsudaMMyoshoTSusterMLKawakamiKShinITCo-option of Sox3 as the male-determining factor on the Y chromosome in the fish Oryzias dancenaNat Commun52014415724948391 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R10"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>10NandaIKondoMHornungUAsakawaSWinklerCShimizuAA duplicated copy of DMRT1 in the sex-determining region of the Y chromosome of the medaka, Oryzias latipesProc Natl Acad Sci U S A992002117781178312193652 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R11"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>11ReichwaldKPetzoldAKochPDownieBRHartmannNPietschSInsights into sex chromosome evolution and aging from the genome of a short-lived fishCell16320151527153826638077 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R12"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>12MatsudaMSex-determination in fish: lessons from the sex-determining gene of the teleost medaka, Oryzias latipesDev Growth Differ45200339740314706065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R13"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>13RondeauEBMessmerAMSandersonDSJantzenSGvon SchalburgKRMinkleyDRGenomics of sablefish (Anoplopoma fimbria): expressed genes, mitochondrial phylogeny, linkage map and identification of a putative sex geneBMC Genomics14201345223829495 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R14"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>14YanoAGuyomardRNicolBJouannoEQuilletEKloppCAn immune-related gene evolved into the master sex-determining gene in rainbow trout, Oncorhynchus mykissCurr Biol2220121423142822727696 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R15"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>15LiMSunYZhaoJShiHZengSYeKA tandem duplicate of anti-Müllerian hormone with a missense SNP on the Y chromosome is essential for male sex-determination in Nile Tilapia, Oreochromis niloticusPLoS Genet112015e100567826588702 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R16"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>16NandaIShanZSchartlMBurtDWKoehlerMNothwangH300 million years of conserved synteny between chicken Z and human chromosome 9Nat Genet21199925825910080173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R17"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>17HerpinASchartlMMolecular mechanisms of sex-determination and evolution of the Y chromosome: insights from the medakafish (Oryzias latipes)Mol Cell Endocrinol3062009515819481684 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R18"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>18MillerMRDunhamJPAmoresACreskoWAJohnsonEARapid and cost-effective polymorphism identification and genotyping using restriction site-associated DNA (RAD) markersGenome Res17200724024817189378 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R19"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>19AmoresACatchenJFerraraAFontenotQPostlethwaitJHGenome evolution and meiotic maps by massively parallel DNA sequencing: spotted gar, an outgroup for the teleost genome duplicationGenetics188201179980821828280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R20"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>20GambleTCoryellJEzazTLynchJScantleburyDPZarkowerDRestriction site-associated DNA sequencing (RAD-seq) reveals an extraordinary number of transitions among Gecko sex-determining systemsMol Biol Evol3220151296130925657328 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R21"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>21AndersonJLRodríguez MaríABraaschIAmoresAHohenlohePBatzelPMultiple sex-associated regions and a putative sex chromosome in zebrafish revealed by RAD mapping and population genomicsPloS One72012e4070122792396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R22"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>22WilsonCAHighSKMcCluskeyBMAmoresAYanYTitusTAWild sex in zebrafish: loss of the natural sex determinant in domesticated strainsGenetics19820141291130825233988 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R23"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>23HerpinASchartlMPlasticity of gene-regulatory networks controlling sex-determination: of masters, slaves, usual suspects, newcomers, and usurpatorsEMBO Rep1620151260127426358957 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Vertebrate sex-determining genes play musical chairs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Evolution and diversity of sex-determining genes in vertebrates (see text for details). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Species or groups of species with an already known or highly suspected sex-determining gene are shown in black boxes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Blue triangles represent master sex-determining genes with a certain degree of evolutionary conservation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Red triangles represent group of species with a high turnover of sex-determining genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The red star shows the position of the teleost-specific whole-genome duplication. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms857889f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Distribution of Restriction Associated DNA-tag (RAD-tag) markers along the 24 chromosomes of the medaka sequenced genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The significantly sex-biased markers identified mid LG1 (chromosome Y) as the location of the sex-determining locus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Markers retained in this analysis have been scored in at least 25 individuals within the population. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms857889f2"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
