<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5554225</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">8510</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-08510-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>An effective combination of whole-exome sequencing and runs of homozygosity for the diagnosis of primary ciliary dyskinesia in consanguineous families </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Ting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Zhi-Ping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Hua-Mei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Dong-yuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>liu</surname><given-names>Lv</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Xin-Gang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Ping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Hong</given-names></name><address><email>Luohong1003@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Yi-Feng</given-names></name><address><email>yyf627@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0379 7164</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.216417.7</institution-id><institution>Department of Respiratory Medicine, the Second Xiangya Hospital, </institution><institution>Central South University, </institution></institution-wrap>Changsha, Hunan 410011 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0379 7164</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.216417.7</institution-id><institution>Research Unit of Respiratory Disease, </institution><institution>Central South University, </institution></institution-wrap>Changsha, Hunan 410011 China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0379 7164</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.216417.7</institution-id><institution>Diagnosis and Treatment Center of Respiratory Disease, </institution><institution>Central South University, </institution></institution-wrap>Changsha, Hunan 410011 China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Central South University Center for Clinical Gene Diagnosis and Treatment, the Second Xiangya Hospital, Central South University, Changsha, Hunan 410011 China </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0379 7164</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.216417.7</institution-id><institution>Department of Cardiovascular Surgery, the Second Xiangya Hospital, </institution><institution>Central South University, </institution></institution-wrap>Changsha, Hunan 410011 China </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Chang Sha Central Hospital, Changsha, Hunan 410011 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>7905</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>7</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Primary ciliary dyskinesia (PCD) is clinically characterized by neonatal respiratory distress, chronic sinusitis, bronchiectasis and infertility, and situs inversus in 50% of the patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>PCD is a result of mutations in genes encoding proteins involved in ciliary function, and is primarily inherited in an autosomal recessive fashion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Diagnosis of PCD is often a challenging task due to its high clinical and genetic heterogeneities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we attempted to use whole-exome sequencing (WES) combined with runs of homozygosity (ROH) approaches to identify the genetic defects in four Chinese consanguineous families with clinical PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We successfully identified three recently acknowledged PCD genes: DYX1C1, CCNO and ARMC4, and one well-characterized PCD gene, DNAI1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Our study provides compelling evidence that WES in combination with ROH analysis is an efficient diagnostic tool for identifying genetic causes of PCD in consanguineous families. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, our work expands the genetic mutation spectrum in PCD, and provides the additional tools to better serve the counseling of the families with PCD. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par2"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Primary ciliary dyskinesia (PCD; MIM: 244400) is a clinically heterogeneous disorder due to impairment of ciliary function and has an estimated prevalence of approximately 1 in 15,000–20,000 individuals1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Ineffective cilium movement of cells lining the upper and lower respiratory tracts may result in limited mucus clearance, leading to neonatal respiratory distress, rhinitis, sinusitis, rhinorrhea, chronic cough, recurrent respiratory infections and bronchiectasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Male infertility may occur as functional cilia are required for proper sperm flagella function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Approximately 50% of the PCD patients present with situs inversus due to the cilium dysfunction during early embryonic development1, 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par3"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Currently, there is no “gold standard” reference test for PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The traditional diagnosis of PCD largely depends on the careful evaluation of clinical features, ciliary function, ultrastructural defects, nasal nitric oxide (nNO) levels, and genetic analysis2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>However, some of these diagnostic approaches are not easily accessible and require specialized expertise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Some tests are challenging due to the heterogeneity of the disease, including atypical or overlapping phenotypes, which could lead to incorrect clinical diagnosis and suboptimal treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par4"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>PCD is primarily a rare autosomal recessive disorder caused by mutations in genes encoding proteins involved in cilium function1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>As a Mendelian genetic disorder, PCD can be identified through genetic analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Since the first identified disease gene DNAI1 in PCD patients with immotile respiratory cilia in 19993, remarkable efforts have been made to define the genetic cause of PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>So far, genetic mutations in over 40 genes account for an estimated 65% of individuals1, 4–10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>However, approximately 35% of PCD individuals remain genetic elusive11, highlighting the genetic heterogeneity and challenges of using conventional targeted gene panels based on the currently known PCD-associated genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Recently, WES in combination with multiple strategies, including runs of homozygosity (ROH)12, 13, linkage analysis14, and filtering of reported disease-related genes15–18, have shown tremendous potentials for genetic diagnosis and for identification of novel variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In some cases, these strategies appear to be the only way for achieving a precise diagnosis19. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par5"><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of PCD has a higher rate in consanguineous families20 and has been occasionally reported in China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>We hypothesize that the consanguineous families with PCD provide a great opportunity to recover novel causative PCD gene(s). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we examine the clinical diagnosis of PCD with WES in combination with ROH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Six PCD patients from four consanguineous families were analyzed using WES, and a total of four PCD causative genes, CCNO, DYX1C1, ARMC4 and DNAI1 were identified in these consanguineous families. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Patients and subjects </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par6"><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The study protocol was approved by the Review Board of the Second Xiangya Hospital of Central South University in China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Informed consent was obtained from all subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed in accordance with the relevant guidelines and regulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Four consanguineous families with PCD were recruited, in which one individual was affected in families 1 and 4, and two individuals were affected in families 2 and 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The medical records of the subjects, including pulmonary, paranasal sinus, abdominal computed tomography (CT) (Fig. 1 and Supplementary Figure 1), nNO level21, and transmission electron microscopy (TEM) findings (Supplementary Figure 2) were documented and reviewed.Figure 1Clinical features of PCD in the consanguineous families. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The patient (P6 from family 4) presented the classical clinical features of PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>(A) The chest computed tomography (CT) scan showed bronchiectasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>(B) The paranasal sinus CT scan of the patient showed apparent rhinosinusitis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Typical situs inversus is shown in C, D. CT images of the remaining patients are shown in Supplementary Figure 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>WES and filtering </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par7"><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Blood samples (3–5 ml) were obtained from the affected probands and their family members (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA was extracted using the DNeasy Blood &amp; Tissue Kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Whole-exome capture and high-throughput sequencing (HTS) were performed by the Novogene Bioinformatics Institute (Beijing, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Briefly, whole exomes were captured using the Agilent SureSelect Human All ExonV5 Kit (Agilent, California, USA) and sequenced on the Illumina HiSeq. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>2500 platform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The sequencing reads were aligned to the human reference genome (UCSC hg19), and the details of the sequencing data are provided in Supplementary Table S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Single nucleotide variants (SNVs) and short insertions and deletions (InDels) were filtered as follows: (i) Variants within intergenic, intronic, and UTR regions and synonymous mutations were excluded from subsequent analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>(ii) High-frequency (minor allele frequency &gt;0.01) polymorphisms found in the 1000 Genomes Project, ESP6500, Exac, and Novogene Bioinformatics Institute in-house exomeSeq databases were excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>(iii) Based on the principle that the identification of a new disease-causing gene should exclude known causal genes17, variants in the 40 PCD-related genes (Supplementary Table S2) were selected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>This approach prevented the omission of any compound heterozygotes of known genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>(iv) Due to the examination of consanguineous families, ROH12, 13 analysis was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>ROH analysis is an important approach because it can effectively exclude false-positive variants in the case of a large deletion on the other allele. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The detailed steps of filtering are shown in Supplementary Figure 3.Figure 2Pedigree of the families and the Sanger DNA sequencing chromatogram of the patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Roman numerals refer to generations, and individuals within a generation are numbered from left to right. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Black circles/squares are affected, and white circles/squares are unaffected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Arrows indicate the probands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>P1-P6 are the probands (P1 refers to IV-4 in family 1; P2 and P3 refer to IV-1 and IV-2 in family 2, respectively; P4 and P5 refer to IV-2 and IV-3 in family 3, respectively; and P6 refers to IV-5 in family 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Seven large circles (in red) represent the 7 individuals who underwent WES. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The Sanger sequencing chromatogram of the affected patient, unaffected carrier, and control is shown under each pedigree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The genotype is indicated in the pedigree charts:+/+, affected patient (homozygous mutation);+/−, unaffected carrier (heterozygous mutation); and −/−, unaffected control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par8"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The effect of the identified variants on protein function was predicted using bioinformatic programs (Sift, Polyphen-2, MutationTaster, PROVEAN, LRT and MutationAssessor), and potential effects on protein structure were determined using the Swiss Model tool. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the degree of conservation, alignment of the amino acid sequences of the targeted genes from various species was obtained from MutationTaster (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mutationtaster.org">http://www.mutationtaster.org</ext-link>), and domain analyses were performed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Structure/cdd/wrpsb.cgi">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Structure/cdd/wrpsb.cgi</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Mutation validation and co-segregation analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par9"><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Sanger sequencing was used to validate the candidate variants identified by WES, and segregation analyses were performed in the family members. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Primer pairs were designed using an online tool (PrimerQuest, IDT), and the sequences of the primers are listed in Supplementary Table S3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Clinical features </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par10"><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Six PCD patients (P1–6) (Table 1) from four consanguineous families (families 1 to 4) (full pedigrees are shown in Fig. 2) were identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>P1 refers to IV-4 in family 1; P2 and P3 refer to IV-1 and IV-2 in family 2, respectively; P4 and P5 refer to IV-2 and IV-3 respectively in family 3; and P6 refers to IV-5 in family 4 (see Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The parents of all probands are first cousins, and the inbreeding coefficient (F) is 1/16 for each family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>All patients in these families presented with typical PCD manifestations, including recurrent upper and lower respiratory infections from childhood, bronchiectasis, chronic rhinosinusitis, left-right laterality, reduced nNO or infertility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The specific clinical manifestations of each patient are shown in Table 1.Table 1Summary of the clinical features of PCD.CharacteristicsP1 (family1:IV-4)P2 (family2:IV-1)P3 (family2: IV-2)P4 (family3: IV-2)P5 (family3: IV-3)P6 (family4: IV-5)SexFemaleMaleFemaleFemaleMaleFemaleAge60 y29 y23 y43 y41 y52 yOnsetChildhoodChildhoodChildhoodChildhoodChildhoodChildhoodConsanguinityYesYesYesYesYesYesInbreeding coefficient1/161/161/161/161/161/16CTBronchiectasis Rhinosinusitis Visceral inversionBronchiectasis RhinosinusitisBronchiectasis RhinosinusitisBronchiectasis Rhinosinusitis Visceral inversionBronchiectasis Rhinosinusitis Visceral inversionBronchiectasis Rhinosinusitis Visceral inversionFertility problemsNoUnknownUnknownYesYesNoSmell problemsNoNoNoYesYesNoHearing problemsNoNoNoNoNoNoComorbiditiesAsthmaNoNoTGA,ASD,PAHNoAsthmaTEMNANANANANAEquivocalPFTFEV1%32%33%49%44%NA37.2%FEV1/FVC40.21%54.73%50%60%NA36.37%PaO2NA78 mmHg82 mmHg80 mmHgNANANasal NO23.6 ppb3.3 ppb31 ppb2.3 ppb8.3 ppb16.1 ppbTGA, corrected transposition of great arteries; ASD, atrial septal defect; PAH, pulmonary arterial hypertension; TEM, transmission electron microscopy; PFT, pulmonary function test; FEV1, forced expiratory volume in 1 second; FVC, forced vital capacity; Nasal NO, nasal nitric oxide measurement; NA, not available. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Genetic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par11"><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>WES was performed on seven individuals (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Sequence read of 7.88, 5.65, 4.9, 8.63, 8.23, 5.46 and 6.48 Gbp were generated, with a depth of more than 50 × for each individual, and more than 99% of the targeted bases were covered sufficiently to pass our thresholds for SNVs and InDels (Supplementary Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Exonic InDels, non-synonymous variants, and nonsense and splice-site SNVs were further filtered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>After the discovery of rare variations (minor allele frequency &lt;1%), selection of variants in the 40 PCD-related genes (Supplementary Table S2) was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The coverage of the whole exome by the exome capture kit was approximately 99.7–99.8%, and the coverage of the 40 known PCD genes was greater than 99% (Supplementary Table S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>No compound heterozygotes of known PCD-related genes were identified in these patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, only one homozygous mutation in a known PCD gene was identified in each family (c.1488delG of ARMC4 in family 1, c.248_249insGCCCG of CCNO in family 2, c.384delC of DYX1C1 in family 3, and c.1562T &gt; G of DNAI1 in family 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>All four variants were validated via Sanger sequencing (the PCR primers are listed in Supplementary Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The sequences of these genes from each of these four families were determined, and the variations were found to co-segregate with the disease in each family (Fig. 2).The frequencies of the identified variants in the public databases (Exac, ClinVar, NHLBI exome databases, dbSNP138, 1000 Genomes Project) are shown in Supplementary Table S5. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par12"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Among the four apparently homozygous variants identified in our study, three were nonsense/frameshift mutations and one was missense mutation (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>To exclude the possibility of a large deletion of the other homologous allele, we performed ROH analysis12, 13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>In accordance with the autosomal recessive pattern of inheritance, our data from ROH analysis confirmed the homozygous conditions of these four mutations in all four PCD families.Table 2Functional prediction and conservation analysis for the cosegregating mutationFamilyGeneNMBase changeAAchangeMutationTasterPROVEANSIFTPolyphen2LRTMutationAssessorCADDGERP++phylop100way1 ARMC4 0180761488delGE497Kfs*3Disease-causingDeleteriousNANANANANANANA2 CCNO 021147248_249insGCCCGQ88Rfs*8Disease-causingDeleteriousNANANANANANANA3 DYX1C1 130810384delCY128*Disease-causingDeleteriousNANANANANANANA4 DNAI1 012144T1562GI521SProbably damagingDeleteriousDamagingDisease-causingDeleteriousMedium235.957.002CADD, a value &gt; 15 indicates deleterious; GERP++, a score &gt; 5 indicates highly conserved; phylop100way, the higher the score, the more conserved the site AA, amino acid NA, not available. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par13"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Consistent with the loss of function mechanisms of the known PCD-linked genes, the mutations identified in ARMC4, CCNO, and DYX1C1 in three of the families are either deletions or insertions, leading to loss of function by causing truncation of the encoded proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>However, c.1562T &gt; G (I521S) of DNAI1, found in family 4, was a missense mutation that alters a highly conserved residue (Supplementary Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The I521S mutation was predicted to be damaging according to SIFT, Polyphen2, MutationTaster, PROVEAN, LRT and MutationAssessor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The GERP score was 5.95 (prediction: highly conserved); the CADD value was 23 (prediction: deleterious); and the phylop100way value was 7.002 (prediction: conserved) (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Domain analysis suggested all of the variants were located in key domains that are essential for function of cilia (Supplementary Figures 4 and 5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par14"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The identified CCNO variant (Table 2) (c.248_249insGCCCG/p.Q88Rfs*8)22 was previously reported to be linked to PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The remaining three mutations are novel (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>None of these three mutations were found in our in-house 200 controls and other public databases, including ExAC.Figure 3Schematic drawing of ARMC4, DYX1C1, and DNAI1, in which the positions of all identified mutations are indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Novel mutations that were identified in the present study are indicated in red. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par15"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>In the present study, WES combined with ROH was employed to determine the causative genes in four consanguineous families with PCD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Four distinct homozygous mutations were identified in these families. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Among them, three of the variants are either deletions or insertions leading to frameshift (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Our findings are consistent with previous studies that the majority of mutations reported in PCD patients are null alleles (nonsense or frameshift variants)23. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>A novel missense variant (c.1562T &gt; G/p.I521S) in DNAI1 was identified in Family 4 and was predicted to be disease-causing variant by different in silico prediction methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>This variant site (I521) located in the WD40 domain, a key domain for the assembly and maintenance of cilia, strongly indicates the DNAI1 variant is causative in this case. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Cumulatively, a total of 12 missense mutations (out of the 27, Fig. 3) have been reported in DNAI1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Among these, several missense mutations closely flanking I521, including L513P, G515S, S527A and A538T24–27 have previously been identified in PCD, suggesting missense mutations represent a significant fraction of PCD-linked mutations in DNAI1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par16"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The identification of ultrastructural defects through transmission electron microscopy (TEM) has been previously considered a “gold standard” diagnostic test for PCD28. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>However, it was challenged by recent findings29–32, due to its limited sensitivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Approximately 30% of patients with genetically verified PCD exhibit a normal ciliary ultrastructure29. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Of note, defective cilia have also been found in 3 to 10% of healthy individuals30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>In our study, the affected individuals present some of the typical PCD manifestations such as: recurrent respiratory infections, bronchiectasis, left-right laterality and low nasal nitric oxide (nNO) levels (3.3–31 ppb in contrast to normal values &gt;100 ppb) (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>However, the TEM results of the only obtained ciliated sample from P6 are not conclusive (Supplementary Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>In consistent with European guidelines for PCD diagnosis, we further employed WES to investigate these consanguineous families. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>In the absence of TEM evidence, our strategy emphasizes a role of genetic testing in the PCD diagnostic, especially in cases with difficulties using other diagnostic approaches (e.g., HSVA, TEM or IF)33. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par17"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>In the present study, the filtering of the 40 PCD genes was performed prior to ROH analysis, as this order allowed the identification of compound heterozygotes in known PCD genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Copy number variations are prevalent in many autosomal recessive diseases17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>However, the detection of copy number variations using WES data remains challenging34. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>ROH analysis presents the advantages of determining the exact nature of mutations in this aspect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Our findings are consistent with a recent report35 in which WES combined with ROH was shown to be a superior choice for genetic studies in consanguineous families. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>As our study was primarily aimed at detecting PCD mutations, we did not actively search for “the incidental findings” that are recently recommended by the American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics36. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par18"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>To date, a total of 40 known PCD-causing genes have been reported (Supplementary Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Among these genes, ARMC4 (MIM: 615408) encodes a protein required in a late step for proper targeting and anchoring of outer dynein arms (ciliary structure proteins)37. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Thus far, 9 different ARMC4 mutations (2 missense mutants, 6 truncated mutants, and 1 frameshift mutant) have been identified in PCD patients (Fig. 3), with most of these mutations being found in exons 17 and 12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The frameshift mutation ARMC4 (c.1488delG/p.E497Kfs*3) in our study is located in the ARM-repeat unit (ARM) domain (Supplementary Figure 4) and is predicted to cause premature protein truncation, resulting in the assembly defect of the outer dynein arm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par19"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The DYX1C1 gene (MIM: 608706) was another gene reported to be involved in PCD38. DYX1C1 encodes a 420-amino acid protein with 3 tetratricopeptide repeat (TPR) domains that are thought to be protein interaction modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>DYX1C1 is a cytoplasmic axonemal dynein assembly factor, acting together with DNAAF2 at an early step in the cytoplasmic assembly of the inner and outer dynein arms38. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>To date, seven pathogenic variants of DYX1C1 have been reported38. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Our finding that a single-base deletion of C at position 384 (c.384delC) results in p.Y128* is consistent with the previous report by Tarkar et al.38. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par20"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The pathogenetic variant (c.248_249insGCCCG/p.Q88Rfs*8) identified in CCNO (MIM: 607752) was previously reported22. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Due to the lack of situs inversus phenotype, the patients in family 2 were initially diagnosed with common pulmonary infection and bronchiectasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Additional examinations revealed that both siblings exhibited chronic sinusitis symptoms, which was further confirmed via computerized tomography (CT) scan of the paranasal sinuses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Genetic analysis identified only one candidate variant CCNO (c.248_249insGCCCG/p.Q88Rfs*8). CCNO promotes mother centriole amplification and maturation in preparation for apical docking and ciliogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The phenotype of our patients was consistent with the observation in previous study22. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Retrospective study revealed a delayed diagnosis in our patient due to the atypical clinical PCD features (without situs inversus)1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>This highlights the advantage of early genetic analysis with WES to obtain an efficient diagnosis and management of PCD patients in cases of consanguinity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par21"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>In summary, using a combination of WES, ROH and bioinformatics analyses, three novel homozygous variants, including ARMC4 (c.1488delG/p.E497Kfs*3), DYX1C1 (c.384delC/p.Y128*) and DNAI1 (c.1562T &gt; G/p.I521S), and one previously reported variant, CCNO (c.248_249insGCCCG/p.Q88Rfs*8), were identified in four PCD families. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The identification of these variants contributes to the growing number of candidate mutations associated with PCD and might benefit future genetic counseling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Our data have also demonstrated a great value of WES combined with ROH in PCD diagnosis in consanguineous families, especially when the other diagnostic tests fail to be conclusive. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec11"><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Supplementary </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Ting Guo and Zhi-Ping Tan contributed equally to this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at doi:10.1038/s41598-017-08510-z </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Publisher's note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>We thank all the patients and their family for participating in the present study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>We thank the State Key Laboratory of Medical Genetics of China for technical assistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>This study was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (81470202 to Hong Luo, 81470445 to Zhi-Ping Tan, 81570288 to Yi-Feng Yang), the Natural Science Foundation of Hunan Province, China (13JJ3020 to Hong Luo), the Planned Science and Technology Project of Hunan Province, China (2015JC3032 to Yi-Feng Yang), the Science and Technology Program of Changsha, China (K1406020–31 to Hong Luo), and the National Key Clinical Specialty Construction Projects of China. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: Hong Luo and Yi-Feng Yang. Performed the experiments: Zhi-Ping Tan, Ting Guo, Lv liu. Collected samples: Ting Guo, Hua-Mei Chen, Dong-yuan Zheng, Xin-Gang Huang. Analyzed the data: Hong Luo, Ping Chen, Ting Guo, Zhi-Ping Tan. Wrote the text of the main manuscript and prepared the figures: Ting Guo. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></notes></SecTag><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par22">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>1.LoboJZariwalaMANoonePGPrimary ciliary dyskinesiaSemin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Respir. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Crit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Care Med.20153616917910.1055/s-0035-1546748<?supplied-pmid 25826585?>25826585 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>2.WernerCOnnebrinkJGOmranHDiagnosis and management of primary ciliary dyskinesiaCilia20154210.1186/s13630-014-0011-8<?supplied-pmid 25610612?>25610612 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>3.PennarunGLoss-of-function mutations in a human gene related to Chlamydomonas reinhardtii dynein IC78 result in primary ciliary dyskinesiaAM J HUM GENET199965150810.1086/302683<?supplied-pmid 10577904?>10577904 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>4.ShapiroAJDiagnosis, monitoring, and treatment of primary ciliary dyskinesia: PCD foundation consensus recommendations based on state of the art reviewPediatr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Pulmonol.20165111513210.1002/ppul.23304<?supplied-pmid 26418604?>26418604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>5.OlbrichHLoss-of-function GAS8 mutations cause primary ciliary dyskinesia and disrupt the Nexin-Dynein regulatory complexAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Hum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Genet.20159754655410.1016/j.ajhg.2015.08.012<?supplied-pmid 26387594?>26387594 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>6.LiYDNAH6 and its interactions with PCD genes in heterotaxy and primary ciliary dyskinesiaPLOS Genet.201612e100582110.1371/journal.pgen.1005821<?supplied-pmid 26918822?>26918822 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>7.WallmeierJTTC25 deficiency results in defects of the outer dynein arm docking machinery and primary ciliary dyskinesia with left-right body asymmetry randomizationAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Hum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Genet.20169946046910.1016/j.ajhg.2016.06.014<?supplied-pmid 27486780?>27486780 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>8.El Khouri, E. et al. Mutations in DNAJB13, encoding an HSP40 family member, cause primary ciliary dyskinesia and male infertility. Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Hum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Genet.99, 489–500 (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>9.PaffTMutations in PIH1D3 cause X-linked primary ciliary dyskinesia with outer and inner dynein arm defectsAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Hum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Genet.201710016016810.1016/j.ajhg.2016.11.019<?supplied-pmid 28041644?>28041644 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>10.Edelbusch, C. et al. Mutation of serine/threonine protein kinase 36 (STK36) causes primary ciliary dyskinesia with a central pair defect. HUM MUTAT (2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>11.KurkowiakMZiętkiewiczEWittMRecent advances in primary ciliary dyskinesia geneticsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Genet.2015521910.1136/jmedgenet-2014-102755<?supplied-pmid 25351953?>25351953 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>12.MagiAH3M2: detection of runs of homozygosity from whole-exome sequencing dataBIOINFORMATICS.201430285210.1093/bioinformatics/btu401<?supplied-pmid 24966365?>24966365 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>13.PippucciTHomozygous NOTCH3 null mutation and impaired NOTCH3 signaling in recessive early-onset arteriopathy and cavitating leukoencephalopathyEMBO Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Med.2015784885810.15252/emmm.201404399<?supplied-pmid 25870235?>25870235 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>14.KimHJSNP linkage analysis and whole exome sequencing identify a novel POU4F3 mutation in autosomal dominant late-onset nonsyndromic hearing loss (DFNA15)PLOS ONE.20138e7906310.1371/journal.pone.0079063<?supplied-pmid 24260153?>24260153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>15.LiuJJFanLLChenJLTanZPYangYFA novel variant in TBX20 (p.D176N) identified by whole-exome sequencing in combination with a congenital heart disease related gene filter is associated with familial atrial septal defectJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Zhejiang Univ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>B.20141583083710.1631/jzus.B1400062<?supplied-pmid 25183037?>25183037 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>16.DjakowJAn effective combination of sanger and next generation sequencing in diagnostics of primary ciliary dyskinesiaPediatr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Pulmonol.20165149850910.1002/ppul.23261<?supplied-pmid 26228299?>26228299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>17.MarshallCRWhole-exome sequencing and targeted copy number analysis in primary ciliary dyskinesiaG3 (Bethesda).201551775178110.1534/g3.115.019851<?supplied-pmid 26139845?>26139845 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>18.TanZPWhole-exome sequencing identifies Y1495X of SCN5A to be associated with familial conduction disease and sudden deathSci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Rep.20144561610.1038/srep05616<?supplied-pmid 25010007?>25010007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>19.RabbaniBMahdiehNHosomichiKNakaokaHInoueINext-generation sequencing: impact of exome sequencing in characterizing Mendelian disordersJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Hum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Genet.20125762163210.1038/jhg.2012.91<?supplied-pmid 22832387?>22832387 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>20.OnoufriadisACombined exome and whole-genome sequencing identifies mutations in ARMC4 as a cause of primary ciliary dyskinesia with defects in the outer dynein armJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Genet.201451616710.1136/jmedgenet-2013-101938<?supplied-pmid 24203976?>24203976 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>21.WalkerWTJacksonCLLackiePMHoggCLucasJSNitric oxide in primary ciliary dyskinesiaEur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Respir. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>J.2012401024103210.1183/09031936.00176111<?supplied-pmid 22408195?>22408195 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>22.WallmeierJMutations in CCNO result in congenital mucociliary clearance disorder with reduced generation of multiple motile ciliaNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Genet.20144664665110.1038/ng.2961<?supplied-pmid 24747639?>24747639 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>23.PraveenKDavisEEKatsanisNUnique among ciliopathies: primary ciliary dyskinesia, a motile cilia disorderF1000Prime Rep.201573610.12703/P7-36<?supplied-pmid 25926987?>25926987 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>24.ZiętkiewiczEPopulation specificity of the DNAI1 gene mutation spectrum in primary ciliary dyskinesia (PCD)Respir. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Res.20101117410.1186/1465-9921-11-174<?supplied-pmid 21143860?>21143860 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>25.GuichardCAxonemal dynein intermediate-chain gene (DNAI1) mutations result in situs inversus and primary ciliary dyskinesia (Kartagener syndrome)Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Hum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Genet.2001681030103510.1086/319511<?supplied-pmid 11231901?>11231901 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>26.NakhlehNHigh prevalence of respiratory ciliary dysfunction in congenital heart disease patients with heterotaxyCirculation.20121252232224210.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.111.079780<?supplied-pmid 22499950?>22499950 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>27.ZariwalaMAMutations of DNAI1 in primary ciliary dyskinesia: evidence of founder effect in a common mutationAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Respir. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Crit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Care Med.200617485886610.1164/rccm.200603-370OC<?supplied-pmid 16858015?>16858015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>28.NoonePGPrimary ciliary dyskinesia: diagnostic and phenotypic featuresAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Respir. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Crit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Care Med.200416945946710.1164/rccm.200303-365OC<?supplied-pmid 14656747?>14656747 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>29.KnowlesMRMutations of DNAH11 in patients with primary ciliary dyskinesia with normal ciliary ultrastructureThorax.20126743344110.1136/thoraxjnl-2011-200301<?supplied-pmid 22184204?>22184204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>30.MorillasHNZariwalaMKnowlesMRGenetic causes of bronchiectasis: primary ciliary dyskinesiaRespiration.20077425226310.1159/000101783<?supplied-pmid 17534128?>17534128 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>31.O’CallaghanCRutmanAWilliamsGMHirstRAInner dynein arm defects causing primary ciliary dyskinesia: repeat testing requiredEur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Respir. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>J.20113860360710.1183/09031936.00108410<?supplied-pmid 21406509?>21406509 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>32.OlinJTDiagnostic yield of nasal scrape biopsies in primary ciliary dyskinesia: a multicenter experiencePediatr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Pulmonol.201146483488<?supplied-pmid 21284095?>21284095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>33.Lucas, J. S. et al. European Respiratory Society guidelines for the diagnosis of primary ciliary dyskinesia. Eur. Respir. J. 49 (2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>34.TanRAn evaluation of copy number variation detection tools from whole-exome sequencing dataHUM MUTAT.20143589910.1002/humu.22537<?supplied-pmid 24599517?>24599517 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>35.RafiullahRHomozygous missense mutation in the LMAN2L gene segregates with intellectual disability in a large consanguineous Pakistani familyJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Genet.20165313814410.1136/jmedgenet-2015-103179<?supplied-pmid 26566883?>26566883 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>36.GreenRCACMG recommendations for reporting of incidental findings in clinical exome and genome sequencingGenet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Med.20131556557410.1038/gim.2013.73<?supplied-pmid 23788249?>23788249 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>37.HjeijRARMC4 mutations cause primary ciliary dyskinesia with randomization of left/right body asymmetryAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Hum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Genet.20139335736710.1016/j.ajhg.2013.06.009<?supplied-pmid 23849778?>23849778 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>38.TarkarADYX1C1 is required for axonemal dynein assembly and ciliary motilityNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Genet.201345995100310.1038/ng.2707<?supplied-pmid 23872636?>23872636 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
