<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5430759</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28446769</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1180</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-01180-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Identification of key proteins and pathways in cadmium tolerance of <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> strains by proteomic analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Qixiao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Yue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Jianxin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Fengwei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Hao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Narbad</surname><given-names>Arjan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name><address><email>chenwei66@jiangnan.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0708 1323</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.258151.a</institution-id><institution>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Technology, School of Food Science and Technology, </institution><institution>Jiangnan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Wuxi, Jiangsu People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>UK-China Joint Centre on Probiotic Bacteria, Norwich, NR4 7UA UK </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9347 0159</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.40368.39</institution-id><institution>Gut Health and Food Safety Programme, </institution><institution>Institute of Food Research, </institution></institution-wrap>Norwich, NR4 7UA United Kingdom </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9938 1755</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411615.6</institution-id><institution>Beijing Innovation Centre of Food Nutrition and Human Health, </institution><institution>Beijing Technology &#x00026; Business University, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, 100048 People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>1182</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p>Our previous study confirmed the protective potential of <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> (<italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic>) strains in alleviation of cadmium (Cd) toxicity <italic>in vivo</italic> and demonstrated that the observed protection largely depended on the tolerance of the strains to Cd-induced stress. It was also observed that there were significant intra-species differences in Cd tolerance of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains. In this study, we investigated the mechanism of Cd induced stress response of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains using the isobaric tags for relative and absolute quantitation (iTRAQ) based comparative proteomics. <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> CCFM8610 (strongly resistant to Cd) and <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> CCFM191 (sensitive to Cd) were selected as target strains, and their proteomic profiles in the presence and absence of Cd exposure were compared. We propose that the underlying mechanism of the exceptional Cd tolerance of CCFM8610 may be attributed to the following: (a) a specific energy-conservation survival mode; (b) mild induction of its cellular defense and repair system; (c) an enhanced biosynthesis of hydrophobic amino acids in response to Cd; (d) inherent superior Cd binding ability and effective cell wall biosynthesis ability; (e) a tight regulation on ion transport; (f) several key proteins, including prophage P2b protein 18, CadA, mntA and lp_3327.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cadmium (Cd) is a representative non-essential element and known as an environmental hazard to human health. This heavy metal can contaminate the food chain and cause cumulative toxic effects in the liver, kidney, bone and the reproductive systems of humans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Cd has also been classified as a potent human carcinogen by the International Agency for Research on Cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Chelation therapies, the most commonly used treatments for heavy metal toxicity, have a number of safety and efficacy concerns and as yet none of them have been approved for clinical use against Cd poisoning in humans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. The development of dietary supplements against Cd toxicity represents a potential alternative strategy.</p><p>Lactic acid bacteria (LAB) are members of commensal inhabitants of the human intestinal microbiota that can confer health benefits on the host<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Among these LAB, <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> (<italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic>) strains have been widely used in the food industry as probiotics and functional food supplements<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Our previous studies have demonstrated that <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> CCFM8610 can sequester Cd in the intestines of the host, which in turn promotes fecal Cd excretion and reduction in Cd accumulation in tissues, indicating that this strain can be considered a dietary supplement for the prevention and alleviation of Cd toxicity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. It was further noted that CCFM8610 offers significantly better protection than some other <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains <italic>in vivo</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, and the protective effects were dependent on bacterial cell viability<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>.</p><p>Cd exposure, even at low levels, can disrupt cell wall synthesis, respiratory chain function and metal ion homeostasis in microorganisms, which in turn causes oxidative stress, DNA damage and energy metabolism dysfunctions, inducing extreme cellular toxic effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. As <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> cells contact with Cd directly in the intestines of the host, the protective effects of the strains against Cd toxicity largely depend on their abilities to thrive after Cd exposure. Therefore, understanding the mechanism of Cd tolerance of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains is essential for the development of probiotic based strategy against Cd toxicity. Our previous work showed that the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> CCFM8610 (tested on Cd-containing agar plates) is more than 1000&#x02009;mg/L, while some other <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains have MIC values 10 to 20 times lower<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. A bacterium is considered tolerant to Cd if its MIC value exceeds 100&#x02009;mg/L<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> or 112.4&#x02009;mg/L of Cd<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Based on this definition, <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> CCFM8610 can be considered a highly Cd-resistant strain. This may partly explain the protection of the host against Cd toxicity <italic>in vivo</italic> offered by this strain. Therefore, it is of interest to understand the resistance mechanism of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains against Cd exposure, and to explore why CCFM8610 is highly tolerant to Cd.</p><p>The physiological bases of heavy metal tolerance have been well investigated in environmental and industrial microorganisms such as <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp., <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> and <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisia</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. The related metabolomic pathways and key proteins identified include sulfur assimilation/glutathione synthesis pathway, metallothionein, oxidoreductase and ion transport proteins. However, comprehensive heavy metal tolerance mechanisms have not yet been well defined in LAB strains. To our knowledge, the Cd resistance modes have only been studied in <italic>Streptococcus thermophiles</italic> and <italic>Lactococcus lactis</italic>, with a focus on two Cd resistance-associated genes, CadA and CadC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Numbers of reports also indicated the presence of these genes in some strains of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, but the Cd stress response network in these strains is yet to be elucidated.</p><p>Proteomics has been reported to be efficient to provide global physiological profiles of bacteria in protein level<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. The most commonly used approaches for proteomic analysis are gel-based methods, such as two-dimensional gel electrophoresis (2-DE) and two-dimensional difference gel electrophoresis (2-D DIGE). However, these methods were reported to have limitations in sensibility, reproducibility, and proteome coverage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Isobaric tags for relative and absolute quantitation (iTRAQ) is a labelling approach that allows reliable quantitative description of differentially regulated proteins in complex systems. The main advantage is to have the possibility to analyze several samples together, with biological and technical replicates (4 or 8 plex). The subsequent use of high resolution mass spectrometry analyses provides accurate relative ratio between protein concentrations, present in the different samples<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Therefore, this approach was selected in this study.</p><p>In this study, the Cd-tolerance related key proteins and pathways within the <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> species were investigated by using iTRAQ based proteomic approach. <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains CCFM8610 (strongly resistant to Cd) and CCFM191 (sensitive to Cd) were selected for comparative proteomic analysis based on their differing Cd tolerant phenotype. The comparative proteomic profiles between non-stimulating and Cd-exposed conditions were compared in the two strains. The proteomic results were further confirmed by RT-qPCR and by the measurement of several biological properties of the bacterial cells in response to Cd exposure.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Cd tolerance</title><p>Twenty <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains were cultured in MRS broth containing different concentrations of Cd, and the relative growth rates were determined (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). While increasing Cd concentration caused a continuous decrease in the growth rate of all strains, significant Cd tolerance diversity could be observed, and the 20 strains could be categorized into four general groups, MIC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;50&#x02009;mg/L, MIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;50&#x02009;mg/L, MIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;20&#x02009;mg/L and MIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;10&#x02009;mg/L. All tested strains showed no obvious growth since the Cd concentration reaching over 100 ppm (data not shown). <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> CCFM8610 belonged to one of the eight strains with the highest MIC values, which was in agreement with our previous study on the tolerance of LAB strains tested on Cd-containing agar plates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Based on the category of Cd tolerance of bacteria reported in a previous report<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>, CCFM191, one of the three strains with lowest MIC value (10 ppm), was selected as a Cd-sensitive strain for the comparative proteomic analysis with CCFM8610. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, the dose of Cd at 5&#x02009;mg/L (1/2 MIC value of the Cd-sensitive strain CCFM191) was selected for modeling a moderate and sublethal Cd exposure in the following experiments based on the previous related study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Relative growth rate of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains grown in MRS broth containing different Cd concentrations.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">MIC value</th><th colspan="6">Relative growth rate<sup>a</sup> of strains grown in MRS broth containing different Cd concentrations (%)</th></tr><tr><th>Strains</th><th>5 ppm</th><th>10 ppm</th><th>20 ppm</th><th>50 ppm</th><th>100 ppm</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="8">MIC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;50</td><td>CCFM11</td><td>96.31&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.55</td><td>91.52&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.02</td><td>60.47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.72</td><td>18.98&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.18</td><td>13.61&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.47</td></tr><tr><td>CCFM232</td><td>94.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.40</td><td>89.36&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.35</td><td>63.53&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.24</td><td>16.38&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.55</td><td>11.13&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.17</td></tr><tr><td>CCFM240</td><td>94.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.34</td><td>92.49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.42</td><td>64.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.31</td><td>17.62&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.59</td><td>11.34&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.23</td></tr><tr><td>CCFM8610</td><td>90.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.98</td><td>86.75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.54</td><td>67.21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.00</td><td>20.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.63</td><td>13.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.35</td></tr><tr><td>CCFM405</td><td>101.93&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.39</td><td>90.78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.26</td><td>60.30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.50</td><td>20.22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.90</td><td>11.61&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.25</td></tr><tr><td>CCFM595</td><td>102.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07</td><td>101.23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.23</td><td>91.38&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.63</td><td>29.37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.88</td><td>10.52&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.45</td></tr><tr><td>CCFM579</td><td>96.81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21</td><td>91.22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.17</td><td>64.47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.52</td><td>21.98&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td>12.88&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.61</td></tr><tr><td>CCFM8661</td><td>99.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.59</td><td>92.20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.88</td><td>60.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.28</td><td>19.44&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.97</td><td>12.69&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.31</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">MIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;50</td><td>CCFM241</td><td>99.68&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.09</td><td>100.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.69</td><td>79.28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.49</td><td>8.73&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.15</td><td>6.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.30</td></tr><tr><td>CCFM231</td><td>95.68&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.11</td><td>92.13&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.22</td><td>61.76&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.74</td><td>7.61&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05</td><td>5.61&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.09</td></tr><tr><td>CCFM198</td><td>102.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.30</td><td>94.91&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.06</td><td>25.36&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.71</td><td>7.50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.29</td><td>5.79&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.14</td></tr><tr><td>CCFM239</td><td>98.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.51</td><td>95.67&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.43</td><td>45.55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.47</td><td>7.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.22</td><td>5.37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">MIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;20</td><td>CCFM308</td><td>79.68&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.51</td><td>19.30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.38</td><td>9.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.33</td><td>6.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.36</td><td>3.99&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.28</td></tr><tr><td>CCFM309</td><td>84.95&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.46</td><td>21.58&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.86</td><td>10.96&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.43</td><td>6.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.09</td><td>4.62&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11</td></tr><tr><td>CCFM602</td><td>97.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.62</td><td>84.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.46</td><td>9.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.56</td><td>4.55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.29</td><td>2.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.08</td></tr><tr><td>CCFM605</td><td>96.78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.45</td><td>72.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.99</td><td>12.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.67</td><td>4.32&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.20</td><td>3.30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.45</td></tr><tr><td>CCFM166</td><td>91.17&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.12</td><td>37.30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.80</td><td>4.76&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.47</td><td>3.20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.15</td><td>2.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">MIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;10</td><td>CCFM191</td><td>84.63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.14</td><td>9.30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td><td>6.69&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.25</td><td>6.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.38</td><td>4.76&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.10</td></tr><tr><td>CCFM436</td><td>95.82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.84</td><td>13.94&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.96</td><td>4.81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td>4.16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.13</td><td>3.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td></tr><tr><td>CCFM578</td><td>94.88&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.48</td><td>9.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.32</td><td>1.32&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.09</td><td>4.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.26</td><td>1.21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.25</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<sup>a</sup>Relative growth rate of each strain was expressed as percentage of OD<sub>600</sub> value of control culture (without Cd exposure) which was assigned a value of 100%. Data are expressed as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM of three independent experiments per assay.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Relative growth rate of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> CCFM8610 and CCFM191 grown in MRS broth of different Cd concentrations. Relative growth rate was expressed as percentage of OD<sub>600</sub> value of control culture (without Cd exposure) which was assigned a value of 100%. Data are expressed as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM of three independent experiments per assay.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_1180_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e1045"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Proteomic characteristics of two <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains</title><p>1592 and 1527 proteins were detected and identified in CCFM8610 (with and without Cd exposure, &#x0201c;A&#x0201d; round) and CCFM191 (with and without Cd exposure, &#x0201c;B&#x0201d; round), respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The 1415 overlapped proteins identified in both rounds were selected for protein function analysis. The protein function annotation was conducted by Gene Ontology (GO) analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), and the related metabolomics pathways of these proteins were analyzed by KEGG classification (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The results indicated that the detected proteins covered a large range with functions categorizing into biological process, cellular component and molecular function. The relevant metabolic pathways were related to carbohydrate metabolism (149 proteins), amino acid metabolism (120 proteins), translation (83 proteins), membrane transport (78 proteins), lipid metabolism (49 proteins), etc.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Workflow of iTRAQ experiment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_1180_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1075"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Functional categories of overlapped proteins identified in two <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains by GO analysis. GO analysis was conducted by the software blast2go with the GO ID from the ensmbl database for each identified protein.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_1180_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1091"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Related metabolomics pathways of overlapped proteins identified in two <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains by KEGG classification. Each digital on the right of each bar indicates the number of proteins in each category. The letters A, B, C, D and E represent the 5 branches in KEGG pathways including Metabolism (A), Genetic Information Processing (B), Environmental Information Processing (C), Cellular Processes (D) and Organismal Systems (E).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_1180_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1108"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Differentially expressed protein profiles</title><p>Intra-species difference of inherent proteomic profiles between Cd resistant and sensitive strains was evaluated, so as to pinpoint the proteins that might be implicated in the Cd stress response process. Total of 206 proteins with fold change more than 1.5 were selected as differentially expressed proteins (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) for the comparison of CCFM8610 and CCFM191 in non-treated conditions (without Cd exposure). These proteins were categorized into global stress response, carbohydrate and lipid metabolism, transporters, some membrane and extracellular proteins, etc., based on the KEGG pathway analysis and their annotated functions in the Uniprot database. Compared with CCFM191, lower abundances of proteins that belong to global stress response, carbohydrate metabolism, phosphotransferase (PTS) system, two-component system, membrane protein and cell surface protein and hydrolase could be observed in CCFM8610. On the other hand, proteins involved in amino acid metabolism, nucleic acid metabolism and extracellular protein showed higher abundances in CCFM8610.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Differentially expressed proteins between <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> CCFM8610 and CCFM191 in Cd-free conditions.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Category<sup>a</sup>
</th><th/><th>Accession<sup>b</sup>
</th><th>Description<sup>c</sup>
</th><th>FC<sup>d</sup>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="37">Global Stress Response</td><td rowspan="6">DNA repair, metabolism, regulation</td><td>F9UQY3</td><td>lp_2444; Prophage P2a protein 13</td><td>&#x02212;3.30</td></tr><tr><td>F9ULA4</td><td>lp_0641; Prophage P1 protein 18, DNA single-strand annealing protein RecT</td><td>&#x02212;1.87</td></tr><tr><td>Q6LWF5</td><td>traI; DNA topoisomerase</td><td>6.30</td></tr><tr><td>F9URZ6</td><td>endA; DNA-entry nuclease</td><td>1.58</td></tr><tr><td>Q88V16</td><td>mutS2; Endonuclease MutS2</td><td>&#x02212;1.70</td></tr><tr><td>Q88W97</td><td>recU; Holliday junction resolvase RecU</td><td>&#x02212;1.52</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="23">Oxidoreductase</td><td>F9UUA8</td><td>lp_3430; Peroxidase</td><td>5.14</td></tr><tr><td>F9USL4</td><td>lp_3100; Aldo/keto reductase family protein</td><td>3.41</td></tr><tr><td>F9UPP0</td><td>lp_1918; NAD(P)(H)-dependent oxidoreductase, quinone oxidoreductase (QOR) family</td><td>2.10</td></tr><tr><td>F9URK6</td><td>lp_2732; NADPH-dependent FMN reductase family protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.50</td></tr><tr><td>F9UQD7</td><td>lp_2212; NADH-flavin reductase</td><td>&#x02212;1.51</td></tr><tr><td>F9UQI9</td><td>trxA2; Thioredoxin</td><td>&#x02212;1.56</td></tr><tr><td>F9UPR0</td><td>lp_1939; Oxidoreductase, medium chain dehydrogenases/reductase (MDR)/zinc-dependent alcohol dehydrogenase-like family</td><td>&#x02212;1.64</td></tr><tr><td>F9USA2</td><td>lp_2968; Nitroreductase</td><td>&#x02212;1.65</td></tr><tr><td>F9UTJ8</td><td>lp_3318; Aldo/keto reductase family protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.65</td></tr><tr><td>F9USK5</td><td>lp_3091; Short-chain dehydrogenase/oxidoreductase, atypical SDR family, subgroup 1</td><td>&#x02212;2.83</td></tr><tr><td>F9UT37</td><td>trxA1; Thioredoxin</td><td>2.04</td></tr><tr><td>F9UTD6</td><td>lp_3236; Short-chain dehydrogenase/oxidoreductase, atypical SDR family, TMR-like</td><td>1.70</td></tr><tr><td>F9URB2</td><td>lp_2604; NAD(P)-dependent oxidoreductase</td><td>1.53</td></tr><tr><td>F9US17</td><td>nrdG; Anaerobic ribonucleoside-triphosphate reductase-activating protein</td><td>1.55</td></tr><tr><td>F9UTT1</td><td>acdH; Acetaldehyde dehydrogenase</td><td>1.55</td></tr><tr><td>F9UNI0</td><td>ribB; Riboflavin synthase, alpha chain</td><td>&#x02212;5.89</td></tr><tr><td>F9UR64</td><td>npr2; NADH peroxidase</td><td>&#x02212;4.38</td></tr><tr><td>F9ULD3</td><td>cat; Catalase</td><td>&#x02212;3.76</td></tr><tr><td>F9UN44</td><td>gshR2; glutathione reductase</td><td>&#x02212;4.67</td></tr><tr><td>F9UUC2</td><td>nox5; NADH oxidase</td><td>&#x02212;2.30</td></tr><tr><td>F9UTJ6</td><td>pflA; Pyruvate formate-lyase-activating enzyme</td><td>&#x02212;2.09</td></tr><tr><td>F9UUK7</td><td>lp_3545; D-arabitol-phosphate dehydrogenase</td><td>&#x02212;3.08</td></tr><tr><td>F9USK6</td><td>gabD; succinate-semialdehyde dehydrogenase (NAD(P)&#x02009;+&#x02009;)</td><td>&#x02212;2.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Protein repair</td><td>F9UPH1</td><td>msrA; Peptide methionine sulfoxide reductase MsrA</td><td>&#x02212;6.02</td></tr><tr><td>Q88W33</td><td>msrB; Peptide methionine sulfoxide reductase MsrB</td><td>&#x02212;2.67</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Protease</td><td>F9UTF5</td><td>lp_3259; Zinc-dependent proteinase</td><td>&#x02212;1.96</td></tr><tr><td>F9UT31</td><td>pepD1; Dipeptidase</td><td>&#x02212;1.54</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Other</td><td>F9US30</td><td>lp_2952; Bacteriocin immunity protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.58</td></tr><tr><td>F9URC0</td><td>lp_2616; Bacteriocin immunity protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.96</td></tr><tr><td>F9USV1</td><td>hsp1; Small heat shock protein</td><td>&#x02212;2.32</td></tr><tr><td>Q88V03</td><td>ruvB; Holliday junction ATP-dependent DNA helicase RuvB</td><td>1.92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="12">Regulation network</td><td rowspan="9">Transcriptional regulation</td><td>F9UT59</td><td>treR; Trehalose operon transcriptional repressor, GntR family</td><td>&#x02212;1.91</td></tr><tr><td>F9UM95</td><td>lp_0892; Transcription regulator, MarR family</td><td>&#x02212;1.70</td></tr><tr><td>Q88X36</td><td>argR1; Arginine regulator</td><td>&#x02212;1.65</td></tr><tr><td>F9UNC5</td><td>lp_1360; Transcription regulator, MarR family</td><td>2.06</td></tr><tr><td>F9USP8</td><td>lp_3138; Bifunctional protein: transcriptional antiterminator, BglG family PTS system, EIIA component</td><td>1.87</td></tr><tr><td>F9UPQ9</td><td>lp_1938; Transcription regulator, LysR family</td><td>1.82</td></tr><tr><td>F9USH9</td><td>lp_3060; Transcription regulator, AraC family</td><td>1.53</td></tr><tr><td>F9UMJ7</td><td>lp_1020; Transcription regulator, TetR family</td><td>1.57</td></tr><tr><td>F9UL40</td><td>tex; Transcription accessory protein, contains S1 RNA binding domain</td><td>&#x02212;1.82</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Other regulation proteins</td><td>Q88XG5</td><td>recX; Regulatory protein RecX</td><td>2.02</td></tr><tr><td>F9UM52</td><td>spx1; RNA polymerase (RNAP)-binding regulatory protein, arsenate reductase (ArsC) family, Spx subfamily</td><td>&#x02212;1.59</td></tr><tr><td>F9ULW6</td><td>lp_0737; Sigma 54 modulation protein/ribosomal protein S30EA</td><td>&#x02212;1.53</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="26">Carbohydrate metabolism</td><td rowspan="5">TCA cycle</td><td>F9UMS1</td><td>fum; fumarate hydratase</td><td>&#x02212;3.81</td></tr><tr><td>F9UQ90</td><td>pdhD; pyruvate dehydrogenase complex, E3 component; dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase</td><td>&#x02212;1.90</td></tr><tr><td>F9UQ91</td><td>pdhC; pyruvate dehydrogenase complex, E2 component; dihydrolipoamide S-acetyltransferase</td><td>&#x02212;2.30</td></tr><tr><td>F9UQ92</td><td>pdhB; pyruvate dehydrogenase complex, E1 component, beta subunit</td><td>&#x02212;2.21</td></tr><tr><td>F9UQ93</td><td>pdhA; pyruvate dehydrogenase complex, E1 component, alpha subunit</td><td>&#x02212;2.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7">Pyruvate metabolism</td><td>F9UTR4</td><td>ack2; acetate kinase</td><td>&#x02212;1.59</td></tr><tr><td>F9UM63</td><td>pox1; pyruvate oxidase</td><td>&#x02212;2.79</td></tr><tr><td>P59390</td><td>ldhL2; L-lactate dehydrogenase</td><td>&#x02212;3.36</td></tr><tr><td>Q88VJ2</td><td>ldhD; D-lactate dehydrogenase</td><td>1.69</td></tr><tr><td>F9URC8</td><td>pox3; pyruvate oxidase</td><td>&#x02212;8.87</td></tr><tr><td>F9UTJ5</td><td>pflB; formate C-acetyltransferase</td><td>&#x02212;1.85</td></tr><tr><td>P37063</td><td>pox5; pyruvate oxidase</td><td>&#x02212;4.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">Pentose phosphate pathway</td><td>F9UN42</td><td>gntK; gluconokinase</td><td>&#x02212;1.99</td></tr><tr><td>F9URA8</td><td>tal1; Transaldolase</td><td>&#x02212;5.21</td></tr><tr><td>F9UN43</td><td>lp_1251;6-phosphogluconate dehydrogenase</td><td>&#x02212;7.13</td></tr><tr><td>Q88S87</td><td>xfp; xylulose-5-phosphate phosphoketolase</td><td>&#x02212;1.64</td></tr><tr><td>F9ULK7</td><td>rbsK1; ribokinase</td><td>&#x02212;1.72</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Glycolysis</td><td>Q88YY8</td><td>pgm2; phosphoglycerate mutase family protein</td><td>2.56</td></tr><tr><td>F9URP6</td><td>pbg4; 6-phospho-beta-glucosidase</td><td>&#x02212;1.94</td></tr><tr><td>F9URP7</td><td>pbg5; 6-phospho-beta-glucosidase</td><td>&#x02212;2.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">Other</td><td>F9US84</td><td>pgmB2; Beta-phosphoglucomutase</td><td>&#x02212;2.71</td></tr><tr><td>F9USZ1</td><td>malS; Alpha-amylase, maltodextrins and cyclomaltodextrins</td><td>&#x02212;1.61</td></tr><tr><td>F9USY2</td><td>dak3; Dihydroxyacetone phosphotransferase, phosphoryl donor protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.66</td></tr><tr><td>F9UP85</td><td>mapA; Maltose phosphorylase</td><td>&#x02212;2.73</td></tr><tr><td>Q88RZ2</td><td>rbsD; D-ribose mutarotase</td><td>&#x02212;1.78</td></tr><tr><td>Q88S51</td><td>rhaA; L-rhamnose isomerase</td><td>&#x02212;1.56</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="13">PTS system</td><td rowspan="13">PTS system</td><td>F9UT61</td><td>pts4ABC; PTS system trehalose-specific transporter subunit IIBC</td><td>&#x02212;1.86</td></tr><tr><td>F9UL45</td><td>pts9AB; PTS system, mannose-specific EIIAB component</td><td>1.73</td></tr><tr><td>F9UL47</td><td>pts9D; PTS system, mannose-specific EIID component</td><td>1.82</td></tr><tr><td>F9UL56</td><td>pts10A; PTS system, mannose-specific EIIA component</td><td>&#x02212;1.52</td></tr><tr><td>F9UL57</td><td>pts10B; PTS system, mannose-specific EIIB component</td><td>&#x02212;3.91</td></tr><tr><td>F9URE1</td><td>pts19D; PTS system, N-acetylglucosamine&#x02013;specific EIID component</td><td>&#x02212;1.79</td></tr><tr><td>F9URE3</td><td>pts19B; PTS system, N-acetylglucosamine&#x02013;specific EIIB component</td><td>&#x02212;1.70</td></tr><tr><td>F9URP8</td><td>pts20A; PTS system, cellobiose-specific EIIA component</td><td>&#x02212;2.47</td></tr><tr><td>F9URP9</td><td>pts20B; PTS system, cellobiose-specific EIIB component</td><td>&#x02212;2.99</td></tr><tr><td>F9UUH8</td><td>pts30BCA; PTS system, beta-glucoside&#x02013;specific EIIBCA component</td><td>&#x02212;1.71</td></tr><tr><td>F9UUK9</td><td>pts35B; PTS system, galactitol-specific EIIB component</td><td>&#x02212;2.50</td></tr><tr><td>F9ULA5</td><td>pts35A; PTS system, galactitol-specific EIIA component</td><td>&#x02212;1.54</td></tr><tr><td>F9UUH6</td><td>lp_3510; PTS-associated protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.80</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9">Amino acid metabolism</td><td rowspan="3">Lysine biosynthesis</td><td>F9UPP5</td><td>dapE1; succinyl-diaminopimelate desuccinylase</td><td>2.86</td></tr><tr><td>F9URV7</td><td>dapE2; succinyl-diaminopimelate desuccinylase</td><td>1.95</td></tr><tr><td>F9UT53</td><td>cblB; cystathionine beta-lyase/cystathionine gamma-lyase</td><td>&#x02212;3.54</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Sulfur amino acid metabolism</td><td>F9UQB3</td><td>iscS; Cysteine desulfurase</td><td>1.64</td></tr><tr><td>F9UTH2</td><td>lp_3283; Methonine synthase (Cobalamine-independent), C-terminal domain</td><td>&#x02212;2.40</td></tr><tr><td>Q88UW5</td><td>gshAB; glutathione biosynthesis bifunctional protein: glutamate-cysteine ligase; glutathione synthetase</td><td>1.50</td></tr><tr><td>F9UR58</td><td>oahS; O-acetylhomoserine sulfhydrylase</td><td>&#x02212;2.44</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="8">Other</td><td>Q88UT5</td><td>glyA; glycine hydroxymethyltransferase</td><td>1.53</td></tr><tr><td>Q88WI3</td><td>trpD; anthranilate phosphoribosyltransferase</td><td>4.58</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">Nucleic acid metabolism</td><td>F9UT41</td><td>ndk; nucleoside-diphosphate kinase</td><td>&#x02212;1.72</td></tr><tr><td>F9UM77</td><td>gmk2; guanylate kinase</td><td>1.64</td></tr><tr><td>F9URN3</td><td>lp_2762; phosphohydrolase</td><td>1.87</td></tr><tr><td>F9US18</td><td>nrdD; anaerobic ribonucleoside-triphosphate reductase</td><td>2.16</td></tr><tr><td>P71479</td><td>pyrR1; pyrimidine operon regulator</td><td>1.62</td></tr><tr><td>F9UNA0</td><td>dgk2; Deoxynucleoside kinase</td><td>2.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="16">Lipid metabolism</td><td rowspan="3">Fatty acid biosynthesis</td><td>F9UP42</td><td>accC2; acetyl-CoA carboxylase, biotin carboxylase subunit</td><td>1.90</td></tr><tr><td>Q88WG0</td><td>accD2; acetyl-CoA carboxylase, carboxyl transferase subunit beta</td><td>1.84</td></tr><tr><td>F9UP44</td><td>accA2; acetyl-CoA carboxylase, carboxyl transferase subunit alpha</td><td>1.98</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9">Glycerol lipid metabolism</td><td>F9USY0</td><td>dak1B; dihydroxyacetone phosphotransferase, dihydroxyacetone binding subunit</td><td>&#x02212;1.70</td></tr><tr><td>F9USY1</td><td>dak2; dihydroxyacetone phosphotransferase, ADP-binding subunit</td><td>&#x02212;1.70</td></tr><tr><td>Q88ZF1</td><td>glpK; glycerol kinase</td><td>&#x02212;5.69</td></tr><tr><td>F9UTW9</td><td>glpF3; Glycerol uptake facilitator protein</td><td>&#x02212;3.30</td></tr><tr><td>Q88YD9</td><td>glpK2; Glycerol kinase 2</td><td>&#x02212;3.04</td></tr><tr><td>F9UT65</td><td>tagF1; CDP-glycerol glycerophosphotransferase</td><td>&#x02212;2.15</td></tr><tr><td>F9UT64</td><td>tagD1; glycerol-3-phosphate cytidylyltransferase</td><td>&#x02212;5.85</td></tr><tr><td>F9UPG2</td><td>tarL; Ribitolphosphotransferase</td><td>4.22</td></tr><tr><td>F9UTW8</td><td>glpD; glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase, FAD-dependent</td><td>&#x02212;6.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Terpenoid backbone biosynthesis</td><td>Q88W46</td><td>tarI; D-ribitol-5-phosphate cytidylyltransferase</td><td>6.81</td></tr><tr><td>F9URB5</td><td>dxs; 1-deoxy-D-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase</td><td>2.46</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Other</td><td>F9UT87</td><td>cfa2; Cyclopropane-fatty-acyl-phospholipid synthase</td><td>1.67</td></tr><tr><td>F9UMC4</td><td>lp_0925; Acyltransferase</td><td>2.30</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">Two-component system</td><td rowspan="5"/><td>F9UMR7</td><td>citC; [citrate (pro-3S)-lyase] ligase</td><td>&#x02212;1.52</td></tr><tr><td>Q88XS8</td><td>citD; citrate lyase, gamma chain, acyl carrier protein</td><td>&#x02212;2.43</td></tr><tr><td>F9UMR9</td><td>citE; citrate lyase, beta chain</td><td>&#x02212;1.82</td></tr><tr><td>F9UMS0</td><td>citF; citrate lyase, alpha chain</td><td>&#x02212;1.95</td></tr><tr><td>Q88VM8</td><td>dltC1; D-alanine&#x02013;poly(phosphoribitol) ligase subunit 2-1</td><td>&#x02212;1.65</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9">Transporter</td><td rowspan="9"/><td>F9USY7</td><td>mdxE; maltodextrin ABC transporter, substrate binding protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.91</td></tr><tr><td>F9USZ2</td><td>msmX; maltodextrin ABC transporter, ATP-binding protein</td><td>&#x02212;2.23</td></tr><tr><td>F9USG5</td><td>lp_3042; Multidrug ABC transporter, ATP-binding and permease protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.97</td></tr><tr><td>F9UM05</td><td>lp_0783; Oligopeptide ABC transporter, substrate binding protein</td><td>2.77</td></tr><tr><td>F9UR50</td><td>lp_2525; ABC transporter, ATP-binding protein</td><td>1.75</td></tr><tr><td>F9UPR5</td><td>lp_1945; Multidrug ABC transporter, ATP-binding protein</td><td>1.65</td></tr><tr><td>F9USL7</td><td>fhuD; iron chelatin ABC transporter, substrate binding protein</td><td>1.74</td></tr><tr><td>F9UMR4</td><td>citP; Citrate transport protein</td><td>&#x02212;2.16</td></tr><tr><td>F9UP84</td><td>malT; Carbohydrate (Maltose)/proton symporttransporter, GPH family</td><td>&#x02212;2.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">Membrane protein and cell surface protein</td><td rowspan="6"/><td>F9URF3</td><td>lp_2663; Hypothetical membrane protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.53</td></tr><tr><td>F9UU92</td><td>lp_3413; Cell surface protein, CscA/DUF916 family</td><td>&#x02212;1.69</td></tr><tr><td>F9UTN0</td><td>lp_3359; Hypothetical membrane protein, DUF125 family</td><td>&#x02212;2.24</td></tr><tr><td>F9ULS6</td><td>lp_0689; Cell surface protein, lipoprotein</td><td>2.05</td></tr><tr><td>F9URZ3</td><td>lp_2901; Hypothetical membrane protein</td><td>1.73</td></tr><tr><td>F9UU47</td><td>lp_3360; Hypothetical membrane protein, DUF125 family</td><td>&#x02212;3.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="11">Extracellular protein</td><td rowspan="11"/><td>F9USP4</td><td>lp_3134; Extracellular protein, DUF 1093 family, membrane-bound</td><td>&#x02212;2.04</td></tr><tr><td>F9UR45</td><td>lp_2520; Extracellular protein, NlpC/P60 family, gamma-D-glutamate-meso-diaminopimelate muropeptidase</td><td>&#x02212;1.79</td></tr><tr><td>F9UQA0</td><td>lp_2162; Extracellular protein, NlpC/P60 family, gamma-D-glutamate-meso-diaminopimelate muropeptidase</td><td>1.55</td></tr><tr><td>F9URD4</td><td>lp_2636; Extracellular protein</td><td>1.55</td></tr><tr><td>F9UUA0</td><td>lp_3421; Extracellular protein, gamma-D-glutamate-meso-diaminopimelate muropeptidase</td><td>2.39</td></tr><tr><td>F9USJ3</td><td>lp_3077; Extracellular protein</td><td>2.37</td></tr><tr><td>F9UQ85</td><td>lp_2145; Extracellular protein, cell wall&#x02013;anchored</td><td>1.90</td></tr><tr><td>F9UNC2</td><td>lp_1357; Extracellular protein, membrane-anchored</td><td>1.88</td></tr><tr><td>F9UL67</td><td>zmp2; Extracellular zinc metalloproteinase, M10 family</td><td>1.96</td></tr><tr><td>F9USE1</td><td>lp_3014; Extracellular transglycosylase, with LysM peptidoglycan&#x02013;binding domain</td><td>1.62</td></tr><tr><td>F9USH2</td><td>lp_3050; Extracellular transglycosylase, membrane-bound</td><td>3.29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="12">Hydrolase</td><td rowspan="12"/><td>F9UTL5</td><td>lp_3341; Cell surface hydrolase, DUF915 family, membrane-bound</td><td>2.01</td></tr><tr><td>F9UM81</td><td>gph1; Phosphohydrolase</td><td>1.58</td></tr><tr><td>F9UM42</td><td>lp_0824; Hydrolase, HAD superfamily, Cof family</td><td>&#x02212;3.78</td></tr><tr><td>F9URL1</td><td>lp_2737; Cell surface hydrolase, DUF915 family, membrane-bound</td><td>&#x02212;2.25</td></tr><tr><td>F9URQ4</td><td>lp_2787; Hydrolase, HAD superfamily, Cof family</td><td>&#x02212;1.96</td></tr><tr><td>F9URF0</td><td>xynC; Acetyl xylosidase (Promiscuous)</td><td>1.51</td></tr><tr><td>F9USG7</td><td>amd; Aminohydrolase/peptidase, M20D family</td><td>&#x02212;2.33</td></tr><tr><td>Q06115</td><td>cbh; Choloylglycine hydrolase</td><td>&#x02212;2.05</td></tr><tr><td>F9UTI3</td><td>folQ; Dihydroneopterin triphosphate pyrophosphohydrolase</td><td>&#x02212;1.98</td></tr><tr><td>F9UPB8</td><td>lp_1767; Glycosyl hydrolase, family 25</td><td>1.84</td></tr><tr><td>F9UQI5</td><td>lp_2266; Phosphoesterase</td><td>1.75</td></tr><tr><td>F9UL25</td><td>lp_0552; Phosphoesterase</td><td>&#x02212;1.62</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="10">Other</td><td rowspan="2">Galactose metabolism and cell wall synthesis</td><td>F9UMX4</td><td>glf1; UDP-galactopyranose mutase</td><td>1.72</td></tr><tr><td>F9URD9</td><td>acm2; Cell wall hydrolase/muramidase</td><td>1.51</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Inositol phosphate metabolism</td><td>Q88S38</td><td>iolG; myo-inositol 2-dehydrogenase (promiscuous)</td><td>&#x02212;6.86</td></tr><tr><td>Q88S37</td><td>iolE; 2-keto-myo-inositol dehydratase (promiscuous)</td><td>&#x02212;2.18</td></tr><tr><td>F9ULG2</td><td>lp_3608; myo-inositol 2-dehydrogenase-like (promiscuous)</td><td>&#x02212;3.25</td></tr><tr><td>F9ULG4</td><td>lp_3612; myo-inositol 2-dehydrogenase-like (promiscuous)</td><td>&#x02212;2.95</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Amino sugar and nucleotide sugar metabolism</td><td>F9USZ6</td><td>sacK1; fructokinase</td><td>1.61</td></tr><tr><td>Q88SC3</td><td>murQ1; N-acetylmuramic acid 6-phosphate etherase</td><td>&#x02212;1.80</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Oxidative phosphorylation</td><td>Q88UT8</td><td>atpE; H(+)-transporting two-sector ATPase, C subunit</td><td>1.62</td></tr><tr><td>F9UQR9</td><td>atpB; H(+)-transporting two-sector ATPase, A subunit</td><td>1.73</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="16"/><td rowspan="2">Riboflavin metabolism</td><td>F9UNI1</td><td>ribA; 3,4-dihydroxy-2-butanone 4-phosphate synthase/GTP cyclohydrolase II</td><td>&#x02212;4.71</td></tr><tr><td>Q88X16</td><td>ribH; riboflavin synthase, beta chain</td><td>&#x02212;4.63</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="14">Other</td><td>F9UQZ9</td><td>lp_2463; Prophage P2b protein 18, major capsid protein</td><td>6.88</td></tr><tr><td>F9UQX7</td><td>lp_2437; Prophage P2a protein 20, replication protein DnaD domain</td><td>1.95</td></tr><tr><td>F9US31</td><td>lp_2953; Esterase</td><td>1.68</td></tr><tr><td>F9UNU9</td><td>fthC; 5-formyltetrahydrofolate cyclo-ligase</td><td>1.98</td></tr><tr><td>Q890D7</td><td>lp_0089; UPF0246 protein</td><td>1.71</td></tr><tr><td>Q88V85</td><td>sepF; Cell division protein SepF</td><td>2.24</td></tr><tr><td>F9UPG0</td><td>tarJ; ribitol-5-phosphate 2-dehydrogenase</td><td>10.23</td></tr><tr><td>F9URL0</td><td>cah; Carbonate dehydratase</td><td>1.51</td></tr><tr><td>F9URA1</td><td>rnh; Ribonuclease H</td><td>1.62</td></tr><tr><td>F9UPE3</td><td>lp_1796; DegV family protein</td><td>1.50</td></tr><tr><td>Q6LWH3</td><td>repB; Copy number control protein</td><td>&#x02212;4.51</td></tr><tr><td>Q88VB0</td><td>lp_2157; UPF0356 protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.52</td></tr><tr><td>F9UNZ6</td><td>tpk; Thiamin pyrophosphokinase</td><td>2.12</td></tr><tr><td>F9ULU2</td><td>rsmI; Ribosomal RNA small subunit methyltransferase I</td><td>1.74</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="18">Uncharacterized protein</td><td rowspan="18"/><td>F9UQ40</td><td>lp_2093; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.51</td></tr><tr><td>F9UNU5</td><td>lp_1566; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.61</td></tr><tr><td>Q6LWD6</td><td>orf41; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.79</td></tr><tr><td>F9UPK2</td><td>lp_1872; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.56</td></tr><tr><td>F9UU56</td><td>lp_3372; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>&#x02212;2.05</td></tr><tr><td>F9UM53</td><td>lp_0837; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.63</td></tr><tr><td>F9UTZ1</td><td>lp_0402; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.69</td></tr><tr><td>F9UKY5</td><td>lp_0507; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.88</td></tr><tr><td>Q6LWD8</td><td>orf39; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>2.86</td></tr><tr><td>Q6LWD7</td><td>orf40; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>2.66</td></tr><tr><td>F9UT92</td><td>lp_3179; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>1.78</td></tr><tr><td>F9URF7</td><td>lp_2667; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>1.67</td></tr><tr><td>F9UQN8</td><td>lp_2333; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>1.54</td></tr><tr><td>F9UN47</td><td>lp_1257; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>1.54</td></tr><tr><td>F9USX1</td><td>lp_0158; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>1.51</td></tr><tr><td>F9UQ59</td><td>lp_2112; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>1.66</td></tr><tr><td>F9UQ60</td><td>lp_2113; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>&#x02212;4.47</td></tr><tr><td>F9UTE8</td><td>lp_3250; Uncharacterized protein</td><td>&#x02212;3.03</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<sup>a</sup>Category of differently expressed proteins was based on their functions annotated in the database of Uniprot and KEGG. <sup>b</sup>Accession number of each protein in Uniprot database. <sup>c</sup>Description of each differently expressed protein, including corresponding gene name of each protein and full protein name. <sup>d</sup>FC indicates fold change of each differently expressed protein in the comparison of CCFM8610/CCFM191. Negative values indicate down-regulation of proteins, and positive values indicate up-regulation.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>The proteomic dynamic changes of CCFM8610 and CCFM191 after Cd exposure were also evaluated to analyze the possible Cd tolerance mechanisms of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). For CCFM8610, twenty-seven proteins that changed significantly (i.e., a fold change &#x0003e;1.5 or &#x0003c;&#x02212;1.5, and <italic>P</italic> value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) by Cd stress were categorized into biological processes including global stress response, transportation, lipid, amino acid and pyrimidine metabolism and cell wall biosynthesis. For CCFM191, the abundances of 111 proteins were markedly changed after Cd exposure (i.e., a fold change &#x0003e;1.5 or &#x0003c;&#x02212;1.5, and <italic>P</italic> value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). These proteins were associated with global stress response, cell wall biosynthesis and adhesion, transporters, amino acid, lipid, pyrimidine and energy metabolism, membrane proteins and extracellular proteins. It is noted that one protein with the greatest abundance change (4.45 fold up-regulation) in CCFM8610 after Cd exposure was prophage P2b protein 18, major capsid protein (lp_2463). This protein was also in higher abundance (6.88 fold) in CCFM8610 than that in CCFM191 in the untreated condition, while the abundance of this protein was not changed in CCFM191 after Cd exposure. In addition, the abundances of prophage proteins lp_0641 and lp_2444 were significantly up-regulated in CCFM191 after Cd exposure, but remained unaffected in CCFM8610. It was also observed that these two proteins were in lower abundances in CCFM8610 than CCFM191 in non-treated conditions (with fold changes of &#x02212;1.87 and &#x02212;3.30, respectively). This may indicate that the up-regulation of lp_0641 and lp_2444 should be considered a specific Cd response mechanism of CCFM191 itself. Such mechanism seems insufficient to protect the bacterial cell against Cd stress, as CCFM191 showed poorer Cd tolerant ability than CCFM8610.</p><p>The protein-protein interaction networks were constructed for further comparative proteomic analysis (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). For the comparison between CCFM8610 and CCFM191 in natural conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>), the differentially expressed proteins were categorized into 3 main clusters, including PTS system, carbohydrate metabolism and glycerol lipid metabolism. It was observed that some global stress-related proteins (including trxA1, trxA2, gshR2, msrB and msrA2) and some nucleic acid metabolism-related proteins (including pyrR1, gmk2 and ndk) were implicated in the tricarboxylic acid (TCA) sub-cluster (including fum, pdhA, pdhB, pdhC and pdhD) of carbohydrate metabolism. Since only 27 proteins changed after Cd exposure in CCFM8610, the available protein-protein interaction network is transparent (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). The possible interaction between lp_2993 (a global stress response protein) and pdc (PadA) was observed, and the two proteins (dnaE and lp_0811) involved in pyrimidine metabolism interacted with each other. For altered protein profiles of CCFM191 after Cd exposure (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>), proteins related to glycerol lipid metabolism, pyrimidine metabolism and global stress response clustered respectively. Some differentially expressed protein profiles between CCFM8610 and CCFM191 in non-treated conditions (CCFM8610(0)/CCFM191(0); Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) were also altered in CCFM191 after Cd exposure (CCFM191(Cd)/CCFM191(0); Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>), such as carbohydrate metabolism and concomitant transportation (PTS system), and a cluster of enzymes involved in glycerolipid metabolism. This might indicate that CCFM8610 exhibits an inherent resistant status to Cd even in the absence of Cd exposure, while CCFM191 displays a similar response only after Cd exposure.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Transcription confirmation and biological phenomena</title><p>Based on the genome sequence data of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genome/?term=lactobacillus%20plantarum">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genome/?term=lactobacillus%20plantarum</ext-link>) and some well-studied Cd-tolerant microorganisms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>, Cd tolerance related proteins Cd-/zinc-/cobalt-transporting ATPase (lp_3327), Cd-transporting P-type ATPase (CadA) and Cd-/manganese-transporting P-type ATPase (mntA) were further analyzed by RT-qPCR assay, as the information of these low-abundance membrane proteins is easily to be lost during proteomic analysis. Carbamoyl-phosphate synthase, pyrimidine-specific, large chain (pyrAB), Carbamoyl-phosphate synthase, pyrimidine-specific, small chain (pyrAA), D-alanine-poly (phosphoribitol) ligase subunit 2-1 (dltC1), D-alanine-poly(phosphoribitol) ligase subunit 2-2 (dltC2), Transcription regulator of CopAB ATPases (copR), Prophage P2a protein 13 (lp_2444), Nucleotide-binding protein, universal stress protein UspA family (lp_2993), DNA-directed DNA polymerase III subunit epsilon (lp_0811) and Cold shock protein 1 (CspP), were randomly selected for RT-qPCR assay to confirm the reliability of proteomic results. For this reason, the proteins in the same operon are preferred, such as pyrAA and pyrAB, and dltC1 and dltC2. The mRNA expressions of Cd tolerance-related proteins, CadA, mntA and lp_3327, showed clear up-regulation in CCFM8610 after Cd exposure, while these genes (lp_3327 and mntA) were down-regulated or remained unchanged (CadA) in CCFM191 after Cd exposure (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). The alterations in the mRNA expressions of Csp P and lp_0811 in CCFM8610 after Cd exposure and those of PyrAA, PyrAB, dltC1, dltC2, copR, lp_2444 and lp_2993 in CCFM191 were in accordance with the corresponding changes in protein level, which verified the results of the proteomic study.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Relative mRNA expressions of genes encoding proteins altered in three comparisons, including CCFM8610(0)/CCFM191(0), CCFM8610(Cd)/CCFM8610(0) and CCFM191(Cd)/CCFM191(0). Values are expressed as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM of 4 independent replicates. mRNA expression of denominator in each comparison is set as reference value of 1. *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01; ***<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_1180_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e3487"/></fig>
</p><p>Compared with that of CCFM191, CCFM8610 showed more obvious enhancement of surface hydrophobicity after Cd exposure (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). The autoaggregation ability of non-Cd-treated CCFM8610 was significantly greater than that of CCFM191 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). Cd stress increased the autoaggregation ability of the former strain, but exhibited no marked effects on the latter. The scanning electron microscope (SEM) micrographs further confirmed these results (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). The Cd binding ability of CCFM8610 was more than 2-fold higher than that of CCFM191 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>). After Cd stress, the greatest amount of Cd accumulated on the external surface of the cell wall (59.22%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.94% for CCFM8610 and 45.90%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.03% for CCFM191, respectively) and in the space between the cell wall and the plasma membrane (12.01%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.23% for CCFM8610 and 4.41%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.64% for CCFM191, respectively, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8</xref>). Moreover, there is a significantly higher amount of Cd accumulated in CCFM8610 than that in CCFM191 after Cd exposure (14 times higher in the relative amount; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). The contents of the other metal ions including manganese (Mn), zinc (Zn), potassium (K), sodium (Na) and magnesium (Mg) were either unchanged or showed insignificant perturbations after Cd exposure in both strains.</p><p>We also determined the intracellular reactive oxygen species (ROS) levels of two strains before and after Cd exposure (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S9</xref>). The results showed that in the non-treated conditions (without Cd exposure), the intracellular ROS level of CCFM8610 was significantly lower than that of CCFM191. The former strain could also survive Cd stress with less drastic cellular response than the latter, as CCFM8610 showed a less significant increase in ROS level after Cd exposure. Seven detected hydrophobic amino acids were significantly up-regulated in CCFM8610 and CCFM191 after Cd exposure, with an exception of proline in CCFM8610 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10</xref>). Compared with CCFM191, CCFM8610 consumed significantly less glucose in natural conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S11</xref>). Meanwhile, this strain showed less significant fluctuation in glucose consumption than CCFM191 after Cd exposure.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In order to explore the underlying mechanism of the intra-species differences in Cd tolerance of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains, we examined the proteomic profiles of CCFM8610 (strongly resistant to Cd) and CCFM191 (sensitive to Cd) in non-stimulating conditions as well as after Cd exposure using the iTRAQ approach. The results revealed that <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> CCFM8610 displayed a complex biological network to tackle Cd stress, which may be related to carbohydrate, purine and pyrimidine metabolism, global stress responses, lipid and amino acid metabolism, metal binding properties, cell wall biosynthesis and transporters of the bacterial cell (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The Cd resistant mechanism of this strain involves a specific energy conservation survival mode, a mild induction of cellular defense and repair systems, an enhanced biosynthesis of hydrophobic amino acids, a promoted tolerance against osmotic stress and an inherent superior Cd-binding ability and effective cell wall biosynthesis ability in response to Cd stress. Potential key proteins that are important in protection of the bacterial cells against Cd toxicity were also identified.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Proposed model for response mechanisms of CCFM8610 to Cd stress. Altered proteins (fold change &#x0003e;1.5 or &#x0003c;&#x02212;1.5 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) in three comparisons of CCFM8610(0)/CCFM191(0), CCFM8610(Cd)/CCFM8610(0) and CCFM191(Cd)/CCFM191(0) are presented in the color of blue, red and green, respectively. Red dots represent Cd ions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_1180_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e3556"/></fig>
</p><sec id="Sec8"><title>Carbohydrate metabolism</title><p>The comparative proteomic profiles between the two strains in the absence of Cd treatment showed that CCFM8610 has lower abundance of 24 proteins and higher abundance of only 2 proteins associated with carbohydrate metabolism (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Five enzymes (fum, pdhA, pdhB, pdhC, and pdhD) involved in TCA cycle were in lower abundance in CCFM8610. The genes that encode Pdh proteins are known to share the same operon. The repression of the pdh operon has been reported to switch TCA cycle to a branched or noncyclic anaerobic form, which is regarded as an energy conservation strategy in <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> and <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brassicacearum</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> during Cd stress. This reduces intracellular free radicals and thus protects the bacteria against Cd-induced cytotoxicity. Citrate transport protein (citP) and the four citrate lyases (citC, citD, citE and citF) were in lower abundance in CCFM8610. This corresponded to the lower citrate concentration in this strain (unpublished data). We also observed reduced abundance of 11 proteins involved in the PTS system in CCFM8610, further indicating repression of carbohydrate metabolism even in the absence of Cd stress.</p><p>The differentially expressed proteomic profiles in the two strains after Cd exposure also confirmed this self-protection mechanism of CCFM8610. No significant changes in the proteins involved in carbohydrate metabolism were found in CCFM8610 after Cd stress (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>), indicating that the energy conservation survival mode of this strain is beneficial for tackling Cd toxicity. In contrast, carbohydrate metabolism was markedly down-regulated in CCFM191 after Cd exposure (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). This is further validated by a relative &#x0201c;poised&#x0201d; status of glucose consumption of CCFM8610 both in the presence and absence of Cd stress (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S11</xref>). Such energy conservation and survival can be regarded as an inherent &#x0201c;poised&#x0201d; physiological status of the strain against environmental stresses, including Cd exposure. A previous study on the resistant mechanism of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>pseudoalcaligenes</italic> KF707 and its more resistant mutant (T5) to tellurite exposure indicated that even in the absence of tellurite, T5 cells displayed a &#x0201c;poised&#x0201d; status with altered intracellular levels of glutathione and branched-chain amino acids, along with increased resistance to other toxic metals and metabolic inhibitors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Such a mechanism was believed as an inherent tolerance of the mutant strain primed for tellurite exposure, which further supports our hypothesis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Purine and pyrimidine metabolism</title><p>Very limited effect on pyrimidine metabolism-related proteins was observed after Cd exposure in CCFM8610. PurA, an important enzyme in the de novo pathway of purine nucleotide biosynthesis, was down-regulated in CCFM8610 after Cd exposure. NrdE, lp_0811 and dnaE, three catalytic proteins involved in DNA replication, were also changed by Cd stress. In contrast, nine purine and pyrimidine metabolism-related proteins were altered during the Cd stress responses of CCFM191 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>), most of which (pyrE, pyrF, pyrD, pyrAB, pyrAA, and pyrC) showed down-regulation after Cd exposure. A similar alteration was also observed in other LAB strains in response to acid and bile stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. The superior Cd tolerance of CCFM8610 may be in part due to its ability to maintain a steady physiological status, including purine and pyrimidine metabolism, after Cd exposure, which can be further validated in the following analysis of its global stress responses.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Global stress responses</title><p>Induction of global stress responses is an important strategy for bacteria to endure harsh environmental conditions. The comparative proteomic profiles between native and Cd-treated CCFM8610 showed that Cd stress caused fluctuations of only two proteins that are involved in the universal stress response, lp_2993 (up-regulated) and hsp1 (down-regulated) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). The former has also been reported to play a putative role against Cd stress in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brassicacearum</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>.</p><p>In contrast, CCFM191 showed more marked changes with 16 significantly altered proteins related to stress response after Cd shock (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). These proteins include a key protease (Clp) functioning in maintaining cytoplasmic protein quality, four universal stress related proteins (uvrA, recA, lp_0699 and lp_2993) involving in DNA repair, 10 proteins belonging to oxidoreductases. An increase in the level of Clp, a key protease that functions in maintaining quality of cytoplasmic proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>, was also found after environmental stress in other microorganisms, such as <italic>L</italic>. <italic>reuteri</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>, <italic>L</italic>. <italic>acidophilus</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>, and <italic>Oenococcus oeni</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>.</p><p>In non-stimulating conditions, CCFM191 showed higher abundance (compared to CCFM8610) of two proteins (mutS2 and recU) involved in DNA repair, four proteins (msrA, msrB, lp_3259 and pepD1) related to protein repair, two proteins (lp_2952 and lp_2616) related to bacteriocin immunity, and one protein (hsp1) involved in stress response. In addition, a marked distinction was observed between CCFM8610 and CCFM191 in 23 oxidoreductases, indicating that these two strains display different oxidative stress status even in the absence of Cd exposure.</p><p>However, not all repair or defense proteins are stress-inducible<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Looking at the different nucleic acid metabolism&#x02013;related and global stress response-related proteomic profiles between these two strains in non-stimulating conditions, as well as in response to Cd exposure, we conclude that compared with CCFM191, CCFM8610 is able to respond to environmental stress with weaker induction of the cellular defense and repair system. The intracellular ROS level of CCFM8610 was significantly lower than that of CCFM191 both in the presence and absence of Cd stress, which further supported our conclusion (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S9</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Lipid and amino acid metabolism</title><p>In non-stimulating conditions, cyclopropane-fatty-acyl-phospholipid synthase (cfa2) was in a higher abundance in CCFM8610 than that in CCFM191. This protein is responsible for the methylation reaction that translates preexisting <italic>cis</italic>-UFAs to cyclopropane fatty acids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. As cyclopropane fatty acids have been reported to increase acid resistance in <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>, the relatively high expression of Cfa in CCFM8610 may be a determinant for its stress tolerance.</p><p>A chorismate mutase (aroA) and two acyl carrier proteins (acpA1 and acpA2) were up-regulated in both CCFM8610 and CCFM191 after Cd exposure (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). AroA can trigger the biosynthesis of phenylalanine and tyrosine, which in turn increases the hydrophobicity of the bacterial cell surface to prevent Cd-induced protein damage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. Our <italic>in vitro</italic> assays demonstrated a significant up-regulation of hydrophobic amino acids and surface hydrophobicity in both strains (Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10</xref>), which further supported this hypothesis. AcpA1 and acpA2 are well-known proteins involved in fatty acid biosynthesis and protein translation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. The up-regulation of these two proteins may result in a change in membrane fatty acid composition, which improves the tolerance of bacteria against environmental stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>.</p><p>For CCFM191, significant changes in amino acid metabolism were observed after Cd exposure (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). Two proteins (glyA and gcsH2) involved in glycine biosynthesis and three proteins (cblB, queA and metH) involved sulfur amino acid metabolism were markedly up-regulated. Glycine is one of osmotic protection molecules in bacteria and has been reported to play a role in the response of metal stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. As Cd binds preferentially to sulfur ligand<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>, the up-regulation of sulfur amino acid metabolism may be a self-detoxification mechanism of CCFM191 against Cd exposure.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Metal binding and cell wall biosynthesis</title><p>In conditions without Cd stress, marked differences were observed in the abundance of extracellular, membrane and cell surface proteins between CCFM8610 and CCFM191 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). It has been reported that Cd could compete for the binding sites of proteins with other metals such as iron, zinc, and calcium<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. The higher abundance of fhuD, an iron chelatin, might improve the Cd-binding capacity of CCFM8610. Another protein with higher abundance in CCFM8610, hydrolase phosphohydrolase (gph1), can release free phosphate from lipids and precipitate Cd as CdHPO<sub>4</sub> or other chemical forms onto the cell surface<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. Consistent with these analyses, our <italic>in vitro</italic> adsorption assays in aqueous phase solution showed that CCFM8610 possesses significantly better Cd binding ability and sequesters a higher proportion of Cd in the cellular surface than CCFM191 (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8</xref>). As previously reported, this may be a self-protection of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strain to decrease the risk of Cd-induced intracellular toxicity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>.</p><p>As the cell wall is the first line of defense against environmental stress for bacteria<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>, the enhancement of cell wall biosynthesis may be a self-protective mechanism of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains in response to Cd exposure. DltC1, a protein that plays a role in lipoteichoic acid (LTA) biosynthesis, showed a 2.56-fold up-regulation in CCFM8610, which was higher than that in CCFM191 (1.71-fold, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). Previous study has demonstrated that LTA can bind metal ions and affect electromechanical characteristics of the cell wall in <italic>L</italic>. <italic>casei</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. This can also partly explain the different Cd-binding abilities of the two <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains tested here (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>).</p><p>The observed differences in metal binding and cell wall biosynthesis properties of the two strains were further verified by a significantly higher Cd accumulation in CCFM8610 after Cd exposure compared with CCFM191 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). The intracellular concentrations of other metals were relatively unaltered after Cd exposure. This may indicate that the Cd binding process in CCFM8610 is selective, which is in correspondence with our earlier <italic>in vivo</italic> study which showed that essential elements such as Ca, Zn and Mg were unaltered in the tissues of mice after oral administration of CCFM8610<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. The adsorption of elements on the cell surface have been reported to influence the hydrophobicity and autoaggregation properties, which in turn improves the stress tolerance of the bacteria<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. This is consistent with the more significant changes in the surface properties observed in CCFM8610 after Cd exposure (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>).</p><p>The strong Cd tolerance of CCFM8610 might therefore be partly attributed to its inherent Cd-binding ability provided by surface proteins and the effective cell wall biosynthetic ability during Cd exposure, thus blocking the entry of this toxic metal into the cell cytoplasm.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Transporters</title><p>Cd exposure inevitably induces osmotic stress in bacterial cells, which in turn leads to further cell damage. The tight regulation of metal import is one of the most basic mechanisms of metal homeostasis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>, and ion transporters have been reported to play a role in the Cd stress response in <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. In the present study, cobalt ABC transporter ATP-binding protein (lp_0100) was observed to be down-regulated by 1.68-fold in CCFM8610 after Cd exposure, which could be regarded as a response of the strain to osmotic stress. The phosphoenolpyruvate-dependent PTS is a major carbohydrate transport system in LAB strains. Two PTS sugar transporters (rafP and pts35B) were down-regulated in CCFM8610 after Cd exposure, indicating the energy-conservation survival mode of this strain during Cd stress.</p><p>Compared with CCFM8610, CCFM191 showed extra changes in three carbohydrate transporters (pts29C, pts6C and malT), five ABC transporters (lp_3018, lp_2974, lp_2893, lp_2543 and lp_2541), one branched-chain amino acid transporter (livA) and two glycerol uptake facilitators (glpF4 and glpF3) after Cd exposure. These changes might indicate that in order to survive the Cd stress, the sensitive strain CCFM191 needs to shut down more carbohydrate transporters, optimize ABC transporters and increase the proportion of hydrophobic amino acids.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Potential key proteins</title><p>In the non-treated conditions, the abundance of prophage P2b protein 18 (lp_2463) in CCFM8610 was 6.88-fold higher than that in CCFM191, which was the second-highest fold change among all up-regulated proteins between the two strains. In addition, this prophage protein was observed to be the most significantly up-regulated protein (4.45-fold) in CCFM8610 after Cd exposure. In the Cd-sensitive strain CCFM191, prophage P2b protein 18 remained unaffected (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). In pathogenic bacteria, phage genes are related to genetic islands encoding virulence and colonization factors and play a role in the environmental adaption of the bacteria<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. Prophage-dependent thermo-resistance via plasmid integration has been reported in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. The phage genes have also been observed to be up-regulated in <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> upon Cd stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. These analyses highlighted the prophage P2b protein 18 as a potential key determinant in <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains for the response to Cd stress. The acquisition of this stress resistance-related protein by CCFM8610 is a clear benefit to the strain.</p><p>Cd-tolerance-associated proteins, including CadA, mntA and lp_3327, are believed to be Cd transporters in the cell membranes of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains and some well-studied Cd-tolerant microorganisms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. Since the information of these membrane proteins is easily to be lost during proteomic analysis due to their low abundance and the insufficient extraction, the expressions of their genes were quantified by RT-qPCR (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). The expression of CadA, a P-type ATPase which catalyzes the active efflux of Cd<sup>2+</sup>, was markedly up-regulated (fold change &#x0003e;17) after Cd exposure in CCFM8610, while in CCFM191 it was only marginally down-regulated (0.85 fold). The Cd-resistant function of CadA is well established in <italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic>, <italic>L</italic>. <italic>monocytogenes</italic> and <italic>L</italic>. <italic>lactis</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>, the significantly enhanced efflux of Cd by the up-regulation of CadA might be a detoxification strategy of CCFM8610. The expression of mntA, a Cd<sup>2+</sup>-Mn<sup>2+</sup> shared transporter, and lp_3327, a Cd-/zinc-/cobalt-transporting ATPase, were up-regulated 6.06-fold and 4.57-fold in CCFM8610 after Cd exposure, respectively. However, the expressions of these two proteins slightly decreased in CCFM191. Besides their metal transporting ability, mntA and lp_3327 have been reported to harbor multiple transmembrane domains that bind metal. Therefore, these proteins may also prevent Cd-induced cytotoxicity by Cd sequestration. This may also explain the difference of Cd tolerance between these two strains.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In this study, we investigated the mechanism of Cd stress response of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains using comparative and functional proteomic analysis of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> CCFM8610 (strongly resistant to Cd) and <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> CCFM191 (sensitive to Cd). The proteomic profiles in non-stimulating conditions and the altered proteomic profiles after Cd stress in both strains were explored. Of the total 1415 identified proteins, 206 were differentially expressed for the comparison of natural proteomic profiles of CCFM8610 and CCFM191, 27 were differently regulated in CCFM8610 after Cd exposure, and 111 were changed in CCFM191 in response to Cd stress. Both strains showed physiological alterations in energy metabolism, purine and pyrimidine metabolism, global stress responses, lipid and amino acid metabolism, metal binding properties, cell wall biosynthesis and transporters in response to Cd exposure. The underlying mechanism of the intra-species distinctions between CCFM8610 and CCFM191 on Cd tolerance can be attributed to the following aspects. (a) CCFM8610 possesses a specific energy-conservation survival mode, which can be regarded as an inherent &#x0201c;poised&#x0201d; physiological status primed for Cd exposure. (b) CCFM8610 can cope with environmental stress with mild induction of the cellular defense and repair system, which enables the strain to survive Cd exposure without drastic physiological response. (c) CCFM8610 induces the biosynthesis of hydrophobic amino acids that enhance surface hydrophobicity of the cell and prevent Cd-induced protein damage. (d) CCFM8610 has inherent superior Cd binding ability and effective cell wall structures, which promotes Cd sequestration on the surface of the cell, preventing the uptake of this toxic metal into the cytoplasm. (e) CCFM8610 exhibits a tight regulation on ion transport to withstand the Cd-induced osmotic stress. (f) Several key proteins, including prophage P2b protein 18, CadA, mntA and lp_3327, also play a potential role in Cd tolerance in CCFM8610. This study provides an overview of the Cd stress response network (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>) of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> CCFM8610 that enables this strain to be strongly resistant to Cd.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Experimental Procedures</title><p>Cadmium chloride (CdCl<sub>2</sub>) and other chemicals were purchased from Shanghai Sinopharm Chemical Reagent Company (China). Trizol reagent was obtained from Ambion Life Technologies (USA). TAKARA RR047A kits were purchased from TAKARA BIO INC (China). iTaqTM Universal SYBR&#x000ae; Green Supermix was purchased from Bio-Rad (USA). iTRAQ reagents were purchased from Applied Biosystems (USA).</p><sec id="Sec17"><title>Bacterial Strains and Growth Conditions</title><p>Twenty <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains, including CCFM11, CCFM166, CCFM191, CCFM198, CCFM231, CCFM232, CCFM239, CCFM240, CCFM241, CCFM308, CCFM309, CCFM405, CCFM436, CCFM578, CCFM579, CCFM595, CCFM602, CCFM605, CCFM8610, and CCFM8661, were all obtained from the Culture Collections of Food Microbiology, Jiangnan University (Wuxi, China). All strains were cultured in de Man, Rogosa and Sharpe (MRS) broth (Hopebio Company, Qingdao, China) at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 18&#x02009;h routinely.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Cd tolerance assay</title><p>As it is normally to incubate the bacteria in liquid medium for proteomic analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>, twenty <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains were inoculated (2% v/v) into MRS broth containing Cd<sup>2+</sup> ranging from 0&#x02009;mg/L to 50&#x02009;mg/L and then incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The OD<sub>600</sub> values were measured at different time points until the stationary phase of the strains. The relative growth rate of each strain was expressed as a percentage of that of the control culture (without Cd exposure) which was assigned a value of 100%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. The MIC value of each strain was determined as the lowest Cd concentration that completely inhibited the growth rate of the strains.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Proteomics analysis</title><sec id="Sec20"><title>Whole cell protein extraction</title><p>Based on the data of Cd tolerance assay, two strains with the widest difference in Cd tolerance values were selected for proteomics analysis. The strains were grown in the Cd containing MRS broth at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and the Cd concentration was set as the 1/2 MIC value of the sensitive strain (5&#x02009;mg/L) as that was established previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. The strains were also incubated in Cd-free media as a control.</p><p>At the early stationary phase (OD<sub>600</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.0)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>, the cells were harvested and washed twice with ice-cooled phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) solution and pelleted. The collected pellets were immediately stored at &#x02212;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and used for protein extraction. The cell protein was extracted as previously described with minor modifications<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>. The detailed procedure of protein extraction could be found in supplementary materials.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Protein sample preparation and iTRAQ labeling</title><p>The detailed description of protein sample preparation and iTRAQ labeling can be seen in the supplementary materials. The workflow of the iTRAQ experiment with 9 replicates (3 biological replicates&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;3 mechanical replicates in mass spectrometry runs) in each of four conditions is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Liquid chromatography tandem mass spectrometry (LC/LC&#x02212;MS/MS) Analysis</title><p>The detailed procedures can be seen in the supplementary materials.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Protein identification and screening of differently expressed proteins</title><p>The raw data obtained from LC/LC&#x02212;MS/MS analysis were processed using Thermo Proteome Discoverer software (v1.0 build 43, Thermo Fisher Scientific) and searched with Mascot (Matrix Science, London, UK) at the in-house server to perform database comparisons against <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> WCFS1, based on our preliminary studies revealing that there is a utmost genome similarity between our CCFM8610 and WCFS1. The function of the identified proteins was annotated using Gene Ontology (GO) analysis, and the metabolomics pathway was analyzed using the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) database. The threshold for differentiated expressed proteins was set as <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and fold change &#x0003e;1.5 or &#x0003c;&#x02212;1.5.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Quantifications of key proteins in proteomics</title><p>The total RNA of the strains was extracted using Trizol reagent (Life Technologies). Reverse transcription was performed with TAKARA RR047A kits according to the instruction manual. The alterations of mRNA expressions were evaluated as previously reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. The primers listed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> were designed using Primer 5.0 software based on the genome sequence of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> WCFS1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. The <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> 16S rRNA gene was used as an expression control with primers specific for <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> strains, and each reaction was conducted in four duplicates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Biological phenomena</title><p>Intracellular metal accumulation, Cd binding, bacterial hydrophobicity, autoaggregation, scanning electron microscope (SEM), intracellular reactive oxygen species (ROS) production, cellular components involved in Cd binding, glucose consumption and hydrophobic amino acid production.</p><p>The detailed procedures of these assays can be seen in the material supplementary materials.</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data were expressed as the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard error of the mean (SEM) for each group. Differences between groups were analyzed using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA), followed by the Tukey post-hoc test. A <italic>P</italic> value of &#x0003c;0.05 was considered to indicate statistical significance.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec27"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2017_1180_MOESM1_ESM.doc"><caption><p>Supplementary Info</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Qixiao Zhai and Yue Xiao contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p>
<bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at doi:10.1038/s41598-017-01180-x
</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China Key Program (No. 31530056), National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 31601452), the Natural Science Foundation of Jiangsu Province (BK20160175), the General Financial Grant from the China Postdoctoral Science Foundation (2016M590412), the General Financial Grant from the Jiangsu Postdoctoral Science Foundation (No. 1601113&#x02009;C), BBSRC Newton Fund Joint Centre Award.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Q.Z. and Y.X. carried out the experiment and drafted the manuscript. F.T., J.Z. and H.Z. participated in the RT-qPCR assay, Cd tolerance assay, intracellular metal accumulation and Cd binding, hydrophobicity and autoaggregation assays, and analyzed the data. A.N. and W.C. conceived of the study, managed the project design and helped to revise the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uetani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tissue cadmium (Cd) concentrations of people living in a Cd polluted area, Japan</article-title><source>Biometals</source><year>2006</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10534-005-5619-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16937258?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16937258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hyder</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cadmium exposure and liver disease among US adults</article-title><source>J. Gastrointest. Surg.</source><year>2013</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1265</fpage><lpage>1273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11605-013-2210-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23636881?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23636881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Satarug</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sens</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sens</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cadmium, Environmental Exposure, and Health Outcomes</article-title><source>Environ. Health Perspect.</source><year>2010</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>183</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">IARC. In <italic>Lyon IARC Monographs on the evaluation of carcinogenic risks to humans</italic> Vol. 58, 148&#x02013;161, 206&#x02013;210 (International Agency for Research on Cancer, 1993).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Goyer, R. A. &#x00026; Clarkson, T. W. In <italic>Casarett &#x00026; Doull&#x02019;s Toxicology: The Basic Science of Poisons</italic> (ed. C. D. Klaassen) Ch. 23, 825&#x02013;826 (McGraw-Hill Health Professions Division, 2001).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nordberg, G. F., Nogawa, K., Nordberg, M. &#x00026; Friberg, L. T. In <italic>Handbook on the Toxicology of Metals</italic> (eds Gunnar F. Nordberg, Bruce A. Fowler, Monica Nordberg &#x00026; Lars T. Friberg) vii, 446, 463&#x02013;470 (Academic Press, 2011).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> microflora of the human intestine: composition and succession</article-title><source>Curr. Issues Intest. Microbiol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11721280?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11721280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Folign&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pot</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probiotics from research to market: the possibilities, risks and challenges</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Microbiol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2013.06.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23866974?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23866974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protective effects of <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> CCFM8610 against acute cadmium toxicity in mice</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>1508</fpage><lpage>1515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.03417-12</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23263961?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23263961</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protective effects of <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> CCFM8610 against chronic cadmium toxicity in mice indicate routes of protection besides intestinal sequestration</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>4063</fpage><lpage>4071</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00762-14</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24771031?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24771031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oral administration of probiotics inhibits heavy metal cadmium absorption by protecting intestinal barrier</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>AEM</volume><fpage>00695</fpage><lpage>00616</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global gene expression responses to cadmium toxicity in</article-title><source>Escherichia coli. J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>3259</fpage><lpage>3266</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15838054?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15838054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vido</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A proteome analysis of the cadmium response in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>8469</fpage><lpage>8474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M008708200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11078740?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11078740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banjerdkij</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vattanaviboon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mongkolsuk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exposure to cadmium elevates expression of genes in the OxyR and OhrR regulons and induces cross-resistance to peroxide killing treatment in <italic>Xanthomonas campestris</italic></article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>1843</fpage><lpage>1849</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.71.4.1843-1849.2005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15812010?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15812010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Screening of lactic acid bacteria with potential protective effects against cadmium toxicity</article-title><source>Food Control</source><year>2015</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2015.01.037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matyar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Din&#x000e7;er</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial agents and heavy metal resistance in Gram-negative bacteria isolated from seawater, shrimp and sediment in Iskenderun Bay, Turkey</article-title><source>Sci. Total Environ.</source><year>2008</year><volume>407</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2008.08.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18804847?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18804847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abou-Shanab</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Berkum</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Angle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heavy metal resistance and genotypic analysis of metal resistance genes in gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria present in Ni-rich serpentine soil and in the rhizosphere of <italic>Alyssum murale</italic></article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><year>2007</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>360</fpage><lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2006.12.051</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17276484?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17276484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Glickmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooksey</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromosomal locus for cadmium resistance in <italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic> consisting of a cadmium-transporting ATPase and a MerR family response regulator</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>1437</fpage><lpage>1444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.67.4.1437-1444.2001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11282588?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11282588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exploration of intraclonal adaptation mechanisms of <italic>Pseudomonas brassicacearum</italic> facing cadmium toxicity</article-title><source>Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2820</fpage><lpage>2835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2007.01394.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17922765?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17922765</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaballa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Helmann</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic and physiological responses of <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> to metal ion stress</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2005.04642.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15948947?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15948947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schirawski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagens</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>van Sinderen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of cadmium resistance in <italic>Streptococcus thermophilus</italic> strain 4134: an example of lateral gene transfer</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>5508</fpage><lpage>5516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.68.11.5508-5516.2002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12406744?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12406744</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delorme</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Safety assessment of dairy microorganisms: <italic>Streptococcus thermophilus</italic></article-title><source>Int. J. Food Microbiol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2007.08.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17822794?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17822794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C-Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic Analysis of Regions Involved in Replication and Cadmium Resistance of the Plasmid pND302 from <italic>Lactococcus lactis</italic></article-title><source>Plasmid</source><year>1997</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/plas.1997.1301</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9339465?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9339465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Sullivan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Naturally occurring lactococcal plasmid pAH90 links bacteriophage resistance and mobility functions to a food-grade selectable marker</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>929</fpage><lpage>937</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.67.2.929-937.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11157264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning, expression, and characterization of cadmium and manganese uptake genes from <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic></article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>4746</fpage><lpage>4752</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10543781?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10543781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Kranenburg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional analysis of three plasmids from <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic></article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>1223</fpage><lpage>1230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.71.3.1223-1230.2005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15746322?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15746322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Pajarillo</surname><given-names>EAB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chae</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>D-K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteomic and transcriptional analysis of <italic>Lactobacillus johnsonii</italic> PF01 during bile salt exposure by iTRAQ shotgun proteomics and quantitative RT-PCR</article-title><source>J. Proteome Res.</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>432</fpage><lpage>443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr300794y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23181408?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23181408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proteomic characterization of the <italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic> KT2440 global response to a monocyclic aromatic compound by iTRAQ analysis and 1DE-MudPIT</article-title><source>J. Proteomics</source><year>2011</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>620</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jprot.2011.01.020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21315195?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21315195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Raftery</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kjelleberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Profiling the secretome of the marine bacterium <italic>Pseudoalteromonas tunicata</italic> using amine-specific isobaric tagging (iTRAQ)</article-title><source>J. Proteome Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>967</fpage><lpage>975</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr060416x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17330939?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17330939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Timms</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Difference gel electrophoresis</article-title><source>Proteomics</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>4886</fpage><lpage>4897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.200800298</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19003860?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19003860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative study of three proteomic quantitative methods, DIGE, cICAT, and iTRAQ, using 2D gel- or LC-MALDI TOF/TOF</article-title><source>J. Proteome Res.</source><year>2006</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr050405o</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16512681?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16512681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Surowitz</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Titus</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfister</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of cadmium accumulation on growth and respiration of a cadmium-sensitive strain of <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> and a selected cadmium resistant mutant</article-title><source>Arch. Microbiol.</source><year>1984</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00454911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proteomic analysis of the copper resistance of <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title><source>Metallomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>448</fpage><lpage>454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C4MT00276H</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25608595?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25608595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y-M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proteomic analysis of cadmium exposure in cultured lung epithelial cells: evidence for oxidative stress-induced cytotoxicity</article-title><source>Toxicol. Res.</source><year>2013</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>280</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c3tx50014d</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aguilar-Barajas, E., Ram&#x000ed;rez-D&#x000ed;az, M. I., Riveros-Rosas, H. &#x00026; Cervantes, C. In <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> 255&#x02013;282 (Springer, 2010).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Copper and cadmium: responses in <italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic> KT2440</article-title><source>Lett. Appl. Microbiol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>775</fpage><lpage>783</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1472-765X.2009.02741.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19843215?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19843215</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tremaroli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Metabolomic investigation of the bacterial response to a metal challenge</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01771-08</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19047385?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19047385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heunis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Deane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dicks</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteomic profiling of the acid stress response in <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> 423</article-title><source>J. Proteome Res.</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>4028</fpage><lpage>4039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr500353x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25068841?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25068841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated transcriptomic and proteomic analysis of the bile stress response in a centenarian-originated probiotic <italic>Bifidobacterium longum</italic> BBMN68</article-title><source>Mol. Cell Proteomics</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2558</fpage><lpage>2572</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.M114.039156</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24965555?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24965555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wickner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Maurizi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottesman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Posttranslational quality control: folding, refolding, and degrading proteins</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1999</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>1888</fpage><lpage>1893</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.286.5446.1888</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10583944?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10583944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The early response to acid shock in <italic>Lactobacillus reuteri</italic> involves the ClpL chaperone and a putative cell wall-altering esterase</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>3924</fpage><lpage>3935</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01502-06</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17449683?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17449683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfeiler</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Azcarate-Peril</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Klaenhammer</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of a novel bile-inducible operon encoding a two-component regulatory system in <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>189</volume><fpage>4624</fpage><lpage>4634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00337-07</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17449631?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17449631</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beltramo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandvalet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Guzzo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for multiple levels of regulation of <italic>Oenococcus oeni</italic> clpP-clpL locus expression in response to stress</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>2200</fpage><lpage>2205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.186.7.2200-2205.2003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15028706?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15028706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feder</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heat-shock proteins, molecular chaperones, and the stress response: evolutionary and ecological physiology</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Physiol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.physiol.61.1.243</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10099689?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10099689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rock</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Membrane lipid homeostasis in bacteria</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1839</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18264115?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18264115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronan</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Membrane cyclopropane fatty acid content is a major factor in acid resistance of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1999.01456.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10411742?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10411742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kast</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A strategically positioned cation is crucial for efficient catalysis by chorismate mutase</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>36832</fpage><lpage>36838</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M006351200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10960481?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10960481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fozo</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Quivey</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shifts in the membrane fatty acid profile of <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> enhance survival in acidic environments</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>929</fpage><lpage>936</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.70.2.929-936.2004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14766573?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14766573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Csonka</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological and genetic responses of bacteria to osmotic stress</article-title><source>Microbiol. Rev.</source><year>1989</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><?supplied-pmid 2651863?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2651863</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metal speciation in natural waters with emphasis on reduced sulfur groups as strong metal binding sites</article-title><source>Comp. Biochem. Physiol. C Toxicol. Pharmacol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1532-0456(02)00108-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12356517?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12356517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bridges</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zalups</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular and ionic mimicry and the transport of toxic metals</article-title><source>Toxicol. Appl. Pharmacol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>204</volume><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.taap.2004.09.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15845419?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15845419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macaskie</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheetham</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakeman</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Skarnulis</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cadmium accumulation by a <italic>Citrobacter</italic> sp.: the chemical nature of the accumulated metal precipitate and its location on the bacterial cells</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>1987</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00221287-133-3-539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The cadmium binding characteristics of a lactic acid bacterium in aqueous solutions and its application for removal of cadmium from fruit and vegetable juices</article-title><source>RSC Adv.</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>5990</fpage><lpage>5998</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5RA24843D</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neuhaus</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Heaton</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Debabov</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The dlt operon in the biosynthesis of D-alanyl-lipoteichoic acid in <italic>Lactobacillus casei</italic></article-title><source>Microb. Drug Resist.</source><year>1996</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/mdr.1996.2.77</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9158726?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9158726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Complete genome sequence of enterohemorrhagic <italic>Eschelichia coli</italic> O157: H7 and genomic comparison with a laboratory strain K-12</article-title><source>DNA Res.</source><year>2001</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/dnares/8.1.11</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11258796?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11258796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimsey</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldor</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CTX&#x003d5; and <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic>: exploring a newly recognized type of phage&#x02013;host cell relationship</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2005.04676.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15978069?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15978069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwesinger</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Novick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prophage-dependent plasmid integration in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>1975</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>724</fpage><lpage>738</lpage><?supplied-pmid 125745?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">125745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kleerebezem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Complete genome sequence of <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> WCFS1</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>1990</fpage><lpage>1995</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0337704100</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12566566?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12566566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lebrun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Audurier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cossart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasmid-borne cadmium resistance genes in <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> are similar to cadA and cadC of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and are induced by cadmium</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>1994</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>3040</fpage><lpage>3048</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jb.176.10.3040-3048.1994</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8188605?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8188605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nucifora</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cadmium resistance from <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> plasmid pI258 cadA gene results from a cadmium-efflux ATPase</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><year>1989</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>3544</fpage><lpage>3548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.86.10.3544</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2524829?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2524829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative proteomic analysis of <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> for the identification of key proteins in bile tolerance</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-11-63</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21194490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>iTRAQ-coupled 2-D LC&#x02013;MS/MS analysis of cytoplasmic protein profile in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> incubated with apidaecin IB</article-title><source>J. Proteomics</source><year>2011</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jprot.2011.08.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21889622?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21889622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xiao, Y. <italic>et al</italic>. Metabolomics analysis reveals heavy metal copper-induced cytotoxicity in HT-29 human colon cancer cells. <italic>RSC Adv</italic>. <bold>6</bold> (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chieppa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Beneduce</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Massa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression analysis of putative arcA, arcB and arcC genes partially cloned from <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> isolated from wine</article-title><source>J. Appl. Microbiol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2672.2003.02132.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14678173?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14678173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groot</surname><given-names>MNN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-based in silico detection of putative manganese transport systems in <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> and their genetic analysis</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2005</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>1229</fpage><lpage>1238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.27375-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15817790?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15817790</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>