<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5278366</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep41403</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep41403</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Characterization of faecal microbial communities of dairy cows fed diets containing ensiled Moringa oleifera fodder </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Jiajie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Bin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Zujing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Shijuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Wenjie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Baoli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Qian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xiaoyang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Ting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Qingyan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>Qianyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c2">b</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yongliang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>College of Animal Science, Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Agro-Animal Genomics and Molecular Breeding, National Engineering Research Center for Breeding Swine Industry, South China Agricultural University</institution>, Guangzhou, Guangdong 510642, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>College of Forestry and Landscape Architecture, Guangdong Engineering &amp; Research Center for Woody Fodder Plants, South China Agricultural University</institution>, Guangzhou, Guangdong 510642, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>Agro-biological Gene Research Center, Guangdong Academy of Agricultural Sciences</institution>, Guangzhou 510640, Guangdong Province, <country>China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email>zhangyl@scau.edu.cn</email></corresp><corresp id="c2"><label>b</label><email>xqy0228@163.com</email></corresp><fn id="n1"><label>*</label><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>These authors contributed equally to this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>01</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>41403</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>08</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2017, The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Moringa oleifera (M. oleifera) is a remarkable species with high nutritional value and good biomass production, which can be used as livestock fodder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>In this study, we examined changes in the faecal microbiota of thirty dairy cows in response to alternative M. oleifera diets and their effects on nutrient digestion, milk traits and the faecal concentrations of short-chain fatty acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>No differences in milk yield and constituents were found between the control and the M. oleifera alternative groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Cows fed M. oleifera silage had lower dry matter digestibility, as well as the propionate and isovalerate concentrations in M. oleifera treated group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Using 16S rDNA gene sequencing, 1,299,556 paired-end reads were obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Clustering analysis revealed 13 phyla and 93 genera across all samples. Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes were the co-dominant phyla. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Ten taxa displayed a significant difference in response to the high M. oleifera diet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>In addition, strong correlations between Akkermansia and Prevotella with milk yield and protein indicated that some bacterial groups could be used to improve milk traits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Our results provided an insight into the microbiome-associated responses to M. oleifera in livestock diets, and could aid the development of novel applications of M. oleifera. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Currently, many countries have banned the use of animal by-products and waste materials as a source of proteins in diets for livestock to ensure the consumer safety of animal products1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In addition to processed animal proteins, the availability and price of plant protein sources for animal feed, such as the soybean meal used commonly for protein supplement in animal diets, is a serious issue for animal producers2, especially for small farm stakeholders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Consequently, there is a need for alternative, cheaper ingredients with high protein contents and balanced amino acids profiles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Historically, some trees and browse species have been chosen as livestock fodder, especially during dry periods; for example, poplar and willow3, mulberry4, Leucaena leucocephala, Bauhinia purpurea5, Caragana6, and Moringa oleifera7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Among these potential candidates, M. oleifera is the most useful tree as an animal feed supplement, because its leaves are highly nutritious, with excellent palatability, digestibility, and contain a balanced chemical composition of proteins and minerals7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The protein content of M. oleifera generally ranges from 15% to over 30% dry matter (DM), which depends on the stage of maturity and on the fodder’s respective proportions of leaflets, petioles, and stems; the latter being much poorer in protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Recently, researchers have explored M. oleifera cultivation practices and its utilization as livestock fodder to improve animal production in goats8, sheep9, and cows10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Previous studies using fresh M. oleifera foliage11 or silage12 for dairy cattle have shown improvements in, or at least no affects on, live weights, milk yield, and composition compared with traditional diets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>However, to date, there has been little research investigating the effect of alternative M. oleifera diets on the dynamics of intestinal microbial communities in dairy cows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>In addition, the microbes’ metabolic processes have a direct influence on the host’s gut health and nutrient availability13, which should be considered when formulating diets with unconventional ingredients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The mammalian gastrointestinal tract has been estimated to contain 500–1000 microbial species and to comprise approximately 1014 microbes that constantly interact with the host and other members of the microbial community14. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Culture-dependent methods are inadequate to determine gut microbial profiles because only 1% of intestinal microbes with high copy numbers are culturable15. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Recently, in-depth descriptions of the gut microbiota have been produced mainly using high throughput DNA sequencing of 16S rRNA genes16. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Hence, in the present paper, we aimed to characterize the faecal microflora of dairy cows by sequencing their 16S rRNA genes, and to assess quantitatively whether the underlying faecal microbial composition and structure changed in response to ensiled M. oleifera diets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>16S rRNA gene sequencing and annotation analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Fresh faecal samples were collected from eight dairy cows fed with no M. oleifera (C), twelve cows fed a low M. oleifera diet (L), and ten cows fed a high M. oleifera diet (H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>After DNA extraction, the hypervariable V3–V4 regions of the 16S rDNA were enriched in each sample, and the subsequent high-throughput analysis generated a 1,299,556 paired-end Illumina reads representing more than 435.95 megabases (Mb). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>On average, each sample produced approximately 43,318 joined tags, which were assembled by PandaSeq v2.8 (min = 34,706, max = 58,766). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Over 85.52% ± 5.33% of the total joined tags from each sample passed quality control and were processed for further analysis (Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Clustering of operational taxonomic units (OTUs) analysis of the high-quality tags yielded 1,182 unique OTU candidates at 97% sequence similarity, and 971 candidates that were shared across all samples were defined as core OTUs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The core OTUs comprised approximately 82.15% of the total candidates, while only 29, 18, and 23 OTUs were identified uniquely in the C, L and H groups, respectively (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>We annotated all these OTU tags to the Greengenes database, and found that 99.43% ± 0.20% sequences could be aligned at the phyla taxonomic level, while 99.01% ± 0.57%, 98.99% ± 0.58%, 80.84% ± 2.73%, 35.35% ± 5.48%, and 1.27% ± 0.73% of the annotated OTUs were assigned at the class, order, family, genus, and species level, respectively (Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In addition, the microbial diversity in the faeces of dairy cows was assessed using the quantitative insights into microbial ecology (QIIME) pipeline, based on the OTU annotation, which identified 13 phyla (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The most abundant phylum in the faeces of dairy cows was Firmicutes, which accounted for approximately 54.59% ± 7.07% of all sequences, followed by Bacteroidetes (36.25% ± 5.37%), Spirochaetes (4.16% ± 3.82%), and Proteobacteria (1.87% ± 3.04%) (Table S4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Among the 93 genera detected, ten genera had a relative abundance greater than 1.0%, such as 5-7N15, Treponema, CF231, Ruminococcus, Prevotellaceae-Prevotella, YRC22, Oscillospira, Coprococcus, Clostridium, and Roseburia (Table S4B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Microbial diversity in the faeces of dairy cows </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>To compare the alpha-diversity (within-sample diversity or an estimate of species richness and evenness) of each sample with differing sequence counts/sampling efforts directly, we rarefied the data (i.e., randomly picked an equal number of sequence across the samples) using QIIME. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Rarefaction curve analysis indicated that the sequencing depth was sufficient to wholly capture the diversity present, as displayed by the microbial diversity index Chao1 (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In addition, we further used Chao1, Shannon, observed species, and phylogenetic diversity_whole tree estimator between different groups to evaluate the faecal diversity of dairy cows affected by M. oleifera treatments (Table S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Although there was a trend towards decreased alpha diversity in the M. oleifera groups compared with the control, these differences did not appear to significantly affect the species-level microbial diversity using the three measures (Chao 1 index, observed species, and phylogenetic diversity_whole tree). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>For example, the mean community richness, as estimated by the Chao 1 index, was similar between the C, L, and H groups, comprising 760.84 ± 14.39, 714.79 ± 27.41 and 703.30 ± 29.55, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In addition, the Shannon diversity index, which is used commonly to characterize species richness and evenness in a community, tended to be lower in the L and H groups compared with group C (7.54 ± 0.07 versus 7.32 ± 0.10 and 7.21 ± 0.11, respectively; P = 0.098). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>M. oleifera alternative diets altered the composition of faecal microbiota </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>To test for dissimilarities between samples collected from different M. oleifera diet groups, a global one-way analysis of similarities (ANOSIM) of Bray–Curtis similarities was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>This analysis suggested that there were large and significant differences between groups (global R = 0.122, P = 0.018) (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Pairwise ANOSIM analyses between different groups are shown in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Among the pairwise correlations, significant differences were identified between the C and H groups (P = 0.024). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>In addition, to further confirm whether alternative M. oleifera diets were of greater specific benefit for the faecal microbiome of dairy cows, we also performed a multi-response permutation procedures (MRPP) analysis in the within and between-group populations (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The differences in the between-group homogeneity were higher than those for the within-group population, with an A-value &gt; 0, and the change degree between group C and H reached statistical significance (P = 0.018), as did that between the C and L groups (P = 0.03). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Similar results were obtained using non-metric multi-dimensional scaling (NMDS) analysis, which revealed that the microbial community compositions were significantly different between group C and group H (Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The complementary analyses using ANOSIM, MRPP and NMDS provided similar results; therefore, the differences in the microbial composition (relative abundance) of faecal microbiome between the C and H groups were compared using the Metastat method with Fisher’s exact test17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Ten genus-level taxa displayed a significant difference in response to the high M. oleifera diet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The high M. oleifera diet increased the proportion of Methyloversatilis, Caulobacter, Ruminococcus, Peptococcaceae_ rc4-4, Ralstonia, and Devosia remarkably, and decreased the abundance of Coprococcus, Epulopiscium, Bacteroides, and Fibrobacter significantly, compared with group C (Table S6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>At the OTU (species) level, 180 OTUs showed a significant difference in their abundance between the C and H groups, with 60 and 120 candidates showing increases and decreases in the H group, respectively (Table S6B), which belonged to 28 representative genus taxa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Among them, 15 OTUs were from the genus Ruminococcus, especially the species bromii and gnavus, which responded significantly to the alternative M. oleifera diet. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Apparent nutrient digestibility and milk traits of dairy cows and their correlation with the faecal microbiota </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>No convincing differences in milk yield and its constituents (protein, fat, lactose, and somatic cell count) in dairy cows were found between the control and the M. oleifera-fed groups (P &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Feeding M. oleifera silage to dairy cows dramatically decreased the apparent digestibility of the DM (P &lt; 0.01), but no apparent effect were observed on the digestibility of crude protein (CP) (P &gt; 0.05) (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>To further identify the phyla that correlated significantly with the nutrient digestibility and milk traits of dairy cows, we used the Pearson correlation test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>We observed that the decreased Fibrobacteres abundance was directly and significantly associated with a modest decrease in the apparent digestibility of DM (Pearson’s r = 0.470, P = 0.009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Milk somatic cell count displayed a strong positive (Pearson’s r = 0.547, P = 0.005) and negative correlation (Pearson’s r = −0.497, P = 0.011) with the relative abundances of the bacterial families Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes, respectively (Table S7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>At the genus level, the bacterial abundances of Coprococcus and Clostridium correlated positively with the apparent digestibility of DM, and the bacterial abundances of Treponema were significantly negatively correlated with the apparent digestibility of CP (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>In addition, there were strong correlations between two bacterial families, Akkermansia and Prevotella, with milk yield and protein contents across all samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Analyses of short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs) in the faeces of dairy cows and their correlation with the faecal microbiota </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The major SCFAs observed in the faeces of dairy cows were acetate, propionate, butyrate, and valerate as well as isovalerate (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Comparison of SCFA concentrations between different tested groups revealed that all selected SCFA candidates appeared a general downtrend in response to the M. oleifera diet, and the propionic (P = 0.029) and isovaleric (P &lt; 0.01) acids were substantially and significantly lower in faeces of dairy cows fed M. oleifera silage than in those given the basic diet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>In details, feeding M. oleifera silage to dairy cows dramatically decreased the propionate concentration in H population (P = 0.013), as well as in L group (P = 0.027). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Compared with the C group, the faecal concentrations of isovalerate were lower in L and H groups; and with the increase of the alternative proportion of ensiled M. oleifera fodder, the isovalerate concentration also sharply reduced in H group compared with L group (P = 0.004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>In addition, the correlation analyses of genus taxa with the faecal concentrations of SCFAs were tested (Fig. 5), and the results showed that the gut microbial communities of dairy cows were highly related to isovaleric acid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Briefly, isovaleric acid displayed a strong positive correlation with the relative abundances of the bacterial taxa Prevotella (P = 0.071), Coprococcus (P = 0.011), Prevotella.1 (P = 0.034) and Akkermansia (P = 0.035), and negatively associated with Roseburia abundance (P = 0.025). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>For other SCFAs, Dorea (P = 0.011) correlated positively with acetate concentration, while Parabacteroides (P = 0.046) correlated negatively with propionate, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>In this study, 1,103,963 high quality valid tags were obtained across all samples, and the sequencing size of each sample ranged from 30,246 to 43,732, which were higher than those in previous studies of mouse18, human19, pigs20, and dairy cows21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Rarefaction curves analysis of the Chao1 index indicated that this sequencing depth was sufficient for further analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Clustering analysis revealed that Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes were the most dominant phyla, regardless of diet, representing approximately 90.84% ± 4.22% of the total sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>These results were similar to previous observations in porcine and human faecal samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Niu et al.22 reported that the bacterial communities of porcine faeces primarily comprised Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes, which accounted for approximately 80% of the total sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Lamendella et al.23 further confirmed the observation that most of the beneficial bacteria in porcine gut microbiome were Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>In addition, these two phyla comprised over 90% of the known phylogenetic categories, representing the dominant gut microbiota in the human intestinal tract24. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>In addition to the expression level, the functions of these two phyla taxa require further study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Recently, diet and nutritional status have emerged as major factors affecting the structure and function of the gut microbiome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>In porcine faecal specimens, gut microbiomes were associated significantly with the level of dietary fibre solubility25. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>In mice, a whole-wheat supplemented diet increased the Bacteroidetes/Firmicutes ratio of faecal microbiota and decreased the abundances of the families Enterococcaceae, Turicibacteraceae, and Ruminococcaceae26. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Similarity analysis revealed that the relative proportion of Bacteroidetes decreased in obese people, which correlated strongly with a low-calorie diet27. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>In the present study, feeding M. oleifera silage to dairy cows also resulted in significant shifts in the composition and structure of the faecal microbial community compared with the control diet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>At genus-level taxa, the abundance of Ruminococcus spp. that responded to alternative M. oleifera diets increased obviously in the faeces of dairy cows, which was similar to previous reports in horse28 and cattle29 faeces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>A previous study reported that Ruminococcus mainly inhabits the gastrointestinal tract of ruminants28, and are known for their ability to degrade a wide range of plant polysaccharides, including cellulose30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Therefore, a hypothesis was proposed that alternative M. oleifera diets likely increased the available fibre; however, Ruminococcus could compensate for this effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>More detailed determinations are needed to resolve this issue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>By contrast, the mean abundance of Coprococcus in the faecal microbiome of dairy cows was 1.36% ± 0.33%, and decreased by 28.52% in the high M. oleifera group (P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The genus Coprococcus spp., which is affiliated with the family Lachnospiraceae, was correlated positively with the production of SCFAs in the human intestine31. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The health-promoting functions of SCFAs include their roles as nutrients for the colonic epithelium and modulators of colonic pH, and a decrease in SCFAs resulted in damage to the normal function of the colonic epithelium32. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>In our paper, alternative M. oleifera diets obviously decreased the faecal concentrations of SCFAs, especially for Propionic and Isovaleric acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The correlation analyses of genus taxa with the faecal SCFAs also revealed that Coprococcus correlated positively with isovalerate concentration (P = 0.011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Hence, the M. oleifera-induced decreases in Coprococcus might be involved in intestinal pathogenesis by affecting the function of isovalerate, which supported the results of Dicksved et al.33. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>That study showed that Coprococcus were present in higher abundances in early-weaned piglets compared with suckling piglets, also suggesting the functions of Coprococcus in supplying energy to enterocytes and inhibiting intestinal inflammation33. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Various reports have highlighted the importance of M. oleifera as a cost-effective protein source supplement for livestock fodder that can be used in ruminant feeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Mendieta-Araica et al.1012 reported that feeding fresh M. oleifera foliage to dairy cows caused higher digestibility of DM and CP, but no significant differences were found in milk yield and composition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Goats fed M. oleifera leaves markedly increased their DM intake and the digestibility of most nutrients increased compared with the control diets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Milk yield, energy, and nutrient outputs were also increased by replacing sesame meal with M. oleifera leaf meal in lactating goats11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>In addition, similar performances were observed in goats fed M. oleifera silage or hay, followed by fresh M. oleifera34. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>In contrast to these previous studies, in this study, feeding M. oleifera silage to dairy cows decreased the apparent digestibility of DM, but no additional effects were observed on the digestibility of CP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The discrepancies between the present and previous studies might have resulted from the different parts of M. oleifera plants used in the experiments (whole plant vs. leaves)35, different treatments (silage vs. fresh) or species (dairy cows vs. goat). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Diets are mainly degraded by the gut microbiota36, and a number of microbials, such as Bacteroides and Butyrivibrio, are related to the apparent digestibility of nutrients in sheep37 and cows38, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Coincidentally, the abundance of Fibrobacteres was positively correlated with the apparent digestibility of DM in the present study, as were Coprococcus and Clostridium at genus taxa level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>In addition, the abundances of the phylum Tenericutes and the genus Treponema correlated negatively with the apparent digestibility of CP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>However, to date, few microbiota have been reported to modulate nutrient digestibility in dairy cattle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Generally, milk production is a direct result of improved feed utilization, and our results showed a reduced tendency for milk yield, which agreed with the decreased digestibility of DM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Additionally, correlation analysis revealed that Akkermansia and Prevotella were associated strongly with milk yield and protein contents, indicating that some bacterial groups can be used to improve milk traits. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, M. oleifera fodder can be used as a protein source in diets for lactating cows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The inclusion of M. oleifera meal decreased the apparent digestibility of DM, but no significant differences were found in milk yield and composition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the study investigated M. oleifera-induced shifts of metabolically active bacteria in the faeces of dairy cows, and showed that the variations of bacterial diversity of each individual were affected by less abundant bacterial components in the faeces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>A correlation analysis of feed utilization and milk traits with gut microbiota revealed potential candidate taxa that might prove useful for future inoculation studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Animals, feeding and management </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The animal feeding experiments were conducted at the Ranch of Xianquan Lake, in Guangzhou, Guangdong, China (Latitude: 23.13N, Longitude: 113.65E), from the 13th of December 2015 to the 23rd of January 2016 (Daily maximum temperature: 18.65 ± 2.72 °C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Sixty healthy Holstein cows were selected with similar ages, weights, parities, and lactation periods, and were randomly divided into three equal groups, termed no M. oleifera (fed a basal diet), low (25% alfalfa hay and 50% maize silage were replaced by M. oleifera silage, DM basis), and high (50% alfalfa hay and 100% maize silage were replaced by M. oleifera silage, DM basis) M. oleifera diet groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The ingredients and nutritional composition of each diet group are shown in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>All animals were fed ad libitum and had free access to water during the day except at milking time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>All animal experimentation complied with the regulation of laboratory animal management and welfare approved by the Standing Committee of Guangdong People’s Congress, China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>All experimental procedures were carried out with the approval of the ethics committee of South China Agricultural University. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Sampling and chemical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The Holstein cows were pre-fed with experimental diets for 10 days and were subsequently tested at the same time for 4 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>During the experimental periods, the dairy herds were milked robotically twice daily at an approximately 12 h interval. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The yield from each individual was weighed and recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>At the last day of the four-week experiment, 100 ml milk samples were collected in sterile vials and immediately refrigerated at 4 °C for fat, protein, lactose content, and somatic number analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>During the last 3 days of the experiment, in each group, feed and faecal samples were analysed to estimate the apparent digestibility of DM and CP using the acid-insoluble ash (AIA) method39. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>In brief, the diets and faeces of each animal were collected daily and pooled equally into one sample per cow, and then the mixtures were dried, ground and passed through a 1-mm sieve before the chemical analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The digestibility values of the chemical components were calculated by the following equation: X digestibility = [1 − (diet AIA content/faecal AIA content) × (faecal X content/diet X content)] × 100%, X = DM or CP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>SCFAs determination </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The SCFAs extraction procedures for faecal samples were performed according to the previous study with some modifications40. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Briefly, 50 μL internal standard solution (caproic acid-d3) and 1 mL of 0.005 M aqueous NaOH were added to 100 mg faecal samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Then the samples were vortexed for 15 min, and centrifuged at 13,000 × g for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Next, a total of 500 μL supernatant solution was transferred into a 10 mL glass centrifuge tube followed by adding 150 μL water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>For derivatization, 250 μL propanol/pyridine mixture solvents and 50 μL Propyl-chloroformate (PCF) were subsequently added to the glass tube, and intermittently vortexed for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>After the derivatization, 300 μL hexane was applied for SCFA derivative extraction, and the extraction procedure was then repeated by adding 200 μL of hexane to the reaction mixture again. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>An aliquot of 150 μL and 100 μL SCFAs derivatives (the upper hexane layer) from the two steps was combined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Approximately 10 mg anhydrous sodium sulfate was used to remove the traces of water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>By centrifugation at 13,000 × g for 5 min, 250 μL SCFAs derivatives were transferred to a glass vial prepared for GC-MS analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>A standard mixture containing seven authentic standards (acetic acid, propionic acid, butyric acid, isovaleric acid, valeric acid, caproic acid and caproic acid-d3) dissolved in 0.005 M aqueous NaOH were also prepared with the same procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Analysis was performed using an Agilent 7890A gas chromatography system coupled to an Agilent 5975C inert XL EI/CI mass spectrometric detector (MSD, Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Helium was used as a carrier gas at a constant flow rating at 1 mL/min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The injection volume of the samples was 1 μL in split mode with a ratio of 50:1, and the solvent delay time was set to 2 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The initial oven temperature was held at 50 °C for 2 min, ramped to 70 °C at a rate of 10 °C min−1, to 85 °C at a rate of 3 °C min−1, to 110 °C at a rate of 5 °C min−1, to 290 °C at a rate of 30 °C min−1, and finally held at 290 °C for 8 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The MS was operated in the electron impact ionization mode at −70 eV, and the temperature of the front inlet and transfer line were set at 260 and 290 °C, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Mass spectral data were collected in full scan mode from m/z 30–600. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Raw GC–MS data files were converted to NetCDF files using the Agilent’s MSD Chemstation Data Analysis Application. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, the “Statistical Compare” function in ChromaTOF software (Leco Corp., St. Joseph, MO) was utilized to generate a data table with all the compound information from different chromatograms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>DNA extraction, 16S rRNA gene amplicon preparation and sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Approximately 100 g of mixed faeces were prepared and freeze-dried before DNA extraction using the method of Rius et al.41 DNA integrity was verified using a BioAnalyzer 2000 (Agilent, Palo Alto, CA, USA), and concentration was then determined using a Qubit fluorometer (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The hypervariable V3–V4 regions (Escherichia coli position 341 to 806) of the 16S rRNA gene, which have been targeted frequently for interrogating bacterial communities, were directly amplified from 10 ng of total DNA using PAGE-purified Illumina platform-compatible adaptor oligonucleotides that contained sequencing primers, sample-specific barcodes, and 16S PCR primers (forward primer, 341F: CCTAYGGGRBGCASCAG; reverse primer, 806R: GGACTACNNGGGTATCTAAT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The PCR reaction included 1 U of FastPfu DNA Polymerase (TransStart, Haidian, Beijing, China) in a 20 μl reaction buffer, containing 0.2 μM primers, 0.25 mM dNTPs, 20 mM Tris-SO4 (pH 9.2), 40 mM KCl, 10 mM (NH4)SO4, 2 Mm MgSO4, and 2.5% Glycerol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>PCRs were performed in an Eppendorf Mastercycler (Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany) using the following conditions: 95 °C for 5 min; then 27 cycles of 95 °C for 30 s, 55 °C for 30 s, 72 °C for 45 s; and elongation at 72 °C for 10 min; then 10 °C until halted by user. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Amplicons were purified using an Agencourt AMPure XP bead kit (Beckman Coulter Genomics, Danvers, MA, USA) and pooled using equal amounts of each PCR product. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Finally, the library pool was sequenced using an Illumina MiSeq Reagent Kit (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA) on an Illumina MiSeq sequencer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatics and data analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Raw sequences were preprocessed using MiSeq Control Software (MCS) v2.4.1, and split based on sample-specific barcodes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The sequencing reads were removed if their lengths were shorter than 200 nt, their average quality score was &lt; 25, and they contained more than one ambiguous base “N”, primer mismatches or errors in the barcodes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Finally, the processed pair-end (PE) reads were joined together using PandaSeq v2.8 to generate representative complete nucleotide sequences termed “Raw PE”, with default parameters42. De novo and reference-based chimera checking was then performed by blasting the sequences against the Gold database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://drive5.com/uchime/gold.fa">http://drive5.com/uchime/gold.fa</ext-link>) based on the UCHIME Algorithm43 and raw PE tags that were characterized as chimeras were removed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>After filtering of noisy sequences, the effective tags were uploaded into QIIME and analysed as described previously44. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Briefly, sequences were clustered into OTUs using the UPARSE software45 with a minimum pair-wise identity of 97%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Each cluster was represented by its most abundant sequence, and representative OTU sequences were then aligned to the Greengenes database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://greengenes.secondgenome.com/">http://greengenes.secondgenome.com/</ext-link>) using assign_taxonomy.py program (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://qiime.org/scripts/assign_taxonomy.html">http://qiime.org/scripts/assign_taxonomy.html</ext-link>), with a minimum support threshold of 80%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Alpha diversity (number of OTUs, Shannon’s index, Chao1, Phylogenetic diversity_whole tree) and relative abundance of different taxa were calculated by alpha_diversity.py (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://qiime.org/scripts/alpha_diversity.html">http://qiime.org/scripts/alpha_diversity.html</ext-link>) included in the QIIME. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Using the Vegan package (Version 2.4.0, Department of Statistics, Iowa State University, IA, USA), two different complementary analyses, ANOSIM and MRPP, were used to determine the significant differences in faecal microbiota in response to M. oleifera alternative diets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Sequencing data submission </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>All sequencing raw datasets have been deposited in the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) Sequence Read Archive (SRA) database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/</ext-link>) with the BioProject accession number PRJNA351736. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The sequencing files of 30 different faecal samples were numbered with accession numbers from SRR4639749 to SRR4639778. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Data for nutrient digestibility, milk traits and faecal SCFAs of dairy cows were analysed using a one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and a protected Least Significant Difference Test (LSD) between groups by SPSS 19.0 (Chicago, IL, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The correlation analyses of genus taxa with the apparent digestibility, milk traits and faecal SCFAs were tested by the cor function (x, y, use = “p”) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://127.0.0.1:11153/library/stats/html/cor.html">http://127.0.0.1:11153/library/stats/html/cor.html</ext-link>), and illustrated with a function-labelled Heatmap (Matrix, xLabels, yLabels) in the R package WGCNA (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://127.0.0.1:11153/library/stats/html/cor.html">http://127.0.0.1:11153/library/stats/html/cor.html</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Metastat test17 was performed using the R software to determine the differences in the microbial composition (relative abundance) of the faecal microbiome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Additional Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>How to cite this article: Sun, J. et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Characterization of faecal microbial communities of dairy cows fed diets containing ensiled Moringa oleifera fodder. Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Rep. 7, 41403; doi: 10.1038/srep41403 (2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Publisher's note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1"><title><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material id="d32e24" content-type="local-data"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep41403-s1.doc"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e27" content-type="local-data"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Table S3 </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep41403-s2.xls"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e30" content-type="local-data"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Table S4 </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep41403-s3.xls"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e33" content-type="local-data"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Table S6 </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep41403-s4.xls"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the Natural Science Foundation of Guangdong Province, China [grant numbers 2016A030310449, 2016A030313413], the Key Project of Transgenic Animal [grant number 2014ZX0800948B], the National Basic Research Program of China (973 Program) [grant number 2013CB127304], the National Natural Science Foundation of China [grant numbers 31272529, 31472163], and the Guangdong Province Science and Technology Department of China [grant number 2016A020210083]. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="b1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>VeysP., BerbenG., DardenneP., BaetenV. &amp; Fink-GremmelsJ. Detection and identification of animal by-products in animal feed for the control of transmissible spongiform encephalopathies. Animal Feed Contamination—Effects on Livestock and Food Safety 104–110 (2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>TrostleR. Global agricultural supply and demand: factors contributing to the recent increase in food commodity prices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Washington, DC, USA: US Department of Agriculture, Economic Research Service (2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>CameronD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>J. Trees and pasture–An overview. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>In Proceedings of “Using trees on farms workshop” organized by the New Zealand Grassland Association and the New Zealand Farm Forestry Association Palmerston North, CharltonJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>L. (ed.) Grassland Research and Practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Series Vol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>10, pp. 5–6 (2003). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>ShowS. Ensilaging of tropical forages with particular reference to South East Asian systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The XIIIth International Silage Conference, Auchincruive, Scotland. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>(2002, September). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>BarshilaI., DevkotaN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>R. &amp; BassilaS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>R. Perception of smallholder farmers on fodder tree utilization and management for livestock production in the mid-hills of Nepal. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Anim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Prod. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Adv 3(10), 290–300 (2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>WangF., WenX. &amp; ZhangH. Feed processing technology and application of caragana. Acta Agriculturae Boreali-Occidentalis Sinica 13(3), 143–147 (2003). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>WorkuA. Moringa oleifera as a potential feed for livestock and aquaculture industry. African Journal of Agricultural Science and Technology (AJAST) 4(4), 666–676 (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>SultanaN. . The feeding value of Moringa (Moringa oleifera) foliage as replacement to conventional concentrate diet in Bengal goats. Adv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Anim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Vet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Sci 3(3), 164–173 (2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>FadiyimuA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>A., AlokanJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>A. &amp; FajemisinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>N. Digestibility, nitrogen balance and haematological profile of West African dwarf sheep fed dietary levels of Moringa oleifera as supplement to Panicum maximum. Journal of American Science 6(10), 10 (2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Mendieta-AraicaB., SpörndlyR., Reyes-SánchezN. &amp; SpörndlyE. Moringa (Moringa oleifera) leaf meal as a source of protein in locally produced concentrates for dairy cows fed low protein diets in tropical areas. Livestock Science 137(1), 10–17 (2011b). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>KholifA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>E. . Moringa oleifera leaf meal as a protein source in lactating goat’s diets: feed intake, digestibility, ruminal fermentation, milk yield and composition, and its fatty acids profile. Small Ruminant Research, 129, 129–137 (2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Mendieta-AraicaB., SpörndlyE., Reyes-SánchezN. &amp; SpörndlyR. Feeding Moringa oleifera fresh or ensiled to dairy cows—effects on milk yield and milk flavor. Tropical animal health and production 43(5), 1039–1047 (2011a).21344294 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>SommerF. &amp; BäckhedF. The gut microbiota—masters of host development and physiology. Nature Reviews Microbiology 11(4), 227–238 (2013).23435359 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>MondotS. &amp; LepageP. The human gut microbiome and its dysfunctions through the meta-omics prism. Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>HugenholtzP., GoebelB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>M. &amp; PaceN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>R. Impact of culture-independent studies on the emerging phylogenetic view of bacterial diversity. Journal of bacteriology 180(18), 4765–4774 (1998).9733676 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>van DijkE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>L., AugerH., JaszczyszynY. &amp; ThermesC. Ten years of next-generation sequencing technology. Trends in genetics 30(9), 418–426 (2014).25108476 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>WhiteJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>R., NagarajanN. &amp; PopM. Statistical methods for detecting differentially abundant features in clinical metagenomic samples. PLoS Comput Biol 5(4), e1000352 (2009).19360128 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>XuX. &amp; ZhangX. Lentinula edodes-derived polysaccharide alters the spatial structure of gut microbiota in mice. PloS one 10(1), e0115037 (2015).25608087 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>MartínezI., MullerC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>E. &amp; WalterJ. Long-term temporal analysis of the human fecal microbiota revealed a stable core of dominant bacterial species. PloS one 8(7), e69621 (2013).23874976 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>LuX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>M., LuP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Z. &amp; ZhangH. Bacterial communities in manures of piglets and adult pigs bred with different feeds revealed by 16S rDNA 454 pyrosequencing. Applied microbiology and biotechnology 98(6), 2657–2665 (2014).24068333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>SongE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>S. . Comparison of fecal microbiota between German Holstein dairy cows with and without left-sided displacement of the abomasum. Journal of clinical microbiology 54(4), 1140–1143 (2016).26842700 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>NiuQ. . Dynamic distribution of the gut microbiota and the relationship with apparent crude fiber digestibility and growth stages in pigs. Scientific reports 5 (2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>LamendellaR., Santo DomingoJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>W., GhoshS., MartinsonJ. &amp; OertherD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>B. Comparative faecal metagenomics unveils unique functional capacity of the swine gut. BMC microbiology 11(1), 1 (2011).21194490 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>EckburgP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>B. . Diversity of the human intestinal microbial flora. Science 308(5728), 1635–1638 (2005).15831718 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>YangF., ChiaN., SchookL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>B. &amp; WhiteB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>A. Shifts in the fecal microbial community composition are associated with dietary fiber solubility. The FASEB Journal 27 (1 Supplement), 1056–2 (2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>NorattoG., García-PérezE., IvanovI. &amp; MillsD. Whole-Wheat Supplemented Diet Changed Fecal Microbial Ecology of Obese Diabetic Mice. The FASEB Journal 29 (1 Supplement), 385–5 (2015).25366346 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>LeyR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>E., TurnbaughP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>J., KleinS. &amp; GordonJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>I. Microbial ecology: human gut microbes associated with obesity. Nature 444(7122), 1022–1023 (2006).17183309 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>JulliandV., de VauxA., MilletL. &amp; FontyG. Identification of Ruminococcus flavefaciens as the predominant cellulolytic bacterial species of the equine cecum. Applied and environmental microbiology, 65(8), 3738–3741 (1999).10427077 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>DursoL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>M. . Animal-to-animal variation in fecal microbial diversity among beef cattle. Applied and environmental microbiology, 76(14), 4858–4862 (2010).20472731 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>StiversonJ., MorrisonM. &amp; YuZ. Populations of select cultured and uncultured bacteria in the rumen of sheep and the effect of diets and ruminal fractions. International journal of microbiology (2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>DuncanS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>H., LouisP. &amp; FlintH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>J. Cultivable bacterial diversity from the human colon. Letters in applied microbiology 44(4), 343–350 (2007).17397470 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>WongJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>M., De SouzaR., KendallC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>W., EmamA. &amp; JenkinsD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>J. Colonic health: fermentation and short chain fatty acids. Journal of clinical gastroenterology 40(3), 235–243 (2006).16633129 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>DicksvedJ., JanssonJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>K. &amp; LindbergJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>E. Fecal microbiome of growing pigs fed a cereal based diet including chicory (Cichorium intybus L.) or ribwort (Plantago lanceolata L.) forage. Journal of animal science and biotechnology 6(1), 1 (2015).25838897 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>KholifA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>E. . Effect of feeding diets with processed Moringa oleifera meal as protein source in lactating Anglo-Nubian goats. Animal Feed Science and Technology 217, 45–55 (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>NoumanW. . Potential of Moringa oleifera L. as livestock fodder crop: a review. Turkish Journal of Agriculture and Forestry 38(1), 1–14 (2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>AshidaH., OgawaM., KimM., MimuroH. &amp; SasakawaC. Bacteria and host interactions in the gut epithelial barrier. Nature chemical biology 8(1), 36–45 (2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>BlackburnT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>H. &amp; HobsonP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>N. Further studies on the isolation of proteolytic bacteria from the sheep rumen. Microbiology 29(1), 69–81 (1962). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>HazlewoodG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>P., OrpinC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>G., GreenwoodY. &amp; BlackM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>E. Isolation of proteolytic rumen bacteria by use of selective medium containing leaf fraction 1 protein (ribulosebisphosphate carboxylase). Applied and environmental microbiology 45(6), 1780–1784 (1983).6881961 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Van KeulenJ. &amp; YoungB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>A. Evaluation of acid-insoluble ash as a natural marker in ruminant digestibility studies. Journal of Animal Science 44(2), 282–287 (1977). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>ZhengX. . A targeted metabolomic protocol for short-chain fatty acids and branched-chain amino acids. Metabolomics 9(4), 818–827 (2013).23997757 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b41"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>RiusA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>G. . Nitrogen metabolism and rumen microbial enumeration in lactating cows with divergent residual feed intake fed high-digestibility pasture. Journal of dairy science 95(9), 5024–5034 (2012).22916906 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b42"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>MasellaA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>P., BartramA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>K., TruszkowskiJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>M., BrownD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>G. &amp; NeufeldJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>D. PANDAseq: paired-end assembler for illumina sequences. BMC bioinformatics 13(1), 1 (2012).22214541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b43"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>EdgarR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>C., HaasB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>J., ClementeJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>C., QuinceC. &amp; KnightR. UCHIME improves sensitivity and speed of chimera detection. Bioinformatics 27(16), 2194–2200 (2011).21700674 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b44"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>CaporasoJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>G. . QIIME allows analysis of high-throughput community sequencing data. Nature methods 7(5), 335–336 (2010).20383131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b45"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>EdgarR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>C. UPARSE: highly accurate OTU sequences from microbial amplicon reads. Nature methods 10(10), 996–998 (2013).23955772 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>The authors declare no competing financial interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Author Contributions Conceived and designed the experiments: Y.L.Z., X.Y.C., Q.Y.X. and J.J.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: B.Z., S.J.Y., W.J.H. and J.J.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: J.J.S. and Z.J.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: Y.L.Z., X.Y.C., Q.Y.Z., Q.Y.X., B.L.S., Q.H., T.C., Z.J.C. and J.J.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: J.J.S. and Z.J.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>All authors have read and approved the final version of manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Common and specific OTU distribution of the faecal microbiota among three groups.</title><p><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Note: Blue represents the no M. oleifera group (N = 8); Red represents the low M. oleifera group (N = 12); Green represents the high M. oleifera group (N = 10). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep41403-f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Phylum-level microbial compositions in the faecal microbiome.</title><p><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Note: The x-axis is labelled with the sample names, and y-axis represents the relative abundance of each phylum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>C represents the no M. oleifera group; L represents the low M. oleifera group; H represents the high M. oleifera group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep41403-f2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Rarefaction curve analysis in the faecal microbiome.</title><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Note: (A) Rarefaction curves between individuals (left) and groups (right). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>C represents the no M. oleifera group (N = 8); L represents the low M. oleifera group (N = 12); H represents the high M. oleifera group (N = 10). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep41403-f3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Anosim analyses of the significant differences between groups at genus-taxa level.</title><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Note: Anosim, analysis of similarity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>The R-value ranged from −1 to 1, and an R-value &gt; 0 that showed the significant differences in the between-group population compared those in the within-group population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>The P-values &lt; 0.05 indicate a significantly different level between groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep41403-f4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Correlation analyses of genus taxa with the apparent digestibility, milk traits and faecal SCFA concentrations.</title><p><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Note: Each cell contains the corresponding correlation and P-value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>The table is colour-coded by correlation according to the colour legend. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>DM: dry matter digestibility; CP: crude protein digestibility; My: milk yield; Mf: milk fat; Mp: milk protein; Mi: lactose, Sc: somatic cell count; Aa: acetic acid; Pa: propionic acid; Ba: butyric acid; Ia: isovaleric acid; Va: valeric acid. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep41403-f5"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap position="float" id="t1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Significant differences in community structure in the faecal microbiota of dairy cows among the three groups.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Group </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Anosim analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="4" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>MRPP analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>R-value </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>P-value </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>A-value </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Observed delta </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Expected delta </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>P-value </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>L-H </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>0.048 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>0.167 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>0.006 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>0.321 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>0.323 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>0.207 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>C-H </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>0.224 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>0.024 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>0.036 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>0.325 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>0.337 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>0.018 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>C-L </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>0.138 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>0.069 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>0.022 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>0.326 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>0.334 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>0.030 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t1-fn1"><p>Note: C, no <italic>M. oleifera</italic> diet; L, low <italic>M. oleifera</italic> diet; and H, high <italic>M. oleifera</italic> diet. Anosim, analysis of similarity; MRPP, multiresponse permutation procedure. The R-value ranged from −1 to 1, and an R-value &gt; 0 that showed the significant differences in the between-group population compared with those in the within-group population, as well as A-value (analysed by MRPP, multiresponse permutation procedure). The <italic>P</italic>-values indicated the significant differences at the levels of <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap position="float" id="t2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Nutrient apparent digestibility, milk yield, and composition in dairy cows fed <italic>M. oleifera</italic> silage.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Item </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="3" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Group (mean values ± standard error) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>L </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>H </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Dry matter digestibility (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>67.087 ± 0.4345A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>63.898 ± 0.4431B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>63.580 ± 0.3602B </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Crude protein digestibility (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>61.063 ± 0.6309 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>61.650 ± 0.6700 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>60.295 ± 0.6603 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Milk yield (kg/d) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>17.735 ± 0.5597 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>17.859 ± 0.5692 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>15.764 ± 0.2045 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Milk fat (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>4.824 ± 0.2575 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>4.706 ± 0.2832 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>4.947 ± 0.2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Milk protein (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>4.256 ± 0.2009 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>4.138 ± 0.1652 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>4.195 ± 0.1507 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Lactose (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>4.836 ± 0.0699 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>4.953 ± 0.0430 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>4.851 ± 0.0700 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Somatic cell count (×103/mL) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>215.625 ± 55.01 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>214.583 ± 65.66 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>257.200 ± 69.82 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t2-fn1"><p>Note: C, no <italic>M. oleifera</italic> diet; L, low <italic>M. oleifera</italic> diet; and H, high <italic>M. oleifera</italic> diet. Treatments with different capital letters were significantly different at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap position="float" id="t3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Quantitative analysis of SCFAs in the faeces of dairy cows among the three groups.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Item </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="3" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Group (mean values ± standard error) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>C </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>L </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>H </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Acetic acid </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>5.8336 ± 0.1379a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>5.3759 ± 0.2081ab </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>5.0819 ± 0.2489b </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Propionic acid </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>3.6385 ± 0.2041a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>3.1545 ± 0.1433b </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>3.0663 ± 0.0724b </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Butyric acid </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>1.9914 ± 0.0544 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>1.8163 ± 0.1062 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>1.7105 ± 0.1236 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Isovaleric acid </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>0.0802 ± 0.0018A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>0.0654 ± 0.0307B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>0.0539 ± 0.0233C </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Valeric acid </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>0.2173 ± 0.0152 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>0.2152 ± 0.0141 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>0.1937 ± 0.0099 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t3-fn1"><p>Note: C, no <italic>M. oleifera</italic> diet; L, low <italic>M. oleifera</italic> diet; and H, high <italic>M. oleifera</italic> diet. Treatments with different lowercase letters were significantly different at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, and different capital letters identified a significant level at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
