<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName archivearticle3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Plant Biotechnol J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Plant Biotechnol. J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1111/(ISSN)1467-7652</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PBI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Plant Biotechnology Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1467-7644</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1467-7652</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5069455</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12544</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PBI12544</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Ectopic expression of a cytochrome P450 monooxygenase gene PtCYP714A3 from Populus trichocarpa reduces shoot growth and improves tolerance to salt stress in transgenic rice </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head"><italic>Cuiting Wang</italic> et al.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="pbi12544-cr-0001" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Cuiting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="pbi12544-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="pbi12544-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Yang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="pbi12544-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="pbi12544-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Haihai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="pbi12544-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="pbi12544-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ran</surname><given-names>Xiaojuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="pbi12544-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="pbi12544-cr-0005" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Bei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="pbi12544-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="pbi12544-cr-0006" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Jiantao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="pbi12544-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="pbi12544-cr-0007" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Hongxia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="pbi12544-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="pbi12544-aff-0001"><label><sup>1</sup></label><named-content content-type="organisation-division">National Key Laboratory of Plant Molecular Genetics</named-content><named-content content-type="organisation-division">Shanghai Institute of Plant Physiology and Ecology</named-content><institution>Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution><named-content content-type="city">Shanghai</named-content><country country="CN">China</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><italic>Correspondence</italic> (Tel +86‐21‐54924705; fax +86‐21‐54924015; email <email>hxzhang@sippe.ac.cn</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.2016.14.issue-9</issue-id><fpage>1838</fpage><lpage>1851</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>02</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">© 2016 The Authors. <italic>Plant Biotechnology Journal</italic> published by Society for Experimental Biology and The Association of Applied Biologists and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</copyright-statement><license license-type="creativeCommonsBy"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="file:PBI-14-1838.pdf"/><abstract id="pbi12544-abs-0001"><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Summary </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In Arabidopsis thaliana and Oryza sativa, the cytochrome P450 (CYP) 714 protein family represents a unique group of CYP monooxygenase, which functions as a shoot‐specific regulator in plant development through gibberellin deactivation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Here, we report the functional characterizations of PtCYP714A3, an OsCYP714D1/Eui homologue from Populus trichocarpa. PtCYP714A3 was ubiquitously expressed with the highest transcript level in cambium–phloem tissues, and was greatly induced by salt and osmotic stress in poplar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Subcellular localization analyses indicated that PtCYP714A3‐YFP fusion protein was targeted to endoplasmic reticulum (ER). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Expression of PtCYP714A3 in the rice eui mutant could rescue its excessive‐shoot‐growth phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Ectopic expression of PtCYP714A3 in rice led to semi‐dwarfed phenotype with promoted tillering and reduced seed size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Transgenic lines which showed significant expression of PtCYP714A3 also accumulated lower GA level than did the wild‐type (WT) plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The expression of some GA biosynthesis genes was significantly suppressed in these transgenic plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, transgenic rice plants exhibited enhanced tolerance to salt and maintained more Na+ in both shoot and root tissues under salinity stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>All these results not only suggest a crucial role of PtCYP714A3 in shoot responses to salt toxicity in rice, but also provide a molecular basis for genetic engineering of salt‐tolerant crops. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="pbi12544-kwd-0001">cytochrome P450 monooxygenase</kwd><kwd id="pbi12544-kwd-0002">development</kwd><kwd id="pbi12544-kwd-0003">Pt<styled-content style="fixed-case">CYP</styled-content>714A3</kwd><kwd id="pbi12544-kwd-0004">transgenic plant</kwd><kwd id="pbi12544-kwd-0005">salinity</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>National Science Foundation of China</funding-source><award-id>31370670</award-id><award-id>31371228</award-id><award-id>31171169</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>National Mega Project of GMO Crops</funding-source><award-id>2014ZX08001003‐007</award-id><award-id>2014ZX08004002‐006</award-id><award-id>2014ZX0800942B</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>The comprehensive Survey of Lithium, Boron and Biological Resources in Salt Lake on the Tibetan Plateau</funding-source><award-id>[2015]02‐04‐04‐001</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Chinese Academy of Sciences</funding-source><award-id>XDA08030108</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="14"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>component-id</meta-name><meta-value>pbi12544</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>September 2016</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_NLMPMC version:4.9.5 mode:remove_FC converted:19.10.2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0001"><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>As a class of important plant hormones, gibberellins (GAs) play crucial roles in promoting seed germination, stem elongation, leaf expansion and flower development (Eriksson et al., 2006; King et al., 2001; Ogawa et al., 2003; Schwechheimer, 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>In higher plants, bioactive GA levels can be regulated via controlling the biosynthesis, deactivation and signal transduction of GAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The biosynthesis of bioactive GAs such as GA1 and GA4 was initiated from geranylgeranyl diphosphate (GGDP), and catalysed by three types of enzymes including plastid‐localized terpene cyclases, membrane‐bound cytochrome P450 monooxygenases (P450s) and soluble 2‐oxoglutarate‐dependent dioxygenases (2ODDs) (Yamaguchi, 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The deactivation of GAs also involves several different mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The major enzymes responsible for the deactivation of bioactive GAs (GA1 and GA4) and their immediate precursors (GA20 and GA9) are GA2‐oxidases (GA2ox) that add a hydroxyl group to the C‐2 position of the substrates (Olszewski et al., 2002; Rieu et al., 2008; Thomas et al., 1999). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>In Arabidopsis, AtGA2ox7 and AtGA2ox8 can inactivate the earlier GA biosynthetic intermediates, but cannot deactivate the bioactive GAs lacking C‐20 via 2‐hydroxylation (Lee and Zeevaart, 2005; Schomburg et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>GA methyltransferase (GAMT1 and GAMT2)‐mediated methylation, which is regulated by developmental stimuli, is another route to inactivate bioactive GAs (Varbanova et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In rice, a cytochrome P450 monooxygenase CYP714D1 encoded by Eui gene that was cloned from the recessive tall rice mutant elongated uppermost internode (eui) can deactivate non‐13‐hydroxylated GAs (GA4, GA9 and GA12) by the 16α, 17‐epoxidation (Luo et al., 2006; Zhu et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Although the 16α, 17‐[OH]2‐GAs were found in many other plant species, such as Cibotium glaucum (Yamane et al., 1988), Lupinus albus (Gaskin et al., 1992), Malus domestica (Hedden et al., 1993), Pisum sativum (Santes et al., 1995), Prunus avium (Blake et al., 2000) and Populus trichocarpa (Pearce et al., 2002),no any gene as yet was reported having similar functions to Eui gene in these species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Recently, two other CYP714 gene family members, CYP714B1 and CYP714B2, were found to encode GA13‐oxidases that negatively regulate shoot growth and participate in GA homoeostasis in rice (Magome et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In Arabidopsis, two Eui‐like genes (ELA1/CYP714A1 and ELA2/CYP714A2) encode Eui homologues that subtly regulate plant growth most likely through catalysing the deactivation of bioactive GAs similar to rice Eui (Zhang et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Using a yeast expression system, CYP714A1 was revealed to be a GA‐deactivating enzyme that catalyses the conversion of GA12 to 16‐carboxylated GA12 (16‐carboxy‐16β, 17‐dihydro GA12), while CYP714A2 acts as a 13‐oxidase or 12α‐oxidase of GAs or GA precursors depending on the substrate (Nomura et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>All these reports suggest that CYP714 gene family members from different plant species might have different functions in GA metabolic pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The endogenous GA levels are also affected by environmental stimuli (Huang et al., 2009a; Nelson et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Under salt stress condition, growth inhibition is the primary response of plants and may be the result of positive adaptation mechanisms (Munns, 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In Arabidopsis, DELLA proteins were found to integrate responses to independent hormonal and environmental signals of adverse conditions, and confer growth restraint upon salinity treatment (Achard et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Recently, DWARF AND DELAYED FLOWERING 1 (DDF1), a salinity‐responsive AP2 transcription factor belonging to the DREB1/CBF subfamily, was reported to bind DRE‐like motifs in GA2ox7 promoter and activate the expression of GA2ox7, leading to growth repression for stress adaptation (Magome et al., 2004, 2008). DDF1‐overexpressing Arabidopsis showed increased tolerance to cold, drought and heat stresses (Kang et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In addition, gibberellins were suggested to be involved in Arabidopsis mitochondrial phosphate transporter (AtMPT)‐mediated early response to salt stress (Zhu et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>However, the potential application of GA‐related genes to improve salt tolerance in other plants including important crops and trees is barely reported (Shan et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Although the functions of some CYP714 gene family members in Arabidopsis and rice have been studied, very limited information is known regarding these enzymes from other plant species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>With the finish of genome sequencing and availability of developing genomic tools, Populus has been taken as an ideal model plant for trees (Jansson and Douglas, 2007; Tuskan et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Previously, we investigated the function of rice CYP714D1 gene in Populus (Wang et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In this work, the role of PtCYP714A3 gene from Populus in plant development and salt stress adaptation was investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>We found that PtCYP714A3 was a functional homologue of OsCYP714D1/Eui by complementation tests in the rice eui mutant and showed similar but not exactly the same functions in shoot development as did OsCYP714D1/Eui. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Further study revealed that PtCYP714A3 regulated Na+/K+ homoeostasis in transgenic rice plants to support their survival under salinity stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Our results suggest that PtCYP714A3 exerts distinct functions from OsCYP714D1/Eui in plant growth, and plays important roles in plant salt resistance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0002"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0003"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>PtCYP714A3 encodes a putative cytochrome P450 monooxygenase in Populus </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>A BLAST search of the cytochrome P450 homepage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://drnelson.uthsc.edu/">http://drnelson.uthsc.edu/</ext-link> CytochromeP450.html) resulted in the identification of six homologues in the Populus genome, designated as PtCYP714A3 (Potri.019G064600.1), PtCYP714E2 (Potri014G052000.1), PtCYP714E4 (Potri.013G160800.1), PtCYP714E5 (Potri.008G026300.1), PtCYP714E6 (Potri.008G026200.1) and PtCYP714F1 (Potri.010G116300.1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>These proteins share 63.33% identity and 69.99% similarity, with PtCYP714E6 as a redundant duplicate of PtCYP714E5 (99% identity). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Among these proteins, PtCYP714A3 shares the highest sequence identity with AtCYP714A1 (58.99%), AtCYP714A2 (53.20%) from Arabidopsis and OsCYP714D1 (41.35%) from rice, respectively (Figure 1a,b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Similar to AtCYP714A1, AtCYP714A2 and OsCYP714D1, PtCYP714A3 is characterized by an oxygen binding and activation site, a ERR triad motif and a Haeme binding site, as a common feature of CYP714 subfamily. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The fact that Arabidopsis genome encodes only two CYP714 members suggests that Populus could have duplicated this class of gene during its long evolution for better adaptation to the unstable environments over a long lifespan. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="pbi12544-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Amino acid sequence alignment and phylogenetic tree of different CYP714 protein family members. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>(a) Multiple alignment of the deduced amino acid sequences of CYP714 proteins from Arabidopsis (AtCYP714A1/A2) and rice (OsCYP714D1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>(b) Phylogenetic tree of typical CYP714 proteins in Populus, Arabidopsis and Oryza sativa with bootstrap values conducted with Clustal X and Mega 3 program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The GenBank accession numbers for Populus CYP714 genes are as follows: PtCYP714A3 (XM_00631280.1), PtCYP714E2 (XM_006375124.1), PtCYP714E4 (XM_002319405.2), PtCYP714E5 (XM_002311935.2) and PtCYP714F1 (XM_002314788.1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-1" xlink:href="PBI-14-1838-g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0004"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Expression pattern of PtCYP714A3 in Populus </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>To elucidate the possible roles of PtCYP714A3, we first performed quantitative real‐time PCR and investigated its expression pattern in Populus trichocarpa (Torr. &amp; Gray) genotype Nisqually‐1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>We observed that PtCYP714A3 was predominantly expressed in the cambium–phloem tissues than in the other tissues such as roots, shoot apexes, leaves, petioles and xylem tissues (Figure 2a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>We also generated PtCYP714A3 promoter–GUS reporter vector and introduced it into Shanxin yang. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Consistent with the qRT‐PCR results, GUS was ubiquitously expressed in various tissues (Figure 2b), with a strong GUS expression in the cambium zone of stem (Figure 2c). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="pbi12544-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Expression pattern and subcellular localization of PtCYP714A3 in populus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>(a) Relative expressional levels of PtCYP714A3 gene in different tissues of Populus trichocarpa (Torr. &amp; Gray) genotype Nisqually‐1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>R, Root; Ap, apical bud; L, leaf; Pe, petiole; Ca‐Ph, cambium–phloem zone; X, xylem. the expression value of PtCYP714A3 in root was set to 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Error bars are means ± SD of three biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The experiment was repeated two times independently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>(b, c) Histochemical GUS analysis of a PtCYP714A3 promoter–GUS transgenic plant and a transverse section of the stem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>(d) Subcellular localization of PtCYP714A3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Confocal laser scanning microscopy images of poplar mesophyll protoplasts transiently expressing yellow fluorescent protein (YFP), or PtCYP714A3‐YFP alone and cyan fluorescent protein (CFP)‐HDEL together under the control of the 35S promoter were shown. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="PBI-14-1838-g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0005"><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>PtCYP714A3 is targeted to endoplasmic reticulum (ER) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Cellular and subcellular localization of a certain protein may indicate how and/or where it works. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown that OsCYP714D1/Eui, AtCYP714A1 and AtCYP714A2 are all targeted to ER (Zhang et al., 2011; Zhu et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>To determine the subcellular localization of PtCYP714A3, we transiently expressed PtCYP714A3‐YFP (yellow fluorescent protein) fusion protein in poplar leaf protoplasts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>HDEL, an ER‐localized reporter (Dong et al., 2008), was also co‐transformed with PtCYP714A3‐YFP to verify the ER targeting of PtCYP714A3 protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>As we have expected, the fluorescence of PtCYP714A3‐YFP overlapped perfectly with that of CFP‐HDEL, revealing that PtCYP714A3‐YFP fusion protein was indeed targeted to the ER organella (Figure 2d). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0006"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>PtCYP714A3 can functionally complement the rice eui mutant </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The rice eui mutant displays excessive‐shoot‐growth phenotype (Zhu et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>To understand whether PtCYP714A3 might have similar functions as the rice ortholog, we heterologously expressed PtCYP714A3 driven by the Eui promoter in the eui background (Figure 3a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>In parallel, OsCYP714D1/Eui driven by the Eui promoter was separately introduced into eui mutant as well (Figure 3a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>At least ten independent transgenic lines were obtained for each gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>RT‐PCR analyses confirmed the expression of OsCYP714D1/Eui or PtCYP714A3 in the eui mutant, respectively (Figure 3b,c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Compared to the wild‐type and eui mutant plants, all transgenic lines (L1 and L4) expressing OsCYP714D1/Eui showed severely stunted growth, and failed to flower and produce seeds (Figure 3b), whereas those expressing PtCYP714A3 only showed semi‐dwarfed growth and set seeds successfully (Figure 3c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Detailed studies with the T4 seeds of two PtCYP714A3 transgenic lines (L7 and L8) showed that the semi‐dwarfed phenotype in PtCYP714A3 transgenic plants was attributed to the shortened upper most (1st), the second and the third internodes (Figure 3d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that PtCYP714A3 biologically complemented the excessive‐shoot‐growth phenotype of eui mutant, but did not work exactly the same as did OsCYP714D1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="pbi12544-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Genetic complementation of rice eui mutant by PtCYP714A3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>(a) Schematic representation of T‐DNA region transformed into eui mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>(b) Growth phenotypes of WT, eui and two OsCYP714D1 complementary lines. eui, elongated uppermost internode rice mutant; L1 and L4, independent eui transgenic lines expressing OsCYP714D1/EuicDNA under the control of Eui promoter; WT, wild type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Bar = 10 cm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>(c) Growth phenotypes of WT, eui and two PtCYP714A3 complementary lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>L7 and L8, independent eui transgenic lines expressing PtCYP714A3 cDNA under the control of Eui promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Bar = 10 cm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>(d) Plant heights of eui mutant, wild‐type and the PtCYP714A3 transgenic plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Values are means ± SD from 30 individual plants with three independent biological replicates. * indicates significant difference in comparison with the WT at P &lt; 0.05 (Student's t‐test). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="PBI-14-1838-g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0007"><title><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Expression of PtCYP714A3 inhibits shoot growth and promotes tillering in transgenic rice plants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>To investigate the exact function of PtCYP714A3 in plant, we introduced the construct containing the coding sequence of OsCYP714D1/Eui or PtCYP714A3, driven by the Eui promoter, into the genome of rice (ZH11) by Agrobacterium‐mediated transformation (Figure 3a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>More than 10 independent transgenic lines were successfully obtained for each gene construct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The integration of PtCYP714A3 into the rice genome was confirmed by PCR analyses (Figure S1a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Further analysis by RT‐PCR indicated the successful expression of PtCYP714A3 in the selected transgenic rice plants (Figure S1b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Overexpression of OsCYP714D1/Eui led to severely dwarfed phenotype in all transgenic lines, just the same as its overexpression in the eui mutant (Figure S1c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>However, all transgenic plants ectopically expressing PtCYP714A3 showed consistent semi‐dwarfed phenotype regardless of the expression levels of transgene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we selected two independent homozygous transgenic lines which showed high expression of PtCYP714A3 (Z33, Z38) for subsequent phenotypic analyses (Figure S1c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Compared to WT plants, PtCYP714A3 transgenic plants produced shorter shoots, including internodes and panicles (Figure 4a–c,e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>In addition, increased tiller number of the transgenic lines was also a prominent difference from the WT (Figure 4d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>To determine whether expression of PtCYP714A3 would affect seed development in transgenic plants, wild‐type and homozygous T4 transgenic plants were chosen for field trial in 2013 (transgenic trial permit number: 2013‐T018). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Compared to the wild‐type plants, both transgenic lines produced smaller panicles and seeds with decreased seed setting, leading to reduced grain yield per plant (Figure 4e–j; Table S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="pbi12544-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Expression of PtCYP714A3 inhibits shoot growth and promotes tillering in transgenic rice plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>(a) Field‐grown plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>(b, c) Internode lengths. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>(d) Tiller numbers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>(e) Mature panicles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>(f) Seed‐setting rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>(g) Seed numbers per panicle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>(h) Grain yields per plant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>(I) One‐hundred‐grain weights. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>(j) Seeds with and without seed coat. WT, wild type; Z33 and Z38, independent transgenic lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Values are means ± SD from 30 individual plants with three independent biological replicates. * indicates significant difference in comparison with the WT at P &lt; 0.05 (Student's t‐test). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="PBI-14-1838-g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0008"><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Expression of PtCYP714A3 reduces the contents of bioactive GAs in transgenic rice plants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>To understand whether PtCYP714A3 indeed functions in GA deactivation, endogenous levels of GA precursors and bioactive GAs in the internodes of WT and PtCYP714A3 transgenic plants were examined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Compared to the WT, the levels of both bioactive GAs (GA1 and GA4) and GA12, the common precursor in GAs biosynthesis pathway, were extremely lower or even undetectable in transgenic plants (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>On the contrary, the level of the other important precursor, such as GA53, was significantly higher in both transgenic lines, especially in line Z33 (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>We also determined several other immediate precursors of bioactive GAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Both GA19 and GA20 were measurable in transgenic rice plants with the concentrations waving from 0.79 to 6.99 (ng/g), but they were undetectable in WT plants (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>GA9 was too low to be detected in both WT and transgenic plants (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="pbi12544-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Endogenous GA levels in the stems of 2.5‐month‐old wild‐type and PtCYP714A3 transgenic plants. WT, wild type; Z33 and Z38, independent transgenic lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Values are means ± SD of three biological replicates of ten individual plants from the WT or the transgenic lines. ND, not detected. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="PBI-14-1838-g005"/></fig><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>To explain why GA accumulation was affected in transgenic plants, we examined the expression levels of genes in GA biosynthesis, deactivation and signal pathways by quantitative real‐time PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Among these genes, the transcription levels of those involved in the synthesis of the common precursor GA12, such as CPS, KS1, KO2 and KAO, all decreased significantly (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>GA20ox and GA3ox are the main enzymes that catalyse the syntheses of bioactive GAs (GA1 and GA4) (Itoh et al., 2001; Sasaki et al., 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>We found that the expression level of GA20ox2 decreased whereas that of GA3ox2 increased, implying that they showed opposite variation in these transgenic plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>In addition, the transcription levels of the bioactive GA deactivation gene GA2ox3 (Sakai et al., 2003), the GA receptor gene GID1 (Ueguchi‐Tanaka et al., 2005) and the F‐box protein gene GID2 (Sasaki et al., 2003) also decreased in transgenic rice compared with that in the WT plants (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that expression of PtCYP714A3 influences GA accumulation and GA metabolic gene expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="pbi12544-fig-0006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Relative expressional levels of GA‐related genes in wild‐type and PtCYP714A3 transgenic plants. WT, wild type; Z33 and Z38, independent transgenic lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The name and the accession numbers of the genes are as the following: CPS1, ent‐copalyl diphosphate synthase (AP004572); KS1, ent‐kaurene synthase (OSJN00255); KO2, eht‐kaurene oxidase (AP005471); KAO, ent‐kaurenoic acid oxidase (AP000616); GA20ox2, GA 20‐oxidase (AB077025); GA3ox2, GA 3‐oxidase (AB056519); GA2ox3, GA 2‐oxidase (NM_001050827); GID1, soluble GA receptor (AB211399); GID2, F‐box protein (AB100246). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Values are means ± SD of three biological replicates from the WT or the transgenic lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Significant differences were analysed with Student's t‐test. *, P &lt; 0.05; **, 0.05 &lt; P &lt; 0.01; ***, 0.01 &lt; P &lt; 0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-11" xlink:href="PBI-14-1838-g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0009"><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Expression of PtCYP714A3 confers salt tolerance on transgenic rice plants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown that GAs also function in plant response to abiotic stress (Magome et al., 2004, 2008; Shan et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>To investigate the functions of PtCYP714A3 and its potential value in improving salt tolerance in plants, we first extracted total RNA from the leaves of Shanxin yang treated with 150 mm NaCl for increasing periods of time and performed qRT‐PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>We found that expression of PtCYP714A3 was steadily induced by salt from 0 to 24 h, and reached a maximal 87‐fold induction at 18 h (Figure 7a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>We then examined the effects of salt on the growth of transgenic plants at whole‐plant scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Under normal growth condition, both WT and transgenic lines all grew well (Figure 7b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>However, after the plants were treated with 150 mm NaCl for 12 days, obvious differences were observed between WT and transgenic plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>While WT plants became wilted, transgenic lines appeared to be less impaired by salt stress (Figure 7b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Although salt stress considerably affected the growth of all the plants in general, transgenic plants were remarkably more vigorous. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Compared to WT, most PtCYP714A3‐expressing plants exhibited near‐to‐normal leaf colour and showed a superior survival rate at the end of treatment: more than 70% of PtCYP714A3 transgenic, whereas less than 30% of WT plants survived (Figure 7c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>All these results indicate that expression of PtCYP714A3 in rice enhanced salt tolerance in transgenic plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="pbi12544-fig-0007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Expression PtCYP714A3 in response to high‐salinity and salt stress tolerance analyses of transgenic rice plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>(a) Expression of PtCYP714A3 is responsive to NaCl stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Poplar leaves were cut into sections and divided into several groups that were treated separately with 200 mm NaCl for different time points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Samples were collected at 0, 3, 6, 12, 18 and 24 h after the initiation of treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Data represent the average of three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>(b, c) Phenotypes (b) and survival rates (c) of three‐week‐old seedlings of wild‐type and PtCYP714A3 transgenic plants treated with 150 mm NaCl for 12 d followed by 10 days of recovery without NaCl. WT, wild type; Z33 and Z38, independent transgenic lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Values are means ± SD (n = 4) from three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate statistically significant difference in comparison with the WT (Student's t‐test, **, P &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-13" xlink:href="PBI-14-1838-g007"/></fig></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0010"><title><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>PtCYP714A3 expression regulates tissue Na+ and K+ distribution </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>To understand how the introduced PtCYP714A3 gene improved salt‐tolerant capacity in transgenic plants, we examined the distribution of Na+ and K+ contents in different tissues of WT and transgenic rice plants after treated with or without 150 mm NaCl for 12 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Under normal growth condition, WT showed less Na+ and more K+ content in the roots, although both WT and transgenic Z33, Z38 lines contained approximately equal Na+ and K+ content in the shoots (Figure 8a,c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Under salt stress condition, Na+ content increased in all plant tissues accompanied by a decrease in K+ content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>However, Na+ content in Z33 and Z38 was significantly higher than that in WT in both shoots and roots (Figure 8b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Generally, WT and transgenic plants accumulated equivalent levels of K+ in both shoots and roots (Figure 8d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Taken together, our data suggest that PtCYP714A3 regulates Na+ and K+ homoeostasis under salt stress condition in transgenic rice plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="pbi12544-fig-0008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Na+ and K+ contents in roots and shoots of wild‐type (WT) and transgenic rice plants (Z33 and Z38). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>At the end of 0 or 150 mm NaCl treatment, plant materials were harvested and pooled into roots and shoots for the measurement of Na+ and K+ contents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>(a) Na+ contents of different tissues at 0 mm NaCl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>(b) Na+ contents of different tissues at 150 mm NaCl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>(c) K+ contents of different tissues at 0 mm NaCl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>(d) K+ contents of different tissues at 150 mm NaCl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Values are means ± SD (n = 4) from two independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate statistically significant difference in comparison with the WT (Student's t‐test, *, P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-15" xlink:href="PBI-14-1838-g008"/></fig></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0011"><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Expression of salt stress‐related genes is affected in transgenic plants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>To further investigate the role of PtCYP714A3 in salt stress adaptation of plants, the relative transcript levels of a series of salt stress‐related marker genes before or after NaCl stress treatment were analysed (Figure 9). NHX1 and SOS1 encode Na+/H+ the antiporters that compartment Na+ from cytoplasm into the vacuole (NHX1) or out of the plant cell (SOS1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The expression levels of NHX1 and SOS1 in transgenic rice (except SOS1 in Z33) were slightly higher than in WT under nonstress condition, and increased significantly after salt stress in both WT and transgenic lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Compared to NHX1, the expression increase of SOS1 in transgenic plants was more significant than that in WT, indicating that in transgenic rice, more sodium ions were pumped out of the plant cells than were compartmented into the vacuole under salt stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The enzyme of P5CS (Δ1‐pyrroline‐5‐carboxylate synthase) controls the rate‐limiting step of glutamate‐derived proline biosynthesis and is induced by high salt, dehydration, cold and ABA treatment (Igarashi et al., 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The transcription of P5CS was also induced by NaCl, and an almost fourfold increase was observed in Z33 upon NaCl treatment, much higher than that in WT (about 2 folds). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The SPY gene encodes an O‐linked N‐acetylglucosamine transferase, a negative regulator of plant GA signalling, and is inducible by drought stress and slightly responsive to salt stress in Arabidopsis (Qin et al., 2011; Steiner et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The expression of a homologous SPY in rice named SPY‐like was analysed in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The expression level of SPY‐like was slightly lower in Z33, but higher in Z38 than in WT before NaCl treatment, although no obvious difference was seen among these three lines after NaCl stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>DREBs (the dehydration‐responsive element‐binding proteins) are a kind of transcript factors in response to drought, high‐salt and cold stresses (Dubouzet et al., 2003; Wang et al., 2008; Mao and Chen 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>So the expressions of DREB1 genes in rice were analysed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>All of these genes were induced to varying degrees by salt stress in the wild‐type rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>All these genes were expressed at higher levels in Z33 and Z38 than in WT under normal situations (except DREB1F in Z33). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Under NaCl stress, the expression levels of DREB1A, DREB1C and DREB1F were decreased in Z38. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>All these results indicate that expression of PtCYP714A3 altered the expression of salt stress‐related genes in transgenic plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="pbi12544-fig-0009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real‐time PCR analyses of salt tolerance‐related marker genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Three‐week‐old seedlings treated with 150 mm NaCl for 12 h or 0 h (Control) were harvested for total RNA extraction, transverse transcription and real‐time PCR analyses. WT, wild type; Z33 and Z38, independent transgenic lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Values are means ± SD of three biological replicates from the WT or the transgenic lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate statistically significant difference in comparison with the WT (Student's t‐test, *, P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The TIGR loci of these genes are as follows: NHX1 (Os07g0600900); SOS1 (Os12g0641100); P5CS (Os05g0455500); SPY‐like (Os08g0559300); DREB1A (Os09g35030); DREB1F (Os01g73770); DREB2A (Os01g07120). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-17" xlink:href="PBI-14-1838-g009"/></fig></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0012"><title><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Previous reports that CYP714D1/Eui functions as a GA 16α, 17‐epoxidase to inactivate GA12, GA9 and GA4 in rice suggest that 16α, 17‐epoxidation might be an important process of GA deactivation existed in a variety of plant species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Indeed, 16α, 17‐[OH]2‐GAs have been detected in many plant species including Populus trichocarpa (Blake et al., 2000; Gaskin et al., 1992; Hedden et al., 1993; Pearce et al., 2002; Santes et al., 1995; Yamane et al., 1988; Zhu et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>In our previous study, heterologous expression of CYP714D1/Eui gene led to improved growth rate and biomass of transgenic Populus, just opposite to the phenotypes of CYP714D1/Eui‐overexpressing rice (Wang et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>To understand these unexpected results, it is necessary to verify whether Populus CYP714 gene family members have similar functions to CYP714D1/Eui. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>As PtCYP714A3 has the maximum sequence similarity with CYP714D1/Eui, we cloned this gene and verified its possible biological function in transgenic rice plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>We show here that PtCYP714A3, a member of the P450 (CYP) 714 gene family, is involved in GA deactivation and salt resistance in rice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>PtCYP714A3 shares very high amino acid sequence identity with CYP714D1/Eui (OsCYP714D1), AtCYP714A1 and AtCYP714A2 that contain all the highly conserved domains (Figure 1a,b; Zhang et al., 2011; Zhu et al., 2006), indicating its possible role as a putative cytochrome P450 monooxygenase in Populus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>As the genus Populus has become an ideal model plant for forest trees (Jansson and Douglas, 2007; Tuskan et al., 2006), a comparative study on the genetic functions of CYP714 gene family between rice and Populus could shoot inspective light into the difference in the mechanisms of plant growth and development under different environmental conditions between herbaceous and woody plants. PtCYP714A3 was predominantly expressed in cambium–phloem cells, and its expression was strongly induced by salt stress in poplar (Figures 2a–c and 7a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the high expression of PtCYP714A3 in cambium–phloem tissues of wild‐type poplar may imply a crucial role of PtCYP714A3 in GA metabolism and abiotic stress response in trees. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>With a view to the high sequence homology of CYP714D1/Eui and PtCYP714A3, the biological role of PtCYP714A3 was investigated by eui mutant analyses (Figure 3a–d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The most dramatic phenotypic change in eui mutant was the elongated shoot growth, especially the uppermost internode. PtCYP714A3 restored the growth phenotype of eui to the wild type, indicating that PtCYP714A3 can be employed as a functional allele of CYP714D1/Eui in plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>However, a severely dwarfed phenotype was observed in the transgenic eui plants complemented with CYP714D1/Eui (Figure 3b–d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>One explanation of this observation is that CYP714D1/Eui and PtCYP714A3 may have overlapped but not exactly the same function in rice and poplar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Another possibility is that CYP714D1/Eui is more powerful than PtCYP713A3 in controlling plant height. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>This postulation is also supported by the observation in transgenic poplar plants overexpressing PtCYP714A3, which showed no significant changes in the growth rate and biomass production (Figure S2a–e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>More detailed molecular and biochemical studies will help to dissect the exact functions of both proteins in plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>To clarify the exact biological functions of PtCYP714A3, we further ectopically expressed PtCYP714A3 in ZH11 (Figures 4a–i and S1a–c), and examined the endogenous GA contents and the transcript levels of GA pathway‐related genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>We found that PtCYP714A3 transgenic rice showed the most comparability with transgenic plants expressing AtCYP714A2 (Nomura et al., 2013; Zhang et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>First, both PtCYP714A3 and AtCYP714A2 transgenic rice plants were semi‐dwarfed, with increased tillers (Figure 4a–d; Zhang et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Second, the variation tendencies of most endogenous GA levels in these two kinds of transgenic plants were consistent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Based on the previous report, in AtCYP714A2 transgenic plants, the levels of GAs in the non‐13‐hydroxylation pathway, including GA12, GA15, GA24 and GA4, all decreased, whereas those of 13‐hydroxy GAs, including GA44, GA19, GA20 and GA1, all increased with the exception of GA53 which was unaffected (Nomura et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>In our study, most of detected GAs (GA12, GA4, GA53, GA19 and GA20) showed similar tendencies in PtCYP714A3 transgenic rice, except for bioactive GA1, which decreased rather than increased (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>In addition, the expression level variations of GA pathway‐related genes in PtCYP714A3‐expressing plants sustained that PtCYP714A3 most likely possesses the function of AtCYP714A2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The expression of GA receptors (GID1), F‐box protein (GID2) as well as bioactive GA‐deactivating enzyme (GA2ox3) was all reduced along with decreased bioactive GAs (GA1 and GA4) (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The transcript level of GA3ox which catalyses the conversion of GA20 and GA9 to bioactive GAs (GA1 and GA4) also increased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>However, the transcript level of GA20ox2 which encode the important GA‐oxidase involved in most steps of the bioactive GA biosynthesis pathway decreased, opposite to that of the GA3ox2 gene (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>As the contents of GA19 and GA20, the intermediates produced in the 13‐hydroxylation (13‐H) pathway of GA biosynthesis, dramatically increased (Figure 5), we presumed that the inconformity between the expressions of GA20ox2 and GA3ox2 was attributed to the regulatory mechanism of intermediate substrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Among the detected GA pathway genes, the most intriguing ones are those genes (CPS, KS, KO and KAO) participating in the biosynthesis of GA12, the common precursor of both 13‐H and non‐13‐H GA pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Expressions of all these genes reduced significantly, although the content of GA12 was extremely low or even undetectable in transgenic rice (Figures 5 and 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>In Arabidopsis, AtCYP714A2 was reported as a bifunctional enzyme that preferentially catalyses C‐12 hydroxylation of the ent‐gibberellane carbon skeleton, leading to the conversion of GA12 to 12α‐hydroxy GA12, and C‐13 hydroxylation of the ent‐kaurane carbon skeleton, by which steviol (ent‐13‐hydroxy asurenoic acid) was detected as the sole product when ent‐kaurenoic acid was added as a substrate (Nomura et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>As the content of GA53 was not affected along with the decrease of its immediate precursor GA12 in PtCYP714A3 transgenic rice (Figure 5), and GA53 was also produced from steviol in AtCYP714A2 transgenic plants (Nomura et al., 2013), we postulate that PtCYP714A3 might have similar function as AtCYP714A2 and could also catalyse the production of steviol‐like substance, and thus, the transcripts of CPS, KS, KO and KAO were inhibited by feedback regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we deduced that, just similar to AtCYP714A2, PtCYP714A3 also functions directly in deactivating GA12 and converting ent‐kaurenoic acid into steviol, and thus plays an important role in regulating plant growth and development through fine‐tuning GA homoeostasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>However, due to the tremendous species differences between perennial woody Populus and annual herbaceous Arabidopsis or rice, delicate differences could exist among the CYP714 families members, including their expression patterns (Figure 2; Zhang et al., 2011), their functions on the metabolism of GA1 (Figure 5; Nomura et al., 2013; Zhang et al., 2011), and phenotypes in transgenic Populus and rice overexpressing PtCYP714A3 (Figures 4, S1c and S2d). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have suggested that GA2ox genes including GA2ox7 were up‐regulated by high‐salinity stress in Arabidopsis (Magome et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Overexpression of OsGA2ox5 or DDF1, an AP2 transcription factor of the DREB/CBF subfamily, activated the expression of GA2ox7, and enhanced the salt tolerance in transgenic plants (Magome et al., 2004, 2008; Shan et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>We found that expression of PtCYP714A3 was also responsive to high‐salinity and osmotic stress (Figures 7a and S3a), and transgenic rice seedlings expressing PtCYP714A3 showed improved tolerance to salt and osmotic stress, with higher survival rates and less growth inhibition, than did the wild‐type seedlings (Figures 7b,c and S3b,c). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Maintaining low levels of sodium ions in the cell cytosol is critical for plant growth and development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Salt‐tolerant plants usually had lower Na+ contents (Huang et al., 2009b; Tang et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Under high‐salt stress condition, Na+ content in both shoots and roots of the PtCYP714A3 transgenic rice was higher than that of in WT (Figure 8b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>This could be due to the different functional mechanisms of PtCYP714A3 and other salt‐resistant genes (Tang et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Similar results were also observed in transgenic poplar plants overexpressing PtCLB10s which accumulated lower Na+ in leaves but higher Na+ in stems than did the WT plants (Tang et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>In addition, the semi‐dwarfed transgenic rice plants might have higher concentration ratio of sodium ion than the wild type. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>To further understand the salt‐tolerant mechanism in PtCYP714A3‐overexpressing plants, we compared the transcript levels of marker genes related to abiotic stress before or after high‐salinity stress (Figure 9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Three kinds of genes have been selected: antiporters (NHX1 and SOS1) or enzyme genes (P5CS), negative regulator gene (SPY‐like), and DREB transcript factor genes (DDF1‐like and DREB1A‐G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>In transgenic rice plants (Z33 and Z38), almost all selected genes were expressed at higher levels than that in the WT plants under normal condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>After treated with NaCl stress, all of them were expressed highly in both WT and transgenic plants, indicating that these genes are high‐salinity‐responsive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Among them, the expression of SOS1 gene, which encodes an Na+/H+ antiporter pumping Na+ out of the plant cell from cytosol, was significantly enhanced in NaCl‐treated transgenic lines compared with the WT plants, suggesting that one of functions of PtCYP714A3 is promoting the Na+ efflux in transgenic rice, although the exact mechanism that how PtCYP714A3 affects the expression of SOS1 gene still remains to be clarified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Another intriguing observation is the expression patterns of dehydration‐responsive element‐binding protein 1 (DREB1s). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>In Arabidopsis, DREB1A, DREB1B, DREB1C, DREB2A, and DREB2B proteins are probably the major transcription factors that function in cold‐, high‐salt‐ and drought‐inducible gene expression (Dubouzet et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>In rice, ten putative DREB1 homologues (OsDREB1A to OsDREB1J) have been identified and several of them were induced by cold, drought or salinity stress (Dubouzet et al., 2003; Mao and Chen, 2012; Wang et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>As DREB genes were responsive to drought, we also examined the dehydration tolerance of PtCYP714A3 transgenic plants (Figure S3b,c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>After PEG treatment for 20 days, growth inhibitions were observed in both WT and transgenic rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Following the recovery without PEG for 2 weeks, transgenic line Z38 grew quite better than did Z33 (Figure S3b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>The percentage of biomass with and without PEG treatment (relative biomass) showed that, under osmotic stress condition, the relative biomass ratio in shoots of line Z38 was about 70% of the control, obviously higher than that of the WT plants (49.05%) and transgenic line Z33 (36.88%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that although PtCYP714A3 has function on enhancing salt stress tolerance in transgenic rice, it might have no relevant to dehydration resistance of plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Semi‐dwarfism has been described as ‘Green Revolution’ morphological phenotype for more resistant to wind and rain damage (Sakamoto, 2006; Sakamoto et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Previous report has shown that AtCYP714A2‐expressing rice produced more yielding tillers and resulted in higher grain productivity than did the wild‐type rice, suggesting a favourable approach for molecular designing of crops with higher grain yield (Zhang et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>To explore the potential of PtCYP714A3 gene, we compared the yield of wild‐type and transgenic plants grown in the field with or without high‐salinity stress (Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Compared with the wild‐type control, the trait of increased tiller numbers for transgenic plants was not affected by high‐salt stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>In addition, although under both normal and salt stress conditions, the 100‐grain weight and plot yield of the transgenic plants were lower than the wild‐type control, the reductions of 100‐grain weight caused by high‐salinity stress in the transgenic plants were 1.04% (Z33) and 1.92% (Z38), much lower than that of in the wild‐type control (6.23%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>All these results suggest that PtCYP714A3 could be used as an effective gene for engineering transgenic rice with improved salt resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The undesirable affects in grain size and plot yield could be due to the unsuitable OsCYP714D1/Eui promoter used in this study, as OsCYP714D1/Eui was strongly expressed in young panicle and flowering panicle during the heading stage (Zhu et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Therefore, more suitable promoters such as the OsGA3ox2 gene promoter could be tried in the future work to avoid the influence of PtCYP714A3 expression on flower and grain development in transgenic plants (Sakamoto et al., 2003; Zhang et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Taken together, our data suggest that PtCYP714A3 could function in one or several pathway(s) by affecting GA biosynthesis and metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Although the precise mode of the action of PtCYP714A3 in plant growth and response to abiotic stress is still intangible, the results of our study provide direct evidence that altered expression of PtCYP714A3 can significantly modify GA biosynthesis, growth and salt resistance in transgenic plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0013"><title><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Experimental procedures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0014"><title><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Plant materials and growth conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Populus trichocarpa (Torr. &amp; Gray) genotype Nisqually‐1 and a commercial hybrid clone Shanxin yang (P. davidiana Dode × P. bolleana Lauche) were used in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Plants were subcultured on MS medium (Murashige and Skoog, 1962) supplemented with 0.1 mg/L naphthalene acetic acid (NAA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Plants were also grown in the greenhouse under a 12‐h light/12‐h dark photoperiod at 20–25 °C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Wild‐type rice (Oryza sativa) Zhonghua 11 (ZH11) and the eui mutant were grown under field conditions or in a greenhouse with a 16‐h/8‐h light and dark photoperiod at 28–30 °C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0015"><title><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Gene isolation, vector construction and plant transformation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>PtCYP714A3 was cloned into the Sma I site in pBlueScript II KS (pKS, Stratagene, La Jolla, CA) for sequence confirmation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>For PtCYP714A3 promoter–GUS construction, the 5'‐flanking DNA (2046 bp) of the PtCYP714A3 coding region was cloned into the pCAMBIA1300 + pBI101 vector (Liu et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>For rice transformation, a 2.5‐kb fragment containing the promoter region of Eui was cloned into the EcoR V site in pKS for sequence confirmation, then digested with Pst I and Bgl II, and cloned into pCAMBIA1301 to replace the original CaMV 35S promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>To construct the expression vector of ProEui::PtCYP714A3, PtCYP714A3 was placed downstream of the Eui promoter in p1301‐ProEui. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>For the construction of the control expression vector ProEui::OsCYP714D1, CYP714D1/Eui cDNA was also cut off with BamH I and Kpn I from the vector 35S‐C1301 (Zhu et al., 2006) and put downstream of the Eui promoter. ProEui::PtCYP714A3 and ProEui::OsCYP714D1 were separately transformed into wild‐type ZH11 and eui mutant to generate independent transgenic and complementary plants, respectively, as described previously (Hiei et al., 1994). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>T3 or T4 generations of PtCYP714A3‐expressing plants were used for phenotypic analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Plant height and other agronomic traits were compared upon maturing with 30 plants for each line. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>For poplar transformation, the relative vector was transformed into Shanxin yang as described previously (Wang et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0016"><title><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>β‐galactosidase (GUS) expression analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>For histochemical GUS activity assays, the whole plantlet or hand‐cut sections of the stem from three‐week‐old wild‐type and transgenic plants were stained as described previously (Gallagher, 1992). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0017"><title><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Subcellular localization analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>To determine the subcellular localization of PtCYP714A3‐YFP fusion protein, the encoding region without the stop codon of PtCYP714A3 was fused in‐frame to the N‐terminal of yellow fluorescent protein (YFP) via the Xho I/Spe I sites in the pA7‐YFP vector and transfected into the mesophyll protoplasts of Shanxin yang by polyethylene glycol (PEG)‐mediated transfection as described previously (Yoo et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>pA7‐YFP was used as a positive control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>For colocalization, the encoding region without the start codon of HDEL, an endoplasmic reticulum (ER)‐localized marker protein (Dong et al., 2008), was amplified from Arabidopsis cDNA, digested with BamH I/Spe I and cloned into the pA7‐CFP vector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>After transfected with plasmid DNA, the protoplasts were incubated at 23 °C for 16 h and then examined using a confocal laser scanning microscope (Zeiss LSM 510, Oberkochen, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>The excitation wavelengths for YFP and CFP were 514 and 433 nm, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0018"><title><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>PCR and reverse transcriptase (RT)‐PCR analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>For PCR analyses, genomic DNA was isolated from fresh leaves (about 500 mg for each sample) of WT and transgenic plants cultured in greenhouse as described previously (Kang et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Gene‐specific primers (Table S1) and GC buffer (TaKaRa, Dalian, China) were used to amplify a 530‐bp PCR product. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>For RT‐PCR analyses, total RNA was isolated with the RNAiso Reagent (TaKaRa, Japan) from leaves (for Populus) or stems (for rice) of WT and transgenic plants cultured in the greenhouse for 1 month (Populus) or 2.5 months (rice). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>After treated with DNase I (Promega, Madison, USA), 2 μg of total RNA was subjected to reverse transcription reaction using a RevertAid First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Thermo Scientific, Burlington, Canada) at 42 °C for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>GC buffer and gene‐specific primers were the same as used for PCR analysis (30 cycles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>The elongation factor gene PtEF1β (for Populus) and ubiquitin gene Ubi_1 (for rice) were employed as internal controls with the primers shown in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0019"><title><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real‐time (qRT)‐PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>For qRT‐PCR analyses, total RNA was extracted from different organs and tissues of Populus or rice as needed, and subjected to reverse transcriptions using a RevertAid First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Thermo Scientific) at 42 °C for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>qRT‐PCR was performed on an AceQ qPCR SYBR Green Master Mix (Vazyme Biotech, Nanjing, China) using a CFX Connect Real‐Time System (Bio‐Rad, Hercules, California) with gene‐specific primers (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>The log2 fold change in value was calculated based on 2−▵Ct method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>The relative expression of each target gene was normalized using the housekeeping gene OsUbi‐1(for rice) or PtEF1β (for Populus). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>The error bars were calculated from three biological replicates, and the experiment was repeated at least two times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>For expression pattern analysis, the expression value of PtCYP714A3 in root was set to 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>For the expression level analyses of the selected marker genes, the expression value of wild type was set to 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>For the response analyses of PtCYP714A3 to high salinity, the expression of the gene under nonsalt stress condition was set to 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0020"><title><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>GA content determination </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Sampled rice stems from 2.5‐month‐old plants (mainly including nodes and internodes) were homogenized in liquid nitrogen using a mortar and pestle, and then lyophilized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>An amount of 0.5 g dry weight (DW) of each sample was purified and analysed as described previously (Chen et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0021"><title><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Salt stress treatment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>To analyse whether the expression of PtCYP714A3 gene is inducible by salt and other abiotic stresses, leaves of Shanxin yang were cut into pieces (about 1 cm2 each piece) and treated with 150 mm NaCl for 0, 3, 6, 12, 18 and 24 h. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>For salt tolerance tests, rice seeds were sown in a 96‐well plate (bottom removed). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>The plate was floated on water and placed to a growth chamber with a 13‐h light (28 °C)/11‐h dark (26 °C) photoperiod. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Five days later, the seedlings were cultured with Yoshida's culture solution (Yoshida et al., 1976) and the solution was refreshed every 3 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>For salt treatment, three‐week‐old seedlings were transferred to Yoshida's culture solution supplemented with 150 mm NaCl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>The solutions were changed every 3 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>The survival rates were counted 10 days after recovering. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Plants were also grown in Binhai (Jiangsu Province, China) for field trial in 2013 (transgenic trial permit number: 2013‐T018). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0022"><title><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Na+ and K+ content assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>After salt treatments, plant materials were harvested and pooled as roots and shoots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>The samples were dried for 48 h at 80 °C, milled to fine powder, weighed and digested with concentrated HNO3 at 90 °C for 1–2 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>The concentrations of Na+ and K+ were determined in the digested liquid using an atomic absorption spectrophotometer as described previously (Hitachi Z‐8000, Tokyo, Japan; Wang and Zhao, 1995). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="pbi12544-sec-0023"><title><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>For statistical analyses, the Student's t‐test was used to generate every P value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>The tests were one‐tailed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>All data in this work were obtained from at least three independent experiments with three replicates each. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Supporting information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Figure S1 Molecular identification and phenotypes of transgenic plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Figure S2 Molecular confirmation and phenotype analyses of transgenic Shanxin yang overexpression of PtCYP714A3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Figure S3 Expression of PtCYP714A3 gene in response to PEG treatment and osmotic stress analyses of wild‐type and transgenic plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Table S1 Primers used in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Table S2 Mean comparisons for tillers and yields of field‐grown wild‐type and PtCYP714A3 transgenic rice plants with or without high‐salinity stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="PBI-14-1838-s001.doc"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="PBI-14-1838-s002.tiff"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="PBI-14-1838-s003.tiff"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>  </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="PBI-14-1838-s004.tiff"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack id="pbi12544-sec-0024"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>We are very grateful to Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Zhuhua He for providing us the eui mutant seeds, Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Hongxuan Lin for ion measurement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>This work was jointly supported by the following grants: the National Science Foundation of China (NSFC) 31370670, 31371228 and 31171169; the National Mega Project of GMO Crops 2014ZX08001003‐007, 2014ZX08004002‐006 and 2014ZX0800942B; The comprehensive Survey of Lithium, Boron and Biological Resources in Salt Lake on the Tibetan Plateau [2015]02‐04‐04‐001; and the Strategic Priority Research Program of the Chinese Academy of Sciences XDA08030108. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="pbi12544-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0001"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>  Achard, P. ,  Cheng, H. ,  De Grauwe, L. ,  Decat, J. ,  Schoutteten, H. ,  Moritz, T. ,  Van Der Straeten, D.  et al (2006) Integration of plant responses to environmentally activated phytohormonal signals. Science, 311, 91–94.16400150 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0002"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>  Blake, P.S. ,  Browning, G. ,  Benjamin, L.J.  and  Mander, L.N.  (2000) Gibberellins in seedlings and flowering trees of Prunus avium L. Phytochemistry, 53, 519–528.10731033 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0003"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>  Chen, M.L. ,  Huang, Y.Q. ,  Liu, J.Q. ,  Yuan, B.F.  and  Feng, Y.Q.  (2011) Highly sensitive profiling assay of acidic plant hormones using a novel mass probe by capillary electrophoresis‐time of flight‐mass spectrometry. J. Chromatogr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>B, 879, 938–944. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0004"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>  Dong, C.H. ,  Rivarola, M. ,  Resnick, J.S. ,  Maggin, B.D.  and  Chang, C.  (2008) Sub‐cellular co‐localization of Arabidopsis RTE1 and ETR1 supports a regulatory role for RTE1 in ETR1 ethylene signaling. Plant J. 53, 275–286.17999643 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0005"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>  Dubouzet, J.G. ,  Sakuma, Y. ,  Ito, Y. ,  Kasuga, M. ,  Dubouzet, E.G. ,  Miura, S. ,  Seli, M.  et al (2003) OsDREB genes in rice, Oryza sativa L., encode transcription activators that function in drought‐, high‐salt‐ and cold‐responsive gene expression. Plant J. 33, 751–763.12609047 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0006"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>  Eriksson, S. ,  Bohlenius, H. ,  Moritz, T.  and  Nilsson, O.  (2006) GA4 is the active gibberellin in the regulation of LEAFY transcription and Arabidopsis floral initiation. Plant Cell, 18, 2172–2181.16920780 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0007"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>  Gallagher, S.R.  (1992) GUS Protocols: Using the GUS Gene as a Reporter of Gene Expression. San Diego, CA: Academic Press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0008"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>  Gaskin, P. ,  Hoad, G.V. ,  Macmillan, J. ,  Makinson, I.K.  and  Readman, J.E.  (1992) Gibberellins A82 and A83 in seed of Lupinus albus . Phytochemistry, 31, 1869–1877. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0009"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>  Hedden, P. ,  Hoad, G.V. ,  Gaskin, P. ,  Lewis, M.J. ,  Green, J.R. ,  Furber, M.  and  Mander, L.N.  (1993) Kaurenoids and gibberellins, including the newly characterized gibberellin A88, in developing apple seeds. Phytochemistry, 32, 231–237. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0010"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>  Hiei, Y. ,  Ohta, S. ,  Komari, T.  and  Kumashiro, T.  (1994) Efficient transformation of rice (Oryza sativa L.) mediated by Agrobacterium and sequence analysis of boundaries of the T‐DNA. Plant J. 6, 271–282.7920717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0011"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>  Huang, J.G. ,  Yang, M. ,  Liu, P. ,  Yang, G.D. ,  Wu, C.A.  and  Zheng, C.C.  (2009a) GhDREB1 enhances abiotic stress tolerance, delays GA‐mediated development and represses cytokinin signalling in transgenic Arabidopsis. Plant, Cell Environ. 32, 1132–1145.19422608 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0012"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>  Huang, X.Y. ,  Chao, D.Y. ,  Gao, J.P. ,  Zhu, M.Z. ,  Shi, M.  and  Lin, H.X.  (2009b) A previously unknown zinc finger protein, DST, regulates drought and salt tolerance in rice via stomatal aperture control. Genes Dev. 23, 1805–1817.19651988 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0013"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>  Igarashi, Y. ,  Yoshiba, Y. ,  Sanada, Y. ,  Yamaguchi‐Shinozaki, K. ,  Wada, K.  and  Shinozaki, K.  (1997) Characterization of the gene for Δ1‐pyrroline‐5‐carboxylate synthetase and correlation between the expression of the gene and salt tolerance in Oryza sativa L. Plant Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Biol. 33, 857–865.9106509 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0014"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>  Itoh, H. ,  Ueguchi‐Tanaka, M. ,  Sentoku, N. ,  Kitano, H. ,  Matsuoka, M.  and  Kobayashi, M.  (2001) Cloning and functional analysis of two gibberellin 3β‐hydroxylase genes that are differently expressed during the growth of rice. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>USA, 98, 8909–8914.11438692 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0015"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>  Jansson, S.  and  Douglas, C.J.  (2007)  Populus, a model system for plant biology. Annu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Plant Biol. 58, 435–458.17280524 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0016"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>  Kang, B.G. ,  Ye, X. ,  Osburn, L.D. ,  Stewart, C.N. Jr  and  Cheng, Z.M.  (2010) Transgenic hybrid aspen overexpressing the Atwbc19 gene encoding an ATP‐binding cassette transporter confers resistance to four aminoglycoside antibiotics. Plant Cell Rep. 29, 643–650.20383769 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0017"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>  Kang, H. ,  Kim, J. ,  Kim, B. ,  Jeong, H. ,  Choi, S.H. ,  Kim, E.K. ,  Lee, H.  et al (2011) Overexpression of FTL1/DDF1, an AP2 transcription factor, enhances tolerance to cold, drought, and heat stresses in Arabidopsis thaliana . Plant Sci. 180, 634–641.21421412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0018"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>  King, E.K. ,  Moritz, T.  and  Harberd, N.P.  (2001) Gibberellins are not required for normal stem growth in Arabidopsis thaliana in the absence of GAI and RGA. Genetics, 159, 767–776.11606551 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0019"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>  Lee, D.J.  and  Zeevaart, J.A.D.  (2005) Molecular cloning of GA 2‐oxidase 3 from spinach and its ectopic expression in Nicotiana sylvestris . Plant Physiol. 138, 243–254.15821147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0020"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>  Liu, W. ,  Xu, Z.H. ,  Luo, D.  and  Xue, H.W.  (2003) Roles of OsCKI1, a rice casein kinase I, in root development and plant hormone sensitivity. Plant J. 36, 189–202.14535884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0021"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>  Luo, A. ,  Qian, Q. ,  Yin, H. ,  Liu, X. ,  Yin, C. ,  Lan, Y. ,  Tang, J.  et al (2006)  EUI1, encoding a putative cytochrome P450 monooxygenase, regulates internode elongation by modulating gibberellin responses in rice. Plant Cell Physiol. 47, 181–191.16306061 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0022"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>  Magome, H. ,  Yamaguchi, S. ,  Hanada, A. ,  Kamiya, Y.  and  Oda, K.  (2004)  dwarf and delayed‐flowering 1, a novel Arabidopsis mutant deficient in gibberellin biosynthesis because of overexpression of a putative AP2 transcription factor. Plant J. 37, 720–729.14871311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0023"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>  Magome, H. ,  Yamaguchi, S. ,  Hanada, A. ,  Kamiya, Y.  and  Oda, K.  (2008) The DDF1 transcriptional activator upregulates expression of a gibberellin‐deactivating gene, GA2ox7, under high‐salinity stress in Arabidopsis . Plant J. 56, 613–626.18643985 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0024"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>  Magome, H. ,  Nomura, T. ,  Hanada, A. ,  Takeda‐Kamiya, N. ,  Ohnishi, T. ,  Shinma, Y. ,  Katsumata, T.  et al (2013)  CYP714B1 and CYP714B2 encode gibberellin 13‐oxidases that reduce gibberellin activity in rice. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>USA, 110, 1947–1952.23319637 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0025"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>  Mao, D.  and  Chen, C.  (2012) Colinearity and similar expression pattern of rice DREB1s reveal their functional conservation in the cold‐responsive pathway. PLoS ONE, 7, e47275.23077584 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0026"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>  Munns, R.  (2002) Comparative physiology of salt and water stress. Plant, Cell Environ. 25, 239–250.11841667 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0027"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>  Murashige, T.  and  Skoog, F.  (1962) A revised medium for rapid growth and bioassays with tobacco tissue cultures. Physiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Plant. 15, 473–495. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0028"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>  Nelson, D.C. ,  Riseborough, J.A. ,  Flematti, G.R. ,  Stevens, J. ,  Ghisalberti, E.L. ,  Dixon, K.W.  and  Smith, S.M.  (2009) Karrikins discovered in smoke trigger Arabidopsis seed germination by a mechanism requiring gibberellic acid synthesis and light. Plant Physiol. 149, 863–873.19074625 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0029"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>  Nomura, T. ,  Magome, H. ,  Hanada, A. ,  Takeda‐Kamiya, N. ,  Mander, L.N. ,  Kamiya, Y.  and  Yamaguchi, S.  (2013) Functional analysis of Arabidopsis CYP714A1 and CYP714A2 reveals that they are distinct gibberellin modification enzymes. Plant Cell Physiol. 54, 1837–1851.24009336 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0030"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>  Ogawa, M. ,  Hanada, A. ,  Yamauchi, Y. ,  Kuwahara, A. ,  Kamiya, Y.  and  Yamaguchi, S.  (2003) Gibberellin biosynthesis and response during Arabidopsis seed germination. Plant Cell, 15, 1591–1604.12837949 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0031"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>  Olszewski, N. ,  Sun, T.P.  and  Gubler, F.  (2002) Gibberellin signaling: biosynthesis, catabolism, and response pathways. Plant Cell, 14(Suppl.), S61–S80.12045270 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0032"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>  Pearce, D.W. ,  Hutt, O.E. ,  Rood, S.B.  and  Mander, L.N.  (2002) Gibberellins in shoots and developing capsules of Populus species . Phytochemistry, 59, 679–687.11867101 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0033"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>  Qin, F. ,  Kodaira, K.S. ,  Maruyama, K. ,  Mizoi, J. ,  Tran, L.S. ,  Fujita, Y. ,  Morimoto, K.  et al (2011) SPINDLY, a negative regulator of gibberellic acid signaling, is involved in the plant abiotic stress response. Plant Physiol. 157, 1900–1913.22013217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0034"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>  Rieu, I. ,  Eriksson, S. ,  Powers, S.J. ,  Gong, F. ,  Griffiths, J. ,  Woolley, L. ,  Benlloch, R.  et al (2008) Genetic analysis reveals that C19‐GA 2‐oxidation is a major gibberellin inactivation pathway in Arabidopsis. Plant Cell, 20, 2420–2436.18805991 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0035"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>  Sakai, M. ,  Sakamoto, T. ,  Saito, T. ,  Matsuoka, M. ,  Tanaka, H.  and  Kobayashi, M.  (2003) Expression of novel rice gibberellin 2‐oxidase gene is under homeostatic regulation by biologically active gibberellins. J. Plant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Res. 116, 161–164.12736788 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0036"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>  Sakamoto, T.  (2006) Phytohormones and rice crop yield: strategies and opportunities for genetic improvement. Transgenic Res. 15, 399–404.16906440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0037"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>  Sakamoto, T. ,  Morinaka, Y. ,  Ishiyama, K. ,  Kobayashi, M. ,  Itoh, H. ,  Kayano, T. ,  Iwahori, S.  et al (2003) Genetic manipulation of gibberellin metabolism in transgenic rice. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol. 21, 909–913.12858182 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0038"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>  Santes, C.M. ,  Hedden, P. ,  Gaskin, P.  and  Garcia‐Martinez, J.  (1995) Gibberellins and related compounds in young fruits of pea and their relationship to fruit‐set. Phytochemistry, 40, 1347–1355. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0039"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>  Sasaki, A. ,  Ashikari, M. ,  Ueguchi‐Tanaka, M. ,  Itoh, H. ,  Nishimura, A. ,  Swapan, D. ,  Ishiyama, K.  et al (2002) Green revolution: a mutant gibberellin‐synthesis gene in rice. Nature, 416, 701–702.11961544 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0040"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>  Sasaki, A. ,  Itoh, H. ,  Gomi, K. ,  Ueguchi‐Tanaka, M. ,  Ishiyama, K. ,  Kobayashi, M. ,  Jeong, D.H.  et al (2003) Accumulation of phosphorylated repressor for gibberellin signaling in an F‐box mutant. Science, 299, 1896–1898.12649483 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0041"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>  Schomburg, F.M. ,  Bizzell, C.M. ,  Lee, D.J. ,  Zeevaart, J.A.D.  and  Amasino, R.M.  (2003) Overexpression of a novel class of gibberellin 2‐oxidases decreases gibberellin levels and creates dwarf plants. Plant Cell, 15, 151–163.12509528 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0042"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>  Schwechheimer, C.  (2008) Understanding gibberellic acid signaling – are we there yet? Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Opin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Plant Biol. 11, 9–15.18077204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0043"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>  Shan, C. ,  Mei, Z. ,  Duan, J. ,  Chen, H. ,  Feng, H.  and  Cai, W.  (2014) OsGA2ox5, a gibberellin metabolism enzyme, is involved in plant growth, the root gravity response and salt stress. PLoS ONE, 9, e87110.24475234 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0044"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>  Steiner, E. ,  Efroni, I. ,  Gopalraj, M. ,  Saathoff, K. ,  Tseng, T.S. ,  Kieffer, M. ,  Eshed, Y.  et al (2012) The Arabidopsis O‐linked N‐acetylglucosamine transferase SPIDLY interacts with classI TCPs to facilitate cytokinin responses in leaves and flowers. Plant Cell, 24, 96–108.22267487 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0045"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>  Tang, R.J. ,  Yang, Y. ,  Yang, L. ,  Liu, H. ,  Wang, C.T. ,  Yu, M.M. ,  Gao, X.S.  et al (2014) Poplar calcineurin B‐like proteins PtCBL10A and PtCBL10B regulate shoot salt tolerance through interaction with PtSOS2 in the vacuolar membrane. Plant, Cell Environ. 37, 573–588.23941462 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0046"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>  Thomas, S.G. ,  Phillips, A.L.  and  Hedden, P.  (1999) Molecular cloning and functional expression of gibberellin 2‐oxidases, multifunctional enzymes involved in gibberellin deactivation. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>USA, 96, 4698–4703.10200325 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0047"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>  Tuskan, G.A. ,  DiFazio, S. ,  Jansson, S. ,  Bohlmann, J. ,  Grigoriev, I. ,  Hellsten, U.  and  Bokhsar, D.  (2006) The genome of black cottonwood, Populus trichocarpa (Torr. &amp; Gray). Science, 313, 1596–1604.16973872 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0048"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>  Ueguchi‐Tanaka, M. ,  Ashikari, M. ,  Nakajima, M. ,  Itoh, H. ,  Katoh, E. ,  Kobayashi, M. ,  Chow, T.Y.  et al (2005)  GIBBERELLIN INSENSITIVE DWARF1 encodes a soluble receptor for gibberellin. Nature, 437, 693–698.16193045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0049"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>  Varbanova, M. ,  Yamaguchi, S. ,  Yang, Y. ,  McKelevy, K. ,  Hanada, A. ,  Borochov, R. ,  Yu, F.  et al (2007) Methylation of gibberellins by Arabidopsis GAMT1 and GAMT2. Plant Cell, 19, 32–45.17220201 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0050"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>  Wang, B.S.  and  Zhao, K.F.  (1995) Comparison of extractive methods of Na+, K+ in wheat leaves. Plant Physiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Commun. 31, 50–52 (in Chinese). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0051"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>  Wang, Q. ,  Guan, Y. ,  Wu, Y. ,  Chen, H. ,  Chen, F.  and  Chu, C.  (2008) Overexpression of a rice OsDREB1F gene increases salt, drought, and low temperature tolerance in both Arabidopsis and rice. Plant Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>Biol. 67, 589–602.18470484 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0052"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>  Wang, H. ,  Wang, C. ,  Liu, H. ,  Tang, R.  and  Zhang, H.  (2011) An efficient Agrobacterium‐mediated transformation and regeneration system for leaf explants of two elite aspen hybrid clones Populus alba × P. Berolinensis and Populus Davidiana×P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Bolleana . Plant Cell Rep. 30, 2037–2044.21717184 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0053"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>  Wang, C. ,  Bao, Y. ,  Wang, Q.  and  Zhang, H.  (2013) Introduction of rice CYP714D1 gene into Populus inhibits expression of its homologous genes and promotes growth, biomass production and xylem fiber length in transgenic trees. J. Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Bot. 64, 2847–2857.23667043 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0054"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>  Yamaguchi, S.  (2008) Gibberellin metabolism and its regulation. Annu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>Plant Biol. 59, 225–251.18173378 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0055"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>  Yamane, H. ,  Fujioka, S. ,  Spray, C.R. ,  Phinney, B.O. ,  Macmillan, J. ,  Gaskin, P.  and  Takahashi, N.  (1988) Endogenous gibberellins from sporophytes of two tree ferns, Cibotiumglaucum and Dicksonia antarctica . Plant Physiol. 86, 857–862.16666000 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0056"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>  Yoo, S.D. ,  Cho, Y.H.  and  Sheen, J.  (2007) Arabidopsis mesophyll protoplasts: a versatile cell system for transient gene expression analysis. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Protoc. 2, 1565–1572.17585298 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0057"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>  Yoshida, S. ,  Forno, D.A. ,  Cock, J.H.  and  Gomez, K.A.  (1976) Laboratory Manual for Physiological Studies of Rice. Manila, Philippines: International Rice Research Institute. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0058"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>  Zhang, Y. ,  Zhang, B. ,  Yan, D. ,  Dong, W. ,  Yang, W. ,  Li, Q. ,  Zeng, L.  et al (2011) Two Arabidopsis cytochrome P450 monooxygenases, CYP714A1 and CYP714A2, function redundantly in plant development through gibberellin deactivation. Plant J. 67, 342–353.21457373 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0059"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>  Zhu, Y. ,  Nomura, T. ,  Xu, Y. ,  Zhang, Y. ,  Peng, Y. ,  Mao, B. ,  Hanada, A.  et al (2006)  ELONGATED UPPERMOST INTERNODE encodes a cytochrome P450 monooxygenase that epoxidizes gibberellins in a novel deactivation reaction in rice. Plant Cell, 18, 442–456.16399803 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbi12544-bib-0060"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>  Zhu, W. ,  Miao, Q. ,  Sun, D. ,  Yang, G. ,  Wu, C. ,  Huang, J.  and  Zheng, C.  (2012) The mitochondrial phosphate transporters modulate plant responses to salt stress via affecting ATP and gibberellin metabolism in Arabidopsis thaliana . PLoS ONE, 7, e43530.22937061 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
