<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Nurs</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Nurs</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Nursing</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1472-6955</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5237197</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">201</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12912-017-0201-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Conditions for success in introducing telemedicine in diabetes foot care: a qualitative inquiry </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kolltveit</surname><given-names>Beate-Christin Hope</given-names></name><address><email>bchk@hib.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gjengedal</surname><given-names>Eva</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Graue</surname><given-names>Marit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iversen</surname><given-names>Marjolein M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thorne</surname><given-names>Sally</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kirkevold</surname><given-names>Marit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Faculty of Health and Social Science, Centre for Evidence-Based Practice, Bergen University College, Bergen, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Global Public Health and Primary Care, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Faculty of Health and Social Care, Molde University College, Molde, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Medicine, Section of Endocrinology, Stavanger University Hospital, Stavanger, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>School of Nursing, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, Canada </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Nursing Science, Institute of Health and Society, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>13</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>2</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The uptake of various telehealth technologies to deliver health care services at a distance is expanding; however more knowledge is needed to help understand vital components for success in using telehealth in different work settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>This study was part of a larger trial designed to investigate the effect of an interactive telemedicine platform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The platform consisted of a web based ulcer record linked to a mobile phone to provide care for people with diabetic foot ulcers in outpatient clinics in specialist hospital care in collaboration with primary health care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The aim of this qualitative study was to identify perceptions of health care professionals in different working settings with respect to facilitators to engagement and participation in the application of telemedicine. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Ten focus groups were conducted with health care professionals and leaders in Western Norway between January 2014 and June 2015 using Interpretive Description, an applied qualitative research strategy. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Four key conditions for success in using telemedicine as a new technology in diabetes foot care were identified: technology and training that were user-friendly; having a telemedicine champion in the work setting; the support of committed and responsible leaders; and effective communication channels at the organizational level. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Successful larger scale implementation of telemedicine must involve consideration of complex contextual and organizational factors associated with different work settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>This form of new care technology in diabetes foot care often involves health care professionals working across different settings with different management systems and organizational cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Therefore, attention to the distinct needs of each staff group seems an essential condition for effective implementation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Telehealth</kwd><kwd>Telemedicine</kwd><kwd>Health care professionals</kwd><kwd>Diabetic foot ulcer</kwd><kwd>Focus groups interviews</kwd><kwd>Interpretive description</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Norwegian Research Council</institution></funding-source><award-id>221065</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Graue</surname><given-names>Marit</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>People with diabetic foot ulcers need frequent consultations with health care professionals in specialized hospital care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Telehealth technology, often labeled as telemedicine [1], can be helpful in meeting these follow up care needs [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Telemedicine supports distant interaction between health care professionals in primary and specialized care, thereby reducing the need for patients to visit the hospital [3], and the uptake of this kind of technology to deliver health care services at a distance is expanding [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, adoption of telemedicine in clinical practice is notoriously slow [5, 6], in part because of its complexity when introduced into a heavily burdened clinical practice work situation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, problems have been identified in scaling up smaller telemedicine initiatives into wider health care service system redesign [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Developments in the technological field have grown more rapidly than has our knowledge about how its organizational and contextual aspects influence how we deliver health care [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Evidence to support understanding and addressing these factors is essential to ensuring that telehealth care services are both effective and appropriate for patients [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In this evolving telemedicine technology context, a systematic review by Brewster and colleagues in 2014 pointed out that the acceptance of new technologies by health care professionals, as well as their participation and engagement in introduction and implementation, is a vital component of their ultimate effectiveness [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>However, as Mair and colleagues observed in a another systematic review in 2012, less priority has been directed to date on understanding barriers and facilitators to successful application in relation to involvement and engagement of the health care professionals [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Although there have been significant numbers of studies addressing the technology itself and its feasibility, few have focused on understanding the health care professional engagement aspect in either specialist health care or primary health care settings [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Interventions that are tailored to increase conditions for success when applying telemedicine across settings might therefore help improve this modality of professional practice [13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>This qualitative study was conducted in alignment with a large cluster randomized controlled trial which was designed to investigate clinical outcomes associated with telemedicine follow-up care for people with diabetic foot ulcers in outpatient clinics in specialist hospital care in collaboration with primary health care (home- based care services) [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Qualitative investigations aligned with randomized controlled trials can assist in providing in-depth insights into the processes at play and that may explain the observable effects (or lack thereof) in complex interventions [15, 16], including the implications of the intervention for the actual health care setting and the manner in which new technologies change care delivery patterns [17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The national health care service system in Norway is financed by taxation, under the principle that all legal residents have equal access regardless of socioeconomic status and area of residence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>However, national evidence-based practice guidelines do not specify whether patients with foot ulcers should be enrolled in orthopaedics, dermatology or endocrine outpatient follow-up clinics, or followed by primary health care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Thus, in the Norwegian context, usual follow-up procedures for diabetic foot ulcer can differ depending upon the arrangement of specialty outpatient care options. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In most instances, patients have been followed-up by specialized hospital care (outpatient clinics) supported by primary health care (home-based care services) with limited communication between those forms of health care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The aim of this qualitative study was to identify what health care professionals in distinct staff groups perceived as essential conditions for effective implementation of telemedicine as a new health care technology in diabetes foot care. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The intervention </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The general field of telehealth includes a wide range of technology applications, often including computers and mobile phones [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The intervention in the current study consisted of an interactive telemedicine platform comprised of a web based ulcer record combined with wound assessment images and text sent via mobile phone or computer from primary health care providers to specialist health care providers (ClinicalTrials.gov: NCT01710774). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Images were taken using the camera function of a standard mobile smartphone dedicated to this purpose, and there were no differences in equipment used across sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The health care professionals in specialist health care contacted the nurse in primary health care in case of uncertainty or if text or images were not received on a weekly basis [14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>For patients included in the intervention group, this constituted a change in the treatment routines for their diabetic foot ulcer, reducing reliance on outpatient consultations in specialist hospital care and replacing them with local follow up by registered primary care nurses who were supervised by health care professionals (mainly but not exclusively nurses) in specialist health care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Primary care nurses used the technology and performed wound care mostly in patients` homes, but for some patients this care took place in a nurse-led primary care clinic or at a general practitioner’s office. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The key ingredient in the intervention was the close integration between health care levels with the use of telemedicine equipment to transfer images of the foot ulcer from home care nurses to specialist health care professionals in hospital outpatient specialty services. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Nurses performed wound care in accordance with the specialist’s assessment and were required to initiate contact with the clinic should the ulcers exacerbate regardless of prior agreements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>In addition to the primary care follow up, patients in the intervention group were seen approximately every sixth week in the outpatient specialty clinic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Those not randomized to the intervention group were followed up in a standard manner in the specialist hospital care outpatient clinics with consultations, usually every second week. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>When a patient participated in the intervention group, the nurse in charge in the community (home based care service), a nurse at the nurse-led primary care clinic or a nurse at the general practitioners office was contacted by the specialist hospital care outpatient clinics [14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Health care professionals involved in the intervention received basic training in the use of telemedicine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The training consisted of a review of written information about the study and study procedures together with a hands-on training session that focused on use of the web-based ulcer record as well as the mobile phone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Beyond this basic training, a more advanced level of training with respect to the management of the intervention processes was provided to a small group of health professionals in specialist health care involved in clinical leadership positions who were intended to function as resource persons for the remainder of the participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The training sessions also presented an opportunity for the visiting health care professionals and hospital staff to meet and get to know each other prior to cooperating on the project. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Health care professionals from primary health care were also offered the opportunity to observe consultation as conducted in the hospital outpatient clinic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>As the intervention continued, nurses in the hospital outpatient clinic were communicating with the home care nurses at least once a week, and could also communicate with them on an ongoing basis [14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>An applied qualitative research strategy known as Interpretive Description was used in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Interpretive description is an inductive approach inspired by grounded theory, naturalistic inquiry, ethnography and phenomenology [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The hallmark of Interpretive Description is the integration of knowledge development in relation to clinical phenomena, such that health care professionals can obtain new insights informing the clinical field [19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The study sample for this project was comprised of two groups: 1) point-of-care professionals (primarily nurses, but also including other providers) working in either primary/home based care or in specialist hospital outpatient settings, and 2) registered nurses in various clinical leadership roles in primary/home based care or hospital outpatient settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The point-of-care health care professionals worked either in specialty outpatient clinics located in two Western Norway hospitals or in a primary health care context in the municipalities (municipality districts or clusters) associated with that hospital’s health authority region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Sampling was purposive, including seeking variation in health care occupation, and ensuring inclusion of health care professionals with some experience in how to use telemedicine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Invitations to participate in focus groups were sent by e-mail to all of the health care professionals who had experienced some level of telemedicine within the clusters in the intervention group (n = &lt;40). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>As a result, a total of 34 health care professionals from seven home based care services, one nurse-led primary care clinic, one general practitioner’s office and two specialty outpatient hospital clinics responded and participated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Most of the health care professionals were registered nurses (n = 24) or clinical leaders (n = 5); the sample of direct care providers also included one nurse assistant, two podiatrists and two physicians (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The majority of the study participants worked in primary health care (n = 21). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The original plan was to interview all participants twice with a 6-month interval to find out more about the process they undertook when using telemedicine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>However, it turned out that the participants had less experience than assumed after 6 months because fewer patients were recruited in the cluster randomized controlled trial than expected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Therefore, additional participants who had experience with the ongoing intervention into the second round of focus groups were invited to participate.Table 1Staff participants working siteWorking siteNumber of participantsNurses in home based care services18Nurse-led primary care clinic1Nurse assistant in home based care services1Nurse in a general practitioners office1Nurses in outpatient clinics4Nurses in various clinical leadership roles5Physicians in outpatient clinic2Podiatrists in outpatient clinic2 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The sample reflected some diversity in education and experience. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Eighteen of the nurses had completed advanced nurse education such as wound care, diabetes specialist nurse, intensive care nursing education, and the physicians were specialists in endocrinology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>All but one were female, and the participants’ mean age was 47 years (range 24–64). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>They ranged in wound care experience from 1 to 30 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Those working in home-based care service were in rural districts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Some of the participants were in the initial stages of introducing telemedicine in their work because of their participation in the ongoing cluster RCT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>There was also a range of work experiences related to telemedicine; those working in specialist health care were more experienced in using telemedicine than those working in primary health care due to their more frequent use of the web based ulcer record system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Ethical considerations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The Regional Committee for Medical Research Ethics (2011/1609/REK vest) approved the study protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>In keeping with local conditions for ethical approval in studies involving health professionals, confirmation that they had received written information about the study was obtained in lieu of written informed consent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The participants were assured that their participation was voluntary, and that it was fully possible to withdraw from the study at any time without consequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Their anonymity was preserved by using numeric signifiers instead of names in all transcripts and notes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Data collection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Data was collected from ten focus group interviews during 2014 and 2015. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Focus groups were found to be a relevant method for exploring the participants experience in a collaborative environment (Krueger &amp; Casey, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The first author served as moderator with the second author as co-moderator in these interviews, and neither was associated with the telemedicine intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The size of the focus groups varied between three and seven participants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The focus groups were generally held in the professionals` work sites, but for the convenience of the nurses, some focus groups from primary health care were held in a meeting room in the hospital. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>We chose to hold separate groups for participants from primary health care and specialist health care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>There was also one focus group with only clinical leaders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>This was done to avoid a possible problem due to the difference in experience in using telemedicine, assuming that this could cause some of the participants to hold back on their thoughts in a group discussion format. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>It was also assumed that mixing the health care professions within their own working site could facilitate an exploration and discussion on different perspectives within their work context. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The length of the focus group interviews ranged from seventy to ninety minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>A digital voice recorder was used to audiotape the interviews. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>A thematic interview guide was developed, including open ended questions designed to ensure as full as possible coverage of the topics related to our study aim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The scope of these questions was informed by previous research on telemedicine as well as important factors known to influence quality improvement (structural aspects, care processes and outcomes of the new way of working). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The set of guiding questions aimed at capturing the participants` experience of the planning process, applying telemedicine in their care and the changes they perceived in relation to being introduced to telemedicine (Table 2) [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>During the focus groups interviews, health care professionals were also encouraged to raise other issues that they considered important in relation to conditions for success in enacting telemedicine in diabetes foot care.Table 2Guiding questions for focus groupsGuiding questions for focus groups• Participants` experiences of using telemedicine, and how it was organized where they work• Participants` experiences in using telemedicine as a new tool in documentation and communication• Participants` experiences in communication and collaboration between outpatient clinic (physicians, nurses and foot therapists) and nurses in home care through tele-communication, and among professions• Changes in their competence in caring for people with diabetes foot ulcers during the intervention </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Interpretive Description methodology served as a guide for the process of analyzing the data [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Gathering and analyzing the data occurred concurrently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Early data analysis was conducted immediately following each focus group interview in order to inform and guide the next one. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>This process helped to compare elements in the data throughout the data collection and analysis process, using a constant comparative approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Notes were taken during all focus group interviews by the co-moderator, and after each interview the moderator and co-moderator talked through their impressions with respect to what had taken place. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>All interviews were transcribed verbatim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Immersion in the analysis was achieved by reading and rereading the transcripts to become familiar with all features of the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Key verbatim segments of the transcripts were extracted and collated for ongoing interpretation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="?"><plain>Questions repeatedly asked during this process included: What is seen here in this data? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="?"><plain>What is not seen? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="?"><plain>What is going on here? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="?"><plain>What does it mean? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Through this ongoing iterative process, a sense of the whole was developed, from which the body of transcribed material was more formally coded and organized. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The coding process started inductively, using open-ended codes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>In accordance with the Interpretive Description approach, data segments were grouped in a manner that was as broad-based as possible to avoid premature closure of our interpretations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The material was independently coded, followed by a discussion around the codes to achieve consensus about the patterns in the material at each stage of the analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Through this coding process, groupings emerged that helped organize the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>As the team viewed the collected data and the analysis of it in process, the tentative initial groupings enabled a consideration of the various patterns and variety within those patterns across all the interviews. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>As possible relationships between these patterns became more apparent, the analytic process was concluded by conceptualizing findings in a manner that optimally illuminated the facilitators to engagement and participation in the application of diabetes foot ulcer telemedicine from the perspective of these health care professionals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Throughout the accounts of various facilitators regarding the use of telemedicine in the care of patients with diabetic foot ulcers, it was observed that health care professionals were highly enthusiastic about the idea itself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, they encountered challenges in the process of the telemedicine intervention, at least in the initial phase that was followed for this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Exploring these challenges in-depth, it was possible to identify four key conditions perceived by the health care professionals involved to be crucial to a successful telemedicine care delivery experience; user-friendly technology and training, a telemedicine champion, committed and responsible leaders and effective communication channels at the organizational level. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>User-friendly technology and training </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The health care professionals in this study emphasized the importance of having a user-friendly technology upon which to rely when using telemedicine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>After the initial phase, in which they noted some minor difficulties with the mobile phone, passwords and the web ulcer record, the technology seemed to function very well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Many of the health care professionals experienced the technology as easy to learn and use, and this facilitated the intervention for that group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>As one explained it, “The technology must be easy to use, and it is. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>If it takes a lot of time and attention it would make us more reluctant to use it.” Opinions similar to this were common across the focus groups with both primary health care and specialist health care professionals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>They frequently emphasized the need for technology that actually helped them in their work without being too time consuming: “One must remember that using this technology is one of many tasks during our day.” There was also agreement on recognition that the telemedicine technology was improving all the time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Participants across all of the focus groups highlighted the importance of being asked and listened to when adjustments were made with the technology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>To learn to use the technology, the health care professionals in the intervention arm in primary health care were invited to participate in an early meeting with the patient when wound care was being performed in the hospital outpatient clinics; however, in some cases, this aspect of the intended plan seemed to slip away as time went by. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>This led to some differences in how they experienced the training in using the technology and what that training consisted of. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the health care professionals in specialist health care, those working in home based care services seemed to have more varied experiences in the training for using the technology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Over time, some experienced having to manage the training of their new colleagues in using the technology, and help them perform the wound care expected as part of the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The following example illustrates the frustration they experienced when this occurred:One of my colleagues received training in using the technology from me. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>She chose not to use the computer when reporting to the outpatient clinic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>She used the smart phone because she had problems with the password on the computer I think. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>She had many problems in the beginning,…She told me later that she was frustrated and wanted to quit. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Some of the health care professionals in the home based services also experienced the training to be unsystematic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>They found this challenging, because they felt they were given more responsibility than expected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>In such situations, they expressed the desire for access to more training as needed over time because, when they were not using telemedicine, they forgot how to use it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>However, even with gaps in systematic training, the health care professionals generally remained enthusiastic, because they clearly saw the potential benefit for the patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>A telemedicine champion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Although the health care professionals generally described the use of the new technology in a positive manner, they also emphasized the importance of having someone close to them who could facilitate the telemedicine intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The health care professionals in the outpatient clinics felt that some colleagues in the intervention were their “leading lights or champions” when using this new technology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>They referred to these facilitators as essential to this intervention, and crucial for the telemedicine intervention’s success. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Such individuals were described as facilitating the intervention by being professionally updated, engaged in the intervention and performing the practical tasks like maintenance and adjustments in the technology; they seemed highly committed to and enthusiastic about using telemedicine. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The importance of having a colleague who could champion this intervention was described as a prominent success condition among those who experienced it as well as those who did not. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The following example illustrates the role played by such a facilitator in their midst:Well, we have some among us who facilitate it all. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>They have encouraged us, and when some of us think this is too much work, they have been there with their enthusiasm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>This enthusiasm has been valuable to us. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>In contrast, it was found that the health care professionals in primary health care in particular were unlikely to have a champion at hand to serve in this facilitator role. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Instead, they experienced having to be their own champion in motivating and performing the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>This made them more vulnerable to exhaustion in relation to the telemedicine intervention, especially when they were the only one over time or during specific periods in their particular district to be using it. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Committed and responsible leaders </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>From the perspective of the health care professionals, it was apparent that a related condition of success beyond colleague facilitators was having organizational leadership within their care systems that was aware of and supportive of the telemedicine intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Focus group participants highlighted the need for a committed and a responsible organizational leader to support the conditions under which success was made possible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Their accounts made it apparent that the locations and contexts of their work – such as whether they worked in specialist health care or in primary health care – influenced the likelihood of having a leader appropriately positioned in a role with the ability to support the use of telemedicine in their daily care. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The specialist health care work setting made it possible for the leaders to play a more active role when applying the telemedicine intervention in diabetes foot care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Because they were visible in the outpatient clinics, the leaders actively contributed in different ways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>They were conscious of being available when needed for the health care professionals taking part in the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The health care professionals experienced their leaders as supportive and helpful in organizing their everyday tasks in the outpatient clinic so they could perform the intervention as planned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>One nurse leader in an outpatient clinic described her experience in this manner: “I help in organizing on a daily basis so everything works out fine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>I try to be there if they need me. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>They are skillful, and it is nice to be a part of this.” </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the leaders in specialist health care, the leaders in primary health care were unable to provide the same level of direct support, mainly because they did not work alongside the nurses in home based care in the same manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>As home based care nurses work in the homes of their patients across a wide geographical area, they have to work independently and make many decisions on the spot without direct access and support from their leader. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the leaders in home based care services operated from the sidelines rather than in the more visible role of leaders in the outpatient clinics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The differing organizational structures between these two kinds of settings shaped the distinct roles of leaders and thus their approach towards supporting the intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Despite this difference, many health care professionals in home based care services participating in the telemedicine intervention experienced their leaders to be a positive factor in the use of telemedicine, even though they did not engage in it directly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Some of them characterized them as “leaders on the sideline.” As one explained: “In my municipality it is not organized at all. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>There is no guarantee that I will be sent to a patient involved in the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>I have to tell my leader to send me there.” Another member of that focus group quickly responded: “It is the same where I work, I have to remind my leader to send me to the right patient.” Clearly this was not the case in every municipality, as some experienced their leaders as mindful of which nurse to send when patients were involved in the intervention: “In our place the leader makes sure that the health care professionals involved in the intervention visit patients involved in the intervention.” </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Even where health care professionals had to organize and manage the telemedicine use on their own, they could still feel some support from leaders when they experienced their attitudes toward telemedicine to be positive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>However, when unexpected events occurred, with either equipment or patients in the intervention, their experience was that they had to manage it by themselves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Therefore, taking ownership of the telemedicine intervention seemed to be of utmost importance for the health care professionals in the primary health care context. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Overall, we also found that the home based care nurses needed to be more highly qualified and autonomous than those in specialist services. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>In some focus groups in the primary care context, we encountered reports such as this: “I do not think they (the leaders) know what we are doing when we are using telemedicine.” Another study participant explained: “There is an interest for this intervention by the leaders, but they are not so interested in knowing more about the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>My leader is pleased with the fact that I am handling it all.” </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Among the health care professionals in home based care services, some concerns were expressed about the vulnerability of the intervention with respect to overall leadership. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>In particular, where there were limited numbers of health care professionals involved in the intervention, it could seem that no one was assuming full responsibility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Some of these health care professionals expressed the view that their leaders did not know what they were dealing with on a daily basis when using telemedicine, and they had to organize their working day as best as they could. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>When there were no leaders fully engaged in the intervention, it seemed most vulnerable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>This was especially the case when those involved were unable to participate in the intervention, such as when care staff were sick, on maternity leave or holiday, or there was a change in the job situation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>As one explained: “It has been a challenge when I have been on a holiday. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>No one is responsible then. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>No one follows up these patients in particular.” Another similarly commented: “I wish we were two health care professionals involved in the intervention because my experience is that when I am away no one follows up messages from the outpatient clinic.” The effect of such situations was that the intervention was not carried out as intended, and pictures were not taken and reported as planned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Because performing wound care and documentation within the intervention was more time consuming than usual care, some of the health care professionals had to argue for spending more time with patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>They interpreted this not as a lack of enthusiasm from their leaders, but rather as a lack of involvement in the intervention because they trusted the health care professionals to perform the intervention as planned. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>It was noted that some participants in a focus group interview with the leaders in home based care services described a similar limited degree of involvement in the intervention to that which the health care professionals in that setting had experienced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>For example, some were very uncertain about what the elements the intervention actually consisted of, and did not know what kind of training the health care professionals had in relation to the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>They strongly felt that they had delegated responsibility for performing the intervention to the selected health care professionals in the municipality, and seemed satisfied with the situation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>A comment by one leader illustrates: “Some nurses were given this responsibility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>They have taken this responsibility, and have control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>I am here on the sideline, but I find it exciting.” Another agreed: “It is the same in our municipality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Those nurses involved in the intervention have total control, and they inform me when needed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>I just follow them from the sideline.” In this manner, the leaders relied on the competence of the health care professionals and made them responsible for carrying out the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>While they did not feel that they had facilitated anything for the health care professionals, they stated that they were very positive with respect to the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>For these leaders, the intervention was not perceived as time-consuming at all. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>They reflected primarily on the positive aspects of care that this intervention contributed to, such as more competence in wound care within all health care professionals in primary health care. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Effective communication channels at the organizational level </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The final condition for success observed in this study had to do with effective lines of communication within health care organizations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>In primary health care there are leaders at several levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The leaders in primary health care felt that they missed information about the intervention, and had some concerns that information from “higher up” in the system did not reach them at all. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, they did not know who to talk to in order to get such information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>A typical remark in the focus group by the leaders was: “I do not receive much information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>I do not know if there is any key person to ask either. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>If there are any meetings for some key persons, they do not pass on information to us.” In addition, opinions like this were expressed: “If leaders higher up in our system know something they should inform us. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>We do not know if this project is still running.” Several felt that this intervention should have been more strategically driven by leaders above them who were prepared to keep them better informed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Lack of information impeded the ability of the leaders to follow up on the implementation of the telemedicine intervention and fully support their staff in the implementation process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Effective communication was also influenced by the fact that, in each municipality, there were only one or two selected health care professionals in home based care services involved in the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>From the perspective of the specialist health care professionals involved in the intervention, this facilitated communication in that they found it easier to have to cooperate with only a few individuals in primary health care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>As one explained: “We do not want more people to be involved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>It is much easier to communicate with a few.” In contrast, those involved in the intervention in the primary health care experienced this to be a problem because of the vulnerability in there being too few involved when some of them could not participate for various reasons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Then communication sometimes broke down or was delayed, which might threaten the continuity of the foot ulcer follow up care. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>To summarize, identifying these four distinct but intersecting key conditions for success provides additional layers of knowledge about the complex processes involved in introducing telemedicine in diabetes foot care. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The findings of this study reflect conditions for success from the health care professionals’ perspective in the initial phase of introducing telemedicine in diabetes foot care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>A set of distinctive but interrelated conditions have been identified that seem central to a positive experience for the health care professionals involved and therefore for the success of the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>These conditions seem linked to one another, reflecting variations in the contexts in which the health care professionals work as well as structural and organizational conditions of the telemedicine intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The importance of having technology that is easy to learn and use, which was identified as one of the main conditions in this study, has also been described in other studies [7, 10, 11, 20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The need for a user-friendly technology, such as was highlighted both in specialty outpatient clinics and in primary health care, was crucial on the basis that early negative experiences could make them reluctant to use the technology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Continual improvements in the technology, such as 3D imaging systems to image and measure the wounds, might well facilitate the use of telemedicine when the new technology is ready and available [21], as well as support in using the technology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Training in using the technology in the initial phase, a factor that was crucial for the health care professionals in this study, has also been reported as a success factor in other studies [7, 10, 11, 20, 22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>However, the health care professionals in the current study found that they required training not only in the initial phase, but also later on in the process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The absence of this ongoing training contributed to a sense of insecurity about using the technology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>In some cases, especially in the primary health care context, this insecurity seemed to reduce their enthusiasm for telemedicine and therefore hindered its use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Similarly, in a study from United Kingdom, it was found that ongoing training served as a key facilitator in this process [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The importance of new technology is not always visible for the health care professionals, and their enthusiasm might therefore be correspondingly low. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>In this study the health care professionals’ enthusiasm in using telemedicine from the beginning seemed especially important when they encountered equipment limitations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The primary source of that enthusiasm was information they had received about the potential added value telemedicine could contribute to care for their diabetes foot ulcer patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>They experienced that it provided a better health care service to their patients and higher quality in the care. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>It has been recognized in the literature that reservations by health care professionals about using this new technology may hinder the uptake of it [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Based on the current findings as well as confirmatory evidence in the literature, it seems obvious that having a robust system involving user-friendly technology and a good support and training system available at all times would be the ideal in implementing telemedicine [10, 20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>It might be an option in the future to use electronic devices, such as web-based courses, to facilitate ongoing training and support for the health care professionals during the implementation process, including in the context of long-term use of the technology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Thus, early consideration of these kinds of contextual and organizational factors is needed for a successful adoption of the technology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>In the current study, the lack of robustness of the intervention plan was found to be more conspicuous in the primary health care context than in the specialist settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>In that context, the health care professionals were more likely to work alone with the new technology and were therefore more vulnerable to unpredictable situations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The infrequency of their use of the technology because they encounter fewer patients in the intervention group made confidence in using telemedicine more difficult to achieve. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The current findings also stress the importance of having nurses in primary health care who are highly qualified, autonomous and self-reliant due to their independent role in that setting. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Having a competent professional colleague was an especially important condition for success according to the participants in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Professionals in both the specialist health care and the primary health care contexts emphasized the impact of the facilitating role that some of their colleagues had assumed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Such individuals motivated ongoing enthusiasm and willingness to use the technology among their colleagues even when problems occurred. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>This suggests that it would be important to take into account the presence or absence of a potential champion when planning an intervention such as this. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Although the potential value of champions has been noted in earlier studies [7, 20, 22, 23], this condition for success has not featured strongly in prior accounts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Given the diversity within our sample with respect to this condition, it would seem that this aspect ought to be emphasized in future initiatives so the health care professionals in all settings can benefit from the champion aspect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Thus, one question arising from these results is whether it will be possible to identify individuals with the capacity to serve a champion role and guide them into that role at an early stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Understanding what motivates champions within such interventions and how best to facilitate their involvement through the entire process seems essential for future implementation projects. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>An observation arising from other studies is that using telemedicine necessitates a change in organizational thinking around collaboration and health care professional roles within a given work setting [20, 22, 24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>In the current study, having organizational leadership within the care system that was supportive and aware of the telemedicine intervention was an important condition for success. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest that implementation plans for such projects should not neglect the importance of having deep knowledge around the kind of work context or culture into which the new technology is being introduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>It may be that different strategies will be required for the introduction of telemedicine approaches to diabetes foot care within different contexts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Technical devices might be received differently in different work settings [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>The current findings clearly demonstrated different issues arising in the work setting of the primary health care context relative to that of specialist health care. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Specifically, it was noted that there was an increased requirement for attention to leadership and effective communication channels within the organizational level in the primary health care context. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>This aspect would likely be of particular importance to any implementation of telemedicine on a larger scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Beyond this essential collaboration and communication, however, these findings also suggest that having health care professionals who are capable of working independently and championing their own work may be a necessity for the successful introduction of these new technological innovations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Methodological considerations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>One limitation to this study might be the difficulty in gathering the participants for a second focus group interview. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Despite attempts to reschedule to accommodate all potential participants, some of the health care professionals were unable to join a focus group for various reasons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>There is a possibility that some of those who were missed would be more experienced, and could have provided more variation in degrees of experience. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>On the other hand it is more plausible that those who are more reluctant did not participate in the focus groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>They could have provided more knowledge related to negative experiences on the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>A further limitation to this study might be the use of only focus group to gather data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Given the opportunity to use observational methods, it might have been possible to benefit from richer data with respect to what was going on in the actual care context into which the telemedicine intervention was being introduced. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>More research will be needed in the future to explore this implementation processes in detail. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Both observational studies with health care professionals and individual interviews with patients would expand our knowledge base. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>There will also be a need for future research into the implications for success when interventions are more tailored to each working context. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, on the basis of this analysis from the perspective of a diverse group of health professionals engaging in this innovation in their care of patients, it has been possible to provide useful insights for future efforts in technological innovations in the care of patients with diabetic foot ulcers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>This study draws attention to the value of careful planning to accommodate the needs of health care professionals using new technologies, recognizing that they often work in different settings with different management systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Although a study using qualitative methods within a specific regional context cannot yield findings that are formally generalizable, what has been learned about these four key conditions for success in using telemedicine can provide those planning such transformations in health care services with an understanding of possible obstacles and facilitators when introducing new technology in a range of health care settings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to the participants who gave their time to participate in the study.</p><p>This research was supported through the authors` involvement in the European Science Foundation Research Network Programme “REFLECTION” – 09-RNP-049. The views expressed are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the European Science Foundation.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p>The clustered randomized trial (Clinicaltrials.gov: NCT01710774) is funded by the Norwegian Directorate of Health, Innovation Norway, the Western Norway Regional Health Authority and the Norwegian Diabetes Association. The present study is part of a larger study funded by a grant from the Norwegian Research Council (project number 221065) and from Bergen University College.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>Western Norway Regional Committee for Medical and Health Research Ethics approved this study. Due to ethical and legal restrictions related to confidentiality, the data cannot be deposited online as the study participants have not explicitly been informed about, nor approved data sharing when the data were gathered in 2014–2015.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Authors` contributions</title><p>BCHK, MG, EG and MK designed the study. MMI facilitated for collecting data. BCHK and EG collected the data. BCHK, EG, ST and MK contributed to data analysis. BCHK, MG, EG, MMI, ST and MK contributed to drafting the manuscript and read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>Western Norway Regional Committee for Medical and Health Research Ethics approved this study (Project no: 2011/1609/REK vest). In keeping with local conditions for ethical approval in studies involving health professionals, confirmation that they had received written information about the study was obtained in lieu of written informed consent. The participants were assured that their participation was voluntary, and that it was fully possible to withdraw from the study at any time without consequence.</p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="?"><plain>1.FatehiFWoottonRTelemedicine, telehealth or e-health? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>A bibliometric analysis of the trends in the use of these termsJ Telemed Telecare2012188460410.1258/jtt.2012.GTH108<?supplied-pmid 23209265?>23209265 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>2.RasmussenBSFroekjaerJBjerregaardMRLauritsenJHangaardJHenriksenCWHalekohUYderstraedeKBA randomized controlled trial comparing telemedical and standard outpatient monitoring of diabetic foot ulcersDiabetes Care20153891723910.2337/dc15-0332<?supplied-pmid 26116717?>26116717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>3.Oudshoorn N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Telecare technologies and the transformation of healthcare. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Palgrave Macmillan: Citeseer; 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>4.DanielHSulmasyLSHealth, Public Policy Committee of the American College of PPolicy recommendations to guide the use of telemedicine in primary care settings: an American College of Physicians position paperAnn Intern Med201516310787910.7326/M15-0498<?supplied-pmid 26344925?>26344925 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>5.Larsen SB, Sorensen NS, Petersen MG, Kjeldsen GF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Towards a shared service centre for telemedicine: Telemedicine in Denmark, and a possible way forward. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Health Informatics J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>2015;1460458215592042. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>6.TjoraAHScamblerGSquare pegs in round holes: information systems, hospitals and the significance of contextual awarenessSoc Sci Med20096835192510.1016/j.socscimed.2008.11.005<?supplied-pmid 19054601?>19054601 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>7.BroensTHVeld RMH i'tVollenbroek-HuttenMMHermensHJvan HalterenATNieuwenhuisLJDeterminants of successful telemedicine implementations: a literature studyJ Telemed Telecare2007136303910.1258/135763307781644951<?supplied-pmid 17785027?>17785027 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>8.DemirisGHenselBKTechnologies for an aging society: a systematic review of “smart home” applicationsYearb Med Inform200833340 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>9.SugarhoodPWhertonJProcterRHinderSGreenhalghTTechnology as system innovation: a key informant interview study of the application of the diffusion of innovation model to telecareDisabil Rehabil Assist Technol201491798710.3109/17483107.2013.823573<?supplied-pmid 23919407?>23919407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>10.BrewsterLMountainGWesselsBKellyCHawleyMFactors affecting front line staff acceptance of telehealth technologies: a mixed-method systematic reviewJ Adv Nurs2014701213310.1111/jan.12196<?supplied-pmid 23786584?>23786584 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>11.MairFSMayCO'DonnellCFinchTSullivanFMurrayEFactors that promote or inhibit the implementation of e-health systems: an explanatory systematic reviewBull World Health Organ20129053576410.2471/BLT.11.099424<?supplied-pmid 22589569?>22589569 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>12.RasmussenBSJensenLKFroekjaerJKidholmKKensingFYderstraedeKBA qualitative study of the key factors in implementing telemedical monitoring of diabetic foot ulcer patientsInt J Med Inform2015841079980710.1016/j.ijmedinf.2015.05.012<?supplied-pmid 26093794?>26093794 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>13.BakerRCamosso-StefinovicJGilliesCShawEJCheaterFFlottorpSRobertsonNTailored interventions to overcome identified barriers to change: effects on professional practice and health care outcomesCochrane Database Syst Rev201033CD005470 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>14.Iversen MM, Espehaug B, Hausken MF, Graue M, Østbye T, Skeie S, Cooper JG, Tell GS, Günther BE, Dale H, Smith-Strøm H, Kolltveit BCH, Kirkevold M, Rokne B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Telemedicine versus standard follow-up care for diabetes-related foot ulcers: protocol for a cluster randomized controlled noninferiority trial (DiaFOTo). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>JMIR Res Protoc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>2016;5(3):e148 doi:10.2196/resprot.5646. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>15.LewinSGlentonCOxmanADUse of qualitative methods alongside randomised controlled trials of complex healthcare interventions: methodological studyBMJ2009339b349610.1136/bmj.b3496<?supplied-pmid 19744976?>19744976 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>16.OakleyAStrangeVBonellCAllenEStephensonJHealth services research: process evaluation in randomised controlled trials of complex interventionsBMJ Brit Med J2006332753841310.1136/bmj.332.7538.413<?supplied-pmid 16484270?>16484270 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>17.OudshoornNHow places matter: telecare technologies and the changing spatial dimensions of healthcareSoc Stud Sci20124211214210.1177/0306312711431817<?supplied-pmid 22530385?>22530385 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>18.ThorneSInterpretive description2008Walnut CreekLeft Coast Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>19.ThorneSELeavyPApplied interpretive approachesThe Oxford handbook of qualitative research2014OxfordOxford University Press99115 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>20.TaylorJCoatesEBrewsterLMountainGWesselsBHawleyMSExamining the use of telehealth in community nursing: identifying the factors affecting frontline staff acceptance and telehealth adoptionJ Adv Nurs20157123263710.1111/jan.12480<?supplied-pmid 25069605?>25069605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>21.BowlingFLPatersonJNdipAApplying 21st century imaging technology to wound healing: an Avant-Gardist approachJ Diabetes Sci Technol2013751190410.1177/193229681300700536<?supplied-pmid 24124945?>24124945 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>22.ZanniGRTelemedicine: sorting out the benefits and obstaclesConsult Pharm2011261181010.4140/TCP.n.2011.810<?supplied-pmid 22079791?>22079791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>23.JensenLKKnarvikUPedersenCDTangeneWWhitehouseDDeliverable 3.4: personalised blueprint for telemedicine deployment: validated and tested version2015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>24.AasIHA qualitative study of the organizational consequences of telemedicineJ Telemed Telecare200171182610.1258/1357633011936093<?supplied-pmid 11265934?>11265934 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
