<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ImpactJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Oncotarget</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1949-2553</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Impact Journals LLC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5041910</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27015122</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">8295</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.8295</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Chronic TGF&#x003b2; stimulation promotes the metastatic potential of lung cancer cells by Snail protein stabilization through integrin &#x003b2;3-Akt-GSK3&#x003b2; signaling</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>Gab-Yong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Soon-Ki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Jeong-Rak</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>Ok-Seon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Keun-Tae</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>JaeHyung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>Ensel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>Hyuk-Jin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><sup>1</sup> College of Natural Sciences, Department of Life Sciences, Sogang University, Seoul, Republic of Korea</aff><aff id="A2"><sup>2</sup> Department of Brain and Cognitive Sciences, DGIST, Daegu, Republic of Korea</aff><aff id="A3"><sup>3</sup> Laboratory of Cancer Genomics and Molecular Pathology, Samsung Biomedical Research Institute, Samsung Medical Center, Seoul, Republic of Korea</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence to:</bold> Hyuk-Jin Cha, <email>hjcha@sogang.ac.kr</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2">Gab-Yong Bae, <email>gabyong977@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>3</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>25366</fpage><lpage>25376</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2016 Bae et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Chronic exposure to TGF&#x003b2;, a frequent occurrence for tumor cells in the tumor microenvironment, confers more aggressive phenotypes on cancer cells by promoting their invasion and migration while at the same time increasing their resistance to the growth-inhibitory effect of TGF&#x003b2;. In this study, a transdifferentiated (TD) A549 cell model, established by chronically exposing A549 cells to TGF&#x003b2;, showed highly invasive phenotypes in conjunction with attenuation of Smad-dependent signaling. We show that Snail protein, the mRNA expression of which strongly correlates with a poor prognosis in lung cancer patients, was highly stable in TD cells after TGF&#x003b2; stimulation. The increased protein stability of Snail in TD cells correlated with elevated inhibitory phosphorylation of GSK3&#x003b2;, resulting from the high Akt activity. Notably, integrin &#x003b2;3, whose expression was markedly increased upon sustained exposure to TGF&#x003b2;, was responsible for the high Akt activity as well as the increased Snail protein stability in TD cells. Consistently, clinical database analysis on lung cancer patients revealed a negative correlation between overall survival and integrin &#x003b2;3 mRNA levels. Therefore, we suggest that the integrin &#x003b2;3-Akt-GSK3&#x003b2; signaling axis plays an important role in non-canonical TGF&#x003b2; signaling, determining the invasive properties of tumor cells chronically exposed to TGF&#x003b2;.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>chronic TGF&#x003b2; exposure</kwd><kwd>integrin &#x003b2;3</kwd><kwd>Akt</kwd><kwd>GSK3&#x003b2;</kwd><kwd>Snail</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>TGF&#x003b2; signaling plays an important role in tumor suppression as well as tumor promotion events such as initiation, progression and metastasis [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. As a tumor promoter, TGF&#x003b2;, the prototype of the TGF&#x003b2; superfamily, confers metastatic potential to tumor cells by inducing epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT), characterized by the acquisition of invasive phenotypes. Conversely, growth-inhibitory or apoptosis-inducing effects of TGF&#x003b2; suppress tumor progression [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The dual roles of TGF&#x003b2;, as either a tumor promoter or a tumor suppressor, depend on the stage of tumor development; it serves as a tumor promoter for aggressive tumors and a tumor suppressor for normal cells or early carcinoma [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. However, the molecular mechanisms underlying these different responses are still unclear despite extensive studies and numerous hypotheses [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>Considering that tumor microenvironments are often enriched in secreted TGF&#x003b2; [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], cancer cells are considered to be chronically exposed to TGF&#x003b2;. Consistently, emerging reports demonstrate that after chronic TGF&#x003b2; exposure, cancer cells acquire resistance to the growth-inhibitory effect of TGF&#x003b2; and concurrently acquire malignancy or/and invasive potential (e.g., EMT). Adaptation to chronic TGF&#x003b2; exposure is achieved via alterations in the signaling networks of tumor cells that make them more prone to malignant progression [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>Resistance to TGF&#x003b2;-mediated growth arrest is attributed to loss-of-function mutations or reduced expression of TGF&#x003b2; signaling components [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], including Smad4, the common mediator of Smad-dependent (canonical) TGF&#x003b2; signaling [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Paradoxically, attenuation of TGF&#x003b2; signaling can also reduce tumor cell malignancy by causing the defective production of key EMT-regulatory factors such as <italic>ZEB1</italic>, <italic>TWIST</italic>, <italic>SLUG</italic> and <italic>SNAIL</italic> [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Therefore, in this regard, cancer malignancy can be seen as a corollary of the abrogation of the tumor suppressive effect of TGF&#x003b2; and the simultaneous potentiation of its tumor-promoting effect, mediated by alterations in TGF&#x003b2; signaling pathways.</p><p>TGF&#x003b2; receptor activation by TGF&#x003b2; also transmits signals to Smad-independent (non-canonical) pathways through the mitogen activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathway, Rho-like GTPase pathway, and phosphatidylinositol-3-kinase (PI3K)/Akt pathway [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Interestingly, the protein stability of key EMT-regulatory factors, such as Twist, Slug and Snail, is also regulated by ERK, Akt, and GSK3&#x003b2; [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Thus, it is highly plausible that the acquisition of dependence on non-canonical TGF&#x003b2; pathways accounts for the promotion of cancer malignancy even in the absence of <italic>SMAD4</italic> [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>In the present study, we established transdifferentiated (TD) cells by exposing A549 tumor cells to chronic TGF&#x003b2; exposure [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], which revealed skewed signaling toward Akt-GSK&#x003b2;. The increased invasive properties of TD cells were associated with Akt/GSK3&#x003b2;-mediated up-regulation of Snail protein. We also reasoned that integrin &#x003b2;3 might direct TGF&#x003b2; signals toward Akt and GSK3&#x003b2; to stabilize Snail. Consistently, clinical database analysis revealed a poor survival outcome for cancer patients with high integrin &#x003b2;3 mRNA expression, suggesting that the integrin &#x003b2;3-Akt-GSK3&#x003b2; signaling axis could be used as an important therapeutic target for preventing malignant cancer progression.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2_1"><title>Chronic TGF&#x003b2; stimulation enhances tumor cell migration and invasion</title><p>In this study, chronic exposure of A549 tumor cells to TGF&#x003b2; was sufficient by itself to induce EMT, which is characterized by reduced E-cadherin expression and increased N-cadherin expression and cytoskeletal reorganization (see F-actin staining in green; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A and 1B</xref>). Additionally, real-time PCR analysis revealed that typical EMT markers, such as <italic>ZEB1, ZEB2, SLUG</italic> and <italic>SNAIL</italic>, were highly expressed in TD cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>). Consistent with these EMT characteristics, TD cells showed greater migration and invasion than control A549 cells. Moreover, additional TGF&#x003b2; stimulation further promoted the cell migration (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>) and invasion (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1E</xref>) of TD cells, but not that of control A549 cells. The increased invasiveness of TD cells after chronic exposure to TGF&#x003b2; occurred concomitantly with the up-regulation of MMP9 activity (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1F</xref>). TD cells also exhibited resistance to TGF&#x003b2;-induced growth inhibition, whereas control cells exhibited sensitivity to the inhibitory effects of TGF&#x003b2; on cell cycle and cell proliferation (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S1A and S1B</xref>). Similar to TD cells, a mesenchymal-like cancer cell model with evident pro-metastatic potential, established via E-cadherin depletion, (shEcad) [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], also exhibited resistance to TGF&#x003b2;-induced growth arrest (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S1C and S1D</xref>). Taken together, these results suggest that TD cells could serve as a model for the study of the &#x02018;tumor-prone signaling shift&#x02019; that occurs upon TGF&#x003b2; stimulation.</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Chronic TGF&#x003b2; stimulation enhances tumor cell migration and invasion</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Immunoblotting with E-cadherin or N-cadherin antibody. &#x003b2;-actin was used as a loading control. (<bold>B</bold>) The cell-cell adhesion was visualized by immunostaining with E-cadherin antibody (Red) and cytoskeletal organization was visualized by F-actin staining with Phalloidin (Green). DAPI (Blue) was used to counterstain nuclear. (<bold>C</bold>) Quantitative real-time PCR for measuring the mRNA levels of EMT-genes in basal culture condition. (<bold>D</bold>) Wound healing assay was performed after TGF&#x003b2; treatment for 24 hours. Representative images (left) and migration rate (right graph) are shown. (<bold>E</bold>) Two chamber-matrigel invasion assay was performed after TGF&#x003b2; treatment for 24 hours. Invading cells across the membranes (left images) and invasion capacity (right graph) are shown. (<bold>F</bold>) After TGF&#x003b2; treatment for 24 hours, cell culture supernatants were subjected to zymography to measure MMP9 activity. <italic>Columns</italic>, means &#x000b1; SE. *<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; ns, non-significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25366-g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_2"><title>Attenuated Smad-dependent TGF&#x003b2; signaling caused by chronic TGF&#x003b2; exposure</title><p>Considering the increased invasiveness of TGF&#x003b2;-stimulated TD cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), we expected that TGF&#x003b2;-dependent gene expression would be markedly induced in TD cells. However, unexpectedly, the relative fold change in TGF&#x003b2;-induced mRNA expression of major EMT-regulatory factors (<italic>ZEB1, ZEB2, TWIST, SNAIL</italic> and <italic>SLUG</italic>), whose expression is positively regulated in a Smad-dependent manner [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], was markedly lower in TD cells than in control cells, despite the higher basal expression levels of these genes (except for <italic>TWIST</italic>) in TD cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). More importantly, phosphorylation of Smad2 and Smad3 upon TGF&#x003b2; stimulation was significantly attenuated in TD cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>), and the total protein expression level of not only Smad2 and Smad3 but also Smad4, a key co-factor for Smad2/3 nuclear translocation [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], was markedly reduced in TD cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>). To verify the Smad-dependent gene response, we employed Smad-binding element (SBE) luciferase (SBE-luc) reporter assays to determine TGF&#x003b2;/Smad-dependent gene responses [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. These assays revealed that TGF&#x003b2;/Smad-dependent gene expression in TD cells was not more induced than in control cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2D</xref>). Considering the above results, we decided to focus on non-canonical (Smad-independent) rather than canonical TGF&#x003b2; pathways to elucidate the distinctive signaling features of TD cells.</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Attenuated Smad-dependent TGF&#x003b2; signaling caused by chronic TGF&#x003b2; exposure</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) After incubation in the presence or absence of TGF&#x003b2; for 24 hours, transcript levels of TGF&#x003b2;-inducible EMT genes were quantified with real-time PCR. (<bold>B</bold>) Immunoblotting was performed to determine time-dependent expression of phospho-Smad2 (Ser465/467) or phospho-Smad3 (Ser423/425) after TGF&#x003b2; stimulation. (<bold>C</bold>) Total protein levels of Smad2, 3 and 4 were determined with immunoblotting. (<bold>D</bold>) The activity of TGF&#x003b2;/Smad signaling was determined with SBE-Luciferase reporter systems. Luciferase activity was measured at 10 hour after TGF&#x003b2; addition, and its fold induction is shown as graph. Columns, means &#x000b1; SE. *<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; ns, non-significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25366-g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_3"><title>Increased Snail protein stability in TD cells</title><p>In addition to Smad-dependent transcriptional regulation, EMT-regulatory factors are also post-transcriptionally regulated by non-canonical TGF&#x003b2; pathways [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Thus, we examined the protein levels of key EMT factors in TD cells after TGF&#x003b2; stimulation. Surprisingly, Snail and Slug protein levels were dramatically increased after TGF&#x003b2; stimulation in TD cells within 2 hours (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). Conversely, Zeb1 and Twist expression levels were not significant different between A549 and TD cells (data not shown). Considering the weak <italic>SNAIL</italic> and <italic>SLUG</italic> mRNA expression in TD cells after TGF&#x003b2; exposure (at 2 hours and 10 hours) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>), the increase in Snail and Slug protein levels in TD cells (at 2 hours) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>) cannot be explained by Smad-dependent <italic>SNAIL</italic> or <italic>SLUG</italic> transcription alone (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). Next, we searched the TCGA database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://tcga-data.nci.nih.gov/">https://tcga-data.nci.nih.gov</ext-link>) to determine the significance of the <italic>SNAIL</italic> and <italic>SLUG</italic> mRNA expression levels in lung cancer patients (the Snail protein level is not available in the TCGA database). Both overall survival and post progression survival were negatively correlated with the expression level of <italic>SNAIL</italic>, while there was no reliable correlation in the case of <italic>SLUG</italic> (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S2A</xref>). These data suggest that Snail expression, but not Slug expression is clinically significant in lung cancer.</p><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Increased Snail protein stability in TD cells</title><p>(<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) Time-dependent protein (A) and mRNA (B) induction of Snail and Slug after TGF&#x003b2; stimulation was determined with immunoblotting and real-time PCR, respectively. (<bold>C</bold>) Stabilization of Snail protein was determined by MG132, a proteasome inhibitor, in the presence or absence of TGF&#x003b2;. Cells were pretreated with MG132 (10 &#x003bc;M) for 30 minutes and subsequently stimulated with TGF&#x003b2; for additional 1 hour. (<bold>D</bold>&#x02013;<bold>F</bold>) The effect of Snail knockdown on TGF&#x003b2;-induced invasiveness of TD cells was determined with wound healing assay (D), invasion assay (E) and zymography (F). TD cells were incubated with siRNA targeting SNAIL for 24 hours, followed by TGF&#x003b2; stimulation and then subjected to wound healing and invasion assay. Supernatant of cell culture was subjected to zymography. DM, DMSO; MG, MG132. <italic>Columns</italic>, means &#x000b1; SE. *<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; ns, non-significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25366-g003"/></fig><p>We next examined the possibility that the increased protein level of Snail in TD cells after TGF&#x003b2; treatment results from increased Snail protein stabilization. The level of Snail was determined in the presence and absence of MG132, a proteasome inhibitor, after TGF&#x003b2; treatment. In the presence of MG132, the amount of Snail in TD cells remained high regardless of TGF&#x003b2; treatment, whereas the amount of Snail in control cells increased (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). These results suggest that up-regulation of Snail protein stability rather than mRNA expression in TD cells is responsible for the induction of Snail at 2 hours after TGF&#x003b2; treatment (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>).</p><p>To determine the effect of Snail induction after TGF&#x003b2; treatment on TD cells, Snail was depleted using a knockdown approach. As shown in <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S2B</xref>, Snail protein induction by TGF&#x003b2; in TD cells was significantly decreased following knockdown, and the elevated invasion and migration capacity of TD cells was markedly suppressed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D and 3E</xref>). Specifically, the enzymatic activity of MMP9, the expression of which strongly correlates with poor prognosis in lung cancer [<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], was not activated by TGF&#x003b2; treatment in Snail knockdown-TD cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3F</xref>). Taken together, these data strongly suggest that, under chronic TGF&#x003b2; stimulation, a high level of Snail protein expression is associated with increased metastatic potential of lung cancers.</p></sec><sec id="s2_4"><title>Inhibition of GSK3&#x003b2; by Akt is responsible for the increased stability of Snail</title><p>We next examined whether the increased stability of Snail in TD cells after TGF&#x003b2; treatment could have been caused by a decrease in the rate of its degradation. Because phosphorylation of Snail by GSK3&#x003b2; triggers ubiquitination of Snail and its degradation [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], determining GSK3&#x003b2; activity in TD cells is critical. As predicted, GSK3&#x003b2; phosphorylation, which leads to GSK3&#x003b2; inhibition and is governed by Akt activity, was high in TD cells. Consistently, Akt phosphorylation was higher in TD cells, an indication of active Akt, than in control cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Inhibition of GSK3&#x003b2; by Akt is responsible for the increased stability of Snail</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Immunoblotting for determining the phosphorylation levels of Akt (Ser473) and GSK3&#x003b2; (Ser9) in the basal culture condition. (<bold>B</bold>) The effect of MK2206, an Akt inhibitor, on GSK3&#x003b2; phosphorylation and Snail expression was determined with immunoblotting. MK2206 was treated at various concentrations for 3 hours before cell harvesting. (<bold>C</bold>) The inhibitory role of GSK3&#x003b2; on the stability of Snail protein was determined using a GSK3&#x003b2;-specific inhibitor, CHIR99021. Cells was pretreated with CHIR (3 &#x003bc;M) for 50 minutes and then incubated with or without TGF&#x003b2; for 3 hour and 30 minutes before cell harvesting. The expression level of Snail protein was analyzed with immunoblotting. Cyclin D1, a substrate of GSK3&#x003b2;, was used as a positive control for the effect of CHIR. DM, DMSO; CHIR, CHIR99021. (<bold>D</bold>) Cells were harvested at the indicated time after TGF&#x003b2; treatment, and then subjected to immunoblotting to determine the inhibitory phosphorylation levels of GSK3&#x003b2;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25366-g004"/></fig><p>To prove that high Akt activity in TD cells was responsible for the high level of Snail protein, Snail protein levels were monitored following inhibition of Akt activity by treatment with MK2206, a potent Akt inhibitor currently used in clinical trials for the treatment of advanced solid tumors [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>, Snail protein levels were markedly reduced while Akt active phosphorylation, as well as GSK3b inhibitory phosphorylation, was significantly reduced by Akt inhibitor treatment (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>). Conversely, GSK3&#x003b2; inhibition by CHIR99021 (CHIR) increased the level of Snail in TD cells. The extent of the increase was similar to that of the increase in the level of Cyclin D1, whose proteolysis is also determined by GSK3&#x003b2;-dependent phosphorylation [<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>). In the light of this, inhibitory phosphorylation of GSK3&#x003b2; remained high in TD cells after TGF&#x003b2; stimulation, whereas it was slightly reduced in A549 cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D</xref>). These data indicate that the increase in the Snail protein level in TD cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>) is due to Snail protein stabilization mediated by increased Akt activity and subsequent inhibition of GSK3&#x003b2; activity.</p></sec><sec id="s2_5"><title>Increased integrin &#x003b2;3 expression in TD cells contributes to the activation of Akt-GSK3&#x003b2;-Snail signaling</title><p>The question remains as to how Akt activity was elevated in TD cells after TGF&#x003b2; stimulation. Previously, we have reported that lung cancer cells become resistant to sheer stress after EMT [<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], which is consistent with previously reported findings [<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Based on this observation, we attempted to deduce a gene candidate(s) whose altered expression in TD cells contributes to both increased adhesion (e.g., resistance to sheer stress) and intracellular signaling (e.g., toward GSK3&#x003b2;). In this regard, we took advantage of GEO (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>) and chose three independent GSE studies that reported metastasis of colon (GSE2509), melanoma (GSE8401), and pancreatic cancer cells after TGF&#x003b2; exposure (GSE23952) to find commonly altered gene(s) after metastasis (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S3A</xref>). We found 28 genes with altered expression (greater than two fold, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S3B</xref>). We further narrowed down these 28 candidates using Gene Ontology (GO) analysis with the terms &#x0201c;adhesion&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;signal&#x0201d;, and identified 16 gene candidates (nine downregulated genes and seven up-regulated genes) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). Of note, downregulation of CDH1 (encoding E-cadherin), an indicator of loss of epithelial features [<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], was observed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>), which validates this approach for identifying gene candidates. It seemed likely that one of the seven up-regulated genes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>, right panel) contributed to &#x02018;increased adhesion&#x02019; and &#x02018;increased GSK3&#x003b2; phosphorylation&#x02019;. Thus, we first focused on ITGB3 and ITGB8, which play critical role(s) in mediating adhesive signaling [<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Moreover, there is emerging evidence that integrins are involved in cancer metastasis [<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</p><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Increased integrin &#x003b2;3 expression in TD cells contributes to the activation of Akt-GSK3&#x003b2;-Snail signaling</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) GEO analysis to deduce candidate genes that regulate the distinctive signaling of TD cells. Three independent GSE studies including colon cancer cell (GSE2509), melanoma (GSE8401) and pancreatic cancer cell after TGF&#x003b2; exposure (GSE23952) were used to select out common metastasis-regulating genes. Gene Ontology (GO) with &#x02018;adhesion&#x02019; and &#x02018;signaling&#x02019; was applied to narrow down candidate genes (left) and the gene information is shown in right table. Red and black indicate upregulated or downregulated, respectively. (<bold>B</bold> and <bold>C</bold>) Transcript levels of integrin &#x003b2;3, integrin &#x003b2;8 and integrin &#x003b1;v were analyzed with real-time PCR (B) and validated with immunoblotting against integrin &#x003b1;v or &#x003b2;3 (C). (<bold>D</bold> and <bold>E</bold>) Integrin &#x003b2;3 dependency toward the expression of its downstream signal components was evaluated with siRNA-mediated knockdown (D) and overexpression approach (E). siRNA against integrin &#x003b2;3 was introduced and after 2 day incubation, cell lysate was subjected to immunoblotting (D). And CMV expression vector encoding a human integrin &#x003b2;3 cDNA was transiently introduced and after 48 hours the cell lysate was subjected to immunoblotting (E). (<bold>F</bold>) FAK-dependent expression of Snail was determined. Cells were incubated with PF-562271, a FAK inhibitor, for 24 hours and immunoblotting was performed. (<bold>G</bold>) Contribution of integrin &#x003b2;3 on invasiveness of TD cells was analyzed. TD cells were introduced with siRNA Ctl (siCtl) or siRNA integrin &#x003b2;3 (si&#x003b2;3) and were subjected to invasion assay. Representative images (left) and a bar graph (right), quantifying the invasiveness, are shown. <italic>Columns</italic>, means &#x000b1; SE. *<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; ns, non-significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25366-g005"/></fig><p>As predicted, ITGB3 but not ITGB8 expression was markedly increased in TD cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B and 5C</xref>). Additionally, integrin &#x003b1;v, a counterpart of integrin &#x003b2;3, was also increased in TD cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>), suggesting that the integrin &#x003b1;v&#x003b2;3 complex might be involved in promoting the cancer-associated features of TD cells. It is worth noting that the integrin &#x003b1;v&#x003b2;3 complex is also linked to cancer metastasis [<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p><p>We next monitored phosphorylation of focal adhesion kinase (FAK), which is regulated by integrin engagement and which subsequently activates Akt [<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], in the presence of knockdown or overexpression of integrin &#x003b2;3. As expected, phosphorylation of FAK (at Y397) and subsequent Akt activity were dependent on integrin &#x003b2;3 expression (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D and 5E</xref>). More importantly, Snail protein levels were also markedly reduced as a result of the depletion of integrin &#x003b2;3 in TD cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>) and were increased by ectopic expression of integrin &#x003b2;3 (&#x003b2;3 OE) in A549 control cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5E</xref>). To further confirm the FAK-dependent regulation of Snail protein stabilization, the effect of PF562271, a FAK inhibitor, was evaluated. Consistently, the Snail protein level decreased in parallel with FAK inhibition by PF562271 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5F</xref>). Furthermore, the depletion of Snail (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3E</xref>) or the loss of integrin &#x003b2;3 decreased the invasive capacity of the TD cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5G</xref>). Taken together, these results indicate that a high expression level of integrin &#x003b2;3 contributes to the metastatic potential of TD cells via FAK-Akt-GSK3&#x003b2; axis-dependent stabilization of Snail.</p></sec><sec id="s2_6"><title>Prognostic significance of integrin &#x003b2;3 expression in lung cancer survival</title><p>To examine the prognostic significance of integrin &#x003b2;3 mRNA expression in lung cancer, survival analysis was carried out with a large clinical dataset (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.kmplot.com/">http://www.kmplot.com</ext-link>). The dataset was generated by combining several independent mRNA expression datasets from approximately 1, 700 lung cancer patients [<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Survival analysis was performed on lung adenocarcinoma patients. The lung adenocarcinoma patients were divided into two subgroups, ITGB3-high and ITGB3-low, based on their median expression level of ITGB3. The KM curves showed a significant difference in the probability of both overall survival (<italic>p</italic> value = 4e-04) and first progression survival (<italic>p</italic> value = 0.0002) between the two groups (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). In univariate Cox regression analysis, the estimated hazard ratios for ITGB3-high, compared with ITGB3-low, were 1.52 and 1.44 for overall survival and first progression survival, respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Survival analysis showed that the expression levels of ITGB3 correlated with the prognosis of the lung adenocarcinoma patients, supporting the idea that high integrin &#x003b2;3 expression in TD cells resulting from chronic TGF&#x003b2; exposure (e.g., mesenchymal cancer) is an important determinant of patient survival.</p><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Prognostic significance of integrin &#x003b2;3 expression in lung cancer survival</title><p>(<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) Kaplan-Meier survival analysis and univariate Cox regression analysis were performed according to ITGB3 mRNA expression levels. (A) Overall survival, (B) First progression survival. The end point of first progression survival is the first relapse after surgery. (<bold>C</bold>) The proposed model explaining the signal signature of mesenchymal-type TD cells. Arrowline indicates &#x02018;activation&#x02019;, and perpendicular line indicates &#x02018;inhibition&#x02019;. Dashed arrowline indicates &#x02018;upregulation&#x02019;. P on a red background presents the activating phosphorylation, and P on a blue background presents the inhibitory phosphorylation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25366-g006"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>It is widely accepted that cancer cells become refractory to TGF&#x003b2;-mediated growth suppression and become more aggressive upon chronic exposure to TGF&#x003b2;, once the cancer acquires mesenchymal properties [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]; this favors a TGF&#x003b2;-enriched microenvironment. Therefore, identification of the molecular targets that govern the distinctive TGF&#x003b2; signaling of mesenchymal cancer cells could help develop novel chemotherapeutic approaches to treating cancer.</p><p>To this end, we established a mesenchymal cancer model by exposing A549 tumor cells to chronic TGF&#x003b2; exposure, which resulted in them becoming refractory to TGF&#x003b2;-induced growth arrest and susceptible to TGF&#x003b2;-induced tumor promotion. This model is similar to the irreversible mesenchymal cancer cell model induced by E-cadherin knockdown (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S1</xref>). The &#x02018;chronic TGF&#x003b2; model (TD)&#x02019; is distinguishable from the &#x02018;TGF&#x003b2;-induced EMT model&#x02019; because the latter is achieved by a single treatment with TGF&#x003b2; and its EMT phenotypes are transient [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Based on the roles of Snail in EMT and metastasis [<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] and the poor prognostic outcomes of patients with high mRNA expression of Snail (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S2</xref>), we suggest that the increased Snail protein stability observed within 2 hours after treatment with TGF&#x003b2; (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>), which increased the invasiveness of TD cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D and 3E</xref>), is important for the metastatic potential of mesenchymal cancer cells. Thus, the Akt activity toward GSK3&#x003b2; that leads to Snail protein stabilization could serve as a therapeutic target for reducing metastatic potential (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>). In agreement with this, increased Akt phosphorylation correlates positively with the poor prognosis of non-small cell lung cancer patients [<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], emphasizing the clinical significance of high Akt activity in TD cells.</p><p>We further demonstrated that the increase in the integrin &#x003b2;3 level in several metastatic cancers with low E-cadherin expression, an indicator of loss of epithelial features [<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>), directed the adhesive signal toward the FAK and Akt signaling, which in turn affected Snail protein stability in TD cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). In this regard, Akt inhibitors, such as MK-2206 [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], or the FAK inhibitor, PF-562271 [<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], could be used as starting points for the development of new drugs against mesenchymal cancer.</p><p>Identifying a pivotal signaling molecule that decides the metastatic capacity of a certain type of cancer would be highly advantageous for developing new drug targets. For example, induction of N-acetylgalactosaminyltransferase 14 (GalNAc-T14), whose expression is extremely low in normal lung tissue [<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], in specific types of cancer cells contributes to metastasis through Wnt signaling [<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Thus, a &#x003b2;-catenin inhibitor that abrogates the Wnt-dependent gene responses is highly effective in inhibiting metastasis in GalNAc-T14-expressing cancers [<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Similarly, because its high expression indicates a poor prognostic outcome (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>) and tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) resistance [<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], integrin &#x003b2;3 could serve as an indicator for determining whether or not a therapeutic regimen consisting of Akt or FAK inhibitors would be suitable for the treatment of mesenchymal cancers expressing high levels of Snail protein, as summarized in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6D</xref> [<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p><p>In summary, chronic TGF&#x003b2; promotes the metastatic potential of lung adenocarcinoma by increasing Snail protein stability via its effect on the integrin &#x003b2;3-FAK-Akt-GSK3&#x003b2; signaling axis, suggesting that integrin &#x003b2;3 could be used as an indicator for determining the effectiveness of Akt- or FAK-targeted therapies.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s4"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s4_1"><title>Establishment of TD cells and the use of TGF&#x003b2;1</title><p>To generate transdifferentiated A549 (TD) cells, A549 cells were repeatedly treated with TGF&#x003b2;1 (CYT-716, PROSPEC) at 2 ng/ml concentration every 3 days for 60 days and then TD cells were divided and frozen into a number of vials. For further experiments, newly thawed frozen TD cells were used for 30 days, during which TD cells were also exposed to repetitive TGF&#x003b2; at 2 ng/ml concentration every 3 days, thus 60~90 day TGF&#x003b2;1-exposed TD cells being used in this study. And TGF&#x003b2;1 was used at 5 ng/ml concentration in all experiments with additional TGF&#x003b2;1 treatment.</p></sec><sec id="s4_2"><title>Invasion and migration assay</title><p>For invasion assay, trans-wells (6.5 mm) with 8 &#x003bc;m pore polycarbonate membrane inserts (Corning) were embedded with matrigel (BD) in DMEM. Cells (1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> per well) were added into the Matrigel-embedded inserts (the top chambers) and the inserts were placed into the bottom chambers containing DMEM media. After 24 hours, the membranes were fixed with 4% formaldehyde in PBS for 10 min, and the invading cells on the membranes were stained with 0.1% crystal violet. Wound healing assay was performed in low serum (0.2% FBS) condition. A wound was formed by scratching a confluent cell monolayer and after that the images were taken. Migration area was calculated by subtracting the scratched area from the total area of image.</p></sec><sec id="s4_3"><title>Zymography</title><p>The supernatants of cell culture were concentrated using centricon (Millipore, 30 kDa cut), and added with non-reducing sample buffer (without DTT). The samples were loaded into the SDS-PAGE gel-containing gelatin B (Sigma-Aldrich). After electrophoresis, gel was washed with 2.5% Triton X-100 in Tris-HCL buffer (pH 7.5). Then the gel was incubated with reaction buffer (15 mM Nacl, 10 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> in Tris-HCl butter (pH 7.5)) overnight at room temperature to induce gelatin lysis by MMP9, and then stained with Coomassie brilliant blue for 30 min followed by destaining.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS FIGURES</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25366-s001.pdf" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d36e866" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS AND FUNDING</title><p>This research was supported by Basic Science Research Program through the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by the Ministry of Education (No.2009&#x02013;0093822) and the Ministry of Science, ICT and future Planning (2014R1A2A2A01005970 and 2011&#x02013;0030043).</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST</bold></p><p>The author declares that he has no Conflicts of Interest.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bachman</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Duel nature of TGF-beta signaling: tumor suppressor vs. tumor promoter</article-title><source>Current opinion in oncology</source><year>2005</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15608513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Padua</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Massague</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Roles of TGFbeta in metastasis</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19050696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakefield</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The two faces of transforming growth factor beta in carcinogenesis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>8621</fpage><lpage>8623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12861075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pardali</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Moustakas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Actions of TGF-beta as tumor suppressor and pro-metastatic factor in human cancer</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2007</year><volume>1775</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16904831</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Derynck</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhurst</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Balmain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TGF-beta signaling in tumor suppression and cancer progression</article-title><source>Nature genetics</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11586292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Massague</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TGFbeta in Cancer</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18662538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sjoblom</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedorova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Imreh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Beug</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Moustakas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sustained TGF beta exposure suppresses Smad and non-Smad signalling in mammary epithelial cells, leading to EMT and inhibition of growth arrest and apoptosis</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2008</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1218</fpage><lpage>1230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17724470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Koizumi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Toyoda</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawaguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Imamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic exposure of transforming growth factor beta 1 confers a more aggressive tumor phenotype through downregulation of p21(WAF1/CIP1) in conditionally immortalized pancreatic epithelial cells</article-title><source>Surgery</source><year>2004</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>364</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15300203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Mahony</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamps</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Albo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Isakson</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>DuBois</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Beauchamp</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transformation of intestinal epithelial cells by chronic TGF-beta1 treatment results in downregulation of the type II TGF-beta receptor and induction of cyclooxygenase-2</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>855</fpage><lpage>867</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10023661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bierie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Moses</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tumour microenvironment: TGFbeta: the molecular Jekyll and Hyde of cancer</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>506</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16794634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inactivation of SMAD4 tumor suppressor gene during gastric carcinoma progression</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17200344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heldin</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanlandewijck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moustakas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of EMT by TGFbeta in cancer</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>2012</year><volume>586</volume><fpage>1959</fpage><lpage>1970</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22710176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Non-Smad pathways in TGF-beta signaling</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>128</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19114990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayberry</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Basile</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Aplin</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TWIST1 is an ERK1/2 effector that promotes invasion and regulates MMP-1 expression in human melanoma cells</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>6382</fpage><lpage>6392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23222305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vichalkovski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gresko</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Restuccia</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemmings</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PKB/AKT phosphorylation of the transcription factor Twist-1 at Ser42 inhibits p53 activity in response to DNA damage</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2010</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>3554</fpage><lpage>3565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20400976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunduz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dual regulation of Snail by GSK-3beta-mediated phosphorylation in control of epithelial-mesenchymal transition</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>931</fpage><lpage>940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15448698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Washington</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loss of Smad4 in colorectal cancer induces resistance to 5-fluorouracil through activating Akt pathway</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2014</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>946</fpage><lpage>957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24384683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>ten Dijke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signaling interplay between transforming growth factor-beta receptor and PI3K/AKT pathways in cancer</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>612</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24239264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loss of E-cadherin activates EGFR-MEK/ERK signaling, which promotes invasion via the ZEB1/MMP2 axis in non-small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>2512</fpage><lpage>2522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.1463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24318272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Massague</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Seoane</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wotton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Smad transcription factors</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2005</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2783</fpage><lpage>2810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16322555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moustakas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Souchelnytskyi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Heldin</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Smad regulation in TGF-beta signal transduction</article-title><source>Journal of cell science</source><year>2001</year><volume>114</volume><issue>Pt 24</issue><fpage>4359</fpage><lpage>4369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11792802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Byrne</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Matrix metalloproteinase 9 and the epidermal growth factor signal pathway in operable non-small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>2349</fpage><lpage>2355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10873086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Patnaik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fearen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Olmos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lupinacci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Riisnaes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Heaton</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>First-in-man clinical trial of the oral pan-AKT inhibitor MK-2206 in patients with advanced solid tumors</article-title><source>Journal of clinical oncology</source><year>2011</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>4688</fpage><lpage>4695</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22025163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diehl</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roussel</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherr</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glycogen synthase kinase-3beta regulates cyclin D1 proteolysis and subcellular localization</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1998</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>3499</fpage><lpage>3511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9832503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Doh</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>G-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell-matrix adhesion characterization using multiple shear stress zones in single stepwise microchannel</article-title><source>Applied Physics Letters</source><year>2014</year><fpage>105</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voulgari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pintzas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epithelial-mesenchymal transition in cancer metastasis: mechanisms, markers and strategies to overcome drug resistance in the clinic</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2009</year><volume>1796</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19306912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epithelial-mesenchymal plasticity in carcinoma metastasis</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2013</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>2192</fpage><lpage>2206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24142872</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hynes</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrins: versatility, modulation, and signaling in cell adhesion</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1992</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1555235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganguly</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrins and metastasis</article-title><source>Cell Adh Migr</source><year>2013</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23563505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bendas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Borsig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer cell adhesion and metastasis: selectins, integrins, and the inhibitory potential of heparins</article-title><source>International journal of cell biology</source><year>2012</year><volume>2012</volume><fpage>676731</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22505933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of integrins in tumor invasion and metastasis</article-title><source>Exp Dermatol</source><year>2004</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>663</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15447732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bacac</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamenkovic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metastatic cancer cell</article-title><source>Annu Rev Pathol</source><year>2008</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18233952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Giancotti</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrin signalling during tumour progression</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>816</fpage><lpage>826</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15459662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gyorffy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Surowiak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Budczies</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanczky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Online survival analysis software to assess the prognostic value of biomarkers using transcriptomic data in non-small-cell lung cancer</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e82241</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24367507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Neil</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiemann</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transforming growth factor-beta and the hallmarks of cancer</article-title><source>Cell Signal</source><year>2011</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>951</fpage><lpage>962</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20940046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanahan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hallmarks of cancer: the next generation</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2011</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>646</fpage><lpage>674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21376230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barrallo-Gimeno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieto</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Snail genes as inducers of cell movement and survival: implications in development and cancer</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2005</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>3151</fpage><lpage>3161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15983400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>RX</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphorylated Akt overexpression and loss of PTEN expression in non-small cell lung cancer confers poor prognosis</article-title><source>Lung Cancer</source><year>2006</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16324768</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Golubovskaya</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting FAK in human cancer: from finding to first clinical trials</article-title><source>Frontiers in bioscience</source><year>2014</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>687</fpage><lpage>706</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Padilla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Amler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashkenazi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of immunohistochemistry assays to assess GALNT14 and FUT3/6 in clinical trials of dulanermin and drozitumab</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1587</fpage><lpage>1596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20179215</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GalNAc-T14 promotes metastasis through Wnt dependent HOXB9 expression in lung adenocarcinoma</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.6019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seguin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Desgrosellier</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Weis</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheresh</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrins and cancer</article-title><source>Trends Cell Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25572304</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>