<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Ther Ultrasound</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Ther Ultrasound</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Therapeutic Ultrasound</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2050-5736</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5629772</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">105</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40349-017-0105-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Current and emerging brain applications of MR-guided focused ultrasound </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3180-2404</contrib-id><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Ying</given-names></name><address><email>ying.meng@medportal.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Suppiah</surname><given-names>Suganth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mithani</surname><given-names>Karim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>Benjamin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>Michael L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lipsman</surname><given-names>Nir</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2157 2938</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.17063.33</institution-id><institution>Division of Neurosurgery, Department of Surgery, Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre, </institution><institution>University of Toronto, </institution></institution-wrap>2075 Bayview Avenue, Toronto, ON Canada </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2157 2938</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.17063.33</institution-id><institution>Physical Sciences Platform, Sunnybrook Research Institute, </institution></institution-wrap>Toronto, ON Canada </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>5</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>26</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>MRI guided focused ultrasound is an emerging technique that uses acoustic energy to noninvasively treat intracranial disorders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>At high frequencies, it can be used to raise tissue temperatures and ablate discrete brain targets with sub-millimeter accuracy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>This application is currently under investigation for a broad range of clinical applications, including brain tumors, movement disorders, and psychiatric conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>At low frequencies MRI guided focused ultrasound can be used to modulate neuronal activity and in conjunction with injected microbubbles, can open the blood-brain barrier to enhance the delivery of therapeutic compounds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The last decade has seen dramatic advances in the science of MRI guided focused ultrasound, helping elucidate both its mechanisms and potential in pre-clinical models, and its translational promise across myriad clinical applications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>This review provides an update of current and emerging MRI guided focused ultrasound applications for intracranial disorders and describes future directions and challenges for the field. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Focused ultrasound</kwd><kwd>MRI guided focused ultrasound</kwd><kwd>MRgFUS</kwd><kwd>Neuroablation</kwd><kwd>Blood-brain barrier disruption</kwd><kwd>Neurologic disorders</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par25"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The ability to focus acoustic energy through the intact skull on discrete brain targets has been a goal of ultrasound research for decades. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Early efforts at therapeutic ultrasound in the brain, pioneered by the Fry brothers in the early 1950’s, though successful, required removal of the overlying skull due to the bone’s absorption and reflection of a large portion of ultrasound energy [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In the late 1990s, completely noninvasive treatment was realized with the development of a helmet device lined with multiple independent transducers, and the coupling of FUS to real-time magnetic resonance (MR) image guidance [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The MR guided FUS (MRgFUS) design allowed computer calculated and controlled steering of each element to achieve accurate targeting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The device is further coupled with thermography to allow real-time feedback on the effect of sonications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>In one commercially available design, a spherical helmet device harnesses acoustic energy from over 1000 individual transducer elements operating between 650 and 720 kHz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Currently, the patient’s head must be stabilized in a stereotactic frame and their hair must be shaved to allow good coupling between the transducers and scalp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Other devices may use fewer transducers, as well as the possibility to implant the system in the skull for ongoing ultrasound application [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par26"><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Over the last decade the potential applications of MRgFUS in neurosurgery have significantly expanded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>MRgFUS was recently approved by the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) to perform thalamotomy for patients with medically refractory essential tremor (ET), and is currently under investigation for treatment of brain tumors, as well as treatment resistant psychiatric conditions (Fig. 1) [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a recent cost-effective analysis suggested that MRgFUS may be cost-effective compared to other neuromodulation modalities, such as deep brain stimulation or stereotactic radiosurgery for the treatment of ET [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Currently, there are more than 25 focused ultrasound clinical trials publically registered for patients with neurological disorders ranging from neuro-oncology, Parkinson’s disease, Alzheimer’s disease, obsessive-compulsive disorder, and epilepsy (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>This review provides an update of MRgFUS research in the preclinical and clinical realm within the last decade, and describes the challenges ahead and future directions for the field.Fig. 1Schematic of intracranial regions targeted by MRgFUS in published human studies on an axial T1 and T2 weighted 3 Tesla MR images. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>OCD = obsessive compulsive disorder; MDD = major depressive disorder; PD = Parkinson’s disease; ET = essential tremor; NP = neuropathic pain Table 1List of clinical trials investigating neurological applications of MRgFUS by disorderIndicationStageDescriptionETPhase IINCT02289560 – multi-centered, single arm study to look at efficacy for ETNCT01827904 - prospective, randomized, double blind, crossover, multi-centered, two arm study to test efficacy and further demonstrate safetyPDPhase INCT02347254, NCT01772693, NCT02263885, NCT02246374, NCT02252380 - phase I trial to study unilateral Vim nucleus/subthalamic nucleus/globus pallidus sonication for PDBrain tumor – ablationPhase INCT00147056, NCT02343991, NCT01473485 – phase I trial for tumor ablation, ongoingNCT01698437 – phase I trial for tumor ablation, completed, University Children’s Hospital in ZurichBrain tumor – BBB disruptionPhase INCT02343991 – phase I trial to study BBB opening for delivery of doxorubicinDepression/anxietyPhase INCT02348411 – phase I trial to study safety and initial effectiveness of MRgFUS bilateral anterior capsulotomy in medication-refractory MDDNCT02685488 – phase I trial of right frontotemporal area sonication for mild to moderate depressionOCDPhase INCT01986296 - phase I trial of anterior cingulate cortex, anterior limb of internal capsule, ventral striatum or subgenual cingulate cortex sonicationNCT03156335 - phase I trial to evaluate the safety and efficacy of MRgFUS for patients with treatment-refractory OCDPain syndromesPhase INCT01699477 - phase I trial of thalamic sonication for neuropathic pain, pediatric, University Children’s Hospital in ZurichCentral lateral thalamic nucleus sonication (Neurosurgery Focus 2012)NCT03111277 - phase I trial for MRgFUS thalamotomy of central lateral thalamic nucleusEpilepsy – ablationPhase INCT02804230 – phase I trial, ablation of subcortical focal epileptic targetsEpilepsy - neuromodulationPhase INCT02151175 – phase I trial, stimulation or suppression of neuronal activity in temporal lobeADPhase INCT02986932 – phase I trial of ultrasound mediated BBB opening for ADThrombolysis/ICHPreclinicalSwine and human cadaveric models demonstrated feasibility of ICH liquefaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Rabbit carotid occlusion model demonstrated feasibility of this model for vascular recanalizationCSF diversionPreclinicalProof-of principle study of MRgFUS third ventriculostomyNeuromodulationPhase IVagus nerve modulation can stimulate or dampen neuronal activity ET essential tremor, PD Parkinson’s disease, BBB blood-brain barrier, MDD major depressive disorder, OCD obsessive compulsive disorder, AD Alzheimer’s disease, CSF cerebrospinal fluid, FUS focused ultrasound, ICH intracerebral hemorrhage, NCT national clinical trial (number) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Movement disorders </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par27"><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The application of MRgFUS to movement disorders has been among the most promising to date. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Targets for movement disorder symptoms, such as tremor, are near the geographic center of the skull in key motor relay nuclei, making these amenable to heating with minimal heating of the overlying skull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In addition, the ability to monitor patient symptoms in real-time, and evaluate the impact of a lesion on tremor, provides a powerful behavioral assay on which to base treatment decisions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>To date, essential tremor (ET) and Parkinson’s Disease (PD) have been the primary applications, owing in large part to the large experience with these conditions in the ablative neurosurgical literature. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Essential tremor </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par28"><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Approximately 4% of people over 40 years of age are affected by essential tremor, which is marked by postural and intention tremors of about 4–7 Hz [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In some patients, these tremors can be severe enough to affect daily activities such as eating, drinking, and writing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>15–25% of patients are forced to retire prematurely as a result of ET, and 60% of patients do not apply for jobs or promotions due to uncontrollable shaking [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>First-line therapy for ET is medical, typically with propranolol and primidone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>However, one third of the patients will find the side effects of these medications intolerable or have refractory symptoms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Alternative treatments for ET includes surgical targeting of the ventral intermediate nucleus (Vim) of the thalamus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The Vim is part a circuit that connects the cerebellum with cortical motor pathways important for tremor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>While deep brain stimulation electrodes are implanted bilaterally [8], the target contralateral to the more disabled side is treated in radiofrequency (RF) ablation to minimize severe neurological complications [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>These two modalities are the most well-established interventions in the treatment of ET. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>While they are effective, both involve cranial access, which carries a risk of infection and hemorrhage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The rates of infection, seizures, and intracranial hemorrhage after DBS, which may be taken as correlates to brain penetration, are 1.7%, 1.5% and 3.9% respectively [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Device-related issues such as hardware breakage, mal-placement or migration, and battery depletion make life-long maintenance necessary for DBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Gamma knife radiosurgery is another ablative technique. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Despite being noninvasive, radiosurgery is less favorable because the results are variable and delayed often requiring weeks to months to become noticeable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par29"><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Two pilot studies of focused ultrasound Vim ablation were published in 2013 demonstrating promising clinical results after MRgFUS thalamotomy [11, 12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In one study of fifteen patients, the Clinical Rating Scale for Tremor (CRST) score improved by 74% at 12 months (p = 0.001) and disability score by 85% at 12 months (p = 0.001) [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>A subsequent multicenter randomized sham control trial in 76 patients with ET showed that MRgFUS treatment was superior to placebo with 47% improvement in hand-tremor score at 3 months and 62% reduction in disability score [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>More recently, Zaaroor et al. reported their experience with MRgFUS thalamotomy in thirty patients with tremor across a wide-range of disorders (18 with ET, 9 with PD and 3 with ET-PD) [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>At six-month follow-up, patients with ET had a significant decrease of CRST score from 40.7 to 8.2; patient with PD or ET-PD had a significant decrease in motor component of PDQ-39 from 38.6 to 20.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Quality of Life in Essential Tremor (QUEST) score similarly improved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Common adverse events following MRgFUS thalamotomy include paresthesia, taste disturbances, headaches, and reported sense of imbalance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>While pin site discomfort from the stereotactic frame is common, no infection has been reported so far. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>More serious complications such as ataxia are approximately 1.6% [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Zaaroor et al. reported that all neurological complications improved by three months after treatment [13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Parkinson’s disease </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par30"><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Parkinson’s disease (PD) is the second most common neurodegenerative disorder, with a prevalence of approximately 50 per 100,000 people at 65 years of age [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>PD is characterized by motor symptoms such as tremor, bradykinesia, and rigidity, with tremor present in 50% of patients at the time of diagnosis [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Motor symptoms are caused by the progressive death of dopaminergic neurons in the substantia nigra pars compacta (SN) [16], and although a wide range of medications are used to manage PD, dopamine replacement is the mainstay of treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>For patients who become refractory to medical treatment neurosurgical intervention may be appropriate, targeting critical motor nuclei that are pathophysiologically linked to the core motor symptoms of PD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Currently, the most widely practiced surgical treatment is DBS of subcortical motor structures, the globus pallidus internus (GPi) and subthalamic nucleus (STN) [10, 17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>While DBS is the gold-standard surgical approach to refractory PD that is still responsive to levodopa, the operation may not be suitable for every patient, nor every symptom. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>For example, older patients are often excluded from DBS, and the procedure may not be suitable for those who cannot undergo general anesthesia, or who suffer from levodopa induced dyskinesia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, there is growing interest and experience in MRgFUS for PD, as an alternative to DBS and other open ablative procedures, such as RF pallidotomy [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Various targets have been proposed for MRgFUS ablation to treat tremor-dominant PD in early clinical studies, including the pallidothalamic tract [18], Vim thalamus, [13, 19, 20], and GPi [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The optimal target in PD is unclear, and will depend on the symptomology of the patient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Recent studies in PD patients treated with MRgFUS, report clinical significant improvement in motor symptoms after treatment ranging from 61% reduction in Unified PD Rating Scale (UPDRS) motor score at 3 months for pallidothalamic tractomy [18] to 46.2% at 6 months for Vim thalamotomy [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>However, different methodologies and outcome measures make direct comparison difficult (For detailed discussion see Schlesinger et al. [15]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Future studies will need to compare outcomes after MRgFUS ablation compared to placebo or current surgical treatment options for tremor-dominant PD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par31"><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The potential of low intensity ultrasound in conjunction with microbubbles to safely and transiently open the blood brain barrier (BBB) has also attracted considerable interest by PD researchers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The BBB is the brain’s primary defense against large (&gt; 400 Da) and hydrophilic molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Small molecules and certain drugs can pass through the BBB through diffusion or receptor mediated cellular transport [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>However, the BBB has hampered therapeutic development for various neurological disorders such as PD and Alzheimer’s disease (AD) [23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par32"><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Multiple animal studies have shown that ultrasound mediated BBB disruption is temporary, reversible within hours, and safe to surrounding tissue at appropriately selected ultrasound parameters [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Interactions between ultrasound and pockets of gas or injected microbubbles lead to inertial cavitation, oscillations of the microbubbles, resulting in mechanical force on tight junctions and endothelial cells [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The extent of the BBB opening depends on the microbubbles (e.g. size, conjugates) as well as ultrasound parameters (e.g. intensity, sonication time) [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Preclinical studies ranging from mouse to nonhuman primates have demonstrated the safe delivery of macromolecules [27], viruses [28], and substances as large as cells [29, 30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par33"><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Randomized control trials of direct intraparenchymal inoculation of neurotrophic agents, such as glial cell-derived neurotrophic factor (GDNF), or embryonic dopamine neurons in degenerating dopaminergic pathways have largely failed to date [31–33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>One possible explanation could be inadequate delivery of therapeutic compounds across the blood brain barrier [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>A growing preclinical MRgFUS literature has demonstrated increased intraparenchymal concentration of growth factors, stem cells, and gene therapy after BBB opening [30, 35–37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>In one study, done in a 6-OHDA model of PD, MRgFUS delivery of GDNF resulted in significantly higher levels of dopamine and less abnormal apomorphine-induced rotational behavior than after direct intraparenchymal infusion of GDNF [35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Pain </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par34"><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Neuropathic pain (NP) is complex, multifactorial, and difficult to treat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>NP can originate from a dysfunction in the nervous system due to disease, injury, or iatrogenic causes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Prevalence of chronic pain with neuropathic features in the general population may be as high as 8% [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Primary management includes tricyclic antidepressants (TCAs), selective serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), anti-epileptic medications, and opioids, which may result in intolerable side effects and tolerance over time [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Various surgical strategies have been developed to treat chronic pain, including cordotomy, sympathectomy, myelotomy, dorsal root entry zone lesions, mesencephalotomy, and cingulotomy, depending largely on the nature of the pain, it’s location, and previous treatment attempts [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Ablative procedures in the thalamus have also been performed for several decades [41], and now MRgFUS offers a less invasive alternative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>In one study, central lateral thalamotomy using MRgFUS in 12 patients suffering from chronic medically-refractory NP reported mean pain relief of 57% at 12 months [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Further clinical trials are underway to investigate the effects of MRgFUS thalamotomy for neuropathic pain (NCT01699477). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Obsessive-compulsive disorder </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par35"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) is among the most challenging and debilitating anxiety disorders, with an estimated lifetime prevalence of 1.6% [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>OCD is marked by unwanted intrusive, recurrent, and persistent thoughts, images, or urges that are often accompanied by time-consuming and repetitive behaviors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>OCD has been linked to various neurochemical and neuroanatomical pathways, including hypersensitivity of post-synaptic serotonin receptors, and mutations in serotonin transporter and receptor genes [44–47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, first-line treatment has typically focused on brain chemistry, using selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors or tricyclic antidepressants such as clomipramine, paired with psychotherapeutic interventions, such as exposure and cognitive behavioral therapy [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>However, despite optimal care, up to 30 to 40% of patients remain significantly disabled [49, 50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Recent imaging, preclinical, neuropsychological, and treatment studies have increasingly supported the view that OCD is a disorder of neural circuitry [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>For treatment resistant patients, therefore, surgical approaches which target specific brain regions and circuitry, may be an emerging option. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par36"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The anterior limb of the internal capsule (ALIC) has been closely associated with the surgical management of refractory OCD [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The ALIC contains a rich network of fibers that connect both the prefrontal cortex and anterior cingulate cortex with the hippocampus, amygdala, and thalamus [53–55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Disruption of these tracts is believed to be important in treating refractory OCD, by disrupting limbic cortico-thalamic fibers affecting depression and anxiety and influencing circuits critical for emotion and affective processing [53–57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>A meta-analysis of DBS and open label prospective anterior capsulotomy studies in patients with refractory OCD found a 51% reduction on the Yale-Brown Obsessive Compulsive Scale (Y-BOCS) after ablation (radiofrequency and gamma-knife radiosurgery) compared to 40% after DBS [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, individuals who underwent the ablative therapy were 9% more likely to go into remission than DBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>A recent systematic review of eight observational studies with a total of 112 patients after AC showed a mean reduction of 55% on the Y-BOCS at 12 months, superior to results from meta-analysis of outcomes after dorsal anterior cingulotomy [59]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par37"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Non-invasive approaches to capsulotomy include gamma knife radiosurgery (GKRS) and MRgFUS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>GKRS uses ionizing radiation for incision-less ablation, but results have a latency period of weeks to months [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Additional concerns about exposure to ionizing radiation include risk of neoplasm and injuries to off target structures [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The effect of MRgFUS is immediate, permitting real-time monitoring of the lesion and the temperature required to achieve it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Jung et al. reported the proof-of-concept study of bilateral thermal capsulotomy using MRgFUS in four patients with medically refractory OCD [62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Gradual improvements in Y-BOCS score were noted over 6 months, with an ultimate mean improvement of 33%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>These patients also had comorbid major depressive disorder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Over the same period, patients experienced sustained reductions in symptoms of depression (mean 61.1%) and anxiety (mean 69.4%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>No adverse effects or significant differences in neuropsychological test scores were noted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>This result is promising, but durability of the outcome, cumulative safety profile, and its value over placebo or traditional nonablative methods (e.g. DBS) and ablative methods (e.g. GKRS) will require further investigations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par38"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The development of MRgFUS ablation as a therapy for other psychiatric illnesses are also underway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The first MRgFUS procedure for treatment-resistant major depressive disorder (MDD) showed initial safety and improvement in the Hamilton Depression Rating Scale score from 26 pre-procedure to 7 at 12 months, Beck Depression Inventory score from 26 to 12 at 12 months [63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The lesion target for treatment-resistant MDD is also ALIC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>This single case report demonstrated marked clinical improvement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Two clinical trials (NCT02348411, NCT02685488) are currently underway to further define the role of ultrasound in depression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Brain tumors </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par39"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The most common brain tumors, metastatic and glioblastoma multiforme (GBM), have prognoses of 3 [64] and 4 months survival, respectively, if left untreated [65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Indeed, despite advances in genetics and concerted multidisciplinary efforts in developing new therapeutics, the gains in patient survival have been modest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>With modern treatment, the median overall survival of patients with GBM is only 14.6 months [66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Tumors in eloquent or deep brain regions are poor candidates for surgical resection and, though traditionally treated with radiotherapy, may benefit from alternative modalities now under investigation, including proton beam radiation and laser interstitial thermal therapy (LITT) [67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>MRgFUS may represent an additional option. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Ablation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par40"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Focused ultrasound thermoablation of bone metastases, prostate cancer, and uterine fibroids are approved by the FDA [34, 68, 69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>At temperatures above approximately 55 °C, tumor tissue shows homogenous coagulative necrosis leading to irreversible cell death [70]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Early clinical studies of MRgFUS thermoablation for brain tumors have predominantly focused on high-grade gliomas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>McDannold et al. published the first experience with sonication of high-grade glioma through the intact skull [71]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>While the procedure proceeded without any complications seen in previous studies (e.g. thermal injury in the pre-tumor area), coagulative necrosis was not achieved due to insufficient power. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>As such, the adjustments including doubling the number of transducer elements, decreasing the frequency from 650 kHz to 230 kHz and increasing the power capabilities were made to the system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, the fourth patient suffered a post procedure intracranial hemorrhage, which was linked to possible underlying coagulopathy and inertial cavitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>This complication highlighted the challenges of ablating a large volume and vascular neoplastic tissue as well as greater attention to patients or pathologies with increased risk of hemorrhage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Currently phase I trials (NCT01698437, NCT00147056, NCT01473485) are underway with results pending. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par41"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Targets located close to the skull are difficult to thermoablate without unacceptable rise in temperature in bone, scalp, or neighboring neurovascular structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Recently, two proof of concept animal studies of non-thermal ablation of skull base lesions were reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>McDannold et al. demonstrated that low-duty cycle sonication at 525 kHz with intravenously injected microbubbles can produce lesions at the skull base close to the optical nerve in rats [72]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Sonicated microbubbles undergo inertial cavitation, leading to vascular injuries and ischemic necrosis in the target. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Evidence from histology and evoked potential data supports preservation of the optic nerve. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>This study was replicated in nonhuman primates using MRgFUS operating at 220 kHz, low duty cycles and intravenous Definity® microbubble contrast [73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>However, off-target effects included unintentional BBB opening, particularly in the pre-tumor area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Further safety studies are necessary to examine the tradeoff to this approach, a greater risk of inertial cavitation along the acoustic path [74]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Blood brain barrier disruption for chemotherapy delivery </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par42"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>While tumor cells can break down the blood barrier, they also infiltrate into surrounding tissue resulting in angiogenesis and blood vessels with an intact BBB [75]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>A majority of chemotherapies have limited bioavailability in the brain and tumor tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Additionally, while targeted therapies for specific cancers (e.g. trastuzumab for HER2 positive breast cancer and vemurafenib, BRAF kinase inhibitor, for melanoma) have dramatically changed the prognosis of patients without intracranial metastasis, these drugs poorly penetrate the BBB [76, 77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>As a result, several attempts have been made to couple chemotherapy with transient opening of the BBB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>For example, simultaneous intra-arterial administration of mannitol and carboplatin or bevacizumab infusion has been examined in early clinical trials to treat high grade gliomas [78]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>In addition to mixed and modest outcomes, patients were exposed to potential complications from the endovascular procedure and neurotoxicity from nonspecific brain uptake of the chemotherapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>MRgFUS offers a less invasive approach to open the BBB transiently with enhanced spatial and temporal specificity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par43"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>An early animal study demonstrated successful and safe delivery of trastuzumab in mouse [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In another study, ultrasound mediated BBB opening plus temozolomide (TMZ) administration compared to TMZ alone in rats with implanted 9 L glioma cells reduced 7-day tumor progression and extended median survival from 20 to 23 days [79]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>CSF-to-plasma ratio of TMZ level was increased by 1.7 times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>In another study, eight treatments of ultrasound delivered NK-95 cells in mice injected with human HER2-expressing breast tumor resulted in an increase in overall survival from approximately 50 to 150 days [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>As the result of compelling preclinical data, a pilot trial is underway to investigate safety and feasibility of ultrasound mediated BBB disruption for patients with high-grade gliomas to deliver TMZ (NCT02343991). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Alzheimer’s disease </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par44"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Alzheimer’s disease (AD) is the most common neurodegenerative disease, affecting more than five million people in the United States, and increasing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The pathologic hallmarks of AD consist of beta-amyloid plaques and neurofibrillary tangles resulting in synaptic dysfunction and neurodegeneration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Current FDA approved medications, anti-cholinesterase inhibitors and NMDA receptor antagonist, have only modest clinical benefit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, biologic agents, such as bapineuzumab and solanezumab, aim to improve clearance of Aβ plaques and oligomers [80]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>While they have proven to be effective both histologically and behaviorally in animal models and early clinical trials, there has yet to be an immunotherapy proven to be clinically effective in phase 3 clinical trials [81, 82]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par45"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>As with PD and Brain tumors, the BBB is a major obstacle to the effective delivery of potential therapeutic compounds to AD brains, and MRgFUS has been explored as a possible means to overcome it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>In a transgenic mouse model of AD, treated with ultrasound delivered, anti-BAM, an antibody against Ab plaque, to a single hemisphere results in a reduction of plaque number and surface area by more than 20% compared to the contralateral hemisphere after four days [83]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>After treatment, transgenic animals performed as well as wild-type animals on the Y maze task, suggesting a rescue of spatial memory deficits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, BBB opening alone also led to a significant plaque reduction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Increased endogenous IgG and IgM antibodies bound to beta amyloid plaques and glial activation after BBB opening suggests that the influx of endogenous antibodies can lead to activation of the innate immune system against the pathologic plaques. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Moreover, an increased hippocampal neurogenesis was found after sonication, which may also contribute to the memory rescue. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par46"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Reductions in plaque number and surface area after ultrasound mediated BBB opening alone were replicated by another research group in APP23 transgenic mouse line [84], along with behavioral improvement as well as a five-fold reduction of Aβ monomer and two-fold reduction of Aβ trimer, which may have an even greater role in AD pathogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>More recently, the same group demonstrated ultrasound delivered RN2N, an antibody to tau, reduced phosphorylated tau levels in a transgenic TauP301L mouse [85]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The presence of neurofibrillary tangles and hyper-phosphorylated tau are closely correlated with the progression of cognitive deficits in patients with AD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>An ongoing phase I trial will study the feasibility and safety of BBB opening in patients with mild Alzheimer’s disease (NCT02986932). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Conclusion and future directions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par47"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>MRI guided focused ultrasound can be used at high and low intensities for neuroablation, opening the BBB and potentially neuromodulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>We reviewed the clinical applications of neuroablation and BBB opening that are established or currently under investigation in human studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Although promising, several challenges exist for brain applications of MRgFUS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>For example, targets close to the skull are challenging to treat with high frequencies, given the bone heating that results from the large amount 0of energy necessary to achieve coagulative necrosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Non-thermal ablation may circumvent this problem [72], although the experience is preliminary and can be associated with unintended off-target changes (e.g. BBB opening) [6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par48"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Further, the relative efficacy of MRgFUS ablation for tremor, and other indications such as OCD, compared to traditional open surgical approaches will need to await longer follow-up and larger clinical experiences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Current treatment times require several hours in the MRI machine, and improvements in sonication protocol and workflow are needed to decrease treatment time and enhance tolerability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Similarly, technologic advances eliminating the need for complete head shave and the use of a stereotactic frame, will contribute to making the procedure more tolerable for patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par49"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Basic scientists will continue to study how ultrasound interacts with tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Questions exist as to the chronic changes to the neurovascular unit after BBB opening and how they will affect repeat treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>A recent study reported that ultrasound mediated BBB opening leads to a sterile inflammatory reaction [86]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Although inflammation is expected after mechanical opening of the BBB and may in fact contribute to clearance of beta amyloid plaques, further studies are needed to quantify the cellular and molecular genetics changes from BBB opening at minimal energy settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>On the clinical front, researchers are exploring the potential of combining MRgFUS mediated BBB opening with drugs or biologic agents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>In doing so, FUS could be a valuable tool in treating a wide range of neurological conditions, such as neurodegenerative diseases and demyelinating diseases, but phase I studies will need to first establish the safety and feasibility of BBB opening in these populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>As research teams are poised to translate existing animal data to human studies in the next decade, there remains promise that intracranial MRgFUS can have an increasingly important role in the management of the most challenging brain conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AD</term><def><p id="Par2">Alzheimer’s disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BBB</term><def><p id="Par3">blood brain barrier</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CRST</term><def><p id="Par4">clinical rating scale for tremor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DBS</term><def><p id="Par5">deep brain stimulation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ET</term><def><p id="Par6">essential tremor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FUS</term><def><p id="Par7">focused ultrasound</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GDNF</term><def><p id="Par8">glial cell line derived neurotrophic factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GKRS</term><def><p id="Par9">gamma knife radiosurgery</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GPi</term><def><p id="Par10">globus pallidus interna</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HER2</term><def><p id="Par11">human epidermal growth factor receptor 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LITT</term><def><p id="Par12">laser interstitial thermal therapy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MDD</term><def><p id="Par13">major depressive disorder</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MRgFUS</term><def><p id="Par14">magnetic resonance image guided focused ultrasound</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NP</term><def><p id="Par15">neuropathic pain</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OCD</term><def><p id="Par16">obsessive compulsive disorder</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PD</term><def><p id="Par17">Parkinson’s disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>QUEST</term><def><p id="Par18">quality of life in essential tremor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RF</term><def><p id="Par19">radiofrequency</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SN</term><def><p id="Par20">substantia nigra</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TMZ</term><def><p id="Par21">temozolomide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UPDRS</term><def><p id="Par22">unified Parkinson’s disease rating scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Vim</term><def><p id="Par23">ventral immediate nucleus of the thalamus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Y-BOCS</term><def><p id="Par24">Yale-Brown Obsessive Compulsive Scale</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Available data and materials</title><p id="Par50"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Not applicable. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par51"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>No funding was used for the creation of this manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></ack></SecTag><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>MLS, NL, and YM conceived of the idea for this manuscript. All authors contributed to writing of the manuscript. YM, KM, and BS helped format the table and figure. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par52">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par53">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par54">Dr. Lipsman has served as a paid consultant on expert steering committees for Focused Ultrasound Foundation, which is a non-profit organization that promotes the use of image-guided focused ultrasound. YM, SS, KM, BS, and MLS have no conflicts of interest or financial disclosures.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher’s Note</title><p id="Par55">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>1.FryWJUltrasound in neurologyNeurology1956669370410.1212/WNL.6.10.693<?supplied-pmid 13369651?>13369651 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>2.HynynenKJoleszFADemonstration of potential noninvasive ultrasound brain therapy through an intact skullUltrasound Med Biol19982427528310.1016/S0301-5629(97)00269-X<?supplied-pmid 9550186?>9550186 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>3.CarpentierACanneyMVignotAReinaVBeccariaKHorodyckidCClinical trial of blood-brain barrier disruption by pulsed ultrasoundSci Transl Med20168343re210.1126/scitranslmed.aaf6086<?supplied-pmid 27306666?>27306666 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>4.EliasWJLipsmanNOndoWGGhanouniPKimYGLeeWA randomized trial of focused ultrasound thalamotomy for essential tremorN Engl J Med201637573073910.1056/NEJMoa1600159<?supplied-pmid 27557301?>27557301 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>5.RavikumarVKParkerJJHornbeckTSSantiniVEPaulyKBWintermarkMCost-effectiveness of focused ultrasound, radiosurgery, and DBS for essential tremorMov Disord Off J Mov Disord Soc20173281165117310.1002/mds.26997 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>6.Louis ED, Ferreira JJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="?"><plain>How common is the most common adult movement disorder? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Update on the worldwide prevalence of essential tremor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Mov Disord Off J Mov. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Disord. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Soc 2010;25:534–541. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>7.LouisEDTreatment of essential tremor: Are there issues we are overlooking?Front Neurol2011291<?supplied-pmid 22275907?>22275907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>8.YuHNeimatJSThe treatment of movement disorders by deep brain stimulationNeurother J Am Soc Exp Neurother20085263610.1016/j.nurt.2007.10.072 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>9.NiranjanARajuSSKooshkabadiAMonacoEFlickingerJCLunsfordLDStereotactic radiosurgery for essential tremor: Retrospective analysis of a 19-year experienceMov Disord Off J Mov Disord Soc201732576977710.1002/mds.26925 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>10.Kleiner-FismanGHerzogJFismanDNTammaFLyonsKEPahwaRSubthalamic nucleus deep brain stimulation: summary and meta-analysis of outcomesMov Disord Off J Mov Disord Soc200621Suppl 14S290S30410.1002/mds.20962 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>11.EliasWJHussDVossTLoombaJKhaledMZadicarioEA pilot study of focused ultrasound thalamotomy for essential tremorN Engl J Med201336964064810.1056/NEJMoa1300962<?supplied-pmid 23944301?>23944301 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>12.LipsmanNSchwartzMLHuangYLeeLSankarTChapmanMMR-guided focused ultrasound thalamotomy for essential tremor: a proof-of-concept studyLancet Neurol20131246246810.1016/S1474-4422(13)70048-6<?supplied-pmid 23523144?>23523144 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>13.Zaaroor M, Sinai A, Goldsher D, Eran A, Nassar M, Schlesinger I. Magnetic resonance-guided focused ultrasound thalamotomy for tremor: a report of 30 Parkinson’s disease and essential tremor cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>J Neurosurg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>2017;1–9. doi:10.3171/2016.10.JNS16758. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>14.PostumaRBBergDAdvances in markers of prodromal Parkinson diseaseNat Rev Neurol20161262263410.1038/nrneurol.2016.152<?supplied-pmid 27786242?>27786242 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>15.SchlesingerISinaiAZaaroorMMRI-guided focused ultrasound in Parkinson’s disease: a reviewPark Dis201720178124624 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>16.KaliaLVLangAEParkinson’s diseaseLancet201538689691210.1016/S0140-6736(14)61393-3<?supplied-pmid 25904081?>25904081 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>17.VolkmannJAlbaneseAKulisevskyJTornqvistA-LHouetoJ-LPidouxBLong-term effects of pallidal or subthalamic deep brain stimulation on quality of life in Parkinson’s diseaseMov Disord2009241154116110.1002/mds.22496<?supplied-pmid 19412954?>19412954 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>18.MagaraABühlerRMoserDKowalskiMPourtehraniPJeanmonodDFirst experience with MR-guided focused ultrasound in the treatment of Parkinson’s diseaseJ Ther Ultrasound201421110.1186/2050-5736-2-11<?supplied-pmid 25512869?>25512869 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>19.SchlesingerIEranASinaiAErikhINassarMGoldsherDMRI guided focused ultrasound thalamotomy for moderate-to-severe tremor in Parkinson’s DiseasePark Dis20152015e219149 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>20.BondAEDallapiazzaRHussDWarrenALSperlingSGwinnR132 A randomized, sham-controlled trial of transcranial magnetic resonance-guided focused ultrasound thalamotomy trial for the treatment of tremor-dominant, idiopathic Parkinson DiseaseNeurosurgery201663Suppl 115410.1227/01.neu.0000489702.18785.5f<?supplied-pmid 27399411?>27399411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>21.NaYCChangWSJungHHKweonEJChangJWUnilateral magnetic resonance-guided focused ultrasound pallidotomy for Parkinson diseaseNeurology20158554955110.1212/WNL.0000000000001826<?supplied-pmid 26180137?>26180137 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>22.PardridgeWMCSF, blood-brain barrier, and brain drug deliveryExpert Opin Drug Deliv20161396397510.1517/17425247.2016.1171315<?supplied-pmid 27020469?>27020469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>23.DesaiBSMonahanAJCarveyPMHendeyBBlood–brain barrier pathology in Alzheimer’s and Parkinson’s disease: implications for drug therapyCell Transplant20071628529910.3727/000000007783464731<?supplied-pmid 17503739?>17503739 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>24.HynynenKMcDannoldNVykhodtsevaNRaymondSWeisslederRJoleszFAFocal disruption of the blood–brain barrier due to 260-kHz ultrasound bursts: a method for molecular imaging and targeted drug deliveryJ Neurosurg200610544545410.3171/jns.2006.105.3.445<?supplied-pmid 16961141?>16961141 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>25.BurgessAShahKHoughOHynynenKFocused ultrasound-mediated drug delivery through the blood-brain barrierExpert Rev Neurother20151547749110.1586/14737175.2015.1028369<?supplied-pmid 25936845?>25936845 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>26.ChenHKonofagouEEThe size of blood-brain barrier opening induced by focused ultrasound is dictated by the acoustic pressureJ Cereb Blood Flow Metab Off J Int Soc Cereb Blood Flow Metab2014341197120410.1038/jcbfm.2014.71 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>27.KinoshitaMMcDannoldNJoleszFAHynynenKNoninvasive localized delivery of Herceptin to the mouse brain by MRI-guided focused ultrasound-induced blood-brain barrier disruptionProc Natl Acad Sci U S A2006103117191172310.1073/pnas.0604318103<?supplied-pmid 16868082?>16868082 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>28.ThévenotEJordãoJFO’ReillyMAMarkhamKWengY-QFoustKDTargeted delivery of self-complementary adeno-associated virus serotype 9 to the brain, using magnetic resonance imaging-guided focused ultrasoundHum Gene Ther2012231144115510.1089/hum.2012.013<?supplied-pmid 22838844?>22838844 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>29.AlkinsRBurgessAKerbelRWelsWSHynynenKEarly treatment of HER2-amplified brain tumors with targeted NK-92 cells and focused ultrasound improves survivalNeuro-Oncol20161897498110.1093/neuonc/nov318<?supplied-pmid 26819443?>26819443 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>30.BurgessAAyala-GrossoCAGangulyMJordãoJFAubertIHynynenKTargeted delivery of neural stem cells to the brain using MRI-guided focused ultrasound to disrupt the blood-brain barrierPLoS One20116e2787710.1371/journal.pone.0027877<?supplied-pmid 22114718?>22114718 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>31.LangAEGillSPatelNKLozanoANuttJGPennRRandomized controlled trial of intraputamenal glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor infusion in Parkinson diseaseAnn Neurol20065945946610.1002/ana.20737<?supplied-pmid 16429411?>16429411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>32.Warren OlanowCBartusRTBaumannTLFactorSBoulisNStacyMGene delivery of neurturin to putamen and substantia nigra in Parkinson disease: a double-blind, randomized, controlled trialAnn Neurol20157824825710.1002/ana.24436<?supplied-pmid 26061140?>26061140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>33.FreedCRGreenePEBreezeRETsaiWYDuMouchelWKaoRTransplantation of embryonic dopamine neurons for severe Parkinson’s diseaseN Engl J Med200134471071910.1056/NEJM200103083441002<?supplied-pmid 11236774?>11236774 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>34.ArrigoniFBarileAZugaroLSpendingADi CesareECaranciFIntra-articular benign bone lesions treated with Magnetic Resonance-guided Focused Ultrasound (MRgFUS): imaging follow-up and clinical resultsMed Oncol Northwood Lond Engl2017345510.1007/s12032-017-0904-7 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>35.FanC-HTingC-YLinC-YChanH-LChangY-CChenY-YNoninvasive, targeted, and non-viral ultrasound-mediated GDNF-plasmid delivery for treatment of Parkinson’s DiseaseSci Rep201661957910.1038/srep19579<?supplied-pmid 26786201?>26786201 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>36.SamiotakiGAcostaCWangSKonofagouEEEnhanced delivery and bioactivity of the neurturin neurotrophic factor through focused ultrasound—mediated blood–brain barrier opening in vivoJ Cereb Blood Flow Metab20153561162210.1038/jcbfm.2014.236<?supplied-pmid 25586140?>25586140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>37.MeadBPKimNMillerGWHodgesDMastorakosPKlibanovALNovel focused ultrasound gene therapy approach noninvasively restores dopaminergic neuron function in a rat Parkinson’s disease modelNano Lett2017173533354210.1021/acs.nanolett.7b00616<?supplied-pmid 28511006?>28511006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>38.TorranceNSmithBHBennettMILeeAJThe epidemiology of chronic pain of predominantly neuropathic origin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Results from a general population surveyJ Pain Off J Am Pain Soc2006728128910.1016/j.jpain.2005.11.008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>39.DworkinRHO’ConnorABBackonjaMFarrarJTFinnerupNBJensenTSPharmacologic management of neuropathic pain: evidence-based recommendationsPain200713223725110.1016/j.pain.2007.08.033<?supplied-pmid 17920770?>17920770 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>40.GillerCAThe neurosurgical treatment of painArch Neurol2003601537154010.1001/archneur.60.11.1537<?supplied-pmid 14623724?>14623724 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>41.YoungRFVermeulenSSGrimmPPosewitzAEJacquesDBRandRWGamma Knife thalamotomy for the treatment of persistent painStereotact Funct Neurosurg199564Suppl 117218110.1159/000098777<?supplied-pmid 8584825?>8584825 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>42.JeanmonodDWernerBMorelAMichelsLZadicarioESchiffGTranscranial magnetic resonance imaging-guided focused ultrasound: noninvasive central lateral thalamotomy for chronic neuropathic painNeurosurg Focus201232E110.3171/2011.10.FOCUS11248<?supplied-pmid 22208894?>22208894 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>43.KesslerRCBerglundPDemlerOJinRMerikangasKRWaltersEELifetime prevalence and age-of-onset distributions of DSM-IV disorders in the national comorbidity survey replicationArch Gen Psychiatry20056259310.1001/archpsyc.62.6.593<?supplied-pmid 15939837?>15939837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>44.HuX-ZLipskyRHZhuGAkhtarLATaubmanJGreenbergBDSerotonin transporter promoter gain-of-function genotypes are linked to obsessive-compulsive disorderAm J Hum Genet20067881582610.1086/503850<?supplied-pmid 16642437?>16642437 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>45.Raz Gross, Yehuda Sasson, Miriam Chopra, Joseph Zohar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Biological models of obsessive-compulsive disorder: the serotonin hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>In: Richard P. Swinson, Martin M. Antony, S. Rachman MAR, editor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Obsessive-Compuls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Disord. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Theory Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Treat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>New York: Guilford Press; 2001. p. 141–53. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>46.DickelDEVeenstra-VanderWeeleJBivensNCWuXFischerDJVan Etten-LeeMAssociation studies of serotonin system candidate genes in early-onset obsessive-compulsive disorderBiol Psychiatry20076132232910.1016/j.biopsych.2006.09.030<?supplied-pmid 17241828?>17241828 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>47.ChakrabartyKBhattacharyyaSChristopherRKhannaSGlutamatergic dysfunction in OCDNeuropsychopharmacology2005301735174010.1038/sj.npp.1300733<?supplied-pmid 15841109?>15841109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>48.FranklinMEFoaEBTreatment of obsessive compulsive disorderAnnu Rev Clin Psychol2011722924310.1146/annurev-clinpsy-032210-104533<?supplied-pmid 21443448?>21443448 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>49.BlochMHLanderos-WeisenbergerAKelmendiBCoricVBrackenMBLeckmanJFA systematic review: antipsychotic augmentation with treatment refractory obsessive-compulsive disorderMol Psychiatry20061162263210.1038/sj.mp.4001823<?supplied-pmid 16585942?>16585942 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>50.AtmacaMTreatment-refractory obsessive compulsive disorderProg Neuro-Psychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry20167012713310.1016/j.pnpbp.2015.12.004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>51.InselTCuthbertBGarveyMHeinssenRPineDSQuinnKResearch domain criteria (RDoC): toward a new classification framework for research on mental disordersAm J Psychiatry201016774875110.1176/appi.ajp.2010.09091379<?supplied-pmid 20595427?>20595427 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>52.Talairach J, Hecaen H, David M. Lobotomie préfrontale limitée par électro-coagulation des fibres thalamo-frontales à leur émergence du bras antérieur de la capsule interne. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>4e Congr Neurol Intern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Paris II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>1949;141. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>53.ScovilleWBSelective cortical undercutting as a means of modifying and studying frontal lobe function in manJ Neurosurg19496657310.3171/jns.1949.6.1.0065<?supplied-pmid 18106833?>18106833 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>54.KellyDPsychosurgery and the limbic systemPostgrad Med J19734982583310.1136/pgmj.49.578.825<?supplied-pmid 4618902?>4618902 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>55.ChristmasDEljamelMSButlerSHazariHMacVicarRSteeleJDLong term outcome of thermal anterior capsulotomy for chronic, treatment refractory depressionJ Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry20118259460010.1136/jnnp.2010.217901<?supplied-pmid 21172856?>21172856 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>56.HurwitzTAHoneyCRAllenJGosselinCHewkoRMartzkeJBilateral anterior capsulotomy for intractable depressionJ Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci20122417618210.1176/appi.neuropsych.11080189<?supplied-pmid 22772665?>22772665 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>57.PapezJWA proposed mechanism of emotion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>1937 [classical article]J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci1995710311210.1176/jnp.7.1.103<?supplied-pmid 7711480?>7711480 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>58.PepperJHarizMZrinzoLDeep brain stimulation versus anterior capsulotomy for obsessive-compulsive disorder: a review of the literatureJ Neurosurg20151221028103710.3171/2014.11.JNS132618<?supplied-pmid 25635480?>25635480 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>59.BrownLTMikellCBYoungermanBEZhangYMcKhannGMShethSADorsal anterior cingulotomy and anterior capsulotomy for severe, refractory obsessive-compulsive disorder: a systematic review of observational studiesJ Neurosurg2016124778910.3171/2015.1.JNS14681<?supplied-pmid 26252455?>26252455 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>60.Ganz JC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Gamma knife neurosurgery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>New York: Springer; 2011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>61.RückCKarlssonASteeleJDEdmanGMeyersonBAEricsonKCapsulotomy for obsessive-compulsive disorderArch Gen Psychiatry20086591410.1001/archpsyc.65.8.914<?supplied-pmid 18678796?>18678796 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>62.JungHHKimSJRohDChangJGChangWSKweonEJBilateral thermal capsulotomy with MR-guided focused ultrasound for patients with treatment-refractory obsessive-compulsive disorder: a proof-of-concept studyMol Psychiatry2015201205121110.1038/mp.2014.154<?supplied-pmid 25421403?>25421403 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>63.Kim M, Kim C-H, Jung HH, Kim SJ, Chang JW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Treatment of major depressive disorder via magnetic resonance-guided focused ultrasound surgery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Biol Psychiatry; 2017. doi:10.1016/j.biopsych.2017.05.008. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>64.NussbaumESDjalilianHRChoKHHallWABrain metastases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Histology, multiplicity, surgery, and survivalCancer1996781781178810.1002/(SICI)1097-0142(19961015)78:8&lt;1781::AID-CNCR19&gt;3.0.CO;2-U<?supplied-pmid 8859192?>8859192 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>65.AdamsonCKanuOOMehtaAIDiCLinNMattoxAKGlioblastoma multiforme: a review of where we have been and where we are goingExpert Opin Investig Drugs2009181061108310.1517/13543780903052764<?supplied-pmid 19555299?>19555299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>66.TranBRosenthalMASurvival comparison between glioblastoma multiforme and other incurable cancersJ Clin Neurosci20101741742110.1016/j.jocn.2009.09.004<?supplied-pmid 20167494?>20167494 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>67.MissiosSBekelisKBarnettGHRenaissance of laser interstitial thermal ablationNeurosurg Focus201538E1310.3171/2014.12.FOCUS14762<?supplied-pmid 25727222?>25727222 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>68.GuanLXuGDamage effect of high-intensity focused ultrasound on breast cancer tissues and their vascularitiesWorld J Surg Oncol20161415310.1186/s12957-016-0908-3<?supplied-pmid 27230124?>27230124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>69.ChaussyCGThüroffSHigh-intensity focused ultrasound for the treatment of prostate cancer: a reviewJ Endourol201731S30S3710.1089/end.2016.0548<?supplied-pmid 28355119?>28355119 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>70.DewhirstMWVigliantiBLLora-MichielsMHansonMHoopesPJBasic principles of thermal dosimetry and thermal thresholds for tissue damage from hyperthermiaInt J Hyperth Off J Eur Soc Hyperthermic Oncol North Am Hyperth Group20031926729410.1080/0265673031000119006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>71.McDannoldNClementGTBlackPJoleszFHynynenKTranscranial magnetic resonance imaging- guided focused ultrasound surgery of brain tumors: initial findings in 3 patientsNeurosurgery20106632333210.1227/01.NEU.0000360379.95800.2F<?supplied-pmid 20087132?>20087132 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>72.McDannoldNZhangY-ZPowerCJoleszFVykhodtsevaNNonthermal ablation with microbubble-enhanced focused ultrasound close to the optic tract without affecting nerve function: Laboratory investigationJ Neurosurg2013119120810.3171/2013.8.JNS122387<?supplied-pmid 24010975?>24010975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>73.ArvanitisCDVykhodtsevaNJoleszFLivingstoneMMcDannoldNCavitation-enhanced nonthermal ablation in deep brain targets: feasibility in a large animal modelJ Neurosurg20151241450145910.3171/2015.4.JNS142862<?supplied-pmid 26381252?>26381252 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>74.TopCBWhitePJMcDannoldNJNonthermal ablation of deep brain targets: a simulation study on a large animal modelMed Phys20164387088210.1118/1.4939809<?supplied-pmid 26843248?>26843248 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>75.QuailDFJoyceJAThe microenvironmental landscape of brain tumorsCancer Cell20173132634110.1016/j.ccell.2017.02.009<?supplied-pmid 28292436?>28292436 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>76.RochetNMDroncaRSKottschadeLAChavanRNGormanBGilbertsonJRMelanoma brain metastases and vemurafenib: need for further investigationMayo Clin Proc20128797698110.1016/j.mayocp.2012.07.006<?supplied-pmid 23036672?>23036672 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>77.PestalozziBCBrignoliSTrastuzumab in CSFJ Clin Oncol Off J Am Soc Clin Oncol2000182349235110.1200/JCO.2000.18.11.2349 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>78.BurkhardtJ-KRiinaHAShinBJMoliternoJAHofstetterCPBoockvarJAIntra-arterial chemotherapy for malignant gliomas: a critical analysisInterv Neuroradiol20111728629510.1177/159101991101700302<?supplied-pmid 22005689?>22005689 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR79"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>79.WeiK-CChuP-CWangH-YJHuangC-YChenP-YTsaiH-CFocused ultrasound-induced blood–brain barrier opening to enhance temozolomide delivery for glioblastoma treatment: a preclinical studyPLoS One20138e5899510.1371/journal.pone.0058995<?supplied-pmid 23527068?>23527068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR80"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="?"><plain>80.KarranEDe StrooperBThe amyloid cascade hypothesis: are we poised for success or failure? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>JNeurochem2016139Suppl 223725210.1111/jnc.13632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR81"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>81.SallowaySSperlingRFoxNCBlennowKKlunkWRaskindMTwo phase 3 trials of bapineuzumab in mild-to-moderate Alzheimer’s diseaseN Engl J Med201437032233310.1056/NEJMoa1304839<?supplied-pmid 24450891?>24450891 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR82"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>82.DoodyRSThomasRGFarlowMIwatsuboTVellasBJoffeSPhase 3 trials of solanezumab for mild-to-moderate Alzheimer’s diseaseN Engl J Med201437031132110.1056/NEJMoa1312889<?supplied-pmid 24450890?>24450890 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR83"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>83.JordãoJFAyala-GrossoCAMarkhamKHuangYChopraRMcLaurinJAntibodies targeted to the brain with image-guided focused ultrasound reduces amyloid-beta plaque load in the TgCRND8 mouse model of Alzheimer’s diseasePLoS One20105e1054910.1371/journal.pone.0010549<?supplied-pmid 20485502?>20485502 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR84"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>84.LeinengaGGötzJScanning ultrasound removes amyloid-β and restores memory in an Alzheimer’s disease mouse modelSci Transl Med20157278ra3310.1126/scitranslmed.aaa2512<?supplied-pmid 25761889?>25761889 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR85"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>85.Nisbet RM, Van der Jeugd A, Leinenga G, Evans HT, Janowicz PW, Götz J. Combined effects of scanning ultrasound and a tau-specific single chain antibody in a tau transgenic mouse model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Brain J Neurol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>2017;140(5):1220–1230. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR86"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>86.KovacsZIKimSJikariaNQureshiFMiloBLewisBKDisrupting the blood-brain barrier by focused ultrasound induces sterile inflammationProc Natl Acad Sci U S A2017114E75E8410.1073/pnas.1614777114<?supplied-pmid 27994152?>27994152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
