<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Environ Res Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Environ Res Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijerph</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1661-7827</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1660-4601</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6406689</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph16040557</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ijerph-16-00557</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Haplotype and Haplotype-Environment Interaction Analysis Revealed Roles of SPRY2 for NSCL/P among Chinese Populations </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5776-3100</contrib-id><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Ren</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijerph-16-00557">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0162-5355</contrib-id><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Mengying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijerph-16-00557">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Wenyong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijerph-16-00557">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Siyue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijerph-16-00557">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Hongchen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijerph-16-00557">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Zhibo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijerph-16-00557">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Yonghua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijerph-16-00557">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Jing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijerph-16-00557">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Tao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijerph-16-00557">1</xref><xref rid="c1-ijerph-16-00557" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Hongping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijerph-16-00557">2</xref><xref rid="c1-ijerph-16-00557" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Beaty</surname><given-names>Terri H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-ijerph-16-00557">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-ijerph-16-00557"><label>1</label>School of Public Health, Peking University, Beijing 100191, China; <email>zhouren1994@163.com</email> (R.Z.); <email>mywang@bjmu.edu.cn</email> (M.W.); <email>lwy_edu@163.com</email> (W.L.); <email>yzmagiw@163.com</email> (S.W.); <email>zhc_1995@163.com</email> (H.Z.); <email>yhhu@bjmu.edu.cn</email> (Y.H.); <email>jli@bjmu.edu.cn</email> (J.L.)</aff><aff id="af2-ijerph-16-00557"><label>2</label>School of Stomatology, Peking University, Beijing 100081, China; <email>zzbooo@126.com</email></aff><aff id="af3-ijerph-16-00557"><label>3</label>School of Public Health, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD 21218, USA; <email>tbeaty1@jhu.edu</email></aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-ijerph-16-00557"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>zhuhongping@cndent.com</email> (H.Z.); <email>twu@bjmu.edu.cn</email> (T.W.)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>557</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2019 by the authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Non-syndromic cleft lip with or without cleft palate (NSCL/P) is one of common birth defects in China, with genetic and environmental components contributing to the etiology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Genome wide association studies (GWASs) have identified SPRY1 and SPRY2 to be associated with NSCL/P among Chinese populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>This study aimed to further explore potential genetic effect and gene—environment interaction among SPRY genes based on haplotype analysis, using 806 Chinese case—parent NSCL/P trios drawn from an international consortium which conducted a genome-wide association study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>After the process of quality control, 190 single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) of SPRY genes were included for analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Haplotype and haplotype—environment interaction analyses were conducted in Population-Based Association Test (PBAT) software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>A 2-SNP haplotype and three 3-SNP haplotypes showed a significant association with the risk of NSCL/P after Bonferroni correction (corrected significance level = 2.6 × 10−4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Moreover, haplotype—environment interaction analysis identified these haplotypes respectively showing statistically significant interactions with maternal multivitamin supplementation or maternal environmental tobacco smoke. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>This study showed SPRY2 to be associated with NSCL/P among the Chinese population through not only gene effects, but also a gene—environment interaction, highlighting the importance of considering environmental exposures in the genetic etiological study of NSCL/P. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>haplotypes</kwd><kwd>genetic association study</kwd><kwd>gene-environmental interaction</kwd><kwd>cleft lip and palate</kwd><kwd>case-parent trios</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-ijerph-16-00557"><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Non-syndromic oral cleft (NSOC) is a complex disease with genetic and environmental factors together contributing to the etiology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of NSOC varies across geographical regions or ethnic groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Compared with Europeans and Africans, Chinese have a higher prevalence of 1.39~1.46/1000 live births, which is lower than the prevalence of American Indians and Japanese [1,2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Genome wide association studies (GWASs) have contributed extraordinarily to gene mapping in the etiological exploration of NSCL/P, by identifying vast numbers of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) that are associated with diseases of interest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Despite the vast number of associations, only a small proportion of heritability could be explained by those identified variants from GWASs for many complex diseases [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>It has been raised that individual SNP analysis might miss some genetic information due to the incomplete linkage disequilibrium (LD) between the tagged markers and causal variants, which then probably leads to a loss of efficiency in gene mapping [4,5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Recently, evidence has increasingly demonstrated that a large proportion of genetic variance for complex diseases or traits could be explained by the genome-wide SNPs simultaneously [5,6], which implies that heritability is not actually missing, but instead undiscovered in GWAS by individual SNP analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Thus, further exploration of GWAS data were demanded to detect those remaining genetic risks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Haplotype analysis generally contains more LD information compared with the individual SNP analysis [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>This method has been applied to explore evidence for gene mapping using GWAS data, and successfully explained greater genetic variance than individual SNP analysis [8,9,10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Moreover, haplotype analysis can also explore cis—interaction in the same quantitative trait loci (QTL) [11], which may facilitate the understanding about the genetic architecture of diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>It is therefore reasonable to use haplotype analysis to excavate the remaining heritability in GWAS data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>SPRY genes were recently identified as playing roles in the etiology of NSCL/P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Previous GWASs reported rs908822 (SPRY1), rs8001641 (SPRY2), and rs9545308 (SPRY2) showing a significant association among different populations, including Chinese people [12,13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Evidence of a gene—gene interaction was also shown in this gene family to be associated with NSCL/P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In a recent published study, multiple pairs of SNP—SNP interactions among SPRY1-SPRY2 and SPRY2-SPRY4 contributed to the risk of NSCL/P in European and Asian populations, indicating the important roles of this gene family in the etiology of NSCL/P [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>However, whether environment exposures participated in the relationship between SPRYs and NSCL/P has not been reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Gene—environment interactions among SPRY genes and maternal environmental exposures should be explored to further clarify the roles of SPRY genes in the etiology of NSCL/P. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>This study aimed to explore the potential genetic effect and gene—environment interaction among SPRY genes based on haplotype analysis, using GWAS data of 806 Chinese case-parent NSCL/P trios, which were recruited by an international consortium. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec2-ijerph-16-00557"><title><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2dot1-ijerph-16-00557"><title><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Study Population </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>A total of 806 Chinese NSCL/P case-parent trios, recruited from Taiwan, Shandong, Hubei, and Sichuan, were drawn from an international consortium which conducted a genome-wide association study [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Of which, 539 cases were males and 267 were females; 597 cases had cleft lip and palate, and 209 cases had cleft lip only. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Syndromic forms of CL/P were excluded by clinicians through clinical examination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The research protocol was reviewed and approved by the Institutional Review Boards (IRBs) of each institution participating in this international consortium, including IRBs at the Johns Hopkins School of Public Health, University of Pittsburgh, Utah State University, University of Iowa, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Wuhan University, Peking University, and West China School of Stomatology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The latest annual approval number was 91-06-10-03-2 approved by Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health Committee on Human Research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Written informed consent was obtained from each participant and the study was performed in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The whole blood, saliva, or mouthwash sample for cases and their parents were collected to extract DNA samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot2-ijerph-16-00557"><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Genotyping and SNP Selection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The process of DNA genotyping was conducted by the Center for Inherited Disease Research (CIDR) in the Johns Hopkins University, using Illumina Human610-Quad v.1_B Bead Chip. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>A total of 245 SNPs were genotyped in SPRY genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The following four criteria were used to perform quality control: (1) Missing genotype information in the 806 trios &gt;10%, (2) low minor allele frequency (MAF) among founders &lt;0.05, (3) p-value of Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium test &lt;0.001, (4) Mendelian errors &gt;5%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>After quality control, 55 SNPs were filtered due to a low minor allele frequency, leaving 190 SNPs for further analysis (shown in Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The process of quality control was conducted by PLINK (v1.07, http://pngu.mgh.harvard.edu/purcell/plink/) [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The hg38 version of the human genome was used to indicate the genomic coordinates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot3-ijerph-16-00557"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The Assessment of Environmental Exposures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The information about maternal exposures was obtained through a face to face interview for each trio, including environmental tobacco smoke (ETS), maternal cigarette smoking, maternal alcohol consumption, and multivitamin supplementation from three months prior to pregnancy through the first trimester of pregnancy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The exposure status was recorded as 0 or 1, corresponding to unexposed or exposed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>As less than 3% of mothers in the study population were exposed to maternal cigarette smoking and alcohol consumption, only ETS and multivitamin supplementation were included in haplotype—environment interaction analysis, with exposure rates of 40.9% and 12.9%, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot4-ijerph-16-00557"><title><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Statistical Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Haplotype and haplotype—environment (HxE) interaction analysis were both performed using PBAT (population-based association test) software (v3.60, Harvard University, Boston, MA, USA) [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The statistical basis of PBAT was an approach introduced by Rabinowitz and Laird et al. [18,19], in which a score test was used to compare the observed genotypes among offspring with the expected distribution under Mendel’s law of segregation and the null hypothesis of ‘no linkage and no association’ [18,19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>PBAT could also incorporate the gene/covariate interactions into the test to further investigate the haplotype—environment interaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Analyses were conducted under an additive genetic model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The method of sliding windows was used to determine the haplotypes for analyses, including 2-SNP haplotypes and 3-SNP haplotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Haplotypes with a frequency lower than 5% were excluded when reporting the results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>To minimize the false positive results, Bonferroni correction was applied and the significance level was set as 2.6 × 10−4 (0.05/190). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3-ijerph-16-00557"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>A total of 806 NSCL/P trios were included in the haplotype analysis and haplotype—environment interaction analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The haplotype analysis under the additive genetic model yielded one 2-SNP haplotype and three 3-SNP haplotypes showing a significant association with NSCL/P among 806 Chinese trios after Bonferroni correction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The haplotype with the lowest p-value was T-A-G for rs541731-rs9531050-rs9545409 (p-value = 1.30 × 10−5), located in SPRY2, with a frequency of 5.7% (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Haplotype—environment interaction analysis tested for the potential interaction between haplotypes in SPRY genes and maternal multivitamin supplementation as well as maternal environmental tobacco smoke (ETS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The analysis yielded a 3-SNP haplotype showing statistical interactions with maternal multivitamin supplementation: A-A-A for rs496932-rs9545412-rs9669948 (p-value = 3.43 × 10−5), located in SPRY2, with a frequency of 10.9%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>For the interaction with maternal ETS, a 2-SNP haplotype and two 3-SNP haplotypes showed significant interactions with ETS after Bonferroni correction, with T-A-G for rs541731-rs9531050-rs9545409 showing the lowest p-value (p-value = 9.18 × 10−5). Table 2 presents the results of the interaction analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4-ijerph-16-00557"><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>SPRY genes have been suggested in previous studies to participate in the development of NSCL/P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>In this study, haplotype analysis and haplotype-environment interaction analyses were conducted to further explore the evidence of the SPRY genes in the etiology of NSCL/P, using 806 Chinese trios. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>A 2-SNP haplotype and three 3-SNP haplotypes showed a significant association with the risk of NSCL/P after Bonferroni correction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>For the haplotype—environment interaction, these haplotypes respectively yielded statistically significant interactions with maternal multivitamin supplementation or maternal environmental tobacco smoke. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Several studies have previously shown evidence regarding the association between SPRY genes and NSCL/P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Ludwig et al. [13] first reported the SPRY2 in 13q31 among a European population in a meta-analysis of GWASs, while the p-value for rs8001641 reached 6.51 × 10−11 and the homozygote relative risk was 2.41 (95%CI: 1.84–3.16). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Then, Jia et al. [20] replicated the finding of rs8001641 using combined genotyping data of case-control samples and trios among a European population, but they failed to replicate the findings in Asian populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Moreover, Yu et al. [12] found that rs908822 in SPRY1 and rs9545308 in SPRY2 showed significant associations with NSCL/P recently, using 3379 cases and 8593 controls in a Chinese Han population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Although Yu et al. did not replicate the first reported rs3005666 and rs8001641, respectively, in SPRY1 and SPRY2, the novel markers identified in their study enriched the evidence of SPRY genes among the Chinese population, which implied that SPRY genes might influence the risk of NSCL/P not only among Europeans, but also among Chinese people or Asians. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>A recent study focused on gene—gene interactions among SPRY genes demonstrated that these genes contributed to the risk of NSCL/P through mutual interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Based on previous evidence of SPRY genes, the current study moved forward to explore potential susceptibility regions in SPRYs using haplotype analysis, as well as gene—environment interactions responsible for the risk of NSCL/P. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Based on data used in the current study, no individual SNP in SPRY genes showed a significant association with the risk of NSCL/P in the individual SNP analysis as well as the analysis of the SNP—environment interaction (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Target sequencing on SPRY genes could be a considerable approach to further explore potential variants associated with NSCL/P in these regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Considering the higher statistical power of haplotype analysis compared to individual SNP analysis when LD was exploited to explore genes associated with diseases, we conducted the haplotype analysis and haplotype—environment interaction analysis to further investigate the roles of SPRY genes in Chinese NSCL/P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The results of haplotype analysis altogether indicated that one genetic segment (rs541731- rs9669948, from 80345577 to 80372188) located at 4.5 kb—31.1 kb downstream of SPRY2 was associated with NSCL/P, indicating that the neighborhood region of this segment might contain causal variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Although the position drifted a little compared with formerly reported positions (rs8001641, 222.4 kb upstream of SPRY2; rs9545308, 270.7 kb upstream of SPRY2), our findings still enriched the evidence of this gene in the etiology of NSCL/P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The biological function of SPRY2 has also been identified by several experimental studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Abnormal palates were observed in SPRY2 knock-out mice [21,22,23], and the possible mechanism was suggested to be the regulation of the expression of the fibroblast growth factors (FGF) signaling pathway, which was shown to be important for the control of craniofacial development [12,24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Gene—environment interactions have been suggested in several studies to influence the risk of NSCL/P, such as IRF6—multivitamin supplementation [25], and RUNX2—environmental tobacco smoke [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>However, in most of the studies exploring potential SNP—environment factors’ interactions, the haplotype—environment interaction was rarely investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Multivitamin supplementation was previously identified as a protective factor of non-syndromic oral clefts, whereas environmental tobacco smoke was shown to be a risk factor [27,28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>In the current study, the haplotype—environment interaction analysis identified several haplotypes in SPRY2 showing the statistical interactions with maternal multivitamin supplementation or ETS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Besides, these haplotypes were those that were significant in the haplotype analysis, which eliminated the probability that our results were accidentally significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>However, the similarity did not mean the roles of environmental factors could be ignored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>On the contrary, this similarity and the interaction signals implied that the effect size of the association between these haplotypes and the risk of NSCL/P might be changed when environmental exposures were present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>When exposed to harmful environmental factors, ones carrying the haplotype could suffer a higher risk of NSCL/P compared to those unexposed to the environmental factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>In such a situation, the similarity and interaction signals could provide evidence for practical preventions against environmental factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Although statistical interactions do not always guarantee biological interaction, evidence about the biological function of SPRY2 [21,29,30] and the signals in the single haplotype analysis might together support a biological interaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Moreover, four SNPs in the identified genetic region, respectively, rs541731, rs496932, rs9545412, and rs9669948, are enhancer histone marks in embryonic stem cells or embryonic stem derived cells, which play important roles in the development of NSCL/P, as reported by ChromHMM software [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Genes with histone marks have been reported to have a significantly higher expression, while gene expression levels are correlated with DNA methylation [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Based on the general understanding that DNA methylations can be influenced by environmental exposures, it was reasonable to infer that ETS or multivitamin supplementation affected the DNA methylation processes of SPRY2 in embryonic stem cells or embryonic stem derived cells, and then influenced the development of NSCL/P. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The case-parent design used in this study was robust to population stratification, which was an advantage compared to a case-control design. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Besides, haplotypes contained more LD information and the haplotype analysis used in the current study could provide a higher statistical power for gene mapping, especially when the individual markers were not exactly the causal variants [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Despite these advantages, this study could not provide functional explanations for what we found, especially regarding how the haplotypes interacted with multivitamin supplementation and ETS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Thus, further studies are required to validate the findings as well as reveal the mechanism of how SPRY2 influences the risk of NSCL/P, both individually and under certain environmental exposures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec5-ijerph-16-00557"><title><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>This study identified that SPRY2 was associated with the risk of NSCL/P among the Chinese population, and could interact with multivitamin supplementation and environmental tobacco smoke. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>It highlighted the importance of using haplotype analysis to explore the effect of genes and gene—environment interactions when no signal can be found in individual SNP analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Our study enriches the understanding of the role of SPRY2 in the development of NSCL/P, and underlines the importance of considering environmental exposures in the etiological study of NSCL/P. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>We gratefully appreciate all families recruited in this study, and sincerely acknowledge the effort of the clinical, field and laboratory staff who made this work possible, and the Smile Train Foundation for supporting data collection in China. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app id="app1-ijerph-16-00557"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><p>The following are available online at <uri xlink:href="http://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/4/557/s1">http://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/4/557/s1</uri>, Figure S1. LD plot for single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in <italic>SPRY1</italic>, Figure S2. LD plot for single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in <italic>SPRY2</italic>, Figure S3. LD plot for single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in <italic>SPRY4</italic>, Table S1. 190 single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) included in analysis among 806 Chinese NSCL/P trios, Table S2. The 5-SNP haplotypes in SPRY genes showing significant association with the risk of NSCL/P or among 806 Chinese trios after Bonferroni correction.</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ijerph-16-00557-s001"><media xlink:href="ijerph-16-00557-s001.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></app></app-group></SecTag><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Conceptualization, R.Z., T.W. and H.Z. (Hongping Zhu); Data curation, T.W. and T.H.B.; Formal analysis, R.Z. and M.W.; Funding acquisition, T.W., H.Z. (Hongping Zhu) and T.H.B.; Investigation, T.H.B.; Project administration, W.L. and H.Z. (Hongchen Zheng); Supervision, Z.Z., J.L., Y.H., T.W., H.Z. (Hongping Zhu) and T.H.B.; Writing—original draft, R.Z.; Writing—review &amp; editing, R.Z., M.W., W.L., S.W., H.Z. (Hongchen Zheng), Z.Z., J.L., Y.H., T.W., H.Z. (Hongping Zhu) and T.H.B.</p></notes><notes><title>Funding</title><p>The International Cleft Consortium for genotyping and analysis was funded by the National Institute for Dental and Craniofacial Research through U01-DE-018993; ‘‘International Consortium to Identify Genes &amp;Interactions Controlling Oral Clefts’’, 2007–2009; TH Beaty, PI. This study was also supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (81102178, 81573225, PI: Tao Wu), Beijing Natural Science Foundation of China (7172115, PI: Tao Wu) and Peking University Health Science Center Interdisciplinary Research Fund (BMU2017MX018, PI: Hongping Zhu and Tao Wu).</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>1.CooperM.E.RatayJ.S.MarazitaM.L.Asian oral-facial cleft birth prevalenceCleft Palate-Craniofac. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Off. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Publ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Cleft Palate-Craniofac. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Assoc.20064358058910.1597/05-167<?supplied-pmid 16986997?>16986997 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>2.PanamontaV.PradubwongS.PanamontaM.ChowchuenB.Global Birth Prevalence of Orofacial Clefts: A Systematic ReviewJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Assoc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Thail.201598Suppl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>7S11S21 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>3.MaherB.Personal genomes: The case of the missing heritabilityNature2008456182110.1038/456018a<?supplied-pmid 18987709?>18987709 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>4.MoskvinaV.O’DonovanM.C.Detailed analysis of the relative power of direct and indirect association studies and the implications for their interpretationHum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Hered.200764637310.1159/000101424<?supplied-pmid 17483598?>17483598 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>5.YangJ.BenyaminB.McEvoyB.P.GordonS.HendersA.K.NyholtD.R.MaddenP.A.HeathA.C.MartinN.G.MontgomeryG.W.Common SNPs explain a large proportion of the heritability for human heightNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Genet.20104256556910.1038/ng.608<?supplied-pmid 20562875?>20562875 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>6.YangJ.BakshiA.ZhuZ.HemaniG.VinkhuyzenA.A.LeeS.H.RobinsonM.R.PerryJ.R.NolteI.M.van Vliet-OstaptchoukJ.V.Genetic variance estimation with imputed variants finds negligible missing heritability for human height and body mass indexNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Genet.2015471114112010.1038/ng.3390<?supplied-pmid 26323059?>26323059 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>7.LiuN.ZhangK.ZhaoH.Haplotype-association analysisAdv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Genet.20086033540518358327 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>8.KhankhanianP.GourraudP.A.LizeeA.GoodinD.S.Haplotype-based approach to known MS-associated regions increases the amount of explained riskJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Genet.20155258759410.1136/jmedgenet-2015-10307126185143 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>9.SunW.LvW.LvH.ZhangR.JiangY.Genome-wide haplotype association analysis identifies SERPINB9, SERPINE2, GAK, and HSP90B1 as novel risk genes for oral squamous cell carcinomaTumour Biol.2016371845185110.1007/s13277-015-3965-226318431 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>10.WangQ.LvH.LvW.ShiM.ZhangM.LuanM.ZhuH.ZhangR.JiangY.Genome-wide haplotype association study identifies BLM as a risk gene for prostate cancer in Chinese populationTumour Biol.2015362703270710.1007/s13277-014-2893-x25472581 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>11.GarnierS.TruongV.BrochetonJ.ZellerT.RovitalM.WildP.S.ZieglerA.CardiogenicsC.MunzelT.TiretL.Genome-wide haplotype analysis of cis expression quantitative trait loci in monocytesPLoS Genet.20139e100324010.1371/journal.pgen.1003240<?supplied-pmid 23382694?>23382694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>12.YuY.ZuoX.HeM.GaoJ.FuY.QinC.MengL.WangW.SongY.ChengY.Genome-wide analyses of non-syndromic cleft lip with palate identify 14 novel loci and genetic heterogeneityNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Commun.201781436410.1038/ncomms14364<?supplied-pmid 28232668?>28232668 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>13.LudwigK.U.MangoldE.HermsS.NowakS.ReutterH.PaulA.BeckerJ.HerberzR.AlChawaT.NasserE.Genome-wide meta-analyses of nonsyndromic cleft lip with or without cleft palate identify six new risk lociNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Genet.20124496897110.1038/ng.2360<?supplied-pmid 22863734?>22863734 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>14.ZhouR.WangM.LiW.WangS.ZhouZ.LiJ.WuT.ZhuH.BeatyT.H.Gene-Gene Interactions among SPRYs for Nonsyndromic Cleft Lip/PalateJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Dent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Res.201810.1177/0022034518801537<?supplied-pmid 30273098?>30273098 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>15.BeatyT.H.MurrayJ.C.MarazitaM.L.MungerR.G.RuczinskiI.HetmanskiJ.B.LiangK.Y.WuT.MurrayT.FallinM.D.A genome-wide association study of cleft lip with and without cleft palate identifies risk variants near MAFB and ABCA4Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Genet.20104252552910.1038/ng.580<?supplied-pmid 20436469?>20436469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>16.PurcellS.NealeB.Todd-BrownK.ThomasL.FerreiraM.A.BenderD.MallerJ.SklarP.de BakkerP.I.DalyM.J.PLINK: A tool set for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analysesAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Hum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Genet.20078155957510.1086/51979517701901 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>17.LangeC.DeMeoD.SilvermanE.K.WeissS.T.LairdN.M.PBAT: Tools for family-based association studiesAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Hum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Genet.20047436736910.1086/38156314740322 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>18.RabinowitzD.LairdN.A unified approach to adjusting association tests for population admixture with arbitrary pedigree structure and arbitrary missing marker informationHum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Hered.20005021122310.1159/00002291810782012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>19.LairdN.M.HorvathS.XuX.Implementing a unified approach to family-based tests of associationGenet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Epidemiol.200019Suppl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>1S36S4210.1002/1098-2272(2000)19:1+&lt;::AID-GEPI6&gt;3.0.CO;2-M11055368 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>20.JiaZ.LeslieE.J.CooperM.E.ButaliA.StandleyJ.RigdonJ.SuzukiS.GongorjavA.ShonkhuuzT.E.NatsumeN.Replication of 13q31.1 association in nonsyndromic cleft lip with cleft palate in EuropeansAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Genet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>A2015167A1054106010.1002/ajmg.a.3691225786657 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>21.WelshI.C.Hagge-GreenbergA.O’BrienT.P.A dosage-dependent role for Spry2 in growth and patterning during palate developmentMech. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Dev.200712474676110.1016/j.mod.2007.06.007<?supplied-pmid 17693063?>17693063 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>22.GoodnoughL.H.BrugmannS.A.HuD.HelmsJ.A.Stage-dependent craniofacial defects resulting from Sprouty2 overexpressionDev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Dyn.20072361918192810.1002/dvdy.21195<?supplied-pmid 17576140?>17576140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>23.MatsumuraK.TaketomiT.YoshizakiK.AraiS.SanuiT.YoshigaD.YoshimuraA.NakamuraS.Sprouty2 controls proliferation of palate mesenchymal cells via fibroblast growth factor signalingBiochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Commun.20114041076108210.1016/j.bbrc.2010.12.116<?supplied-pmid 21195053?>21195053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>24.WangH.ZhangT.WuT.HetmanskiJ.B.RuczinskiI.SchwenderH.LiangK.Y.MurrayT.FallinM.D.RedettR.J.The FGF and FGFR Gene Family and Risk of Cleft Lip with or without Cleft PalateCleft Palate-Craniofac. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Off. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Publ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Cleft Palate-Craniofac. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Assoc.2013509610310.1597/11-132<?supplied-pmid 22074045?>22074045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>25.WuT.LiangK.Y.HetmanskiJ.B.RuczinskiI.FallinM.D.IngersollR.G.WangH.HuangS.YeX.Wu-ChouY.H.Evidence of gene-environment interaction for the IRF6 gene and maternal multivitamin supplementation in controlling the risk of cleft lip with/without cleft palateHum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Genet.201012840141010.1007/s00439-010-0863-y<?supplied-pmid 20652317?>20652317 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>26.WuT.FallinM.D.ShiM.RuczinskiI.LiangK.Y.HetmanskiJ.B.WangH.IngersollR.G.HuangS.YeX.Evidence of gene-environment interaction for the RUNX2 gene and environmental tobacco smoke in controlling the risk of cleft lip with/without cleft palateBirth Defects Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>A Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Teratol.201294768310.1002/bdra.22885<?supplied-pmid 22241686?>22241686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>27.JiaZ.L.ShiB.ChenC.H.ShiJ.Y.WuJ.XuX.Maternal malnutrition, environmental exposure during pregnancy and the risk of non-syndromic orofacial cleftsOral Dis.20111758458910.1111/j.1601-0825.2011.01810.x<?supplied-pmid 21535328?>21535328 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>28.HoneinM.A.RasmussenS.A.ReefhuisJ.RomittiP.A.LammerE.J.SunL.CorreaA.Maternal smoking and environmental tobacco smoke exposure and the risk of orofacial cleftsEpidemiology20071822623310.1097/01.ede.0000254430.61294.c0<?supplied-pmid 17202867?>17202867 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>29.YangX.KilgallenS.AndreevaV.SpicerD.B.PinzI.FrieselR.Conditional expression of Spry1 in neural crest causes craniofacial and cardiac defectsBMC Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Biol.2010104810.1186/1471-213X-10-48<?supplied-pmid 20459789?>20459789 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>30.SongT.ShiJ.GuoQ.LvK.JiaoX.HuT.SunX.FuS.Association between NOGGIN and SPRY2 polymorphisms and nonsyndromic cleft lip with or without cleft palateAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Genet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>A2015167A13714110.1002/ajmg.a.36802<?supplied-pmid 25339627?>25339627 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>31.ErnstJ.KellisM.ChromHMM: Automating chromatin-state discovery and characterizationNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Methods2012921521610.1038/nmeth.1906<?supplied-pmid 22373907?>22373907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32-ijerph-16-00557"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>32.RoadmapE.C.KundajeA.MeulemanW.ErnstJ.BilenkyM.YenA.Heravi-MoussaviA.KheradpourP.ZhangZ.WangJ.Integrative analysis of 111 reference human epigenomesNature201551831733025693563 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="TABLE"></SecTag></floats-group></article>
