<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Molecules</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Molecules</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">molecules</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Molecules : A Journal of Synthetic Chemistry and Natural Product Chemistry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1420-3049</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6155707</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules22010169</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">molecules-22-00169</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Toxicity of Plant Secondary Metabolites Modulating Detoxification Genes Expression for Natural Red Palm Weevil Pesticide Development </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>AlJabr</surname><given-names>Ahmed Mohammed</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-molecules-22-00169">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-molecules-22-00169">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>Abid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-molecules-22-00169">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-molecules-22-00169">†</xref><xref rid="c1-molecules-22-00169" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rizwan-ul-Haq</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-molecules-22-00169">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Ayedh</surname><given-names>Hassan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-molecules-22-00169">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Iriti</surname><given-names>Marcello</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-molecules-22-00169"><label>1</label>Laboratory of Bio-Control and Molecular Biology, Department of Arid Land Agriculture, College of Agricultural and Food Sciences, King Faisal University, Hofuf 31982, Al-Ahsa, Saudi Arabia; <email>aljabr@kfu.edu.sa</email> (A.M.A.); <email>mianrizwan15@gmail.com</email> (M.R.-H.)</aff><aff id="af2-molecules-22-00169"><label>2</label>Life Science and Environment Research Institute, King Abdulaziz City for Science and Technology, P.O. Box 6086, Riyadh 11442, Saudi Arabia; <email>alayedh@kacst.edu.sa</email></aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-molecules-22-00169"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>solvia_aah@yahoo.com</email>; Tel.: +966-135-895-851</corresp><fn id="fn1-molecules-22-00169"><label>†</label><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>These authors contributed equally to this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>169</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2017 by the authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>This study aimed to explore the larvicidal and growth-inhibiting activities, and underlying detoxification mechanism of red palm weevil against phenylpropanoids, an important class of plant secondary metabolites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Toxicity of α-asarone, eugenol, isoeugenol, methyl eugenol, methyl isoeugenol, coumarin, coumarin 6, coniferyl aldehyde, diniconazole, ethyl cinnamate, and rosmarinic acid was evaluated by incorporation into the artificial diet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>All of the phenylpropanoids exhibited dose- and time-dependent insecticidal activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Among all the tested phenylpropanoids, coumarin exhibited the highest toxicity by revealing the least LD50 value (0.672 g/L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>In addition, the most toxic compound (coumarin) observed in the current study, deteriorated the growth resulting tremendous reduction (78.39%) in efficacy of conversion of digested food (ECD), and (ECI) efficacy of conversion of ingested food (70.04%) of tenth-instar red palm weevil larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The energy-deficient red palm weevil larvae through their intrinsic abilities showed enhanced response to their digestibility resulting 27.78% increase in approximate digestibility (AD) compared to control larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The detoxification response of Rhynchophorus ferrugineus larvae determined by the quantitative expression of cytochrome P450, esterases, and glutathione S-transferase revealed enhanced expression among moderately toxic and ineffective compounds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>These genes especially cytochrome P450 and GST detoxify the target compounds by enhancing their solubility that leads rapid excretion and degradation resulting low toxicity towards red palm weevil larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the most toxic (coumarin) silenced the genes involved in the red palm weevil detoxification mechanism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Based on the toxicity, growth retarding, and masking detoxification activities, coumarin could be a useful future natural red palm weevil-controlling agent. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd><italic>cytochrome P450</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>esterases</italic></kwd><kwd>feeding indices</kwd><kwd><italic>glutathione S-transferase</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Rhynchophorus ferrugineus</italic></kwd><kwd>toxicity</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1-molecules-22-00169"><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Red palm weevil, Rhynchophorus ferrugineus (Olivier) (Coleoptera, Curculionidae), is a severe pest of a wide genera of palms with a worldwide distribution [1,2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Weevils destroy the vascular system of the palm trunk, which eventually lead towards the collapse and death of the infested palm [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The cryptic life cycle of weevils, which occurs inside the palm truck, presents serious management challenges [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Previously, the red palm weevil control strategy mainly depended on the use of synthetic insecticides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The intensive use of insecticides against the invaded populations of red palm weevil impart detrimental effects on non-target animals, environmental pollution, and insecticide residues in the food [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Recent reports on the continued low efficacy of insecticides due to the development of insecticide resistance in the most destructive pest of palm, R. ferrugineus is challenging for farmers, researchers, and policy-makers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>These facts signify the importance on the development of alternative control approaches. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Different environmental friendly strategies including entomopathogenic fungi [4,5,6], nematodes [7], bacteria [8,9], development of pheromone traps [10,11,12,13], sterile insect technique [14,15,16,17], and plant based insecticides [18,19,20,21] remained the subject of previous research investigations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Among them, plant-based products especially plant secondary metabolites are the most promising alternatives to environmental deteriorating insecticides. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The metabolic pathways of plants generate tens of thousands of secondary products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>These plant secondary metabolites have shown numerous benefits in different industries [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Currently, the untapped reservoir of plant secondary metabolites are of particular interest in insecticide development [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>These natural compounds gaining importance in pest management due to various deleterious effects including anti-feedant, toxic, repellent, fumigant, attractant, molting disruption, respiratory inhibition, pheromone-based behavioral adaptations, oviposition deterrence, and fecundity reduction against target pest populations [23,24,25,26,27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In the past, this broad-spectrum approach was ignored in red palm weevil control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Little research data of preliminary stages are available on the use of plant-based raw products including essential oils [18,28], plant extracts [20,29,30], plant metabolites, such as rotenone and limonine [31], against red palm weevils. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Phenylpropanoid plant secondary metabolites are synthesized by phenylalanine within the plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>These compounds (phenylpropanoids) have been isolated from throughout the plant kingdom. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The insecticidal potential of different phenylpropanoids have been tested against different pest species in a number of investigations [32,33,34,35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>A literature survey has shown that there is no report on the use of phenylpropanoids against red palm weevils, thus, we decided for the first time, to investigate the insecticidal potential of phenylpropanoids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Our study aimed to (1) screen the toxicity of selected phenylpropanoid plant secondary metabolites including α-asarone, eugenol, isoeugenol, methyl eugenol, methyl isoeugenol, coumarin, coumarin 6, coniferyl aldehyde, diniconazole, ethyl cinnamate, and rosmarinic acid against red palm weevils; (2) determine the influence of phenylpropanoids on the feeding performance of R. ferrugineus larvae; and (3) explore the host detoxification mechanism against the toxicity of phenylpropanoids to pave the way for the isolation and development of eco-friendly compounds against red palm weevils. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="sec2-molecules-22-00169"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2dot1-molecules-22-00169"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Dose Mortality Response </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Toxicity of selected phenylpropanoids toward red palm weevil larvae varied significantly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>However, only coumarin caused 100% mortality with the least LD50 value after three days (0.672 g/L); and found to be the most toxic phenylpropanoid in the current study (Figure 1; Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Comparatively, coumarin at all tested doses (F = 893.67; df = 4, 64; p &lt; 0.0001), time intervals (F = 189.63; df = 3, 64; p &lt; 0.0001), and their interaction (F = 95.28; df = 12, 64; p &lt; 0.0001) imparted significantly higher mortality (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>In our toxicity analysis, rosmarinic acid, methyl isoeugenol, and methyl eugenol showed very little promise in red pam weevil control because they failed to impart 50% mortality even at a dose of 25 g/L during the course of whole experimentation (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, seven phenylpropanoids, including ethyl cinnamate, diniconazole, isoeugenol, coumarin 6, α-asarone, eugenol, and coniferyl aldehyde imparted &gt; 50% mortality and their LD50 values calculated after 12 days ranged between 6 and 28 g/L (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>However, the interaction of dose mortality response at different time intervals for ethyl cinnamate (F = 10.30; df = 12, 64; p &lt; 0.0001), diniconazole (F = 6.42; df = 12, 64; p &lt; 0.0001), isoeugenol (F = 9.65; df = 12, 64; p &lt; 0.0001), coumarin 6 (F = 13.37; df = 12, 64; p &lt; 0.0001), α-asarone (F = 4.64; df = 12, 64; p &lt; 0.0001), eugenol (F = 3.22; df = 12, 64; p &lt; 0.0001), and coniferyl aldehyde (F = 1.14; df = 12, 64; p &lt; 0.0001) were significantly different (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Overall, these seven phenylpropanoids due to high LD50 values and slow mode of action found to be less toxic to red palm weevil larvae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot2-molecules-22-00169"><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Growth Inhibition Activities of Red Palm Weevil Larvae </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The incorporation of each tested phenylpropanoid at a dose of 0.672 g/L into the artificial diet to calculate nutritional indices including ECI, ECD, and AD after 72 h of feeding have shown tremendous variations in their response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Red palm weevil larvae fed on diets incorporated with coumarin showed the highest reduction in ECD (78.39%), and remained significantly different to all other diets incorporated with other phenylpropanoids (F = 146; df = 11, 48; p &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>However, the lowest reduction (&lt;15%) was observed from the diets incorporated with methyl eugenol, methyl isoeugenol, rosmarinic acid, coniferyl aldehyde, eugenol, and α-asarone (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The most toxic compound (coumarin) screened in the current study also tremendously reduced (70.04%) the ECI of R. ferrugineus larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The remaining treatments failed to impart tremendous reduction, resulting in &lt;12% reduction compared to the control treatment diet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>However, significant differences in the ECI index among the tested compounds were observed (F = 170; df = 11, 48; p &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the ECI index of methyl eugenol and methyl isoeugenol remained significantly at the same level compared to the control treatment diets (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Overall, inhibition in growth indices (ECI and ECD) directly proportional to the toxicity of phenylpropanoids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The highly toxic compound, coumarin, screened in the current study, imparted the highest inhibition in the ECI and ECD indexes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the least toxic compounds failed to inhibit growth indices of R. ferrugineus larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>On the contrary, an inversely proportional relationship was observed between AD and toxicity of the isolates compared to the ECI and ECD indices (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The most toxic compound, coumarin, significantly enhanced (27.78%) the AD of R. ferrugineus larvae compared to the control treatment larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The artificial diets incorporated with all other tested phenylpropanoids failed to tremendously enhance AD. and resulted in &lt;11% compared to control treatment larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>However, AD significantly increased upon exposure to different treatments (F = 208; df = 11, 48; p &lt; 0.0001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot3-molecules-22-00169"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Quantitative Reverse Transcription Polymerase Chain Reaction Analyses of Red Palm Weevil Detoxification Genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Toxicity of tested plant phenylpropanoids induced different levels of detoxification (cytochrome P450, glutathione S-transferase, and esterase) genes (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The expression of detoxification genes (F = 2269.48; df = 2, 132; p &lt; 0.0001), upon feeding on different treatments (F = 500.51; df = 10, 132; p &lt; 0.0001) and their interaction (F = 136.94; df = 20, 132; p &lt; 0.0001), showed significant differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Larvae fed on diet incorporated with methyl eugenol, methyl isoeugenol, and rosmarinic acid tremendously enhanced the expression of tested detoxification genes especially GST and cytochrome P450 (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Among all the detoxification genes, GST showed the highest expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>All of the treatments, except coumarin, greatly induced the expression of GST and cytochrome P450 (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>However, esterase failed to induce expression and remained significantly at lower level compared to other tested detoxification genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="sec3-molecules-22-00169"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Red palm weevil control is facing a threat because of the development of insecticide resistance in Rhynchophorus ferruginous against conventional synthetic insecticides, warranting the development of newer plant-based eco-friendly insecticides [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Our screening program for discovering potent compounds was designed by evaluating toxicity, feeding performance and host detoxification against selected phenylpropanoids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>We have reported for the first time the toxicity and growth retarding activities of coumarin that disturbed the genes that regulate detoxification mechanism. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Dietary laboratory experimentation of selected phenylpropanoids (Figure 3) against red palm weevil larvae exhibited various biological effects from low to high degrees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Among all the tested compounds, artificial diet incorporated with coumarin, showed acute toxicity, imparting the least LD50 (0.672 g/L) against red palm weevil larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The efficacy of coumarin is equivalent to the efficacy observed by Moreira et al. [34], who examined the effect of coumarin on coleopterons infesting stored products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>They found coumarin as the best treatment against Oryzaephilus surinamensis (L), and Rhyzopertha dominica (F) at all the studied time intervals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The LD50 results reported by Moreira et al. [34], coincides with our findings against red palm weevil larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The LD50 of R. dominica reported by Moriera after 6 h was 39.71 mg/g (39,710 ppm), while after 12 h it was 20.82 mg/g (20,820 ppm) that was 47.57% decrease in LD50 value compared to 6 h LD50 value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, LD50 value after 24 h was 11.82 mg/g (11,820 ppm) that was 70.23% decrease in LD50 value compared to 6 h LD50 value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The difference in LD50 values between our results against red palm weevil with R. dominica and O. surinamensis mainly because of the time to calculate LD50 values as reflected in the Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>However, the toxicity calculated through LD50 values of other phenylpropanoids ranged from moderate (ethyl cinnamate, diniconazole, isoeugenol, coumarin 6, α-asarone, eugenol and coniferyl aldehyde) to ineffective (rosmarinic acid, methyl isoeugenol, and methyl eugenol) against red palm weevil larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Toxicity results of rosmarinic acid, methyl isoeugenol, and methyl eugenol at the highest concentration (25 g/L) during the course of whole experimentation without attaining 50% mortality showed that these compounds have little promise to be used as bio-pesticide against R. ferruginous larvae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Coumarin imparted significant reductions in the feeding performance of R. ferrugineus larvae, when it incorporated into the diet at a dose of 0.672 g/L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Tenth-instar R. ferruginous larvae fed on a coumarin-containing diet showed the least efficacy of conversion of ingested (ECI), and digested (ECD) diet, which meant that less food was available for growth because most of the energy was metabolized for host defense. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Similar nutritional indices patterns of ECD and ECI in red palm weevil larvae were reported, when larvae were dipped in conidial suspensions of entomopathogenic fungi [4,5], or larvae fed on diets incorporated with synthetic pesticides [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Such tremendous reductions in ECI (70.04%), and ECD (78.39%) by coumarin compared to control larvae observed in the current study revealed that most of the energy from ingested food is being used to perform physiological activities to combat the toxin (coumarin), which means that less food is being utilized for larval growth and development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>In contrast, coumarin 6, α-asarone, eugenol and coniferyl aldehyde, rosmarinic acid, methyl isoeugenol, and methyl eugenol failed to impart significant reductions in ECI and resulting less than 10% reduction in ECI compared to control suggesting low toxicity potential of these tested compounds against tenth-instar red palm weevil larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>In addition, such minor reductions in ECD compared to control were observed when larvae were fed on diet incorporated with rosmarinic acid (10.36%), methyl isoeugenol (5.26%), and methyl eugenol (2.42%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Previous research reported the contact and fumigation action of methyleugenol, (E)-methyl isoeugenol, and α-asarone against Liposcelis bostrychophila Badonnel [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Their findings reported much lower LD50 (125.73 μg/cm2) of α-asarone by contact toxicity bioassays compared to our LD50 (17.670 g/L) results suggesting its little potential in controlling red palm weevil larvae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Bioactivity of the most potent compound (coumarin) evaluated in the current study greatly enhanced (27.78%) the approximate digestibility (AD) compared to the control treatment R. ferrugineus tenth-instar larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The enhanced response of AD values among coumarin-fed R. ferrugineus larvae unveil the fact of the use of some extra energy for host defense. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>In order to fulfill this energy shortfall, treated larvae through their intrinsic abilities enhanced their approximate digestibility of the limited foodstuff. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Previous laboratory investigations also reported similar enhanced AD response among R. ferrugineus larvae to pesticides [3]; and fungal conidia [4,5]; Ocinara varians larvae to fungal suspensions [36]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The physiological responses of R. ferrugineus larvae promote the expression of genes involved in the detoxification of toxic phenylpropanoids by enhancing metabolic mechanisms of target pest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Hussain et al. [3] reported the enhanced activity of GST among resistant populations of red palm weevil fed on artificial diet incorporated with cypermethrin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Among all the detoxification genes evaluated in the current study, GST gene was highly expressed indicating that GST rapidly detoxify the compounds especially α-asarone, eugenol, coniferyl aldehyde, rosmarinic acid, methyl isoeugenol, and methyl eugenol resulting more than 10% GST expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Similar enhanced expression was also reported in the current investigations in the case of cytochrome P450. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>However, their expression remained significantly lower compared to GST expression (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>In the past, the expression of GST, cytochrome P450, and esterase against toxicants in other pest species is well documented [37,38,39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The high expression of GST and cytochrome P450 directly related with the detoxification of host against the tested compounds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>These genes detoxify the target compounds by enhancing their solubility that leads rapid excretion and degradation [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The lethality of phenylpropanoids are greatly reduced by the enhanced expression of detoxification genes especially GST and cytochrome P450. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The most toxic compound (coumarin) target GST and cytochrome P450 genes resulting silencing/masking their expression that ultimately lead to the lowest LD50 value (0.672 g/L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>In contrast, esterase studied in the current investigations did not greatly stimulate the tested compounds and their expression remained very little. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The low expression does not necessarily mean that these genes are not involved in host defense against toxicant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, it cannot be ruled out that low expression genes might involve in defense to other toxicants not tested. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec4-molecules-22-00169"><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec4dot1-molecules-22-00169"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>4.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Insects </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The red palm weevils (R. ferruginous) were obtained from the laboratory cultures previously collected from the date palm infested fields in October-December 2014. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Adults were shifted to pineapples in cages (57.5 cm × 29 cm × 58 cm) for mating and oviposition at 30 ± 1 °C, 75% ± 5% relative humidity (RH), with a 16-h light photoperiod. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Neonates were fed on pineapples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>However, second instar R. ferrugineus larvae were shifted individually to an artificial diet in 400 mL perforated plastic cups at 30 ± 1 °C, 75% ± 5% relative humidity (RH) with a 16-h light photoperiod [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot2-molecules-22-00169"><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>4.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Phenylpropanoid Plant Secondary Metabolites </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Eleven phenylpropanoids, including α-asarone, eugenol, isoeugenol, methyl eugenol, methyl isoeugenol, coumarin, coumarin 6, coniferyl aldehyde, diniconazole, ethyl cinnamate, and rosmarinic acid, based on their toxicity to other pest species as shown in Figure 3 were purchased from Sigma Aldrich, London, UK. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot3-molecules-22-00169"><title><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>4.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Toxicity Bioassays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>In the laboratory, range-finding studies were performed to decide the appropriate doses of phenylpropanoids against red palm weevil larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The pure compounds were dissolved in acetone and diluted in distilled water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Five doses of each tested compound were incorporated into the artificial diet to determine the toxicity of red palm weevil larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Control treatment diet was prepared using similar volume of acetone and distilled water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Twenty-five tenth-instar red palm weevil larvae were used for each treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Each larva was singly-fed on a treated artificial diet in aerated plastic bowls at 30 ± 1 °C, 75% ± 5% relative humidity (RH) with a 16-h light photoperiod. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Five replicates from different red palm weevil generations for each treatment and control were prepared to compile toxicity bioassays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Dose mortality data were recorded daily. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Toxicity bioassays were repeated over time on different red palm weevil generations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The observed mortality data of red palm weevil larvae were corrected for control mortality by commonly used Abbott’s formula [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>All replicate results were subjected to Probit analysis to determine LD50 values using POLO software (LeOra Software LLC, Berkeley, CA, USA) [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Angularly transformed corrected cumulative mortality data at different time intervals were analyzed by repeated measures ANOVA with Fisher’s LSD test [43]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot4-molecules-22-00169"><title><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>4.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Nutritiopnal Indices of Red Palm Weevils </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Feeding performance was calculated with tenth-instar red palm weevil larvae as these larger larvae and their frass could easily be handled and accurately weighed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Diets were prepared separately using LD50 value for each compound based on toxicological laboratory bioassays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>In this experiment, twenty-five red palm weevil tenth-instar larvae per replicate were separately provided with artificial diet incorporated with the phenylpropanoids in aerated plastic bowls at 30 ± 1 °C, 75% ± 5% relative humidity (RH) with a 16-h light photoperiod. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Among all of the treatments, coumarin was found to be the most potent compound. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>For nutritional indices, artificial diets were supplemented with either α-asarone, eugenol, isoeugenol, methyl eugenol, methyl isoeugenol, coumarin, coumarin 6, coniferyl aldehyde, diniconazole, ethyl cinnamate, and rosmarinic acid at the dose of 0.672 g/L based on the LD50 value of the most potent treatment (coumarin) as determined in laboratory toxicology bioassays against same instar (tenth) red palm weevil larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Five replicates from different red palm weevil generations for each treatment and control were prepared for feeding performance bioassays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>After three days of experimentation, weight gained by each larva was accurately measured by analytical weight balance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>In addition, food consumed and frass produced by each larva was determined by analytical weight balance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>These measurements were used to determine nutritional indices of tenth-instar R. ferrugineus larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Nutritional indices including, efficacy of conversion of digested food (ECD = weight gained by the larva/(food ingested by the larva-dry weight of frass excreted by larvae)), efficacy of conversion of ingested food (ECI = 100 × dry weight gained by the larva/dry weight of food consumed by larva), and approximate digestibility (AD = (food ingested − frass weight)/food ingested × 100) were calculated as described in previous experimentation [4,5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Significant differences between growth nutritional indices generated from larvae fed on diets incorporated with different phenylpropanoids were determined using one-way ANOVA and Fisher’s LSD test using SAS [44]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4dot5-molecules-22-00169"><title><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>4.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Host Detoxification Mechanism </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The expression profiles of detoxification genes were validated by real-time quantitative PCR from the midgut portion of the alimentary canal of tenth-instar red palm weevil larvae, as these larger larvae have enough midgut to extract total RNA from single larva. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In this exploration, red palm weevil (tenth-instar) larvae were fed in separate aerated plastic bowls on each treatment diet prepared by incorporating each tested phenylpropanoid compound separately at a dose of 0.672 g/L based on the LD50 value of the most potent treatment (coumarin) as determined in laboratory toxicology bioassays against same instar (tenth) red palm weevil larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The experimental units were kept at 30 ± 1 °C, 75% ± 5% relative humidity (RH) with a 16-h light photoperiod. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Seventy-two hours post-feeding, tenth-instar larvae were dissected in saline for subsequent grinding of mid-gut portion in liquid nitrogen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>A commercially available RNeasy® Universal Mini Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) was used to extract total RNA from five larvae and each regarded as one replicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The extracted total RNA of each treatment was reverse-transcribed using PrimeScript First Strand cDNA Kit (TaKaRa Clontech, Paris, France). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>This template (first strand cDNA) of each treatment along with specific primers (Table 3) were used to quantify target gene expression in CFX96 TouchTM (Bio-Rad, London, UK) using SYBR® Premix Ex Taq™ II kit (TaKaRa Clontech, Paris, France). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The numerical values obtained from each experimental unit were compared with those of the control by relative fold expression obtained by transforming the obtained results into absolute values using 2−ΔΔCt [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>In case of control, the relative expression of each gene was set to 1. beta-Actin (GenBank accession #KM438516) due to its low expression variations was chosen as housekeeping gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The mid-gut samples extracted from red palm weevil larvae fed on different diets were analyzed by one-way ANOVA and the significant differences between means were determined by applying Fisher’s LSD test [44]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="sec5-molecules-22-00169"><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, feeding red palm weevil larvae on coumarin tremendously reduced their survival, adversely affected their growth and development, and inhibited the expression of detoxification genes, including GST and cytochrome P450. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>These characteristics suggest coumarin as a biologically-active valuable source for future eco-friendly commercial development of coumarin against the infestations of red palm weevils. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The study was supported by the Deanship of King Faisal University, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (Project No. 160078). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Sample Availability: Not available. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Ahmed Mohammed AlJabr and Abid Hussain conceived and designed the experiments; Abid Hussain and Muhammad Rizwan-ul-Haq performed the experiments; Muhammad Rizwan-ul-Haq, Hassan Al-Ayedh and Ahmed Mohammed AlJabr analyzed the data; Hassan Al-Ayedh and Ahmed Mohammed AlJabr contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools; Abid Hussain, Muhammad Rizwan-ul-Haq, Ahmed Mohammed AlJabr and Hassan Al-Ayedh wrote the paper.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. The founding sponsor had no role in the design of the study; in the collection, analyses, or interpretation of data; in the writing of the manuscript, and in the decision to publish the results.</p></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>1. HussainA.Rizwan-ul-haqM.Al-jabrA.M. Red palm weevil: Understanding the fungal disease mechanism and host defense Microbial Pathogens and Strategies for Combating Them: Science, Technology and Education Formatex Research Center Badajoz, Spain 2013 1278 1286  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>2. HussainA.Rizwan-ul-HaqM.Al-JabrA.M.Al-AyiedH.Y. Managing invasive populations of red palm weevil: A worldwide perspective J. Food Agric. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Environ. 2013 11 456 463  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>3. Al-AyedhH.HussainA.Rizwan-ul-HaqM.Al-JabrA.M. Status of insecticide resistance in field-collected populations of Rhynchophorus ferrugineus (Olivier) (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Agric. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2016 18 103 110 10.17957/IJAB/15.0070  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>4. HussainA.Rizwan-ul-HaqM.Al-AyedhH.AlJabrA. Susceptibility and immune defence mechanisms of Rhynchophorus ferrugineus (Olivier) (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) against entomopathogenic fungal infections Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Sci. 2016 17 1518 10.3390/ijms17091518 <?supplied-pmid 27618036?>27618036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>5. HussainA.Rizwan-ul-HaqM.Al-AyedhH.AhmedS.Al-JabrA.M. Effect of Beauveria bassiana infection on the feeding performance and antioxidant defence of red palm weevil, Rhynchophorus ferrugineus BioControl 2015 60 849 859 10.1007/s10526-015-9682-3  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>6. DembilioÓ.Quesada-MoragaE.Santiago-ÁlvarezC.JacasJ.A. Potential of an indigenous strain of the entomopathogenic fungus Beauveria bassiana as a biological control agent against the red palm weevil, Rhynchophorus ferrugineus J. Invertebr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Pathol. 2010 104 214 221 10.1016/j.jip.2010.04.006 <?supplied-pmid 20398670?>20398670 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>7. DembilioÓ.LlácerE.de Martínez AltubeM.JacasJ.A. Field efficacy of Imidacloprid and Steinernema carpocapsae in a chitosan formulation against the red palm weevil Rhynchophorus ferrugineus (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) in Phoenix canariensis Pest Manag. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Sci. 2010 66 365 370 10.1002/ps.1882 <?supplied-pmid 19924729?>19924729 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>8. PuY.HouY. Isolation and identification of bacterial strains with insecticidal activities from Rhynchophorus ferrugineus Oliver (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) J. Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Entomol. 2016 140 617 626 10.1111/jen.12293  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>9. FrancescaN.AlfonzoA.VerdeG.L.SettanniL.LucidoP. Biological activity of Bacillus spp. evaluated on eggs and larvae of red palm weevil Rhynchophorus ferrugineus Ann. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 2015 65 477 485 10.1007/s13213-014-0881-4  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>10. GuarinoS.ColazzaS.PeriE.BueP.Lo.GermanàM.P.KuznetsovaT.GindinG.SorokerV. Behaviour-modifying compounds for management of the red palm weevil (Rhynchophorus ferrugineus Oliver) Pest Manag. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Sci. 2015 71 1605 1610 10.1002/ps.3966 <?supplied-pmid 25523649?>25523649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>11. GuarinoS.PeriE.Lo BueP.GermanàM.P.ColazzaS.AnshelevichL.RavidU.SorokerV. Assessment of synthetic chemicals for disruption of Rhynchophorus ferrugineus response to attractant-baited traps in an urban environment Phytoparasitica 2013 41 79 88 10.1007/s12600-012-0266-9  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>12. HoddleM.Al-AbbadA.H.El-ShafieH.FaleiroJ.SallamA.HoddleC. Assessing the impact of areawide pheromone trapping, pesticide applications, and eradication of infested date palms for Rhynchophorus ferrugineus (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) management in Al Ghowaybah, Saudi Arabia Crop Prot. 2013 53 152 160 10.1016/j.cropro.2013.07.010  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>13. AbbasM.S.T.HanounikS.B.ShahdadA.S.AI-BaghamS.A. Aggregation pheromone traps, a major component of IPM strategy for the red palm weevil, Rhynchophorus ferrugineus in date palms (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) J. Pest Sci. 2006 79 69 73 10.1007/s10340-005-0113-6  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>14. Al-AyedhH.Y.RasoolK.G. Determination of the optimum sterilizing radiation dose for control of the red date palm weevil Rhynchophorus ferrugineus Oliv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>(Coleoptera: Curculionidae) Crop Prot. 2010 29 1377 1380 10.1016/j.cropro.2010.06.019  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>15. PaoliF.DallaiR.CristofaroM.ArnoneS.FrancardiV.RoversiP.F. Morphology of the male reproductive system, sperm ultrastructure and γ-irradiation of the red palm weevil Rhynchophorus ferrugineus Oliv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>(Coleoptera: Dryophthoridae) Tissue Cell 2014 46 274 285 10.1016/j.tice.2014.06.003 <?supplied-pmid 25015762?>25015762 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>16. MazzaG.InghilesiA.F.StasollaG.CiniA.CervoR.BenvenutiC.FrancardiV.CristofaroM.ArnoneS.RoversiP.F. Sterile Rhynchophorus ferrugineus males efficiently impair reproduction while maintaining their sexual competitiveness in a social context J. Pest Sci. 2015 89 459 468 10.1007/s10340-015-0709-4  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>17. El NaggarS.E.M.MohamedH.F.MahmoudE.A. Studies on the morphology and histology of the ovary of red palm weevil female irradiated with gamma rays J. Asia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Pac. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Entomol. 2010 13 9 16 10.1016/j.aspen.2009.08.004  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>18. ShuklaP.VidyasagarP.S.P.V.AldosariS.A.Abdel-AzimM. Antifeedant activity of three essential oils against the red palm weevil, Rhynchophorus ferrugineus Bull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Insectol. 2012 65 71 76  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>19. CangelosiB.ClematisF.MonroyF.RoversiP.F.TroianoR.CurirP.LanzottiV. Filiferol, a chalconoid analogue from Washingtonia filifera possibly involved in the defence against the red palm weevil Rhynchophorus ferrugineus Olivier Phytochemistry 2015 115 216 221 10.1016/j.phytochem.2015.02.008 <?supplied-pmid 25725962?>25725962 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>20. SalamaH.IsmailI. Potential of certain natural extracts for the control of the red palm weevil, Rhynchophorus ferrugineus (Oliver) Arch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Phytopathol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Plant Prot. 2007 40 233 236 10.1080/03235400500383669  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>21. AbdullahM.A. Toxicological and histopathological studies of Boxus chinensis oil and precocene II on larvae of the red palm weevil Rynchophorus ferrugineus (Oliver) (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) Egypt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Sci. 2009 2 45 54  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>22. NascimentoN.C.Fett-NetoA.G. Plant secondary metabolism and challenges in modifying its operation: An overview Plant Secondary Metabolism Engineering Methods and Applications Fett-NetoA.G. Humana Press New York, NY, USA 2010 1 13  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>23. IsmanM.B. Botanical insecticides, deterrents, and repellents in modern agriculture and an increasingly regulated world Annu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Entomol. 2006 51 45 66 10.1146/annurev.ento.51.110104.151146 <?supplied-pmid 16332203?>16332203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>24. TanK.H.NishidaR. Methyl eugenol: Its occurrence, distribution, and role in nature, especially in relation to insect behavior and pollination J. Insect Sci. 2012 12 10.1673/031.012.5601 <?supplied-pmid 22963669?>22963669 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>25. ScottI.JensenH.ScottJ.IsmanM.ArnasonJ.PhilogèneB. Botanical insecticides for controlling agricultural pests: Piperamides and the Colorado Potato Beetle Leptinotarsa decemlineata Say (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae) Arch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Insect Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Physiol. 2003 54 212 225 10.1002/arch.10118 <?supplied-pmid 14635182?>14635182 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>26. ZhaoB.GrantG.LangevinD.MacDonaldL. Deterring and inhibiting effects of quinolizidine alkaloids on spruce budworm (Lepidoptera: Tortricidae) oviposition Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Entomol. 1998 27 984 992 10.1093/ee/27.4.984  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>27. KoulO. Phytochemicals and insect control: An antifeedant approach CRC Crit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Plant Sci. 2008 27 1 24 10.1080/07352680802053908  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>28. NassarM.AbdulahA. Assessment of Boxus chinensis oil and precocene II for the control of the red palm weevil, Rhychophorus ferrugineus (Oliv.) (Coleoptera-Curculionidae) and the palm beetle, Pseudophilus testaceous J. Entomol. 2005 2 1 8  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>29. El-BoklM.M.BakerR.F.El-GammalH.L.MahmoudM.Z. Biological and histopathological effects of some insecticidal agents against red palm weevil Rhynchophorus ferrugineus Egypt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Histol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Histochem. 2010 1 7 22  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>30. NassarM.AbdullahM. Evaluation of azadirachtin for control of the red palm weevil Rhynchophorus ferrugineus (Olivier) (Coleoptera, Curculionidae) J. Egypt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Ger. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Zool. 2001 36 163 173  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>31. AbdullahM.A.R. Identification of the biological active compounds of two natural extracts for the control of the red palm weevil, Rhynchophorus ferrugineus (Oliver) (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) Egypt Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Sci. 2009 2 35 44  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>32. AhnY.J.KimN.J.ByunS.G.ChoJ.E.ChungK. Larvicidal activity of Kaempferia galanga rhizome phenylpropanoids towards three mosquito species Pest Manag. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Sci. 2008 64 857 862 10.1002/ps.1557 <?supplied-pmid 18324612?>18324612 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>33. LiuX.ZhouL.LiuZ.DuS. Identification of insecticidal constituents of the essential oil of Acorus calamus rhizomes against Liposcelis bostrychophila Badonnel Molecules 2013 18 5684 5696 10.3390/molecules18055684 <?supplied-pmid 23676474?>23676474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>34. MoreiraM.D.PicançoM.C.de BarbosaL.C.A.GuedesR.N.C.de CamposM.R.SilvaG.A.MartinsJ.C. Plant compounds insecticide activity against coleoptera pests of stored products Pesqui. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Agropecuária Bras. 2007 42 909 915 10.1590/S0100-204X2007000700001  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>35. SharmaR.NegiD.S.ShiuW.K.P.GibbonsS. Characterization of an insecticidal coumarin from Boenninghausenia albiflora Phyther. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Res. 2006 20 607 609 10.1002/ptr.1909 <?supplied-pmid 16619334?>16619334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>36. HussainA.TianM.Y.HeY.R.AhmedS. Entomopathogenic fungi disturbed the larval growth and feeding performance of Ocinara varians (Lepidoptera: Bombycidae) larvae Insect Sci. 2009 16 511 517 10.1111/j.1744-7917.2009.01272.x  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>37. RashidM.KhanR.A.ZhangY.L. Over-expression of cytochrome P450s in Helicoverpa armigera in response to bioinsecticide, cantharidin Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Agric. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2013 15 993 997  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>38. HalonE.EakteimanG.MoshitzkyP.ElbazM.AlonM.PavlidiN.VontasJ.MorinS. Only a minority of broad-range detoxification genes respond to a variety of phytotoxins in generalist Bemisia tabaci species Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Rep. 2015 5 17975 10.1038/srep17975 <?supplied-pmid 26655836?>26655836 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>39. ZhouB.-G.WangS.DouT.-T.LiuS.LiM.-Y.HuaR.-M.LiS.-G.LinH.-F. Aphicidal activity of Illicium verum fruit extracts and their effects on the Acetylcholinesterase and Glutathione S-transferases activities in Myzus persicae (Hemiptera: Aphididae) J. Insect Sci. 2016 16 11 10.1093/jisesa/iev163 <?supplied-pmid 26826651?>26826651 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>40. FrancisF.VanhaelenN.HaubrugeE. Glutathione S-transferases in the adaptation to plant secondary metabolites in the Myzus persicae aphid Arch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Insect Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Physiol. 2005 58 166 174 10.1002/arch.20049 <?supplied-pmid 15717317?>15717317 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>41. AbbottW.S. A method of computing the effectiveness of an insecticide J. Econ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Entomol. 1925 18 265 267 10.1093/jee/18.2.265a  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>42. RussellR.M.RobertsonJ.L.SavinN.E. POLO: A new computer program for Probit analysis Bull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Entomol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Am. 1977 23 209 213 10.1093/besa/23.3.209  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>43. Statistix Statistix 8.1: Analytical Software 2003 Analytical Software Tallahassee, FL, USA Available online: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://statistix.com">http://statistix.com</ext-link> (accessed on 19 January 2017)  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>44. SAS Institute SAS User’s Guide: Statistics; SAS Institute, Cary 2000 SAS Cary, NC, USA Available online: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.sas.com">www.sas.com</ext-link> (accessed on 19 January 2017)  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45-molecules-22-00169"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>45. LivakK.J.SchmittgenT.D. Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2−ΔΔCT Method Methods 2001 25 402 408 10.1006/meth.2001.1262 <?supplied-pmid 11846609?>11846609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="molecules-22-00169-f001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Percent corrected cumulative dose-mortality response of R. ferrugineus larvae against (a) coumarin; (b) ethyl cinnamate; (c) diniconazole; (d) isoeugenol; (e) coumarin 6; (f) asarone; (g) eugenol; (h) coniferyl aldehyde; (i) rosmarinic acid; (j) methyl isoeugenol; and (k) methyl eugenol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Bars (means ± SE) followed by different letters are significantly different. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>(Fisher’s LSD test, α = 0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="molecules-22-00169-g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="molecules-22-00169-f002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Expression pattern of detoxification genes of red palm weevil larval midguts in response to different phenylpropanoids by qRT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Bars (means ± SE) followed by different letters are significantly different (Fisher’s LSD test, α = 0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="molecules-22-00169-g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="molecules-22-00169-f003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Chemical structures of α-asarone 1, eugenol 2, isoeugenol 3, methyl eugenol 4, methyl isoeugenol 5, coumarin 6, coumarin 6 7, coniferyl aldehyde 8, diniconazole 9, ethyl cinnamate 10, and rosmarinic acid 11. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="molecules-22-00169-g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="molecules-22-00169-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">molecules-22-00169-t001_Table 1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Dose mortality response of red palm weevil larvae against different phenylpropanoids. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Treatments </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>LD50 (g/L) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>95% CL </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>χ2 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Slope ± SE </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Coumarin 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>0.672 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>0.580–0.778 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>4.51 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>1.91 ± 0.25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Ethyl cinnamate 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>6.974 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>6.113–7.955 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>5.60 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>2.07 ± 0.25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Diniconazole 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>9.756 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>8.531–11.158 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>4.42 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>1.99 ± 0.25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Isoeugenol 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>11.560 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>10.080–13.270 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>4.50 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>1.98 ± 0.25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Coumarin 6 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>13.330 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>11.580–15.350 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>1.57 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>1.87 ± 0.25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>α-Asarone 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>17.670 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>15.040–20.750 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>5.94 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>1.80 ± 0.25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Eugenol 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>23.260 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>18.020–30.030 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>1.81 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>1.43 ± 0.25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Coniferyl aldehyde 2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>27.010 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>19.740–36.970 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>1.58 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>1.34 ± 0.25 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Rosmarinic acid 3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>n/a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>n/a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>n/a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>n/a </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Methyl isoeugenol 3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>n/a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>n/a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>n/a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>n/a </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Methyl eugenol 3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>n/a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>n/a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>n/a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>n/a </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>1</sup> LD<sub>50</sub> values were calculated after three days of feeding. <sup>2</sup> LD<sub>50</sub> values were calculated after 12 days of feeding. <sup>3</sup> could not attain LD<sub>50</sub> values because the treatments could not cause 50% mortality within the course of whole experimentation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="molecules-22-00169-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">molecules-22-00169-t002_Table 2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Nutritional indices of red palm weevil larvae against different phenylpropanoids. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Treatments </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>AD </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>ECI </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>ECD </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Coumarin </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>74.01 ± 0.35 a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>05.75 ± 0.53 f </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>07.76 ± 0.71 h </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Ethyl cinnamate </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>60.02 ± 0.15 b </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>15.01 ± 0.17 e </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>25.01 ± 0.30 g </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Diniconazole </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>59.02 ± 0.44 bc </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>16.01 ± 0.11 d </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>27.13 ± 0.20 f </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Isoeugenol </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>58.06 ± 0.50 cd </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>16.88 ± 0.24 c </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>29.09 ± 0.62 e </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Coumarin 6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>57.71 ± 0.32 de </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>17.34 ± 0.21 bc </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>30.05 ± 0.53 de </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>α-Asarone </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>57.17 ± 0.49 de </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>17.52 ± 0.19 bc </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>30.66 ± 0.60 cde </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Eugenol </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>56.72 ± 0.40 ef </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>17.69 ± 0.30 b </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>31.20 ± 0.73 cd </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Coniferyl aldehyde </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>55.92 ± 0.25 fg </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>17.71 ± 0.27 b </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>31.68 ± 0.62 cd </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Rosmarinic acid </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>55.66 ± 0.33 g </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>17.91 ± 0.10 b </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>32.19 ± 0.31 c </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Methyl isoeugenol </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>55.34 ± 0.45 gh </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>18.81 ± 0.40 a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>34.02 ± 0.99 b </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Methyl eugenol </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>54.33 ± 0.36 hi </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>19.03 ± 0.30 a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>35.04 ± 0.74 ab </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Control </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>53.45 ± 0.28 i </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>19.19 ± 0.21 a </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>35.91 ± 0.58 a </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Means ± SE values having the same letter(s) within the column are not significantly different (Fisher’s LSD test, α = 0.05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="molecules-22-00169-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">molecules-22-00169-t003_Table 3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>Target genes and primer sequences used for quantitative PCR expression analysis of detoxification genes from red palm weevil larvae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>Target Gene </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Accession No </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Amplicon Size </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Primer 5′–3′ (Forward and Reverse) </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Detoxification </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text></text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text></text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text></text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Cytochrome P450 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>KT748789 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>118 bp </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>TGGAGAAACACCCGCAAGAA CGGCGATTTTGCCTACCAAG </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>Glutathione S-transferase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>KR902496 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>92 bp </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>ATAGCCAACCACCACTGTCG CGTTCCTCTTGCCGCTAGTT </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Esterase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>KT748822 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>70 bp </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>ACCTACAAGAATCCGACGCC ACTCCGAAACTTTGGGCCAT </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Housekeeping </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text></text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text></text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text></text></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>beta-Actin </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>KM438516 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>129 bp </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>AAAGGTTCCGTTGCCCTGAA TGGCGTACAAGTCCTTCCTG </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
