<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Endocrinol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Endocrinology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-2392</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6389629</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2019.00078</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Endocrinology</subject><subj-group><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The Gonadotropin-Inhibitory Hormone: What We Know and What We Still Have to Learn From Fish </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Di Yorio</surname><given-names>María P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/669438/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Muñoz-Cueto</surname><given-names>José A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/19701/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Paullada-Salmerón</surname><given-names>José A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/477027/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Somoza</surname><given-names>Gustavo M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/19708/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tsutsui</surname><given-names>Kazuyoshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/10812/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vissio</surname><given-names>Paula G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/154308/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Departamento de Biodiversidad y Biología Experimental, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales, Universidad de Buenos Aires</institution>, <addr-line>Buenos Aires</addr-line>, <country>Argentina</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Instituto de Biodiversidad y Biología Experimental y Aplicada (IBBEA), CONICET-Universidad de Buenos Aires</institution>, <addr-line>Buenos Aires</addr-line>, <country>Argentina</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Biology, Faculty of Marine and Environmental Sciences, University of Cádiz</institution>, <addr-line>Puerto Real</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Marine Research Institute (INMAR), Marine Campus of International Excellence (CEIMAR) and Agrifood Campus of International Excellence (ceiA3)</institution>, <addr-line>Puerto Real</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Instituto Tecnológico de Chascomús (CONICET-UNSAM)</institution>, <addr-line>Chascomús</addr-line>, <country>Argentina</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup><institution>Department of Biology and Center for Medical Life Science, Waseda University</institution>, <addr-line>Tokyo</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Edited by: Honoo Satake, Suntory Foundation for Life Sciences, Japan </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Reviewed by: Hironori Ando, Niigata University, Japan; Satoshi Ogawa, Monash University Malaysia, Malaysia </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Paula G. Vissio <email>pvissio@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>This article was submitted to Experimental Endocrinology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Endocrinology </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>78</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2019 Di Yorio, Muñoz-Cueto, Paullada-Salmerón, Somoza, Tsutsui and Vissio.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Di Yorio, Muñoz-Cueto, Paullada-Salmerón, Somoza, Tsutsui and Vissio</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone, GnIH, is named because of its function in birds and mammals; however, in other vertebrates this function is not yet clearly established. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>More than half of the vertebrate species are teleosts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>This group is characterized by the 3R whole genome duplication, a fact that could have been responsible for the great phenotypic complexity and great variability in reproductive strategies and sexual behavior. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>In this context, we revise GnIH cell bodies and fibers distribution in adult brains of teleosts, discuss its relationship with GnRH variants and summarize the few reports available about the ontogeny of the GnIH system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Considering all the information presented in this review, we propose that in teleosts, GnIH could have other functions beyond reproduction or act as an integrative signal in the reproductive process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>However, further studies are required in order to clarify the role of GnIH in this group including its involvement in development, a key stage that strongly impacts on adult life. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>GnIH</kwd><kwd>fish</kwd><kwd>brain</kwd><kwd>ontogeny</kwd><kwd>GnRH</kwd><kwd>growth</kwd><kwd>reproduction</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Agencia Nacional de Promoción Científica y Tecnológica<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100003074</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn001">PICT 2015-2783</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002">Universidad de Buenos Aires<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100005363</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn002">20020160100110BA</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn003">Consejo Nacional para Investigaciones Científicas y Tecnológicas<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100010268</named-content></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn004">Junta de Andalucía<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100011011</named-content></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn005">Seventh Framework Programme<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/100011102</named-content></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="97"/><page-count count="11"/><word-count count="9256"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>In 2000, Tsutsui's group isolated, for the first time, a novel hypothalamic neuropeptide from the brain of the Japanese quail, Coturnix japonica, which inhibited luteinizing hormone (LH) release from the anterior pituitary and named it gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone (GnIH) (1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>This finding had the novelty that, at that moment, it was known that gonadotropin secretion was mainly under the stimulatory effect of gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH), but an inhibitory neuropeptide of gonadotropin secretion had been not discovered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The discovery of GnIH opened a new research field in reproductive neuroendocrinology from a novel standpoint. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Since then, GnIH orthologs were described in protochordates (2) and many vertebrate taxa including agnathans, teleosts, amphibians, reptiles, birds, and mammals [for review see (3, 4)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>In some of these groups, it is clear that GnIH is involved in the regulation of reproduction, inhibition of pituitary gonadotropins, and sexual behavior [for reviews see (5–9)]; however, up to this moment this is far to be a common feature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>After Tsutsui's first finding (1), Satake et al. (10) characterized in quail a cDNA encoding GnIH and two GnIH-related peptides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Later, in most vertebrate species, these peptides were deduced from the cDNA sequences of their precursors, but the GnIH peptide was isolated and identified only in a few species: quail (1), starlings (11), zebra finches (12), chicken (13), rats (14), Siberian hamsters (15), bullfrog (16), turtles (17), primates (18), humans (19), and goldfish (20). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>All these GnIH orthologs have an Arg-Phe-amide as a C-terminal sequence and thus, they are part of the RF-amide family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Particularly, GnIH and its related peptides, either putative or identified, possess a common LPXRFamide or MPXRFamide (X: L or Q) C-terminus motif [for reviews see (5–9)]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>It is known that more than half of the vertebrate species are teleosts, and teleost-3R genome duplication could have been responsible for the great phenotypic complexity observed in this group of vertebrates (21). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>They occupy all aquatic environments and present a tremendous variability of reproductive strategies and sexual behavior (22). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In this context, fish GnIH and their related peptides could have undertaken new and maybe unexpected functions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Early-branching lineages of ray-finned fishes (such as gars) and teleosts already present a GnIH precursor suggesting that this peptide emerged before to the teleost whole genome duplication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Early-branching lineages of teleosts, such as anguiliforms and otophysans (Cypriniformes, Characiformes, and Siluriformes), and salmoniforms, ovalentarians (some Cichliformes, Cyprinodontiformes, Atheriniformes, and Beloniformes) (23) and some Pleuronectiformes (24), exhibit a GnIH precursor encoding three peptides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>However, in late-branching evolved species belonging to ovalentarians (some Cichliformes, Perciformes), Pleuronectiformes and Tetraodontiformes, two peptides were described (3) (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Then, it seems that species belonging to early branching teleost lineages contain GnIH and 2 related peptides, whereas those species belonging to late branching lineages possessed GnIH and 1 or 2 related peptides, suggesting that one was lost in the course of teleost evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The meaning of this fact is still unknown, but it represents an interesting matter of study in neuropeptide evolution (3, 25). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic tree of fish showing the different orders in which GnIH precursor genes have been identified and the number of LPXRFamide peptides present in these GnIH precursors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The amino acid motifs present in the C-terminal region of these LPXRFamide peptides are also presented. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>SP, signal peptide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The accession numbers of the identified and possible GnIH precursor sequences obtained from US National Center for Biotechnology Information database are: Lepisosteiformes: Atractosteus tropicus (Álvarez-González, C.A., personal communication; transcriptome sequencing: PRJNA395289), Lepisosteus oculatus (XP_015213317.1); Elopomorpha: Anguila japonica (XP_013998456.1); Cypriniformes: Carassius auratus (BAC06473.1), Catla catla (AUO16369.1), Cyprinus carpio (AML83913.1), Danio rerio (NP_001076418.1), Pygocentrus natteri (XP_017549097.1), Sinocyclocheilus grahami (XP_016150344.1), Sinocyclocheilus rhinocerous (XP_016370559.1); Siluriformes: Ictalurus punctatus (XP_017336524.1); Salmoniformes: Salmo salar (XP_013998456.1); Carangaria: Cynoglossus semilaevis (AMB48604.1), Paralichthys orbignyanus (Mechaly A.S., personal communication), Solea senegalensis (24); Ovalentaria: Austrofundulus limnaeus (XP_013866639.1), C. dimerus (25), Cyprinodon variegates (XP_015229614.1), Fundulus heteroclitus (XP_012729657.1), Iconisemion striatum (SBP35361.1), Kryptolebias marmoratus (XP_017278134.1), Neolamprologus brichardi (XM_006788075.1), Nothobranchius furzeri (XP_015811406.1), Nothobranchius kuhntae (SBQ91527.1), Nothobranchius pienaari (SBR89569.1), Odontesthes bonariensis (Somoza G.M., personal communication), Oreochromis niloticus (NP_001298256.1), Oryzias latipes (XP_004073896.1), Poecilia formosa (XP_007562706.1), Poecilia latipinna (XP_014884496.1), Poecilia mexicana (XP_014852162.1), Poecilia reticulata (XP_008419875.1), Pundamilia nyererei (XP_013765199.1), Stegastes partitus (XP_008290012.1), Xiphophorus maculatus (XP_005802819.1); Eupercaria: Dicentrarchus labrax (CEK03537.1), Takifugu rubripes (NP_001092115.1), Tetraodon nigroviridis (BAF34880.1), Thalassomabi fasciatum (ANV28067.1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic tree was taken from Figure 1 of Betancur et al. (23). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fendo-10-00078-g0001"/></fig></SecTag></sec></SecTag><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The GnIH System in Fish </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Neuroanatomical Distribution of GnIH Cell Bodies and Fibers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In order to gain understanding about the GnIH system in fishes, several studies have investigated the precise localization of GnIH-producing cells in the brain and peripheral organs of teleosts by using PCR, in situ hybridization and immunohistochemical techniques [for review see (3)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Although these studies have reported important consistencies in the brain GnIH innervation pattern, the localization of GnIH cell bodies showed considerable dissimilarities in many of the analyzed species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>For instance, in sockeye salmon, Oncorhynchus nerka, (26) and tilapia, Oreochromis niloticus (27), immunohistochemistry revealed the presence of GnIH-immunoreactive (GnIH-ir) cells only in the diencephalic posterior periventricular nucleus (NPPv), whereas studies developed in other species reported the presence of GnIH-ir cell populations also in other brain regions (3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>In this sense, increasing evidence obtained in the last years also suggest that GnIH neurons in teleosts are not only restricted to the caudal preoptic area/hypothalamus (24, 25, 28–31), as it occurs in birds and mammals (32) (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Schematic representation of a sagittal section of the fish brain showing GnIH cell populations described in several brain areas of different fish species, which are represented by gray circles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The red circle indicates the presence of GnIH cells in the nucleus posterioris periventricularis (NPPv) that has been reported in all fish species studied until now. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>OB, olfactory bulb; Tel, telencephalon; Hyp, hypothalamus; OT, optic tectum; Pit, pituitary; Cer, cerebellum; M, medulla. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fendo-10-00078-g0002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Analyzing the cell clusters reported in fish species from the forebrain to the hindbrain, the most rostral GnIH-cell population described is the one present in the olfactory bulb or terminal nerve ganglion cells (TNgc)/the nucleus olfacto retinalis (NOR) of goldfish, Carassius auratus (20); developing Indian major carp, Labeo rohita (33); sea bass, Dicentrarchus labrax (29); cichlid fish, Cichlasoma dimerus (25); zebrafish, Danio rerio (30); sole, Solea senegalesis (24), and pejerrey, Odontesthes bonariensis (31). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>This immunostaining was consistent with gnih expression detected in these areas of sea bass brain by RT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Moreover, these results were confirmed by sensitive laser-capture microdissection followed by quantitative real-time PCR (29). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Similar analysis and/or in situ hybridization studies in this brain region appear necessary to confirm the presence of GnIH in these cells in other teleost species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>More recently, immunohistochemical studies also showed that GnIH neurons are located in this transitional region between the olfactory bulbs and telencephalic hemispheres of pejerrey, Odontesthes bonariensis, an atheriniform species (31), and the tropical gar, Atractosteus tropicus, an ancient lepisosteiform fish (28). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>More caudally, in the ventral telencephalic area, another GnIH-cell population was described, for the first time, in sea bass (29). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Similarly, Aliaga-Guerrero et al. (24) reported the presence of GnIH-ir neurons in the central and lateral subdivision of the ventral telencephalon using specific antibodies developed against sole GnIH. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>In the diencephalon, GnIH-ir neurons were detected in the suprachiasmatic nucleus in the tropical gar (28); while, in the India major carp, GnIH-cell masses were observed in the magnocellular preoptic nucleus (NOPm) (33). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Among the diencephalic GnIH cell masses identified in different species, the one present in the posterior periventricular nucleus (NPPv) of the caudal preoptic area is the most conserved in all fish species studied so far, including goldfish (20), sockeye salmon (26), Indian major carp (33), orange-spotted grouper, Epinephelus coioides (34), sea bass (29), tilapia (27), Cichlasoma dimerus (25), pejerrey (31), zebrafish (35), sole (24), and tropical gar (28). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Moreover, in agnathans, the most ancient lineage of vertebrates, a lamprey gnih precursor mRNA was only expressed in the rostral and caudal regions of the bed nucleus of the tract of the postoptic commissure (nTPOC) in the hypothalamus (36). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The presence of other, but more posterior, hypothalamic GnIH-ir cell population was also seen in tropical gar, within the tuberal hypothalamus (28). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>In addition, GnIH-ir cells were also present in the dorsal mesencephalic tegmentum, as well as the rostral rhombencephalon of Indian major carp, sea bass and sole (24, 29, 33). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The analysis of gnih expression in the mesencephalic tegmentum confirmed these neurons as genuine GnIH-expressing cells by using sensitive laser-capture microdissection followed by quantitative real-time PCR in sea bass (29). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The profuse innervation of GnIH cells in the brain is a common feature of all birds and mammals studied so far, as well as in fishes (20, 24–29, 31, 33). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>This pattern of the distribution of GnIH projections strongly suggests that GnIH acts in many brain sites and then its function can be not only related to reproduction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>GnIH Fiber Projections to the Pituitary Gland </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>In fish, GnIH-ir fibers were found running along the ventral hypothalamus, reaching the infundibulum to project into the pituitary [for review see (3)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>It is important to highlight to the readers who are not specialized in fish neuroendocrinology, that nerve terminals of hypophysiotropic neuroendocrine cells from fish can establish direct contacts (like a “synaptic terminal”) or end close to pituitary cells to release their neurohormones (37), and they do not exhibit neither a median eminence nor the portal vasculature reported in tetrapods (38). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>These fibers were found in the proximal pars distalis (PPD) of goldfish (20), sockeye salmon (26), sea bass (29), tilapia (27), zebrafish (35), pejerrey (31), and sole (24) and, more recently, they were also found in the neurohypophysis of the tropical gar (28). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The presence of GnIH-ir fibers in the PPD reinforces the role of this neuropeptide in the regulation of pituitary hormone secretion also in fish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, GnIH-ir fibers were observed in close proximity to FSH, LH, and GH cells in the pituitary of sea bass (29), and FSH, LH, POMC, and α-MSH cells in the pituitary of tilapia (27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, GnIH-pituitary innervation has not been demonstrated in adult specimens of other fish species, such as the Indian mayor carp and C. dimerus (25, 33). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>However, we cannot discard that a sexual-stage-dependent plasticity in the GnIH-pituitary innervation, or a neurovascular supply to the pituitary, exists as it was reported in zebrafish (39). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>GnIH and Photoperiodic Control of Reproduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Much has been written about the role of the GnIH system in transducing and/or mediating photoperiodic effects on reproduction through its interactions with the pineal organ and retina in vertebrates (40–43). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The pineal organ of fish is a light-sensitive structure responsible for the nocturnal production of melatonin, playing a central role in the transduction of daily and seasonal information (44). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>To date in fish, only a few studies have investigated the links between GnIH and melatonin (45–49). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>In cinnamon clownfish, Amphipirion melanopus, it was shown that GnIH and the melatonin receptor MT1 co-localized in diencephalic cells (46). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Moreover, it has been reported the existence of day-night differences in the expression of gnih in sea bass, suggesting a role of melatonin in the modulation of the GnIH system in this species (50). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, GnIH fibers were localized in the pineal organ of sea bass (29), sole (24), pejerrey (31), and tropical gar (28), suggesting the existence of bidirectional connections between the pineal organ and GnIH cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Besides GnIH-ir fibers were found in the vascular sac of sea bass (29), sole (24) and C. dimerus (51), an organ that represents a sensor of daily and seasonal changes in day length and has been involved in the photoperiodic control of reproduction and other rhythmic processes in some teleost species (52). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The interactions between GnIH and both sensor systems (pineal organ and vascular sac) could imply a role of GnIH in the relay between environment and seasonal reproduction in this group of vertebrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Other studies observed that gnih was expressed in the retina of different fish species, such as sea bass (29), zebrafish (30), sole (24), and C. dimerus (51). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>However, only one report relating retinal GnIH with the reproductive cycle has been published so far, showing a decrease in retinal gnih expression in late-vitellogenic zebrafish females (30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The fact that GnIH is expressed in the retina could indicate its modulatory role in this photosensory organ, but further studies appear necessary to clarify the physiological significance of this GnIH action. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>GnIH Receptors </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The study of distribution of GnIH receptors (GnIH-R) has provided relevant information to recognize the neural targets of GnIH cells, helping to identify new putative roles of this neuropeptide in the brain and peripheral organs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, the precise identification of GnIH-R containing cells is still scarce and only a few studies have used molecular tools and antibodies to address its detailed localization in the fish brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Both GnIH-ir fibers and GnIH-R were widely distributed in the tilapia brain but they were particularly evident in cells bodies of the preoptic area, hypothalamus, optic tectum, semicircular torus, and caudal midbrain tegmentum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>They also coexist in the olfactory bulbs, ventral/dorsal telencephalon and in the rhombencephalon (27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>In addition, GnIH-R immunoreactivity was found in LH, ACTH, and α-MSH cells of tilapia pituitary (27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Moreover, three different GnIH-R subtypes have been identified in goldfish (53) and zebrafish (54), but their presence in other fish is still not reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>In goldfish, three subtypes of GnIH-Rs were localized in neuroendocrine regions as the preoptic area and the NPPv, the preoptic nucleus (NPO), and the lateral tuberal nucleus (NLT), whereas only two GnIH-R subtypes (GnIH-R1 and GnIH-R2) were observed in the pars intermedia of the pituitary gland. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, no signals of GnIH-R were observed in the proximal and rostral pars distalis of the goldfish pituitary (54). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the presence of gnih-r transcripts was also revealed in the brain and pituitary of zebrafish (53), grass puffer, Takifugu niphobles (45), and tongue sole, Cynoglossus semilaevis (55), by using RT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>In addition, RT-PCR and in situ hybridization studies have reported the expression of gnih and gnih-r in some peripheral fish organs, including the gonads (24, 25, 29, 30, 34, 45, 46, 53, 54, 56–58), which could indicate an autocrine/paracrine role of GnIH in gonadal function. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>GnIH and GnRH Relationships </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>It is well-established that in vertebrates, multiple GnRH variants are expressed by different neurons in the brain of a single species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>These variants are currently classified into three different types, according to their amino-acid sequence, neuroanatomical localization, embryological origin, and synteny: GnRH1, GnRH2, and GnRH3 [for review see (59)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>In the case of teleost fish, GnRH1, the most variable GnRH type according to its amino-acid sequence, is expressed in neurons originated from the olfactory placode during embryogenesis (59–62) and plays the classical hypophysiotropic function in most species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>GnRH2 is mainly produced by midbrain tegmental neurons and it has been proposed that plays a key role in reproductive behavior [for review see (63)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Finally, GnRH3 is expressed in ventral forebrain neurons, from the olfactory bulbs to the hypothalamus, and seems to act as a neuromodulator of olfactory and visual information related to reproduction (64, 65). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>This variant also plays hypophysiotropic functions especially in those teleost species expressing two GnRH variants: GnRH2 and GnRH3 as most of Cypriniformes and Salmoniformes (38, 66). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>In birds and mammals, GnIH regulates gonadotrophs' function either directly or indirectly via GnRH neurons (11, 67–69). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Considering that GnRH is the key neuropeptide in the control of gonadotropin synthesis and secretion, it could be the candidate through which GnIH acts in fish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>In this conceptual frame, several studies have analyzed the relationship between both systems, although most of the mare focused on physiological approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Even though it could be considered that morphological associations may allow us to infer physiological interactions, there is scarce information on the relationship between GnIH and GnRH neurons in fishes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>GnIH-GnRH1 Neuroanatomical Interactions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>As it was previously mentioned, GnRH1 is the main hypophisiotropic variant in most fishes, but neither in tilapia (27) nor in C. dimerus (70), axo-somatic or fiber-fiber contacts were observed between GnRH1 and GnIH neurons; although, in C. dimerus GnIH axons were detected in close proximity to GnRH1 fibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Additionally, in sea bass (71) and zebrafish (35), GnIH terminals contacted GnRH1 cells or GnRH3 in the preoptic area, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Taking into consideration these results, it is possible that either there are interspecific differences in this interaction, or it shows plasticity depending on the sexual stage, as it was suggested in sea bass (71) and C. dimerus (70). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Another possibility is that GnIH can modulate other neurons, as those producing kisspeptin, dopamine or neuropeptide Y, to control gonadotropin secretion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>For instance, in zebrafish, GnIH-immunoreactive fibers were observed interacting with kisspeptin receptor-1a-expressing neurons in the preoptic area (35), and a GnIH innervation on Kiss2 cells of the nucleus of the lateral recess has been reported in sea bass (71), although in tilapia, GnIH cells do not seem to be connected with either GnRH1, GnRH3 or kisspeptin neurons (27). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>GnIH-GnRH2 Neuroanatomical Interactions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>In Indian major carp (33), sea bass (29), and sole (24) a cluster of GnIH somas were localized in the midbrain; however, this is not a common feature of all analyzed species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Only one study reported the GnRH2 and GnIH relationship and demonstrated fiber-to-fiber contacts in the nucleus lateralis tuberis and the midbrain tegmentum, suggesting a possible regulation between them (70). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>This GnIH-GnRH2 association could represent the morphological substrate of a network mediating the transduction of environmental information to the reproductive axis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>This is further supported by the interactions among GnRH2, GnIH and melatonin reported in several fish species (24, 29, 46–48, 72, 73). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>GnIH-GnRH3 Neuroanatomical Interactions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Finally, GnRH3 and GnIH neurons were observed in the TNgc of most fish species [for review see, (20, 24, 25, 29, 30, 53, 62)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The co-localization of both peptides in the same neurons was observed in C. dimerus since early developmental stages (51) and in adults of this species (70), pejerrey (31), and sea bass (Figures 3A,B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a deeper study on co-localization showed, for the first time, that GnIH and GnRH3 peptides are localized in different neurosecretory vesicles (Figure 3C), suggesting that both peptides can be independently regulated and secreted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>It is also interesting to notice that in most of the brain regions analyzed in C. dimerus, some fibers co-expressed GnRH3 and GnIH; whereas some other fibers only expressed GnRH3 or GnIH, suggesting that these fibers correspond to neurons located in other brain areas as the NPPv (for GnIH) or from the OB, ventral TEL and POA (for GnRH3) (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>However, no contacts between GnRH3 fibers and GnIH neurons were observed (70). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Coexpression of GnIH and GnRH3 in the terminal nerve area of sea bass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>GnRH3 positive immunolabeling (red, A) and GnIH positive immunolabeling (green, B) in the same cell bodies of the terminal nerve region, presenting evidence of co-expression of these two neurohormones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Images (A,B) were captured on a conventional fluorescence photomicroscope. (C) High resolution confocal image presenting evidence for the co-localization of GnIH (green) and GnRH3 (red) in the same cell bodies, but packaged in separate neurosecretory vesicles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In A and B, the nuclei of cells are stained with DAPI (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>TNgc: terminal nerve ganglion cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Scale bars = 100 μm in (A,B), and 50 μm in (C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fendo-10-00078-g0003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Double-labeling immunofluorescence in parasagittal brain sections of 27 days post-hatching C. dimerus larvae using GnIH and GnRH3-GAP antisera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Microphotographs present GnRH3-GAP-immunoreactive (GnRH3) neurons (red, A) and GnIH-immunoreactive (GnIH) neurons (green, B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>In (C), a merge image of (A,B) is presented. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Immunoreactive cell somata are indicated by arrows and some representative fibers appear marked by arrowheads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Co-localization is indicated by asterisks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Scale bar: 200 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>OB, olfactory bulb; NOR, nucleus olfacto retinalis; Tel, telencephalon; Hyp, hypothalamus; OT, optic tectum; MBT, midbrain tegmentum; E, eye. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fendo-10-00078-g0004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Physiological Interactions Between GnIH and GnRHs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The physiological action of GnIH on GnRH synthesis and its modulating effects over GnRH-stimulatory action on the synthesis and release of gonadotropins or GH are summarized in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>From these data, GnIH can prevent the GnRH-stimulatory action on the synthesis and/or release of FSH, LH, and GH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>For example, Moussavi et al. (74, 75) showed that when GnRH2 or GnRH3 are co-administrated with goldfish GnIH-III (gGnIH-III), the stimulatory action of GnRH2/GnRH3 on LH secretion was attenuated by goldfish GnIH-III, together with lhβ or fshβ synthesis, especially during mid and late recrudescence (74); while gGnIH-III prevented GnRH2/GnRH3 stimulation of gh transcript levels and GH secretion (75). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Moreover, gGnIH-III differentially affected GnRH2 and GnRH3 actions depending on the sexual stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Similar effects of GnIH peptides were demonstrated in Amphiprion melanopus (46) and in Astyanax altiparanae (78). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>This preventive-GnRH-stimulatory effect has been proposed to depend on the action of estradiol or neuroestrogen levels; the abundance of GnIH-R, GnRH and estrogen receptors, and the inhibition of cAMP pathways or the hyperpolarization of gonadotropes by activating K+, both exerted by the activation of GnIH-R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Other possibility is that GnIH-R and GnRH-R could form heterodimers modifying the action of their ligands on gonadotrophs [for review see (79)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Although these statements have been mostly established in birds and mammals (80, 81), there is evidence that a similar mechanism could be operating in teleosts (34, 55, 82, 83). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, GnIH can stimulate, inhibit, or even have no effect on the synthesis of GnRH variants (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>These discrepancies could be due to differences in sexual stage, route of administration, sampling times and brain regions analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Also, based on studies performed in birds and mammals, it has been proposed that GnIH could indirectly modulate the expression and activity of brain aromatase regulating estradiol levels locally [for review see (79)]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Nowadays, further studies appear necessary to clarify GnIH actions over gonadotropin secretion and/or synthesis in fish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>According to anatomical and physiological results presented in this section, it must be emphasized that GnIH interaction with GnRH occurs in fish, and either directly or indirectly GnIH can stimulate or inhibits hypothalamic-pituitary axis depending on the reproductive state of individuals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Ontogeny of GnIH System </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>As Sandvik et al. (84) referred, although RFamide peptides are poorly studied during development, the few reports available in the field show interesting results indicating that many of these peptides have different roles in early stages and in adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The few studies addressing GnIH ontogeny show that this peptide is not an exception. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>To date, there are only four studies analyzing the GnIH expression pattern during fish development, showing that this peptide is detected from early developmental stages (33, 50, 51, 53). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>In zebrafish gnih and gnih-r transcripts were detected from 1-day post-fertilization (dpf) (prime-5 stage) or blastula stage, respectively; however, in this study, no temporal variations in the expression were evaluated (53). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>In sea bass, gnih and gnih-r transcripts were detected from 5 dpf, and although the authors did not quantify the expression in stages prior to hatching, two temporal increases in the gnih messengers were observed: one from 5 days post-hatching (dph) to 25 dph, when the larva starts exogenous feeding and the gonad is still undifferentiated, and the other by 150 dph during the onset of gonadal differentiation (50). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Studies performed in C. dimerus showed that gnih was first detected at 1 dph, increased from 12 dph and reached a peak at 20 dph, when the development of gonadal primordia occurred (51). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>As we previously mentioned, in different species one or more GnIH cell clusters were observed apart from that of NPPv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The spatial-temporal expression pattern of these nuclei could suggest different origins or functions during development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>For example, in the Indian major carp, GnIH cells were observed in the NPPv and in the olfactory system (epithelium and bulb) at hatching. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>This mentioned area showed no GnIH-ir in adults, suggesting a role of these cells during development (33). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>By contrast, in C. dimerus GnIH neurons in the NOR was detected by 3 dph, while NPPv cells by 14 dph (51). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The cells in the NOR increase in number from 5 dph, coinciding with the time when larvae start to feed exogenously, and continue to increase in number during the development and differentiation of gonadal primordia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>In the same direction, it was observed an increase of NPPv cell number during the development and differentiation of the gonadal primordia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Based on these results, it is suggested that GnIH could be involved in the onset of feeding and gonadal development or sex differentiation in teleosts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>This new concept is supported by the variations of gnih and gnih-r levels in sea bass and C.dimerus during these critical periods of early gonadal development (50, 51). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, during development GnIH fibers innervate different brain regions (33, 51). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Particularly in C. dimerus, the presence of GnIH fibers was observed reaching the pituitary from 14 dph to 85 dph, but they clearly diminished from 37 dph on (51). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Considering that GnRH1 fibers were detected at 30 dph (85), we could speculate a shift in the neuroendocrine control of pituitary function occurring before gonadal differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The fact that no GnIH fibers innervating the pituitary gland were detected in adults of this species (25), could imply that this neuropeptide would act differently in larvae and adults. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Biotic and abiotic factors, especially temperature and photoperiod, are critical features that could irreversibly affect different biological aspects during development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Even though the neuroendocrine system integrates environmental information, little is known about its development and how it is altered by these factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>For example, low or high incubation temperatures during early developmental stages determine different sex ratio of pejerrey and sea bass larvae (86, 87) indicating that the reproductive axis, at some point, has been altered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, only one study reported the effect of temperature and photoperiod on GnIH system during development (50). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>In this study, sea bass reared at high temperature, showed a decrease in the expression of gnih and gnih-r, suggesting that this neuropeptide could be involved in the reported effect of temperature on sex differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a seasonal shift in a daily variation of GnIH system related to the reproductive season was demonstrated, indicating the influence of the photoperiod on this system (50). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>In summary, GnIH in fish development is an almost unexplored area, so more studies are needed in order to further elucidate its role at this particular stage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Expanding GnIH Functions Beyond Reproduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Since the discovery of GnIH, most studies have analyzed the effect of this peptide on the reproductive axis, leaving aside their possible role in the regulation of other functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>In this sense, neuroanatomical localization studies showed in all fish species analyzed that GnIH fibers are broadly distributed along the nervous system, not only in the preoptic-hypothalamic area but also in the retina-optic tract and midbrain, suggesting a potential role of GnIH as neuromodulator or neurotransmitter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>In sea bass, GnIH seems to participate in the regulation of fish behavior, as their administration affected the diurnal/nocturnal ratio of locomotors activity during the reproductive cycle (48, 77). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>It is important to highlight that in this species a cluster of GnIH cells was observed in the midbrain innervating sensory-motor areas (29). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, there is increasing evidence regarding the effect of GnIH on the synthesis and release of GH (25, 26, 57, 75, 76, 88). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Usually, after GnIH administration different responses on the GH synthesis and release were observed depending on the species or the experimental approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>For example, in vitro administration of GnIH stimulated GH release in sockeye salmon and C. dimerus (25, 26) while in grass puffer, GnIH can increase the abundance of gh messengers (88). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>However, icv administration of GnIH decreased gh in sea bass (76), whereas intraperitoneal administration of GnIH did not affect GH release in tilapia (57). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>However, also concerning to GH regulation, a clear dependence on the reproductive status and on the experimental approach was observed in goldfish (75). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, these results indicate that GnIH exerts complex effects on basal and GnRH-stimulated somatotrope function in a seasonal-reproductive manner, and thus, this peptide could be involved in the regulation of somatic growth and/or in the interaction between growth and reproduction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Finally, the ventral telencephalon and the NPPv also exhibit neuropeptide Y (NPY) producing cells in several fish species (89–91). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>NPY has been implicated in the modulation of gonadotropin release, but also in the regulation of feeding and growth (38, 92). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Since GnIH cells are observed in these regions, it is suggested that this neuropeptide could establish a crosstalk among growth, feeding, and reproductive axes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Whether GnIH and NPY are interacting to modulate reproduction, feeding and growth in fish remains to be elucidated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, although the effects of GnIH on reproduction are very clear in birds and mammals, there are still some inconsistencies in fishes that should be addressed soon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Because of our attempt to generalize GnIH function, it is possible that different modes of action or other roles beyond reproduction are leaving aside in fishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Moreover, as reproduction is a complex event that involves the integration of internal and external cues, it is possible that GnIH acts as a link among them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, recent mutation studies for reproductive neuroendocrine factors have shown that, contrary to mammals, kisspeptin, and GnRH null fish can reproduce normally, suggesting a compensatory multifactorial neuroendocrine control of reproduction (93–97). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Notably, they found an up-regulation of different neuropeptides involved in the control of reproduction in zebrafish including GnIH (97). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>According Marvel et al. (97), the up-regulation of GnIH messengers could be related to the action of GnIH as a stimulator of pituitary gonadotropins, as it was already demonstrated in some teleost fish species (25, 74). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Further studies are still required in order to clarify the role of GnIH in teleosts including its involvement in development, a key stage that strongly impacts on adult biology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec id="s6"><title><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Author Contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>MD, JM-C, JP-S, GS, KT, and PV contributed equally to the manuscript and approved it for publication. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Conflict of Interest Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>We thank Dr. Guillermo Ortí (The George Washington University) for his advice in fish systematic and Dr. Daniela I. Pérez Sirkin and Mr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Federico Obertello for their valuable contributions. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Funding. This work was supported by Agencia Nacional de Promoción Científica y Tecnológica (PICT 2015-2783 to GS), Universidad de Buenos Aires (20020160100110BA to PV), Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas y Técnicas (CONICET) (11220130100501CO to PV), Junta de Andalucía (P10-AGR-05916 to JM-C), and the European Union's Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013, grant no. 331964 to JM-C). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>1.TsutsuiKSaigohEUkenaKTeranishiHFujisawaYKikuchiM. A novel avian hypothalamic peptide inhibiting gonadotropin release. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>(2000) 275:6612–7. 10.1006/bbrc.2000.3350<?supplied-pmid 10964719?>10964719 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>2.OsugiTOkamuraTSonYLOhkuboMUbukaTHenmiY. Evolutionary origin of GnIH and NPFF in chordates: insights from novel amphioxus RFamide peptides. PLoS ONE (2014) 9:e100962. 10.1371/journal.pone.0100962<?supplied-pmid 24983238?>24983238 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>3.Muñoz-CuetoJAPaullada-SalmerónJAAliaga-GuerreroMCowanMEParharISUbukaT. A journey through the gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone system of fish. Front Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>(2017) 8:285. 10.3389/fendo.2017.00285<?supplied-pmid 29163357?>29163357 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>4.TsutsuiKOsugiTSonYLUbukaT. Review: structure, function and evolution of GnIH. Gen Comp Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>(2018) 264:48–57. 10.1016/j.ygcen.2017.07.024<?supplied-pmid 28754274?>28754274 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>5.TsutsuiK Review: a new key neurohormone controlling reproduction, gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone (GnIH): biosynthesis, mode of action and functional significance. Prog Neurobiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>(2009) 88:76–88. 10.1016/j.pneurobio.2009.02.00319428963 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>6.TsutsuiK. How to contribute to the progress of neuroendocrinology: new insights from discovering novel neuropeptides and neurosteroids regulating pituitary and brain functions. Gen Comp Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>(2016) 227:3–15. 10.1016/j.ygcen.2015.05.019<?supplied-pmid 26145291?>26145291 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>7.TsutsuiKBentleyGEBedecarratsGOsugiTUbukaTKriegsfeldLJ Review: gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone (GnIH) and its control of central and peripheral reproductive function. Front Neuroendocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>(2010) 31:284–95. 10.1016/j.yfrne.2010.03.00120211640 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>8.TsutsuiKBentleyGEKriegsfeldLJOsugiTSeongJYVaudryH Review: discovery and evolutionary history of gonadotrophin-inhibitory hormone and kisspeptin: new key neuropeptides controlling reproduction. J Neuroendocrinol. (2010) 22:716–27. 10.1111/j.1365-2826.2010.02018.x20456604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>9.TsutsuiKUbukaTSonYLBentleyGEKriegsfeldLJ. Contribution of GnIH research to the progress of reproductive neuroendocrinology. Front Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>(2015) 6:179. 10.3389/fendo.2015.00179<?supplied-pmid 26635728?>26635728 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>10.SatakeHHisadaMKawadaTMinakataHUkenaKTsutsuiK. Characterization of a cDNA encoding a novel avian hypothalamic neuropeptide exerting an inhibitory effect on gonadotropin release. Biochem J. (2001) 354:379–85. 10.1042/bj3540379<?supplied-pmid 11171117?>11171117 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>11.UbukaTKimSHuangYCReidJJiangJOsugiT. Gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone neurons interact directly with gonadotropin-releasing hormone-I and -II neurons in European starling brain. Endocrinol (2008) 149:268–78. 10.1210/en.2007-0983<?supplied-pmid 17901228?>17901228 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>12.TobariYIijimaNTsunekawaKOsugiTOkanoyaKTsutsuiK. Identification of gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone in the zebra finch (Taeniopygia guttata): peptide isolation, cDNA cloning and brain distribution. Peptides (2010) 31:816–26. 10.1016/j.peptides.2010.01.015<?supplied-pmid 20138947?>20138947 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>13.McConnBWangGYiJGilbertEROsugiTUbukaT. Gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone-stimulation of food intake is mediated by hypothalamic effects in chicks. Neuropeptides (2014) 48:327–34. 10.1016/j.npep.2014.09.001<?supplied-pmid 25305807?>25305807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>14.UkenaKIwakoshiEMinakataHTsutsuiK. A novel rat hypothalamic RFamide-related peptide identified by immunoaffinity chromatography and mass spectrometry. FEBS Lett. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>(2002) 512:255–8. 10.1016/S0014-5793(02)02275-5<?supplied-pmid 11852091?>11852091 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>15.UbukaTInoueKFukudaYMizunoTUkenaKKriegsfeldLJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>(2012). Identification, expression, and physiological functions of Siberian hamster gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone. Endocrinol 153, 373–385. 10.1210/en.2011-1110<?supplied-pmid 22045661?>22045661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>16.UkenaKKodaAYamamotoKKobayashiTIwakoshi-UkenaEMinakataH. Novel neuropeptides related to frog growth hormone-releasing peptide: isolation, sequence, and functional analysis. Endocrinol (2003) 144:3879–84. 10.1210/en.2003-0359<?supplied-pmid 12933661?>12933661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>17.UkenaKIwakoshi-UkenaEOsugiTTsutsuiK. Identification and localization of gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone (GnIH) orthologs in the hypothalamus of the red-eared slider turtle, Trachemysscripta elegans. Gen Comp Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>(2016) 227:69–76. 10.1016/j.ygcen.2015.06.009<?supplied-pmid 26130239?>26130239 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>18.UbukaTLaiHKitaniMSuzuuchiAPhamVCadiganPA. Gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone identification, cDNA cloning, and distribution in rhesus macaque brain. J Comp Neurol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>(2009) 517:841–55. 10.1002/cne.22191<?supplied-pmid 19844991?>19844991 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>19.UbukaTMorganKPawsonAJOsugiTChowdhuryVSMinakataH. Identification of human GnIH homologs, RFRP-1 and RFRP-3, and the cognate receptor, GPR147 in the human hypothalamic pituitary axis. PLoS ONE (2009) 4:e8400. 10.1371/journal.pone.0008400<?supplied-pmid 20027225?>20027225 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>20.SawadaKUkenaKSatakeHIwakoshiEMinakataHTsutsuiK Novel fish hypothalamic neuropeptide: cloning of a cDNA encoding the precursor polypeptide and identification and localization of the mature peptide. Eur J Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>(2002) 269:6000–8. 10.1046/j.1432-1033.2002.03351.x12473095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>21.MeyerASchartlM. Gene and genome duplications in vertebrates: the one-to-four (-to-eight in fish) rule and the evolution of novel gene functions. Curr Opin Cell Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>(1999) 11:699–704. <?supplied-pmid 10600714?>10600714 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>22.JunttiSAFernaldRD. Timing reproduction in teleost fish: cues and mechanisms. Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Opin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Neurobiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>(2016) 38:57–62. 10.1016/j.conb.2016.02.006<?supplied-pmid 26952366?>26952366 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>23.BetancurRRWileyEOArratiaGAceroABaillyNMiyaM Phylogenetic classification of bony fishes. BMC Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>(2017) 17:162 10.1186/s12862-017-0958-328683774 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>24.Aliaga-GuerreroMPaullada-SalmerónJAPiquerVMañanósELMuñoz-CuetoJA. Gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone in the flatfish, Solea senegalensis: molecular cloning, brain localization and physiological effects. J Comp Neurol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>(2018) 526:349–70. 10.1002/cne.24339<?supplied-pmid 29044516?>29044516 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>25.DiYorio MPPérezSirkin DIDelgadinTHShimizuATsutsuiKSomozaGM Gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone in the cichlid fish Cichlasoma dimerus: structure, brain distribution and differential effects on the secretion of gonadotropins and growth hormone. J Neuroendocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>(2017) 28:5 10.1111/jne.12377 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>26.AmanoMMoriyamaSIigoMKitamuraSAmiyaNYamamoriK. Novel fish hypothalamic neuropeptides stimulate the release of gonadotrophins and growth hormone from the pituitary of sockeye salmon. J Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>(2006) 188:417–23. 10.1677/joe.1.06494<?supplied-pmid 16522722?>16522722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>27.OgawaSSivalingamMBiranJGolanMAnthonysamyRSLevavi-SivanB. Distribution of LPXRFa, a gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone ortholog peptide, and LPXRFa receptor in the brain and pituitary of the tilapia. J Comp Neurol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>(2016) 524:2753–75. 10.1002/cne.23990<?supplied-pmid 26917324?>26917324 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>28.DiYorio MPPerezSirkin DIBattistaAÁlvarez-GonzálezCATsutsuiKVissioPG Gonadotropin inhibitory hormone (gnih) distribution in the brain of the ancient fish, Atractosteus tropicus (Lepisosteiformes: lepisosteidae). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>In: 11th International Symposium on Reproductive Physiology of Fish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Manaus (2018). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>29.Paullada-SalmerónJACowanMAliaga-GuerreroMGómezAZanuySMañanosE. LPXRFa peptide system in the European sea bass: a molecular and immunohistochemical approach. J Comp Neurol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>(2016) 524:176–98. 10.1002/cne.23833<?supplied-pmid 26105807?>26105807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>30.CorchueloSMartinezERMButzgeAJDorettoLBRicciJMBValentinFN. Characterization of Gnrh/Gnih elements in the olfacto-retinal system and ovary during zebrafish ovarian maturation. Mol Cell Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>(2017) 450:1–13. 10.1016/j.mce.2017.04.002<?supplied-pmid 28400274?>28400274 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>31.Pahí-RoseroAMPérezMRLópezGCVissioPGSomozaGM Brain distribution of immunoreactive neurons and fibers expressing gnih in pejerrey, Odontesthes bonariensis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>In: 11th International Symposium on Reproductive Physiology of Fish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Manaus (2018). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>32.TsutsuiKUbukaT. How to contribute to the progress of neuroendocrinology: discovery of GnIH and progress of GnIH research. Front Endocrinol. (2018) 9:662. 10.3389/fendo.2018.00662<?supplied-pmid 30483217?>30483217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>33.BiswasSJadhaoAGPinelliCPalandeNVTsutsuiK. GnIH and GnRH expressions in the central nervous system and pituitary of Indian major carp, Labeo rohita during ontogeny: an immunocytochemical study. Gen Comp Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>(2015) 220:88–92. 10.1016/j.ygcen.2014.06.005<?supplied-pmid 24955881?>24955881 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>34.WangQQiXGuoYLiSZhangYLiuX. Molecular identification of GnIH/GnIHR signal and its reproductive function in protogynous hermaphroditic orange-spotted grouper (Epinephelus coioides). Gen Comp Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>(2015) 216:9–23. 10.1016/j.ygcen.2015.04.016<?supplied-pmid 25943851?>25943851 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>35.SpicerOSZmoraNWongTTGolanMLevavi-SivanBGothilfY. The gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone (Lpxrfa) system's regulation of reproduction in the brain-pituitary axis of the zebrafish (Danio rerio). Biol Reprod. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>(2017) 96:1031–42. 10.1093/biolre/iox032<?supplied-pmid 28430864?>28430864 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>36.OsugiTDaukssDGazdaKUbukaTKosugiTNozakiM. Evolutionary origin of the structure and function of gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone: insights from lampreys. Endocrinol (2012) 153:2362–74. 10.1210/en.2011-2046<?supplied-pmid 22454150?>22454150 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>37.Cerdá-ReverterJMCanosaLF Neuroendocrine systems of the fish brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>In: BernierNJVan Der KraakGFarrellAPBraunerCJ Editors. Fish Neuroendocrinology, Vol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>28. Amsterdan: Academic Press (2009). p. 3–74. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>38.ZoharYMuñoz-CuetoJAElizurAKahO. Neuroendocrinology of reproduction in teleost fish. Gen Comp Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>(2010) 165:438–55. 10.1016/j.ygcen.2009.04.017<?supplied-pmid 19393655?>19393655 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>39.GolanMZelingerEZoharYLevavi-SivanB. Architecture of GnRH-gonadotrope-vasculature reveals a dual mode of gonadotropin regulation in fish. Endocrinol (2015) 156:4163–73. 10.1210/en.2015-1150<?supplied-pmid 26261873?>26261873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>40.UbukaTBentleyGEUkenaKWingfieldJCTsutsuiK. Melatonin induces the expression of gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone in the avian brain. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>(2005) 102:3052–7. 10.1073/pnas.0403840102<?supplied-pmid 15708982?>15708982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>41.ChowdhuryVSYamamotoKUbukaTBentleyGEHattoriATsutsuiK. Melatonin stimulates the release of gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone by the avian hypothalamus. Endocrinol (2010) 151:271–80. 10.1210/en.2009-0908<?supplied-pmid 19952272?>19952272 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>42.TsutsuiKUbukaTBentleyGEKriegsfeldLJ. Review: regulatory mechanisms of gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone (GnIH) synthesis and release in photoperiodic animals. Front Neurosci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>(2013) 7:60. 10.3389/fnins.2013.00060<?supplied-pmid 23596387?>23596387 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>43.PiekarskiDJJarjisianSGPerezLAhmadHDhawanNZuckerI. Effects of pinealectomy and short day lengths on reproduction and neuronal RFRP-3, kisspeptin, and GnRH in female turkish hamsters. J Biol Rhythm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>(2014) 29:181–91. 10.1177/0748730414532423<?supplied-pmid 24916391?>24916391 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>44.FalcónJMigaudHMuñoz-CuetoJACarrilloM. Current knowledge on the melatonin system in teleost fish. Gen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Comp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>(2010) 165:469–82. 10.1016/j.ygcen.2009.04.026<?supplied-pmid 19409900?>19409900 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>45.ShahjahanMIkegamiTOsugiTUkenaKDoiHHattoriA. Synchronised expressions of LPXRFamide peptide and its receptor genes: seasonal, diurnal and circadian changes during spawning period in grass puffer. J Neuroendocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>(2011) 23:39–51. 10.1111/j.1365-2826.2010.02081.x<?supplied-pmid 21083774?>21083774 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>46.ChoiYJKimNNHabibiHRChoiCY. Effects of gonadotropin inhibitory hormone or gonadotropin-releasing hormone on reproduction-related genes in the protandrous cinnamon clownfish, Amphiprion melanopus. Gen Comp Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>(2016) 235:89–99. 10.1016/j.ygcen.2016.06.010<?supplied-pmid 27288637?>27288637 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>47.ChoiYJHabibiHRChoiCY. Profiles of gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone and melatonin during the sex change and maturation of cinnamon clownfish, Amphiprion melanopus. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>(2016) 475:189–93. 10.1016/j.bbrc.2016.05.073<?supplied-pmid 27208779?>27208779 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>48.CowanMPaullada-SalmerónJALópez-OlmedaJFSánchez-VázquezFJMuñoz-CuetoJA. Effects of pinealectomy on the neuroendocrine reproductive system and locomotor activity in male European sea bass, Dicentrarchus labrax. Comp Biochem Physiol A Mol Integr Physiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>(2017) 207:1–12. 10.1016/j.cbpa.2017.02.008<?supplied-pmid 28188883?>28188883 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>49.YumnamchaTKhanZARajivCDeviSDMondalGSanjitaDevi H. Interaction of melatonin and gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone on the zebrafish brain-pituitary-reproductive axis. Mol Reprod Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>(2017) 84:389–400. 10.1002/mrd.22795<?supplied-pmid 28295807?>28295807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>50.Paullada-SalmerónJALoentgenGHCowanMAliaga-GuerreroMRendón-UncetaMCMuñoz-CuetoJA. Developmental changes and day-night expression of the gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone system in the European sea bass: effects of rearing temperature. Comp Biochem Physiol A Mol Integr Physiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>(2017) 206:54–62. 10.1016/j.cbpa.2017.01.009<?supplied-pmid 28109838?>28109838 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>51.DiYorio MPSallemiJEToledoSolís FJPérezSirkin DIDelgadinTHTsutsuiK Ontogeny of gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone (GnIH) in the cichlid fish Cichlasoma dimerus. J Neuroendocrinol. (2018) 30:e12608 10.1111/jne.12608 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>52.NakaneYIkegamiKIigoMOnoHTakedaKTakahashiD. The saccus vasculosus of fish is a sensor of seasonal changes in day lenght. Nat Commun. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>(2013) 4:2108. 10.1038/ncomms3108<?supplied-pmid 23820554?>23820554 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>53.ZhangYLiSLiuYLuDChenHHuangX. Structural diversity of the GnIH/GnIH receptor system in teleost: its involvement in early development and the negative control of LH release. Peptides (2010) 31:1034–43. 10.1016/j.peptides.2010.03.003<?supplied-pmid 20226824?>20226824 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>54.QiXZhouWLiSLuDYiSXieR. Evidences for the regulation of GnRH and GTH expression by GnIH in the goldfish, Carassius auratus. Mol Cell Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>(2013) 366:9–20. 10.1016/j.mce.2012.11.001<?supplied-pmid 23201092?>23201092 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>55.WangBYangGLiuQQinJXuYLiW. Characterization of LPXRFa receptor in the half-smooth tongue sole (Cynoglossus semilaevis): molecular cloning, expression profiles, and differential activation of signaling pathways by LPXRFa peptides. Comp Biochem Physiol A Mol Integr Physiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>(2018) 223:23–32. 10.1016/j.cbpa.2018.05.008<?supplied-pmid 29746909?>29746909 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>56.QiXZhouWLuDWangQZhangHLiS. Sexual dimorphism of steroidogenesis regulated by GnIH in the goldfish, Carassius auratus. Biol Reprod. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>(2013) 88:8177. 10.1095/biolreprod.112.105114<?supplied-pmid 23467740?>23467740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>57.BiranJGolanMMizrahiNOgawaSParharISLevavi-SivanB. LPXRFa, the piscine ortholog of GnIH, and LPXRF receptor positively regulate gonadotropin secretion in tilapia (Oreochromis niloticus). Endocrinol (2014) 155:4391–401. 10.1210/en.2013-2047<?supplied-pmid 25144920?>25144920 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>58.WangBLiuQLiuXXuYShiB. Molecular characterization and expression profiles of LPXRFa at the brain-pituitary-gonad axis of half-smooth tongue sole (Cynoglossus semilaevis) during ovarian maturation. Comp Biochem Physiol B Biochem Mol Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>(2018) 216:59–68. 10.1016/j.cbpb.2017.11.016<?supplied-pmid 29223873?>29223873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>59.RochGJBusbyERSherwoodNM. GnRH receptors and peptides: skating backward. Gen Comp Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>(2014) 209:118–34. 10.1016/j.ygcen.2014.07.025<?supplied-pmid 25107740?>25107740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>60.González-MartínezDZmoraNZanuySSarasqueteCElizurAKahO. Developmental expression of three different prepro-GnRH (gonadotrophin-releasing hormone) messengers in the brain of the European sea bass (Dicentrarchus labrax). J Chem Neuroanat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>(2002) 23:255–67. 10.1016/S0891-0618(02)00004-2<?supplied-pmid 12048109?>12048109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B61"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>61.González-MartínezDZmoraNSaligautDZanuySElizurAKahO. New insights in developmental origins of different GnRH (gonadotrophin-releasing hormone) systems in perciform fish: an immunohistochemical study in the European sea bass (Dicentrarchus labrax). J Chem Neuroanat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>(2004) 28:1–15. 10.1016/j.jchemneu.2004.05.001<?supplied-pmid 15363486?>15363486 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B62"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>62.KahOLethimonierCSomozaGGuilgurLGVaillantCLareyreJJ. GnRH and GnRH receptors in metazoa: a historical, comparative, and evolutive perspective. Gen Comp Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>(2007) 153:346–64. 10.1016/j.ygcen.2007.01.030<?supplied-pmid 17350014?>17350014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B63"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>63.ParharISOgawaSUbukaT. Reproductive neuroendocrine pathways of social behavior. Front Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>(2016) 7:28. 10.3389/fendo.2016.00028.<?supplied-pmid 27065948?>27065948 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B64"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>64.KawaiTOkaYEisthenH. The role of the terminal nerve and GnRH in olfactory system neuromodulation. Zoolog Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>(2009) 26:669–80. 10.2108/zsj.26.669<?supplied-pmid 19832678?>19832678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B65"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>65.UmataniCMisuROishiSYamaguchiKAbeHOkaY. GnRH suppresses excitability of visual processing neurons in the optic tectum. J Neurophysiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>(2015) 114:2775–84. 10.1152/jn.00710.2015<?supplied-pmid 26354319?>26354319 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B66"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>66.GuilgurLGMoncautNPCanárioAVSomozaGM. Evolution of GnRH ligands and receptors in gnathostomata. Comp Biochem Physiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>(2006) 144:272–83. 10.1016/j.cbpa.2006.02.016<?supplied-pmid 16716622?>16716622 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B67"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>67.KriegsfeldLJMeiDFBentleyGEUbukaTMasonAOInoueK. Identifcation and characterization of a gonadotropin-inhibitory system in the brains of mammals. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>(2006) 103:2410–5. 10.1073/pnas.0511003103<?supplied-pmid 16467147?>16467147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B68"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>68.TsutsuiKUbukaT. GnIH Control of Feeding and Reproductive Behaviors. Front Endocrinol. (2016) 7:170. 10.3389/fendo.2016.00170<?supplied-pmid 28082949?>28082949 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B69"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>69.PeragineDEPokarowskiMMendoza-ViverosLSwift-GallantAChengHMBentleyGE. RFamide-related peptide-3 (RFRP-3) suppresses sexual maturation in a eusocial mammal. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>(2017) 114:1207–12. 10.1073/pnas.1616913114<?supplied-pmid 28096421?>28096421 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B70"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>70.DiYorio MPPérezSirkin DIMuñoz-CuetoJADelgadinTHTsutsuiKSomozaGM Morphological relationship between GnIH and GnRH neurons in the brain of the neotropical cichlid fish Cichlasoma dimerus. Gen Comp Endocrinol. (2018). 10.1016/j.ygcen.2018.06.010. [Epub ahead of print]. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B71"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>71.Muñoz-CuetoJACowanMELoentgenGHAliaga-GuerreroMFuentèsMBesseauL The gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone system of fish: the case of sea bass (Dicentrarchus labrax. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>In: 11th International Symposium on Reproductive Physiology of Fish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Manaus (2018). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B72"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>72.ServiliALethimonierCLareyreJJLópez-OlmedaJFSánchez-VázquezFJKahO. The highly conserved gonadotropin-releasing hormone-2 form acts as a melatonin-releasing factor in the pineal of a teleost fish, the European sea bass Dicentrarchus labrax. Endocrinol (2010) 151:2265–75. 10.1210/en.2009-1207<?supplied-pmid 20215565?>20215565 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B73"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>73.ServiliAHerrera-PérezPYáñezJMuñoz-CuetoJA. Afferent and efferent connections of the pineal organ in the European sea bass Dicentrarchus labrax: a carbocyanine dye tract-tracing study. Brain Behav Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>(2011) 78, 272–85. 10.1159/000330824<?supplied-pmid 21921581?>21921581 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B74"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>74.MoussaviMWlasichukMChangJPHabibiHR. Seasonal effect of gonadotrophin inhibitory hormone on gonadotrophin-releasing hormone-induced gonadotroph functions in the goldfish pituitary. J Neuroendocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>(2013) 25:506–516. 10.1111/jne.12024<?supplied-pmid 23331955?>23331955 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B75"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>75.MoussaviMWlasichukMChangJPHabibiHR. Seasonal effects of GnIH on basal and GnRH-induced goldfish somatotrope functions. J Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>(2014) 223:191–202. 10.1530/JOE-14-0441<?supplied-pmid 25319842?>25319842 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B76"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>76.Paullada-SalmerónJACowanMAliaga-GuerreroMMoranoFZanuySMuñoz-CuetoJA. Gonadotropin inhibitory hormone down-regulates the brain-pituitary reproductive axis of male European sea bass (Dicentrarchus labrax). Biol Reprod. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>(2016) 94:1–11. 10.1095/biolreprod.116.139022<?supplied-pmid 26984999?>26984999 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B77"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>77.Paullada-SalmerónJACowanMAliaga-GuerreroMLópez-OlmedaJFMañanósELZanuyS. Testicular steroidogenesis and locomotor activity are regulated by gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone in male European sea bass. PLoS ONE (2016) 11:e0165494. 10.1371/journal.pone.0165494<?supplied-pmid 27788270?>27788270 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B78"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>78.BrancoGSMeloAGRicciJMBDigmayerMdeJesus LWOHabibiHR. Effects of GnRH and the dual regulatory actions of GnIH in the pituitary explants and brain slices of Astyanax altiparanae males. Gen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Comp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>(2018). 10.1016/j.ygcen.2018.08.006 [Epub ahead of print].<?supplied-pmid 30098316?>30098316 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B79"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>79.UbukaTParharI. Dual actions of mammalian and piscine gonadotropin-inhibitory hormones, RFamide-related peptides and LPXRFamide peptides, in the hypothalamic-pituitary-gonadal axis. Front Endocrinol. (2018) 8:377. 10.3389/fendo.2017.00377<?supplied-pmid 29375482?>29375482 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B80"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>80.SonYLUbukaTMillarRPKanasakiHTsutsuiK. Gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone inhibits GnRH-induced gonadotropin subunit gene transcriptions by inhibiting AC/cAMP/PKA-dependent ERK pathway in LβT2 cells. Endocrinol (2012) 153:2332–43. 10.1210/en.2011-1904<?supplied-pmid 22374973?>22374973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B81"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>81.WuMDumalskaIMorozovaEvanden Pol ANAlrejaM. Gonadotropin inhibitory hormone inhibits basal forebrain vGluT2-gonadotropin-releasing hormone neurons via a direct postsynaptic mechanism. J. Physiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>(2009) 587:1401–11. 10.1113/jphysiol.2008.16644748<?supplied-pmid 19204051?>19204051 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B82"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>82.WangBYangGLiuQQinJXuYLiW. Inhibitory action of tongue sole LPXRFa, the piscine ortholog of gonadotropin-inhibitory hormone, on the signaling pathway induced by tongue sole kisspeptin in COS-7 cells transfected with their cognate receptors. Peptides (2017) 95:62–7. 10.1016/j.peptides.2017.07.014<?supplied-pmid 28754347?>28754347 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B83"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>83.WangBYangGXuYLiWLiuX. Recent studies of LPXRFa receptor signaling in fish and other vertebrates. Gen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Comp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>(2018). 10.1016/j.ygcen.2018.11.011 [Epub ahead of print].<?supplied-pmid 30465768?>30465768 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B84"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>84.SandvikGKHodneKHaugTMOkuboKWeltzienFA Review: RFamide peptides in early vertebrate development. Front Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>(2014) 5:203 10.3389/fendo.2014.00203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B85"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>85.PandolfiMParharISRavagliaMAMeijideFJMaggeseMCPazDA. Ontogeny and distribution of gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) neuronal systems in the brain of the cichlid fish Cichlasoma dimerus. Anat Embryol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>(2002) 205:271–81. 10.1007/s00429-002-0253-x<?supplied-pmid 12136257?>12136257 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B86"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>86.StrüssmannCASaitoTUsuiMYamadaHTakashimaF Thermal thresholds and critical period of thermolabile sex determination in two atherinid fishes, Odontesthes bonariensis and Patagonina hatcheri. J Experiment Zool. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>(1997) 278:167–77. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B87"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>87.Ospina-AlvarezNPiferrerF. Temperature-dependent sex determination in fish revisited: prevalence, a single sex ratio response pattern, and possible effects of climate change. PLoS ONE (2008) 3:e2837. 10.1371/journal.pone.0002837<?supplied-pmid 18665231?>18665231 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B88"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>88.ShahjahanMDoiHAndoH. LPXRFamide peptide stimulates growth hormone and prolactin gene expression during the spawning period in the grass puffer, a semi-lunar synchronized spawner. Gen Comp Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>(2016) 227:77–83. 10.1016/j.ygcen.2015.09.008<?supplied-pmid 26385315?>26385315 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B89"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>89.PengCGallinWPeterREBlomqvistAGLarhammarD. Neuropeptide-Y gene expression in the goldfish brain: distribution and regulation by ovarian steroids. Endocrinol (1994) 134:1095 e1103. 10.1210/endo.134.3.8119148<?supplied-pmid 8119148?>8119148 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B90"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>90.Cerda-ReverterJMAngladeIMartínez-RodríguezGMazuraisDMuñoz-CuetoJACarrilloM. Characterization of neuropeptide Y expression in the brain of a perciform fish, the sea bass (Dicentrarchus labrax). J Chem Neuroanat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>(2000) 19:197–210. 10.1016/S0891-0618(00)00063-6<?supplied-pmid 11036237?>11036237 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B91"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>91.Rodríguez-GómezFJRendón-UncetaMCSarasqueteCMuñoz-CuetoJA. Distribution of neuropeptide Y-like immunoreactivity in the brain of the Senegalese sole (Solea senegalensis). Anatomical. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>Record. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>(2001) 262: 227–37. 10.1002/1097-0185(20010301)262:3&lt;227::AID-AR1027&gt;3.0.CO;2-X<?supplied-pmid 11241192?>11241192 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B92"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>92.ShahjahanMKitahashiTParharIS. Central pathways integrating metabolism and reproduction in teleosts. Front Endocrinol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>(2014) 5:36. 10.3389/fendo.2014.00036<?supplied-pmid 24723910?>24723910 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B93"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>93.TangHLiuYLuoDOgawaSYinYLiS. The kiss/kissr systems are dispensable for zebrafish reproduction: evidence from gene knockout studies. Endocrinology (2015) 156:589–99. 10.1210/en.2014-1204<?supplied-pmid 25406015?>25406015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B94"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>94.SpicerOSWongTTZmoraNZoharY. Targeted mutagenesis of the hypophysiotropic Gnrh3 in zebrafish (Danio rerio) reveals no effects on reproductive performance. PLoS ONE (2016) 11:e0158141. 10.1371/journal.pone.0158141<?supplied-pmid 27355207?>27355207 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B95"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>95.LiuYTangHXieRLiSLiuXLinH. Genetic evidence for multifactorial control of the reproductive axis in zebrafish. Endocrinology (2017) 158:604–11. 10.1210/en.2016-1540<?supplied-pmid 28359084?>28359084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B96"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>96.TrudeauVL Facing the challenges of neuropeptide gene knockouts: why do they not inhibit reproduction in adult teleost fish? Front Neurosci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>(2018) 12:302 10.3389/fnins.2018.0030229773976 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B97"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>97.MarvelMSmithSpicer OWongTTZmoraNZoharZ. Knockout of the Gnrh genes in zebrafish: effects on reproduction and potential compensation by reproductive and feeding-related neuropeptides. Biol Reprod. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>(2018) 99:565–77. 10.1093/biolre/ioy078<?supplied-pmid 29635430?>29635430 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
