<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6389188</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29703141</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4537</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-018-4537-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genome-wide identification and characterization of the SBP-box gene family in <italic>Petunia</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Qin</given-names></name><address><email>1648516802@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Sisi</given-names></name><address><email>zhangsisi@webmail.hzau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Feng</given-names></name><address><email>755144502@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Baojun</given-names></name><address><email>bjliumail@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Lan</given-names></name><address><email>ivylanblue@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Fei</given-names></name><address><email>841820952@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Jiaqi</given-names></name><address><email>jiaqizhang@mail.hzau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>Manzhu</given-names></name><address><email>mzbao@mail.hzau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Guofeng</given-names></name><address><email>gfliu@mail.hzau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1790 4137</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.35155.37</institution-id><institution>Key Laboratory of Horticultural Plant Biology, Ministry of Education; Key Laboratory of Urban Agriculture in Central China, Ministry of Agriculture; College of Horticulture and Forestry Sciences, </institution><institution>Huazhong Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Shizishan Street No. 1, Wuhan, 430070 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Wuhan Institute of Landscape Architecture, Peace Avenue No. 1240, Wuhan, 430081 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>12</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>193</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">SQUAMOSA PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN (SBP)-box genes encode a family of plant-specific transcription factors (TFs) that play important roles in many growth and development processes including phase transition, leaf initiation, shoot and inflorescence branching, fruit development and ripening etc. The SBP-box gene family has been identified and characterized in many species, but has not been well studied in <italic>Petunia</italic>, an important ornamental genus.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">We identified 21 putative <italic>SPL</italic> genes of <italic>Petunia axillaris</italic> and <italic>P. inflata</italic> from the reference genome of <italic>P. axillaris</italic> N and <italic>P. inflata</italic> S6, respectively, which were supported by the transcriptome data. For further confirmation, all the 21 genes were also cloned from <italic>P. hybrida</italic> line W115 (Mitchel diploid). Phylogenetic analysis based on the highly conserved SBP domains arranged <italic>PhSPLs</italic> in eight groups, analogous to those from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and tomato. Furthermore, the <italic>Petunia SPL</italic> genes had similar exon<bold>-</bold>intron structure and the deduced proteins contained very similar conserved motifs within the same subgroup. Out of 21 <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes, fourteen were predicted to be potential targets of PhmiR156/157, and the putative miR156/157 response elements (MREs) were located in the coding region of group IV, V, VII and VIII genes, but in the 3&#x02019;-UTR regions of group VI genes. <italic>SPL</italic> genes were also identified from another two wild <italic>Petunia</italic> species, <italic>P. integrifolia</italic> and <italic>P. exserta</italic>, based on their transcriptome databases to investigate the origin of <italic>PhSPLs</italic>. Phylogenetic analysis and multiple alignments of the coding sequences of <italic>PhSPLs</italic> and their orthologs from wild species indicated that <italic>PhSPLs</italic> were originated mainly from <italic>P. axillaris</italic>. qRT-PCR analysis demonstrated differential spatiotemperal expression patterns of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes in petunia and many were expressed predominantly in the axillary buds and/or inflorescences. In addition, overexpression of <italic>PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL9b</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> suggested that these genes play a conserved role in promoting the vegetative-to-reproductive phase transition.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par3">Petunia genome contains at least 21 <italic>SPL</italic> genes, and most of the genes are expressed in different tissues. The <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes may play conserved and diverse roles in plant growth and development, including flowering regulation, leaf initiation, axillary bud and inflorescence development. This work provides a comprehensive understanding of the SBP-box gene family in <italic>Petunia</italic> and lays a significant foundation for future studies on the function and evolution of <italic>SPL</italic> genes in petunia.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12864-018-4537-9) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Petunia</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>SPL</italic> genes</kwd><kwd>Transcription factor</kwd><kwd>Expression patterns</kwd><kwd>miR156/miR157</kwd><kwd>Flowering</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>37471914</award-id><award-id>31772345</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Guofeng</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Ministry of Education of the People's Republic of China (CN)</institution></funding-source><award-id>IRT13065</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Guofeng</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par13">Transcription factors (TFs) are essential for the regulation of precise and coordinate gene expression via activating and/or repressing transcription in response to various endogenous and environmental signals, which plays crucial roles in the regulation of gene networks for many important developmental processes and defense responses in plants. TFs are usually classified into different families based on the sequence of DNA-binding domains and other conserved motifs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. SQUAMOSA PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN (SBP)-box genes encode a family of plant-specific TFs that contain a highly conserved DNA-binding domain of 76 amino acids called the SBP domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], which can form two tandem zinc fingers (Cys-Cys-His-Cys and Cys-Cys-Cys-His), and possesses a nuclear localization signal (NLS) at the C-terminus partially overlapping with the second zinc finger [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The SBP domain is involved in both nuclear import and binding to a consensus DNA sequence with a GTAC core motif and gene-specific flanking regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p><p id="Par14">AmSBP1 and AmSBP2 are the first SBP-domain proteins discovered in plants, which were isolated from <italic>Antirrhinum majus</italic> in an in vitro approach and named after their binding ability to the promoter of the floral meristem identity gene <italic>SQUAMOSA</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Since then, SBP-box genes have been found in diverse plant species, including single-celled green algae, mosses, gymnosperms, and angiosperms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Furthermore, genome-wide identified and analysis of the whole gene family were reported recently in some species, such as <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], tomato [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], grape [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], apple [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], castor bean [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], <italic>Populus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], <italic>Citrus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], <italic>Gossypium</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], pepper [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], tobacco [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], oilseed rape [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], soybean [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], and moso bamboo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, there are 16 <italic>SBP-LIKE</italic> (<italic>SPL</italic>) genes, which can be categorized into eight clades based on the amino acid sequence of their conserved SBP domain: <italic>AtSPL1/12/14/16</italic>, <italic>AtSPL2/10/11</italic>, <italic>AtSPL3/4/5</italic>, <italic>AtSPL6</italic>, <italic>AtSPL7, AtSPL8, AtSPL9/15</italic>, and <italic>AtSPL13</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Among them, ten genes from five clades (<italic>AtSPL2/10/11</italic>, <italic>AtSPL3/4/5</italic>, <italic>AtSPL6</italic>, <italic>AtSPL9/15</italic> and <italic>AtSPL13</italic>) are targeted by miR156 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], an evolutionarily highly conserved miRNA in plants that plays master function of regulating the transition from the juvenile to the adult phase of vegetative development (vegetative phase change) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p><p id="Par15"><italic>SPL</italic> genes control many aspects of plant development and physiology, including the vegetative phase change, flowering time, leaf initiation, shoot and inflorescence branching, fruit development and ripening, floral organ development and fertility, pollen sac development, trichome development, root development, and stress responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Recent studies provide a detailed picture of the function of miR156-targeted <italic>SPL</italic> genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>: <italic>AtSPL2/9/10/11/13/15</italic> contribute to both the juvenile-to-adult phase transition (vegetative phase change) and the vegetative-to-reproductive phase transition (reproductive phase change or flowering), with <italic>AtSPL9</italic>/<italic>13/15</italic> being more important than <italic>SPL2/10/11</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]; <italic>AtSPL3/4/5</italic> were previously reported to redundantly promote flowering through direct activation of <italic>LEAFY</italic> (<italic>LFY</italic>), <italic>FRUITFUL</italic> (<italic>FUL</italic>), and <italic>APETALA1</italic> (<italic>AP1</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], and they may act synergistically with the <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> (<italic>FT</italic>)-<italic>FD</italic> module to induce flowering under long-day (LD) condition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], whereas a recent study suggested that <italic>AtSPL3/4/5</italic> don&#x02019;t play a major role in vegetative phase change or flowering, but promote the floral meristem identity transition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]; <italic>AtSPL6</italic> does not have a major function in vegetative morphogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], it can positively regulate a subset of defense genes, however, and plays a role in effector-triggered immunity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Among the miR156 non-targeted <italic>SPL</italic> genes, <italic>AtSPL7</italic> is a central regulator of copper (Cu) homeostasis and play a major role in cadmium (Cd) response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. <italic>AtSPL8</italic> was found to be a tissue-dependent regulator in GA signaling and regulate early anther development and gynoecium differential patterning in concert with multiple miR156 targeted <italic>SPL</italic> genes, as well as trichome formation on sepals, stamen filament elongation, and root growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. <italic>AtSPL14</italic> gene may function to delay phase transition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].</p><p id="Par16">Studies in other species revealed that <italic>SPL</italic> genes underwent an extensive neofunctionalization during their evolution. For instance, the maize <italic>TEOSINTE GLUME ARCHITECTURE1</italic> (<italic>tga1</italic>) gene, an <italic>AtSPL13</italic> homolog, controls glume development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. The rice <italic>TGA1</italic> ortholog <italic>GW8/OsSPL16</italic> gene controls grain size, shape and quality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. The maize <italic>LIGULELESS1</italic> (<italic>LG1</italic>) gene (closest to <italic>AtSPL8</italic>) and its ortholog in rice (<italic>OsLG1</italic>) were found to control the formation of the ligule and auricule [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Recently, they were found to also control the branch angle of tassel and panicle, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. The tomato <italic>Colorless non-ripening</italic> (<italic>Cnr</italic>) locus encode an <italic>AtSPL3</italic> ortholog and is essential for fruit ripening [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>].</p><p id="Par17">Petunia (<italic>Petunia hybrida</italic>) is a popular and important ornamental species belonging to the economically important family Solanaceae that has been used as a genetic model system for a long history [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Petunia is also a good model for comparative research of gene function become of its many advantages, including the evolutionary position of asterid, ease of cultivation and propagation, highly efficient genetics and transformation. However, our knowledge on the evolution and function of <italic>SBP</italic>-box gene family in petunia is very limited yet. Only one recent study functionally characterized two petunia <italic>SPL</italic> genes, <italic>PhSBP1</italic> and <italic>PhSBP2</italic>, which showed that they have overlapping but divergent functions in the reproductive transition and leaf initiation rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Recently, the whole-genome sequencing was achieved for inbred derivatives of two wild <italic>Petunia</italic> species, <italic>P. axillaris</italic> N and <italic>P. inflata</italic> S6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], which provides a good opportunity to study the important gene family of TFs on a genome-wide scale. <italic>P. hybrida</italic> was considered to be originated from the hybridization of two biological species, one with erect habit and white flowers (<italic>P. axillaris</italic>), and the other with decumbent stems and purple flowers (<italic>P. integrifolia</italic>). <italic>P. inflata</italic> was previously considered as a synonym of <italic>P. integrifolia</italic>, and subsequently as a subspecies under <italic>P. integrifolia</italic> (<italic>P. integrifolia</italic> Subs<italic>p. inflata</italic>), but a recent study accepted it as distinct from <italic>P. integrifolia</italic> with the unfolded and straight calyx lobes as useful diagnostic characters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Here, we report a genome- and transcriptome-wide analysis of the SBP-box gene family in <italic>Petunia</italic>, including <italic>P. axillaris</italic>, <italic>P. inflata</italic>, <italic>P. integrifolia</italic>, <italic>P. hybrida</italic>, and <italic>P. exserta</italic>, a unique species in the genus, with red corolla and distinct exserted stamens and stigma. Based on genome and transcriptome scanning, 21 SBP-box genes were identified in <italic>P. axillaris</italic> and <italic>P. inflata</italic>, respectively, confirmed by cloning from <italic>P. hybrida</italic> line W115. The gene structure, phylogeny, motif composition, miRNA target site and expression pattern in various tissues were systematically analyzed. In addition, the function of two representative genes, <italic>PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL9b</italic>, was characterized in transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants. The data presented here provide good foundation for understanding the key roles of <italic>SPL</italic> genes in petunia development and other biological processes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Identification of <italic>Petunia SPL</italic> genes</title><p id="Par18">The <italic>SPLs</italic> of Arabidopsis, tomato and tobacco were used to search the genome and transcriptome datasets of <italic>P. axillaris</italic> and <italic>P. inflata</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>], which identified 21 putative <italic>SPL</italic> genes in the two species, designated as <italic>PaSPLs</italic> and <italic>PiSPLs</italic> (Additional files <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>), respectively. To validate the full-length open reading frame (ORF) sequences and predicted exon-intron structures of the <italic>Petunia SPL</italic> genes, the coding sequence of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes (<italic>PhSPLs</italic>) were cloned by RT-PCR from <italic>P. hybrida</italic> line W115. As a result, all 21 <italic>SPL</italic> genes were isolated successfully from W115 and confirmed by sequencing. We named these genes according to the closest homologs of them in Arabidopsis (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Nomenclature of <italic>SPL</italic> genes in <italic>Petunia hybrida</italic> line W115 (Mitchel diploid)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Gene name</th><th>Accession number</th><th>Preston et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]</th><th>CDS length (bp)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL2</italic>
</td><td>MF580469</td><td/><td>1404</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhCNR</italic>
</td><td>MF580470</td><td>
<italic>PhCNR</italic>
</td><td>285</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL3</italic>
</td><td>MF580471</td><td>
<italic>PhSBP1</italic>
</td><td>423</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL4a</italic>
</td><td>MF580472</td><td/><td>420</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL4b</italic>
</td><td>MF580473</td><td/><td>636</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL4c</italic>
</td><td>MF580474</td><td>
<italic>PhSBP2</italic>
</td><td>537</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL6a</italic>
</td><td>MF580475</td><td/><td>1575</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL6b</italic>
</td><td>MF580476</td><td/><td>1491</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL6c</italic>
</td><td>MF580477</td><td/><td>1563</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL6d</italic>
</td><td>MF580478</td><td/><td>1539</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL6e</italic>
</td><td>MF580479</td><td/><td>1527</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL7</italic>
</td><td>MF580480</td><td/><td>2406</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL8</italic>
</td><td>MF580481</td><td/><td>915</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL9a</italic>
</td><td>MF580482</td><td/><td>1164</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL9b</italic>
</td><td>MF580483</td><td/><td>1125</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL9c</italic>
</td><td>MF580484</td><td/><td>1146</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL12a</italic>
</td><td>MF580485</td><td/><td>3021</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL12b</italic>
</td><td>MF580486</td><td/><td>2958</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL12c</italic>
</td><td>MF580487</td><td/><td>2910</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL12d</italic>
</td><td>MF580488</td><td/><td>3027</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PhSPL13</italic>
</td><td>MF580489</td><td/><td>990</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Phylogenetic analysis of SPL proteins from petunia, tomato, and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></title><p id="Par19">To figure out the evolutionary relationship of <italic>PhSPLs</italic>, an unrooted phylogenetic tree was constructed using the highly conserved SBP-domains (76 aa, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) of 21 petunia SPL proteins (PhSPLs), 16 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> SPL proteins (AtSPLs) and 15 tomato SPL proteins (SlySBPs) by the maximum likelihood algorithm in MEGA 6.0, which demonstrated that 21 petunia SPL proteins were clustered into eight groups (Group I to Group VIII), and each group contained at least one member from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and tomato (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The Group I and Group VII contained only one SPL from petunia, Arabidopsis and tomato (PhSPL7, AtSPL7 and SlySBP7 in Group I; PhSPL13, AtSPL13 and SlySBP13 in Group VII), respectively, suggesting potential functional conservation of <italic>SPL7</italic> and <italic>SPL13</italic> genes in plants. The Group II consisted of four petunia SPLs (PhSPL12a to PhSPL12d), four Arabidopsis SPLs (AtSPL1, AtSPL12, AtSPL14 and AtSPL16), and two tomato SPLs (SlySBP12a and SlySBP12b). The Group III contained also only one SPL in petunia (PhSPL8) and Arabidopsis (AtSPL8), but two in tomato (SlySBP8a and SlySBP8b). The Group IV contained five petunia SPLs (PhSPL6a to PhSPL6e), three tomato SPLs (SlySBP6a to SlySBP6c), but only one Arabidopsis genes (AtSPL6), suggesting the fast gene duplication of SPL6 clade in petunia and even in Solanaceae family. The Group V consisted of three Arabidopsis SPLs (AtSPL2, AtSPL10 and AtSPL11), two tomato SPLs (SlySBP2 and SlySBP10) and one petunia SPL (PhSPL2)<italic>.</italic> PhCNR, PhSPL3, and PhSPL4a/b/c were clustered in Group VI, and PhSPL9a, PhSPL9b and PhSPL9c belong to Group VIII. The recognition of these different protein groups was reflected in their different gene length and genomic intron-exon structures (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Multiple alignments of the highly conserved SBP-domains. Multiple alignments of the highly conserved SBP-domains (76 aa) of 21 PhSPL proteins, 15 SlySBP proteins, and 15 AtSPL proteins. The conserved SBP domain included 2 Zn-finger structures and NLS</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic tree based on the conserved SBP domains. Phylogenetic tree based on the conserved SBP domains (76aa) alignment of 21 PhSPL predicted proteins, 16 AtSPL proteins and 15 SlySBP proteins. The tree was generated with MEGA v6.0 software, using the maximum likelihood (ML) method, and bootstrap values were calculated with 500 replicates. Groups defined were shown on the outside of the circle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Intron-exon structures of <italic>PaSPL</italic> and <italic>PiSPL</italic> genes. <bold>a</bold>, Intron-exon structures of <italic>PaSPLs.</italic>
<bold>b</bold>, Intron-exon structures of <italic>PiSPLs</italic>. 5&#x02019;UTR and 3&#x02019;UTR were not showed, the exons and intron were indicated by black block and gray thin line, respectively. The 0, 1 and 2 represented intron phases</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Sequence feature and gene structure of <italic>Petunia SPL</italic> genes</title><p id="Par20">Sequence feature analysis indicated that the length of <italic>Petunia SPL</italic> genes varied from 1024&#x000a0;bp (<italic>PaSPL4c</italic>) to 9487&#x000a0;bp (<italic>PaSPL7</italic>) in <italic>P. axillaris</italic> (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>) and 1133&#x000a0;bp (<italic>PiSPL4c</italic>) to 9350&#x000a0;bp (<italic>PiSPL7</italic>) in <italic>P. inflata</italic> (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>). The ORF length of <italic>PhSPLs</italic> varied from 285&#x000a0;bp (<italic>PhCNR</italic>) to 3027&#x000a0;bp (<italic>PhSPL12d</italic>); the size of deduced PhSPL proteins varied between 94 and 1008 amino acids (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Gene structure analysis showed that the number of exon was diverse in different groups, but was nearly consistent in the same group, such as genes in Group VI (<italic>SPL3</italic> and <italic>SPL4a/b/c</italic>) have two exons, genes in Group IV (<italic>SPL6a</italic> to <italic>SPL6e</italic>) contain 3 exons, with the exception of <italic>PaSPL6c</italic> that seems have lost the second exon, whereas genes in Group I (<italic>SPL7</italic>) and Group II (<italic>SPL12a</italic> to <italic>SPL12d</italic>) possess 10&#x02013;11 exons (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, Additional files <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>). All <italic>Petunia SPL</italic> genes were found to have an intron at an evolutionary highly conserved position in the SBP domain, although its length varied greatly among the members from the shortest 117&#x000a0;bp in <italic>PiSPL2</italic> to the longest 4396&#x000a0;bp in <italic>PiSPL9a</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Origin of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes</title><p id="Par21">To understand the origin of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes, the coding sequences of <italic>PhSPLs</italic> were used to query the Transcriptome Shotgun Assembly (TSA) database in NCBI of another two wild <italic>Petunia</italic> species, <italic>P. integrifolia</italic> and <italic>P. exserta</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Finally, nineteen <italic>SPL</italic> genes were recognized in <italic>P. integrifolia</italic> (designated as <italic>PintSPLs</italic>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>) and <italic>P. exserta</italic> (designated as <italic>PeSPLs</italic>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>), respectively. To elucidate whether <italic>P. axillaris</italic>, <italic>P. inflata</italic>, <italic>P. integrifolia</italic> or <italic>P. exserta</italic> is the donor of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes in hybrid petunia, multiple alignments of the nucleotide sequences (CDS region) of <italic>PhSPLs</italic>, <italic>PaSPLs</italic>, <italic>PiSPLs</italic>, <italic>PintSPLs</italic> and <italic>PeSPLs</italic> was conducted, and then a phylogenetic tree was constructed by the Neighbor-Joining (NJ) method. The phylogenetic analysis showed that 17 of 21 <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes, including <italic>PhSPL</italic>2, <italic>PhCNR</italic>, <italic>PhSPL3, PhSPL4a/b</italic>, <italic>PhSPL6a</italic>, <italic>PhSPL6c/d/e</italic>, <italic>PhSPL7</italic>, <italic>PhSPL9a/b/c</italic>, and <italic>PhSPL12a/b/c/d</italic>, were clustered together with their orthologs from <italic>P. axillaris</italic>, and three <italic>PhSPL</italic>s (<italic>PhSPL4c</italic>, <italic>PhSPL6b</italic> and <italic>PhSPL</italic>8) were grouped together with the orthologs of <italic>P. exserta</italic>. Interestingly, only one <italic>PhSPL</italic>s (<italic>PhSPL13</italic>) were grouped together with the orthologs of <italic>P. integrifolia</italic>, and no <italic>PhSPL</italic> gene was clustered together with the orthologs from <italic>P. inflata</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), implying that most <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes might be derived from <italic>P. axillaris</italic> or <italic>P. exserta</italic>.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic tree based on the cDNA sequence alignment of <italic>PhSPL</italic>s, <italic>PaSPL</italic>s, <italic>PiSPL</italic>s, <italic>PintSPL</italic>s and <italic>PeSPL</italic>s. <italic>PaSPL</italic>, the <italic>SPL</italic> genes of <italic>P. axillaris</italic>. <italic>PiSPL</italic>, the <italic>SPL</italic> genes from <italic>P. inflata</italic>. <italic>PintSPL</italic>, the <italic>SPL</italic> genes from <italic>P. intergrifolia</italic>. <italic>PeSPL</italic>, the <italic>SPL</italic> genes from <italic>P. exserta</italic>. The tree was generated with MEGA v6.0 software using the Neighbor-Joining (NJ) method and 1000 bootstrap replicates</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par22">To further confirmed the relationship of these <italic>SPL</italic> genes, the coding sequences of orthologs from <italic>P. hybrida</italic> W115, <italic>P. axillaris</italic>, <italic>P. integrifolia</italic>, <italic>P. inflata</italic> and <italic>P. exserta</italic>, respectively, were aligned and compared for each member. The results showed that the coding sequences of <italic>PhCNR</italic>, <italic>PhSPL3</italic>, <italic>PhSPL6a</italic>, <italic>PhSPL6d</italic>, <italic>PhSPL7</italic> and <italic>PhSPL12a/b/c</italic> were exactly the same as that of the orthologs from <italic>P. axillaris</italic>, but different at least for two nucleotides from that of the orthologs in <italic>P. inflata</italic>, <italic>P. integrifolia</italic> and <italic>P. exserta</italic> (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>), indicating that these genes are originated from <italic>P. axillaris</italic>; the coding sequences of <italic>PhSPL4c</italic> was identical to that of <italic>PeSPL4c</italic>, indicating it was most probably originated from <italic>P. exserta. PhSPL6b</italic> as well as <italic>PhSPL8</italic> showed few (1 or 2) and same number of nucleotide differences compared to the orthologs of <italic>P. axillaris</italic> and <italic>P. exserta</italic>, but with more changes (23 and 13/11 nucleotides, respectively) in comparison to <italic>PiSPL6b</italic> and <italic>PiSPL8</italic>/<italic>PintSPL8</italic>, and the differential 1&#x02013;2 nucleotides are also different from that of <italic>PiSPL6b</italic> and <italic>PiSPL8/PintSPL8</italic>, suggesting <italic>PhSPL6b</italic> and <italic>PhSPL8</italic> were derived from <italic>P. axillaris</italic> or <italic>P. exserta</italic> (the coding sequences of <italic>PaSPL6b</italic> and <italic>PeSPL6b</italic> as well as <italic>PaSPL8</italic> and <italic>PeSPL8</italic> are identical). For the rest of <italic>PhSPLs</italic> except <italic>PhSPL6c</italic> and <italic>PhSPL13</italic>, also only few (1&#x02013;8) nucleotides are different when compared with <italic>PaSPLs</italic>, while when compared with <italic>PiSPLs</italic>, <italic>PintSPLs</italic> and <italic>PeSPLs,</italic> especially the sequences from <italic>PiSPLs</italic> and <italic>PintSPLs</italic>, more nucleotide and amino acid changes were found (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>). Further inspection of the differential nucleotides showed that changed nucleotides in <italic>PhSPL4a</italic>, <italic>PhSPL6e</italic>, and <italic>PhSPL12d</italic> are also different from the genes of <italic>P. inflata</italic>, <italic>P. integrifolia</italic> and <italic>P. exserta</italic>, suggesting they may be derived from <italic>P. axillaris</italic> or originated from other relatives; in <italic>PhSPL4b,</italic> the varied 3 nucleotides are located in the latter part of the coding sequence that is identical to the sequence of <italic>PeSPL4b</italic>, indicating it may be derived from the recombination of <italic>PaSPL4b</italic> and <italic>PeSPL4b</italic>, i.e. a hybrid origin of <italic>P. axillaris</italic> and <italic>P. exserta</italic>; in <italic>PhSPL2</italic> and <italic>PhSPL9a/b/c</italic>, some of the varied nucleotides are identical to the sequences of <italic>P. inflata</italic>, <italic>P. integrifolia</italic> and/or <italic>P. exserta</italic> orthologs, while the others are different from the genes of all four species, suggesting these members may also have a hybrid origin between <italic>PhSPLs</italic> and <italic>PeSPLs</italic> or <italic>PiSPLs/PintSPLs</italic>. <italic>PhSPL13</italic>, however, showed fewer nucleotide changes compared to <italic>PeSPL13</italic> and <italic>PintSPL13</italic> than to <italic>PaSPL13</italic>, and 3 of 4 different nucleotides between <italic>PhSPL13</italic> and <italic>PeSPL13</italic> are identical to the sequences of <italic>PintSPL13</italic> and <italic>PaSPL13,</italic> while the other one is <italic>PhSPL13</italic>-specific, indicating it may be derived from the recombination of <italic>PeSPL13</italic> and <italic>PintSPL13</italic> or <italic>PaSPL13</italic>. As for <italic>PhSPL6c</italic>, it is strange that its coding sequence was almost identical (only one nucleotide variation) to that of <italic>PaSPL6c</italic> (accession number: GBRU01020485.1) from the transcriptome database of <italic>P. axillaris</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>], but the <italic>PaSPL6c</italic> gene identified in the genome of <italic>P. axillaris</italic> N [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>] showed an extended first exon (635 to 670&#x000a0;bp) and loss of the second exon (89&#x000a0;bp), so resulting in 66 nucleotide changes between <italic>PhSPL6c</italic> and the <italic>PaSPL6c</italic> identified from the genome, which was confirmed by our recent transcriptome data of <italic>P. axillaris</italic> N [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Excluding the extended and lost sequences of the genome <italic>PaSPL6c,</italic> the rest part of coding sequence was identical to that of <italic>PhSPL6c</italic>, suggesting <italic>PhSPL6c</italic> should also be derived from <italic>P. axillaris.</italic></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Conserved domains and motifs of PhSPL proteins</title><p id="Par23">The identified 21 PhSPL proteins were analyzed for conserved domains using the Conserved Domain Database in NCBI, which showed that all PhSPL proteins contained the conserved SBP domain. Multiple alignments of the SBP domains demonstrated that all SBP domain of PhSPLs except that of PhCNR contained two zinc finger motifs, Zn1 (CCCH type) and Zn2 (CCHC type), and a C-terminal nuclear localization signal (NLS), like that in other plant species (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The PhCNR protein terminated at the beginning of Zn2, so lacking the second zinc finger motif and NLS. Furthermore, four PhSPLs (PhSPL12a to PhSPL12d) belong to Group II contained an ANK domain with two ankyrin repeats, which mediate protein-protein interactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], and this is consistent with previous reports in other plants.</p><p id="Par24">The MEME was used to analyze conserved and potential motifs in PhSPL protein sequences (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>). The number of motifs in each PhSPL varies from 1 to 17 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Three motifs (motif 1, 2 and 3) constitute the SBP domain, and are conserved in all PhSPLs except for PhCNR which lack motif 2 and 3. Motif 1 is located at the first Zn finger; Motif 2 and 3 present the second Zn finger and NLS, respectively. PhSPL12a/b/c/d (Group II) are the longest group of proteins and correspondingly possess maximum number of motifs as compared to other PhSPLs. For example, motif 4, 7&#x02013;16, and 20 are all exclusively present in PhSPL12a/b/c/d proteins. Motif 5 was recognized in two members of Group II (PhSPL12b and PhSPL12d) and three members of Group IV (PhSPL6c/d/e) proteins. Motif 6 was shared by all members of Group I (PhSPL7) and Group II (PhSPL12a-d) proteins. Motif 17 was only recognized in PhSPL6c, PhSPL6d and PhSPL6e. Motif 17 was found in all Group IV proteins (PhSPL6a-e) and two Group VIII proteins (PhSPL9a and PhSPL9b). Motif 19 was present specially in the Group IV members.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>The conserved and potential motifs in PhSPL protein sequences predicted by MEME</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><italic>PhSPL</italic>s targeted by miR156/157</title><p id="Par25">In order to understand the miR156-mediated posttranscriptional regulation of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes, we searched the CDS and 3&#x02019;-UTR sequences of all <italic>PhSPLs</italic> for target site identification of petunia miR156 and miR157. Previously, ten <italic>miR156</italic> (<italic>miR0156a-g</italic> and <italic>miR0156j-l</italic>) and five <italic>miR157</italic> (<italic>miR0157a-e</italic>) genes were identified from petunia genome, which produced three kinds of mature miRNA sequences (miR0156a-g, miR0156j-l and miR0157a-e) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. A comparison of the mature PhmiR156/157 sequences to <italic>PhSPLs</italic> transcript sequences showed that 14 out of 21 <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes contained sequences complementary to the PhmiR156 or PhmiR157 mature sequences with one to two mismatches as maximum (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>), which suggests that PhmiR156/157 may specifically target these gene in petunia. These putative miR156/157 response elements (MREs) of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes were located downstream of the SBP-box in the coding region of genes in groups IV (<italic>PhSPL6a-e</italic>), V (<italic>PhSPL2</italic>), VII (<italic>PhSPL13</italic>) and VIII (<italic>PhSPL9a/b/c</italic>), while in the case of members in Group VI (<italic>PhSPL3</italic> and <italic>PhSPL4a/b/c</italic>), it was present in the 3&#x02019;-UTR regions.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Sequence alignment of petunia miR156/157 complementary sequences with the target sites in <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes. The target sites are located in the coding regions with the exception of <italic>PhSPL3</italic>, <italic>PhSPL4a</italic>, <italic>PhSPL4b</italic> and <italic>PhSPL4c</italic> where they are located in the 3&#x02019;-UTR. RC, reverse complementary sequence of the mature petunia miR156/157</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Expression patterns of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes</title><p id="Par26">Transcription activity of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes was investigated in various tissues using qPCR with gene-specific primers (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>). According to their expression patterns (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>), <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes can be roughly classified into several groups. The first group was ubiquitiously expressed at relatively high levels in all tested tissues, such as <italic>PhSPL6a</italic>, <italic>PhSPL6b</italic>, <italic>PhSPL7</italic>, <italic>PhSPL12a</italic>, <italic>PhSPL12c</italic> and <italic>PhSPL12d</italic>. <italic>PhSPL6a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL12a</italic> showed the highest expression levels in most tissues among all <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes, with <italic>PhSPL6a</italic> expressed higher in axillary buds, flower buds, and roots than in other tissues, <italic>PhSPL12a</italic> expressed higher in axillary buds, inflorescences and flower buds than in other tissues (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). <italic>PhSPL6b</italic> was expressed at significantly lower level (about 100 folds less) than <italic>PhSPL6a</italic>, with more expression in roots, inflorescences, and axillary buds than in other tissues. <italic>PhSPL7</italic> showed the expression level of higher (about 10 folds more) than <italic>PhSPL6b</italic>, but lower (about 10 folds less) than <italic>PhSPL6a</italic>, with higher expression in axillary buds, inflorescences, flower buds and young fruits. <italic>PhSPL12c</italic> and <italic>PhSPL12d</italic> displayed comparable expression levels to the <italic>PhSPL7</italic>, but they have different expression pattern, for instance, <italic>PhSPL12c</italic> was expressed at the highest level in cotyledons, followed by inflorescences, while <italic>PhSPL12c</italic> showed highest expression in inflorescences with the lowest expression level in cotyledons. The second group had no expression or was expressed at very low levels in all tissues, such as <italic>PhSPL4a, PhSPL6e</italic> and <italic>PhSPL9b</italic>. No expression was detected for <italic>PhSPL4a</italic> in most tissues but very weak expression in inflorescences and cotyledons. <italic>PhSPL6e</italic> and <italic>PhSPL9b</italic> showed the expression levels less than millesimal of the first group genes, with <italic>PhSPL6e</italic> mainly expressed in axillary buds and bracts, and <italic>PhSPL9b</italic> mainly in roots, axillary buds and flower buds. The third group was expressed specially in some tissues, including <italic>PhSPL2, PhCNR</italic>, <italic>PhSPL3, PhSPL4b</italic>, <italic>PhSPL4c</italic>, <italic>PhSPL6c</italic>, <italic>PhSPL6d</italic>, <italic>PhSPL8</italic>, <italic>PhSPL9a</italic>, <italic>PhSPL9c, PhSPL12b</italic>, and <italic>PhSPL13</italic>. <italic>PhSPL2</italic> and <italic>PhSPL13</italic> were expressed in bracts and inflorescences. <italic>PhCNR</italic> and <italic>PhSPL3</italic> were expressed mainly in axillary buds followed by inflorescences and flower buds, but the expression levels of <italic>PhCNR</italic> were significantly lower than that of <italic>PhSPL3</italic>. <italic>PhSPL4b</italic> and <italic>PhSPL4c</italic> was expressed in most tissues including stems, leaves, axillary buds, inflorescences, flower buds and bracts, but almost no transcripts were detected in fruits, young seedlings and cotyledons. <italic>PhSPL6c</italic> and <italic>PhSPL6d</italic> were expressed mainly in axillary buds and inflorescences. <italic>PhSPL8</italic> was expressed mainly in inflorescences, flower buds and fruits. <italic>PhSPL9a</italic>, <italic>PhSPL9c</italic> and <italic>PhSPL12b</italic> showed similar expression patterns, with the highest expression level in inflorescences followed by axillary buds or flower buds.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Expression patterns of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes in petunia. R, roots (7d after flowering); S, stems (7d after flowering); L, leaves (7d after flowering); Ab, axillary buds (7d after flowering); If, inflorescences; Fb, flower buds (0.5&#x000a0;cm); Fr, fruits (7d after pollination); Sl, young seedlings (4 euphylla seedling); Gs, germinal seeds (3 d after sowing); Br, bracts; and Co, cotyledons (7 d after sowing). The level of expression was normalized to petunia <italic>EF1&#x003b1;</italic> gene. Error bars represent SE for three replicates</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Overexpression of <italic>PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL9b</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></title><p id="Par27">To characterized the functions of <italic>PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL9b</italic>, two co-orthologs of <italic>AtSPL9</italic> and <italic>AtSPL15</italic>, we constructed expression vectors <italic>35S:PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>35S:PhSPL9b,</italic> then introduced into <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. Fifty-two and thirty-five independent T<sub>1</sub> transgenic lines were achieved for <italic>35S:PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>35S:PhSPL9b</italic>, respectively. Twenty-eight and twenty-one of T<sub>1</sub> transgenic lines from <italic>35S:PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>35S:PhSPL9b</italic>, respectively, showed earlier flowering than the empty pCAMBIA2300 plasmid transformed control plants (CK). According to the phenotypic alterations, for each gene construction three T<sub>1</sub> transgenic lines whose progenies showed a 3:1 segregation ratio for kanamycin resistance, which may indicate a single-copy insertion of transgenes, were chosen for further experiment of. 32&#x000a0;T<sub>2</sub> transgenic plants for each line were used to investigate the flowering time and floral phenotypes.</p><p id="Par28">Under long day conditions, the control plants initiated flowering when average 12.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8 rosette leaves and 2.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5 cauline leaves were produced (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>). In contrast, transgenic lines that exhibit severe phenotype such as <italic>PhSPL9a</italic>-4 bolted obviously earlier than CK, with significantly (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) decreased number of rosette leaves and usually determinate inflorescence that terminated with a polygynoecial flower (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8b</xref>). Most transgenic lines of <italic>35S:PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>35S:PhSPL9b</italic> showed moderate phenotypes, which bolted and flowered after producing nine to eleven rosette leaves (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8a, c</xref>; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>) under the same condition. However, there was no significant difference in the number of cauline leaf between the transgenic plants and CK.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Phenotypic analyses of transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants ectopically expressing <italic>PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL9b</italic>. gene. <bold>a</bold> The control (CK, left) and <italic>35S:PhSPL9a</italic> transgenic plants (right) showing early flowering. <bold>b</bold>
<italic>35S:PhSPL9a</italic> transgenic plants showing determinate inflorescence with a terminal polygynoecial flower (close-up). <bold>c</bold> CK (left) and <italic>35S:PhSPL9b</italic> transgenic plants (right) showing early flowering. <bold>d</bold> The numbers of rosette leaves (RL) and flowering time (FT) in CK, <italic>35S:PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>35S:PhSPL9b</italic> transgenic lines; asterisks indicate statistically significant differences (* <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, ** <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) from the CK plants. <bold>e</bold> RT-PCR analysis of transgenes in CK and transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> lines. Bars: 10&#x000a0;mm (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>c</bold>), 1&#x000a0;mm (<bold>b</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p><p id="Par29">RT-PCR analysis indicated that the phenotypic variations are related in a large extent to the expression levels of the transgenes, namely higher expression levels tend to result in more severe phenotypic changes such as earlier bolting and flowering time, and vice versa (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8d, e</xref>; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Evolution of <italic>SPL</italic> genes in <italic>Petunia</italic></title><p id="Par30">The SBP-box proteins (SPLs) constitute a family of transcription factors that play diverse roles in plant growth and development. Phylogenetic evidence indicated that SBP-box genes had underwent several ancient and more recent duplication events, resulted in the formation and retention of multiple <italic>SPL</italic> paralogs and clades [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Salinas et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] reported eight (I-VIII) major <italic>SPL</italic> clades in plants based on a phylogenetic tree of 105 <italic>SPL</italic> protein sequences from seven species using the neighbor-joining (NJ) algorithm, at least four of which predate the diversification of land plants. A latter phylogenetic analysis with a slightly different dataset of <italic>SPL</italic> genes using the maximum likelihood (ML) method supported the eight major clades, and suggested a possible ninth clade containing <italic>OsSPL14/17</italic> from rice and <italic>ZmSBP6/8</italic> from maize [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Recently, phylogenetic reconstruction with 104 full length SBP-box protein sequences from five species including moss, <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, poplar, rice and maize demonstrated that the SBP-box genes form two lineages (group I and II) through an early duplication event, and the latter is further divided into two distinct subgroups (subgroup II-1 and II-2) caused by several rounds of duplication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>].</p><p id="Par31">In this work, the <italic>SPL</italic> genes were identified from four <italic>Petunia</italic> species at genome or transcriptome scale, followed by cloning and sequencing of the orthologs from a hybrid petunia line W115. As a result, 21 putative <italic>SPL</italic> genes were identified in the genome of <italic>P. axillaris</italic> (<italic>PaSPLs</italic>) and <italic>P. inflata</italic> (<italic>PiSPLs</italic>), respectively, 19 <italic>SPL</italic> genes were recognized from the transcriptome of <italic>P. integrifolia</italic> (<italic>PintSPLs</italic>) and <italic>P. exserta</italic> (<italic>PeSPLs</italic>), respectively, and 21 <italic>SPL</italic> genes were isolated from petunia line W115 (<italic>PhSPLs</italic>), a number similar to that found in <italic>Nicotiana tomentosiformis</italic> (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref>), grape [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], and <italic>Ziziphus jujuba</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. However, in contrast to several other species in Solanaceae family, including tomato [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], pepper [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], and potato [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>], <italic>Petunia</italic> appears to contain a larger number of <italic>SPL</italic> genes (21 vs. 15), suggesting possible more duplication events of <italic>SPL</italic> genes in <italic>Petunia</italic> genome or faster loss of some members in other Solanaceae species. For instance, there are two orthologs in petunia corresponding to one gene in tomato for several members, such as <italic>PhSPL4a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL4b</italic> vs. <italic>SlySBP4</italic>, <italic>PhSPL6a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL6b</italic> vs. <italic>SlySBP6b</italic>, <italic>PhSPL12a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL12c</italic> vs. <italic>SlySBP12a</italic>, <italic>PhSPL12b</italic> and <italic>PhSPL12d</italic> vs. <italic>SlySBP12b</italic>, and <italic>PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL9b</italic> vs. <italic>SlySBP15</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The <italic>PhSPL12b</italic> and <italic>PhSPL12d</italic> gene pair was evidently produced by a more recent additional duplication in <italic>Petunia</italic>, but for other members it also could be resulted from the loss of duplicated genes in tomato. In addition, tomato has no counterparts of <italic>PhSPL4c</italic> and <italic>PhSPL9c</italic>, suggesting they may also had lost. The duplicated genes are usually followed by two kinds of destiny: loss of function by pseudogenization, or evolution of function via subfunctionalization or neofunctionalization. <italic>Petunia</italic> contains more <italic>SPL</italic> genes than the other Solanaceae species suggests that the <italic>SPLs</italic> in <italic>Petunia</italic> may undergo fast functional evolution. Similarly, there are much more Group IV <italic>SPL</italic> members in <italic>Petunia</italic> than in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, five vs. one, suggesting these duplicated genes must undergo fast subfunctionalization or neofunctionalization, and may play redundant but divergent functions. Phylogenetic analysis indicated that 21 petunia <italic>SPL</italic> genes can be divided into eight groups (Group I-VIII), which is consistent with the results of <italic>SPLs</italic> from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] and tomato [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The Group I is corresponding to the first lineage (group I) described by Zhang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>], and contains only one member (<italic>PhSPL7</italic>); the Group II is corresponding to the subgroup II-1 in the second lineage described by Zhang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>], and contains 4 members (<italic>PhSPL12a-d</italic>). This phylogenetic relationship is in accordance with the result described by Zhang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>], but different from that reported by Preston and Hileman [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], maybe due to different algorithms being used. Within each group, the exon-intron structures are almost constant, but it varied among different groups, such as the Group I and II genes are evidently longer and contain more exons compared to the other groups (10&#x02013;11 vs. 2&#x02013;4), which is consistent with the situation in most species, including monocots rice and maize [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], suggesting the <italic>SPL</italic> gene structures are relatively conserved during the evolution.</p><p id="Par32">All PhSPLs contained highly conserved SBP domain with 76 amino acid residues except for PhCNR that possess only the front part of the SBP domain (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) and lack the motif 2 and 3 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) due to a nonsense mutation at the middle of SBP domain, i.e. <italic>PhCNR</italic> gene contains a premature stop codon and encodes a truncated protein with only 94 amino acids (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The same mutation was found in <italic>PaCNR</italic> of <italic>P. axillaris</italic> (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>) but not in <italic>PiCNR</italic> of <italic>P. inflata</italic>, however, a 55-bp deletion resulting in frame shift and premature translation termination was found in <italic>PiCNR</italic> (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>), suggesting that the <italic>CNR</italic> in <italic>Petunia</italic> might be pseudogenization, which was supported further by the fact that no <italic>CNR</italic> ortholog was identified in <italic>P. exserta</italic> transcriptome (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>), but it was indeed expressed in <italic>P. axillaris, P. inflata,</italic> and W115. Similar motifs and their positions were revealed in the same group of PhSPLs and comparable with the results in other plant species, especially for the Group I and II genes, which supports the results reported by Zhang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>] that group I and subgroup II-1 genes are constrained by stronger purifying selection and evolved at a lower substitution rate than II-2 genes. The erratic gene is <italic>SPL9c</italic>, which was phylogenetically closer to the genes of Group IV (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), but has more similar gene length and intron-exon structure to members in Group VIII (Additional files <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>), so we designated it as the genes in Group VIII. However, unlike the other two members (SPL9a and SPL9b) of Group VIII, SPL9c lack the motif 18, which is similar to the members in Group IV (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p><p id="Par33">Multiple alignments of the coding sequences of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes with the orthologs from <italic>P. axillaris</italic>, <italic>P. inflata</italic>, <italic>P. integrifolia</italic>, and <italic>P. exserta</italic> demonstrated that most <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes were derived from <italic>P. axillaris,</italic> which is in consistent with the fact that <italic>P. hybrida</italic> &#x02018;Mitchell&#x02019; is a backcross hybrid of <italic>P. axillaris</italic> &#x000d7; (<italic>P. axillaris</italic> &#x000d7; <italic>P. hybrida</italic> &#x02018;Rose of Heaven&#x02019;). Sequence alignment analysis in our study suggested that several <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes including <italic>PhSPL2</italic>, <italic>PhSPL4b</italic>, <italic>PhSPL9a/b/c</italic> and <italic>PhSPL13</italic> may have a hybrid origin from <italic>P. axillaris</italic> and <italic>P. integrifolia/P. inflata</italic> or some other wild species such as <italic>P. exserta</italic>.</p><p id="Par34">It has been reported that most SBP-box family of genes are targeted by miR156/157 in a number of plant species, such as 10 of 16 <italic>Arabidopsis SPL</italic> genes are the targets of miR156/157 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], 11 of 19 <italic>OsSPL</italic> genes are predicted to be targeted by OsmiR156 in rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], and 10 of 15 <italic>SPL</italic> genes were found to be targets of miR156 in tomato [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. A target search of PhmiR156/157 against the coding regions and 3&#x02019; UTRs of petunia <italic>SPLs</italic> indicated that 14 out of 21 (two-thirds) <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes were potential targets of PhmiR156/157. All the putative PhmiR156-targeted <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes were clustered into groups IV to VIII, and miR156/157-targeting sites in 10 <italic>PhSPLs</italic> belonging to groups IV, V, VII and VIII locate in the coding region, while the target sites for other 4 <italic>PhSPLs</italic> belonging to group VI locate in the 3&#x02019; UTRs (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>), which is consistent with the results from other plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>], suggesting miR156/157-mediated post-transcriptional regulation of <italic>SPLs</italic> is a highly conserved mechanism in plants. In animals, miRNAs are prone to act by repressing translation and their target sites are mostly found in 3&#x02019; UTRs, however, plant miRNAs were believed to exert their function mainly by mediating target cleavage, so the target sites are often located in ORFs that may facilitate the destruction of target mRNA after cleavage. Besides cleavage, accumulating genetic evidence indicates that plant miRNAs also can mediate translation repression, in which situation the target sites could be located in 3&#x02019; UTRs or ORFs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Petunia group IV, V, VII and VIII <italic>SPL</italic> genes contain their miR156/157-binding sites in the coding region suggests they may be regulated by miRNA-mediated cleavage, while the group VI genes with the target sites in 3&#x02019; UTRs should be controlled by translation repression.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Expression patterns and potential functions of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes</title><p id="Par35">At present, there was few functional data of <italic>SPL</italic> genes available in petunia. Usually, the gene functions are expected to correlate in a large extent with their expression patterns. In this study, the expression of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes in various tissues were investigated by qPCR analysis, which indicated <italic>PhSPLs</italic> exhibited distinct expression patterns in terms of specificity and expression level (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Similar to the results from many other species, where <italic>SPL</italic> genes exhibited higher expression levels in the shoot apices (apical buds), inflorescences (panicles), and flower buds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>], most <italic>PhSPL</italic>s expressed predominantly in the axillary buds, inflorescences, and/or flower buds (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>), suggesting they might be involved in the development of these organs in petunia. There is no obvious correlation between gene structures and expression patterns, although some genes within the same group demonstrated similar expression profiles.</p><p id="Par36"><italic>SPL</italic> Group I and II genes are characterized by their large size and lack of miR156 and miR157-binding sites. Previous studies demonstrated that these two groups of <italic>SPL</italic> genes were almost ubiquitously expressed across different plant organs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. For instance, <italic>SlySBP7</italic>, the Group I gene in tomato, is expressed in seedlings, roots, stems, leaves, vegetative shoot apices, inflorescences, flowers, and fruits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]; the four <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Group II genes, <italic>AtSPL1</italic>, <italic>AtSPL12</italic>, <italic>AtSPL14</italic>, and <italic>AtSPL16</italic>, are expressed wildly in seedlings, roots, rosette and cauline leaves, shoot apical meristem, flowers, and fruits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Petunia Group I (<italic>PhSPL7</italic>) and Group II (<italic>PhSPL12a/b/c/d</italic>) genes also showed ubiquitous expression in all tested tissues, although they were expressed most strongly in different tissues, and <italic>PhSPL12c</italic> exhibited much lower expression levels than other genes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Currently, the only functional analysis of Group I genes is limited to <italic>Arabidopsis SPL7</italic> (<italic>AtSPL7</italic>), which was characterized to play a pivotal role in the regulation of copper homeostasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. <italic>PhSPL7</italic> may have similar functions to <italic>AtSPL7</italic> based on their conserved gene structures and expression patterns. Functional data for Group II genes exist for two members, <italic>PpSBP2</italic> and <italic>AtSPL14</italic>. Like <italic>AtSPL7</italic>, <italic>PpSBP2</italic> is involved in the regulation of copper homeostasis in <italic>Phycomitrella patens</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>], while <italic>AtSPL14</italic> is involved in response to the fungal toxin fumonisin B1 (FB1) and may also function to delay the juvenile to adult transition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Functional diversification in Group II make the function prediction of <italic>PhSPL12a/b/c/d</italic> genes unreliable, while their expression patterns suggest that they should play redundant roles in regulating the development of axillary buds, inflorescences and/or flowers, with <italic>PhSPL12c</italic> may also in cotyledon development. It might also be of interest to investigate if <italic>PhSPL12a</italic> to <italic>PhSPL12d</italic> are associated with programmed cell death in response to the FB1 in petunia.</p><p id="Par37">Group III <italic>SPL</italic> genes also lack the miR156/157-binding site, although short relative to Group I and II genes. The first Group III gene to be functionally characterized was <italic>AtSPL8</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis,</italic> which is a tissue-dependent regulator of GA response and regulate early anther development and gynoecium differential patterning, trichome formation on sepals, stamen filament elongation, and root growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. High expression of the <italic>AtSPL8</italic> orthologs <italic>SlySBP8a</italic> and <italic>SlySBP8b</italic> in inflorescences, carpels, and young fruits but very low in roots, seedlings, and stamens of tomato suggests at least partial conservation of function in gynoecium differentiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. In maize and rice, <italic>AtSPL8</italic> ortholog (<italic>LG1</italic> and <italic>OsLG1</italic>, respectively) is involved in development of the ligule and auricule [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], and controls the branch angle of tassel and panicle, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. <italic>PhSPL8</italic> was expressed more highly in inflorescences, flower buds, and young fruits versus other tissues, suggesting it may play partial conserved roles in inflorescence, anther and gynoecium development.</p><p id="Par38">Group IV contains only one <italic>SPL</italic> gene (<italic>AtSPL6</italic>) in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, but three genes (<italic>SlySBP6a/b/c</italic>) in tomato, five genes (<italic>PhSPL6a/b/c/d/e</italic>) in petunia (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), five genes (<italic>PpSBP3/6/6b/13/14</italic>) in <italic>Phycomitrella</italic>, and no orthologs in the fully sequenced genomes of rice and other grasses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], suggesting a loss of this gene lineage at least in some monocots and differential duplication and expansion in different species. <italic>AtSPL6</italic> and its ortholog <italic>NbSPL6</italic> of <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> play a conserved role in the TIR-NB-LRR receptor-mediated plant innate immunity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], while the function of <italic>PpSBP3</italic> was characterized to repress reproduction development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. In petunia, expression of the five Group IV <italic>SPL</italic> genes suggests divergence of function. Similar to <italic>AtSPL6</italic> and <italic>SlySBP6a</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], <italic>PhSPL6a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL6b</italic> were expressed constitutively across the plant, but <italic>PhSPL6a</italic> expressed predominantly in axillary buds, flower buds, and roots while <italic>PhSPL6b</italic> expressed mainly in roots, inflorescences, and axillary buds. By contrast, <italic>PhSPL6c</italic> and <italic>PhSPL6d</italic> expression was somewhat tissue-specific and confined primarily to the axillary buds and inflorescences; <italic>PhSPL6e</italic> showed very low expression and mainly in axillary buds, bracts and cotyledons (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). The additional duplications of <italic>SPL6</italic> in petunia also suggest functional redundancy, which need to be characterized yet.</p><p id="Par39">Group V contains three <italic>SPL</italic> genes (<italic>AtSPL2</italic>, <italic>AtSPL10</italic>, and <italic>AtSPL11</italic>) in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, while only one member (<italic>PhSPL2</italic>) exists in petunia. Recent studies demonstrated that <italic>AtSPL2/10/11</italic> have overlapping functions in promoting vegetative phase change and flowering [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. <italic>AtSPL2</italic> might also control floral organ development and plant fertility by directly regulating <italic>ASYMMETRIC LEAVES 2</italic> (<italic>AS2</italic>) expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. It is interesting that <italic>PhSPL2</italic> was expressed mainly in bracts and inflorescences, which is different from the constitutive expression of <italic>AtSPL2/10/11</italic> and tomato orthologs <italic>SlySBP2</italic> and <italic>SlySBP10</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. The special expression pattern of <italic>PhSPL2</italic> suggests a distinct function from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genes, which remains to be revealed.</p><p id="Par40"><italic>AtSPL3</italic>/<italic>4/5</italic> are Group VI <italic>SPL</italic> genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, which were previously considered to redundantly promote vegetative phase change and flowering based on the overexpression data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Recent detailed analysis of <italic>spl</italic> mutants, however, revealed that <italic>AtSPL3/4/5</italic> play a major role in floral meristem identity transition rather than in vegetative morphogenesis or flowering induction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Similar to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, the single <italic>AtSPL3/4/5</italic> ortholog <italic>AmSBP1</italic> in snapdragon (<italic>Antirrhinum majus</italic>) is involved in initiating flower development after the switch to inflorescence development; silencing of <italic>AmSBP1</italic> also causes an increase in vegetative branching under long days [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. By contrast, the tomato <italic>AtSPL3</italic> ortholog <italic>CNR</italic> is required for fruit ripening [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. In petunia, there are five Group VI <italic>SPL</italic> genes, <italic>PhSPL3</italic>, <italic>PhSPL4a</italic>, <italic>PhSPL4b</italic>, <italic>PhSPL4c</italic>, and <italic>PhCNR</italic>, with significantly different expression patterns and levels (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). A recent study demonstrated that <italic>PhSBP1</italic> (<italic>PhSPL3</italic>) and <italic>PhSBP2</italic> (<italic>PhSPL4c</italic>) differentially promote discrete stages of the reproductive transition, and <italic>PhSBP1,</italic> possibly also <italic>PhCNR,</italic> accelerates leaf initiation rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. This is consistent with the relatively high expression of <italic>PhSPL3</italic> and <italic>PhSPL4c</italic> in axillary buds, inflorescences, and late stage of shoot apices (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. <italic>PhCNR</italic> also expressed mainly in axillary buds, however, our sequence analysis demonstrated that <italic>PhCNR</italic>, as well as <italic>PaCNR</italic> and <italic>PiCNR</italic>, is likely to be pseudogene due to nucleotide change or deletion mutation. Compared with <italic>PhSPL3</italic> and <italic>PhSPL4c</italic>, <italic>PhSPL4a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL4b</italic> showed much lower expression, especially <italic>PhSPL4a</italic> that only expressed very faintly in inflorescence and cotyledon (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). The differential expression was also found in tomato Group VI <italic>SPL</italic> genes, <italic>SlySBP3</italic>, <italic>SlySBP4</italic>, and <italic>CNR</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], suggesting divergent and elusive evolution of functions in this group.</p><p id="Par41">Expression and functional data demonstrated that Group VII <italic>SPL</italic> genes were involved in various aspects of above ground plant development. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, the single <italic>SPL</italic> Group VII gene <italic>AtSPL13</italic> has been implicated in the regulation of the post-germinative switch from the cotyledon stage to the vegetative-leaf stage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]; it also plays overlapping roles with <italic>SPL2/10/11</italic> and <italic>SPL9/15</italic> in promoting vegetative and reproductive phase change [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In contrast, the <italic>AtSPL13</italic> ortholog in maize and rice, <italic>TGA1</italic> and <italic>OsSPL16</italic>, is involved in ear glume development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] and controls grain size, shape and quality, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], suggesting divergent functional evolution of the Group VII <italic>SPL</italic> genes. Different from <italic>AtSPL13</italic> that is expressed highly in the hypocotyl, shoot apical meristem, leaf primordia, and developing inflorescence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>], <italic>PhSPL13</italic> expressed mainly in inflorescence and bract in petunia (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>), suggesting it might have distinct functions from <italic>AtSPL13</italic>.</p><p id="Par42">Similar to <italic>AtSPL2/10/11</italic>, <italic>AtSPL9</italic> and <italic>AtSPL15</italic> belonging to Group VIII also contribute to both the vegetative and reproductive phase change, and play more important role than <italic>SPL2/10/11</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. <italic>AtSPL9</italic> was also suggested to be involved in petal trichome initiation, anthocyanin pigment accumulation, and sesquiterpene biosynthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. The genome-wide analysis indicated that petunia contains three Group VIII <italic>SPL</italic> genes, <italic>PhSPL9a</italic>, <italic>PhSPL9b</italic>, and <italic>PhSPL9c.</italic> The expression of <italic>PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL9c</italic> was mainly in the inflorescences, while <italic>PhSPL9b</italic> was expressed constitutively in all tissues, although with relatively low expression levels (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Overexpression of <italic>PhSPL9a</italic> or <italic>PhSPL9b</italic> in Arabidopsis resulted in early flowering with significantly reduced number of rosette leaves, suggesting <italic>PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL9b</italic> may have conserved functions in promoting the vegetative-to-reproductive phase transition. However, differential expression pattern between <italic>PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL9b</italic> implied their distinct functions in petunia, which awaits to be characterized in the future.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par43">We identified 21 putative <italic>SPL</italic> genes within <italic>P. axillaris</italic> and <italic>P. inflata</italic> genome, respectively, which was confirmed by cloning from <italic>P. hybrida</italic> W115. The analyses of gene structure, expression pattern, and potential functions of petunia <italic>SPLs</italic> support that the plant SBP-box genes are conserved gene family, but underwent differential expression and functional evolution within different groups and species. The present work provides an important foundation for the future elucidation of the biological functions of petunia <italic>SPL</italic> genes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec16"><title>Plant materials and bacterial strains</title><p id="Par44">The plant materials used in this study included <italic>Petunia hybrida</italic> line W115 (Mitchel diploid) and Col-0 ecotype of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. They were grown under long-day conditions (16&#x000a0;h light/8&#x000a0;h dark) with 75% humidity in a growth chamber at 21&#x02013;22&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C.</p><p id="Par45"><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strain DH5&#x003b1; was used as host in cloning of the coding sequences of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes. <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> strain GV3101 was used for transformation of <italic>Arabidopsis.</italic></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Identification and cloning of <italic>SPL</italic> genes in <italic>Petunia</italic></title><p id="Par46">Petunia SBP-box genes were identified from <italic>P. axillaris</italic> N and <italic>P. inflata</italic> S6 genome databases in Sol Genomics Network (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://solgenomics.net/">https://solgenomics.net/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>] by BLAST homology search using the nucleotide and protein sequences of 16 Arabidopsis <italic>SPL</italic> genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], 15 tomato SBP-box genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], and 22 <italic>Nicotiana tomentosiformis SPL</italic> genes (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref>), respectively. The transcriptome databases of <italic>Petunia</italic> species including <italic>P. axillaris</italic>, <italic>P. integrifolia</italic>, <italic>P. exserta</italic> and <italic>P. inflata</italic> in the NCBI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>], and <italic>P. hybrida</italic> &#x02018;Mitchell&#x02019; in Sol Genomics Network [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>] were searched for the transcripts of <italic>Petunia</italic> SBP-box genes by nucleotide BLAST with identified <italic>Petunia SPL</italic> genes.</p><p id="Par47">To confirm the results, gene-specific primers (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>) were designed to amplify the complete coding sequences of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes from <italic>P. hybrida</italic> line W115. Total RNA was extracted from mix samples of seedlings, leaves, inflorescences and flowers with RNA pure Total RNA Kit (Aidlab, China). 2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g of RNA was used for cDNA synthesis (Takara, Japan), the resulting cDNA was diluted 1:10, and then 2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l was used in PCR with 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;High-Fidelity Master Mix DNA Polymerase (Tsingke, China). The PCR conditions were 94&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 4&#x000a0;min, followed by 32&#x02013;35&#x000a0;cycles of 94&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;s, 55&#x02013;60&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;s, 72&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02013;3&#x000a0;min, and a final extension of 72&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 10&#x000a0;min. PCR products were purified from agarose gel with Axyprep DNA Gel Extraction Kit (Axygen, USA), then cloned into pMD18-T (Takara, Japan) and transformed into <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5&#x003b1;, and 4&#x02013;5 positive clones for each gene were selected randomly for sequencing analysis (Augct, China).</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Multiple sequence alignments and phylogenetic analysis</title><p id="Par48">The coding sequences of the orthologous <italic>SPL</italic> genes in <italic>P. axillaris</italic>, <italic>P. inflata</italic> and <italic>P. exserta</italic> were deduced from the genomic DNA sequences and/or the cDNA sequences from transcriptome databases by BLAST search and alignment with the confirmed coding sequences of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes. These nucleotide sequences were first aligned with the MUSCLE program implemented in MEGA 6.0 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. Phylogenetic tree of the nucleotide sequences of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes and their orthologous genes in <italic>P. axillaris</italic>, <italic>P. inflata</italic> and <italic>P. exserta</italic> was constructed using MEGA 6.0 with the Neighbor-Joining (NJ) method and 1000 bootstrap replicates.</p><p id="Par49">The SPL protein sequences of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and tomato were downloaded from the website of TAIR (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arabidopsis.org/">http://www.arabidopsis.org/</ext-link>) and the tomato genome database in Sol Genomics Network, respectively. Multiple alignments of the conserved SBP domains (76 aa) of protein sequences encoded by <italic>SPL</italic> genes of petunia, <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and tomato were conducted by the ClustalW program of MEGA 6.0. Phylogenetic relationship of SBP-box genes was estimated using the maximum likelihood (ML) method in MEGA 6.0, and bootstrap values were calculated with 500 replicates.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Analyses of the gene structure and conserved motifs in <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes</title><p id="Par50">The Gene Structure Display Server 2.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gsds.cbi.pku.edu.cn">http://gsds.cbi.pku.edu.cn</ext-link>/) was used to predict the exon-intron structure and locations of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes in the downloaded genomic sequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]. Conserved domains of PhSPL proteins were identified using the Conserved Domain Database (CDD) in NCBI with default parameters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. The MEME (Multiple Expectation Maximization for Motif Elicitation) 4.12.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://meme-suite.org/tools/meme">http://meme-suite.org/tools/meme</ext-link>) was used to predict both conserved and potential motifs of the putative PhSPL protein sequences using the parameter settings: the minimum motif width&#x02009;=&#x02009;6, the maximum motif width&#x02009;=&#x02009;50, and the maximum number of motifs&#x02009;=&#x02009;20 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Prediction of miR156/157-targeted <italic>PhSPLs</italic></title><p id="Par51"><italic>PhSPLs</italic> potentially targeted by miR156/157 were determined with petunia miR156/157 sequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>] against the coding regions and 3&#x02019;-UTRs of all PhSPLs for complementary sequences of PhmiR156/157 on the psRNATarget server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plantgrn.noble.org/psRNATarget/">http://plantgrn.noble.org/psRNATarget/</ext-link>) with default parameters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Expression pattern analyses of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes by real-time quantitative RT-PCR</title><p id="Par52">Different vegetative and reproductive tissues were harvested from petunia line W115, represented by germinating seeds (3d after sowing), cotyledons (7d after sowing), young seedlings (four euphylla stage), roots, stems, leaves and axillary buds of adult plants (after flowering), bracts, inflorescences, flower buds (0.5&#x000a0;cm), and young fruits (7d after pollination). All samples were frozen in liquid nitrogen immediately after collection and stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C until used for qPCR analysis.</p><p id="Par53">Total RNA was extracted with RNA pure Total RNA Kit (Aidlab, China). First-strand cDNA synthesis was carried out with 2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g of total RNA for each sample using the PrimeScript&#x02122; RT reagent Kit with gDNA Eraser (Takara, Japan). Real-time quantitative RT-PCR (qPCR) was performed with the SYBR Premix Ex Taq (Takara, Japan) and the ABI7500 Real-Time System (Applied Biosystems, USA) to reveal the expression level of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes in various tissues. qPCR products were amplified with 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l template of 20-fold diluted RT reaction mixture, 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;SYBR Green Master Mix, 0.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l forward and reverse primers (10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;mol/&#x003bc;l), and water to a final volume of 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l. The transcript levels of <italic>PhEF1&#x003b1;</italic> was determined for reference [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]. qPCR was performed with three biological replicates for each sample and the mean values &#x000b1; SD (standard deviation) were calculated. Data was analyzed using the 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;CT</sup> method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]. All the primers were designed by Primer-BLAST online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/tools/primer-blast/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/tools/primer-blast/</ext-link>) to avoid conserved regions and listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>. Product size was 120&#x02013;300&#x000a0;bp. Primer specificity was tested via PCR using recombinant plasmid DNA containing purpose fragment.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Vector construction and plant transformation</title><p id="Par54">The full-length cDNA sequences of the <italic>PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL9b</italic> genes were amplified and cloned into pMD-18&#x000a0;T vector (Takara, Japan). Sequence accuracy and insertion direction were confirmed by sequencing. Digestion of these vectors was conducted using SalI and BamHI (Takara, Japan) restriction endonuclease enzymes, and the digested products were ligated into the appropriate sites of pCAMBIA2300 vector containing the <italic>CaMV35S</italic> promoter, to create the constructs <italic>35S:PhSPL9a</italic> and 35S<italic>:PhSPL9b</italic>. All the constructed plasmids were confirmed by PCR and restriction digestions. <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> GV3101 containing the respective expression vectors was used for <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (Col-0) transformation via the floral dip method. The transformed seeds were surface-sterilized with 8% (<italic>v</italic>/v) sodium hypochlorite solution for 4&#x000a0;min followed by 95% (v/v) ethanol for 2&#x000a0;min, then rinsed 3 times in sterile water and screened on half-strength Murashige and Skoog (1/2MS) medium supplemented with 50&#x000a0;mg/L kanamycin sulfate (Biosharp, China) and 50&#x000a0;mg/L cefotaxime sodium salt (Biosharp, China). The plants that survived were transplanted into soil and grown under long-day conditions (16&#x000a0;h light/8&#x000a0;h dark) at 22&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C to obtain self-pollinated seeds.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Phenotype and transgene expression analysis</title><p id="Par55">Following the segregation tests, 32 kanamycin-resistant transgenic plants of the T<sub>2</sub> generation lines which fitted a segregation ratio of 3:1 were chosen to record flowering time and floral phenotype. Seedlings were grown in a growth incubator at 22&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C under a long day (LD) conditions (16/8&#x000a0;h, light/dark). Flowering time and the number of rosette leaves were measured when the plants bore a 1&#x000a0;cm long inflorescence.</p><p id="Par56">RT-PCR was performed to analysis the expression of the transgene in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, which were carried out on 14-d-old seedlings. Total RNA was isolated and then reverse-transcribed from the control plants (Col-0 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> transformed with the empty pCAMBIA2300 plasmid) and T<sub>1</sub> transgenic lines with the same reagent kit described above. <italic>Arabidopsis EF1&#x003b1;</italic> gene was used as the reference gene to normalize small differences in template amounts. Primers used for the detection of <italic>PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL9b</italic> expression levels in the transgenic plants were listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par57">Statistical differences were analyzed using ANOVA (analysis of variance) in IBM SPSS Statistics 22 based on Duncan&#x02019;s multiple range test (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec25"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p>Orthologous <italic>SPL</italic> genes in <italic>P. axillaris</italic> N genome. <sup>a</sup>Sequence ID corresponds to annotations provided by <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://solgenomics.net/organism/Petunia_axillaris/genome">https://solgenomics.net/organism/Petunia_axillaris/genome</ext-link> (v1.6.2) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. <sup>b</sup> The transcripts were identified by nucleotide BLAST search of the TSA (Transcriptome Shotgun Assembly) database of <italic>Petunia axillaris</italic> in the NCBI and confirmed by alignment with AlignX program in Vector NTI Advance v11.5.2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. (DOCX 18 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_MOESM2_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p>Orthologous <italic>SPL</italic> genes in <italic>P. inflata</italic> S6 genome and <italic>P. intergifolia</italic> transcriptome. <sup>a</sup> Sequence ID corresponds to annotations provided by <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://solgenomics.net/organism/Petunia_axillaris/genome">https://solgenomics.net/organism/Petunia_axillaris/genome</ext-link> (v1.0.1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>] <sup>b</sup> The transcripts were identified by nucleotide BLAST search of the TSA (Transcriptome Shotgun Assembly) database of <italic>Petunia integrifolia</italic> (GBRV) and <italic>P. integrifolia</italic> Subs<italic>p. inflata</italic> (GBDS) in the NCBI and confirmed by alignment with AlignX program in Vector NTI Advance v11.5.2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. &#x02018;/&#x02019; indicates no orthologous transcript was found. (DOCX 22 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_MOESM3_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 3:</label><caption><p>Orthologous <italic>SPL</italic> genes in the transcriptome database of <italic>P. exserta </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. The genes were identified by nucleotide BLAST search of the TSA (Transcriptome Shotgun Assembly) database of <italic>Petunia exserta</italic> in the NCBI with <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes and confirmed by alignments with AlignX program in Vector NTI Advance v11.5.2. &#x02018;&#x02013;&#x02019; indicated no transcripts was identified. Partial represent the ORF sequence was not complete [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. (DOCX 14 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_MOESM4_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 4:</label><caption><p>The analysis of nucleotide differences and the resultant amino acid variations between <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes and their orthologs in <italic>P. axillaris</italic> N, <italic>P. inflata</italic> S6, <italic>P. intergifolia</italic> and <italic>P. exserta</italic>. &#x02018;/&#x02019; indicates no ortholog was identified in this species; &#x02018;-&#x02019; indicates no protein can be translated for this gene. (DOCX 16 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_MOESM5_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 5:</label><caption><p>The specific information of conserved and potential motifs in PhSPL protein sequences predicted by MEME. (DOCX 1340 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_MOESM6_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 6:</label><caption><p>Primers used in this study. <bold>a</bold> Primer pairs used for the cloning of complete CDS. <bold>b</bold> Primer pairs used for qRT-PCR and transgene RT-PCR. (DOCX 18 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7"><media xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_MOESM7_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 7:</label><caption><p>Heat map of <italic>PhSPL</italic> genes expression in various tissues. Differences in gene expression are shown in color according to the scale. R, roots; S, stems; L, leaves; Ab, axillary buds; If, inflorescencess; Fb, flower buds; Fr, young fruits; Sl, young seedlings; Gs, germinating seeds; Br, bracts; Co, cotyledons. (DOCX 89 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM8"><media xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_MOESM8_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 8:</label><caption><p>Phenotypes of the transgenic Arabidopsis plants overexpressing <italic>PhSPL9a</italic> and <italic>PhSPL9b</italic> genes. 32&#x000a0;T<sub>2</sub> transgenic plants of putative single-copy transgenic lines were chosen to record flowering time and floral phenotype. Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;32). Asterisk indicated significant difference in comparison with the empty plasmid transgenic Col-0 plants (CK) (*<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). (DOCX 12 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM9"><media xlink:href="12864_2018_4537_MOESM9_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 9:</label><caption><p><italic>SPL</italic> genes of <italic>Nicotiana tomentosiformis</italic> annotated in NCBI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. (DOCX 15 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ML</term><def><p id="Par4">maximum likelihood</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NJ</term><def><p id="Par5">Neighbor-Joining</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NLS</term><def><p id="Par6">nuclear localization signal</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>qPCR</term><def><p id="Par7">real-time quantitative RT-PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RT-PCR</term><def><p id="Par8">reverse transcription PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SBP</term><def><p id="Par9">SQUAMOSA PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>SPL</italic></term><def><p id="Par10">
<italic>SQUAMOSA PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN-LIKE</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TFs</term><def><p id="Par11">transcription factors</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UTR</term><def><p id="Par12">untranslated region</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank all colleagues in our laboratory for helpful discussions and technical assistance.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par58">This work was financially supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 31471914, 31772345) and the Ministry of Education of China (IRT13065). The funding bodies had no role in the design of the study and collection, analysis, and interpretation of data and in writing the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par59">The genome sequences of <italic>P. axillaris</italic> and <italic>P. inflata</italic> used for identifying the SBP-box genes in current study were located in Sol Genomics Network (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://solgenomics.net/organism/Petunia_axillaris/genome">https://solgenomics.net/organism/Petunia_axillaris/genome</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://solgenomics.net/organism/Petunia_inflata/genome">https://solgenomics.net/organism/Petunia_inflata/genome</ext-link>, respectively) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. The transcriptome databases used to identify <italic>SPL</italic> genes of <italic>P. axillaris</italic>, <italic>P. exserta</italic> and <italic>P. integrifolia</italic> were available in NCBI under accessions GBRU01000000, GBRT01000000, and GBRV01000000, respectively.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>] The transcriptome databases of <italic>P. inflata</italic> were available in NCBI under accessions GBDS00000000, GBDR00000000, and GBDQ00000000.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>] The transcriptome sequences of <italic>P. hybrida</italic> &#x02018;Mitchell&#x02019; was located in Sol Genomics Network (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://solgenomics.net/">https://solgenomics.net/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. The sequences information of <italic>PhSPLs</italic> were registered in the NCBI (accession number MF580469-MF580489).</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>QZ designed and performed the experiments, carried out the bioinformatics analyses, and drafted the manuscript. SSZ participated in guiding and carrying out some experiments. FC participated in gene expression analysis. BJL, LW, and FL participated in data analysis and taking care of the plant materials. JQZ participated in directing the study. MZB participated in the design of this project. GFL, as the corresponding author, provided the idea and designed the framework of this study, and modified the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>The seeds of <italic>Petunia hybrida</italic> line W115 (Mitchel diploid) and Col-0 ecotype of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> were collected in Huazhong Agricultural University (HZAU), China. These plant materials are widely used laboratory strains all over the world. No permits are required for the collection of plant samples. The plant materials are maintained following the institutional guidelines of College of Horticulture and Forestry Sciences, HZAU, China. All the experiments including field studies were conducted in accordance with China&#x02019;s legislation and the regulations of HZAU. This article did not contain any studies with human participants or animals, and did not involve any endangered or protected species.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PlantTFDB 4.0: toward a central hub for transcription factors and regulatory interactions in plants</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>45</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><fpage>D1040</fpage><lpage>D1045</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw982</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27924042?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27924042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new family of DNA binding proteins includes putative transcriptional regulators of the <italic>Antirrhinum majus</italic> floral meristem identity gene <italic>SQUAMOSA</italic></article-title><source>Mol Gen Genet</source><year>1996</year><volume>250</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><?supplied-pmid 8569690?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8569690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative study of SBP-box gene family in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and rice</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2008</year><volume>407</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2007.02.034</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17629421?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17629421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birkenbihl</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jach</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional dissection of the plant-specific SBP-domain: overlap of the DNA-binding and nuclear localization domains</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>352</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2005.07.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16095614?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16095614</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kigawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tateno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yabuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunokawa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A novel zinc-binding motif revealed by solution structures of DNA-binding domains of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> SBP-family transcription factors</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>337</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2004.01.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15001351?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15001351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kropat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tottey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Birkenbihl</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Depege</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A regulator of nutritional copper signaling in <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> is an SBP domain protein that recognizes the GTAC core of copper response element</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><issue>51</issue><fpage>18730</fpage><lpage>18735</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0507693102</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16352720?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16352720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazarenus</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a consensus DNA-binding site for the <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> SBP domain transcription factor, <italic>AtSPL14</italic>, and binding kinetics by surface plasmon resonance</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2008</year><volume>47</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>3645</fpage><lpage>3653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi701431y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18302343?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18302343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hileman</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional evolution in the plant <italic>SQUAMOSA-PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN-LIKE</italic> (<italic>SPL</italic>) gene family</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>80</fpage><?supplied-pmid 23577017?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23577017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Earley</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Poethig</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developmental functions of miR156-regulated <italic>SQUAMOSA PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN-LIKE</italic> (<italic>SPL</italic>) genes in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e1006263</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1006263</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardon</surname><given-names>GHS</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nettesheim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterisation of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> SBP-box genes</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>1999</year><volume>237</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-1119(99)00308-X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10524240?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10524240</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salinas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Berndtgen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic organization, phylogenetic comparison and differential expression of the SBP-box family of transcription factors in tomato</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2012</year><volume>235</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1171</fpage><lpage>1184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-011-1565-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22160465?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22160465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic organization, phylogenetic comparison and differential expression of the SBP-box family genes in grape</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e59358</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059358</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23527172?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23527172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassett</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide identification and analysis of the SBP-box family genes in apple (<italic>Malus</italic> &#x000d7; <italic>domestica</italic> Borkh.)</article-title><source>Plant Physiol Bioch</source><year>2013</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2013.05.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>LZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide identification and evolutionary analysis of the SBP-box gene family in castor bean</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e86688</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086688</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24466202?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24466202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of the <italic>SPL</italic> gene family in <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic></article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>131</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-14-131</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24884654?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24884654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shalom</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shlizerman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zur</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Doron-Faigenboim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumwald</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of <italic>SQUAMOSA PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN-LIKE</italic> (<italic>SPL</italic>) gene family from citrus and the effect of fruit load on their expression</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>389</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.00389</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26074947?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26074947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic organization, differential expression, and functional analysis of the <italic>SPL</italic> gene family in <italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic></article-title><source>Mol Genet and Genomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>290</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00438-014-0901-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25159110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide identification and analysis of the SBP-box family genes under phytophthora capsici stress in pepper (<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>504</fpage><?supplied-pmid 27148327?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27148327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>DZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization and phylogenetic analysis of fifteen <italic>NtabSPL</italic> genes in <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> L. cv. Qinyan95</article-title><source>Dev Genes Evol</source><year>2016</year><volume>226</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00427-015-0522-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26635304?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26635304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fu L, Hu Q. Genomic identification, characterization and differential expression analysis of SBP-box gene family in <italic>Brassica napus</italic></article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>196</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-016-0852-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27608922?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27608922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Goel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahuja</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic organization, phylogenetic comparison, and expression profiles of the <italic>SPL</italic> family genes and their regulation in soybean</article-title><source>Dev Genes Evol</source><year>2017</year><volume>227</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00427-017-0574-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28133699?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28133699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide identification and expression analysis of SBP-like transcription factor genes in Moso bamboo (Phyllostachys edulis)</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>486</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-017-3882-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28655295?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28655295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The miR156/SPL module, a regulatory hub and versatile toolbox, gears up crops for enhanced agronomic traits</article-title><source>Mol Plant</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2015.01.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25617719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25617719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chuck</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cigan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Saeteurn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The heterochronic maize mutant <italic>Corngrass1</italic> results from overexpression of a tandem microRNA</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2007</year><volume>39</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>544</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng2001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17369828?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17369828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Poethig</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temporal regulation of shoot development in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> by miR156 and its target <italic>SPL3</italic></article-title><source>Development</source><year>2006</year><volume>133</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>3539</fpage><lpage>3547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.02521</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16914499?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16914499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferreira e Silva</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Azevedo-Mda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Guivin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramiro</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueiredo</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Peres</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nogueira</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>microRNA156-targeted SPL/SBP-box transcription factors regulate tomato ovary and fruit development</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2014</year><volume>78</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>604</fpage><lpage>618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12493</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24580734?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24580734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>QW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of miR156/SPLs modules in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> lateral root development</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2015</year><volume>83</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12919</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26096676?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26096676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohalmi</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Amyot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannoufa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>SQUAMOSA PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN-LIKE 2</italic> controls floral organ development and plant fertility by activating <italic>ASYMMETRIC LEAVES 2</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>92</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-016-0536-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27605094?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27605094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Poethig</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The microRNA-regulated SBP-box transcription factor <italic>SPL3</italic> is a direct upstream activator of <italic>LEAFY</italic>, <italic>FRUITFULL</italic>, and <italic>APETALA1</italic></article-title><source>Dev Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2009.06.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19686687?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19686687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>SPL3/4/5</italic> integrate developmental aging and photoperiodic signals into the FT-FD module in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flowering</article-title><source>Mol Plant</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1647</fpage><lpage>1659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2016.10.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27815142?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27815142</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Padmanabhan</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Burch-Smith</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Czymmek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinesh-Kumar</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel positive regulatory role for the <italic>SPL6</italic> transcription factor in the N TIR-NB-LRR receptor-mediated plant innate immunity</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e1003235</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003235</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23516366?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23516366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukazawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shikanai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>SQUAMOSA promoter binding protein-like 7</italic> is a central regulator for copper homeostasis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.108.060137</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19122104?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19122104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gielen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Remans</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vangronsveld</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuypers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxicity responses of cu and cd: the involvement of miRNAs and the transcription factor <italic>SPL7</italic></article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>145</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-016-0830-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27352843?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27352843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Unte</surname><given-names>US</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pesaresi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gandikota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leister</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>SPL8</italic>, an SBP-box gene that affects pollen sac development in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1009</fpage><lpage>1019</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.010678</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12671094?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12671094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Salinas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Berndtgen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR156-targeted and nontargeted SBP-box transcription factors act in concert to secure male fertility in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>3935</fpage><lpage>3950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.110.079343</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21177480?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21177480</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>SPL8</italic>, a local regulator in a subset of gibberellin-mediated developmental processes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>63</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-006-9099-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17093870?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17093870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Salinas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Molina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Berndtgen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>SPL8</italic> and miR156-targeted <italic>SPL</italic> genes redundantly regulate <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> gynoecium differential patterning</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2013</year><volume>75</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12221</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23621152?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23621152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Nekl</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Stiers</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis <italic>AtSPL14</italic>, a plant-specific SBP-domain transcription factor, participates in plant development and sensitivity to fumonisin B1</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2005</year><volume>41</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>744</fpage><lpage>754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02334.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15703061?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15703061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nussbaum-Wagler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Vigouroux</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Faller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bomblies</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukens</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Doebley</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The origin of the naked grains of maize</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>436</volume><issue>7051</issue><fpage>714</fpage><lpage>719</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature03863</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16079849?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16079849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Control of grain size, shape and quality by <italic>OsSPL16</italic> in rice</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2012</year><volume>44</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>950</fpage><lpage>954</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2327</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22729225?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22729225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The OsSPL16-GW7 regulatory module determines grain shape and simultaneously improves rice yield and grain quality</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2015</year><volume>47</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>949</fpage><lpage>954</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3352</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26147620?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26147620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dellaporta</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>liguleless1</italic> encodes a nuclear-localized protein required for induction of ligules and auricles during maize leaf organogenesis</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1997</year><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>616</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.11.5.616</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9119226?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9119226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations in the rice liguleless gene result in a complete loss of the auricle, ligule, and laminar joint</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>65</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>499</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-007-9196-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17594063?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17594063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Numaguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Thanh</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Htun</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Komeda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Terauchi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>OsLG1</italic> regulates a closed panicle trait in domesticated rice</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>45</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>462</fpage><lpage>465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2567</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23435087?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23435087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic control of inflorescence architecture during rice domestication</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>2200</fpage><?supplied-pmid 23884108?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23884108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinheimer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Durantini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kellogg</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TCP transcription factor, BRANCH ANGLE DEFECTIVE 1 (BAD1), is required for normal tassel branch angle formation in maize</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><issue>30</issue><fpage>12225</fpage><lpage>12230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1202439109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22773815?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22773815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A naturally occurring epigenetic mutation in a gene encoding an SBP-box transcription factor inhibits tomato fruit ripening</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2006</year><volume>38</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>948</fpage><lpage>952</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1841</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16832354?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16832354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vandenbussche</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambrier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues Bento</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Petunia, your next supermodel?</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>72</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2016.00072</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26870078?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26870078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Orozco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hileman</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Paralogous <italic>SQUAMOSA PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN-LIKE</italic> (<italic>SPL</italic>) genes differentially regulate leaf initiation and reproductive phase change in petunia</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2016</year><volume>243</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-015-2413-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26445769?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26445769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bombarely</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Amrad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bapaume</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bliek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boersma</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Borghi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruggmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insight into the evolution of the Solanaceae from the parental genomes of <italic>Petunia hybrida</italic></article-title><source>Nat Plants</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>16074</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nplants.2016.74</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27255838?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27255838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stehmann</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenz-Lemke</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Semir</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gerats</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Strommer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genus petunia</article-title><source>Petunia: evolutionary, developmental and physiological genetics</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer Science &#x00026; Business Media</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiegert-Rininger</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallejo</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome-enabled marker discovery and mapping of plastochron-related genes in <italic>Petunia</italic> spp</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>726</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-015-1931-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26400485?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26400485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hybrid sequencing and map finding (HySeMaFi): optional strategies for extensively deciphering gene splicing and expression in organisms without reference genome</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>43793</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep43793</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28272530?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28272530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahajan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ankyrin repeat: a unique motif mediating protein-protein interactions</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2006</year><volume>45</volume><issue>51</issue><fpage>15168</fpage><lpage>15178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi062188q</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17176038?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17176038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>LZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution and divergence of SBP-box genes in land plants</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>787</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-015-1998-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26467431?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26467431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide identification and characterization of the <italic>SPL</italic> gene family in <italic>Ziziphus jujuba</italic></article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2017</year><volume>627</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2017.06.044</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28652183?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28652183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kavas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kizildogan</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Abanoz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative genome-wide phylogenetic and expression analysis of <italic>SBP</italic> genes from potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic>)</article-title><source>Comput Biol Chem</source><year>2017</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compbiolchem.2017.01.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28081487?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28081487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide identification and evolutionary analysis of the plant specific SBP-box transcription factor family</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2008</year><volume>418</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2008.03.016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18495384?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18495384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MicroRNAs inhibit the translation of target mRNAs on the endoplasmic reticulum in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2013</year><volume>153</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>562</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2013.04.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23622241?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23622241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>LZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic organization, differential expression, and interaction of <italic>SQUAMOSA</italic> promoter-binding-like transcription factors and microRNA156 in rice</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>142</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>280</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.106.084475</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16861571?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16861571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagae</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of negative cis-acting elements in response to copper in the chloroplastic iron superoxide dismutase gene of the moss <italic>Barbula unguiculata</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>146</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1687</fpage><lpage>1696</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.107.114868</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18258690?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18258690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Coruh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Axtell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR156 and miR390 regulate tasiRNA accumulation and developmental timing in <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>4837</fpage><lpage>4849</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.103176</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23263766?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23263766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shikata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Koyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsuda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohme-Takagi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> SBP-box genes <italic>SPL10</italic>, <italic>SPL11</italic> and <italic>SPL2</italic> control morphological change in association with shoot maturation in the reproductive phase</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>50</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2133</fpage><lpage>2145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcp148</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19880401?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19880401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hileman</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>SQUAMOSA-PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN 1</italic> initiates flowering in <italic>Antirrhinum majus</italic> through the activation of meristem identity genes</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2010</year><volume>62</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>704</fpage><lpage>712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04184.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20202170?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20202170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Asahina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristof</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Coppersmith</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pluskota</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassel</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Goloviznina</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Andujar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The regulation of post-germinative transition from the cotyledon- to vegetative-leaf stages by microRNA-targeted <italic>SQUAMOSA PROMOTER-BINDING PROTEIN LIKE 13</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Seed Sci Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>20</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0960258510000073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progressive regulation of sesquiterpene biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and patchouli (<italic>Pogostemon cablin</italic>) by the miR156-targeted SPL transcription factors</article-title><source>Mol Plant</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2014.11.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25578275?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25578275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gou</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Felippes</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Negative regulation of anthocyanin biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> by a miR156-targeted SPL transcription factor</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2011</year><volume>23</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1512</fpage><lpage>1522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.111.084525</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21487097?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21487097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temporal control of trichome distribution by microRNA156-targeted <italic>SPL</italic> genes in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>2322</fpage><lpage>2335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.109.072579</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20622149?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20622149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Der</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>dePamphilis</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome analysis reveals the same 17 S-locus F-box genes in two haplotypes of the self-incompatibility locus of <italic>Petunia inflata</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2014</year><volume>26</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>2873</fpage><lpage>2888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.114.126920</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25070642?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25070642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Villarino</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bombarely</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scanlon</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptomic analysis of <italic>Petunia hybrida</italic> in response to salt stress using high throughput RNA sequencing</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e94651</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094651</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24722556?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24722556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Filipski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEGA6: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2725</fpage><lpage>2729</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mst197</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24132122?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24132122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GSDS 2.0: an upgraded gene feature visualization server</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2015</year><volume>31</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1296</fpage><lpage>1297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu817</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25504850?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25504850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marchler-Bauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Derbyshire</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chitsaz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Geer</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Geer</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gwadz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurwitz</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CDD: NCBI's conserved domain database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>43</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><fpage>D222</fpage><lpage>D226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku1221</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25414356?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25414356</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Boden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Buske</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Frith</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Clementi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEME SUITE: tools for motif discovery and searching</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><issue>Web Server</issue><fpage>W202</fpage><lpage>W208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkp335</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19458158?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19458158</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>PX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>psRNATarget: a plant small RNA target analysis server</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>39</volume><issue>Web Server issue</issue><fpage>W155</fpage><lpage>W159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr319</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21622958?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21622958</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallona</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lischewski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hause</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Egea-Cortines</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validation of reference genes for quantitative real-time PCR during leaf and flower development in <italic>Petunia hybrida</italic></article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-10-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20056000?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20056000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;CT</sup> method</article-title><source>Methods</source><year>2001</year><volume>25</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11846609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>