<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vet Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Vet. Med. Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JVMS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Veterinary Medical Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0916-7250</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1347-7439</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6207528</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">18-0341</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.18-0341</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical Pathology</subject><subj-group><subject>Note</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Detection of bovine papillomavirus type 2 DNA in calf conjunctival myofibroblastoma </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>HATAMA</surname><given-names>Shinichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>MURAKAMI</surname><given-names>Kenji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>YAMAMOTO</surname><given-names>Shinji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>KADOTA</surname><given-names>Koichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1)</label>National Institute of Animal Health, National Agriculture
and Research Organization, 3-1-5 Kannondai, Tsukuba, Ibaraki 305-0856, Japan</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2)</label>Nakasorachi NOSAI, 1-5-14 Omachi, Takikawa, Hokkaido
073-0022, Japan</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3)</label>Souya Livestock Hygiene Service Center, 8-3 Midorigaoka,
Hamatonbetsu, Esashi, Hokkaido 098-5738, Japan</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4)</label>Hokkaido Research Station, National Institute of Animal
Health, National Agriculture and Research Organization, 4 Hitsujigaoka, Toyohira, Sapporo,
Hokkaido 062-0045, Japan</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Hatama, S.: <email xlink:href="hatama@affrc.go.jp">hatama@affrc.go.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>80</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1544</fpage><lpage>1548</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>©2018 The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. (CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0:
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>)</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>An 8-month-old male Japanese Black calf was referred for the evaluation of a slow-growing conjunctival mass in the right eye. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>A superficial keratectomy was performed followed by recurrence on two occasions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>No metastases were found in surrounding tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Histological, immunohistochemical, and ultrastructural investigation revealed that both the primary and the recurrent lesions were benign, conjunctival, myofibroblastomas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, bovine papillomavirus type 2 (BPV-2) DNA was detected in both myofibroblastoma lesions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Archival bovine myofibroblastomas from the vulva and neck were also analyzed for papillomaviral genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>BPV-2 DNA was also amplified from these lesions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report describing a potential causal relationship between BPV-2 infection and conjunctival myofibroblastoma. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>bovine papillomavirus type 2</kwd><kwd>calf</kwd><kwd>conjunctival myofibroblastoma</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Myofibroblastoma is an uncommon, benign, mesenchymal tumor, predominantly occurring in the breast tissue of menopausal women and older men [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Sarcomas of myofibroblastic origin have also been described in the leg and the mammary glands of two cats [5, 11] and in the mesentery and abdomen of two horses [12, 20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>In cattle, three cases of myofibroblastoma of the nose, neck, and abdomen [12, 26], and two cases of the vulva [1, 26] have been described. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Myofibroblastoma of the eye has not yet been described. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Myofibroblasts are seen in both normal and damaged tissue; in the intestine, lung, testis, ovary, and adrenal gland and in granulation and scar tissue, where they perform both a contractile and a secretory function [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Myofibroblasts are also found in numerous fibroblastic tumors, e.g., fibroma, fibrosarcoma, and liposarcoma [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Some histologically-defined cases of myofibroblastoma have been composed almost entirely of myofibroblasts [8] and could have originated from different types of precursor cells, e.g., fibroblasts, pericytes, smooth muscle cells, bone marrow-derived stem cells, epithelium, and endothelium [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Neoplastic transformation of myofibroblasts occasionally occurs in humans and various other animal species but their etiology is not yet clearly defined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>In humans, genetic evidence for an association with human herpesvirus 8 and Epstein-Barr virus has been described [2, 9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Tumorigenesis caused by bovine papillomavirus (BPV) infection in cattle is well studied and the causal virus is believed to be highly epitheliotropic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>However, new BPV type 2 (BPV-2) tissue tropisms are increasing and a recent study revealed that BPV-2 can infect not only bovine epithelial, but also bovine mesenchymal cells, e.g., glomus tumors [21], hemangioma [4], bovine peripheral blood mononuclear cells [23], and bovine trophoblast cells, such as the placenta [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The goal of this study was to describe the clinical and histological features of a calf conjunctival myofibroblastoma and to investigate its potential relationship with BPV infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>An 8-month-old male Japanese Black calf with a history of a slow-growing, isolated, conjunctival mass in the right eye was referred to the Livestock Hygiene Service Center, Hokkaido, Japan for diagnosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>No systemic abnormalities were noted on routine physical examination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmic examination revealed a soft, milky-white, pedunculated nodule with red areas of hemorrhage, 1.2 × 1.0 cm in size and localized in the dorsolateral aspect of the cornea (Fig. 1Fig. 1.Conjunctival myofibroblastoma in an 8-month-old male Japanese Black calf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>A pedunculated solid nodule is observed in the dorsolateral aspect of the cornea.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The limbus was not involved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The tissue on the cut surface was traversed by bands of fibrous tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Two months after the first superficial keratectomy, recurrence was detected, and the lesion was surgically removed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>A further recurrence occurred 2 months later, and a third keratectomy was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>After these treatments, no further recurrence was observed during a 24-month follow-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The primary and the first recurrent lesions, which had similar macroscopic features, were processed for histological and immunohistochemical examination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The second recurrent lesion was not available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Surgical treatments were performed in the lying position (the first keratectomy) or the standing position (the second and the third keratectomy) under sedative and analgestic conditions via intravenous injection of 0.15 mg/kg xylazine, and under nerve block condition via injection of 10 ml of 2% lidocaine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Animal housing, treatment, and sampling conformed to the institutional guidelines approved by the ethics committee of National Institute of Animal Health. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The lesions were fixed in 10% buffered formalin and embedded in paraffin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Four µm sections were prepared for hematoxylin-eosin (H&amp;E) and immunohistochemistry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemical staining was carried out using a streptavidin-biotin-peroxidase complex method (Nichirei, Tokyo, Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The primary antibodies used were mouse monoclonal antibodies to alpha smooth muscle actin (SMA) (DAKO A/S, Glostrup, Denmark), vimentin (Dako Corporation, Carpinteria, CA, U.S.A.), desmin (Bio-Science Products, Emmenbrücke, Switzerland), proliferating cell nuclear antigen (PCNA) (BioGenex Laboratories, San Ramon, CA, U.S.A.), rabbit polyclonal antibody to BPV-1 L1 protein (Quartett, Berlin, Germany), and mouse monoclonal antibody to BPV-1 E2 protein (1E2, Thermo Scientific, Rockford, IL, U.S.A.). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Small blocks of formalin-fixed neoplastic tissue from the primary mass were post-fixed with 1% osmium tetroxide and embedded in epoxy resin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Ultra-thin sections were cut, stained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate, and examined with an electron microscope (EM) [1]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Total DNA was extracted from paraffin sections using the phenol-chloroform-isoamyl alcohol method [15] and it was used as a template for polymerase chain reaction (PCR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>PCR amplification of the BPV L1 gene with primers subAup/subAdw followed by nucleotide sequencing and genotyping was performed as previously described [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>These primers were designed to target highly conserved L1 regions of Delta and Epsilon papillomavirus and could amplify all the known BPVs in both genera [10, 17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>For comparison, bovine herpesviruses-specific PCR, which targeted infectious bovine rhinotracheitis virus, bovine herpes mammillitis virus, Movar-type herpesvirus, bovine herpesvirus type 5, and alcelaphine herpesvirus 1, was performed as described by Kálmán et al. [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Similar PCR for detection of BPVs and bovine herpesviruses and nucleotide sequencing analyses was also performed on the previously diagnosed neck and vulva myofibroblastomas [1, 13, 26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>To prepare the gene probe for in situ hybridization (ISH), 1 µg of cloned BPV-2 DNA (~8 kb) was labeled with digoxigenin-11-dUTP (DIG) using a DIG-High Prime kit (Roche Applied Science, Basel, Switzerland) and stored at −20°C until used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>ISH was performed according to the manufacturer’s protocol (Roche Applied Science). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Tissue sections were deparaffinized with xylene, rehydrated, and digested with proteinase K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Hybridization was carried out at 42°C for 3 hr with 2 ng/µl of DIG-labeled DNA probe in the hybridization solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>After washing twice in 2 × SSC and once in 0.1 × SSC, the slides were soaked in antibody dilution (AB) buffer and then in blocking solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Antibody incubation was performed for 1 hr at room temperature (RT) with alkaline phosphatase (AP)-labeled goat-anti-DIG antibody (1:1,000 dilution; Roche Applied Science) in blocking solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Sections were then washed thoroughly in AB buffer and equilibrated in AP buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>AP activity was detected by the addition of the chromogen/substrate 4-nitrobluetetrazolium chloride and 5 bromo-4 chloro-3-indolyl-phosphate (NBT/BCIP, Roche) in AP buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The sections were briefly washed with PBS, counterstained with neutral red, and examined by light microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Sections of fibropapilloma with BPV-2 infection and normal bovine conjunctiva for positive and negative controls were also included. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Histologically, the primary tumor mass was composed of tumor cells and collagen fibers and had relatively unclear boundaries with the adjacent normal tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The predominant tumor cells were large and fusiform in shape, having plump cytoplasm (Fig. 2Fig. 2.Fascicles of spindle-shaped tumor cells with interstitial collagen are visible; H&amp;E; scale bar=10 µm.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The nuclei were oval to spindled, with finely dispersed chromatin and small to medium-sized nucleoli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Mitoses were occasionally seen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>In less cellular and more fibrous areas; however, smaller and slender tumor cells with oval to elongated nuclei were observed, and mitotic structures were rare. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemistry revealed positive staining for SMA and vimentin in most neoplastic cells, but desmin was absent (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>3Fig. 3.SMA immunolabeling is observed not only in vascular smooth muscle cells (arrows) but also in surrounding tumor cells; immunohistochemistry; scale bar=20 µm. and 4Fig. 4.In contrast to Fig. 3, smooth muscle cells alone are positively stained for desmin (arrows); immunohistochemistry; scale bar=20 µm.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Most tumor cells stained intensely or moderately for PCNA (data not shown), although faintly positive or negative cells predominated in less cellular areas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The BPV-1 L1 antigen, the major capsid protein, was not detected in the tumor cells or stratified squamous epithelium (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>However, the BPV-1 E2 antigen, the transcription and replication regulatory protein E2, was detected in most of the tumor cells (Fig. 5Fig. 5.Nuclei of most tumor cells are immunoreactive for BPV-1 E2; immunohistochemistry; scale bar=20 µm.) and intact, overlying squamous cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Similar histological and immunohistochemical data were collected from the recurrent lesions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Ultrastructurally, the tumor cells were characterized by moderately developed rough endoplasmic reticulum (RER) and thin filaments with or without focal densities (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Accumulations of intermediate filaments were also observed in some cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Partial L1 genes in the BPV genome, which encode major capsid proteins, were amplified from both the primary and the recurrent tumor samples using Delta papillomavirus and Epsilon papillomavirus-specific subAup/subAdw primer sets (Fig. 6Fig. 6.PCR detection of BPV DNA using Delta and Epsilon papillomavirus-specific primers (subAup: CCAGAYTAYYTMAAAATGGC and subAdw: ATAAMKG CTAGCTTATATTC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Amplicons of 443 bp were detected in all myofibroblastoma samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>M: 100 bp ladder; lane 1: positive control (pBPV-2); lanes 2 and 3: negative control (pBPV-9 and normal bovine skin); lane 4: conjunctival myofibroblastoma; lanes 5 and 6: bovine myofibroblastoma of the neck and vulva.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Both amplified DNAs were 437 bp in length and were 100% homologous with 99.5% identity to previously reported BPV-2 sequences (accession number AB823004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, bovine herpesvirus-specific DNA could not be detected in any of the myofibroblastoma lesions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>For further verification of the presence of BPV-2 in myofibroblastomas, similar analyses were performed on two previously diagnosed myofibroblastoma samples from the neck and vulva [1, 13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>DNA with 99.7% homology to previously reported BPV-2 sequences was detected in each myofibroblastoma sample (accession number AB823005 and AB823006) (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The ISH results confirmed that BPV-2 specific DNA was present in the nuclei of most tumor cells in the primary lesion (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Intense ISH-positive cells predominated in more cellular areas, in which most cells stained positive for PCNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Similar results were obtained from the recurrent lesions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Myofibroblasts display several biological traits that are intermediate between fibroblasts and smooth muscle; they are spindle-shaped cells that secrete collagen and have well-defined contractile properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>In conventional histological sections, myofibroblasts cannot be readily distinguished from fibroblasts, but immunohistochemical detection of SMA (not seen in fibroblasts) and ultrastructural detection of contractile proteins show that they are distinct [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Although myofibroblasts and smooth muscle cells in bovine tissues are both positive for SMA, only myofibroblasts show minimal or absent staining with the anti-desmin antibody [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The present neoplasm, displaying SMA positivity in almost all cells and no detectable staining for desmin, was clearly different from a fibroma, of fibroblast cell origin, and a leiomyoma, of smooth muscle cell origin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Based on these findings, a myofibroblast progenitor is confirmed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The neoplasm recurred after inadequate surgical excision, but not after complete excision. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>There appeared to be regressive changes in the eye and no metastases were found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the present case was diagnosed as a benign conjunctival myofibroblastoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Normally myofibrolastoma in cattle arises in adult animals [1, 13, 26], but was present in an immature young animal in the present case. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Recently, the presence of the papillomavirus (PV) genome in various non-epithelial cells has been described [7, 23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Schwann cells, fibroblast cells, and peripheral blood mononuclear cells of mesenchymal origin are possible reservoirs of PV [7, 23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Glomus cells of mesenchymal origin and placenta of cytotrophoblast origin are also possible reservoirs of BPV-2 [21, 22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The detection of BPV-2 DNA in the conjunctival myofibroblastoma, as well as in the neck and vulval myofibroblastoma, reported here, suggests that BPV-2 can cause neoplasia derived from myofibroblasts in different locations of the body [1, 13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>A pairwise comparison of the nucleotide sequences of amplified DNA from each lesion showed that each DNA was different by one or two bases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>We suggest that three different BPV-2 variants are responsible for these lesions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>BPV E2 proteins have been identified to activate viral transcription and replication by binding with E2-specific recognition sequences located within the promoter region of the viral genome [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Expression of BPV E6 and E7 transforming genes are under the control of the E2 proteins [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>E2 proteins also tether BPV genomes to the mitotic chromosomes via cell cycle regulator proteins, such like bromodomain-containing protein 4; thus, they advance the distribution and retention of the viral genomes in the tumor tissue [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>We report here the expression of the E2 proteins in most of the tumor cells, suggesting that the harboring BPV-2s are transcriptionally active in the myofibroblastoma and are likely to be associated with tumorigenesis through the multifunctional E2 proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Ford et al. [6] isolated and identified PV-like particles by electron microscopy in approximately 33% of putative bovine ocular squamous cell carcinoma precursor lesions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Although they did not study myofibroblastoma cases, these results combined with our results suggest the presence of BPV in various ocular lesions in cattle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>BPV structural antigens were not detected by immunohistochemistry using a cross-reactive, BPV-1-induced antibody, and PV-like particles were not ultrastructurally observed in the conjunctival myofibroblastoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>However, it should be noted that this finding is not unusual because similar results were obtained from previous observations of BPV-associated feline and equine sarcoids [27, 29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Also, BPV replication and virion production are confined to epithelial regions of the lesion, whilst infection of mesenchymal cells is generally non-productive [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Thus, we consider that the BPV infection is non-productive and that productive BPV replication, with synthesis of complete virions, does not occur in myofibroblastoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Although further investigation of the molecular mechanism of myofibroblastoma development is required, we report here the first firm evidence for BPV infection in myofibroblastoma in cattle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The authors appreciate the technical assistance of Ms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Ishihara and Mr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Y. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Ishikawa, Hokkaido Research Station, National Institute of Animal Health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>This research was supported by a grant from the Project of NARO Bio-oriented Technology Research Advancement Institution (the special scheme project on vitalizing management entities of agriculture, forestry, and fisheries). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="r1"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>1AnjikiT.TakeyaG.HashimotoN.KadotaK.1991. An ultrastructural study of vulval myofibroblastoma in a cow. Zentralbl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Veterinarmed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>A38: 770–775. doi: 10.1111/j.1439-0442.1991.tb01077.x<?supplied-pmid 1796679?>1796679 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r2"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>2ArberD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>A.KamelO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>W.van de RijnM.DavisR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>E.MedeirosL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>J.JaffeE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>S.WeissL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>M.1995. Frequent presence of the Epstein-Barr virus in inflammatory pseudotumor. Hum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Pathol.26: 1093–1098. doi: 10.1016/0046-8177(95)90271-6<?supplied-pmid 7557942?>7557942 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r3"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>3BorzacchielloG.RopertoF.2008. Bovine papillomaviruses, papillomas and cancer in cattle. Vet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Res.39: 45. doi: 10.1051/vetres:2008022<?supplied-pmid 18479666?>18479666 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r4"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>4BorzacchielloG.RussoV.SpoletoC.RopertoS.BalcosL.RizzoC.VenutiA.RopertoF.2007. Bovine papillomavirus type-2 DNA and expression of E5 and E7 oncoproteins in vascular tumours of the urinary bladder in cattle. Cancer Lett.250: 82–91. doi: 10.1016/j.canlet.2006.09.022<?supplied-pmid 17125915?>17125915 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r5"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>5DubielzigR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>R.HawkinsK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>L.MillerP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>E.1993. Myofibroblastic sarcoma originating at the site of rabies vaccination in a cat. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Vet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Diagn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Invest.5: 637–638. doi: 10.1177/104063879300500427<?supplied-pmid 8286472?>8286472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r6"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>6FordJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>N.JenningsP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>A.SpradbrowP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>B.FrancisJ.1982. Evidence for papillomaviruses in ocular lesions in cattle. Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Vet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Sci.32: 257–259. <?supplied-pmid 6281870?>6281870 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r7"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>7FüleT.MáthéM.SubaZ.CsapóZ.SzarvasT.TátraiP.PakuS.KovalszkyI.2006. The presence of human papillomavirus 16 in neural structures and vascular endothelial cells. Virology348: 289–296. doi: 10.1016/j.virol.2005.12.043<?supplied-pmid 16499942?>16499942 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r8"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>8GhadiallyF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>N.1985 Myofibroblastoma (a tumour of myofibroblasts). pp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>456–466. In: Diagnostic Electron Microscopy of Tumours, 2nd ed., Butterworths, London. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r9"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>9Gómez-RománJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>J.Ocejo-VinyalsG.Sánchez-VelascoP.NietoE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>H.Leyva-CobiánF.Val-BernalJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>F.2000. Presence of human herpesvirus-8 DNA sequences and overexpression of human IL-6 and cyclin D1 in inflammatory myofibroblastic tumor (inflammatory pseudotumor). Lab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Invest.80: 1121–1126. doi: 10.1038/labinvest.3780118<?supplied-pmid 10908158?>10908158 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r10"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>10HatamaS.IshiharaR.UedaY.KannoT.UchidaI.2011. Detection of a novel bovine papillomavirus type 11 (BPV-11) using xipapillomavirus consensus polymerase chain reaction primers. Arch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Virol.156: 1281–1285. doi: 10.1007/s00705-011-0970-7<?supplied-pmid 21424729?>21424729 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r11"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>11HaydenD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>W.GhobrialH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>K.JohnsonK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>H.BuoenL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>C.1986. Feline mammary sarcoma composed of cells resembling myofibroblasts. Vet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Pathol.23: 118–124. doi: 10.1177/030098588602300203<?supplied-pmid 3962079?>3962079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r12"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>12HikitaM.IshikawaY.ShibaharaT.KadotaK.2004. Mesenteric myofibroblastoma in a horse. Vet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Rec.154: 795–796. doi: 10.1136/vr.154.25.795<?supplied-pmid 15233461?>15233461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r13"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>13HikitaM.YabukiY.IshikawaY.ShibaharaT.KadotaK.1999. Myofibroblastoma of the neck in a heifer. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Vet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Sci.61: 1157–1159. doi: 10.1292/jvms.61.1157<?supplied-pmid 10563296?>10563296 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r14"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>14HinzB.PhanS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>H.ThannickalV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>J.GalliA.Bochaton-PiallatM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>L.GabbianiG.2007. The myofibroblast: one function, multiple origins. Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Pathol.170: 1807–1816. doi: 10.2353/ajpath.2007.070112<?supplied-pmid 17525249?>17525249 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r15"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>15ImaiK.MaseM.YamaguchiS.YuasaN.NakamuraK.1998. Detection of chicken anaemia virus DNA from formalin-fixed tissues by polymerase chain reaction. Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Vet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Sci.64: 205–208. doi: 10.1016/S0034-5288(98)90126-6<?supplied-pmid 9690604?>9690604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r16"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>16KálmánD.EgyedL.2005. PCR detection of bovine herpesviruses from nonbovine ruminants in Hungary. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Wildl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Dis.41: 482–488. doi: 10.7589/0090-3558-41.3.482<?supplied-pmid 16244057?>16244057 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r17"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>17KawauchiK.TakahashiC.IshiharaR.HatamaS.2015. Development of a novel PCR-RFLP assay for improved detection and typing of bovine papillomaviruses. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Virol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Methods218: 23–26. doi: 10.1016/j.jviromet.2015.03.005<?supplied-pmid 25794797?>25794797 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r18"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>18MaedaY.ShibaharaT.WadaY.KadotaK.KannoT.UchidaI.HatamaS.2007. An outbreak of teat papillomatosis in cattle caused by bovine papilloma virus (BPV) type 6 and unclassified BPVs. Vet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Microbiol.121: 242–248. doi: 10.1016/j.vetmic.2006.12.015<?supplied-pmid 17239550?>17239550 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r19"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>19MagroG.2008. Mammary myofibroblastoma: a tumor with a wide morphologic spectrum. Arch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Pathol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Lab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Med.132: 1813–1820. <?supplied-pmid 18976021?>18976021 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r20"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>20NewmanS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>J.CheramieH.DunihoS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>M.ScarrattW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>K.1999. Abdominal spindle cell sarcoma of probable myofibroblastic origin in a horse. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Vet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Diagn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Invest.11: 278–282. doi: 10.1177/104063879901100312<?supplied-pmid 10353361?>10353361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r21"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>21RopertoS.BorzacchielloG.BrunR.PerilloA.RussoV.UrraroC.RopertoF.2008. Multiple glomus tumors of the urinary bladder in a cow associated with bovine papillomavirus type 2 (BPV-2) infection. Vet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Pathol.45: 39–42. doi: 10.1354/vp.45-1-39<?supplied-pmid 18192572?>18192572 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r22"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>22RopertoS.BorzacchielloG.EspositoI.RiccardiM.UrraroC.LucàR.CorteggioA.TatèR.CermolaM.PacielloO.RopertoF.2012. Productive infection of bovine papillomavirus type 2 in the placenta of pregnant cows affected with urinary bladder tumors. PLoS One7: e33569. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0033569<?supplied-pmid 22479413?>22479413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r23"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>23RopertoS.ComazziS.CiusaniE.PaoliniF.BorzacchielloG.EspositoI.LucàR.RussoV.UrraroC.VenutiA.RopertoF.2011. PBMCs are additional sites of productive infection of bovine papillomavirus type 2. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Gen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Virol.92: 1787–1794. doi: 10.1099/vir.0.031740-0<?supplied-pmid 21525209?>21525209 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r24"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>24Shafti-KeramatS.SchellenbacherC.HandisuryaA.ChristensenN.ReiningerB.BrandtS.KirnbauerR.2009. Bovine papillomavirus type 1 (BPV1) and BPV2 are closely related serotypes. Virology393: 1–6. doi: 10.1016/j.virol.2009.07.036<?supplied-pmid 19729180?>19729180 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r25"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>25StevensA.LoweJ.1996 Contractile cells. pp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>65–76. In: Human Histology, 2nd ed., Mosby, London. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r26"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>26TakaiH.TakahashiT.TakayamaH.WadaY.UemuraN.ShibaharaT.IshikawaY.KadotaK.2004 A histologic, immunohistochemical and ultrastructural study of fibroma, myofibroblastoma, leiomyoma and hemangiopericytoma in cattle. Jpn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Agric. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Q.38: 191–197. doi: 10.6090/jarq.38.191 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r27"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>27TeifkeJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>P.KidneyB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>A.LöhrC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>V.YagerJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>A.2003. Detection of papillomavirus-DNA in mesenchymal tumour cells and not in the hyperplastic epithelium of feline sarcoids. Vet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Dermatol.14: 47–56. doi: 10.1046/j.1365-3164.2003.00324.x<?supplied-pmid 12603685?>12603685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r28"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>28UneY.ShirotaK.NomuraY.1993 Immunostaining of bovine myogenic tumors. Vet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Pathol.30: 455. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="r29"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>29WilsonA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>D.ArmstrongE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>R.GoftonR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>G.MasonJ.De ToitN.DayM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>J.2013. Characterisation of early and late bovine papillomavirus protein expression in equine sarcoids. Vet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Microbiol.162: 369–380. doi: 10.1016/j.vetmic.2012.10.010<?supplied-pmid 23123175?>23123175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
