<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Microbiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-302X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6129610</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01850</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The Effect of Strain Level Diversity on Robust Inference of Virus-Induced Mortality of Phytoplankton </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Beckett</surname><given-names>Stephen J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/423042/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Weitz</surname><given-names>Joshua S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/49692/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>School of Biological Sciences, Georgia Institute of Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Atlanta, GA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>School of Physics, Georgia Institute of Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Atlanta, GA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Edited by: Télesphore Sime-Ngando, Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (CNRS), France </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Reviewed by: Stéphan Jacquet, Institut National de la Recherche Agronomique (INRA), France; Pradeep Ram Angia Sriram, UMR6023 Laboratoire Microorganismes Génome Et Environnement (LMGE), France </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Stephen J. Beckett <email>sjbeckett@gatech.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>This article was submitted to Aquatic Microbiology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Microbiology </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1850</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2018 Beckett and Weitz.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Beckett and Weitz</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Infection and lysis of phytoplankton by viruses affects population dynamics and nutrient cycles within oceanic microbial communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>However, estimating the quantitative rates of viral-induced lysis remains challenging in situ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The modified dilution method is the most commonly utilized empirical approach to estimate virus-induced killing rates of phytoplankton. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The lysis rate estimates of the modified dilution method are based on models which assume virus-host interactions can be represented by a single virus and a single host population with homogeneous life-history traits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Here, using modeling approaches, we examine the robustness of the modified dilution method in multi-strain, complex communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>We assume that strains differ in their life history traits, including growth rates (of hosts) and lysis rates (by viruses). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>We show that trait differences affect resulting experimental dynamics such that lysis rates measured using the modified dilution method may be driven by the fastest replicating strains; which are not necessarily the most abundant in situ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>We discuss the implications of using the modified dilution method and alternative dilution-based approaches for estimating viral-induced lysis rates in marine microbial communities. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>diversity</kwd><kwd>dilution method</kwd><kwd>trait-based models</kwd><kwd>viruses</kwd><kwd>viral lysis</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Simons Foundation<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/100000893</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn001">329108</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="10"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="16"/><ref-count count="43"/><page-count count="15"/><word-count count="7707"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Viruses and grazers impact marine microbial populations and biogeochemical cycling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Grazing by micrograzers transfers carbon from primary producers to higher trophic levels and modifies rates of remineralization and sinking of organic matter (Sherr and Sherr, 2002; Calbet and Landry, 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Viruses are the most abundant and diverse biological entities in the known universe/ocean and contribute significantly to phytoplankton mortality (Breitbart et al., 2018). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Viral induced cellular lysis may release resources that can be utilized by primary producers in the so-called “viral shunt” (Fuhrman, 1999; Wilhelm and Suttle, 1999; Weitz and Wilhelm, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In facilitating this recycling network, viral mediated mortality may actually enhance primary productivity in the ocean (Suttle, 2007; Weitz et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In addition, some recent studies suggest viral-induced lysis may promote particle aggregation and export via the “viral shuttle” (Weinbauer, 2004; Guidi et al., 2016; Sullivan et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>It is clear that different cell fates can lead to differing biogeochemical consequences and that quantifying the rates of grazing and viral lysis on marine microbes is important to understand the dynamics of marine ecosystems. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The dilution method is the prevailing technique used to evaluate the impact of grazers on microbial populations (Landry and Hassett, 1982). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>We term this the “classic” dilution method (CDiM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The CDiM measures the differential rate of recovery across incubation experiments containing different levels of diluted seawater. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The modified dilution method (MDiM) (Evans et al., 2003; Kimmance and Brussaard, 2010) is used to quantify the impact of both grazing and viral lysis on microbial populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Empirical measurements made via the MDiM suggest that both grazing and viral lysis are important mortality drivers of marine microbes; and that both can be the dominant source of mortality (Tsai et al., 2013; Mojica et al., 2015; Pasulka et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Yet, the MDiM can yield negative rates of viral lysis (Pasulka et al., 2015) and there are concerns about the ability to detect viral impact e.g., due to previously infected cells, the length of latent period, and the specificty of viral infection (Jacquet et al., 2005; Kimmance et al., 2007; Kimmance and Brussaard, 2010; Pasulka et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Irrespective of the system, the core inference approach underlying the MDiM assumes that the community includes a single, dominant host and viral population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Whilst this has not prevented the MDiM from being applied in natural ecosystems, whose diversity is a subject of ongoing analysis at multiple scales (Fredrickson et al., 2011; Menden-Deuer and Rowlett, 2014; Aylward et al., 2017; Needham et al., 2017)—the implicit assumption of trait heterogeneity may limit the performance of the MDiM within diverse environments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In this manuscript, we evaluate the potential for the modified dilution method to infer viral lysis in complex multi-strain communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In doing so, we develop nonlinear dynamic models of virus-host interactions taking place in diluted media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In doing so, we also propose an alternative conceptual approach: a virus dilution method (VDiM) which dilutes only viruses, but not microbes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>We find that the VDiM may reduce estimation bias compared to the MDiM, particularly given multi-strain scenarios. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>In doing so, we provide a theoretical framework to connect empirical measurements with the nonlinear feedbacks and interactions we are trying to infer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>We hope that improved estimates of viral lysis rates will deepen understanding of the role of viruses in shaping community structure and biogeochemical fluxes (Brussaard et al., 2008; Weitz et al., 2015; Mateus, 2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Modified dilution method </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The modified dilution method (Evans et al., 2003) utilizes two dilution series: the classical dilution series which dilutes phytoplankton and grazers (but not viruses) and the modified dilution series which dilutes phytoplankton, grazers and viruses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>To determine rates of viral induced lysis using the modified dilution method two parallel dilution series are created (Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Two diluents are created using different filter sizes; the classic filter which excludes phytoplankton and grazers [as in the classical dilution method (Landry and Hassett, 1982)], and another filter small enough to exclude viruses, phytoplankton and grazers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Typical filter sizes used to achieve these purposes are 0.1 μm and 30 kDa, respectively (Tsai et al., 2013; Pasulka et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Each dilution series contains several incubation experiments which comprise a different proportion F of sampled seawater and (1−F) diluent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Each incubation typically lasts a day, upon which the change in phytoplankton abundance is measured allowing the approximate growth rate within an incubation bottle to be calculated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>By plotting apparent growth rate vs. dilution level (F), it is possible to draw dilution curves for both the classical and modified dilution series (Figure 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The expectation is that the slope of the classical dilution curve is equivalent to the grazing rate (Landry and Hassett, 1982; Kimmance and Brussaard, 2010; Beckett and Weitz, 2017), the intercept of the modified dilution curve at F = 0 is the phytoplankton growth rate (Kimmance and Brussaard, 2010), whilst the slope of the modified dilution curve is the sum of both grazing and lysis rates (Kimmance and Brussaard, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Hence, the difference in slopes between the classical and modified dilution curves is expected to be the viral lysis rate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Schematic representing the modified dilution method. (A) Scheme to generate the classical dilution series (top), by mixing WSW with a diluent that filters out phytoplankton and grazers; and the modified dilution series (bottom) by mixing WSW with a diluent that filters out viruses (V), phytoplankton (P) and grazers (G). (B) A diagram showing growth and mortality processes of phytoplankton P. (C) Idealized apparent growth curves from the classical and modified dilution series. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Viral lysis rates are estimated based on the differences between slopes of the classic and modified dilution curves. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-01850-g0001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Virus dilution method </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>We propose an alternative conceptual approach to estimating rates of viral-induced lysis of phytoplankton. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The VDiM is comprised of one dilution series. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The virus dilution series dilutes the ambient levels of viruses (but not phytoplankton or grazers). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Each incubation experiment within the viral dilution series contains a proportion F of sampled seawater and a proportion (1−F) of seawater from which free viruses are removed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>By plotting the apparent growth rates of phytoplankton against the dilution level (F) a viral dilution curve can be drawn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Because only the concentration of viruses changes across the virus dilution series, that the slope of the viral dilution curve represents an alternative approach to infer viral lysis rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>We recognize that practical implementation of this method may be challenging and we return to this in section 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>However, we can directly apply and assess the viral dilution methodology in silico as a means to test the potential accuracy and associated biases of the approach. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>2.3. In silico dilution experiments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>In silico dilution experiments were used to estimate viral lysis and compare it against the model input viral lysis rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Ten dilution levels were used (F = 0.1, 0.2, 0.3, 0.4, 0.5, 0.6, 0.7, 0.8, 0.9, 1.0) in each simulation series. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Apparent growth rates, r~, are calculated as: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">˜</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>where T is the length of incubation and P(0) and P(T) are countable phytoplankton cell densities at the beginning (time 0) and end of the incubation period (time T), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Slopes and intercepts of the respective dilution curves are estimated using linear regression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Grazing rate is estimated as the slope of the classical dilution curve and the viral lysis rate is estimated by (a) the difference in slopes between the modified and classical dilution curves and (b) the slope of the viral dilution curve. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Bias is calculated by dividing the estimated viral lysis rate by the model input viral lysis rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Ambient concentrations of phytoplankton and viruses are assumed to be at steady-state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Population dynamics are simulated using package deSolve v1.20 (Soetaert et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>All code is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/sjbeckett/DilutionMethod-ViralLysisEstimation">https://github.com/sjbeckett/DilutionMethod-ViralLysisEstimation</ext-link> and is archived at (Beckett and Weitz, 2018). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Non-linear dynamics of virus-host interactions in the bottle </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>2.4.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Baseline model </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The densities of phytoplankton, grazers, and viruses are represented as P, G and V, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>We can represent bulk population dynamics of these groups (see Figure 1B) as: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>where we assume that the population of grazers stays constant within the time-scales of the dilution experiment (i.e., dGdt=0 and G = G0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Here phytoplankton grow logistically with an intrinsic maximal growth rate r up to a carrying capacity K, are ingested by grazers at rate a and infected by viruses at rate ϕ. We assume, for now, that viral induced lysis is instantaneous creating a burst size, β, of viral progeny and that infective virions become inactive at rate ω. The baseline model, described by Equation (2), has an initial viral-induced lysis rate given by: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>where V0 indicates the viral concentration at the time of sampling. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>2.4.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Extension 1: considering infection dynamics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>In the baseline model described in Equation (2) viruses instantaneously lyse cells upon infection and there is no latent period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Here, we introduce an infected cell state, denoted I, which represents infected cells that can produce viral progeny. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>We assume that grazers are unable to differentiate between susceptible and infected cells, which are grazed upon at equal rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The dynamics of this system are given as: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>where we set </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E5"><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>so that the average burst size in the explicit infection model is equal to that in the baseline model (Weitz, 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>In the previous model phytoplankton cells were directly lysed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Here, it is only the phytoplankton cells in the infected class which lyse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>As such, the rate of viral-induced lysis in the sample MI, that we wish to estimate is found as the rate of lysis from infected cells as a proportion of the total cell concentration (both infected and sucseptible cells): </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E6"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>where I0 and P0 denote the sampled concentrations of infected and susceptible cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>2.4.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Extension 2: effects of strain level diversity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>We extend the baseline model presented in Equation (2) to include viral and phytoplankton strain diversity as: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E7"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>where both phytoplankton populations are limited by the same environmental conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>For simplicity we assume that phytoplankton differ in growth rate, and that viruses only differ in their ability to adsorb to their respective hosts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Therefore we assume both viruses have the same burst size, β1 = β2 = β, and inactivation rates, ω1 = ω2 = ω. We also assume that grazer clearance rates are the same regardless of prey type (a1 = a2 = a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The range of life-history traits evaluated are shown in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>We consider this model in two ways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>First, we assume that the experimenter can tell the difference between the two phytoplankton types P1 and P2 and is able to count them separately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>In this case the individual rates of viral-induced lysis, M1 and M2, are found respectively as: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E8"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>where V1(0) and V2(0) are the concentrations of each virus type at sampling time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, if the experimenter is unable to identify differences between the phytoplankton types and counts them together, then the community wide bulk averaged rate of viral lysis, MC, with this model at sampling time is: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E9"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>We choose to evaluate the perfomance of both community wide and individual viral lysis rate estimates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>As before we assume that sampled concentrations are taken at the steady state for the system described in Equation (6) given in Supplementary Data A. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Analytical expressions for dilution growth rates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The difference in slopes between the classical and modified dilution curves is expected to be the viral lysis rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>We can check this expectation using the proposed dynamical model (Equation 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>By calculating the instantaneous per capita phytoplankton growth rates for each incubation experiment at a particular dilution level F we find analytical forms for each of the respective dilution series: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E10"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="E11"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="M"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>where P0, G0 and V0 are the initial sampled densities of phytoplankton, grazers and viruses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The viral induced lysis rate (ϕV0) in the sample can be calculated as the difference between the slope values (or equivalently the intercepts) of the two dilution curves (Kimmance and Brussaard, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>We also consider an alternative approach—the VDiM–in which only viruses are diluted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Following the viral dilution approach, one can also estimate viral lysis as the slope from the corresponding dilution curve: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E12"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>This suggests the viral dilution approach could be used as an alternative or complementary step in estimating viral lysis rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Given these analytical expressions, we would expect the MDiM and the VDiM to perform well in the instantaneous limit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>But inferences based on instantaneous growth rate measurements may not correspond well to growth rates based on measurements collected after a 24 h incubation, during which the populations of viruses, in addition to cells, will deviate from their initial values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>We attempted to derive analytical expressions for each of the model extensions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>For the model including an infected class (Equation 4) our analytical expressions were unable to predict that we should recover viral lysis (see Supplemental Data D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>This is due to the fact that the expression for total phytoplankton (susceptible and infected) per capita growth rates does not explicitly depend on the concentration of viruses, rather the rate of lysis is dependent on the concentration of infected cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Whilst we were unable to recover the rate of viral-induced lysis using analytical expressions, we do not use this as evidence against the performance of dilution based approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Rather, this shows that even limited changes to nonlinear responses can make what may appear to be straightforward predictions difficult to analyse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>In the second model extension, where diversity is examined, we were able to derive analytical expressions for the dilution curves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The case in which the experimenter can distinguish between phytoplankton types is trivially similar to that given for the baseline model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>In the case in which the experimenter cannot distinguish between phytoplankton types we find theoretical expectations for the classic dilution series curve as: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E13"><label>(12)</label><mml:math id="M13"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>and for the modified dilution series: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E14"><label>(13)</label><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The difference in both the intercepts and the slopes of these series (Equations 12, 13) is equal to the bulk-average rate of viral lysis in the community: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E15"><label>(14)</label><mml:math id="M15"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>as previously defined in Equation (8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Similarly for the VDiM, we find: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="E16"><label>(15)</label><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>where the slope is predicted to estimate the bulk-average rate of viral lysis for the community, as defined in Equation (8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>As such, the expectation is that we should be able to infer rates of viral lysis at both the type- and community-level for the system described in Equation (6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Whilst these analytical expressions match our expectations under instantaneous measurement, the ability to which they are able to do so may differ depending on the life-history traits exhibited in the microbial community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Whilst growth increases the phytoplankton population, this can be limited through niche competition and by the top-down controls of grazing and viral lysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>At steady state these limitation processes are equal to growth (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The ability to estimate viral lysis rates might depend on which of these limitation mechanisms is dominant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>We now use in silico dilution experiments to test and evaluate these expectations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Schematic representing mortality processes affecting the phytoplankton. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The sum of three mortality processes: grazing, viral-induced lysis, and niche competition must add to 100%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Grazing and lysis are indicated on the axes, whilst niche competition is indicated by shading. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>5, 50, and 95% isoclines of niche competition are labeled. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-01850-g0002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Evidence of potential bias in lysis rate estimates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Figure 3 shows the rate estimates for growth, grazing, and viral lysis made by the CDiM, MDiM, and VDiM following a 24 h incubation of the population dynamics described in Equation (2) using parameters in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Figure 3A shows the population dynamics of phytoplankton cells and viruses from time 0 to 24 h (as indicated by arrows) within individual incubation bottles in each of the three types of dilution series. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>This phase portrait shows that the dynamical trajectories of viruses and cells differ across incubation bottles, but also that they oscillate around the systems fixed point - in our simulations the sampled density of viruses and cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Apparent growth rates were calculated for each incubation bottle in each of the classic, modified and viral dilution series using Equation (1) and are plotted in Figure 3B with the best fitting linear regression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>All three dilution curves appear to be linear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Using the intercept and slope values calculated from the dilution curves as defined by the CDiM, MDiM, and VDiM protocols we compare inferred ecological rates to model input rates in Figure 3C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Note that only the MDiM provides estimates of all rates simultaneously; and that the CDiM and MDiM estimate grazing the same way and are therefore equal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>For this set of parameters the CDiM appears to underestimate growth rates, whilst grazing rates appear to be overestimated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Both the MDiM and the VDiM infer high rates of viral lysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>However, the MDiM underestimates the viral lysis rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The mechanistic basis for these biases in estimates of lysis rates can be understood in terms of the nonlinear dynamics that arise in 24 h (see Figure 3A) vs. those expected given the theory of instantaneous lysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The signal of these nonlinear dynamics is not apparent from analysis of the dilution curves. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Inference of ecological rates using dilution methods. (A) Population dynamics of phytoplankton cells and viruses within individual incubation bottles from the classical, modified and virus dilution series between 0 and 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The intital sampled concentrations of cells and viruses (F = 1) are shown as the single point. (B) Dilution curves constructed from calculations of apparent growth rates within each of the incubation bottles at 24 h. (C) Comparing model rate inputs to dilution-based rate estimates of growth, grazing, and viral induced lysis derived from the dilution curves. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-01850-g0003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Density of estimation bias in the baseline model made by the MDiM and VDiM for incubations of 2 h (Left) and 24 h (Right). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Density plots are from N simulations (out of 500) from random latin hypercube sampled parameter choices. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-01850-g0006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>3.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Robustness of lysis rate estimates given variation in viral latent periods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>The results from the baseline model (Figures 3–6) suggest that viral-induced lysis rate estimation may be improved by using shorter incubations and, in some instances, the viral dilution method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>However, the baseline model assumes that viral adsorption leads to instantaneous cellular lysis and release of new infectious virions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Using the extended model that includes infected phytoplankton (Equation 4) we ask whether the latent period duration affects inference of viral lysis rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>We chose to examine this model using three different latent periods: 15 min, 4 and 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>A similar analysis to that in Figures 4, 5, using the extended model, is shown in Supplementary Data C,E,F via Figures S1–S6. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>The results from a system with a short 15 min latent period (Figure 7A and Figures S1, S4) are qualitatively similar to the baseline model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>However, the efficacy of both the MDiM and the VDiM is reduced relative to that found under the assumptions of the baseline model—this is particularly apparent in comparing the estimation bias under a short incubation (Figure S1 relative to Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>This can be seen firstly by the drop in observed variation of estimation bias following a 2 h incubation for a 4 h latent period (Figure 7B and Figure S2) and a 24 h latent period (Figure 7C and Figure S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Additionally, as can be seen in Figures 7B,C when the latent period exceeds the incubation period, the estimates from both the MDiM and the VDiM are not only low, but also quantitatively similar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>During 24 h incubations the VDiM appears more robust than the MDiM, Figures 7B,C, but both methods had large variation in estimation bias. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Density of estimation bias in the infected class model, with (A) 15 min latent period (B) 4 h latent period (C) 24 h latent period, made by the MDiM and VDiM for incubations of 2 h (left) and 24 h (right). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Density plots are from N simulations (out of 500) from random latin hypercube sampled parameter choices. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-01850-g0007"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>3.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Strain level diversity may effect the ability to estimate viral-induced lysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Life-history trait differences between the members of interacting microbial communities could lead to biased measurements within dilution method experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>To highlight this potential effect we consider a community with two phytoplankton types P1 and P2, which are each infected by a strain-specific virus, V1 and V2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>We further assume that P1 has a faster growth rate relative to P2, but has a lower ambient steady-state concentration, as shown in Figure 8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>This is an expectation of Kill-the-Winner dynamics in which faster growing phytoplankton are capable of supporting a larger virus population via negative density-dependent selection (Thingstad, 2000; Zhao et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Following the dilution of populations (time 0 h) type P1 is able to recover much faster than type P2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>If the observer is unable to distinguish between these two phytoplankton types a different dynamic is apparent and may lead to misleading interpretations of viral-lysis in the community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>In Figure 8B the model input rates of viral-lysis and the corresponding estimates of viral-induced lysis are shown at the level of the community and at type-level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Here, viral-induced lysis was underestimated at the type levels for both phytoplankton. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>However, the community viral-induced lysis rate was overestimated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Differences between strains may hinder efforts to estimate lysis rates. (A) Phytoplankton population dynamics during an incubation experiment in the modified dilution series with F = 0.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Here phytoplankton type P1 grows much faster than type P2, but has a lower steady state abundance (population level before t = 0 h). (B) The viral lysis rate model input and estimated rates for the system shown in (A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Viral lysis rates are measured at the community- and type-level. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-01850-g0008"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>To explore the ability of the modified and viral dilution methods to robustly estimate viral-induced lysis rates in phytoplankton communities we fixed the life-history traits of phytoplankton type P2 whilst varying the ambient concentration and growth rates of phytoplankton P1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>The results are shown following a 2 h incubation in Figure 9 and following a 24 h incubation in Figure 10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Similarly to the baseline model we find that estimation ability improves with shorter incubation periods, but we note that this model does not include an infected class and lysis is instantaneous. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Community estimates of viral-induced lysis may be overestimated or underestimated depending on the life-history traits in the community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>These effects are larger during 24 h incubations than 2 h incubations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Following a 2 h incubation the 95% quantiles of estimation bias reported in Figures 9, 10 are (0.98, 1.34) for the MDiM and (1.00, 1.21) for VDiM; but following a 24 h incubation are (−0.14, 5.63) for MDiM and (0.14, 1.69) for VDiM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>The regimes in which overestimation and underestimation occur are also dependent on observation timing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>At the type-level (bottom two rows) we see both the MDiM and the VDiM generally underestimate viral-induced lysis rate across the variation in life-history traits. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Estimation bias in viral lysis rates by the modified dilution method (Left) and viral dilution method (Right) following a 2 h incubation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Rows show community-wide estimates (Top), P1 estimates (Middle), and P2 estimates (Bottom). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>White contours indicate an estimation bias equal to one, where the estimated rate is equal to the model input. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-01850-g0009"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F10" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Estimation bias in viral lysis rates by the modified dilution method (Left) and viral dilution method (Right) following a 24 h incubation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Rows show community-wide estimates (Top), P1 estimates (Middle), and P2 estimates (Bottom). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>White contours indicate an estimation bias equal to one, where the estimated rate is equal to the model input. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Red contours indicate an estimation bias of zero. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>This shows where dilution slopes go from negative to positive such that estimates of viral lysis rates take negative values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-01850-g0010"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>We have systematically analyzed the potential for dilution-based methods to infer viral lysis rates of phytoplankton. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>In doing so we have combined nonlinear models of community dynamics in a specific experimental context. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>We derived equations for expected dilution curves (Equations 9, 10) which provides a principled basis for why the difference in these slopes may be able to approximate viral lysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>We were also able to recover the rate of viral lysis when analysing the case of viral dilution (Equation 11), under the knowledge that this analysis represents instantaneous expectations, and not those after a long incubation period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>However, our in silico simulations suggest viral lysis rate may be difficult to measure in practice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Our simulation results suggest that estimation ability of viral-lysis rates is poorer under increased bottom-up control via niche competition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>This complements previous research in which we found that niche competition might also reduce the ability to estimate grazing rates (Beckett and Weitz, 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>This suggests greater understanding of the nutrient and incubation conditions and how they relate to the physiology of plankton communities in dilution experiments is necessary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Nutrient addition is commonly used to alleviate nutrient limitation within dilution experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>As highlighted by Calbet and Saiz (2017) different nutrient addition treatments are applied within different dilution experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>As well as asking how nutrient addition effects niche competition, future consideration should be given to how particular organisms will differentially respond to a particular nutrient addition strategy (Lagus et al., 2004) and how this affects the ability to learn about in situ ecological processes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>We investigated two potential approaches to improve estimates of viral-induced lysis rates—reducing incubation length in the MDiM and applying a new, VDiM in which only virus concentrations are diluted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Reducing incubation timing appeared to improve estimation ability under circumstances when the incubation length was greater than the infection latent period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>This suggests a priori knowledge of latent periods could help improve experimental design—however such a priori knowledge may not be available in situ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Our simulations do not model how ecological processes may be effected by diel forcing e.g., Arias et al., 2017, which could be an additional complicating factor in attempting to use dilution based approaches to estimate ecological rates of phytoplankton, grazers, and viruses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>The VDiM did appear to have improved efficacy relative to the MDiM when populations were not limited by bottom-up control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>In order to practically implement the VDiM we see two possibilities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>First, empiricists could attempt to resuspend viruses e.g., using flocculation techniques (John et al., 2011; Poulos et al., 2018). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>A different approach to achieving a gradient of viral dilution could be to use the filtrate (as opposed to the diluent) of the classical dilution filtered water and mixing this with whole seawater at different proportions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Figure 3 represents a cautionary tale for the field in the interpretation of dilution experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Observations made using dilution experiments typically find similar rates of phytoplankton growth and grazing mortality (e.g., Morison and Menden-Deuer, 2017. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>However, as shown in Figure 3 it is important to remember the ecological context of such measurements—growth rate estimates made by the classical dilution method are limited by the activity of viruses and hence may be underestimated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>We caution empiricists to consider the role of viruses in future experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>In addition to treating phytoplankton and viruses as bulk entities, we investigated how well dilution based estimates perform when diversity is included at both type- and community-level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>We found that fast growing strains have the potential to recover quickly and therefore dominate the apparent lysis rate, even if they are relatively small contributors to the true signal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>This level of virus-host interaction complexity remains over-simplified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>Virus-host interactions are expected to be highly specific (though some viruses have been observed to infect across phyla; Malki et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, at the strain level there may exist a range of specialist to generalist virus types (Weitz et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>In addition we continue to treat grazers as a bulk entity, though Calbet and Saiz (2013) find that trophic chains can affect the results of dilution experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Grazing is also assumed to be non-preferential which is an assumption that could be challenged (Wirtz, 2014; Pasulka et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>The structure of the network of interactions between viruses, phytoplankton cells and grazers will affect both the observed population dynamics and the expected individual type- and community-level rates of mortality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Investigating how well simple approximations, such as those made by bulk-population models of the dilution method, work in more complex ecological communities warrants further investigation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>There are a number of additional assumptions that could prove limiting to the dilution method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Inherent in our assumptions are that life-history traits are constant and do not vary in time or with changing environmental conditions during the incubation time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Additionally we assume that grazing and viral infection processes are linearly affected by dilution (i.e., Holling type I) which may be a simplistic assumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Saturation in grazing responses (Li et al., 2017), or viral infection (Kimmance and Brussaard, 2010) could lead to nonlinear dilution curves which need different methods of interpretation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Without observations of the population dynamics between the beginning and end of the dilution experiments it may be difficult to assess the appropriateness of the conceptual mechanistic framework from which dilution-based rate estimates are inferred. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>We assume that the filters used by the classical, modified and viral dilution series all perform perfectly which may not be the case (e.g., Pasulka et al., 2015), and that nutrient levels are not reduced by dilution (though see Pasulka et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Additional challenges arise from consideration of nutrient regeneration via viral lysis, lysogeny, the potential for preferential grazing on infected cells, removal of free viruses by grazing (Kimmance and Brussaard, 2010) and mixotrophy (Caron, 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>These could all serve as routes for future study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>We have shown that even with perfect measurement ability, large uncertainty exists in the ability of dilution based methods to estimate rates of viral-induced lysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>These uncertainties are related to mismatch between the expectation of exponential recovery from dilution for the bulk community and predicted nonlinear dynamics and time-delayed feedbacks within complex microbial communities of viruses, grazers and their microbial prey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>For the cases outlined in our manuscript, the VDiM provides better estimation of viral induced lysis than the MDiM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>The strength of such an approach is that it only requires one, rather than two dilution series. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>However, the VDiM is unable to provide estimates of growth or grazing rates, and it has yet to be demonstrated in practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>We also note that both methods exhibited strong sensitivity to the length of incubation relative to the latent period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Shorter incubations improve estimation ability, but the ability to infer viral mediated mortality is severely reduced when the incubation length is shorter than the latent period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>We suggest that both increasing the temporal sampling resolution, and increasing our resolution of community membership and individual virus-host linkages that exist within dilution-based experiments will be an important future step in helping to constrain estimates of growth, grazing, and viral-induced lysis rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>Improving estimates of viral effects in situ requires that we revisit the mechanistic assumptions of experimental protocols in light of the increasing understanding of the diversity of marine microbial and viral communities. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>Author contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>SB designed the research, performed the simulations, led the analysis, and wrote the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>JW designed the research, contributed analysis, and contributed to writing the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>Conflict of interest statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>We thank Will Ratcliff, David Caron, Debbie Lindell, Joey Leung, and Mick Follows for feedback which improved this article. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>We also thank Daniel Muratore for conducting a review of the simulation code. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Funding. This work was supported by a grant from the Simons Foundation (SCOPE Award Id 329108, JW). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s8"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2018.01850/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2018.01850/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.PDF"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>AriasA.SaizE.CalbetA. (2017). Diel feeding rhythms in marine microzooplankton: effects of prey concentration, prey condition, and grazer nutritional history. Mar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>Biol. 164:205 10.1007/s00227-017-3233-7 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>AylwardF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>O.BoeufD.MendeD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>R.Wood-CharlsonE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>M.VislovaA.EppleyJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>M.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>(2017). Diel cycling and long-term persistence of viruses in the ocean's euphotic zone. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>U.S.A. 114, 11446–11451. 10.1073/pnas.1714821114<?supplied-pmid 29073070?>29073070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>BeckettS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>J.WeitzJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>S. (2017). Disentangling niche competition from grazing mortality in phytoplankton dilution experiments. PLoS ONE 12:e0177517. 10.1371/journal.pone.0177517<?supplied-pmid 28505212?>28505212 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>BeckettS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>J.WeitzJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>S. (2018). Code for: The effect of strain level diversity on robust inference of virus-induced mortality of phytoplankton. Zenodo. 10.5281/zenodo.1189793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>BreitbartM.BonnainC.MalkiK.SawayaN. (2018). Phage puppet masters of the marine microbial realm. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 3, 754–766. 10.1038/s41564-018-0166-y<?supplied-pmid 29867096?>29867096 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>BrussaardC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>D.WilhelmS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>W.ThingstadF.WeinbauerM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>G.BratbakG.HeldalM.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>(2008). Global-scale processes with a nanoscale drive: the role of marine viruses. ISME J. 2, 575–578. 10.1038/ismej.2008.31<?supplied-pmid 18385772?>18385772 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>CalbetA.LandryM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>R. (2004). Phytoplankton growth, microzooplankton grazing, and carbon cycling in marine systems. Limnol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>Oceanogr. 49, 5–57. 10.4319/lo.2004.49.1.0051 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>CalbetA.SaizE. (2013). Effects of trophic cascades in dilution grazing experiments: from artificial saturated feeding responses to positive slopes. J. Plankton Res. 35, 1183–1191. 10.1093/plankt/fbt067 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>CalbetA.SaizE. (2017). How much is enough for nutrients in microzooplankton dilution grazing experiments? J. Plankton Res. 40, 109–117. 10.1093/plankt/fbx070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>CaronD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>A. (2016). Mixotrophy stirs up our understanding of marine food webs. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>U.S.A. 113, 2806–2808. 10.1073/pnas.1600718113<?supplied-pmid 26933215?>26933215 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>EvansC.ArcherS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>D.JacquetS.WilsonW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>H. (2003). Direct estimates of the contribution of viral lysis and microzooplankton grazing to the decline of a Micromonas spp. population. Aquat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>Microb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>Ecol. 30, 207–219. 10.3354/ame030207 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>FredricksonK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>A.StromS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>L.CrimR.CoyneK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>J. (2011). Interstrain variability in physiology and genetics of Heterosigma akashiwo (Raphidophyceae) from the west coast of North America. J. Phycol. 47, 25–35. 10.1111/j.1529-8817.2010.00942.x<?supplied-pmid 27021707?>27021707 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>FuhrmanJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>A. (1999). Marine viruses and their biogeochemical and ecological effects. Nature 399, 541–548. 10.1038/21119<?supplied-pmid 10376593?>10376593 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>GuidiL.ChaffronS.BittnerL.EveillardD.LarhlimiA.RouxS.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>(2016). Plankton networks driving carbon export in the oligotrophic ocean. Nature 532, 465–470. 10.1038/nature16942<?supplied-pmid 26863193?>26863193 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>JacquetS.DomaizonI.PersonnicS.RamA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>P.HedalM.DuhamelS. (2005). Estimates of protozoan-and viral-mediated mortality of bacterioplankton in Lake Bourget (France). Freshw. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>Biol. 50, 627–645. 10.1111/j.1365-2427.2005.01349.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>JohnS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>G.MendezC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>B.DengL.PoulosB.KauffmanA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>M.KernS.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>(2011). A simple and efficient method for concentration of ocean viruses by chemical flocculation. Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>Rep. 3, 195–202. 10.1111/j.1758-2229.2010.00208.x<?supplied-pmid 21572525?>21572525 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>KimmanceS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>A.BrussaardC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>D. (2010). Estimation of viral-induced phytoplankton mortality using the modified dilution method. Limnol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>Oceanogr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>Methods 7, 65–73. 10.4319/mave.2010.978-0-9845591-0-7.65 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>KimmanceS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>A.WilsonW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>H.ArcherS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>D. (2007). Modified dilution technique to estimate viral versus grazing mortality of phytoplankton: limitations associated with method sensitivity in natural waters. Aquat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>Microb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>Ecol. 49, 207–222. 10.3354/ame01136 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>LagusA.SuomelaJ.WeithoffG.HeikkiläK.HelminenH.SipuraJ. (2004). Species-specific differences in phytoplankton responses to N and P enrichments and the N:P ratio in the Archipelago Sea, northern Baltic Sea. J. Plankton Res. 26, 779–798. 10.1093/plankt/fbh070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>LandryM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>R.HassettR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>P. (1982). Estimating the grazing impact of marine micro-zooplankton. Mar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>Biol. 67, 283–288. 10.1007/BF00397668 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>LiQ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>P.FranksP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>J.LandryM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>R. (2017). Recovering growth and grazing rates from nonlinear dilution experiments. Limnol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>Oceanogr. 62, 1825–1835. 10.1002/lno.10536 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>MalkiK.KulaA.BruderK.SibleE.HatzopoulosT.SteidelS.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>(2015). Bacteriophages isolated from Lake Michigan demonstrate broad host-range across several bacterial phyla. Virol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>J. 12:164. 10.1186/s12985-015-0395-0<?supplied-pmid 26453042?>26453042 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>MateusM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>D. (2017). Bridging the gap between knowing and modeling viruses in marine systems–an upcoming frontier. Front. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>Mar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>Sci. 3:284 10.3389/fmars.2016.00284 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>Menden-DeuerS.RowlettJ. (2014). Many ways to stay in the game: individual variability maintains high biodiversity in planktonic microorganisms. J. R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>Interface 11:20140031. 10.1098/rsif.2014.0031<?supplied-pmid 24647904?>24647904 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>MojicaK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>A.HuismanJ.WilhelmS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>W.BrussaardC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>D. (2015). Latitudinal variation in virus-induced mortality of phytoplankton across the North Atlantic Ocean.  ISME J. 10, 500–513. 10.1038/ismej.2015.130<?supplied-pmid 26262815?>26262815 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>MorisonF.Menden-DeuerS. (2017). Doing more with less? balancing sampling resolution and effort in measurements of protistan growth and grazing-rates. Limnol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>Oceanogr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>Methods 15, 794–809. 10.1002/lom3.10200 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>NeedhamD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>M.SachdevaR.FuhrmanJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain>A. (2017). Ecological dynamics and co-occurrence among marine phytoplankton, bacteria and myoviruses shows microdiversity matters. ISME J. 11, 1614–1629. 10.1038/ismej.2017.29<?supplied-pmid 28398348?>28398348 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="550" pm="."><plain>PasulkaA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="551" pm="."><plain>L.SamoT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="552" pm="."><plain>J.LandryM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="553" pm="."><plain>R. (2015). Grazer and viral impacts on microbial growth and mortality in the southern California current ecosystem. J. Plankton Res. 37, 320–336. 10.1093/plankt/fbv011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="555" pm="."><plain>PoulosB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="556" pm="."><plain>T.JohnS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="557" pm="."><plain>G.SullivanM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="558" pm="."><plain>B. (2018). Iron chloride flocculation of bacteriophages from seawater in Bacteriophages: Methods and Protocols, Vol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="559" pm="."><plain>3, eds ClokieM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="560" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="561" pm="."><plain>J.KropinskiA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="562" pm="."><plain>M.LavigneR. (New York, NY: Humana Press), 49–57. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="563" pm="."><plain>SherrE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="564" pm="."><plain>B.SherrB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="565" pm="."><plain>F. (2002). Significance of predation by protists in aquatic microbial food webs. Antonie van Leeuwenhoek 81, 293–308. 10.1023/A:1020591307260<?supplied-pmid 12448728?>12448728 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="566" pm="."><plain>SoetaertK.PetzoldtT.SetzerR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="567" pm="."><plain>W. (2010). Solving differential equations in R: Package deSolve. J. Stat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="569" pm="."><plain>Softw. 33, 1–25. 10.18637/jss.v033.i0920808728 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="570" pm="."><plain>SullivanM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="571" pm="."><plain>B.WeitzJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="572" pm="."><plain>S.WilhelmS. (2017). Viral ecology comes of age. Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="573" pm="."><plain>Microb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="574" pm="."><plain>Rep. 9, 33–35. 10.1111/1758-2229.12504<?supplied-pmid 27888577?>27888577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="575" pm="."><plain>SuttleC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="576" pm="."><plain>A. (2007). Marine viruses–major players in the global ecosystem. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="577" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="578" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 5, 801–812. 10.1038/nrmicro1750<?supplied-pmid 17853907?>17853907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="579" pm="."><plain>ThingstadT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="580" pm="."><plain>F. (2000). Elements of a theory for the mechanisms controlling abundance, diversity, and biogeochemical role of lytic bacterial viruses in aquatic systems. Limnol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="581" pm="."><plain>Oceanogr. 45, 1320–1328. 10.4319/lo.2000.45.6.1320 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="582" pm="."><plain>TsaiA.GongG.-C.HungJ. (2013). Seasonal variations of virus-and nanoflagellate-mediated mortality of heterotrophic bacteria in the coastal ecosystem of subtropical western pacific. Biogeosciences 10, 3055–3065. 10.5194/bg-10-3055-2013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="583" pm="."><plain>WeinbauerM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="584" pm="."><plain>G. (2004). Ecology of prokaryotic viruses. FEMS Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="585" pm="."><plain>Rev. 28, 127–181. 10.1016/j.femsre.2003.08.001<?supplied-pmid 15109783?>15109783 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="586" pm="."><plain>WeitzJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="587" pm="."><plain>S. (2015). Quantitative Viral Ecology: Dynamics of Viruses and Their Microbial Hosts. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="588" pm="."><plain>WeitzJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="589" pm="."><plain>S.PoisotT.MeyerJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="590" pm="."><plain>R.FloresC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="591" pm="."><plain>O.ValverdeS.SullivanM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="592" pm="."><plain>B.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="593" pm="."><plain>(2013). Phage–bacteria infection networks. Trends Microbiol. 21, 82–91. 10.1016/j.tim.2012.11.003<?supplied-pmid 23245704?>23245704 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="594" pm="."><plain>WeitzJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="595" pm="."><plain>S.StockC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="596" pm="."><plain>A.WilhelmS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="597" pm="."><plain>W.BourouibaL.ColemanM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="598" pm="."><plain>L.BuchanA.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="599" pm="."><plain>(2015). A multitrophic model to quantify the effects of marine viruses on microbial food webs and ecosystem processes. ISME J. 9, 1352–1364. 10.1038/ismej.2014.220<?supplied-pmid 25635642?>25635642 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="600" pm="."><plain>WeitzJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="601" pm="."><plain>S.WilhelmS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="602" pm="."><plain>W. (2012). Ocean viruses and their effects on microbial communities and biogeochemical cycles. F1000 Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="603" pm="."><plain>Rep. 4:17. 10.3410/B4-17<?supplied-pmid 22991582?>22991582 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="604" pm="."><plain>WilhelmS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="605" pm="."><plain>W.SuttleC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="606" pm="."><plain>A. (1999). Viruses and nutrient cycles in the sea: viruses play critical roles in the structure and function of aquatic food webs. Bioscience 49, 781–788. 10.2307/1313569 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="607" pm="."><plain>WirtzK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="608" pm="."><plain>W. (2014). A biomechanical and optimality-based derivation of prey-size dependencies in planktonic prey selection and ingestion rates. Mar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="609" pm="."><plain>Ecol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="610" pm="."><plain>Prog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="611" pm="."><plain>Ser. 507, 81–94. 10.3354/meps10894 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="612" pm="."><plain>ZhaoY.TempertonB.ThrashJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="613" pm="."><plain>C.SchwalbachM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="614" pm="."><plain>S.VerginK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="615" pm="."><plain>L.LandryZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="616" pm="."><plain>C.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="617" pm="."><plain>(2013). Abundant SAR11 viruses in the ocean. Nature 494, 357–360. 10.1038/nature11921<?supplied-pmid 23407494?>23407494 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
