<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.5.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art550.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.5.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_HLY663 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEfigs1 jpg ?><?FILEfigs2 jpg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6039704</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2405-8440(17)31882-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2018.e00663</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e00663</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Study of diatom assemblages in Sundarbans mangrove water based on light microscopy and rbcL gene sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Samanta</surname><given-names>Brajogopal</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bhadury</surname><given-names>Punyasloke</given-names></name><email>pbhadury@iiserkol.ac.in</email><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Integrative Taxonomy and Microbial Ecology Research Group, Department of Biological Sciences, Indian Institute of Science Education and Research Kolkata (IISERK), Mohanpur 741246, Nadia, West Bengal, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author. <email>pbhadury@iiserkol.ac.in</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e00663</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2018 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Sundarbans, the world's largest mangrove deltaic region, is one of the most productive ecosystems in tropical and subtropical latitudes and also serve as a nursery ground for rich coastal fisheries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In this study, we highlighted diatom assemblages from the Indian part of Sundarbans Biosphere Reserve (SBR) area for the first time based on light microscopy and rbcL gene sequencing and phylogeny. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>In total, 15 diatom species (11 centric forms and 4 pennate forms) were documented using light microscopy, and 3 major clades of diatoms were detected in rbcL phylogeny. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Out of 15 diatom species, 7 were the first record from Sundarbans mangrove water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>One of the species, Thalassiosira ferelineata Hasle and Fryxell, was reported for the first time in an Asian mangrove ecosystem based on light microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Our study suggests the importance of establishing cultures and their polyphasic taxonomy are the future necessity to create an authenticated diatom database from mangrove water, which is still overlooked globally. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Microbiology</kwd><kwd>Ecology</kwd><kwd>Environmental sciences</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0010"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Marine ecosystems are key contributors of global primary production accounting for approximately 50 gigatons of carbon each year (Field et al., 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>One of such productive ecosystems is mangrove ecosystem located in tropical and subtropical latitudes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>This ecosystem also serves as the nursery ground for rich fisheries (Robertson and Blaber, 1992). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The sustenance of fishery resources in mangrove ecosystem is mainly due to plankton communities including phytoplankton (Robertson and Blaber, 1992). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Sundarbans, the world's largest deltaic contiguous mangrove region, is situated at the estuarine phases of river Ganga, Brahmaputra and Meghna between latitudes 21°32′ and 21°40′ N and longitudes 88°05′ and 89° E spanning across India and Bangladesh (Spalding et al., 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The salient features of this deltaic mangrove ecosystem include interconnected network of numerous creeks, rivers and rivulets, and semi-diurnal tidal influences across the entire region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>In spite of floristic diversity of mangroves (Barik and Chowdhury, 2014), the large variability in hydrological parameters including both freshwater and coastal water influences, topographic heterogeneity and their interactions, has resulted in rich biodiversity in Sundarbans (Gopal and Chauhan, 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>In 1987, UNESCO declared the core mangrove forest of Indian Sundarbans (2,585 sq. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>km) as Sundarbans Biosphere Reserve (SBR) for protection and conservation of mangrove flora and fauna including the Royal Bengal Tiger from anthropogenic disturbances. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0015"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Phytoplankton, in particular chromophytic phytoplankton, is the major contributor to aquatic primary production in Sundarbans mangrove (e.g., Biswas et al., 2010; Manna et al., 2010; Bhattacharjee et al., 2013; Samanta and Bhadury, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Phytoplankton community fingerprinting techniques based on molecular tools (e.g. gene sequencing and phylogeny) along with microscopy has been found to be promising approaches for accelerating biodiversity research in Sundarbans mangrove ecosystem (Bhattacharjee et al., 2013; Samanta and Bhadury, 2014, 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The high fish productivity in Sundarbans also implicitly depends on net primary production by phytoplankton (Mukherjee et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Diatoms have been found to overwhelmingly dominate phytoplankton assemblages (&gt;75%) in this mangrove ecosystem (Biswas et al., 2010; Manna et al., 2010; Aziz et al., 2012; Samanta and Bhadury, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Diatoms form the basis of world's shortest and most efficient food webs such as sustenance of rich fisheries in coastal ecosystems including mangroves (e.g., Jickells, 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>They are used as a biological proxy to monitor health of coastal ecosystems (e.g., Stevenson et al., 2008; Vilmi et al., 2015); however studies are limited in this aspect with respect to mangroves (Smol and Stoermer, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is necessary to establish baseline information of diatom assemblages from mangroves to test their potential as a reliable bioindicator for assessment of environmental health and also for fisheries stock assessment such as planktivorous fishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The information of diatom assemblages albeit in limited numbers is available from different parts of Sundarbans mangrove ecosystem; however the Indian part of Sundarbans Biosphere Reserve (SBR) region has remained largely unexplored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The SBR which is a protected zone, a pristine environment (lesser human interference) represent a unique opportunity to monitor natural diatom assemblages and their importance in this area of Sundarbans mangrove ecosystem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we documented novel insights into diatom assemblages from the Indian part of SBR area based on light microscopy and rbcL phylogeny to establish the baseline information for future diatom based ecosystem health monitoring of this ecosystem. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Study area and sample collections </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0020"><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The Indian part of SBR is situated in the eastern part of Indian Sundarbans adjoining Bangladesh and bound by Matla River in the west and southern part facing the Bay of Bengal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The study area is strongly influenced by riverine freshwater as well as saline water from Bay of Bengal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Consequently, a salinity gradient is formed across the study sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The area can be divided into three inter-related zones: core area which is largely protected from any external disturbance, buffer zone, and Sajnekhali Sanctuary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Surface water was collected (50 mL) for undertaking phytoplankton analysis from five different stations of SBR (see Fig. 1) during the month of November and December 2012 at low tide following standard protocol (Bhattacharjee et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The selection of stations were undertaken based on prevailing salinity gradient with stations closer to the coastal Bay of Bengal had higher salinity than stations away from the Bay of Bengal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the stations which are largely shallow located in the area of SBR which has rich mangrove species and also serve as the nursery ground of planktivore fish populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Following collection, samples were immediately fixed with molecular grade 100% ethanol (Merck, Billerica, MA, USA) with a ratio of 1:5 (v/v) ethanol: sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>At the time of sampling, salinity was measured in situ using a refractometer (Erma, Japan) in each station (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The stations StnSBRS1, S2 and S3 were located in core area; StnSBRN1 in buffer zone; and StnSBRN2 in Sajnekhali Sanctuary of SBR (Fig. 1).Fig. 1Maps of the study area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>(a) Country map of India and Bangladesh. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>(b) The entire Sundarbans mangrove ecosystem across India and Bangladesh. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>(c) The map showing the stations sampled in Indian part of SBR; StnSBRN1 in buffer zone, StnSBRN2 in Sajnekhali Sanctuary and StnSBRS1, S2, and S3 in core area of SBR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Coordinate of stations sampled are mentioned in Table 1 along with in situ salinity values.Fig. 1Table 1List of diatoms species recorded using light microscopy from five stations of SBR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Taxa marked as bold indicate first report from Indian part of Sundarbans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Salinity and the number of rbcL clones that were sequenced from each sampling station are also mentioned.Table 1Sampling stationCoordinatesSalinity (psu)Diatom species encountered in light microscopyNumbers of rbcL clones sequencedStnSBRN122°05′51.70″N 88°57′19.30″E15Coscinodiscus argus, Cyclotella striata,C. litoralis, Ephemera planamembraneacea, Entomoneis alata,Shionodiscus oestrupii var. venrickae, T. eccentrica, Thalassiosira sp.8StnSBRN221°56′50.90″N 88°52′37.90″E18Bacillaria sp., Coscinodiscus argus, C. marginatus, Cyclotella striata,C. litoralis, Ephemera planamembraneacea, Lauderia annulata,Thalassiosira eccentrica, Thalassiosira sp.9StnSBRS121°40′28.87″N 88°57′28.58″E15Coscinodiscus marginatus, Cyclotella litoralis, Thalassiosira ferelineata, T. eccentrica, T. nodulolineata25StnSBRS221°47′35.27″N 88°55′19.11″E19Coscinodiscus argus, C. jonesianus, Cyclotella striata,C. litoralis, Thalassiosira sp.12StnSBRS321°49′45.37″N 88°53′00.42″E20Bacillaria sp., Coscinodiscus argus, Cyclotella striata, Surirella sp., Thalassiosira eccentrica, Thalassiosira sp.13 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Microscopic observations and molecular analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0025"><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>For diatom cell count, 25 ml of preserved water samples were concentrated by gravity sedimentation (24 h) and subsequently enumerated based on drop count method under a light microscope BX53 (Olympus, Tokyo, Japan) (Verlencar and Desai, 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Water mount samples were observed for species level identification of diatoms under a light microscope BX53 (Olympus), and differential interference contrast (DIC) images were captured using CellSens software (Olympus). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0030"><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Environmental DNA was extracted from 25 mL of water sample from each station using a modified DNA extraction protocol of Boström et al. (2004) with respect to two steps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>In one step, 5 μL of proteinase K (10 mg mL−1) (Amresco, USA) was added during lysis and incubated at 55 °C for 3 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>In the next step, 10 μL of lysozyme (20 mg mL−1) (SRL, India) was added and incubated at 37 °C for 1 hour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Rest of the extraction protocol was same as detailed earlier by Boström et al. (2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Partial rbcL gene fragments (554 bp) were amplified from environmental DNA for all the stations using rbcL primers (Wawrik et al., 2002; Samanta and Bhadury, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>PCR reactions were performed in triplicate for each environmental DNA sample, pooled together and subsequently purified using Gel Purification Kit (Qiagen, Valencia, USA) as per manufacturer's protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Purified PCR products were cloned using pGEM-T Easy vector (Promega, Madison, USA) following manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Sequencing was undertaken with SP6 primer in ABI Prism 3130 Genetic Analyzer based on BigDye Terminator Chemistry (Foster City, CA, USA) following manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0035"><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The base calling of chromatograms were manually checked and vector sequences were trimmed in the two ends of each rbcL sequences in BioEdit v7.0 (Hall, 1999) before undertaking further analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The generated DNA sequences were compared with published rbcL sequences using blastn tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi" id="intref0010">http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Two hundred fifty rbcL reference sequences from databases with the sequences generated in this study were aligned using MUSCLE (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/muscle/" id="intref0015">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/muscle/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analyses were undertaken at the nucleotide level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Bayesian inference (BI) was performed using MrBayes v3.2 by selecting GTR+I+G substitution model (Ronquist et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>A four chains (two cold and two heated) run for 100 millions generations was used and trees were sampled every 5000 generation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Posterior probabilities (PP) were estimated with 50% burn-in, and majority rule consensus tree was constructed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>An online version of PHYML (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.atgc-montpellier.fr/phyml/" id="intref0020">http://www.atgc-montpellier.fr/phyml/</ext-link>; Guindon et al., 2010) was used to construct a maximum-likelihood (ML) tree by selecting AIC criterion for substitution model selection (Lefort et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The rbcL sequences generated as part of this study have been submitted to GenBank and their accession numbers are from KT335295-304, KT335317-324, and KT335346-398. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Results and discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0040"><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Diatom cell abundance at our study area ranged from 12,500 cells/L (StnSBRS1) to 23,000 cells/L (StnSBRN2) (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>In Sundarbans mangrove water, phytoplankton cell density can vary from 1,000 s (Bhattacharjee et al., 2013) to 100,000 s of cells/L (Choudhury et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>It is anticipated that diatom cell abundance in SBR could be similar to other part of this ecosystem studied so far. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>A total of 15 diatom species were identified across five stations in the Indian part of SBR based on light microscopy (Figs. 2a–g and 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The number of diatom species per station ranged from 4 (StnSBRS1) to 9 (StnSBRN2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Stations with higher salinity also had a higher number of diatom species and cell abundance (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Out of the 15 identified diatom species, only 4 were pennate forms, while the rest were centric forms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The pennate diatom species were only encountered in StnSBRN1 (2 species), StnSBRN2 (1 species) and StnSBRS3 (2 species) (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Our result showed relatively low diatom species diversity in SBR compared to other parts of the ecosystem (e.g. Biswas et al., 2010; Manna et al., 2010; Bhattacharjee et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the study area is represented by shallow water depth and very high suspended particulate matter load which limits light penetration and resulting low abundance of phytoplankton cells such as diatoms as found in this ecosystem (e.g. Bhattacharjee et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Also, limited sampling effort due to accessibility issues and logistic could be one of the reasons in addition to possible role of temporal variability in diatom populations that may have accounted for observed low diatom species diversity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The described diatom diversity is a small fraction of total, as only 50 ml of sample was collected to study the diversity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>For phytoplankton monitoring usually large volume of water is sieved through plankton net. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>It is expected that if the sampling effort is increased seasonally then more diatom species could be detected from the study area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>However, it is important to mention that our study area is largely restricted from human intrusion.Fig. 2Differential interference contrast (DIC) images of diatom species reported for the first time from Indian Sundarbans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>(a) Thalassiosira eccentrica. (b) T. ferelineata. (c) Shionodiscus oestrupii var. venrickae. (d) T. nodulolineata. (e) Cyclotella litoralis. (f) Coscinodiscus argus. (g) Ephemera planamembranacea. Scale bars = 20 μm.Fig. 2Fig. 3Differential interference contrast (DIC) images of diatoms encountered from SBR using light microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>(a–b) Coscinodiscus jonesianus. (c) C. marginatus. (d) Entomoneis alata. (e) Thalassiosira sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>(f) Cyclotella striata. (g) Lauderia annulata. (h) Surirella sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>(i) Bacillaria sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Scale bars = 20 μm.Fig. 3 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0045"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Out of 15 encountered diatom species solely based on light microscopic identification, six species namely, Thalassiosira ferelineata Hasle and Fryxell, Thalassiosira nodulolineata (Hendey) Hasle and Fryxell, Shionodiscus oestrupii var. venrickae (Fryxell and Hasle) Alversion, Kang and Theriot, Coscinodiscus argus Ehrenberg, Cyclotella litoralis Lange and Syvertsen, and Ephemera planamembranacea (Hendey) Paddock were recorded for the first time from Sundarbans. Thalassiosira eccentrica (Ehrenberg) Cleve was recorded for the first time from Indian part of SBR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Illustrated accounts including taxonomy and distribution of these species including some as new records from this ecoregion and also from Asia have been provided below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0050"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Thalassiosira eccentrica (Ehrenberg) Cleve (Fig. 2a) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0055"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Coscinodiscus eccentricus Ehrenberg </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0060"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>References: Fryxell and Hasle, 1972, p. 300, Figs 1–18; Harris et al., 1995, p. 123, Fig. 29; Hasle and Syvertsen, 1996, p. 62; Park et al., 2012, Fig. 5U; Li et al., 2013, p. 91–93, Fig. 47. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0065"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Descriptions: Valves faces are flat and cell diameter varies from 40–50 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Areolae are in curved tangential rows (eccentric structure) with a tendency towards fasciculation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Five to eight areolae are present in 10 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>In addition to the eccentric areolae structure on the valve face, the central areola is surrounded by seven areolae is the characteristic diagnostic feature of T. eccentrica under light microscope. T. angulata (Gregory) Hasle and T. pacifica Gran and Angst also have the eccentric areolae patterns, but they have absence of central areola is surrounded by seven areolae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0070"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Distribution: This species is cosmopolitan, usually found in Pacific, Atlantic, and Indian Oceans, more specifically, in Japan as well as in East and South China Sea regions (Li et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Previously this species was reported from Rupsha, Passur, Khalpatura, Arpangachia, Bhola, and Baleswar river systems of Bangladesh part of Sundarbans (Rahaman et al., 2013), but this is the first report from Indian part of Sundarbans. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0075"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Thalassiosira ferelineata Hasle and Fryxell (Fig. 2b) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0080"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>References: Hasle and Fryxell, 1977, P. 26–28, Figs 46–53; Hasle and Syvertsen, 1996, p. 59; Lehmkuhl et al., 2010, p. 316, Fig. 6. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0085"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Descriptions: Valve face is flat with narrow mantle flaring to broad marginal rim, 39–41 μm in diameter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Hexagonal areolae are in straight tangential rows with six to seven areolae in 10 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Additional row of small areolae are present at the valve margin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Diameter of marginal areolae are less than half that at the center. T. tenera Hasle and Fryxell also has the similar areolae pattern as T. ferelineata in light microscopic observation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>These two species can be distinguished by their valve diameter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The valve diameter of T. ferelineata is higher than T. tenera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The valve diameter of T. tenera generally varied from 10–29 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0090"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Distribution: This species is mainly found in warm water regions (Hasle and Syvertsen, 1996) and also reported from Antarctic and sub-Antarctic islands (Scott and Thomas, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>This is the first report of this species not only from Sundarbans mangrove, but also from Asia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0095"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Shionodiscus oestrupii var. venrickae (Fryxell and Hasle) Alversion, Kang and Theriot (Fig. 2c) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0100"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Thalassiosira oestrupii var. venrickae Fryxell and Hasle </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0105"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Reference: Fryxell and Hasle, 1980, p. 810–813, Figs 11–19 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0110"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Descriptions: Cells are 40 μm in diameter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Six to twelve areolae are present in 10 μm on valve face and areolae usually larger in central part of valve than closer to the margin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Areolae patterns are radial to sub-linear array. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0115"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Distribution: This species is generally found in warm water to temperate regions (Fryxell and Hasle, 1980). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>It has been previously reported as Thalassiosira oestrupii from Rupsha, Passur, Bhola and Baleswar river systems of Bangladesh part of Sundarbans (Rahaman et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>This is the first report from Indian part of Sundarbans. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0120"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Thalassiosira nodulolineata (Hendey) Hasle and Fryxell (Fig. 2d) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0125"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Coscinodiscus nodulolineatus Hendey </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0130"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>References: Hasle and Fryxell, 1977, p. 35, Figs 86–93; Torgan and Santos, 2007, p. 716, Figs 1A–C; Lehmkuhl et al., 2010, p. 316, Fig. 10; Li et al., 2013, p. 99, Figs 95–99. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0135"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Descriptions: Cells are 28–30 μm in diameter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Hexagonal areolae arranged in straight tangential rows with six to twelve areolae are present in 10 μm on valve face. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Central areola is slightly larger. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The valve mantle is characteristically ornamented with short ribs. T. nodulolineata can be easily confused with T. nanolineata (Mann) Fryxell in light microscopy. T. nanolineata has strutted process close to the central areolae, while in T. nodulolineata has the strutted process inside the central areolae which is visible based on light microscopy (Torgan and Santos, 2007). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0140"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Distribution: This taxon has a cosmopolitan distribution in coastal water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>It has been recorded frequently reported from South China Sea (Li et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>However, this is the first report from Sundarbans mangrove water. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0145"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Cyclotella litoralis Lange and Syvertsen (Fig. 2e) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0150"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Descriptions: Cell diameter varies from 25–30 μm with undulated valve face. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Ten to eleven striae are present in 10 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Marginal strutted processes are present on every interstria. C. litoralis differs from C. striata by the fact that in the later species undulation of the central area of the valve does not reach the region of marginal ridges. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0155"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>References: Lange and Syvertsen, 1989, p. 343–344, Figs 1–30; Park et al., 2012, Fig. 5i; Lee et al., 2015, p. 587, Figs 8c–d. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0160"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Distribution: This taxon is usually found in marine aquatic ecosystem encompassing Northern and Southern temperate regions (Hasle and Syvertsen, 1996). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The presence of this taxon is the first report from Sundarbans mangrove ecosystem. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0165"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Coscinodiscus argus Ehrenberg (Fig. 2f) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0170"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>References: Hasle and Sims, 1986, p. 33–34, Figs 1–7; Hasle and Syvertsen, 1996, p. 103. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0175"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Descriptions: Cells are 75–85 μm in diameter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Small central hyaline area is present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Areolae pattern is radial and hexagonal in shape. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Areolae increase in size from center of the valve towards the middle of radius, then decrease in size towards the margin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Two to six areolae is present in 10 μm on valve surface. Coscinodiscus radiatus Ehrenberg also have radial areolae pattern, however, C. argus can be distinguished from C. radiatus by areolae of uniform size throughout the entire valve face in the later species under light microscope. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0180"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Distribution: This species has a cosmopolitan distribution (Hasle and Syvertsen, 1996), but in this study, for the first, reported from Sundarbans. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0185"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Ephemera planamembranacea (Hendey) Paddock (Fig. 2g) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0190"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Basionym: Navicula planamembranacea Hendey </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0195"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>References: Hendey, 1964, p. 188, Fig. 8; Paddock, 1988, p. 86, Plate 31; Hasle and Syvertsen, 1996, p. 284, Plate 64. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0200"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Descriptions: Cells usually solitary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Apical axis, 66–69 μm; Parvalver axis, 29–30 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Central nodules are slightly depressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Due to the shape of the cell this species it is usually seen in girdle view under the light microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>In the girdle view, central and terminal nodules of the raphae are distinct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Small raphae fins are present near valve end. Hasle and Syvertsen (1996) considered that E. planamembranacea is more similar to Tropidoneis than to Navicula sensu stricto although, in the past, it has never been referred to Tropidoneis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0205"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Distribution: This genus is mainly found in North Atlantic Ocean (Hasle and Syvertsen, 1996) and also reported from Arctic and Antarctic regions (Scott and Thomas, 2005; Mather et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>This species is the first report from Sundarbans. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0210"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Additionally, rbcL gene sequencing from environmental DNA samples provided valuable information on diatom assemblages at the phylogenetic level from this ecologically important mangrove ecosystem facing the coastal Bay of Bengal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>A total of 67 rbcL clones were sequenced from five different stations of SBR (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The basal topology of the rbcL tree is polytomy (Fig. S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>In rbcL phylogenetic tree, majority of the environmental rbcL clones were grouped into three major clades (Fig. S1; Fig. S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>In clade1, a total of 16 rbcL clones clustered with species of thalassiosiroid diatoms (Fig. S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Among these 16 rbcL clones, nine clones formed a separate sub-clade within the clade1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>This sub-clade did not include any culture thalassiosiroid diatom rbcL sequences and also had strong statistical support both in ML (bootstrap value 90%) and Bayesian (posterior probability value 1.00) analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>This sub-clade may be representing a novel sub-clade of the thalassiosiroid diatoms; however, furthermore culture based study can confirm the same. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>We cannot rule out the other possibility that it could be because of the limited number of rbcL sequences currently available in published databases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Five rbcL sequences in clade1 (three from StnSBRN1, one from StnSBRN2 and one from StnSBRS1) clustered with T. sundarbana. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Incidentally, T. sundarbana is a new species of Thalassiosira that has been recently discovered and described from an estuarine environment in Sundarbans (Samanta and Bhadury, 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The detection of rbcL signatures of T. sundarbana additionally from SBR suggested that this species may be indigenous to Sundarbans mangrove and also has a broad distribution throughout the ecosystem. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0215"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>In clade2, a total of 24 clones clustered with the species of two asymmetrical bi-raphid pennate diatom genera Amphora and Halamphora (Fig. S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The rbcL clones in this clade showed highest identity (98–99%) with Amphora caribaea and Halamphora montana. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>In clade3, 23 clones clustered with a pennate diatom Bacillaria paxillifer, however, showed only 95–96% identity with this species (Fig. S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The statistical support of the node separating B. paxillifer from our rbcL clone cluster is also very weak both in ML (bootstrap value &lt;50%) and Bayesian (posterior probability value &lt;0.95) analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>In addition to these three major clades, one rbcL clone from StnSBRN2 clustered with rbcL sequence of Nitzschia filiformis, one clone from StnSBRS1 clustered with Petrodictyon gemma and another clone from StnSBRN2 clustered with Chaetoceros dayaensis (Fig. S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0220"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>In the present study, several new records of diatom species from the Indian part of SBR were reported using light microscopy and several novel rbcL sequences were detected in the phylogeny which represents an important set of baseline information for diatom assemblages from a mangrove ecosystem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>One of the constraints of this study is that the microscopic observation and the molecular identification of the diatoms had been undertaken independently from each environmental sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>This could be one of the reasons for the lack of correlation between morphological and molecular data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>However, our results from rbcL clone library approach provide first data on the diversity of diatom species in the study area and also highlight the need to expand published sequence databases by adding rbcL sequences representing unique ecosystems such as mangroves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>For DNA barcoding of diatoms, Hamsher et al. (2011) showed that rbcL gene could be good selection based on its variance, whereas Zimmermann and colleagues affirmed that V4 region of SSU rDNA could be a good alternative for diatom barcoding (Zimmermann et al., 2011, 2014, 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The 5.8S+ITS2 could also be another alternative barcoding marker for diatoms (Moniz and Kaczmarska, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Our present study suggests that it is important to establish the cultures for better understanding of diatom assemblages in the mangrove waters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>To create an authenticated diatom database from the mangrove waters, it is also important to characterize those established cultures using multigene phylogeny and detailed morphological documentations using electron microscopy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0225"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Overall this study has documented several new records of diatom species from Indian part of SBR using microscopy, which has hitherto remained unknown so far. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>As part of this study, the rbcL clone library approach provides glimpse of diversity of diatoms from the study area and also highlight that the published sequence databases needs to be populated further with rbcL sequences representing unique ecosystems such as mangrove ecosystems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>With respect to future ecosystem monitoring of SBR, reported diatom species along with rbcL phylogeny provide baseline information of diatom assemblages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>This study indicates that establishment of cultures and their polyphasic taxonomy are essential to create an authenticated diatom database from mangrove water, which is still overlooked globally. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Declarations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec5.1"><title><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Author contribution statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0230"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Brajogopal Samanta: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Wrote the paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0235"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Punyasloke Bhadury: Conceived and designed the experiments; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec5.2"><title><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Funding statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0240"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>This work is partly supported by MoES grant (MMME of MLRP through CMLRE) and start up grant of IISERK awarded to Punyasloke Bhadury. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Brajogopal Samanta is the recipient of an IISERK PhD Fellowship. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec5.3"><title><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Competing interest statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0245"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec5.4"><title><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Additional information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0250"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Data associated with this study has been deposited at Genbank under the accession numbers KT335295-304, KT335317-324, and KT335346-398. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>AzizA.RahmanaM.AhmedA.Diversity, distribution and density of estuarine phytoplankton in the Sundarban mangrove forests, BangladeshBangladesh J. Bot.4120128795 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib2"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>BarikJ.ChowdhuryS.True mangrove species of Sundarbans delta, West Bengal, eastern IndiaCheck List102014329334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib3"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>BhattacharjeeD.SamantaB.DandaA.A.BhaduryP.Temporal succession of phytoplankton assemblages in a tidal creek system of the Sundarbans mangroves – an integrated approachInt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Biodivers.20132013115 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib4"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>BiswasH.DeyM.GangulyD.DeT.K.GhoshS.JanaT.K.Comparative analysis of phytoplankton composition and abundance over a two decade period at the land-ocean boundary of a tropical mangrove ecosystemEstuar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Coast332010384394 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib5"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>BoströmK.H.SimuK.HagströmA.RiemannL.Optimization of DNA extraction for quantitative marine bacterioplankton community analysisLimnol Oceanogr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Meth.22004365373 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib6"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>ChoudhuryA.K.DasM.PhilipP.BhaduryP.An assessment of the implications of seasonal precipitation and anthropogenic influences on a mangrove ecosystem using phytoplankton as proxiesEstuar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Coast382015854872 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib7"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>FieldC.BehrenfeldM.RandersonJ.FalkowskiP.Primary production of the biosphere: integrating terrestrial and oceanic componentsScience28119982372409657713 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib8"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>FryxellG.A.HasleG.R.Thalassiosira eccentrica (Ehrenb.) Cleve, T. symmetrica sp. nov and some related centric diatomsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Phycol.81972297317 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib9"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>FryxellG.A.HasleG.R.The marine diatom Thalassiosira oestrupii: structure, taxonomy and distributionJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Bot., Le671980804814 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib10"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>GopalB.ChauhanM.Biodiversity and its conservation in the Sundarban mangrove ecosystemAquat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Sci.682006338354 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib11"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>GuindonS.DufayardJ.F.FefortV.AnisimovaM.HordijikW.GascuelO.New algorithms methods to estimate maximum-likelihood phylogenies: assessing the performance of PhyML 3.0Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Biol.59201030732120525638 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib12"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>HallT.A.BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NTNucleic Acids Symp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Ser.4119999598 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib13"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>HamsherS.E.EvansK.M.MannD.G.PoulíčkováA.SaunsersG.W.Barcoding diatoms: exploring alternatives to COI-5PProtist162201140542221239228 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib14"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>HarrisA.S.D.MedlinL.K.LewisJ.JonesK.J.Thalassiosira species (Bacillariophyceae) from Scottish sea-lochEur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Phycol.301995117131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib15"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>HasleG.R.FryxellG.A.The genus Thalassiosira: some species with a linear areola arrayNova Hedwigia Beih.5419771566 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib16"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>HasleG.R.SimsP.A.The diatom genus Coscinodiscus Ehrenb.: C. argus Ehrenb. and C. radiatus EhrenbBot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Mar.291986305318 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib17"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>HasleG.R.SyvertsenE.E.Marine diatomsTomasC.R.Identifying marine Diatoms and Dinoflagellates1996Academic PressSan Diego5385 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib18"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>HendeyN.I.An introductory account of the smaller algae of British coastal waters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Part 5: Bacillariophyceae (Diatoms)Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Fishery Investigation Series IV1964HMSOLondon </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib19"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>JickellsT.D.Nutrient biogeochemistry of the coastal zoneScience28119982172229660744 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib20"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>LangeC.B.SyvertsenE.E.Cyclotella litoralis sp. nov. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>(Bacillariophyceae), and its relationships to C. striata and C. stylorumNova Hedwigia481989341356 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib21"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>LeeS.D.YunS.M.ParkJ.S.LeeJ.H.Floristic survey of diatom in the three islands (Baeknyeong, Daecheong, Socheong) from Yellow sea of KoreaJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Ecol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Environ.382015563598 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib22"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>LefortV.LonguevilleJ.-E.GascuelO.SMS: smart model selection in PhyMLMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Evol.3420172422242428472384 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib23"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>LehmkuhlE.A.TremarinP.I.Moreira-FilhoH.LudwingT.A.V.Thalassiosirales (Diatomeae) from Guaratuba bay, Paraná state, BrazilBiota Neotropica102010313324 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib24"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>LiY.ZhaoQ.LüS.The genus Thalassiosira off the Guangdong coast, South China seaBot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Mar.56201383110 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib25"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>MannaS.ChaudhuriK.BhattacharyyaS.BhattacharyyaM.Dynamics of Sundarban estuarine ecosystem: eutrophication induced threats to mangrovesSaline Syst.62010820699005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib26"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>MatherL.MacIntoshK.KaczmarskaI.KleinG.MartinJ.L.A checklist of diatom species reported (and presumed native) from Canadian coastal watersCan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Tech. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Rep. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Fish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Aquat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Sci.28812010178 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib27"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>MonizM.B.J.KaczmarskaI.Barcoding of diatoms: nuclear encoded ITS2 revisitedProtist161201073419674931 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib28"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>MukherjeeS.ChaudhuriA.KunduN.MitraS.HomechaudhuriS.Comprehensive analysis of fish assemblages in relation to seasonal environmental variables in an estuarine river of Indian SundarbansEstuar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Coast362013192202 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib29"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>PaddockT.B.B.Plagiotropis Pfitzer and Tropidonies Cleve, a summary accountBibl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Diatomol.1619881152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib30"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>ParkJ.KhimJ.S.OhtsukaT.ArakiH.WitkowskiA.KohC.H.Diatom assemblages on Nanaura mudflat, Ariake Sea, Japan: with reference to the biogeography of marine benthic diatoms in Northeast AsiaBot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Stud.532012105124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib31"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>RahamanS.M.B.GolderJ.RahamanM.S.HasanuzzamanA.F.M.HaqK.A.BegumS.IslamS.S.BirJ.Spatial and temporal variations in phytoplankton abundance and species diversity in the Sundarbans mangrove forest of BangladeshJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Mar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Dev.32013126 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib32"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>RobertsonA.I.BlaberS.Plankton, epibenthos and fish communitiesRobertsonA.I.AlongiD.M.Tropical Mangrove Ecosystems1992American Geophysical UnionWashington, D.C173224 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib33"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>RonquistF.TeslenkoM.MarkP.V.MrBayes3.2: efficient Bayesian inference and model choice across a large model spaceSyst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Biol.61201253954222357727 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib34"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>SamantaB.BhaduryP.Analysis of diversity of chromophytic phytoplankton in a mangrove ecosystem using rbcL gene sequencingJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Phycol.50201432834026988190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib35"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>SamantaB.BhaduryP.Thalassiosira sundarbana sp. nov. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>(Bacillariophyta), an estuarine diatom from Sundarbans mangrove ecoregion based on morphology and molecular phylogenyPhycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Res.632015102109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib36"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>SamantaB.BhaduryP.A comprehensive framework for functional diversity patterns of marine chromophytic phytoplankton using rbcL phylogenySci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Rep.620162078326861415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib37"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>ScottF.J.ThomasD.P.DiatomsScottF.J.MarchantH.J.Antarctic Marine Protists2005Australian Biological Resources Study: Australian Antarctic DivisionCanberra and Hobart13201 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib38"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>SmolJ.P.StoermerE.F.The Diatoms: Applications for the Environmental and Earth Sciencessecond ed.2010Cambridge University Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib39"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>SpaldingM.D.BlascoE.FieldC.D.World Mangrove Atlas1997International Society for Mangrove EcosystemsOkinawa, Japan </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib40"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>StevensonR.J.PanY.ManoylovK.M.ParkerC.A.LarsenD.P.HerlihyA.T.Development of diatom indicators of ecological conditions for streams of the western USJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>North Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Benthol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Soc.27200810001016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib41"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>TorganL.C.SantosC.B.Ocorrencia de Thalassiosira nodulolineata (Bacillariophyta) na Laguna do Patos, BrasilRev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Brasileira Biociências52007714716 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib42"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>VerlencarX.L.DesaiS.Phytoplankton Identification Manual2004NIOGoa, India </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib43"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>VilmiA.KarjalainenS.M.LanderioV.L.HeinoJ.Freshwater diatoms as environmental indicators: evaluating the effects of eutrophication using species morphology and biological indicesEnviron. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Monit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Assess.187201524325864081 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib44"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>WawrikB.PaulJ.H.TabitaF.R.Real-time PCR quantification of rbcL (ribulose-1.5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase) mRNA in diatoms and pelagophytesAppl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Microbiol.6820023771377912147471 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib45"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>ZimmermannJ.AbarcaN.EnkN.SkibbeO.KusberW.H.JahnR.Taxonomic reference libraries for environmental barcoding: a best practice example from diatom researchPLoS One92014e108793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib46"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>ZimmermannJ.GlöcknerG.JahnR.EnkN.GemeinholzerB.Metabarcoding vs. morphological identification to assess diatom diversity in environmental studiesMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Ecol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Resour.15201552654225270047 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib47"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>ZimmermannJ.JahnR.GemeinholzerB.Barcoding diatoms: evaluation of the V4 subregion on the 18s rRNA gene, including new primers and protocolsOrg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Divers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Evol.112011173192 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0265">The following are the supplementary data related to this article:<SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="dfig1" position="anchor"><label>FigureS1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Selected part of the phylogenetic tree derived from Bayesian Inference (BI) and Maximum Likelihood (ML) analyses based on rbcL sequences at the nucleotide level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Only three major clades containing the rbcL clones generated as part of this study are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Those are: (a) Clade1, (b) Clade2, and (c) Clade3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>The complete tree can be viewed in Supplementary Fig. S2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Values at nodes correspond to BI posterior probabilities values and ML bootstrap values, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Only posterior probabilities &gt;0.95 and bootstrap values &gt;50% are shown on the tree node. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>The numbers of 100% identical clones are mentioned in brackets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>The scale bar indicates 0.2 substitutions per site. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">FigureS1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="figs1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="dfig2" position="anchor"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic tree from the Bayesian inference (BI) and Maximum Likelihood (ML) analyses based on rbcL sequences at the nucleotide level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Values at nodes correspond to BI posterior probabilities values and ML bootstrap values, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Only posterior probabilities &gt;0.95 and bootstrap values &gt;50% are shown on the tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>The numbers of 100% identical clones are mentioned in brackets. Lingulodinium polyedrum (Type II rbcL) was used as an outgroup (not shown in the tree). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>The scale bar indicates 0.2 substitutions per site. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Figure S2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="figs2"/></fig></SecTag></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>We are grateful to field personnel of WWF-India for assistance with sampling activities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>We thank three anonymous reviewers for their constructive comments. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag></back></article>
