<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.5.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art550.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.5.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_CJTEE289 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Chin J Traumatol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Chin. J. Traumatol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Chinese Journal of Traumatology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1008-1275</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6114124</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1008-1275(16)30274-7</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cjtee.2017.04.012</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Normal saline for intravenous fluid therapy in critically ill patients </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Fei-Hu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Chao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Zhi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Peng-Lin</given-names></name><email>mapenglin1@163.com</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Critical Care Medicine, Chinese People's Liberation Army General Hospital, Beijing 100853, China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Critical Care Medicine, 309th Hospital of Chinese People's Liberation Army, Beijing 100091, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author. <email>mapenglin1@163.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>5</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2018 Production and hosting by Elsevier B.V. on behalf of Daping Hospital and the Research Institute of Surgery of the Third Military Medical University.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The efficacy and safety of normal saline (NS) for fluid therapy in critically ill patients remain controversy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In this review, we summarized the evidence of randomized controlled trials (RCTs) which compared NS with other solutions in critically ill patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The results showed that when compared with 6% hydroxyethyl starch (HES), NS may reduce the onset of acute kidney injury (AKI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>However, there is no significant different in mortality and incidence of AKI when compared with 10% HES, albumin and buffered crystalloid solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is important to prescribe intravenous fluid for patients according to their individual condition. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Normal saline</kwd><kwd>Critical care</kwd><kwd>Fluid resuscitation</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0010"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Fluid resuscitation is a fundamental component of the management of acutely ill patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The optimal dose and types of intravenous (IV) fluid for resuscitation remain undetermined.1, 2 0.9% sodium chloride, or the so-called “normal saline” (NS), is one of the most commonly used IV fluid for seriously ill or injured patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Since NS has a totally different level of chloridion from the plasma, its administration would be inevitably causes hyperchloremic metabolic acidosis.3, 4 And the chloride has an important role in tubuloglomerular feedback mechanisms.5 As the chloride concentration in the distal tubule fluid rises, feedback occurs via the macula densa, the afferent arteriole constricts, and the glomerular filtration rate drops.6, 7 However, whether this adverse event will affect mortality and the incidence of acute kidney injury (AKI) remains unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, whether the NS is the solution for crystalloid resuscitation6 or not the first choice for crystalloid resuscitation8 remains controversy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0015"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we summarized the evidence of randomized controlled trials (RCTs) which compared NS with other solutions in critically ill patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The results were expected to lead to a better use of NS in critically ill patients, and may influence clinical outcomes positively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>NS for fluid resuscitation in critically ill patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0020"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>We selected RCTs comparing NS with other solutions in adult critically ill patients who required IV fluid therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The search strategy and inclusion criteria are listed in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The statistical analysis was performed using RevMan software (version 5.2; Cochrane Collaboration, Copenhagen, Denmark) for outcome measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The results of the risk ratio (RR) for dichotomous outcomes or the mean difference (MD) for continuous data were expressed as means and 95% confidence intervals (CI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>A random-effects model was used regardless of heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>A p value less than 0.05 was considered to indicate a statistically significant difference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The outcomes reported across studies included mortality at 28 and 90 days, renal outcomes, and length of stay in intensive care units (ICU).Table 1Search strategy and inclusion criteria.Review eligibility structure PopulationCritically ill patients requiring acute volume replacement (e.g. resuscitation, but not maintenance fluid) InterventionNormal saline ControlHES solutions, albumin, dextran, gelatin or buffered crystalloid solution OutcomesPrimary outcome: incidence of mortality.Secondary outcomes: renal function, use of renal replacement therapy, lengths of stay in ICU, incidence of patients requiring of red cell transfusion. Study designProspective randomized controlled trialsReview eligibility criteria Inclusion criteria1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Randomized controlled trial;2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Participants' age ≥18 years;3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Indication for acute volume resuscitation (e.g. hypovolemia, hypotension, inadequate indicators of pre-load or filling pressures);4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Allocation to resuscitation with normal saline compared with HES, albumin, or buffered crystalloid solution. Exclusion criteria1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Fluids used as maintenance rather than resuscitation;2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>What control group used is whole blood, or blood products;3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Use of normal saline for elective pre-operative volume loading;4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Elective surgical procedures (e.g. cardiac surgery);5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Observational study designs, quasi-randomized, cross-over, or cluster randomized trials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>NS vs 6% hydroxyethyl starch (HES) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0025"><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Seven RCTs investigated the efficacy and safety of 6% HES vs NS during the IV fluid therapy in critically ill patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The results (Table 2) showed that more patients in the 6% HES group met the RIFLE (risk, injury, failure, loss, end-stage kidney disease) criteria for risk and injury (p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Therefore, compared to NS, 6% HES may increase the risk of AKI when prescribed for critically ill patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>However, no significant differences were found between 6% HES and NS in all-cause mortality (at 28 days or at 90 days), renal replacement therapy, RBC transfusion and length of stay in ICU when used for fluid resuscitation in critically ill patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>No RCTs analysed the cost-effectiveness of the two fluid therapies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>One cohort study did a pre-specified cost-effectiveness analysis from New South Wales enrolled in the Crystalloid vs HES trial (CHEST, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ctgov:NCT00935168" id="intref0010">NCT00935168</ext-link>),9 and found that the total hospital costs (including ICU costs) at 24 months were similar between the HES and saline groups ($62,196 vs $62,617; p = 0.83). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>This suggested that there may be no difference in hospital costs when these two fluids were prescribed for fluid resuscitation in critically ill patients.Table 2Comparison of 6% HES and NS on fluid resuscitation.ParametersNo. of patientsRR (95% CI)Heterogeneity I2 (p value)Test for effect (p value)HESNSAll-cause mortality (90 days)10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15828/4089958/44970.97 (0.81, 1.16)51% (0.07)0.73All-cause mortality (28 days)13, 14, 15, 16647/4073746/44760.99 (0.86, 1.13)27% (0.25)0.85All-cause mortality 28 days)–trauma1712/566/531.89 (0.77–4.68)Not applicable0.17All-cause mortality (28 days)–sepsis13, 15136/475181/6521.03 (0.85, 1.25)0% (0.41)0.75AKI- RIFLE- risk13, 14, 171809/34651935/34830.94 (0.90, 0.98)0% (0.56)0.006AKI-RIFLE- risk–trauma178/5612/530.63 (0.28, 1.42)Not applicable0.27AKI-RIFLE- risk–sepsis1313/10011/951.12 (0.53, 2.38)Not applicable0.76AKI-RIFLE- injury13, 14, 171138/34211266/34880.91 (0.85, 0.97)0% (0.51)0.004AKI-RIFLE-injury–trauma174/568/530.47 (0.15, 1.48)Not applicable0.20AKI-RIFLE-injury–sepsis134/1005/950.76 (0.21, 2.75)Not applicable0.68AKI- RIFLE- failure13, 14341/3343308/34701.15 (0.99, 1.33)0% (0.35)0.06AKI-RIFLE- failure–sepsis135/1007/950.68 (0.22, 2.06)Not applicable0.49Renal replacement therapy14, 17237/3408199/34281.20 (1.00, 1.44)0% (0.47)0.05Use of renal replacement therapy–trauma172/563/530.63 (0.11, 3.63)Not applicable0.61RBC transfusion1329/10020/961.38 (0.84, 2.26)Not applicable0.21Length of stayMD (95% CI)Heterogeneity I2 (p value)Test for effect (p value)HESNSGuidet et al1315.4 ± 11.120.2 ± 22.2−1.58 (−6.53, 3.37)76% (0.04)0.53Myburgh et al147.3 ± 0.26.9 ± 0.2AKI: acute kidney injury; CI: confidence interval; HES: hydroxyethyl starch; MD: mean difference; NS: normal saline; RIFLE: risk, injury, failure, loss, end-stage kidney disease; RR: relative risk. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0030"><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>From the acquired evidence, when 6% HES was prescribed for critically ill patients, we must take more attention on the change of renal function and give supportive treatment immediately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>More studies are needed and should focus on long-term outcomes, clinical relative adverse events and the impact on coagulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>NS vs 10% HES </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0035"><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Only two RCTs18, 19 with 86 patients were enrolled in the comparison of NS vs 10% HES (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The results show that there were no differences in all-cause mortality (at 28 days), renal failure and length of stay in ICU between the two groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>For the limited patient data, the conclusion has high risk of inconsistency and thus cannot be applied to guide the clinical practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>It is necessary to use 10% HES according to patients' individual status.Table 3Comparison of 10% hydroxyethyl starch (HES) and NS on fluid resuscitation.ParametersNo. of patientsRR (95% CI)Heterogeneity I2 (p value)Test for effect (p value)HESNSAll-cause mortality (28 days)18, 1927/5111/351.63 (0.92, 2.88)Not applicable0.47All-cause mortality (28 days)–sepsis199/216/191.36 (0.59, 3.10)0% (0.41)0.75AKI- RIFLE- failure –sepsis193/211/192.71 (0.31, 23.93)Not applicable0.37Length of stayMD (95% CI)Heterogeneity I2 (p value)Test for effect (p value)HESNSMcIntyre et al197.5 (3–13)5 (1–13)1.50 (−4.01, 7.01)Not applicable0.59AKI: acute kidney injury; CI: confidence interval; HES: hydroxyethyl starch; MD: mean difference; NS: normal saline; RIFLE: risk, injury, failure, loss, end-stage kidney disease; RR: relative risk. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>NS vs. albumin </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0040"><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Five RCTs10, 11, 15, 18, 20 evaluated the efficacy and safety of albumin vs NS during the IV fluid therapy in critically ill patients (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>There were no differences in all-cause mortality (at 28 days or at 90 days), renal function, renal replacement therapy and length of stay in ICU between albumin and NS groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, two recent meta-analysis21, 22 evaluated albumin vs other fluids for resuscitation in patients with sepsis and suggested that the present evidence did not demonstrate significant advantage of using human albumin solutions at reducing all-cause mortality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, Jiang et al21 reported that 4%–5% albumin may be relative safer than 20%–25% albumin for fluid resuscitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>However, the high cost of albumin may limit its wide applicability.23, 24 Therefore, according to the current state of knowledge, we should carefully consider the hospital costs and the concentration when albumin was prescribed for critically ill patients.Table 4Comparison of albumin and NS on fluid resuscitation.No. of patientsRR (95% CI)Heterogeneity I2 (p value)Test for effect (p value)albuminNSAll-cause mortality (90 days)10, 11, 1536/101355/30551.39 (0.48, 4.01)87% (0.0006)0.54All-cause mortality (28 days)15, 18, 20759/35681009/45111.06 (0.87, 1.29)29% (0.25)0.58All-cause mortality 28 days)–trauma2081/59659/5901.36 (0.99, 1.86)Not applicable0.06All-cause mortality (28 days)–sepsis15, 20204/662374/11720.94 (0.74, 1.19)37% (0.21)0.60renal replacement therapy15, 2045/347341/34601.09 (0.72, 1.67)Not applicable0.68Length of stayMD (95% CI)Heterogeneity I2 (p value)Test for effect (p value)albuminNSFinfer S216.5 ± 6.66.2 ± 6.20.30 (−0.00, 0.60)Not applicable0.05AKI: acute kidney injury; CI: confidence interval; HES: hydroxyethyl starch; MD: mean difference; NS: normal saline; RIFLE: risk, injury, failure, loss, end-stage kidney disease; RR: relative risk. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>NS vs buffered crystalloid solution </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0045"><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Buffered crystalloid solution with electrolyte composition closely mimics human plasma in its content of electrolytes, osmolality, and pH.25, 26 And it has been considered as a good alternative to NS for critically ill patients with AKI.27, 28 However, from two RCTs29, 30 results (Table 5), we concluded that when compared with NS, the buffered crystalloid solution cannot reduce mortality or the risk of AKI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>One cluster randomized trials31 indicated that there was no significant different between NS and Ringer's lactate solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Another cost-minimization analysis32 results suggested that the use of Plasma-Lyte A was associated with a relatively higher fluid acquisition cost but a reduced need for magnesium replacement in critically injured trauma patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Therefore, further large scale RCTs are needed to assess the efficacy in higher-risk populations and significant adverse events.Table 5Comparison of buffered crystalloid and NS on fluid resuscitation.No. of patientsRR (95% CI)Heterogeneity I2 (p value)Test for effect (p value)Buffered crystalloidNSAll-cause mortality (90 days)3087/115295/11101.05 (0.78, 1.40)Not applicable0.75All-cause mortality (28 days)293/224/241.50 (0.40, 5.65)Not applicable0.55AKI- RIFLE- risk30123/1067107/10251.10 (0.86, 1.41)Not applicable0.43AKI- RIFLE- injury3046/106757/10250.78 (0.53, 1.13)Not applicable0.19AKI- RIFLE- failure3054/106736/10251.44 (0.95, 2.18)Not applicable0.08renal replacement therapy3038/115238/11100.96 (0.62, 1.50)Not applicable0.87No. of patientsMD (95% CI)Heterogeneity I2 (p value)Test for effect (p value)Buffered crystalloidNSReceived pRBC transfusion292224−5.00 (−38.99, 28.99)Not applicable0.77AKI: acute kidney injury; CI: confidence interval; MD: mean difference; NS: normal saline; pRBC: packed red blood cells; RIFLE: risk, injury, failure, loss, end-stage kidney disease; RR: relative risk. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0050"><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>In this review, we compared NS vs other fluids for IV fluid therapy in critically ill patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>There is little doubt that excess exogenous chloride administration has been shown to induce renal artery vasoconstriction, AKI, hyperchloremic metabolic acidosis, gastrointestinal dysfunction, and the secretion of inflammatory cytokines.4, 33 Although some observational studies have reported an increased mortality risk associated with the use of NS,34, 35 our results and some recent meta-analysis22, 36, 37 results showed that patients mortality and the risk of AKI were not changed with the excess exogenous chloride administration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0055"><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, inappropriate NS infusion management in hospitals may lead to clinical relative adverse events, prolong length of stay in ICU or increase the mortality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Many of the errors in NS infusion management are due to inadequate knowledge and training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Several survey research38, 39, 40, 41 also suggested that lack of adequate clinician preparation, poor fluid balance monitoring and inadequate knowledge are associated with increased clinical risk and harm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, improved knowledge led to improved confidence in NS infusion management.42 Therefore, it is necessary to use the present evidence to manage NS infusion, and we summarized some principles as follows.1.Assess the fluid and electrolyte status of critically ill patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Provide NS for patients whose demand cannot be met through oral or enteral routes, and stop as soon as possible.2.A NS infusion management plan should be made, in which NS prescription over the next 24 h and monitoring program were indispensable.3.The rate and volume of NS should be carefully considered; and the 4 Rs43 (resuscitation, routine maintenance, redistribution and reassessment) should be also remembered (Fig. 1).Fig. 1The 4 Rs-resuscitation, routine maintenance, replacement and redistribution.434.Other sources of fluid and electrolyte intake should be taken into account, including any oral or enteral intake, and intake from drugs, IV nutrition, blood and blood products.5.If possible, provide written information for patients and their family members. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0085"><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, NS as the most commonly used IV fluid for critically ill patients occupies a very important position in fluid resuscitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>A good understanding of its advantage and disadvantage when compared with other fluid prescribed for critically ill patients is conducive to make good clinical decision. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>1MyburghJ.A.MythenM.G.Resuscitation fluidsN Engl J Med36920131243125124066745 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib2"><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>2ScalesK.NICEC.G.174: intravenous fluid therapy in adults in hospitalBr J Nurs232014S6S824763276 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib3"><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>3KeL.CalzavaccaP.BaileyM.Systemic and renal haemodynamic effects of fluid bolus therapy: sodium chloride versus sodium octanoate-balanced solutionCrit Care Resusc162014293324588433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib4"><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>4ChowdhuryA.H.CoxE.F.FrancisS.T.A randomized, controlled, double-blind crossover study on the effects of 2-L infusions of 0.9% saline and plasma-lyte(R) 148 on renal blood flow velocity and renal cortical tissue perfusion in healthy volunteersAnn Surg2562012182422580944 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib5"><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>5YunosN.M.BellomoR.StoryD.Bench-to-bedside review: chloride in critical illnessCrit Care14201022620663180 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib6"><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>6YoungP.Saline is the solution for crystalloid resuscitationCrit Care Med4420161538154027153047 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib7"><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>7MorsingP.VelazquezH.EllisonD.Resetting of tubuloglomerular feedback by interrupting early distal flowActa Physiol Scand148199363688333296 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib8"><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>8SemlerM.W.RiceT.W.Saline is not the first choice for crystalloid resuscitation fluidsCrit Care Med4420161541154427428117 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib9"><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>9TaylorC.ThompsonK.FinferS.Hydroxyethyl starch versus saline for resuscitation of patients in intensive care: long-term outcomes and cost-effectiveness analysis of a cohort from CHESTLancet Respir Med.4201681882527324967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib10"><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>10RackowE.C.FalkJ.L.FeinI.A.Fluid resuscitation in circulatory shock: a comparison of the cardiorespiratory effects of albumin, hetastarch, and saline solutions in patients with hypovolemic and septic shockCrit Care Med1119838398506194934 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib11"><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>11van der HeijdenM.VerheijJ.van Nieuw AmerongenG.P.Crystalloid or colloid fluid loading and pulmonary permeability, edema, and injury in septic and nonseptic critically ill patients with hypovolemiaCrit Care Med3720091275128119242338 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib12"><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>12DubinA.PozoM.O.CasabellaC.A.Comparison of 6% hydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 and saline solution for resuscitation of the microcirculation during the early goal-directed therapy of septic patientsJ Crit Care252010659.e1659.e8 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib13"><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>13GuidetB.MartinetO.BoulainT.Assessment of hemodynamic efficacy and safety of 6% hydroxyethylstarch 130/0.4 vs. 0.9% NaCl fluid replacement in patients with severe sepsis: the CRYSTMAS studyCrit Care162012R9422624531 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib14"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>14MyburghJ.A.FinferS.BellomoR.Hydroxyethyl starch or saline for fluid resuscitation in intensive careN Engl J Med36720121901191123075127 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib15"><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>15AnnaneD.SiamiS.JaberS.Effects of fluid resuscitation with colloids vs crystalloids on mortality in critically ill patients presenting with hypovolemic shock: the CRISTAL randomized trialJAMA31020131809181724108515 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib16"><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>16LiF.SunH.HanX.D.[The effect of different fluids on early fluid resuscitation in septic shock]Zhongguo Wei Zhong Bing Ji Jiu Yi Xue20200847247518687174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib17"><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>17JamesM.F.MichellW.L.JoubertI.A.Resuscitation with hydroxyethyl starch improves renal function and lactate clearance in penetrating trauma in a randomized controlled study: the FIRST trial (Fluids in Resuscitation of Severe Trauma)Br J Anaesth107201169370221857015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib18"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>18VenemanT.F.Oude NijhuisJ.WoittiezA.J.Human albumin and starch administration in critically ill patients: a prospective randomized clinical trialWien Klin Wochenschr116200430530915237655 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib19"><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>19McIntyreL.A.FergussonD.CookD.J.Fluid resuscitation in the management of early septic shock (FINESS): a randomized controlled feasibility trialCan J Anaesth55200881982619050085 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib20"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>20FinferS.BellomoR.BoyceN.A comparison of albumin and saline for fluid resuscitation in the intensive care unitN Engl J Med35020042247225615163774 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib21"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>21JiangL.JiangS.ZhangM.Albumin versus other fluids for fluid resuscitation in patients with sepsis: a meta-analysisPLoS One92014e114666 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib22"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>22PatelA.LaffanM.A.WaheedU.Randomised trials of human albumin for adults with sepsis: systematic review and meta-analysis with trial sequential analysis of all-cause mortalityBMJ3492014g456125099709 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib23"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>23Latour-PerezJ.New recommendations for the use of serum albumin in patients with severe sepsis and septic shockCrit Care Med412013e289 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib24"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>24LyuP.F.MurphyD.J.Economics of fluid therapy in critically ill patientsCurr Opin Crit Care20201440240724979711 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib25"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>25YunosN.M.BellomoR.GlassfordN.Chloride-liberal vs. chloride-restrictive intravenous fluid administration and acute kidney injury: an extended analysisIntensive Care Med41201525726425518951 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib26"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>26PfortmuellerC.A.FleischmannE.Acetate-buffered crystalloid fluids: current knowledge, a systematic reviewJ Crit Care3520169610427481742 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib27"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>27YunosN.M.BellomoR.HegartyC.Association between a chloride-liberal vs chloride-restrictive intravenous fluid administration strategy and kidney injury in critically ill adultsJAMA.30820121566157223073953 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib28"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>28KrajewskiM.L.RaghunathanK.PaluszkiewiczS.M.Meta-analysis of high- versus low-chloride content in perioperative and critical care fluid resuscitationBr J Surg1022015243625357011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib29"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>29YoungJ.B.UtterG.H.SchermerC.R.Saline versus Plasma-Lyte A in initial resuscitation of trauma patients: a randomized trialAnn Surg259201425526223732264 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib30"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>30YoungP.BaileyM.BeasleyR.Effect of a buffered crystalloid solution vs saline on acute kidney injury among patients in the intensive care unit: the split randomized clinical trialJAMA31420151701171026444692 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib31"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>31SemlerM.W.WandererJ.P.EhrenfeldJ.M.Balanced crystalloids versus saline in the intensive care unit: the SALT randomized trialAm J Respir Crit Care Med19520171362137227749094 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib32"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>32SmithC.A.DubyJ.J.UtterG.H.Cost-minimization analysis of two fluid products for resuscitation of critically injured trauma patientsAm J Health Syst Pharm71201447047524589538 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib33"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>33FrazeeE.KashaniK.Fluid management for critically ill patients: a review of the current state of fluid therapy in the intensive care unitKidney Dis (Basel).22016647127536694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib34"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>34RaghunathanK.ShawA.NathansonB.Association between the choice of IV crystalloid and in-hospital mortality among critically ill adults with sepsis*Crit Care Med4220141585159124674927 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib35"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>35RaghunathanK.BonaviaA.NathansonB.H.Association between initial fluid choice and subsequent in-hospital mortality during the resuscitation of adults with septic shockAnesthesiology12320151385139326414499 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib36"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>36RochwergB.AlhazzaniW.SindiA.Fluid resuscitation in sepsis: a systematic review and network meta-analysisAnn Intern Med161201434735525047428 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib37"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>37QureshiS.H.RizviS.I.PatelN.N.Meta-analysis of colloids versus crystalloids in critically ill, trauma and surgical patientsBr J Surg1032016142626522616 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib38"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>38ChungL.H.ChongS.FrenchP.The efficiency of fluid balance charting: an evidence-based management projectJ Nurs Manag10200210311311882111 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib39"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>39CoombesI.D.MitchellC.A.StowasserD.A.Safe medication practice: attitudes of medical students about to begin their intern yearMed Educ.42200842743118338996 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib40"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>40KellyC.NoonanC.L.MonagleJ.P.Preparedness for internship: a survey of new interns in a large Victorian health serviceAust Health Rev352011146145121612725 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib41"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>41WeisgerberM.FloresG.PomeranzA.Student competence in fluid and electrolyte management: the impact of various teaching methodsAmbul Pediatr7200722022517512882 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib42"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>42OlsonA.F.Outpatient management of electrolyte imbalances associated with anorexia nervosa and bulimia nervosaJ Infusion Nurs282005118122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib43"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>43National Clinical guideline Centre (UK)Intravenous Fluid Therapy: Intravenous Fluid Therapy in Adults in Hospital2013Royal College of Physucuans (UK)London<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25340240" id="intref0015">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25340240</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><fn-group><fn id="d31e983"><p id="ntpara0010"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Peer review under responsibility of Daping Hospital and the Research Institute of Surgery of the Third Military Medical University. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group></back></article>
