<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6192338</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5140</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-018-5140-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>High genomic variability in the plant pathogenic bacterium Pectobacterium parmentieri deciphered from de novo assembled complete genomes </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zoledowska</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Motyka-Pomagruk</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sledz</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mengoni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Lojkowska</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><address><email>ewa.lojkowska@biotech.ug.edu.pl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0531 3426</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11451.30</institution-id><institution>Department of Biotechnology, Intercollegiate Faculty of Biotechnology, </institution><institution>University of Gdansk and Medical University of Gdansk, </institution></institution-wrap>Gdansk, Poland </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1757 2304</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8404.8</institution-id><institution>Department of Biology, </institution><institution>University of Florence, Sesto Fiorentino, </institution></institution-wrap>Florence, Italy </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>751</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Pectobacterium parmentieri is a newly established species within the plant pathogenic family Pectobacteriaceae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Bacteria belonging to this species are causative agents of diseases in economically important crops (e.g. potato) in a wide range of different environmental conditions, encountered in Europe, North America, Africa, and New Zealand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Severe disease symptoms result from the activity of P. parmentieri virulence factors, such as plant cell wall degrading enzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we observe significant phenotypic differences among P. parmentieri isolates regarding virulence factors production and the abilities to macerate plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>To establish the possible genomic basis of these differences, we sequenced 12 genomes of P. parmentieri strains (10 isolated in Poland, 2 in Belgium) with the combined use of Illumina and PacBio approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>De novo genome assembly was performed with the use of SPAdes software, while annotation was conducted by NCBI Prokaryotic Genome Annotation Pipeline. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par2"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The pan-genome study was performed on 15 genomes (12 de novo assembled and three reference strains: P. parmentieri CFBP 8475T, P. parmentieri SCC3193, P. parmentieri WPP163). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The pan-genome includes 3706 core genes, a high number of accessory (1468) genes, and numerous unique (1847) genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>We identified the presence of well-known genes encoding virulence factors in the core genome fraction, but some of them were located in the dispensable genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>A significant fraction of horizontally transferred genes, virulence-related gene duplications, as well as different CRISPR arrays were found, which can explain the observed phenotypic differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Finally, we found also, for the first time, the presence of a plasmid in one of the tested P. parmentieri strains isolated in Poland. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par3"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>We can hypothesize that a large number of the genes in the dispensable genome and significant genomic variation among P. parmentieri strains could be the basis of the potential wide host range and widespread diffusion of P. parmentieri. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The obtained data on the structure and gene content of P. parmentieri strains enabled us to speculate on the importance of high genomic plasticity for P. parmentieri adaptation to different environments. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12864-018-5140-9) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Blackleg</kwd><kwd>Pectinolytic erwinias</kwd><kwd>Pan-genome</kwd><kwd>Comparative genomics</kwd><kwd>Phages</kwd><kwd>Bacterial evolution</kwd><kwd>Genome plasticity</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100004281</institution-id><institution>Narodowe Centrum Nauki</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2014/14/M/NZ8/00501</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par9"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Genomes of a given bacterial species can show considerable variation in gene content, distribution, and presence of mobile elements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Therefore, conducting systematic analyses of the entire gene repertoire of several strains from a specific species, termed the pan-genome study, is vital for understanding bacterial intraspecies diversity, population genetics, and bacterial evolution [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The core pan-genome constitutes of highly-conserved genes present in all the analyzed genomes and usually encodes genes related to fundamental aspects of the bacterial biology contributing to significant phenotypic traits [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>It has been reported previously that some genes of the dispensable (accessory and unique) pan-genome might play a role in bacterial adaptation to specific growth conditions, such as colonization of new ecological niches, symbiosis, host-cell interaction, and pathogenicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In other words, the plasticity of this pan-genome fraction contributes to bacterial evolution [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The diversity/plasticity mentioned above is especially crucial regarding opportunistic bacterial pathogens, such as human, animal and also plant pathogens spreading in new hosts and/or a new environment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par10"><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Specifically, the genomes of a plant quarantine pathogen Ralstonia solanacearum include chromosomal rearrangements and several genes recently acquired via a horizontal gene transfer (HGT) [4–6]. R. solanacearum strains exhibit an unusually broad host range as they can infect more than 250 plant species in monocot and dicot botanical families [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The vast host range of R. solanacearum may be correlated with its high genomic plasticity [8–10] attributed to the occurrence of Mobile Genetic Elements (MGE), such as phages and plasmids [11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par11"><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Amongst plant pathogenic bacteria that trigger economically important losses, the causative agents of soft rot and potato blackleg should be listed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>This subgroup of Gram-negative Gammaproteobacteria, classified to the Pectobacteriaceae family currently encloses two genera: Dickeya and Pectobacterium [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The diseases caused by Dickeya spp. and Pectobacterium spp. result from the activity of Plant Cell Wall Degrading Enzymes (PCWDE) such as pectinases, cellulases, and proteases secreted via Type I or II secretion systems [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The Broad host range of these phytopathogens can be exemplified by the fact that Pectobacteriaceae have been reported to cause soft-rotting symptoms in a large number of plants, including 16 dicot plant families in 11 orders and 11 monocot families in 6 orders [14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par12"><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The development of novel diagnostic methods resulted in several reclassifications within both genera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>High genomic heterogeneity was attributed to Pectobacterium carotovorum strains (exhibiting about 20 different recA PCR-RFLP patterns) in comparison to Pectobacterium atrosepticum (with just two recA PCR-RFLP patterns [15]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The application of molecular techniques: genomic sequences comparison, DNA:DNA hybridization and average nucleotide identity (ANI) analysis resulted in the reevaluation of the taxonomic position of P. carotovorum strains deposited in different collections and/or isolated in the recent years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Finally, some strains of P. carotovorum, including the most frequently studied P. carotovorum SCC3193, were reclassified to Pectobacterium wasabiae [16] and later on to Pectobacterium parmentieri species [17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par13"><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In this study, we focused on P. parmentieri infecting plants worldwide and detected in Europe, North America, Africa, Asia and New Zealand [17–25]. P. parmentieri has been proven to cause disease symptoms on potato plants and tubers and also to survive in unfavourable environmental conditions (such as soil or surface waters). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>By now, their host range in the natural environment has not been fully understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>However, there is some information about the isolation of P. parmentieri (there P. wasabiae) strains from cabbage, eggplants, sweet potato and tomato in Malaysia [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par14"><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Currently, there are five publicly available genomes of P. parmentieri (NCBI servers, June 2018), whereas only 3 of them are closed to a full chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The genome (GenBank accession: NZ_CP015749.1) of the type strain P. parmentieri CFBP 8475T (previously P. wasabiae RNS 08.42.1A) is 5.03 Mb in size with GC content of 50.4% [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Among the 4462 proteins it encodes, there have been described some proteins speculated to ensure specific phenotypic traits that are important for P. parmentieri virulence and adaptation to its primary host - potato, such as PCWDE, components of secretion systems and AHL-dependent quorum sensing system [27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par15"><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The aim of the here presented study is to elucidate the genomic basis of P. parmentieri spread and rapid adaptation to different climate conditions (temperature, humidity). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>It was achieved by completing genome sequencing of 12 P. parmentieri strains isolated from potato plants in various environments, followed by comparative genomic analyses conducted on these twelve strains and three other sequences available in GenBank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The obtained results point to a high abundance of MGE characterizing the reported P. parmentieri pan-genome, which may likely be linked with adaptation to different environmental niches and be the reason for the worldwide spreading of this species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Results and discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Phenotypic characterization of P. parmentieri strains </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par16"><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Phenotypic characterization of the available P. parmentieri strains, isolated in Poland (10), Belgium (2), Finland (1) and France (1) (Table 1), was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>We observed high variability between the analyzed strains regarding the potato maceration efficacy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>It was interesting that the lowest and the highest maceration ability was noted for the strains isolated in Poland. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Besides, IFB5408 indicates 4-fold lower maceration than IFB5626 (Table 2).Table 1Strains used in this studyStrain numberSpeciesYear and country of isolationHostAccession numberReferenceIFB5408 P. parmentieri 2013, PolandPotato stemCP026977[27]IFB5427 P. parmentieri 2013, PolandWeedCP027260[27]IFB5432 P. parmentieri 2013, PolandPotato tuberCP026979[27]IFB5441 P. parmentieri 2013, PolandPotato tuberCP026980[27]IFB5485, GBBC 1786 P. parmentieri 2012, BelgiumPotatoCP026981This studyIFB5486, GBBC 1809 P. parmentieri 2012, BelgiumPotatoCP026982This studyIFB5597 P. parmentieri 2014, PolandPotato stemPSZH00000000[27]IFB5604 P. parmentieri 2014, PolandPotato stemCP026983[27]IFB5605 P. parmentieri 2014, PolandPotato stemCP026984[27]IFB5619 P. parmentieri 2014, PolandPotato stemCP026985[27]IFB5623 P. parmentieri 2014, PolandPotato stemCP026986[27]IFB5626 P. parmentieri 2014, PolandPotato tuberPSZG00000000[27]CFBP 8475T P. parmentieri 2008, FrancePotatoNZ_CP015749.1[36]SCC3193 P. parmentieri 1980s, FinlandPotatoNC_017845.1[39]WPP0163 P. parmentieri 2004, USAPotatoNC_013421.1[23]Table 2Comparison of the maceration ability and phenotypic features: enzyme activities, siderophores production, motility and biofilm formation of the tested P. parmentieri strainsStrainsMaceration, mmPectinases, mmCellulases, mmProteases, mmLipases, mmSiderophores, mmSwimming, mmSwarming, mmBiofilm, OD525IFB54089.5 ± 1.9320.7 ± 0.4610.3 ± 0.306.8 ± 0.2011.1 ± 0.3713.8 ± 0.5042.6 ± 2.9411.3 ± 0.830.113 ± 0.0017IFB542731.0 ± 0.8621.4 ± 0.5710.9 ± 0.3110.5 ± 0.1910.6 ± 0.2814.3 ± 0.5610 ± 1.0211.7 ± 0.740.094 ± 0.0021IFB543215.0 ± 0.9622.2 ± 0.509.8 ± 0.2912.2 ± 0.4911.7 ± 0.528.7 ± 0.4919.4 ± 4.228.4 ± 0.140.062 ± 0.0055IFB544111.7 ± 1.4421.0 ± 0.429.8 ± 0.3011.1 ± 0.3111.3 ± 0.277.67 ± 0.1811.7 ± 1.388.4 ± 0.260.064 ± 0.0091IFB548527.4 ± 2.0320.9 ± 0.2611.8 ± 0.2510.9 ± 0.1911.3 ± 0.3512.8 ± 0.3619.7 ± 2.7821.3 ± 0.490.080 ± 0.0042IFB548629.3 ± 0.8120.5 ± 0.3911.8 ± 0.656.6 ± 0.1410.3 ± 0.2714.6 ± 0.268.5 ± 0.7118.8 ± 0.700.084 ± 0.0064IFB559712.1 ± 0.9225.3 ± 0.317.1 ± 0.3113.2 ± 0.5611.1 ± 0.546.3 ± 0.3732.5 ± 2.5113.6 ± 1.530.079 ± 0.0028IFB560414.4 ± 0.8425.6 ± 0.280.0010.8 ± 0.4211.0 ± 0.2117.7 ± 0.3525.3 ± 1.099.9 ± 0.650.108 ± 0.0063IFB560520.9 ± 0.8724.5 ± 0.500.000.0010.8 ± 0.3214.7 ± 0.5136.5 ± 5.349.9 ± 0.350.098 ± 0.0058IFB561925.7 ± 0.6126.8 ± 0.308.2 ± 0.320.0011.0 ± 0.3013.6 ± 0.789.6 ± 0.7628.6 ± 1.040.093 ± 0.0085IFB562313.6 ± 0.8925.1 ± 0.280.0010.5 ± 0.4810.7 ± 0.318.6 ± 0.2259.4 ± 3.0026.6 ± 0.860.068 ± 0.0057IFB562638.2 ± 1.2024.7 ± 0.480.000.0012.0 ± 0.2716.6 ± 0.3915.6 ± 2.7325.8 ± 1.180.072 ± 0.0073CFBP 8475T34.3 ± 0.6423.1 ± 0.3511.3 ± 0.2110.3 ± 0.1811.1 ± 0.418.2 ± 0.1614.8 ± 1.8721.1 ± 1.410.089 ± 0.0072SCC319311.2 ± 1.2123.2 ± 0.836.7 ± 0.310.0010.8 ± 0.470.0022.6 ± 0.988.1 ± 0.260.063 ± 0.0108P. aeruginosa PA01nt.nt.nt.nt.nt.nt.nt.nt.0.113 ± 0.0030 Significance code  ***  **  **  **  No differences  **  ***  ***  ** The values represent averages from three biological repetitions and standard errornt - not tested;Significance codes: 0 ‘***’ 0.001 ‘**’ 0.01 ‘*’ generated form ANOVA analysis indicating the statistical differences within the analyzed phenotypic feature </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par17"><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The investigation of other P. parmentieri phenotypic features, such as the activity of PCDWEs revealed statistically significant differences between strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The tested strains indicated significant differences in pectinases, cellulases and proteases but not lipases activities (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Strains IFB5597, IFB5604, IFB5619, IFB5623 produced significantly higher amounts of pectinases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>At the same time, none of them produced high levels of cellulases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>However, IFB5597 as the only one of them indicate high activity of proteases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>On the other hand strains IFB5408, IFB5441, IFB5485 and IFB5486 possessed the low activity of pectinases, but IFB5485 and IFB5486 produced significant amounts of cellulases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par18"><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The studied P. parmentieri strains exhibit significant differences regarding both swimming and swarming motility (Table 2). Conserning biofilm formation, IFB5408, IFB5604 and IFB5605 isolates were as efficient in this trait as P. aeruginosa PAO1, a strain commonly applied as a positive control in biofilm formation assessment (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par19"><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we calculated correlation coefficients between different phenotypic traits by applying Pearson statistical method (p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Weak positive linear relationships between the strain’s ability to macerate potato tissue and their cellulases activity in addition to biofilm formation capacity (0.118 and 0.085) were observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Strains possessing the overall moderate activity of pectinases, cellulases and proteases showed the highest ability to macerate potato tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>In other words, the observed effects of different PCDWEs are synergistic, and the individual activity of each enzyme tends to complement each other (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par20"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The here-described P. parmentieri intraspecies variation is in agreement with several previous studies, in which P. parmentieri isolates differed in the plant maceration efficacy and PCWDE activities [20, 21, 23, 24, 28]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Genome structure of the P. parmentieri strains </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par21"><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Comparative genomics on 15 P. parmentieri strains (12 newly sequenced and three available from the GenBank) was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The number of scaffolds, GC content and the amount of N bases for all of the analyzed genomes were determined (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Ten of the newly assembled genomes were closed to a full chromosome, but in two cases we were not able to close specific genomes: strain IFB5626 consists of 2, and IFB5597 of 5 scaffolds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The length of the obtained P. parmentieri genomes varied from 4,877,201 bp (IFB5604) to 5,125,304 bp (IFB5427), which equals approx. 5% difference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>GC content varied between 50.29 and 50.6%, where the strain IFB5441 and IFB5619 had the lowest and the highest values, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>These results are in agreement with those obtained earlier for P. parmentieri CFBP 8475T and P. parmentieri SCC3193 regarding the genome length (5,030,841 bp and 5,164,411 bp) and the GC content (50.4% and 50.37%) [16, 17].Table 3Detailed pan-genome statistics and shapeStrainGenBank Accession no.Genome sizeNo. of N basesaNo of scaffoldsGC%Total number of genesGenes encodingPan-genomebProteinsrRNAstRNAsncRNACRISPRCore genesAccessory genesUnique genesP. parmentieri strainsIFB5408CP0269775,022,0170150.4047074420227784370675645IFB5427CP0272605,125,3040150.41484245612276843706808135IFB5432CP0269795,010,5330150.45470944062277843706632133IFB5441CP0269805,082,1770150.29478244922276943706698177IFB5485CP0269814,885,2490150.564534425222778437066197IFB5486CP0269825,038,1220150.4947834454227784370682212IFB5597PSZH000000005,046,6470550.57473444432277743706652174IFB5604CP0269834,877,2010150.5645354249227784370661019IFB5605CP0269845,040,694100150.4447624494227784370681158IFB5619CP0269854,959,3020150.6046124328227784370667331IFB5623CP0269865,006,798100150.33471344222277843706694112IFB5626PSZG000000005,059,731100250.4847904519227784370681085CFBP 8475TNZ_CP015749.15,030,8410150.4047724462227784370675540SCC3193NC_017845.15,164,4110150.37484144492278843706486346WPP0163NC_013421.15,063,8920150.48469044232275843706604181P. parmentieri plasmid pPAR01pPAR01CP027260101,9980149.45aNumber of undetermined basesbThe pan-genome content has been calculated on PGAP annotated genomes </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par22"><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Obtaining complete genome sequences allowed us to investigate deeply structural variations within the P. parmentieri genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The synteny of the closed genomes is presented in Fig. 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>In general, genomes were highly syntenic with minor structural differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>We detected a sizeable chromosomal rearrangement in one of the strains that have been isolated in Belgium (IFB5486). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>This deviation might have appeared during the long-time period of evolution, which could have subsequently undergone selective pressure under specific environmental conditions during the lengthy process of speciation, as it was reported before in other members of Enterobacteriales [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Moreover, highly variable regions in almost all of the analyzed strains were detected (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>In these highly variable regions, genes encoding phage-related proteins were found (Fig. 1) and a more precise description of these MGE shall be provided later.Fig. 1P. parmentieri genomes shape generated with the use of BRIG software </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par23"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, during de novo genome assembly of IFB5427 strain, the presence of a large plasmid of about 100 kb has been discovered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>This plasmid, for the first time described in P. parmentieri species, was named pPAR01. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Regarding the Pectobacteriaceae genus, the presence of other plasmids was reported only in P. carotovorum SCC1 (5 kb), D. solani PPO9091 (43 kb) and D. fangzhongdai DSM 101947 (5 kb) [30–32]. Notably, the above-listed plasmids are much smaller than pPAR01. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>A more detailed analysis of this plasmid is presented in ‘the mobilome’ paragraph below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>P. parmentieri has an open pan-genome </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par24"><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>With the NCBI Prokaryotic Genome Annotation Pipeline, the number of total predicted genes varied from 4842 to 4534 for strains IFB5427 and IFB5485, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The total number of genes encoding proteins ranged from 4561 to 4252 (Table 3) and was attributed to the strains mentioned above. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par25"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The pan-genome shape of the 15 analyzed P. parmentieri genomes is presented in Fig. 2A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>A total of 7021 gene clusters (orthologs) were found, 3706 of which comprised the core genome (52.8%), 1468 the accessory genome (20.9%) and 1847 (26.3%) the unique genome fraction (Fig. 2a, Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The quantity of the determined accessory genes varied from 486 to 822 for the most diverse strains SCC3193 and IFB5486, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, P. parmentieri SCC3193 indicated the highest quantity of unique genes (346 genes), while the strain IFB5485 the lowest (7 genes).Fig. 2The pan-genome shape of P. parmentieri. a The pan-genome pie chart showing gene content visualised with the use of Roary software. b Heap’s law chart representation regarding conserved genes vs total genes in 15 genomes </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par26"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>To investigate the openness of P. parmentieri pan-genome Heap’s Law was utilized [33, 34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The openness of pan-genome reflects the diversity of the gene pool within bacterial species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>For species with an open pan-genome, an addition of a newly sequenced genome significantly changes the pan-genome size [2], contrarily to what is observed in the case of strains exhibiting a closed pan-genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The calculated alpha value of 0.81 indicated that the P. parmentieri pan-genome is open (Fig. 2b) and that could be the result of high genomic plasticity within this species [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>This finding is in agreement with the level of openness of the pan-genome for other representatives of Gammaproteobacteria as it was reported before [35–38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>In contrast to P. parmentieri pan-genome, closely related and very homogenous D. solani species have a closed pan-genome [39]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Genomic relatedness of P. parmentieri strains </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par27"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Genetic relatedness among the P. parmentieri strains was studied by both computing the ANI values and by establishing genomic similarities with a pan-genome based analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>As expected for strains belonging to the same species, high ANI values ranging from 98.98 to 99.97 were observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analyses derived from the comparison of all protein sequences encoded within the genomes is presented in Fig. 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The genomes of P. parmentieri strains formed two main clades, from which the first (Clade I) is further divided into two subclades (IA and IB). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Clade IA comprises genomes of P. parmentieri reference strain WPP0163 (isolated in the USA), three strains isolated in Poland in the year 2014 (IFB5597, IFB5604, and IFB5619) and also one strain isolated in Belgium (IFB5485) (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Clade IB, on the other hand, encloses genomes of three strains isolated in Poland, two in the year 2013 (IFB5432, IFB5441) and one strain from 2014 (IFB5623). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The second clade (Clade II) consists of genomes of P. parmentieri CFBP 8475T, two strains isolated in 2013 (IFB5408, IFB5427), two in 2014 in Poland (IFB5605, IFB5626) and one strain isolated in Belgium (IFB5486). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, P. parmentieri SCC3193 being the model strain used for studying P. parmentieri molecular biology for many years (previously P. c. subsp. carotovorum SCC3193/P. wasabiae SCC3193 [40–42]) is distinctively separated from the clades mentioned above (has the highest number of unique genes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, strains constituting Clade II, share the highest quantity of accessory genes (on average 794) in contrast to strains grouped within Clade I, for which an average number of accessory genes is 645) (Fig. 3, Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The above-presented grouping corresponds with the ANI-based clustering as ANI Cluster I reflects Clade II, while ANI Cluster II is consistent with Clade IB (Additional file 1: Figure S1A).Fig. 3Phylogenetic tree constructed with the method blast all against all using protein sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The tree was rooted on P. wasabiae CFBP 3304. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The color codes: blue – strains isolated in 2013 (Poland), green – strains isolated in 2014 (Poland), brown – strains isolated in Belgium, pink – reference strains </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par28"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>In general, P. parmentieri strains did not group accordingly to geographical site of isolation (Fig. 3), which may suggest their high geographical mobility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>However, to fully understand the biogeographical pattern of genomic variation in P. parmentieri, a more significant number of strains from different regions should be sequenced and analyzed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par29"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The described phylogenetic pattern was further supported by inspection of the presence/absence of genes in the dispensable (accessory and unique) genome fraction (Additional file 1: Figure S1B), which also showed agreement with the groupings presented in the phylogenetic analysis of all protein sequences (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>We observe that all the strains from Clade II (Fig. 3) form a monophyletic group in Additional file 1: Figure S1B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, P. parmentieri SCC3193 (distinctively separated from other strains in the protein phylogenetic tree), in accessory genome fraction phylogenesis, is grouping with P. parmentieri WPP163 and IFB5597. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Functional annotation of the dispensable genome fraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par30"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>To describe the strain-specific genomic differences, which are usually represented within the dispensable pan-genome fraction, we performed: class of genes (COG) annotation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>It was done for every protein belonging to the dispensable pan-genome fraction to obtain results biased towards genes found in all the analyzed genomes (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>We successfully annotated 900 protein sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>A significant fraction of the proteins was attributed to cell wall and membranes biogenesis (130 genes) and replication and recombination (108 genes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>In particular, among these 108 genes, there were quite a few proteins related to MGE, such as transposases, integrases and also DNA repair proteins and the CRISPR-associated ones.Fig. 4COG classes annotation of the accessory pan-genome fraction </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par31"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Proteins related to transcription were also abundant (93 genes), such as LysR family transcriptional regulators, controlling numerous genes involved in virulence, metabolism, quorum sensing and motility [43], but also other regulators responsible for plasmid maintenance (Xre), initiation of expression of phage-related genes (Ogr/delta) or resistance to multiple antibiotics (MarR) [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Also, 26 proteins were found to be involved in carbohydrate transport and metabolism with the notable presence of pectate lyase, glucosidases, transporters or outer membrane porins (Additional file 2: Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Almost the same number of proteins (24) were attributed to intracellular trafficking, secretion, and vesicular transport, including conjugal transfer proteins, filamentous hemagglutinin, Flp/Tad pilus component, especially crucial for the establishment of virulence [45] in addition to transfer proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Moreover, 18 proteins were designated to inorganic ion transport and metabolism, and in this COG group, we found, among others, TonB-dependent siderophore receptors capable of binding siderophore-iron complexes with high specificity and carrying out active transport across the outer membrane [46]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par32"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Besides, we have discovered that a significant part of COG class K is related to phage-related transcription regulators and phage-related proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Prophages, as genetic elements, may account for a significant fraction of the bacterial genome and pass to the chromosome many genes in a single event of integration [47]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The variability within the pathogenome of P. parmentieri </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par33"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Genes encoding virulence factors, motility features, chemotaxis, secretion system and quorum sensing components were investigated to describe the possible genomic variation related to pathogenesis comprehensively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Focusing on PCWDE, we have assessed the presence of genes encoding: pectinases, polygalacturonases, cellulases, and proteases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>In more detail, genes encoding nine pectate lyases (pel1, pel2, pel3, pelA, pelL, pelW_1, pelW_2, pelX and putative pelC), and also three genes coding for pectin esterases (pemA, pemB, and rhgT) are noted in the core genome fraction (Additional file 2: Table S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par34"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, only one IFB5486 strain having sizeable chromosomal rearrangement (Fig. 1) did not possess the gene coding for a pectin lyase (pnl). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>However, even with the lack of pnl, this strain is still able to effectively destroy plant tissue components (Table 2) probably by producing all other well-known pectate lyases, pectate disaccharides hydrolases and/or pectinesterases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>These results are in agreement with the previously performed study on Dickeya dadantii 3937 where mutations in single genes related to pectinolytic activity did not influence the overall maceration ability [48]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par35"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Regarding other PCWDE, we found 4 genes encoding polygalacturonases: pehA_1, pehA_2, rhiE, and pehX, 3 genes encoding cellulases (celV, celS, bcsZ), and 6 genes coding for proteases (prtS, prtC, prlC, pepT, htpX_1, and pcp_1) in the P. parmentieri core genome fraction (Additional file 2: Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we confirmed the presence of a protease-encoding gene (prtB_2) in all the genomes except P. parmentieri SCC3193 strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Also, genes encoding proteins of type 1 and 2 secretion systems, important for export of proteases, cellulases and pectinases are present in the core genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par36"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Focusing on the genes related to oligogalacturonides degradation, we determined the occurrence of two genes encoding 2-dehydro-3-deoxygluconokinase: kdgK_1 and kdgK_2 in the core pan-genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Besides, genes coding for other essential enzymes involved in oligogalacturonide degradation, namely: kduD, two types of the kduI gene (kduI_2, kduI_1), kdgT, kdsC, kdsD, kdgM_3 and ogl were proven to be present in all the tested genomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par37"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Importantly, among the investigated 15 P. parmentieri genomes we discovered peculiar differences in the quantities and types of kdgT genes encoding a 2-keto-3-deoxygluconate permease and kdgM coding for oligogalacturonate-specific porin KdgM [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Two different paralogs of kdgT, i.e. kdgT and kdgT_1, were identified. kdgT is present in core genomes, while the paralogous copy kdgT_1 is absent in the genomic sequences of IFB5432, IFB5441, and IFB5623 strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>A dendrogram based on KdgT and KdgT_1 protein sequences, available in GenBank, showed branching out of KdgT_1 far away from the other KdgT orthologs originating from different Pectobacteriaceae spp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>(Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Moreover, KdgT_1 protein is more closely related to KdgT from Bacillus spp.Fig. 5The evolution of KdgT protein among the members of Pectobacteriaceae family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The tree was rotted on KdgT of Dickeya dadantii 3937 (Dda 3937) and Dickeya chrysanthemi NCPPB 516 (Ddh NCPPB 516). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Pcc – P. carotovorum subsp. carotovorum, Pcbr - P. carotovorum subsp. brasiliense, Pba – P. atrosepticum, P. c. actinidiae - P. carotovorum subsp. actinidiae </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par38"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Additionally, three paralogs of the kgdM gene were detected among the studied P. parmentieri genomes, where kgdM encodes oligogalacturonate-specific porin KdgM which expression is strongly induced by pectin derivatives [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Precisely, kdgM_3 is present among all the analyzed genomes, whereas kdgM_1 and kdgM_2 are observed among the analyzed genomes in different combinations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Usually, one strain possesses two paralogs of this gene (except for IFB5408, IFB5427, IFB5626 – these strains only have kdgM_3, while IFB5486 and IFB5605 have either kdgM_1 or kdgM_2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The herein reported gene duplication events might undergo a long-term selection pressure ressulting in P. parmentieri genome plasticity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Similar duplications were observed in the genomes of Escherichia coli [29]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par39"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>All the studied P. parmentieri genomes possess genes encoding AHL-dependent quorum sensing system and the components of type 4 and type 6 secretion systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In contrast, none of the tested genomes showed the presence of genes encoding the type 3 secretion system, which were usually detected in the Dickeya and Pectobacterium genomes [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>However, we did notice the presence of genes fliR and flhB coding for effector proteins of the type 3 secretion system in the core genome fraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>These results are in agreement with some earlier data showing the absence of type 3 secretion system in the genome of P. parmentieri, but revealing at the same time the presence of genes encoding its effector proteins [25, 51, 52]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par40"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Analysis of the presence of the structural genes within the genomes of P. parmentieri strains did not adequately explain differences in the abilities of the tested strains to degrade plant cell wall components. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>It can be hypothesized that the variation mentioned above might have resulted from differential regulation of expression of virulence-related genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>There have been some indications that regulatory data are more useful for the explanation of phenotypic differences than the pure genomic information [39, 53]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par41"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>However, all the tested genomes possess regulatory elements affecting the expression of the genes related to virulence: components of AHL-dependent quorum sensing system, 3 functional copies of kdgR (gene encoding a global negative regulator of pectin degradation), crp (encoding cAMP-activated global regulator), fur (coding for ferric iron uptake regulator), cheZ (encoding a chemotaxis regulator) and rcsF (coding for a stress response system protein) (Additional file 2: Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>It can be therefore concluded that future work should be directed towards a better understanding of the regulatory network controlling maceration abilities of different P. parmentieri strains. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par42"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, we cannot a priori exclude that random drift may be related to the lack of correlation between genomic differences and phenotypic differences, as observed in various host-associated microorganisms [54]; still, the number of sequenced genomes of P. parmentieri is too limited to draw a definitive conclusion on such hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par43"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we have analyzed the genes encoding proteins involved in LPS biosynthesis, motility, chemotaxis, iron uptake and utilization in addition to resistance to oxidative stress (Additional file 2: Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Several genes involved in LPS biosynthesis are present in the accessory pan-genome fraction, which correlated with the observed different degrees of pathogenicity-related traits of the P. parmentieri strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>In more detail, superb variation among the strains regarding motility and ability to form biofilm was presented (Table 2). For example, strain IFB5408 showed almost the same ability to form biofilm as P. aeruginosa PAO1, and also indicated the most efficient swimming motility (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Moreover, this strain possesses additional, strain-specific copies of genes encoding lipopolysaccharide ABC transporter substrate-binding protein LptA, LPS export ABC transporter periplasmic protein LptC, and also an additional copy of lipopolysaccharide ABC transporter ATP-binding protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par44"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The occurrence of two genes of possible eukaryotic origin, for example, plant ferredoxin-like protein and benzoic acid/salicylic acid carboxyl methyltransferase, was confirmed in all the tested genomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par45"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>In the previous studies, P. parmentieri SCC3193 was stated to harbour an arsenic resistance cluster [16] common among bacteria that possess it either on the chromosome or on the plasmid. [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>However, in the core pangenome of P. parmentieri, there was only one gene found encoding an arsenate reductase, namely arsC. The other members of the arsenic-resistant cluster were enclosed within the unique pan-genome fraction specific to P. parmentieri SCC3193 strain (Additional file 2: Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Notably, none of the arsC genes present in the P. parmentieri genomes analyzed here was located within any MGE as it was the case of P. parmentieri SCC3193 genome [16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The large mobilome of P. parmentieri </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par46"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>A high number of phage-related genes among the analyzed P. parmentieri strains was found, constituting especially the accessory and the unique pan-genome fraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Therefore, a comprehensive evaluation of unique pan-genome fraction content was subsequently performed. P. parmentieri SCC3193 strain has the highest number of unique genes, namely 346 genes (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Besides, six Polish strains possess an intermediate number of unique genes (from 112 to 177). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par47"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Regarding unique pan-genome fraction almost half of the genes codes for phage-like proteins (e.g. transposases, phage structural proteins) and several conjugation transfer proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>As a consequence of these findings, the presence of prophages was evaluated, and up to 4 intact prophages per strain were found (Table 4, Additional file 3: Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>These prophages harboured genes encoding different toxins (e.g. HigB, CcdB, and YafO), bacteriocins, and a few antitoxins genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>In general, the toxins mentioned above are either involved in the inhibition of the gene expression or blockage of the foreign DNA invasion into the bacterial cell.Table 4Presence of toxins, bacteriocins and antitoxins within phage regions of the analyzed P. parmentieri strainsStrainIntact prophagesGenes encoding toxins in phage regionsGenes encoding antitoxins in phage regionsHigBCcdBYafORelEBacteriocinsHigAYafNIFB54081––––C5E17_10830––IFB54274C5E18_11805–C5E18_11035––C5E18_08010–IFB54322C5E19_17230C5E19_17060–C5E19_17110–––IFB54413–C5E20_17730–––––IFB54850–––––––IFB54863C5E22_20550––––––IFB55971–––––––IFB56040–––––––IFB56054––C5E24_11080–C5E24_10885C5E24_08305–IFB56190–––––––IFB56232–––––––IFB56263–C5E26_17330––C5E00_05110C5E00_02270–CFBP 8475T1–––––A8F97_RS10330–SCC31930–––––––WPP01630––––––– </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par48"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>In more detail, HigB being a ribosome-dependent toxin preferentially cleaving mRNA at adenosine-rich codons is responsible for plasmid stability [56], and have been identified in the genomes of IFB5427, IFB5432 and IFB5486 strains (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>We have also found a putative antitoxin HigA present in prophage regions of the genomes of IFB5427, IFB5605, IFB5626 isolates in addition to CFBP8475T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>HigB and HigA are present in the genome of IFB5427. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>However, it is unlikely that they interact with one another because they do not fall under the regulation of the same operon (Additional file 4: Table S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par49"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The second most common toxin that is known to act on DNA gyrase [57] and is encoded by the F plasmid-carried gene, namely ccdB, was found in the genomes of IFB5432, IFB5441 and IFB5623. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Besides, a gene coding for YafO toxin, which is responsible for protein synthesis inhibition [58] was detected in the genomes of IFB5427 and IFB5605. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Another toxin RelE participating in growth arrest and cell death by inducing mRNA degradation at the ribosomal A-site under stress conditions [59] was encoded by the prophage regions of IFB5432 and IFB5623 sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Notably, genes coding for various bacteriocins were identified within the prophage hot spot regions’ of IFB5408, IFB5605 and IFB5626 genomes (Additional file 4: Table S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par50"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>It is worth to underline that only incomplete prophages were spotted in the genomes of IFB5485, IFB5604, IFB5619 and two reference genomes: SCC3193, WPP0163. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Accordingly to our findings and as it has been stated before [27] P. parmentieri strains are capable of acquiring efficiently large portions of extracellular DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, some additional copies of the toxins mentioned above were found outside of phage regions; for instance, the relE gene is present in each P. parmentieri genome in at least a triplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Besides, genomes of all the tested strains possess a colicin V coding gene (Additional file 4: Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The latter discovery is especially intriguing as the resulting protein is usually produced from large low-copy plasmids and inhibits translation during amino acid starvation [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>However, we only confirmed the presence of any plasmid in just one strain, namely P. parmentieri IFB5427. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Shedding light on phage infections </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par51"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>CRISPR-Cas systems provide adaptive immunity in prokaryotes and can be effective against phage infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>They are composed of CRISPR arrays consisting of short repeats separated by spacer sequences derived from invading nucleic acids in addition to the CRISPR-associated (Cas) genes [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Four loci of CRISPR arrays (specifically four loci of multiple spacers) were detected in each P. parmentieri genome, named here from CRISPR1 to CRISPR4 (Additional file 5: Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>After performing clustering based on nucleotide alignment of the extracted sequences, it turned out that almost all the P. parmentieri CRISPR are grouping into two separate clades: the first cluster includes two CRISPR repeats: CRISPR1 and CRISPR2 and the second one additional two: CRISPR3 and CRISPR4 (Additional file 6: Figure S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>The genomes of P. parmentieri CFBP 8475T (a strain isolated in France) and IFB5486 (strain originating from Belgium) also possess 4 CRISPR repeats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>However, their CRISPR sequences are specific and differ from the previously described CRISPR repeats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Notably, CRISPR1 and CRISPR2 group together, similarly to CRISPR3 and CRISPR4 forming also separate clades. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>We have found differences among quantities of each spacer related to specific CRISPR arrays ranging from 4 spacers up to 94 per one CRISPR array (Additional file 5: Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>It was proven before that when a bacterial cell is infected with a new phage, a piece of its foreign DNA can be integrated at the end of the CRISPR array as a new spacer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>This spacer can then target and destroy the invading DNA [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Therefore, CRISPR regions can reveal information on both phage sequences and order of infection they conducted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>However, we cannot be sure if there is always only one new spacer per phage, or if it is possible that more than one spacer is incorporated within the same infection event. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Undoubtedly, we can say that there were numerous phage infection events in the analyzed P. parmentieri strains. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>P. parmentieri plasmid pPAR01 - a possible source of additional genomic variation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par52"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>As mentioned before, IFB5427 strain harbours a pPAR01 plasmid of 101,998 bp with 125 CDS and GC content of 49.45%, which is approximately 1% lower than the GC content of all the analyzed P. parmentieri bacterial chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Among the encoded proteins IncFII (plasmid replication initiator protein), RepA (initiation replication protein essential for plasmid replication), ParM (plasmid segregation), relaxase TraJ (a conjugation system) and a conjugal transfer protein should be listed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Besides, we have found a gene coding for YafN antitoxin located on the pPAR01 plasmid, and a gene encoding YafO toxin on the chromosome of this strain within a ‘hot spot’, being an entire prophage region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>YafO is a toxin which inhibits protein synthesis and constitutes a type II toxin-antitoxin system, in which the YafN acts as an antitoxin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>However, we do not possess any evidence that this toxin-antitoxin pair complements each other. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par53"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>In addition to YafN, pPAR01 also comprises another putative antitoxin VapB; anyhow, we did not identify a toxin corresponding to this protein either on the plasmid or the chromosome of IFB5427. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Besides, pPAR01 plasmid harbours a toxin RelE, but again without any proper antitoxin gene on any genetic unit. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par54"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The here described pPAR01 plasmid retains other exciting features, which could be related to its possible transmissibility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>For instance, anti-restriction proteins ArdA and KlcA, which may allow for the associated MGE to evade the ubiquitous Type I DNA restriction systems in the recipient bacterium [62] resulting in the acquisition of cognate modification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Also, the presence of the gene coding for N6 DNA methylase suggests that maintaining this plasmid may affect histone methylation pattern within the host DNA to avoid further invasion by foreign nucleic acids [63]. pPAR01 also encodes proteins involved in SOS responses, such as the DNA adenine methyltransferase YhdJ essential for DNA repair, and DNA polymerase V subunit UmuC playing a role in replication under the stress responses [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, SOS inhibition proteins (PsiA and PsiB), which impede bacterial stress responses are also located on this plasmid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Given reported induction of bacterial SOS responses by conjugative DNA transfer, it can be speculated that the presence of genes coding for SOS inhibition proteins may increase plasmid transferability to the host cell [65]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par55"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, the obtained results show differences in the ability of P. parmentieri strains to macerate potato tubers tissue in addition to variation in their phenotypic traits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The observed high genomic plasticity can explain these features within P. parmentieri species expressed by a high number of MGE found both in the core and particularly in the dispensable pan-genome fraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The analysis of the genomes of 15 P. parmentieri strains indicated that the dispensable pan-genome fraction constitutes 47% of the whole pan-genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Also, the occurrence of prophage sequences and CRISPR-Cas system elements is abundant in the dispensable genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The widespread presence of MGE may have caused considerable genome rearrangements in addition to the gene loss, as it was noted in the case of lack of type 3 secretion system components. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Moreover, we can hypothesize that such high genomic variation among P. parmentieri strains could be the basis for the widespread presence of this species and its potential wide host range. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, our comparative genomic analysis of P. parmentieri highlights the contribution of plastic genomic structure to adaptive lifestyle and ability to survive and cause disease symptoms in different climatic zones. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Strains used in the study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par56"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>P. parmentieri strains used in this study are presented in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Ten of these strains originating from Poland have been partially described previously regarding their phenotypic features [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The additional two strains have been isolated in Belgium by Johan van Vaerenbergh (ILVO, Belgium) and are included in this type of analysis for the first time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Also, we have used P. parmentieri CFBP 8475T isolated in France, P. parmentieri SCC3193 isolated in Finland, and P. wasabiae CFBP 3304 as a closely related species and an outgroup for phylogenetic analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>For in silico analysis only, the P. parmentieri WPP163 isolated in the US was utilized. Pseudomonas aeruginosa PAO1 was used as a control in biofilm formation test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Phenotypic characterization of P. parmentieri strains </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par57"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The maceration ability of the selected P. parmentieri strains was evaluated by performing the potato slice assay as previously described [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Briefly, potatoes (cv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Lord) were surface sterilized, washed in tap water and cut into slices (approx. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>2 cm thick). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>In each slice, depending on size, two to three holes were pierced and then into each of them 45 μl of bacterial inoculum (107 cfu x ml− 1) was placed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Potatoes were incubated for 48 h at 28 °C on moistened linen within closed plastic boxes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, maceration spots diameters were measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The experiment was performed in three biological repetitions each including eight technical ones. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par58"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The activity of pectinases, cellulases, proteases, siderophores as well as swarming motility was performed as described before [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>To obtain consistent results and prevent undirected bacterial movement, swimming motility was evaluated on NB medium supplemented with 0.3% agar and also 0.4% PGA (Sigma-Aldrich, USA) [66]. The activity of lipases was tested on dedicated medium supplemented with Tween 80 and rhodamine B [67], where diameters of the clear halo zones appearing around the colonies were measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>The experiments were performed four times involving two technical replicates in each. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Incubations were performed for 24 h at 28 °C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par59"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Biofilm formation assay was performed as described by [45] with following modifications: 10 μl of overnight bacterial cultures in LB medium were transferred to Eppendorf tubes with 400 μl of M9 medium supplemented with 0.4% glucose (M9-C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>After 16 h of incubation at 18 °C without agitation, 70 μl of 1% (w/v) crystal violet solution was added to each tube and incubated at room temperature for 20 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Subsequent washing and OD565 measurement were performed as described by [45]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par60"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Statistical significance of differences noted in the phenotypic assays was analyzed with the use of the agricolae package from the R 3.3.1 programming environment [68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Leven’s test was implemented to verify whether the data variances were equal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Shapiro-Wilk test was used to check whether the data followed a normal distribution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>As the requirements of ANOVA were not always fulfilled, Kruskal-Wallis test with Bonferroni correction was applied for multiple comparisons (R agricolae package). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>All statistical hypotheses were tested at p &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>For testing the Pearson’s correlation Hmisc package with rcorr was utilized. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Genome sequencing, de novo assembly and annotation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par61"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>For shotgun genome sequencing, bacterial overnight cultures were grown on LA plates and subsequently sent to GATC Biotech, Konstanz, Germany. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>DNA was isolated, libraries have been constructed and then subjected to Illumina MiSeq or HiSeq2000 and Pacific BioSciences sequencing methods, to provide both proper coverages, and high-quality reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Illumina paired-end reads were trimmed with Trimmomatic [69] to remove adapter sequences and poorly sequenced read ends. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>De novo genome assembly was performed with the use of SPAdes [70]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>In the case of 2 genomes (i.e. of IFB5604 and IFB5619 strains), we could not achieve satisfactory assembly to the level of one scaffold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Therefore, MeDuSa: a multi-draft based scaffolder was applied [71] to close scaffolds to a full chromosome on the basis of reference genomes (acquired from NCBI) and also the genomes assembled by us to a single chromosome within this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Genome annotation was firstly achieved by utilizing Prokka v1.12 [72]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Afterwards, custom-made Python scripts were used to reorient genomes in order to make them start from the dnaA gene sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Finally, all reoriented genomic fasta outputs were submitted to the NCBI database, and the final annotation was performed by the NCBI Prokaryotic Genome Annotation Pipeline (PGAP, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genome/annotation_prok/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genome/annotation_prok/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>CRISPR spacers were found with the use of CRISPRFinder (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://crispr.i2bc.paris-saclay.fr/Server/">http://crispr.i2bc.paris-saclay.fr/Server/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Comparative genomic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par62"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Average Nucleotide Identity (ANI) was calculated for 15 P. parmentieri genomes applying ChunLab’s online Average Nucleotide Identity Calculator (EzBioCloud) [73] where P. parmentieri CFBP 8475T was used as an internal reference. Synteny was evaluated with the use of Mauve [74]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Phast [75] has been implemented for computational identification and visualization of prophages. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par63"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Gene ontology and the pan-genome shape of P. parmentieri strains were established using Roary [76] with the default settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>PGAP annotated sequences were used as an input. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Calculations of the Heap’s Law and construction of the phylogenetic tree (constructed by hierarchical clustering of gene families established by reciprocal all-against-all protein sequences BLAST) were performed using the micropan R package for microbial pan-genomics [34]. The Class of Genes (COG) annotation of every protein belonging to the accessory fraction was done with eggNOG 4.5 server [77]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Additional files </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec18"><p><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Additional file 1:Figure S1. Phylogenetic relatedness of the analyzed P. parmentieri strains: A. Genomic Average Nucleotide Identity (gANI) heatmap with dendrograms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Gene presence/absence matrix against core pan-genome generated dendrogram. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>The dendrogram was created basing on hierarchical clustering of the rows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>(PNG 1528 kb) Additional file 2:Table S1. Comprehensive analysis with locus_tag information on virulence genes, virulence-related genes, motility, chemotaxis, iron metabolism, resistance to oxidative stress, quorum sensing related genes and regulators within analyzed P. parmentieri strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Format: xlsx file. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>(XLSX 74 kb) Additional file 3:Figure S2. Synteny of intact prophages within the particular P. parmentieri strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>(PNG 1257 kb) Additional file 4:Table S2. Toxins and antitoxins genes encoded within the genomes of analyzed P. parmentieri strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Format: docx. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>(DOCX 16 kb) Additional file 5:Table S3. The number of CRISPR spacers found per each CRISPR array in the analyzed P. parmentieri strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>(DOCX 12 kb) Additional file 6:Figure S3. Clustering of CRISPR arrays from analyzed P. parmentieri strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Two clusters formed from CRISPR1-CRISPR2 and another two CRISPR3-CRISPR4 and two additional clusters formed only from CRISPR arrays from P. parmentieri CFBP 8475T and P. parmentieri IFB5486. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>(PNG 1227 kb) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ANI</term><def><p id="Par4">Average nucleotide identity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>COG</term><def><p id="Par5">Class of genes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HGT</term><def><p id="Par6">Horizontal gene transfer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MGE</term><def><p id="Par7">Mobile genetic elements</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCWDE</term><def><p id="Par8">Plant Cell Wall Degrading Enzymes</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>We would like to acknowledge Dr. Michał Kabza from Adam Mickiewicz University in Poznan for his guidance in NGS data analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>We want to thank Dr. George DiCenzo for critically revising the manuscript and Dr. Johan van Vaerenbergh (ILVO, Belgium) for the bacterial strains. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Availability of data and material</title><p id="Par64"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>GenBank BioProject: This Whole Genome Shotgun project has been deposited at DDBJ/ENA/GenBank under the BioProject PRJNA433470 and link: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/PRJNA433470">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/PRJNA433470</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p id="Par65"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>GenBank Accession This Whole Genome Shotgun project has been deposited at DDBJ/ENA/GenBank under the accessions nos.: CP026977, CP027260, CP026979, CP026980, CP026981, CP026982, PSZH00000000, CP026983, CP026984, CP026985, CP026986, PSZG00000000. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par66"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>This work was conceived and fulfilled during the realization of the project provided by the National Science Centre in Poland via grant no. 2014/14/M/NZ8/00501 awarded to EL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>The founding body did not take part in the design of the study, collection, analysis, and interpretation of data and in writing of the presented manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></ack></SecTag><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>SZ performed all analyses presented in work (phenotypic characterization and bioinformatics analysis) and wrote the manuscript. AMP and WS isolated strains from the environment, read the manuscript and gave comments. EL and AM conceived the work and critically revised the final version of the manuscript. All Authors read and approved the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>Not applicable. The <italic>P. parmentieri</italic> strains analyzed in this study are environmental isolates, that were obtained by the authors. Any other reference strains were bought or received from befriended laboratories/researchers or bought from commercial bacterial banks (<italic>P. parmentieri</italic> CFBP8475 was bought from CIRM-Plant Associated Bacteria / CIRM-CFBP).</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable, no humans were the object of the presented study.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher’s Note</title><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>1.GuimarãesLCFlorczak-WyspianskaJde JesusLBVianaMVCSilvaARamosRTJInside the Pan-genome - methods and software overviewCurr Genomics20151624525210.2174/1389202916666150423002311<?supplied-pmid 27006628?>27006628 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>2.VernikosGMediniDRileyDRTettelinHTen years of pan-genome analysesCurr Opin Microbiol20152314815410.1016/j.mib.2014.11.016<?supplied-pmid 25483351?>25483351 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>3.HackerJCarnielEEcological fitness, genomic islands and bacterial pathogenicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>A Darwinian view of the evolution of microbesEMBO Rep2001237638110.1093/embo-reports/kve097<?supplied-pmid 11375927?>11375927 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>4.SalanoubatMGeninSArtiguenaveFGouzyJMangenotSArlatMGenome sequence of the plant pathogen Ralstonia solanacearumNature200241549750210.1038/415497a11823852 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>5.XueQ-YYinY-NYangWHeuerHPriorPGuoJ-HGenetic diversity of Ralstonia solanacearum strains from China assessed by PCR-based fingerprints to unravel host plant- and site-dependent distribution patternsFEMS Microbiol Ecol20117550751910.1111/j.1574-6941.2010.01026.x<?supplied-pmid 21204873?>21204873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>6.Guarischi-SousaRPuigvertMCollNSSiriMIPianzzolaMJVallsMComplete genome sequence of the potato pathogen Ralstonia solanacearum UY031Stand Genomic Sci201611710.1186/s40793-016-0131-4<?supplied-pmid 26779304?>26779304 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>7.Elphinstone J, Allen C, Prior P, Hayward A. Bacterial Wilt Disease and the Ralstonia solanacearum Species Complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>American Phytopathological Society; 2005. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://my.apsnet.org/ItemDetail?iProductCode=43291">https://my.apsnet.org/ItemDetail?iProductCode=43291</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>8.RemenantBCoupat-GoutalandBGuidotACellierGWickerEAllenCGenomes of three tomato pathogens within the Ralstonia solanacearum species complex reveal significant evolutionary divergenceBMC Genomics20101137910.1186/1471-2164-11-379<?supplied-pmid 20550686?>20550686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>9.BocsanczyAMHuguet-TapiaJCNormanDJComparative genomics of Ralstonia solanacearum identifies candidate genes associated with cool virulenceFront Plant Sci20178156510.3389/fpls.2017.01565<?supplied-pmid 28955357?>28955357 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>10.AilloudFLoweTCellierGRocheDAllenCPriorPComparative genomic analysis of Ralstonia solanacearum reveals candidate genes for host specificityBMC Genomics20151627010.1186/s12864-015-1474-8<?supplied-pmid 25888333?>25888333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>11.GuidotACoupatBFallSPriorPBertollaFHorizontal gene transfer between Ralstonia solanacearum strains detected by comparative genomic hybridization on microarraysISME J2009354956210.1038/ismej.2009.14<?supplied-pmid 19242532?>19242532 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>12.AdeoluMSeemaANaushadSGuptaRSGenome-based phylogeny and taxonomy of the ‘Enterobacteriales’: proposal for Enterobacterales Ord. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Nov. divided into the families Enterobacteriaceae, Erwiniaceae fam. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Nov., Pectobacteriaceae fam. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Nov., Yersiniaceae fam. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Nov., Hafniaceae fam. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Nov., MorganeInt J Syst Evol Microbiol2016665575559910.1099/ijsem.0.001485<?supplied-pmid 27620848?>27620848 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>13.MotykaAgataZoledowskaSabinaSledzWojciechLojkowskaEwaMolecular methods as tools to control plant diseases caused by Dickeya and Pectobacterium spp: A minireviewNew Biotechnology20173918118910.1016/j.nbt.2017.08.01028847714 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>14.MaBHibbingMEKimH-SReedyRMYedidiaIBreuerJJJHost range and molecular phylogenies of the soft rot enterobacterial genera Pectobacterium and DickeyaPhytopathology2007971150116310.1094/PHYTO-97-9-1150<?supplied-pmid 18944180?>18944180 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>15.WaleronKWaleronMPodhajskaAJŁojkowskaEGenotyping of bacteria belonging to the former Erwinia genus by PCR-RFLP analysis of a recA gene fragmentMicrobiology200214858359510.1099/00221287-148-2-583<?supplied-pmid 11832521?>11832521 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>16.NykyriJNiemiOKoskinenPNokso-KoivistoJPasanenMBrobergMRevised phylogeny and novel horizontally acquired virulence determinants of the model soft rot phytopathogen Pectobacterium wasabiae SCC3193PLoS Pathog20128e100301310.1371/journal.ppat.1003013<?supplied-pmid 23133391?>23133391 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>17.KhayiSCignaJChongTMQuêtu-LaurentAChanK-GHéliasVTransfer of the potato plant isolates of Pectobacterium wasabiae to Pectobacterium parmentieri sp. novInt J Syst Evol Microbiol2016665379538310.1099/ijsem.0.001524<?supplied-pmid 27692046?>27692046 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>18.WaleronMWaleronKLojkowskaECharacterization of Pectobacterium carotovorum subsp. odoriferum causing soft rot of stored vegetablesEur J Plant Pathol201413945746910.1007/s10658-014-0403-z </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>19.SuárezM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>B.FeriaF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>J.Martín-RoblesM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>J.del ReyF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>J.PalomoJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>L.Pectobacterium parmentieri Causing Soft Rot on Potato Tubers in Southern EuropePlant Disease201710161029102910.1094/PDIS-01-17-0013-PDN </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>20.NabhanSDe BoerSHMaissEWydraKTaxonomic relatedness between Pectobacterium carotovorum subsp. carotovorum, Pectobacterium carotovorum subsp. odoriferum and Pectobacterium carotovorum subsp. brasiliense subsp. novJ Appl Microbiol201211390491310.1111/j.1365-2672.2012.05383.x<?supplied-pmid 22747943?>22747943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>21.ZoledowskaSMotykaAZukowskaDSledzWLojkowskaEPopulation structure and biodiversity of Pectobacterium parmentieri isolated from potato fields in temperate climatePlant Dis201810215416410.1094/PDIS-05-17-0761-RE </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>22.De BoerSHLiXWardLJPectobacterium spp associated with bacterial stem rot syndrome of potato in CanadaPhytopathology201210293794710.1094/PHYTO-04-12-0083-R<?supplied-pmid 22713077?>22713077 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>23.MolelekiLNOnkendiEMMongaeAKubhekaGCCharacterisation of Pectobacterium wasabiae causing blackleg and soft rot diseases in South AfricaEur J Plant Pathol201313527928810.1007/s10658-012-0084-4 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>24.NgadzeEBradyCLCoutinhoTAvan der WaalsJEPectinolytic bacteria associated with potato soft rot and blackleg in South Africa and ZimbabweEur J Plant Pathol201213453354910.1007/s10658-012-0036-z </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>25.PitmanARHarrowSAVisnovskySBGenetic characterisation of Pectobacterium wasabiae causing soft rot disease of potato in New ZealandEur J Plant Pathol201012642343510.1007/s10658-009-9551-y </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>26.GolkhandanE.SijamK.MeonS.AhmadZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>M.NasehiA.NazerianE.First Report of Pectobacterium wasabiae Causing Soft Rot of Cabbage in MalaysiaPlant Disease20139781110111010.1094/PDIS-01-13-0112-PDN </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>27.KhayiSRaoul des EssartsYQuetu-LaurentAMoumniMHeliasVFaureDGenomic overview of the phytopathogen Pectobacterium wasabiae strain RNS 08.42.1A suggests horizontal acquisition of quorum-sensing genesGenetica201514324125210.1007/s10709-014-9793-2<?supplied-pmid 25297844?>25297844 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>28.DeesMWLebeckaRPerminowJISCzajkowskiRGrupaAMotykaACharacterization of Dickeya and Pectobacterium strains obtained from diseased potato plants in different climatic conditions of Norway and PolandEur J Plant Pathol201714811310.1007/s10658-016-1140-2 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>29.RaesideCGaffeJDeatherageDETenaillonOBriskaAMPtashkinRNLarge Chromosomal Rearrangements during a Long-Term Evolution Experiment with Escherichia coliMBio20145e0137714-e01377–1410.1128/mBio.01377-14<?supplied-pmid 25205090?>25205090 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>30.NiemiOLainePKoskinenPPasanenMPennanenVHarjunpääHGenome sequence of the model plant pathogen Pectobacterium carotovorum SCC1Stand Genomic Sci2017128710.1186/s40793-017-0301-z<?supplied-pmid 29276572?>29276572 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>31.KhayiSBlinPChongTMChanK-GFaureDComplete chromosome and plasmid sequences of two plant pathogens, Dickeya solani strains D s0432-1 and PPO 9019Genome Announc.20186e00233e0021810.1128/genomeA.00233-18<?supplied-pmid 29700139?>29700139 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>32.ZhaoYTianYLiXHuBComplete genome sequence of a Dickeya fangzhongdai type strain causing bleeding canker of pear tree trunksGenome Announc20186e00177e0011810.1128/genomeA.00177-18<?supplied-pmid 29773614?>29773614 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>33.TettelinHRileyDCattutoCMediniDComparative genomics: the bacterial pan-genomeCurr Opin Microbiol20081147247710.1016/j.mib.2008.09.00619086349 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>34.SnipenLLilandKHMicropan: an R-package for microbial pan-genomicsBMC Bioinformatics2015167910.1186/s12859-015-0517-0<?supplied-pmid 25888166?>25888166 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>35.UdaondoZMolinaLSeguraADuqueERamosJLAnalysis of the core genome and pangenome of Pseudomonas putidaEnviron Microbiol2016183268328310.1111/1462-2920.13015<?supplied-pmid 26261031?>26261031 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>36.López-PérezMRodriguez-ValeraFPangenome evolution in the marine bacterium AlteromonasGenome Biol Evol201681556157010.1093/gbe/evw098<?supplied-pmid 27189983?>27189983 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>37.Nourdin-GalindoGSánchezPMolinaCFEspinoza-RojasDAOliverCRuizPComparative Pan-genome analysis of Piscirickettsia salmonis reveals genomic divergences within GenogroupsFront Cell Infect Microbiol2017745910.3389/fcimb.2017.00459<?supplied-pmid 29164068?>29164068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>38.BosiEFondiMOrlandiniVPerrinEMaidaIde PascaleDThe pangenome of (Antarctic) Pseudoalteromonas bacteria: evolutionary and functional insightsBMC Genomics2017189310.1186/s12864-016-3382-y<?supplied-pmid 28095778?>28095778 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>39.GolanowskaMKabzaMBacciGMengoniAPotrykusMMotykaAComparison of highly and weakly virulent Dickeya solani strains, with a view on the pangenome and panregulon of this speciesFront Microbiol20189194010.3389/FMICB.2018.01940<?supplied-pmid 30233505?>30233505 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>40.FlegoDPirhonenMSaarilahtiHPalvaTKPalvaETControl of virulence gene expression by plant calcium in the phytopathogen Erwinia carotovoraMol Microbiol19972583183810.1111/j.1365-2958.1997.mmi501.x<?supplied-pmid 9364909?>9364909 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>41.ErikssonARBAnderssonRAPirhonenMPalvaETTwo-component regulators involved in the global control of virulence in Erwinia carotovora subsp. carotovoraMol Plant-Microbe Interact19981174375210.1094/MPMI.1998.11.8.743<?supplied-pmid 9675890?>9675890 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>42.AnderssonRAErikssonARBHeikinheimoRMäeAPirhonenMKõivVQuorum sensing in the plant pathogen Erwinia carotovora subsp. carotovora : the role of expREccMol Plant-Microbe Interact20001338439310.1094/MPMI.2000.13.4.384<?supplied-pmid 10755301?>10755301 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>43.MaddocksSEOystonPCFStructure and function of the LysR-type transcriptional regulator (LTTR) family proteinsMicrobiology2008154Pt 123609362310.1099/mic.0.2008/022772-019047729 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>44.AlekshunMNLevySBThe mar regulon: multiple resistance to antibiotics and other toxic chemicalsTrends Microbiol1999741041310.1016/S0966-842X(99)01589-9<?supplied-pmid 10498949?>10498949 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>45.NykyriJMattinenLNiemiOAdhikariSKõivVSomervuoPRole and regulation of the Flp/tad pilus in the virulence of Pectobacterium atrosepticum SCRI1043 and Pectobacterium wasabiae SCC3193PLoS One20138e7371810.1371/journal.pone.0073718<?supplied-pmid 24040039?>24040039 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>46.ChimentoDPKadnerRJWienerMCThe Escherichia coli outer membrane cobalamin transporter BtuB: structural analysis of calcium and substrate binding, and identification of orthologous transporters by sequence/structure conservationJ Mol Biol2003332999101410.1016/j.jmb.2003.07.005<?supplied-pmid 14499604?>14499604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>47.OliveiraPHTouchonMCuryJRochaEPCCThe chromosomal organization of horizontal gene transfer in bacteriaNat Commun2017884110.1038/s41467-017-00808-w<?supplied-pmid 29018197?>29018197 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>48.LojkowskaEDorelCReignaultPHugouvieux-Cotte-PattatNRobert-BaudouyJUse of GUS fusion to study the expression of Erwinia chrysanthemi pectinase genes during infection of potato tubersMol Plant-Microbe Interact1993648849410.1094/MPMI-6-488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>49.BlotNBerrierCHugouvieux-Cotte-PattatNGhaziACondemineGThe oligogalacturonate-specific porin KdgM of Erwinia chrysanthemi belongs to a new porin familyJ Biol Chem20022777936794410.1074/jbc.M109193200<?supplied-pmid 11773048?>11773048 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>50.CharkowskiABlancoCCondemineGExpertDFranzaTHayesCThe role of secretion systems and small molecules in soft-rot Enterobacteriaceae pathogenicityAnnu Rev Phytopathol20125042544910.1146/annurev-phyto-081211-173013<?supplied-pmid 22702350?>22702350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>51.KimH-SHSBingMPernaNTCharkowskiAOMaBPernaNTPhylogeny and virulence of naturally occurring type III secretion system-deficient Pectobacterium strainsAppl Environ Microbiol2009754539454910.1128/AEM.01336-08<?supplied-pmid 19411432?>19411432 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>52.Panda P, Vanga BR, Lu A, Fiers M, Fineran PC, Butler R, et al. Pectobacterium atrosepticum and Pectobacterium carotovorum harbor distinct, independently acquired integrative and conjugative elements encoding coronafacic acid that enhance virulence on potato stems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Front Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>2016;7 MAR:397. doi:10.3389/fmicb.2016.00397. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>53.PotrykusMGolanowskaMHugouvieux-Cotte-PattatNLojkowskaERegulators involved in Dickeya solani virulence, genetic conservation, and functional variabilityMol Plant-Microbe Interact20142770071110.1094/MPMI-09-13-0270-R<?supplied-pmid 24625032?>24625032 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>54.SheppardSKGuttmanDSFitzgeraldJRPopulation genomics of bacterial host adaptationNat Rev Genet20181911710.1038/s41576-018-0032-z </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>55.StolzJFBasuPSantiniJMOremlandRSArsenic and selenium in microbial metabolismAnnu Rev Microbiol20066010713010.1146/annurev.micro.60.080805.142053<?supplied-pmid 16704340?>16704340 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>56.SchureckMARepackAMilesSJMarquezJDunhamCMMechanism of endonuclease cleavage by the HigB toxinNucleic Acids Res2016447944795310.1093/nar/gkw598<?supplied-pmid 27378776?>27378776 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>57.BahassiEMO’DeaMHAllaliNMessensJGellertMCouturierMInteractions of CcdB with DNA gyraseJ Biol Chem1999274109361094410.1074/jbc.274.16.10936<?supplied-pmid 10196173?>10196173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>58.ZhangYYamaguchiYInouyeMCharacterization of YafO, an Escherichia coli toxinJ Biol Chem2009284255222553110.1074/jbc.M109.036624<?supplied-pmid 19617347?>19617347 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>59.LiG-YZhangYInouyeMIkuraMInhibitory mechanism of Escherichia coli RelE-RelB toxin-antitoxin module involves a helix displacement near an mRNA interferase active siteJ Biol Chem2009284146281463610.1074/jbc.M809656200<?supplied-pmid 19297318?>19297318 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>60.FrickKKQuackenbushRLKoniskyJCloning of immunity and structural genes for colicin VJ Bacteriol1981148498507<?supplied-pmid 6271732?>6271732 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>61.BrounsS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>J.JoreM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>M.LundgrenM.WestraE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>R.SlijkhuisR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>H.SnijdersA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>L.DickmanM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>J.MakarovaK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>S.KooninE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>V.van der OostJ.Small CRISPR RNAs Guide Antiviral Defense in ProkaryotesScience2008321589196096410.1126/science.115968918703739 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>62.ChenKReuterMSanghviBRobertsGACooperLPTillingMArdA proteins from different mobile genetic elements can bind to the EcoKI type I DNA methyltransferase of E. coli K12Biochim Biophys Acta - Proteins Proteomics2014184450551110.1016/j.bbapap.2013.12.008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>63.LowDAWeyandNJMahanMJRoles of DNA adenine methylation in regulating bacterial gene expression and virulenceInfect Immun2001697197720410.1128/IAI.69.12.7197-7204.2001<?supplied-pmid 11705888?>11705888 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>64.KubanWVaismanAMcDonaldJPKarataKYangWGoodmanMFEscherichia coli UmuC active site mutants: effects on translesion DNA synthesis, mutagenesis and cell survivalDNA Repair (Amst)20121172673210.1016/j.dnarep.2012.06.00522784977 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>65.BaharogluZBikardDMazelDConjugative DNA transfer induces the bacterial SOS response and promotes antibiotic resistance development through integron activationPLoS Genet2010611010.1371/journal.pgen.1001165 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>66.BowdenSDHaleNChungJCSHodgkinsonJTSpringDRWelchMSurface swarming motility by Pectobacterium atrosepticum is a latent phenotype that requires O antigen and is regulated by quorum sensingMicrobiology2013159Pt 112375238510.1099/mic.0.070748-0<?supplied-pmid 24025601?>24025601 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>67.SamadMYARazakCNASallehABZin Wan YunusWMAmponKBasriMA plate assay for primary screening of lipase activityJ Microbiol Methods19899515610.1016/0167-7012(89)90030-4 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>68.R Core TeamR: A language and environment for statistical computing2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>69.BolgerAMLohseMUsadelBTrimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence dataBioinformatics2014302114212010.1093/bioinformatics/btu170<?supplied-pmid 24695404?>24695404 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>70.BankevichANurkSAntipovDGurevichAADvorkinMKulikovASSPAdes: a new genome assembly algorithm and its applications to single-cell sequencingJ Comput Biol20121945547710.1089/cmb.2012.0021<?supplied-pmid 3342519?>22506599 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>71.BosiEDonatiBGalardiniMBrunettiSSagotM-FLióPMeDuSa: a multi-draft based scaffolderBioinformatics2015312443245110.1093/bioinformatics/btv171<?supplied-pmid 25810435?>25810435 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>72.SeemannTProkka: rapid prokaryotic genome annotationBioinformatics2014302068206910.1093/bioinformatics/btu153<?supplied-pmid 24642063?>24642063 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>73.YoonSHHaSMKwonSLimJKimYSeoHIntroducing EzBioCloud: a taxonomically united database of 16S rRNA gene sequences and whole-genome assembliesInt J Syst Evol Microbiol2017671613161710.1099/ijsem.0.001755<?supplied-pmid 5563544?>28005526 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>74.DarlingACEMauve: multiple alignment of conserved genomic sequence with rearrangementsGenome Res2004141394140310.1101/gr.2289704<?supplied-pmid 15231754?>15231754 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>75.ZhouYLiangYLynchKHDennisJJWishartDSPHAST: a fast phage search toolNucleic Acids Res201139supplW347W35210.1093/nar/gkr485<?supplied-pmid 21672955?>21672955 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>76.PageAJCumminsCAHuntMWongVKReuterSHoldenMTGRoary: rapid large-scale prokaryote pan genome analysisBioinformatics2015313691369310.1093/bioinformatics/btv421<?supplied-pmid 26198102?>26198102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>77.Huerta-CepasJSzklarczykDForslundKCookHHellerDWalterMCeggNOG 4.5: a hierarchical orthology framework with improved functional annotations for eukaryotic, prokaryotic and viral sequencesNucleic Acids Res201644D286D29310.1093/nar/gkv124826582926 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
