<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Occup Med Toxicol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Occup Med Toxicol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Occupational Medicine and Toxicology (London, England)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1745-6673</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6480838</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">232</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12995-019-0232-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Examining a novel firefighter exercise training program on simulated fire ground test performance, cardiorespiratory endurance, and strength: a pilot investigation </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6350-8210</contrib-id><name><surname>Hollerbach</surname><given-names>Brittany S.</given-names></name><address><email>bhollerb@ksu.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jahnke</surname><given-names>Sara A.</given-names></name><address><email>sara@hopehri.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Poston</surname><given-names>Walker S. C.</given-names></name><address><email>carlosposton@hopehri.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Harms</surname><given-names>Craig A.</given-names></name><address><email>caharms@k-state.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>Katie M.</given-names></name><address><email>kmhphd@ksu.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0737 1259</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.36567.31</institution-id><institution>Department of Kinesiology, </institution><institution>Kansas State University, </institution></institution-wrap>Natatorium 8, 920 Denison Ave., Manhattan, Kansas, 66506 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0442 0766</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.276773.0</institution-id><institution>Center for Fire, Rescue, and EMS Health Research, National Development &amp; Research Institutes, </institution></institution-wrap>1920 143rd Street, Suite 120, Leawood, KS 66224-7813 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>12</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Firefighting is a dangerous occupation with high rates of injuries and fatalities, with the majority of line of duty fatalities due to cardiovascular events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Additionally, firefighters struggle with poor health/low levels of fitness, including high (&gt; 80%) rates of overweight and obesity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Limited resources exist for fire departments that are tailored to the culture and work requirements of these “tactical athletes”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Though there has been increasing interest in high intensity functional training (HIFT) programs, research data are lacking among firefighters and few studies have focused on training recruits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The purpose of this pilot investigation was to examine a novel HIFT program (TF20) on fire academy recruits’ health, fitness, and performance as determined by a simulated fire ground test (SFGT), as well as determining the program’s acceptability and feasibility. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par2"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Thirteen participants were recruited from an entry level fire academy and were randomly assigned to the control (CG, n = 6) or HIFT group (TF20, n = 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The CG was asked to continue current exercise habits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>TF20 was provided a 10-week online based training program that included periodized workouts, nutritional information, and mental readiness education. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Due to attrition within the first two weeks of the study, 10 male fire recruits (23 ± 3 years) completed the study (CG, n = 3, TF20, n = 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>All 10 participants completed baseline and follow-up assessments. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par3"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The TF20 group showed improvement on numerous outcome measures including SFGT (40% passing at baseline, 86% passing post-intervention). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>TF20 participants significantly increased estimated VO2max (p = 0.028), improved body composition (p = 0.028), and improved grip strength (p = 0.018). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The CG did not experience any significant changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The TF20 group completed approximately 75% of the assigned workouts. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par4"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>While TF20 participants showed significant fitness gains, the small sample size limited direct comparisons to the CG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>TF20 was well-received although there may be a better way to implement the intervention to increase participation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>This investigation provides promising outcomes, useful information about implementation, feasibility, and acceptability for the TF20 HIFT program among firefighter recruits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>IRB #8063 APPROVED 01/04/2016. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Trial registration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT03319394">NCT03319394</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Registered 28 September 2014. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Retrospectively registered. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Firefighter</kwd><kwd>Health</kwd><kwd>Occupational health</kwd><kwd>Fitness</kwd><kwd>HIFT</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Arts, Humanities, and Social Sciences (AHSS) Small Grant Program through Kansas State University</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par36"><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Firefighting is a strenuous and physically demanding occupation [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Firefighters (FFs) work in dangerous and complex environments, which increases their risk for injuries and fatalities [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In addition to the dangerous nature of the job, FFs struggle with poor health and low levels of physical fitness, including very high (&gt; 80%) rates of overweight and obesity (body mass index [BMI] ≥ 25.0 kg/m2), likely related to the culture of the fire service [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Many firefighters experience significant weight gain over the course of an approximate 25-year career, with a range of 29–85 pounds gained (i.e., 1.15–3.4 lbs./year; 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>As a firefighter’s weight increases, their cardiorespiratory fitness plummets and their risk of cardiovascular disease (CVD) increases [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Comorbidities related to overweight and obesity include heart disease, stroke, type 2 diabetes and certain types of cancer which are highly prevalent among the firefighter population [3, 5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par37"><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>It is well documented that physical fitness is related to job performance, including the performance of simulated firefighting tasks that are relevant to actual job tasks (e.g., pulling hose, carrying a ladder, and rescuing a victim; 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Firefighting presents a unique challenge for physical fitness training because it requires concurrently improving multiple fitness training goals [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Firefighting requires optimal levels of power, strength, muscular endurance, and anaerobic/aerobic endurance [6, 7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Inadequate fitness levels may reduce the occupational performance and increase the risk of overexertion injuries for firefighters [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, increased physical fitness is related to lower levels of injury/illness, reduced absenteeism, increased productivity, and increased work capacity for firefighters [6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par38"><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Limited resources exist for fire departments that are tailored to the culture and work requirements of these tactical athletes [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>There has been increasing interest in high-intensity functional training (HIFT) programs among tactical populations, yet key research data are lacking for the firefighter population [6, 8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The National Fire Protection Association (NFPA) has several standards that focus on the health risks of firefighters (e.g., NFPA 1500, NFPA 1582, and NFPA 1583; [9–12]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>While these guidelines exist, there are no nationally-enforced fitness or physical activity requirements for firefighters, which leads to inconsistent fitness training within and between fire departments, substandard fitness levels, and greater risks for obesity, injury, and cardiovascular-related events [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>For example, only 38.7% of career and 23.6% of volunteer firefighters meet the fitness threshold suggested as a minimal return to work post cardiac event by NFPA 1582 which includes a VO2max of at least 42 ml/kg/min [9, 11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par39"><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The NFPA recommends firefighters be allowed to exercise on duty to maintain adequate fitness levels [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>While Poplin et al. (2012) found that on-duty physical exercise was responsible for one-third of all firefighter injuries (32.9%), most of these injuries tended to be minor strains/sprains [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>It is still recommended that firefighters be encouraged to exercise while on duty. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Studies have shown that firefighters who engaged in regular physical training were less likely to incur a serious injury on the fireground [14, 15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, firefighters who train regularly and possess higher fitness levels tend to perform job-specific tasks more efficiently than untrained firefighters, emphasizing the importance of implementing an exercise program for firefighters [7, 13, 16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Thus, there is a need for cost-effective training programs targeted at the unique needs and culture of the fire service as a means of improving readiness, decreasing injury, and preventing line of duty deaths (LODD) related to CVD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par40"><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Fire academies provide instruction for new firefighters and should instill the importance of physical fitness training as recruits begin a physically demanding career in the fire service [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>However, current fire academies across the U.S. do little to address physical fitness other than the physical skills taught during fire training [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The applied coursework requires much time spent on the drill ground learning basic firefighter skills, e.g., donning personal protective equipment such as bunker gear and self-contained breathing apparatus (SCBA), navigating through dark search quarters, searching and removing a victim, climbing ladders, and fighting live fire. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Firefighter recruits also are typically required to take the Candidate Physical Ability Test (CPAT), or an equivalent occupational fire ground test during the Fire Academy, which they must pass to be considered for employment in most fire departments across the country [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>These tests are physically demanding and require high fitness levels. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par41"><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The purpose of this pilot investigation was to assess the acceptability, feasibility, and relevant fitness and occupational performance outcomes of an innovative firefighter HIFT program, The First Twenty Tactical High Performance Program (TF20) with firefighter recruits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>This is the first investigation to examine TF20 among firefighter recruits and significantly adds to the existing literature regarding firefighter fitness training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that the intervention group (TF20) would have greater improvements in performance, fitness, and health outcomes, as described below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par42"><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The aims of this pilot study were to examine the acceptability, feasibility, and fitness and occupational performance outcomes among firefighter recruits after a 10-week randomized trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The institutional review board (IRB) of Kansas State University (KSU) approved the study (IRB #8063). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>All participants provided written consent prior to initiation of their involvement in research. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par43"><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>We solicited study volunteers by visiting a midwestern fire academy that is hosted by a community college fire science degree program with permission from the Fire Academy Program Director. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Participants (N = 13; 92.3% male) reported they were in good health and without physical limitations that prevented them from completing any of the required TF20 workouts and fitness assessments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par44"><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Participants were individually randomly assigned to either the intervention (TF20) or comparison group (CG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Microsoft Excel was used to generate the random allocation sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Both groups completed baseline assessments, 10-weeks of either the TF20 or CG, and follow-up assessments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par45"><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Because recruits also were students in the community college degree program, passing the CPAT prior to entry into the fire academy was not required. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The fire academy provided instruction to prepare recruits to take state tests for firefighter certification, but they were not professional firefighters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Figure 1 shows participant randomization and progress through the study (TF20 = 7 and control [CG] = 6).Fig. 1Randomization of Eligible Participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Legend: TF20 = The First Twenty intervention; CG = comparison group </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Intervention </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par46"><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>TF20 is an innovative online training program developed by firefighters specifically for firefighters that provides foundational educational principles around physical fitness, mental wellness, and nutrition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Using a holistic approach combined with empirical evidence [19–21] TF20 is a comprehensive program that addresses firefighters’ unique physiological challenges by simulating tasks performed on the fire ground. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Specifically, the program’s goals are to optimize a firefighter’s occupational performance, resilience to injury, stability, mobility, strength, and endurance through a series of high intensity circuits, focused on both resistance and endurance exercises. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>TF20 online platform allows participants to apply and track these principles on a daily basis and record their progress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The portal includes private account settings, health programs, fitness tracking with exercise and workout videos, nutrition tracking, health education, results tracking, and communication and social media tools. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par47"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>TF20 Intervention Group (TF20) workouts were part of an online training program that provided endurance and resistance exercises, nutritional information, and mental performance guidance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The original program was a 24-week periodized program which was condensed into a 10-week exercise program to accommodate the time frame of the study and fire academy academic semester. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>A National Strength and Conditioning Association (NSCA) Certified Strength and Conditioning Specialist (CSCS) and Tactical Strength and Conditioning Facilitator (TSAC-F) condensed the program but kept the periodization scheme consistent to mimic the longer cycle of workouts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The workouts are summarized in Table 1.Table 1The first twenty (TF20) study periodization cycleWeekMesocycleExercise descriptionTime/duration (days/week, d/wk)11Resistance Training2 d/wk2Moderate-Intensity Cardiovascular Training2 d/wk. in 20 min. bouts32Resistance Training2 d/wk4Moderate-Intensity Cardiovascular Training2 d/wk. in 30 min. bouts5Walk with SCBA1 d/wk. for 20 min.63Resistance Training2 d/wk7Moderate Cardio2 d/wk. in 45 min. bouts8Vigorous Cardio (stair climb w/SCBA)1 d/wk. for 14 min94Resistance Training2–3 d/wkModerate Intensity Cardio1 d/wk. in 60 min boutsVigorous Cardio (walk w/SCBA)1 d/wk. in 20–30 min bouts10Active Recovery </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par48"><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Workouts contained a combination of aerobic (e.g., running, rowing, jumping), body weight (e.g., air squats, pushups, sit-ups), and weight lifting (e.g., presses, back squats, weighted lunges) exercises with workouts designed to use equipment available in an exercise facility (e.g., weight racks, benches) or in a fire station/on the fire ground (e.g., equipment carry, dummy drag, etc.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Sixty-minute TF20 sessions included a warm-up, workout, and cool down. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>All completed workouts were logged in TF20 software program, which was used to assess intervention adherence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par49"><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The comparison group (CG; i.e.: control group) followed their regular workout routine for 10 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Participants chose the time, duration, frequency, and type of workouts completed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>For the study, participants were asked to log all exercise/workouts online using Google Sheets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par50"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Both the TF20 and CG met weekly with a firefighter fitness trainer with current CPR and First Aid certifications (Firefighter/EMT, CPR/First Aid, TSAC-F certified). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Weekly meetings ensured education on proper movements used in TF20 program, and discussion of proper movement progressions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Both groups were reminded to log their workouts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Any questions the participants had were also discussed during the meetings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Procedures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par51"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The research team enrolled participants during the first week of their 16-week fire academy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The research team generated the random allocation and assigned participants to intervention groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Baseline testing occurred during the second week of the fire academy, the intervention took place the next 10 weeks and the follow-up assessments were completed within the following two weeks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par52"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>As an incentive to participants, this study took the place of the one credit hour physical fitness course requirement for the fire academy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>This one credit hour course was offered through the local community college and allowed participants to access the community college gym. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The class was not associated with the fire academy nor was it instructor-led; it solely provided access to a gym. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The fire academy in this study did not have a structured exercise (fitness training) component. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Measures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par53"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>During the initial (baseline) and final 10-week (follow-up) of the study, participants’ health, fitness, and performance were assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>A Seca stadiometer (Chino, CA) was used to assess height. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The Tanita TBF-300A digital bioelectrical impedance analysis (BIA) scale (Arlington Heights, IL) was used to assess body composition including percent body fat (%BF), fat mass (FM in kg), fat-free mass (i.e., muscle mass; FFM in kg), body mass index (BMI in kg/m2), and weight (to the nearest 0.1 kg). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Research has shown that BIA correlates well (r &gt; 0.8) with the gold-standard measure dual X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA) analysis for body composition [22]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par54"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Maximal aerobic capacity (VO2max) was estimated from the linear relationship between heart rate (HR) and work rate during a submaximal graded exercise test using a StairMaster StepMill 7000PT [23, 24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>A standardized protocol recommended for firefighters by the Joint Labor Management Wellness Fitness Initiative (WFI) was used [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>This test is recommended for firefighters because, unlike other submaximal graded exercise tests, this one requires the participant to exercise to maximal volitional fatigue, similar to completing a physically exhausting task on the fireground [23, 24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Additionally, studies using this test and prediction equation demonstrated accuracy and validity, with no false positives or negatives [24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par55"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Upper body muscular strength (grip strength; GS) was assessed with the Takei 5401 Hand Grip Dynamometer (Digital; Niigata City, Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>A hand grip dynamometer is a valid and reliable measure (p &lt; 0.05) and is a strong correlate (r &gt; 0.9994) with upper body muscular strength [25, 26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Participants’ dominant hand was noted; GS was recorded three times for both hands in an alternating fashion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The best of three attempts was recorded for each hand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>GS was examined alone (unadjusted) and in relation to the participant’s body weight (adjusted). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par56"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Upper body muscular endurance was assessed with a 2-min timed push-up (PU) test [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The PU test required participants to touch their chin to the mat at the bottom of each repetition, and the score was the number of continuous repetitions completed [27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par57"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Muscular power was assessed with a counter-movement jump (Jump, Sunnyvale, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The best of three jumps was recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Participants’ standing reach height was subtracted from their maximal jump height, so their total vertical displacement was recorded to the nearest cm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par58"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Core strength was assessed with a cadence curl-up test [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Two strips of masking tape were placed 12 cm apart. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Participants lay supine across the tape with knees bent 90°. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>A metronome was set at 40 beats/min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>At each beep the participant curled their body upwards so as to move their hands to the second tape line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Repetitions were counted each time the participant reached the bottom position. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The test was concluded either when the participant completed 75 curl-ups or the cadence was broken [27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par59"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Agility was assessed with a timed agility T test [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>This assessment required participants to move in a T-shaped pattern requiring lateral and front-to-back movements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The agility test was recorded in seconds to completion. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par60"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Trunk flexibility was assessed using a standardized sit-and-reach box (Canadian Trunk Forward Flexion test; 27). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par61"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>A simulated fire ground test (SFGT), the Candidate Physical Ability Test (CPAT) was used to measure occupational performance, fitness, and agility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The CPAT provides a traditional frame of reference to evaluate increases or decreases in physical fitness and occupational readiness and provides a firefighter-specific assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The CPAT consists of eight separate events that require the participant to progress along a predetermined path from event to event in a continuous manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>It is a pass/fail test based on finishing all events in a maximum total test time of 10 min and 20 s or less. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Participants were provided with a familiarization session prior to taking the CPAT for the first time as is suggested by the IAFF/IAFC [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Participants were able to familiarize themselves with the equipment at each event but did not take the entire test during the familiarization period. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par62"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>In all eight events (i.e., Stair Climb, Hose Drag, Equipment Carry, Ladder Raise and Extension, Forcible Entry, Search, Dummy Drag, and Ceiling Breach and Pull), candidates wore a 50-pound (22.68-kg) vest to simulate the weight of self-contained breathing apparatus (SCBA) and firefighter protective clothing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>An additional 25 pounds (11.34 kg), using two 12.5-pound (5.67-kg) shoulder weights that simulated a high-rise pack (hose bundle), was added for the stair climb event. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Throughout all events, candidates wore long pants, a hard hat with chin strap, work gloves and footwear with no open heel or toe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Watches and loose or restrictive jewelry were not permitted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>All props were designed to simulate critical fire ground tasks and test the candidate’s physical ability [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Participants’ heart rate and blood pressure were taken immediately (within two minutes) following completion of the CPAT. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par63"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>A questionnaire was completed at baseline and follow-up and included standard demographics (baseline only), health behaviors, current exercise habits, and current nutritional habits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Physical activity was measured using the modified International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) short form, which provided a global, physical activity self-rating during the last 30 days [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Participants were asked to indicate the amount of moderate and vigorous aerobic activity and strength training completed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>From this, researchers created a dichotomous variable for meeting/not meeting the physical activity guidelines for the previous 30 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Participants were also asked if they followed any current diet/meal plans and if their diet had changed in the previous 12 weeks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par64"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>A feasibility analysis was completed to examine participant adherence, their reactions to the intervention, and suggestions for future physical exercise training for the Fire Academy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par65"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Microsoft Excel and SPSS Version 21 (Armonk, NY) were used for statistical analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Means, standard deviations, and proportions were calculated for all variables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>However, the small sample size and uneven groups precluded the use of typical parametric between-groups comparisons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>In order to examine outcomes of all participants initially recruited in the study, we used an Intention to Treat (ITT) Model carrying forward the baseline observations for those that did not have post-test values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>This allowed us to examine all participants, assuming no change for those that did not complete the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The Mann-Whitney U Test was used to examine differences between the two groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Within-group changes over time for both groups were examined for the completers using the Wilcoxon Signed Rank Test to compare repeated measures (pre- and post-intervention) for each group separately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The Wilcoxon converts scores to ranks and compares them at Time 1 (pre-) and Time 2 (post-) [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Statistical significance was set at p &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par66"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Written responses to questionnaires (baseline and follow-up) were analyzed qualitatively by coding and analyzing recurrent themes, areas of consensus and convergence of opinions, experiences, and perceptions about the wellness program using a grounded theory approach [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Data were then coded by identifying passages exemplifying key concepts or ideas related to the major themes using NVivo 10 (QSR International, 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>A feasibility analysis also was completed to examine the relevance of offering this intervention in a fire academy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Adherence to the prescribed workouts for TF20 group and their feedback to the intervention were examined in a follow-up questionnaire. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par67"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Thirteen participants consented to study participation (TF20: n = 7, 100% male, 22.6 ± 2.9 years; CG: n = 6, 83% male, 23.5 ± 3.6 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Participant demographic characteristics are presented in Table 2. The Mann-Whitney U test revealed there were no significant differences at baseline between the two groups with respect to demographic factors or on pre-intervention fitness measures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Ten male fire service recruits (aged 19–27 years) completed the study, including baseline and follow-up assessments and 10 weeks of either the TF20 intervention or self-guided exercise (TF20 n = 7, CG n = 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Overall, the participants were less physically active than expected at baseline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Of the nine (6 TF20, 3 CG) that filled out a baseline questionnaire regarding current exercise behavior (over the past 30 days), 44% of TF20 group (n = 4) and 67% of the CG (n = 2) met either moderate or vigorous aerobic PAG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Only four (all in TF20 group) met the current physical activity guidelines (aerobic and muscle-strengthening).Table 2Participant demographics at baseline (N = 13)VariableCGTF20DifferenceAge (years)23.522.6−0.9Gender (%Male)83.0100.0+ 17.0Weight (kg)72.490.0+ 17.6aBMI (kg/m2)23.929.2+ 5.3VO2max (ml/kg/min)42.338.5−3.8aBody Mass Index: underweight (&gt; 18.5); normal weight (18.5–24.9); overweight (25–29.9) and obese (≥30) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Dropouts </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par68"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>One participant (CG) dropped out of the Fire Academy only two weeks into data collection and was therefore ineligible to complete the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>One participant (CG) dropped out of the study due to time constraints during the 10-week intervention and another participant (CG) completed the 10 weeks of self-directed workouts but was unable to complete follow-up testing due to diabetes-related medical complications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>All three of the subjects who dropped out of the study were assigned to the CG, accounting for the subsequent uneven group distribution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Between group differences on fitness measures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par69"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Using the ITT model, we compared differences between groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The Mann-Whitney U test revealed the two groups differed significantly in two measures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The TF20 group had significantly greater improvements in grip strength and the CG had significantly greater reductions in BMI after 10 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>All results and significance values are presented in Table 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>No participants reported any injuries during the 10-week study.Table 3Fitness and performance changes for both groups using intention to treat analysisVariableMean Change (M ± SD)TF20 (n = 7) CG (n = 6)Within Groups ComparisonaTF20 CGBetween Groups ComparisonbWeight (kg)−0.39 ± 2.9− 0.55 ± 1.01.0000.1090.153% Fat −2.09 ± 1.1 − 1.52 ± 1.7 0.018* 0.1090.063Fat Mass (FM, kg) −1.93 ± 1.2 − 1.42 ± 1.7 0.018* 0.1090.053Lean Mass (FFM, kg) 5.19 ± 4.0 0.87 ± 1.7 0.028* 0.1090.199BMI (kg/m2) −0.03 ± 0.9  − 0.37 ± 0.4 0.9330.109 0.046 Ɨ Grip Strength (adj.) 0.08 ± 0.06 0.03 ± 0.05 0.018* 0.109 0.038 Ɨ Sit &amp; Reach (cm)2.96 ± 3.01.21 ± 3.40.0630.5930.086Vertical Jump (cm)−1.02 ± 2.7−0.85 ± 3.50.6840.6551.000Push-Ups4.43 ± 11.00.67 ± 2.10.2490.4140.830Curl-Ups6.86 ± 22.010.5 ± 16.20.1760.1800.315Agility (sec) −0.57 ± 0.6 0.04 ± 0.1 0.028* 0.1800.775VO2max (ml/kg/min) 2.47 ± 1.1 1.99 ± 2.2 0.028* 0.1090.685%FAT % body fat, BMI Body Mass Index, VO2max estimated VO2max*Statistically significant (p ≤ 0.05) within group change. ƗStatistically significant (p ≤ 0.05) difference between groups. aMann-Whitney U. bWilcoxon Signed RankAll entried in boldface are statistically significant (p &gt; 0.05); this is noted in the table notes </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Within group changes on fitness measures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par70"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>All variables were examined from pre- to post-intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>For within-groups comparisons, we used the ITT model with baseline observations carried forward for those without follow-up scores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The Wilcoxon Signed Rank Test revealed no significant changes within the CG (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>In TF20 group, the Wilcoxon Signed Rank test revealed statistically significant within-group improvements in body fat percentage, fat mass (kg), lean mass (kg), grip strength, agility time, and estimated VO2max from baseline to follow-up (see Table 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par71"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>McNemar’s Test revealed that neither group showed statistically significant differences in CPAT pass rates from pre- to post-intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The average pass rate for CG at baseline was 60% and remained 60% post-intervention under the ITT assumption of no change. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The average pass rate for TF20 group at baseline was 40% and improved to 86% after the intervention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The individual pass/fail rates and times for the CPAT are listed in Table 4.Table 4Candidate Physical Ability Test Pass/Fail Scores and Times at Baseline and PosttestParticipantBaselinePosttestPass/FailTimePass/FailTimeCG-1P8:57P8:21CG-2P8:13P7:46CG-3P9:39P8:31CG-4F2:15aF2:15aCG-5––––CG-6F21:58F21:58TF20–1P10:04P9:07TF20–2F11:54F2:34aTF20–3P8:36P8:19TF20–4F11:01P9:33TF20–5––P9:20TF20–6––P7:36TF20–7F12:32P10:20P Pass (i.e., completed in 10:20 or less), F Fail, indicates the participant did not complete this measure. aParticipant chose not to complete the entire CPAT course after failing on the first event </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par72"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Though the CPAT is a timed test with a time limit of 10 min and 20 s, we encouraged the participants to go through the entire course and recorded their overall time to completion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>This permitted us to observe improvements in time to completion, even if the candidate did not improve from a failing to a passing time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>We did have one participant who, though he had a failing time, completed the test at baseline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>However, at post-intervention testing, the candidate chose not to complete the entire CPAT course after failing on the first event. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Two participants were unable to take the CPAT test at baseline due to scheduling conflicts; their post-intervention scores are listed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Feasibility analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par73"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>To examine the strengths and weaknesses of TF20 intervention, a feasibility analysis was conducted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Participants were asked about adherence, if they found the workouts challenging, any issues they faced, and suggestions for future exercise interventions offered at the Fire Academy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>TF20 participants completed on average 75% of the assigned workouts, accounting for all workouts participants completed, including those the online system did not log. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Participants noted experiencing difficulties logging into the application (app) on their mobile device. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>They reported that sometimes the app would correctly reflect that they had completed and logged a workout but at other times the system did not save their progress after they logged out of the application. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par74"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Participants also noted it was difficult to maintain a workout regimen during the intense 12-credit hour Fire Academy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Although the exercise program was designed to be flexible so participants could complete workouts virtually anywhere, numerous participants noted they had a difficult time completing the workouts without access to a gym or fire station. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Multiple participants noted that having a structured exercise program with a trained individual to lead them through workouts may be more beneficial than participants trying to work out on their own. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par75"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The purpose of this pilot investigation was to assess performance outcomes, acceptability, and feasibility of an innovative firefighter fitness and wellness program (TF20) on firefighter recruits’ health, fitness, and performance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that TF20 participants would demonstrate greater improvements in fire ground performance, body composition, and strength than the CG participants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>This pilot study examined the program’s performance and acceptability in “real world conditions” to determine if TF20 training program was relevant for firefighter recruits as they progressed through a fire academy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par76"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>It is interesting to note that prior to participation in the training program, all firefighter recruits in this study demonstrated aerobic capacity levels below that which is deemed essential for safe and effective fire ground operations [29, 33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Previous reports have stated that the most demanding firefighter tasks, which also were the most commonly encountered, demanded a mean VO2 of 41.5 ml/kg/min (range of 36.6–44.0 ml/kg/min) [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The WFI recommends maximal oxygen uptake of at least 42 ml/kg/min to meet the aerobic demands of the job [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Prior to training, fire recruits in this study possessed an estimated average VO2max of 38.9 ml/kg/min (CG mean = 39.8 ml/kg/min, TF20 mean = 38.5 ml/kg/min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>After the 10-week intervention the CG had a mean estimated VO2max of 43.8 ml/kg/min and TF20 had a mean estimated VO2max of 41.1 ml/kg/min. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par77"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The American College of Sports Medicine (ACSM) classifies VO2max values between 38.0–41.0 ml/kg/min in the “poor” range for males between the ages of 20–29 years [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>In line with previous firefighter research, individuals with decreased comprehensive fitness levels (i.e., VO2max) are at an increased risk of injury, clearly showing a need to better prepare all firefighters for the physical demands of firefighting [9, 15, 27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Our study findings also support the current literature that suggests the general public is not as fit as they should be, thereby effectively lessening those qualified for physically demanding jobs such as firefighting and other tactical occupations (e.g., military and police). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par78"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>At baseline, 67% of the CG and 80% of TF20 group reported meeting moderate/vigorous PAG [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>At the end of the 10-week study, all nine of the participants that took the follow-up questionnaire (TF20 = 6, CG = 3) reported meeting or exceeding the aerobic portion of the PAG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Four TF20 participants met the full PAG at baseline and at follow-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>These findings may be due, in part, to the physically demanding nature of the Fire Academy (e.g., climbing ladders, navigating through dark search quarters). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Fire ground activities may increase aerobic activity so the nature of the Fire Academy itself, may be the reason for the increase in reporting meeting aerobic guidelines. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par79"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The CPAT was used as a critical occupational performance measure since it (or an equivalent test) is required for employment by most fire departments across the country. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>TF20 participants showed marked improvement on their CPAT performance, even with a small sample size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>It is possible that improvement on the CPAT was due to familiarization with fire ground-related tasks in the fire academy and not the intervention itself; the only two participants who failed the test at baseline and passed at post-intervention were in TF20 group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>However, occupationally-relevant physical agility tests are related to several fitness and body composition parameters [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Thus, recruits may learn the basic firefighter skills while in an academy, yet lack the physical fitness to pass the CPAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>This shows the importance of implementing a culture of fitness early in a firefighter’s career. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>If fitness programs can be implemented at the fire academy level, physical fitness training can become habitual for young firefighters. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par80"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Results from this study show promise for utilizing TF20 as part of a fire academy-specific training program to begin instilling the importance of a fit fire service at the start of their careers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Findings from this and other fitness intervention studies [6, 35, 36] support the development and implementation of physical training programs for firefighters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Future research should examine TF20 program in a larger population to determine if it significantly impacts the fitness and performance of firefighter recruits as well as career and volunteer firefighters. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Limitations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par81"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>This study was designed primarily as a pilot study, with the goals of testing the feasibility of implementing the intervention, carrying out the assessment protocol, and deriving parameter estimates from the primary outcomes and attrition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Given the pilot nature of this study, there are several limitations that should be noted including the small initial sample size (n = 13). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The fire academy from which we recruited only had a very small initial group from which we could recruit (n = 24), thus limiting our starting sample size. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par82"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Second, because this was a pilot study with minimal funding, we were limited in the amount of contact we could provide participants and were unable to offer any incentives, unlike other exercise studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>This resulted in a third study limitation, which was high and differential attrition in the CG (50%) vs. TF20 group (0%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>This high CG attrition and the small initial sample led to an even smaller post-treatment sample size for the completers’ analysis (and further limited power to detect group differences in outcomes), as well as negatively impacting our ability to address missing data using common imputation methods for ITT analysis as suggested in the CONSORT Guidelines for clinical trials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par83"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Another limitation was equipment availability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>For example, because the site of data collection was two hours away from our laboratory, we were unable to complete maximal aerobic capacity tests for each participant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Instead, based on recommendations from the WFI, we used a StepMill submaximal graded exercise test to estimate VO2max. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Though there are errors associated with submaximal exercise tests, a recent review article found that submaximal step tests provide a simple, effective, and valid method of submaximally assessing VO2max [37]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par84"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>While weighted vests required for use in the CPAT do not elicit the same physiologic burden as firefighting in full turnout gear, the weighted vest, as well as the other equipment used in the CPAT, were designed to provide the highest level of consistency, safety, and validity in measuring each participant’s physical ability and occupational readiness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>In addition, they represent the recommended “gold standard” set by the IAFF/IAFC WFI for recruit firefighter fitness testing [24, 29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Load carriage decreases exercise tolerance, capacity, and efficiency, although the shape (i.e., a weighted vest vs. protective clothing) and the placement of the load do have an impact on physical performance [38, 39]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par85"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Additionally, a longer intervention (&gt; 10 weeks) may be beneficial as the current 10-week intervention did not show as many improvements as some 16-week interventions [1, 36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>However, fitness improvements were found for military personnel after only 8-weeks of trainer-led circuit-based training [8], which was a suggestion from our study participants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par86"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>This study is the first to systematically document the effects of TF20 and is one of few to examine firefighter recruits specifically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>This investigation provides promising results for the feasibility, acceptability, and potential efficacy of high-intensity training programs designed for the fire service. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>It also provides useful information that will aid in the design and implementation of a larger randomized controlled trial and provides alternative guidance for exercise prescription specifically for firefighters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Further investigation is necessary with a larger sample population to examine different types of physical training and its effects on the firefighter population, specifically firefighter recruits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Future studies should also examine the impact of load carriage on firefighter performance and examine the difference between weighted vests and full firefighter turnout gear on physiologic performance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ACSM</term><def><p id="Par5">American College of Sports Medicine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BF%</term><def><p id="Par6">Body Fat Percentage</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BIA</term><def><p id="Par7">Bioelectrical Impedance Analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BMI</term><def><p id="Par8">Body Mass Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CDC</term><def><p id="Par9">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CG</term><def><p id="Par10">Control Group</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CPAT</term><def><p id="Par11">Candidate Physical Ability Test</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CPR</term><def><p id="Par12">Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CSCS</term><def><p id="Par13">Certified Strength and Conditioning Specialist</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CVD</term><def><p id="Par14">Cardiovascular Disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DEXA</term><def><p id="Par15">Dual X-ray absorptiometry analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EMT</term><def><p id="Par16">Emergency Medical Technician</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FFM</term><def><p id="Par17">Fat-free Mass</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FM</term><def><p id="Par18">Fat Mass</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GS</term><def><p id="Par19">Grip Strength</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IAFC</term><def><p id="Par20">International Association of Fire Chiefs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IAFF</term><def><p id="Par21">International Association of Firefighters</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IPAQ</term><def><p id="Par22">International Physical Activity Questionnaire</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IRB</term><def><p id="Par23">Institutional Review Board</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KSU</term><def><p id="Par24">Kansas State University</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LODD</term><def><p id="Par25">Line of Duty Death</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NFPA</term><def><p id="Par26">National Fire Protection Association</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PAG</term><def><p id="Par27">Physical Activity Guidelines</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PU</term><def><p id="Par28">Push-ups</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SCBA</term><def><p id="Par29">Self-contained Breathing Apparatus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SFGT</term><def><p id="Par30">Simulated Fire Ground Test</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TF20</term><def><p id="Par31">The First Twenty Tactical High Performance Program</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TSAC-F</term><def><p id="Par32">Tactical Strength and Conditioning Facilitator</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>USDHHS</term><def><p id="Par33">US Department of Health and Human Services</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VO<sub>2max</sub></term><def><p id="Par34">Maximal aerobic capacity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WFI</term><def><p id="Par35">Wellness Fitness Initiative</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><sec id="FPar1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="Par87"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The authors wish to acknowledge the following groups/individuals for exceptional work on this project and the subsequent manuscript: </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p id="Par88"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Kanas State University Functional Intensity Training Laboratory (FIT LAB).The First Twenty crew (especially Dave Wurtzel).Johnson County Community College Fire Academy Program Chair (retired) &amp; Chief (retired) Richard Lehmann.All those that assisted with data collection. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par93"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>This project was funded through the Arts, Humanities, and Social Sciences (AHSS) Small Grant Program through Kansas State University. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec><sec id="FPar3" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par94"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></ack></SecTag><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>BH designed the study, recruited participants, carried out data collection, analyzed and interpreted participant data, and was a major contributor in writing the manuscript. SJ assisted with study design, program management, data collection and was a major contributor in writing the manuscript. WP assisted in data collection and analysis and was a major contributor in writing and editing the manuscript. CH made substantial contributions to conception and study design and assisted in writing and editing the manuscript. KMH assisted in study design and project development, aided in data collection and was a major contributor in writing and editing the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar4"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>The Kansas State University Institutional Review Board (IRB) approved this study (IRB #8063 APPROVED 01/04/2016); all participants provided written informed consent prior to participation.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors report no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar7"><title>Publisher’s Note</title><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>1.Abel MG, Sell K, Dennison K. Design and implementation of fitness program for firefighters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Strength Cond J. 2011:31–42. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>2.Haynes HJG, Molis JL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>U.S. firefighter injuries: 2016: National Fire Protection Association Fire Analysis and Research Division; 2017. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>3.PostonWSHaddockCKJahnkeSAJitnarinNTuleyBCKalesSNThe prevalence of overweight, obesity, and substandard fitness in a population-based firefighter cohortJ Occup Environ Med201153326627310.1097/JOM.0b013e31820af36221386691 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>4.Durand G, Tsismenakis AJ, Jahnke SA, Baur DM, Christophi CA, Kales SA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Firefighters physical activity: relation to fitness and cardiovascular disease risk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Med Sci Sports Exerc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>2011. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>10.1249/MSS.0b013e318215cf25. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>5.Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>(2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Adult obesity facts. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/obesity/data/adult.html">http://www.cdc.gov/obesity/data/adult.html</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Accessed 8 Oct 2018. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>6.AbelMGMortaraAJPettittRWEvaluation of circuit-training intensity for firefightersJ Strength Cond Res.201125102895290110.1519/JSC.0b013e31820da00c21873900 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>7.Dennison KJ, Mullineaux DR, Yates JW, Abel MG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>The effect of fatigue and training status on firefighter performance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>J Strength Cond Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>2012:1101–9. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>8.HeinrichKMSpencerVFehlNPostonWCSMission essential fitness: comparison of functional circuit training to traditional army physical training for active duty militaryMil Med2012177101125113010.7205/MILMED-D-12-0014323113436 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>9.Haddock CK, Poston WSC, Jahnke SA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Addressing the epidemic of obesity in the United States fire service: a report prepared for the national volunteer fire council. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>2011. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/ab9f/fb57c9c3e451c438d6b330a72bd4fa3b6576.pdf">https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/ab9f/fb57c9c3e451c438d6b330a72bd4fa3b6576.pdf</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Accessed 10 Nov 2018. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>10.National Fire Protection Association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>2018. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>NFPA 1500: standard on fire department occupational safety, health, and wellness program [data file]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nfpa.org/codes-and-standards/all-codes-and-standards/list-of-codes-and-standards/detail?code=1500">http://www.nfpa.org/codes-and-standards/all-codes-and-standards/list-of-codes-and-standards/detail?code=1500</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Accessed 10 Oct 2018. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>11.National Fire Protection Association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>2018. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>NFPA 1582: standard on comprehensive occupational medical program for fire departments [data file]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nfpa.org/codes-and-standards/all-codes-and-standards/list-of-codes-and-standards/detail?code=1582">http://www.nfpa.org/codes-and-standards/all-codes-and-standards/list-of-codes-and-standards/detail?code=1582</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Accessed 10 Oct 2018. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>12.National Fire Protection Association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>2015. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>NFPA 1583: standard on health-related fitness programs for fire department members [data file]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nfpa.org/codes-and-standards/all-codes-and-standards/list-of-codes-and-standards/detail?code=1583">http://www.nfpa.org/codes-and-standards/all-codes-and-standards/list-of-codes-and-standards/detail?code=1583</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Accessed 10 Oct 2018. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>13.PoplinGSHarrisRBPollackKMPeateWFBurgessJLBeyond the fireground: injuries in the fire serviceInj Prev201218422823310.1136/injuryprev-2011-04014922117024 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>14.JahnkeSAPostonWSCHaddockCKJitnarinNInjury among a population based sample of career firefighters in the Central USAInjury prevention201319639339810.1136/injuryprev-2012-04066223504995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>15.PoplinGSRoeDJBurgessJLPeateWFHarrisRBFire fit: assessing comprehensive fitness and injury risk in the fire serviceInt Arch Occup Environ Health201689225125910.1007/s00420-015-1068-426126735 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>16.Michaelides MA, Parpa KM, Henry LJ, Thompson GB, Brown BS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Assessment of physical fitness aspects and their relationship to firefighters' job abilities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>J Strength Cond Res 2011;25(4), 956–965. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>17.Williams-BellFKapralosMHogueBMurphyAWeckmanEUsing serious games and virtual simulation for training in the fire service: a reviewFire Technol201551355358410.1007/s10694-014-0398-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>18.Johnson County Community College. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>(2018). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Course Descriptions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jccc.edu/academics/credit/fire-science/index.html">http://www.jccc.edu/academics/credit/fire-science/index.html</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Accessed 30 Dec 2018. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>19.SoteriadesESSmithDLTsismenakisAJBaurDMKalesSNCardiovascular disease in US firefighters: a systematic reviewCardiol Rev201119420221510.1097/CRD.0b013e318215c10521646874 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>20.National Fallen Firefighters Foundation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>2014. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Confronting suicide in the fire service: strategies for intervention and prevention. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://thefirsttwenty.org/downloads/Confronting_Suicide.pdf">http://thefirsttwenty.org/downloads/Confronting_Suicide.pdf</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Accessed 10 Oct 2018. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>21.StaleyJAWeinerBLinnanLFirefighter fitness, coronary heart disease, and sudden cardiac death riskAm J Health Behav201135560361710.5993/AJHB.35.5.922040621 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>22.BolanowskiMNilssonBEAssessment of human body composition using dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry and bioelectrical impedance analysisMed Sci Monit20017510291033<?supplied-pmid 11535954?>11535954 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>23.International Association of Firefighters (IAFF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>The fire service joint labor management wellness-fitness initiative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>2008. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iaff.org/hs/wfiresource/default.html">http://www.iaff.org/hs/wfiresource/default.html</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Accessed 20 Dec 2018. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>24.Tierney MT1, Lenar D, Stanforth PR, Craig JN, Farrar RP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Prediction of aerobic capacity in firefighters using submaximal treadmill and Stairmill protocols. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>J Strength Cond Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>2010 Mar;24(3):75. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>25.HamiltonGFMcDonaldCChenierTCMeasurement of grip strength: validity and reliability of the sphygmomanometer and Jamar grip dynamometerJ Orthop Sports Phys Ther199216521521910.2519/jospt.1992.16.5.21518796752 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>26.MathiowetzVComparison of Rolyan and Jamar dynamometers for measuring grip strengthOccup Ther Int20029320120910.1002/oti.16512374997 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>27.American College of Sports MedicineACSM’s guidelines for exercise testing and prescription, ninth edition2014Baltimore, MDWolters Kluwer Health </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>28.BaechleTREarleRWEssentials of strength training and conditioning2008Champaign, ILHuman Kinetics395396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>29.International Association of Firefighters (IAFF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>The fire service joint labor management wellness-fitness initiative candidate physical ability test, 2nd edition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>2007. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.iafc.org/topics-and-tools/safety-health/wellness-fitness-task-force/candidate-physical-ability-test">https://www.iafc.org/topics-and-tools/safety-health/wellness-fitness-task-force/candidate-physical-ability-test</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Accessed 15 Jan 2018. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>30.MaddisonRMhurchuCNJiangYVander HoornSRodgersALawesCMRushEInternational physical activity questionnaire (IPAQ) and New Zealand physical activity questionnaire (NZPAQ): a doubly labelled water validationInt J Behav Nutr Phys Act2007416210.1186/1479-5868-4-6218053188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>31.PallantJSPSS survival manual: a step by step guide to data analysis using SPSS for windows (version 12)20052AustraliaAllen &amp; Unwin </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>32.PattonMQualitative research and evaluation methods2002Thousand Oaks, CASAGE </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>33.Gledhill N, Jamnik V. Characterization of the physical demands of firefighting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Can J Sport Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>1992:207–13. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>34.U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Department of Health and Human ServicesPhysical activity guidelines advisory committee2008Washington, DCPhysical Activity Guidelines Advisory Committee Report </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>35.JahnkeSAHyderMLHaddockCKJitnarinNDayRSPostonWSCHigh-intensity fitness training among a national sample of male career firefightersSaf Health Work20156717410.1016/j.shaw.2014.12.00525830073 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>36.RobertsMAO'DeaJBoyceAMannixEFitness levels of firefighter recruits before and after a supervised exercise training programJ Strength Cond Res2002162271277<?supplied-pmid 11991781?>11991781 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>37.Bennett, H., Parfitt, G., Davison, K., &amp; Eston, R. (2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Validity of submaximal step tests to estimate maximal oxygen uptake in healthy adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>46(5), 737–750. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>38.Knapik, J., Reynolds, K., Santee, W. R., &amp; Friedl, K. E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>(2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Load carriage in military operations: a review of historical, physiological, biomechanical and medical aspects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Military Quantitative Physiology: Problems and Concepts in Military Operational Medicine Office of the Surgeon General and the Borden Institute, Ft Detrick, MD, 303–37. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>39.SmithDLFehlingPCHultquistEMLeffertsWKBarrDAStorerTWCooperCBFirefighter's personal protective equipment and the chronotropic indexErgonomics201255101243125110.1080/00140139.2012.70369622849757 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
