<p id="P2">Studies of children with recurrent invasive pneumococcal infection have led to
the discovery of two primary immunodeficiencies (PIDs), caused by autosomal recessive
mutations in <italic>IRAK4</italic> and <italic>MYD88</italic>, which impair Toll-like
and Interleukin 1 family Receptors (TIR) signaling<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Toll-like receptors
(TLRs) act as sensors of the innate immune system by recognizing specific components
conserved among a variety of microorganisms that invade the host. The ligation of TLRs
by their agonists induces an inflammatory response to control the infection<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>. In humans 10 functional members of the
TLR family have been identified (TLR1-10). MyD88 is a key downstream adapter for most
interleukin-1 receptors (IL-1Rs) and all TLRs except for TLR3 and partially TLR4; IRAK-4
is selectively recruited to TLRs and IL-1Rs by MyD88<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. Thus, loss of
IRAK-4 or MyD88 function interrupts a pathway critical for pathogen sensing (TLR) and
inflammation (IL-1R), known as TIR deficiency<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. Indeed, animal models indicate that deficiency in either one of
the two molecules results in heightened susceptibility to a wide range of
pathogens<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. Yet surprisingly
MyD88- and IRAK-4-deficient patients display a narrow and transient infectious phenotype
mostly limited to Gram-positive bacteria<italic>, Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> and
<italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and to Gram-negative bacteria,
<italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, in particular, and mostly from birth until
adolescence when the condition improves<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P3">The contrast between a broad and profound immunological phenotype and a narrow
and transient infectious phenotype in these patients is intriguing. When assessing
immune competency of patients with PIDs the choice of the panel of analytes used as
readout is crucial. Indeed, a normal response does not exclude the possibility of a
defect affecting a pathway that is not covered by the panel. Conversely, a defective
response detected using a given panel does not exclude the possibility of a conserved,
potentially redundant, response being present. Adopting systems-scale profiling
approaches as the readout can address such limitations. A commonly used systems approach
is <italic>ex-vivo</italic> blood transcriptome profiling. This approach has led to the
identification of novel therapeutic targets and the development of biomarker
signatures<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>. Subsequently the same approach was adopted to
investigate responses to vaccines<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P4">We have developed here an unbiased approach to evaluate the transcriptional
profiles of blood cells from MyD88- and IRAK-4-deficient patients in response to a broad
array of TLR- and IL-1R-agonists as well as whole pathogens (bacteria, virus, and
fungus). Our hypothesis was that MyD88- and IRAK-4-dependent and independent
immunological mechanisms of recognition of pathogens would be revealed <italic>in
vitro</italic>, which could contribute to understanding the <italic>in vivo</italic>
protection against most microbes in these patients. This approach allowed the assessment
of the range of responses that can be elicited in the absence of functional IRAK-4 or
MyD88 and provided insights into essential mechanisms for the maintenance of immunity to
pathogens.</p><sec sec-type="results" id="S1"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="S2"><title>In vitro transcriptome responses to purified TIR agonists</title><p id="P5">Before evaluating the impact of MyD88 and IRAK-4 deficiencies on innate
immune function we set out to establish in a set of control subjects the
baseline response elicited by the engagement of purified TIR agonists We
measured transcriptional responses to TIR agonists in 14 control subjects on a
genome-wide scale. Whole blood was stimulated <italic>in vitro</italic> for 2
hours with an array of agonists spanning all TLRs (PAM3 (TLR1/2), PAM2 (TLR2/6),
Poly (I:C) (TLR3), LPS (TLR4), Flagellin (TLR5), 3M2 (TLR7), 3M13 (TLR8), R848
(TLR7/8), CpG-D19, CpG-C (TLR9), and IL-1Rs (IL-1&#x003b2;, IL-18, IL-33) along
with two positive controls, tumor necrosis factor (TNF) and phorbol ester (PMA)
plus ionomycin. Transcripts displaying consistent differences in stimulated
expression levels across healthy control subjects were selected as described
earlier (in <sup>2</sup> and online <bold>Methods</bold>). This filter
identified sets of transcripts responding to each stimulation. They included a
number of known chemokines, cytokines, co-stimulatory molecules, antibacterial
peptides and transcription regulators involved in the TIR signaling
pathway<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. Pathway analysis confirmed that immune
cell trafficking and inflammatory response genes were significantly
over-represented across these gene lists (p&#x0003c;0. 0001) (Ingenuity pathway
analysis software, Ingenuity Systems, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ingenuity.com">www.ingenuity.com</ext-link>), as well as
type I interferon (IFN) signaling for LPS, Poly (I:C), 3M13, 3M2 and R848
stimulations (p&#x0003c;0. 001). The magnitude of transcriptional changes varied for
each stimulus: LPS, R848 and TNF induced stronger responses (713, 535 and 550
probes, respectively) and PAM3, PAM2, 3M13, IL-1&#x003b2; and IL-18 lower
responses (101, 183, 80, 99 and 119 probes, respectively). Several transcripts
were found to be overlapping among stimuli. For instance, 70 annotated probes
(59 genes) were induced by all TLR agonists except Poly (I:C) (non-specific TLR3
ligand for which signaling is MyD88-independent) (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>). CpG-A (D19),
CPG-C and IL-33 were weak inducers at this early time-point and these conditions
were not included in further analyses. This first step established the
<italic>in vitro</italic> blood transcriptional response to TIR agonists in
healthy individuals.</p></sec><sec id="S3" sec-type="subjects"><title>Characterizing responses in patients with TIR deficiency</title><p id="P6">Next we assessed the ability of IRAK-4- and MyD88-deficient patients to
respond following engagement of TIRs by purified agonists. Our initial cohort
included 4 patients with IRAK-4 deficiency and 4 patients with MyD88 deficiency
(patients P1 to P4, <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). All
<italic>IRAK4</italic> and <italic>MYD88</italic> mutations were
loss-of-function<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. All patients were asymptomatic and without any active
infectious process at the time of sample collection. They were aged 1&#x02013;18
years. The responses to PMA + ionomycin (positive control) and Poly
(I:C) (non-specific TLR3 ligand for which signaling is MyD88-independent), were
conserved -- 92. 4% of transcripts responsive in healthy controls were
also found in patients. The response to LPS (partially MyD88-dependent) was
reduced but not abolished (40. 2% of healthy response). However, a
dramatic drop in the number of responsive transcripts was observed in both
IRAK-4- and MyD88-deficient patients to PAM3 (TLR1/2 agonist; 8. 8% of
healthy response), PAM2 (TLR2/6 agonist; 6% of healthy response),
Flagellin (TLR5 agonist; 19. 7% of healthy response), 3M13 (TLR7
agonist;13. 8% of healthy response), 3M2 (TLR8 agonist; 16. 3%
of healthy response), R848 (TLR7/8 agonist; 3. 9% of healthy response),
IL-1&#x003b2; (IL-1R agonist; 19. 5% of healthy response) and IL-18
(IL-18R agonist; 23. 4% of healthy response). The extent of the defects
for each given stimulus was consistent across patients both quantitatively and
qualitatively (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1a</xref> and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>). When all
stimuli were considered together, clustering according to levels of
responsiveness across subjects resulted in a clear separation between
MyD88-dependent and MyD88-independent signals (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1b</xref>). Conversely, clustering subjects across all stimuli
resulted as expected in a clear separation between patients and controls. No
differences in responsiveness were observed between MyD88- and IRAK-4-deficient
patients. The residual levels of response (10&#x02013;20%) observed for
IL-1&#x003b2; and Flagellin could be explained because the agonists used were
<italic>E. coli</italic> derived, and, despite adding polymyxin B to the
culture, minimal levels of LPS may be present, and thus, activation might have
occurred through TLR4 engagement. Indeed, this residual response was not
observed (&#x0003c;10%) when the agonists used were not produced in bacteria
(PAM2, PAM3, R848). In summary, whole genome transcriptional responses to
MyD88-dependent TIR agonists were nearly abolished in patients compared to
controls. This finding unequivocally demonstrates that the loss of signaling
downstream of TIRs resulting from MyD88 and IRAK-4 deficiency remains
uncompensated in these patients.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Responses to whole bacteria are only marginally impaired</title><p id="P7">To use a stimulus more akinto that experienced by patients during
infection, we exposed samples from 5 MyD88- and 3 IRAK-4-deficient patients with
whole heat-killed bacteria (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The
bacteria chosen in this assay were those IRAK-4- and MyD88-deficient patients
are most susceptible to:<italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> and <italic>S.
aureus</italic><sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. For
<italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>, 3 different strains were used, including a
less virulent non-encapsulated R6 strain. In controls, the magnitude of
transcriptional change varied according to the bacteria: <italic>S.
aureus</italic> (SAC) induced the lowest responses (354 transcripts),
compared to <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> (1553, 865 and 1439 transcripts for
R11470, R8450 and R6 strains, respectively).</p><p id="P8">Patients displayed substantial levels of transcriptional activity in
response to heat-killed bacteria (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a,
2b</xref>). The response in MyD88-deficient patients was consistently lower
than in IRAK-4-deficient patients (R11470: 63% versus 84% for
MyD88- and IRAK-4-deficient patients respectively; R8450: 45% versus
99%; R6: 46% versus 89%; SAC: 47% versus
75%). This difference was not observed earlier when using purified TIR
agonists. Thus the evaluation of transcriptional response to bacterial pathogens
shows that, as opposed to what was observed using purified agonists to TIRs,
patients with MyD88 or IRAK-4 deficiency maintain the capacity to respond to
<italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic> at the
transcriptional level (&#x0003e;50% on average; range 27% to
102% of healthy responses) through MyD88- and IRAK-4-independent
mechanisms, highlighting the redundancy of the microbial sensing system in blood
leukocytes. Furthermore, our findings suggest that patients with MyD88
deficiency could differ from those with IRAK-4 deficiency in their ability to
respond to Gram-positive bacteria (50% versus 87% of
transcriptional change compared to healthy controls respectively, on average for
all 4 bacterial stimulations).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Modular repertoire mapping of TIR transcriptome responses</title><p id="P9">We next sought to characterize the transcriptional programs affected by
loss of MyD88- and IRAK-4-dependent signaling. We employed a data mining
strategy that consists in mapping relationships among group of genes based on
similarities in expression patterns across a wide range of conditions. The
approach devised for the construction of such modular transcriptional
repertoires has been described in detail elsewhere<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> For this study a large gene
co-clustering network was constructed using responses to each stimulus across
all subjects as input datasets. Network analysis identified co-clustered gene
sets &#x02013; also referred to as transcriptional modules. The resulting
collection of modules served as a framework for downstream data analysis and
interpretation. This data-driven process identified a repertoire consisting of
66 modules comprised of 1, 088 transcripts. Functional annotations were obtained
for each module (<xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary
Table 1</xref>). In addition, modules were broadly categorized based on
their patterns of response in control subjects to the different TIR agonists and
bacteria (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). Thus all 66 modules were
grouped into 7 clusters (C0 to C6). Clusters 0, 1, and 6 consist of modules
responsive to both TIR and bacteria. Cluster C6 is uniformly up-regulated upon
these stimulations and is mainly composed of inflammation-related modules,
including cytokines (IL-1&#x003b2;, IL-6, IL-8), chemokines, NF-&#x003ba;B,
acute-phase response elements and neutrophil function and phagocytosis (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table
2</xref>). Cluster C4 is composed of modules responsive to TIR agonists. For
instance, M5. 4 and M7. 2 were preferentially induced by LPS (TLR4), 3M2 or R848
(TLR8) and, to a lesser extent, Poly (I:C), and correspond to an IFN-related
inflammatory response that is not induced by Gram-positive bacteria. Bacterial
stimulations triggered a set of modules that were not induced by
pathogen-associated molecular pattern (PAMP) stimulation of individual TLRs, and
thus could be considered whole bacteria-specific (Cluster C5). The annotation of
C5 suggests a role in cell signaling (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig.
4</xref>, <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). This indicates
that in blood cultures exposed to whole bacteria, receptors other than TIR are
engaged (possibly ITAM-DAP12-associated receptors<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> such as CD300, integrins, Fc Receptors
(FcRs) C-type lectins and complement), and pathways or transcription factors
other than NF-&#x003ba;B triggered (e. g. MAP Kinases, Protein kinase C,
phosphatidylinositol, basic-leucine zipper and NFAT transcription factors).</p></sec><sec id="S6" sec-type="discussion"><title>Impact of TIR deficiencies on the transcriptome repertoire</title><p id="P10">We next used this modular repertoire as a framework for dissecting the
transcriptional programs impacted by MyD88 and IRAK-4 deficiencies. Circular
heatmaps<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> were
employed to represent residual patient responses for each TIR stimulation across
the 7 module clusters, where each circle represents a patient and each spoke
represents a module (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>). As
was expected based on our earlier findings, patients were unable to mount a
response to MyD88-dependent purified TIR agonists for any of the modules
described above, including those found in clusters C4 and C6, which are
associated with inflammation (residual responses to PAM2 <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, bottom left; all others <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>). Residual
responses were observed to LPS stimulations (partially MyD88-dependent) with C6
modules (Inflammation) displaying overall well-conserved responses, in contrast
with C4 modules (Interferon), which displayed poor residual responses (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>, bottom right). Next, IRAK-4- and
MyD88-deficient patients&#x02019; responses to heat-killed bacteria were
analyzed in a similar fashion. The overall responses to all 4 heat-killed
bacteria were relatively well preserved (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig
5</xref>). The most preserved modular responses to Gram-positive bacteria in
both MyD88- and IRAK-4-deficient patients were: 1) M2. 11, which contains
<italic>IL1A, IL1B, TNF, CCL20, CCL3L1, CCL4L1</italic> and <italic>CXCL1;
2)</italic> M5. 5, which contains <italic>IL8, IRAK2, CCL3L3, CXCL2, IL1RN,
PLAU</italic> and <italic>PTGS2; 3)</italic> M6. 6, which contains
<italic>CCRL2, CYP4B1, NRLP3, OSM, PTGS2, TAGAP</italic>; and 4) M8. 4,
which contains <italic>CCL3, CCL3L1, CCL4L2, NFKBIA, NLRP3</italic> and
<italic>PLAUR</italic>. These 4 modules, all from cluster C6, displayed high
levels of up-regulation for all donors (&#x0003e;90% for controls and
IRAK-4-deficient patients, and &#x0003e;50% for MyD88-deficient patients,
<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). This indicates that patients
were able to induce a pro-inflammatory program in response to <italic>S.
pneumoniae</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic> activation, probably
through the participation of other sensors, such as NLRP3-activators in the form
of inflammasome components, which are present in 2 of the 4 most preserved
modules.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Three modules display defective responsiveness to bacteria</title><p id="P11">Further examination of modular patterns of responsiveness to whole
bacteria conversely revealed impairment of specific transcriptional programs.
Indeed, residual levels of responsiveness among modules constituting cluster C6
diverged markedly (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> top left corner,
<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). This heterogeneity was
observed both across modules and bacterial species or strains (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref>). However,
three modules, M4. 3, M4. 7, M6. 3, did present consistently low levels of
residual responsiveness across these conditions. Of the three modules,
responsiveness was most consistently impaired for M4. 3. Module M4. 3 is related
to NF-&#x003ba;B activation (contains <italic>NFKB1</italic>,
<italic>NFKB2</italic>, <italic>IRAK3</italic>), regulation
(<italic>SRC</italic>, <italic>TNIP1</italic>), apoptosis
(<italic>BIRC3</italic>, <italic>CFLAR</italic>,
<italic>DENND5A</italic>-activator of Rab39- <italic>IER5</italic>),
IL-1&#x003b2; and the inflammasome (<italic>CARD16</italic> and
<italic>P2RX7).</italic> Responses to <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> R6
strain were abolished in all but one IRAK-4-deficient patient for M4. 3 (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6a</xref>), who however, displayed a blunted
response when exposed to <italic>S. aureus</italic> (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6b</xref>), thus suggesting species- or strain-specific
fluctuations in pathogen susceptibility (responses to <italic>S.
pneumoniae</italic> strains R8450 and R11470 are shown in <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref>). Overall
responses were also similarly blunted for module M6. 3, which includes
<italic>TNFAIP8</italic>, <italic>IRG1</italic> and molecules related to
cell metabolism (<italic>ACSL1, PDE4B, RIN2</italic>). Of interest, IRG1
enhances macrophage bactericidal activity<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> and ACSL1 has recently been found to play a role as an
inflammatory mediator in LPS-stimulated macrophages<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>. M4. 7 is another module displaying
overall decreased responsiveness. Notably, mutation of <italic>NBN</italic>
(nibrin), which is one of the 9 genes constituting module M4. 7, causes Nijmegen
breakage syndrome, a DNA repair PID characterized by combined cellular and
humoral immunodeficiency with severe recurrent sinopulmonary infections causing
significant mortality in this patient population<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>. A single nucleotide polymorphism for
<italic>NFKBIE</italic>, another gene belonging to this same module, has
been associated with susceptibility to invasive pneumococcal diseases<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. Finally, a third gene from
M4. 7, <italic>CLIC4</italic>, has been found to play an important role in
mediating innate resistance to bacterial infection in an animal model<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>. These module-specific defects
were observed again in a third set of samples (batch 3, <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), including blood drawn from 2 repeat
patients (<italic>IRAK4<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>P5 and
<italic>MYD88<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> P4) and 2 new
patients (<italic>IRAK4<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>P6 and
<italic>MYD88<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>P7). This new set of
patients showed the same degree of preserved transcriptional activity in
response to heat-killed bacteria when compared with previous set of patients
(<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig.
5</xref>), and when dissecting this response, again, all showed low residual
responsiveness for M4. 3, M4. 7 and M6. 3 (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 6</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Residual responses to viral, fungal and bacterial pathogens</title><p id="P12">Mice lacking IRAK-4 or MyD88 are susceptible to a wide range of
pathogens, which is in striking contrast with the narrow range of susceptibility
observed in humans with inborn errors in IRAK-4 or MyD88<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. Thus we subsequently investigated
patterns of transcriptional response in these patients upon whole blood
stimulation with pathogens deficient mice but not humans a resusceptible
to<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. Responses to
Heat-killed <italic>Candida albicans</italic> (HK. CA), Bacillus
Calmette-Gu&#x000e9;rin (BCG), and herpes simplex virus 1 (HSV) were measured in
2 MyD88- and 2 IRAK-4-deficient patients, as well as 8 control subjects (batch
3, <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Patients displayed
substantial levels of transcriptional activity in response to HK. CA with near
normal residual responsiveness observed in 3 of the 4 patients (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7a</xref>, left panel). In response to BCG stimulation
(<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7a</xref>, middle panel),
MyD88-deficient patients showed markedly deficient responses (&#x0003c;30%
globally) that affected all the inflammatory modules, while an IRAK-4 deficient
patient had preserved responsiveness both globally (90%) and at the
module level (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7b</xref>, middle panel) (data
could not be obtained for the second IRAK4 patient). These observations could
not be attributed to prior BCG vaccination status (MyD88 P1: no vaccination,
MyD88 P2: vaccination, IRAK-4 P2: vaccination). Finally, both MyD88- and
IRAK-4-deficient patients showed globally defective transcriptional responses to
whole blood stimulation with HSV (&#x0003c;20% responses) (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7a</xref>, right panel). At the module level one single
inflammatory module, M7. 4, was selectively preserved upon HSV stimulation
(<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7b</xref>, right panel). This module
contains molecules such as NFIL3 (E4BP4), related to macrophage, dendritic cell
and NK differentiation and function, that are required for antiviral
immunity<sup><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>, and MYC
and REL, related to NF-&#x003ba;B signaling. This finding suggests that while
TLR signaling to HSV is for the most part abolished, alternative pathways
involving NF-&#x003ba;B signaling may be preserved and contribute to maintain
resistance to this pathogen in MyD88 and IRAK-4 deficient patients.</p><p id="P13">In summary, the use of a systems approach revealed a multifaceted
pattern of innate immune responsiveness in patients with MyD88 or IRAK-4
deficiencies. Our results demonstrate a profound defect in the ability of blood
leukocytes from MyD88- and IRAK-4-deficient patients to respond to pathogen- and
host-derived TIR agonists. Responses to specific TIR agonists were completely
abrogated, while responses to whole organisms ranged from being relatively
normal (HK. CA) to dramatically reduced (HSV). Differences in levels of
responsiveness between MyD88- and IRAK-4- deficient subjects were also observed
for several conditions. Transcriptional programs elicited by pyogenic bacteria
to which both groups are clinically susceptible were not associated with a
dramatic reduction in overall responsiveness, but rather impairment of specific
inflammatory transcriptional programs.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S9"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p id="P14">We have devised a systems approach for the assessment of TIR and
antibacterial immunity inpatients with increased susceptibility to infection. The
distinct benefit of using a genome-wide approach is that it provides an unbiased
means to interrogate responses to innate immune stimuli as opposed to more
traditional approaches that require relying on <italic>a priori</italic> knowledge
to select a small panel of analytes as readout<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>. Here we assessed the global impact of
defects in IRAK-4 and MyD88 on innate immune transcriptional programs.
Patients&#x02019; responses to TLR2 agonists were less than 10% of healthy
subjects. TLR2 is known to be crucial for Gram-positive bacteria recognition
(<italic>S. pneumoniae</italic><sup><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> and <italic>S. aureus</italic><sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>), which are pathogens to which IRAK-4- and
MyD88-deficient patients are most susceptible.</p><p id="P15">We have confirmed the close dependence between IRAK-4 and MyD88 molecules in
the signaling pathway downstream of TIR, concordant with the functional structure
they form known as the Myddosome<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>.
However, stimulation with whole pathogens, as opposed to purified TIR agonists,
revealed differences in IRAK-4 and MyD88 deficient patient&#x02019;s ability to
mount transcriptional responses. This might be explained considering that MyD88
protein is involved in Ras/MAPK signaling pathway through direct interaction with
ERK without IRAK participation<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>.
Nevertheless, these differences do not translate into cytokine production, which has
been shown equally impaired <sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>, nor in the infectious clinical phenotype, which is
indistinguishable<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P16">Despite the profound defect in the common TIR signaling pathway, IRAK-4- and
MyD88-deficient patients were able to up-regulate major inflammatory modules
(modules M2. 11, M5. 5, M8. 4, M6. 6) when their blood was exposed to <italic>S.
pneumoniae</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic>. This indicates that a
MyD88-independent, but NF-&#x003ba;B- and MAPK-dependent pathway would be
responsible for this proinflammatory response since the same inflammatory program is
observed with specific TIR stimulation<sup><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>. <italic>S.
aureus</italic> and <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> can be recognized by
NOD2<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> and TNFR1<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>, both of which are expressed in
leukocytes, activate NF-&#x003ba;B and MAPKs, initiating the same inflammatory
processes as TLRs<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup>, and they do
not signal via MyD88. There is consistent evidence that both TLRs and NOD2 receptors
synergize to induce combined responses<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>. The lack of synergism with TLR2 might explain the suboptimal
response observed (lack of up-regulation of M4. 3, M4. 7, M6. 3). Those results are
consistent with previously reported data obtained at the protein level: TNF&#x003b1;
secretion in whole blood from IRAK-4 patients was undetectable 24h after TLR
stimulation, but detectable upon heat-killed <italic>Staphylococcus</italic>
stimulation, although to a lower extent compared to healthy controls<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. The residual induction of cytokines
via MyD88/IRAK-4-independent signaling pathways may account for both the resistance
to other infections and the fever/inflammation that can be observed at late stages
of infection.</p><p id="P17">These results raise an important question: can the susceptibility to
bacteria in TIR deficiencies be ascribed to this partially defective inflammatory
response, or other mechanisms contribute to the phenotype? Our assay only evaluated
responses in whole blood, and not in mucosae or skin<sup><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>. IL-1Ris crucial to maintain protective
immunity against invasive staphylococcal skin infection<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>. Indeed neutrophils play a key role in
bacterial clearance of epithelial sites<sup><xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> and IL-1R-mediated signaling by resident skin cells would
be essential for adequate neutrophil recruitment to the site of infection. We
previously published that skin-derived fibroblasts from both IRAK-4- and
MyD88-deficient patients showed no response to IL-1R activation<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Also, IL-1R has proven crucial in other
<italic>S. aureus</italic> infections<sup><xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup>. It might be
that IRAK-4- and MyD88-deficient patients are able to generate an initial
proinflammatory response upon initial encounter with Gram-positive bacteria in whole
blood, as we show, but presumably at epithelial sites as well (NOD2 expression has
been described in keratinocytes and the lung<sup><xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup>; TNFR1 is widely distributed on the airway
epithelium<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>).
Nevertheless, defective IL1-R signaling could result in an impaired systemic
amplification of this initial response, ultimately increasing the risk of not only
epithelial infections, but also bacteremia starting from skin and mucosa, which is
characteristic of these patients. This would also explain why IRAK-4-and
MyD88-deficient patients are clinical phenocopies despite different degrees of
response to whole bacteria in blood, since they display similar levels of defect to
IL-1&#x003b2; stimulation.</p><p id="P18">MyD88-deficient patients showed marked impairment in transcriptional
responses to whole blood activation with BCG, despite prior BCG vaccination. These
results are consistent with the strong TLR2 agonist activity to BCG in
mice<sup><xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>. However,
MyD88-deficient patients are not susceptible to mycobacteria nor to, BCG <sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. In humans resistance to BCG is
known to be dependent on IFN-&#x003b3; and its production is likely to be preserved
through MyD88-and IRAK-4-independent pathways, <sup><xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup>. Similarly, while the abnormal responses to HSV observed in
both in MyD88- and IRAK-4-deficient patients attest to the role of TLR2 and TLR9 in
the initiation of immune responses to HSV<sup><xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup>, it does not result in increased susceptibility to this
pathogen. Earlier work from our group demonstrated that HSV control in the central
nervous system is exquisitely dependent on a functional TLR3-pathway in neurons and
oligodendrocytes but not in blood leukocytes<sup><xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P19">Technologies available for profiling transcript abundance on a genome-wide
scale have become robust and cost-effective<sup><xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup>. Its application in whole blood has been used extensively
for the investigation of disease pathogenesis, identification of biomarkers, and
assessment of responses to vaccines<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. However, molecular
phenotypes may not always be apparent in <italic>ex vivo</italic> blood profiled at
the steady state, as is the case in patients with MyD88 and IRAK-4 deficiencies
(data not shown). We show here that using global profiling as readout in an
<italic>in vitro</italic> functional assay can produce comprehensive innate
immune phenotypes in patients with PID. Possible clinical applications for a
targeted assay derived from the modular transcriptional framework constructed in
this study can be foreseen beyond PID, in clinical settings where defects in innate
immunity are suspected, such as recurrent pyogenic infections<sup><xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> or aging<sup><xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup>, and also for the prediction of responses to
vaccines<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. The choice of conditions for the <italic>in
vitro</italic> stimulations is obviously critical; here we selected a panel
tailored for inborn errors in TIR pathway. This can be adapted depending on the
population being screened.</p><p id="P20">In conclusion, this work demonstrates the use of systems approaches as a
robust means for the global assessment of innate immune competence. Applied to the
study of patients with inborn defects of TIR signaling, this strategy revealed that
patients with MyD88 and IRAK-4 deficiencies suffer from a profound loss of
responsiveness to soluble TIR agonists and that their ability to respond to whole
bacteria is selectively impacted. Such findings are consistent with the delayed
clinical and biological signs of inflammation observed in those patients during the
course of infection<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>. More broadly by lever aging high
throughput profiling technology together with an effective analytic framework, this
work also opens new avenues for the widespread use of systems approaches as a global
readout in functional immunological assays.</p></sec><sec id="S10" specific-use="web-only"><title>Online METHODS</title><sec id="S11"><title>1. Patient information and sample collection</title><p id="P21">A total of 40 blood samples were collected from three groups of
subjects: 7 patients with complete MyD88 deficiency, 6 patients with complete
IRAK-4 deficiency, and 27 healthy donors (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table
1</xref>). <italic>IRAK4</italic> mutations from P1, P2, and P3 are null (no
IRAK-4 protein detected<sup><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>).
Mutations from IRAK-4- P4, P5 and P6<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>, and MyD88- patients 1 to 7 are loss-of-function. MyD88- P1
and P2 have normal levels of non-functional MyD88 protein; MyD88- P3-P7 and
IRAK-4- P4 and P5 have small amounts of non-functional protein<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Subjects were recruited in four
different sets: the first set included 4 healthy controls, MyD88- P1 and P2,
IRAK-4- P1 and P2. The second set included 10 different healthy controls,
MyD88-P3 and P4 and IRAK-4-P3 and P4. First and second set (batch 1) were
analyzed to evaluate patients&#x02019; responses to 13 different TIR agonists
(10 TLR agonists, 3 IL1-R agonists. A third set (batch 2) was included
afterwards to increase the number of MyD88- and IRAK-4-deficient patients for
bacterial stimulations (3 strains of heat killed <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>
and <italic>S. aureus</italic>); batch 2 included 5 new healthy controls, MyD88-
P5 and P6, new samples from MyD88-P1, and IRAK-4-P5. Four patients from batch 1
and four from batch 2 were analyzed to evaluate TIR patients&#x02019; responses
to bacteria. The fourth set (batch 3) was included to test for alternative
pathogens stimulations (1 new IRAK-4-P6, 1 new MyD88-P7 patient, new samples
from IRAK-4-P5 and MyD88-P4, and 8 new healthy controls). Data on patient
antimicrobial prophylaxis at the time of blood drawn is detailed in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><p id="P22">Healthy individuals were considered so based on past medical history (no
recurrent infections) and current health status. All healthy controls were adult
subjects except for batch 3, which included 2 healthy young children age 3 and 7
years-old. Indeed, Toll-like receptor function is mainly age dependent for the
newborn<sup><xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup>, and there
was an evident limitation in obtaining the required high volume of blood from
healthy children to use as controls. Blood samples were obtained at Necker
Hospital, Paris, France, with approval of the local Research Ethics Committee.
All participants aged 18 or their legal tutors gave written informed
consent.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>2. Blood culture</title><p id="P23">Peripheral blood was drawn into sodium heparin vacuum tubes on clinic
site (Necker Hospital, Paris). Immediately, 500&#x003bc;l whole blood (WB) was
diluted with equal amount of RPMI before adding different stimulus, each
experimental condition was performed in replicates. Diluted WB was activated for
2 hours with 10&#x003bc;g/ml of polymyxin B to clear LPS contamination plus a
wide range of agonists Pam3CSK4 (TLR1/2; 100 ng/ml, InvivoGen&#x000ae;);
Pam2CSK4 (TLR2/6; 100 ng/ml, InvivoGen&#x000ae;); poly(I:C) (TLR3; 25
&#x003bc;g/ml, InvivoGen&#x000ae;); LPS (TLR4; 100ng/ml, Sigma&#x000ae;);
Flagellin (TLR5; 100 ng/ml, InvivoGen&#x000ae;); 3M-13 (TLR7; 3&#x003bc;g/ml, 3M
pharmaceuticals&#x000ae;); 3M-2 (TLR8; 3&#x003bc;g/ml, 3M
pharmaceuticals&#x000ae;); R848 (TLR7/8; 3&#x003bc;g/ml, InvivoGen&#x000ae;);
CpG-D19 and CpG-C (TLR9; 3&#x003bc;g/ml, from collaborator);IL1B (IL-1R;
20ng/ml, R&#x00026;D systems&#x000ae;); IL-18 (IL-1R; 50ng/ml, R&#x00026;D
systems&#x000ae;); IL-33 (IL-1R; 50ng/ml, R&#x00026;D systems&#x000ae;); TNF (TNFR;
20ng/ml, R&#x00026;D systems&#x000ae;); PMA (25 ng/ml, Sigma&#x000ae;) +
Ionomycin (1&#x003bc;g/ml, Sigma&#x000ae;); 3 heat-killed pneumococcal strains
(R6, 5.10<sup>6</sup> particle/ml; R8450 10<sup>8</sup> particle/ml; R11470,
5.10<sup>6</sup> particle/ml, heat-killed at 65&#x000b0;C for 15 min, from
collaborator), and heat-killed <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>
(10<sup>7</sup> particle/ml, InvivoGen&#x000ae;); HSV-1, strain KOS-1 (MOI
1:1); live BCG (M. bovis BCG, Pasteurj sub-strain at an MOI of 20
BCG/leukocytes); HK Candida albicans (1.106 particules/ml, InvivoGen&#x000ae;),
or left unstimulated for 2h. After stimulation, WB was lysed with Tempus
solution (from Tempus tubes, Applied Biosystems) to stabilize the RNA at 1:3
ratio after stimulation. The lysates were kept at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C until
mRNA extraction.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>3. RNA extraction and processing for microarray analysis</title><p id="P24">Total RNA was isolated from WB lysate using Tempus MagMAX-96 Blood RNA
isolation kit (Applied Biosystems/Ambion). RNA quality and quantity were
assessed using Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies) and NanoDrop 1000
(NanoDrop Products, Thermo Fisher Scientific). Samples with RNA integrity
numbers values &#x0003e;6 were retained for further processing. Globin mRNA was
depleted using the GLOBIN clear&#x02122; (Applied Biosystems/Ambion).
Globin-reduced RNA was amplified and labeled using the Illumina Total Prep-96
RNA Amplification Kit (Applied Biosystems/Ambion). This process was performed in
3 different batches (batch 1, 2, and 3, <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table
1</xref>). Biotin-labeled cRNA was hybridized overnight to Human HT-12 V4
BeadChip arrays (IIlumina), which contains 47,231 probes, and scanned on an
Illumina BeadStation 500 (batch 1), iScan (batch 2), or HiScan (batch 3) to
generate signal intensity values.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>4. Microarray data analysis</title><p id="P25">To reduce the potential batch effect between the sets, the background
subtracted raw signal values, extracted with Illumina Beadstudio (version 2),
were processed using ComBat<sup><xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup>.
The data was then quantile normalized and the minimum intensity was set to 10.
These data are available at GEO Series accession number GSE25742. Only the
probes called present in at least 10% of the samples (p&#x0003c;0.01) were
retained for downstream analysis (n=19,152). Transcripts differentially
regulated upon stimulation were defined based on a minimum 1.5-fold change (up-
or down-regulation) and a minimum absolute raw intensity difference of 150 with
respect to the respective unstimulated sample. Probes passing these filters in
at least 75% of healthy control samples were considered substantially
affected by stimulation, and were used in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.
1</xref>, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>,<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig.2, 3,
5online</xref>). No explicit statistical test of differential expression was
performed. The &#x0201c;percent of healthy response&#x0201d; quantifies the
number of probes changed in the patients compared to the healthy controls. It is
calculated as the number of stimulation-affected probes divided by the average
number of stimulation-affected probes in the healthy control samples for the
same stimulus. Red/white plots (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1b</xref>,
<bold>2b</bold>) represent the normalized probe counts (number of probes
passing the cutoffs for samples divided by number of probes passing the cut-offs
for 75% of controls) for each subject-stimulation pair.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>5. Module construction</title><sec id="S16"><title>Clustering of probes into co-expressed modules</title><p id="P26">We generated sets of co-expressed probes as described
previously<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>, with
variations as follows. The data used for clustering includes 10 healthy
control and 4 patient samples (2 MyD88- and 2 IRAK-4-deficient) for 19
stimulations (all TLR + IL-1R, TNF and 4 bacteria), available as GEO
Series GSE25742. The raw expression data was background-subtracted and
average-normalized before clustering. Only probes having at least a 1.5-fold
change and &#x000b1;100 difference compared to their matched non-stimulated
sample for all stimulations were clustered. To improve clustering
efficiency, the expression values of the selected probes were first
converted into trinary values (e.g. &#x02212;1, 0, 1) as follows: for cases
where the absolute difference is &#x0003c;100 or the absolute value of the
log<sub>2</sub> fold change was &#x0003c; 0.585, then the signal was
considered to be unchanged, and was set to 0. Otherwise, the signal was set
to 1 if it is greater than the baseline and &#x02212;1 if it was smaller
than the baseline. Next, within the samples for each stimulus, a group
reduction was performed such that for each probe, each group of samples
(healthy, MyD88-/-, IRAK-4-/-) was replaced by a single value that indicated
whether the trinary signal was consistent within 75% of the samples
of the group. This yielded three trinary values (one per group) per probe.
We clustered the group-reduced trinary probe values separately for each
stimulus by grouping probes with the same pattern of values, creating as
many clusters as necessary for all probes to be included in a cluster. The
clusters were then used as input for our module extraction algorithm. The
extraction required that the maximal clique used as the seed of a module
contained at least ten probes. We did not use paraclique to expand the
module. When completed, fourteen rounds of modules were produced, the number
corresponding to the number of input clustered datasets. A total of 66
modules were obtained composed of 1088 transcripts.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Analysis of module-level data</title><p id="P27">Module activity was calculated as the differences between the
percent of up-regulated and down-regulated probes (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). To compare the module response of patient
samples to healthy controls, we calculated a &#x0201c;residual
response&#x0201d; value which is the per-patient module score divided by the
mean of the healthy controls module score for each stimulus. Module scores
for any stimuli with a healthy control absolute value mean score &#x0003c;
10% were considered not detected, so residual responses were not
computed for these modules (shown in gray in (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig.3</xref> online). For cases where healthy
controls&#x02019; mean scores and an individual patient&#x02019;s scores
were of opposite signs, the residual response was set to zero. Circular heat
map plots were generated using Circos<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Functional annotation of modules</title><p id="P28">Acumenta Literature Lab&#x02122; was used to associate each probe
within a particular module to terms in PubMed abstracts. Association scores
reflecting the strength of the associations were used in heat maps and to
calculate &#x0201c;cumulative LitLab Scores&#x0201d;. The terms that showed
a strong association with a module were used to create the functional
annotation. Gene networks for each module were created, using
&#x0201c;direct interactions&#x0201d; in GeneGo MetaCore&#x02122; (version
6.10). Modules were annotated using the network processes that were
indicated for each module. The final annotations are a summary of Acumenta
Literature Lab&#x02122; and GeneGo MetaCore&#x02122;. In the cases where no
terms had a strong association to a module and the gene networks were
inconclusive, the modules were left un-annotated (14 out of 66 modules)
(<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref> online).
The association scores obtained from Acumenta Literature Lab&#x02122; were
plotted in heat maps (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S19"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>1</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS634428-supplement-1.doc" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1170" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>2</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS634428-supplement-2.pdf" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1174" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec>