<sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The immune response underlying protection or pathogenesis in tuberculosis is incompletely understood, hindering the development of new vaccines and therapeutics (reviewed in <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). A third of the world is estimated to be infected with <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>; however, only 10&#x02013;20% of individuals go on to develop active disease during their lifetime, the rest remaining asymptomatic are referred to as &#x02018;latent&#x02019; (reviewed in <xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Furthering our understanding of the immune response would be helpful in determining why some people exposed to <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> remain latent and others go to develop disease. Such knowledge will also be useful for the development of vaccines and therapeutics and may provide information required to support the identification of diagnostic and prognostic markers. Although <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> antigen-specific interferon-gamma (IFN-&#x003b3;) release assays can determine whether individuals have been infected with <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic>, they cannot distinguish individuals with active tuberculosis and those latently infected with <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic>. This determination relies on assessment of clinical symptoms and mycobacterium sputum smear positivity, neither of which are highly specific. Confirmatory diagnosis of tuberculosis requires culture of the mycobacteria for speciation, which alternatively can now be achieved using the nucleic acid amplification testing (NAAT). Both are reliant on obtaining sputum from infected individuals, which is not always feasible, or bronchoalveolar lavage, which requires an invasive technique not easily accessible in countries with a high tuberculosis burden. Therefore, the ability to determine the immune response in active tuberculosis using blood transcriptomics (<xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) offers new opportunities to develop supportive biomarkers to determine whether individuals suffer from active tuberculosis. The diminished blood transcriptomic signature observed during successful tuberculosis treatment (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) could also help in monitoring the response to treatment and in the development of new drugs, since current tests for monitoring drug efficacy such as the early bactericidal assays and 2-month sputum conversion remain inadequate (<xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). The immune response uncovered using blood transcriptomics of active tuberculosis has revealed hitherto unappreciated knowledge, which may also be of great use in the development of therapeutics.</p></sec><sec><title>A view of the immune response from the blood using transcriptomics</title><p>Peripheral blood is easily accessible and represents a reservoir of immune cells trafficking to and from the sites of active disease and lymphoid organs. The use of peripheral blood for determining gene expression profiles in disease was first introduced in studies of cancer (<xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) and then autoimmune pathologies (<xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). More recently the blood transcriptome has been of success in measuring the immune response to infection (reviewed in <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) and can reflect disease activity in the tissue (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). It has been shown that in some cases blood transcriptional signatures may help to distinguish different infectious diseases, such as bacteria or viruses, but can also distinguish between different bacterial or viral infections (<xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). In some cases, however, similar transcriptional signatures can be observed in certain types of diseases with similar pathogenesis (<xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) or infectious agents (<xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). The specificity of the transcriptional signature for a particular infectious disease requires a combination of activated pathways and transcription programs, rather than a set of uniquely activated disease-specific genes. Pathway and modular bioinformatics analyses have been designed to characterize a transcriptional response to identify combinations of pathways and networks associated with diseases (<xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Such approaches have been applied successfully to the study of the immune response in tuberculosis (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Methods for quantitation of transcriptomic profiles to reflect disease severity, such as the molecular distance to health (MDTH) (<xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) or variations on this approach, have been successfully developed and can&#x000a0;also be used to quantify the disease response to treatment (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Overview of transcriptomic studies in human tuberculosis</title><sec><title>Discrimination of active tuberculosis from latent infection</title><p>Strategies to improve and/or support current diagnostic tests for active tuberculosis would be of great use in clinical management of the disease. The ability to provide an earlier diagnosis of the disease would allow more rapid treatment initiation, which could reduce the risk of transmission. Support and improvement of current diagnostic tests would also minimize misdiagnosis of other confounding diseases as tuberculosis and would thus avoid the adverse events resulting from unnecessary anti-tuberculosis treatment. This will be particularly useful for diagnosis of tuberculosis in hard to diagnose groups like infants and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-infected individuals.</p><p>Several studies have reported the blood transcriptome of patients with active tuberculosis (<xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) (<italic>Table</italic>&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">1</xref>). Early studies in patients with active tuberculosis indicated that differences existed between their blood gene expression profiles and those in healthy, latently infected individuals (<xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="b28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). These early studies identified immune response genes and chemokine genes to be differentially expressed in active pulmonary tuberculosis patients and controls, but involved small numbers of patients and required further validation. In 2010, a larger scale study was conducted, including patients recruited in both London, U.K. and Cape Town, South Africa, all recruited before initiation of treatment (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Whole genome blood transcriptomic profiles clearly discriminated individuals with active tuberculosis from those latently infected with <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> and healthy controls (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Furthermore, the magnitude of the transcriptional signature correlated with the extent of disease in the lungs as measured by radiography (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) (<italic>Fig</italic>.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1</xref>), indicating that the immune response in the blood can reflect the local reaction to a pathogen in the lung. The observed transcriptional signature was replicated in independent and validation cohorts (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). The blood transcriptional signature, as defined by various approaches including pathway and modular analysis, was shown to consist of upregulated IFN-inducible genes (both type I and type II), myeloid and inflammatory genes, and downregulated transcripts encoding B and T-cell genes (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Flow cytometric analysis together with purification of leukocyte populations from the blood of identical individuals revealed that the downregulation of T-cell genes was largely due to diminished numbers of subsets of CD4<sup>+</sup> T-cell effector and memory cells (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), possibly reflecting apoptosis and/or migration to the infected lung. A parallel study also demonstrated a blood transcriptional signature that could distinguish patients with active tuberculosis from latently infected individuals (<xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Here, Fc&#x003b3; receptor 1B (FCGRIB) was defined as the most differentially expressed gene and in combination with four other markers gave high specificity for discrimination of active tuberculosis from individuals with latent infection and healthy controls. Elevated expression of innate immune-related genes, including Janus kinase (JAK)-STAT pathway, sensing of microbial patterns by Toll-like receptors, and IFN signaling was also observed in active tuberculosis and suggested a high degree of accuracy in discriminating tuberculosis patients and latently infected donors and that expression of these genes correlated with susceptibility and resistance to tuberculosis (<xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Different studies demonstrating use of transcriptional blood signatures to identify patients with active tuberculosis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geographical region</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study design</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key pathways</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Africa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole blood</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB versus LTB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="b28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PBMC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB versus LTB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fc&#x003b3;-receptor signalling</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK and South Africa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole blood</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB versus LTB versus HC, TB versus OD, TB treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IFN signaling</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Gambia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole blood</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB versus LTB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JAK&#x02013;STAT pathway; IFN signaling; TLR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA &#x00026; Brazil</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole blood</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB versus LTB versus HC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interferon signaling</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Africa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole blood</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB versus LTB versus HC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole blood</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB versus OD</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IFN signaling; Complement; TLR signaling; Fc&#x003b3;-receptor signalling</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="b44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Africa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole blood</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indonesia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PBMC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB versus HC, TB treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IFN signaling</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Africa, Malawi</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole blood</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB versus OD, TB versus LTB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole Blood</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB versus OD, TB treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IFN signaling, Role of pattern recognition receptors, Antigen presentation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Africa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole blood</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complement; B-cell markers; CD64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Africa, Kenya, Malawi</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB versus OD, TB versus LTB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="fig01" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The blood transcriptional signature of active tuberculosis correlates with radiographic extent of disease in the lung. Hierarchical clustering analysis and statistical filtering generated a gene tree (green, left of figure) of 393 transcripts, and an expression profile (vertical columns) (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) (A) here shown for selected participants correlating with lung radiographic extent of disease. Each row of the heatmap represents an individual transcript and each column an individual participant. Relative abundance of transcripts is shown as: over-abundant red; under-abundant blue; median colored yellow. (B) The Weighted Molecular Distance to Health calculated for the transcriptional signature is shown against the score for the radiographic extent of disease. Adapted from Berry <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>., 2010, <italic>Nature</italic> (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="imr0264-0088-f1"/></fig><p>Similarity between these two independent studies (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) was subsequently reported (<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Such whole blood gene expression in tuberculosis patients, as well as in healthy infected and uninfected individuals was also analyzed in an additional cohort in The Gambia, West Africa and validated against the previously identified signatures (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) (<italic>Fig</italic>.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">2</xref>). A unique combination of classical gene expression analysis with pathway and functional association analysis integrated with intra-individual expression correlations was used and revealed high similarities of expression profiles among different cohorts (<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) (<italic>Fig</italic>.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">2</xref>). This study identified a network of Fc&#x003b3; receptor 1 signaling correlating with transcriptional activity as the hallmark of gene expression in tuberculosis (<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) and validated the previously reported (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) functional gene clusters of immunoregulatory interactions involving the JAK-STAT pathway, sensing of microbial patterns by Toll-like receptors and IFN signaling. Collectively, these reports first suggested that the use of blood transcriptomics could provide a robust system for identification and validation of biosignatures for tuberculosis, which could support its diagnosis. In addition, the use of integrated and novel bioinformatic analysis tools (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) to interrogate the blood transcriptional signature revealed novel insights into functional immune and inflammatory networks underlying the pathogenesis of tuberculosis.</p><fig id="fig02" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of differential expression in three independent cohorts. Comparison of differential gene expression between active tuberculosis (TB) and individuals with latently infected with <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> (LTBI) in cohorts in South Africa (SUN) and The Gambia (MRC) with gene profiles in a cohort in the United Kingdom (UK) and South Africa identified by Berry <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>. (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Significance of differential expression at corrected p-value level of q&#x000a0; &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05. From Maertzdorf <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>., 2011, <italic>Plos One</italic> (<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="imr0264-0088-f2"/></fig><p>Further studies describing discriminatory gene expression profiles, which segregate individuals with active tuberculosis from those asymptomatic individuals latently infected with <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> or from uninfected healthy control subjects, have subsequently been published by several different research groups. These studies have been conducted using a variety of microarray platforms, and importantly patients have been recruited in different geographical locations, including Brazil (<xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>), The Gambia (<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), Indonesia (<xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), South Africa, and Malawi (<xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>), again supporting the robustness of using whole blood gene expression profiles in the identification of individuals with active tuberculosis as distinct from those latently infected individuals and healthy controls. Although initially there were concerns that discrimination might be masked unless cell subsets were characterized separately, the IFN-inducible signature identified by Berry <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>. (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) was clearly observable directly in whole blood from active tuberculosis patients versus controls.</p><p>The total transcript composition of whole blood can indicate important differences in cell populations. Berry <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>. (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) reported that the whole blood IFN-inducible signature of active tuberculosis was observed in purified neutrophils from the same individuals, with a subset of the genes also upregulated in purified monocytes. The blood transcriptome of active tuberculosis showed a decrease in B-cell and T-cell-specific genes (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), and flow cytometric analysis of the blood from these patients revealed that the T-cell signature could be explained by decreases in central and effector memory T cells in the blood of active tuberculosis patients (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). This is in keeping with accumulating evidence that the monocyte/lymphocyte ratio is associated with the risk of developing active tuberculosis following infection (<xref rid="b31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) and has been observed in whole blood transcriptomic studies (Fletcher, personal communication). Nevertheless, gene expression profiling of selected CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells provided a highly discriminatory gene expression profile for active tuberculosis versus latent infection (<xref rid="b32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). The identified cytokine receptor signaling regulation included Interleukin (IL-2) receptor &#x003b1;-chain, JAK3, suppressor of cytokine signaling 3 (SOCS3), cytokine-inducible SH2-containing protein, and protoncogene serine/threoinine protein kinase. It needs to be clarified whether this regulatory signaling network indeed contributes to impaired T-cell responses in tuberculosis.</p><p>A comparison (<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) of eight independently obtained tuberculosis microarray datasets (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="b28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) revealed enrichment for genes associated with myeloid cell inflammation and TREM1 signaling as the most significant pathways upon integration of data from all the studies (<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) rather than the IFN signaling pathway (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). This signature of myeloid inflammation had also been observed in earlier studies using the modular approach (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Flow cytometric analysis of leukocyte subsets isolated from the blood of the same active tuberculosis patients indicated that the pronounced myeloid signature resulted from increased numbers of inflammatory monocytes and increased gene expression in purified monocytes (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). True dominance of a particular pathway will require quantitative analysis by other more sophisticated approaches in the future. It is possible, however, that in future in depth meta-analysis of the active tuberculosis blood signature, when quantitatively compared and including a larger set of confounding diseases in increased numbers of individuals, may reveal yet another dominant pathway or set of genes better able to distinguish tuberculosis from other diseases and of use in diagnosis. Regardless, it is likely that the different pathways of genes perturbed during active tuberculosis may all contribute to pathogenesis of the disease, such as the IFN-inducible genes described in the blood signature of active tuberculosis (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Discrimination of active tuberculosis from other confounding diseases</title><p>Remarkable similarities have been reported in the blood transcriptome of individuals with tuberculosis and the granulomatous disease sarcoidosis (<xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Sarcoidosis is a multi-system granulomatous disease, predominantly a respiratory disorder of unknown etiology, which presents with very similar radiological and clinical findings to tuberculosis. Both diseases were found to have significant overlap in the differentially expressed genes in the blood, including the IFN-inducible genes (<xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>), indicating that common pathways may result in the similar pathological features observed in both diseases. In keeping with this theory, another bacterial granulomatous disease affecting the lung, melioidosis, also revealed some overlap with the IFN-dominated blood transcriptional signature of pulmonary tuberculosis (<xref rid="b33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). On the other hand, patients with community-acquired pneumonia and lung cancer were shown to display a distinct blood transcriptional signature to that seen in tuberculosis, which instead is dominated by an inflammatory signature (<xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) and not the dominant IFN-inducible signature of tuberculosis and sarcoidosis. Transcript classifiers that discriminated between tuberculosis were identified (<xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>).</p><p>Around a quarter of all tuberculosis deaths occur in HIV-infected people who often test negative for mycobacteria, e.g. sputum smear negative (<xref rid="b34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>), hence the ability to diagnose active tuberculosis in this group is vital for improved patient care and tuberculosis control programs. The recent identification of gene expression signatures that can distinguish individuals with active tuberculosis from those with other lung diseases and in <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> infection in HIV<sup>+</sup> individuals is very encouraging (<xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). A large case&#x02013;controlled study, involving both HIV-infected and HIV-uninfected individuals, prospectively recruited patients presenting with symptoms of tuberculosis, some of whom on further investigation were diagnosed with another disease and not tuberculosis. This study generated a large clinically relevant and diverse cohort of confounding diseases to act as a comparison group with the positively identified tuberculosis cohorts (<xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). The derived transcriptional signatures were able to differentiate, with a high degree of sensitivity and specificity, between tuberculosis and healthy controls as well as between tuberculosis and other confounding diseases in both HIV-infected and HIV-uninfected individuals (<xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Pediatric tuberculosis is notoriously difficult to diagnose and often depends exclusively on clinical symptoms (<xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). The characterization of an altered blood gene expression profile in children with active tuberculosis comprising both HIV-infected and HIV-uninfected individuals (<xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) provides new leads for the development of new, host-based tests, to support the diagnosis of tuberculosis in pediatric disease (<xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) in addition to adult disease (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>What is needed for blood transcriptomics to support diagnostics or prognostics?</title><p>To develop this approach and to verify proposed classifiers as a support to current diagnostics, testing in further independent cohorts will be necessary to evaluate diagnostic accuracy, and additionally it will be necessary to validate transcript classifiers in a range of independent cohorts of respiratory and systemic illnesses. A dominant algorithm of transcript classifiers, consisting of several sets of ca. 12&#x02013;100 genes associated with active tuberculosis, may be the best approach for the development of a diagnostic with the highest specificity and sensitivity, and this approach would be required considering current costs in order to be of use in the clinic. Yet, as technology advances for processing and gene expression analysis together with advances in analytical tools (<xref rid="b37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) and also becomes more affordable, it is possible that a diagnosis may be based on the whole set of genes&#x000a0;discriminating tuberculosis from other diseases and on selected classifier genes. The use of blood transcriptomics to improve diagnosis of tuberculosis could be applied together with current methods including clinical symptoms, sputum mycobacterium smear positivity, and confirmatory diagnosis, where possible, of tuberculosis by culture or NAAT technology. This will be especially valuable in cases who are smear&#x000a0;negative or culture negative, and in children where such tests are not always feasible. Blood transcriptomics may help to speed up diagnosis and predict which people have disease, allowing faster treatment and thus reduction of transmission.</p><p>Berry <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>. (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) reported that the signature of active tuberculosis was detectable in 10&#x02013;20% of asymptomatic individuals diagnosed with latent <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> infection [by the IGRA test, an <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> specific antigen-stimulated IFN-&#x003b3; release assay of human blood or the tuberculin skin test (TST)-skin test], although this could be reflective of subclinical tuberculosis at early stages of disease. This needs to be verified in larger number of latently infected individuals, and it will be of interest to determine whether those with a signature of tuberculosis go on to develop disease or whether their signature reverts to that of healthy controls and the majority of latently infected individuals. This would be in keeping with the heterogeneity in individuals who are latently infected with <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> that has been reported using high-resolution computed tomography (CT) and positron emission tomography (PeT) (PET-CT) (<xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Currently, data from a longitudinal study which followed household contacts of newly diagnosed tuberculosis patients over several years is being analyzed. In this study, blood transcriptome profiles are compared in those household contacts who remained healthy over the observational period versus those who developed active TB. It is hoped that this study will provide a first hint about a biosignature that can predict&#x000a0;individuals at heightened risk of developing active tuberculosis disease (<xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="b38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomarkers-for-tb.net/">http://www.biomarkers-for-tb.net/</ext-link>). Another ongoing study determines risk of tuberculosis disease in adolescents living in a TB-high-endemic area (<xref rid="b39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="b40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Changes in blood gene expression during tuberculosis treatment</title><p>Monitoring tuberculosis drug efficacy is important for both clinical management and the development of new treatments. Berry <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>. (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) observed that the blood transcriptional signature of active tuberculosis, consisting largely of increased IFN-induced gene expression, diminished by 2 months of treatment and had disappeared by 12&#x000a0;months after diagnosis (<italic>Fig</italic>.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3</xref><italic>A</italic>). This change in the molecular signature paralleled the clinical improvement measured by chest X-ray (<italic>Fig</italic>.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3</xref><italic>B</italic>) and was reflected in the MDTH score measured for individual patients (<italic>Fig</italic>.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3</xref><italic>C</italic>). The diminished T and B-cell signature of active tuberculosis also reverted in some individuals after 2&#x000a0;months of treatment, but this change was most apparent in all individuals by 12 months post-treatment (<italic>Fig</italic>.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3</xref><italic>A</italic>). In two separate subsequent longitudinal studies based in South Africa (<xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) and London (<xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), it was apparent that large-scale changes in blood host gene expression occur very rapidly after initiation of successful tuberculosis treatment (<italic>Fig</italic>.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3</xref><italic>D and E</italic>), with differences detectable after only 1&#x000a0;week of treatment (<italic>Fig</italic>.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">4</xref>). Slower changes continued to occur throughout the duration of tuberculosis treatment (<xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Strikingly, similar results were obtained from both longitudinal studies, despite being conducted by different investigators using different technological platforms (<italic>Figs</italic><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3</xref><italic>D, E and</italic><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">4</xref>). Pathway analysis showed certain genes changed expression immediately upon treatment initiation whereas others changed at later times, indicating that different biological pathways may predominantly be affected during different stages of treatment and recovery. A rapid downregulation of genes involved in the inflammatory response including a dominant C1q complement element occurred first at 1&#x000a0;week postinfection (<italic>Fig</italic>.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">4</xref><italic>A and C</italic>) and was followed by changes in lymphocyte compartments with distinct upregulation of B-cell-related genes (<xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) (<italic>Fig</italic>.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">4</xref><italic>B and C</italic>). Ottenhoff <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>. (<xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) also observed temporal changes in blood gene expression through treatment, in samples collected from Indonesian tuberculosis patients (<xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), with expression patterns after 8&#x000a0;weeks being intermediate to the profiles obtained at tuberculosis diagnosis and at the end of treatment. Samples from healthy control subjects were similar to the samples collected at the end of tuberculosis treatment.</p><fig id="fig03" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The blood transcriptional signature of tuberculosis is diminished upon successful treatment. (A) The transcriptional signature of active TB is extinguished during treatment (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). (B) Transcriptional profiles of Active TB patients, resampled at 2 and 12&#x000a0;months postantimycobacterial drug treatment were compared with baseline and compared to X-ray (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). (C) The Weighted Molecular Distance to Health calculated for the transcriptional signature is shown against the time after treatment (A&#x02013;C From Berry <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>., <italic>Nature</italic> 2010) (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). (D) A blood transcript signature is seen to change on treatment by as early as 1&#x000a0;week (<xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) &#x02018;Cliff <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>., Distinct phases of blood gene expression pattern through tuberculosis treatment reflect modulation of the humoral immune response. (From Cliff <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>., <italic>J Infect Dis</italic> 2013; 207(<xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>): pp. 18&#x02013;29, by permission of Oxford University Press&#x02019; (E) A 664 transcript signature is seen to change on treatment by as early as 2&#x000a0;weeks (From Bloom <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>., <italic>Plos One</italic> 2012) (<xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="imr0264-0088-f3"/></fig><fig id="fig04" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The blood transcriptional signature changes during different phases of treatment. Pathway analysis of the blood transcriptional signature reveals (A) early changes in complement related genes after 1&#x000a0;week; (B) later changes of other gene sets and restoration of T and B-cell related genes. (C) There is heterogeneity in the rate of change of gene expression between patients, but large-scale similarity in the overall pattern of change. (From Cliff <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>., Distinct phases of blood gene expression pattern through tuberculosis treatment reflect modulation of the humoral immune response. <italic>J Infect Dis</italic> 2013; 207(<xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>): pp. 18&#x02013;29, by permission of Oxford University Press).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="imr0264-0088-f4"/></fig><sec><title>Using changes in blood gene expression to monitor tuberculosis treatment</title><p>There is a great need for new tuberculosis drugs or regimens to shorten treatment and cope with drug resistance. The lack of easy and economical methods to test tuberculosis drug efficacy is a serious impediment to drug development. In later phase III drug efficacy trials, the rate of tuberculosis relapse over 2&#x000a0;years post-treatment is measured, and the proof of enhanced or non-inferior drug efficacy compared to existing drug regimens will require enrolment of many thousands of patients at vast expense. Currently, bacteriological approaches, such as the early bactericidal assay and the sputum conversion rate, are the most commonly used methods employed in early clinical studies. Although they provide some indication of early drug efficacy, particularly against actively replicating bacilli, they are not sufficient to predict tuberculosis treatment outcome and do not measure the killing of quiescent or persistent bacterial populations, which could later reactivate.</p><p>Host-derived biomarkers that predict tuberculosis treatment outcome could greatly enhance tuberculosis drug development (<xref rid="b41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Radiological studies using PeT and CT in cynomolgus macaques can directly demonstrate drug efficacy at the level of individual granulomas, with different compounds shown to elicit different metabolic effects (<xref rid="b42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). The translation of such methodologies to human patients may allow early efficacy testing of tuberculosis regimens. However, a simple blood test would be much more easily applied in large-scale drug efficacy trials and may also be beneficial for clinical management. We therefore envisage that a test could be developed based on the blood gene expression changes that occur during successful tuberculosis treatment with conventional first-line four drug therapy consisting of isoniazid, rifampicin, pyrazinamide, and ethambutol. Furthermore, such a test could include genes whose expression changes both immediately upon treatment initiation, including complement and IFN-associated genes, to measure drug activity potentially against rapidly dividing bacilli, and also those transcripts that change expression more slowly, such those encoding B and T-cell genes, potentially reflecting the restoration of the normal gene expression as slower growing persistent mycobacterial populations are eradicated or leukocyte populations are restored. This approach would enable the test to measure the efficacy of compounds or regimens aimed at a wide range of mycobacterial targets.</p><p>To be useful across human populations, the test would need to include genes whose expression changes are consistent in different ethnic groups and in patients in different geographical locations. Furthermore, the test should also work in HIV<sup>+</sup> as well as negative individuals. These issues are being addressed widely in further blood transcriptomic studies conducted in different geographical sites. It will also be important to characterize changes in blood gene expression that occur during non-standard treatments, such as second-line drug treatments used in multi-drug resistant tuberculosis.</p><p>The development of a test that reflects a successful and lasting cure would be beneficial for clinical management of tuberculosis patients. The response to tuberculosis treatment varies between individuals, which may be reflected by the blood signature (<xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), and some risk factors for increased risk of tuberculosis-relapse after treatment completion exist. In this regard, people with type 2 diabetes are not only more likely to develop active tuberculosis upon infection than non-diabetic people (<xref rid="b43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>) but also are more likely to suffer tuberculosis-relapse after treatment, treatment failure, or even death (<xref rid="b44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Prediction of successful tuberculosis treatment in this population would be particularly valuable, and to this end patients are being recruited in different studies worldwide in patients with both tuberculosis and type 2 diabetes, which may help to unravel the causal relationship between the two diseases.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Other methodologies with potential for diagnosis of tuberculosis</title><p>Although gene expression biomarkers from whole blood RNA have been widely applied to characterize differences between individuals with active tuberculosis and those with latent infection or other diseases, other complementary avenues may also be of use to support the analysis of unique parameters perturbed during tuberculosis disease. While it is understood that whole blood RNA expression reflects changes in peripheral blood cells migrating from infected tissue sites, additional and complementary information can be gained by measuring molecules that are derived directly from the site of infection (<xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="b45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="b46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Studies systematically profiling the host response have employed numerous different methods. Proteomic studies have suggested that combinations of plasma or serum proteins can differentiate individuals with active tuberculosis from those latently infected with <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> (<xref rid="b47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>), from other diseases (<xref rid="b48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>), and reflect changes during successful treatment (<xref rid="b38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="b49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). There have been differing reports on whether cytokines will be of use in treatment monitoring (reviewed in <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), possibly due to instability of cytokines/chemokines due to post-transcriptional and post-translational regulation/degradation (<xref rid="b50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>).</p><p>Metabolomic profiling of serum has the potential to discriminate patients with active tuberculosis from latently infected individuals (<xref rid="b51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>) and has highlighted a potential pathogenic role for tryptophan metabolism (<xref rid="b52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>), which has previously been linked with mortality in tuberculosis (<xref rid="b53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>) and may allow therapeutic limitation of inflammation (<xref rid="b46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Specifically, Weiner <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>. (<xref rid="b52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>) analyzed metabolic profiles in serum samples of tuberculosis patients and healthy controls and showed that a biosignature based on profiles comprising less than 20 metabolites can achieve sensitivity and specificity (<italic>Fig</italic>.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">5</xref>), although this will need validation in further cohorts. Some of the predictive metabolites were suggested to have derived directly from the site of infection. For example, kynurenine, which was found at significantly higher levels in the sera of tuberculosis patients than in controls, is synthesized from tryptophan by the enzyme indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase 1, induced in macrophages and dendritic cells in contact with <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic>, and it is possible that high kynurenine abundance in serum reflects release of this molecule from granulomas in the lung. Several processes comprising changes in their metabolic components (including higher levels of kynurenine and cortisol and lower abundance of lysophosphatidilcholines, which may be caused by inhibition of phospholipase A2) can be linked to immunosuppressive mechanisms. In a parallel approach, cytokines were determined in the same study groups (<xref rid="b52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>).</p><fig id="fig05" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Metabolomics uncovers a signature of active tuberculosis in the blood reflecting immunosuppression. Heat map showing fold changes of small metabolic compounds in the three study groups, tuberculosis patients, healthy uninfected, and latently infected individuals. Fold changes are relative to the average abundance in the tuberculin skin test (TST) &#x02013; group. Red indicates relative abundance higher than average in the TST&#x02013; group; blue indicates relative abundance lower than average in the TST&#x02013; group. Horizontal axis: samples belonging to the three study groups; vertical axis: top 50 compounds selected by variable importance in RF analysis, including compounds that could not be identified, but were strong predictors of sample status. Color bars above the heat map denote study groups: gray, TST&#x02013;; green, TST+; red, TBactive. (From Weiner <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>., <italic>Plos One</italic> 2012) (<xref rid="b52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="imr0264-0088-f5"/></fig><p>Distinct cytokines correlated with defined metabolites, showing the link between metabolite abundance in serum and the immune processes in response to tuberculosis disease. For example, the chemokine C-X-C motif chemokine 10 (CXCL10, IP-10), the cytokine interleukin 6, and the growth factor granulocyte colony-stimulating factor showed a negative correlation with abundant amino acids, including glutamine and tryptophan, and positive correlation with metabolic markers elevated in the sera of tuberculosis patients, including N&#x02013;acetylneuraminate and hypoxanthine. It will be important that these findings are validated in independent cohorts (<xref rid="b51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="b52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>) and in different locations, as has been done in the case of blood transcriptomics, to avoid overestimating diagnostic accuracy, especially with small sample sizes (<xref rid="b54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>).</p><p>A microRNA-223 (miR-223) has been identified as an upregulated small non-coding RNA in blood and lung parenchyma of tuberculosis patients and during experimental mouse models of the disease (<xref rid="b55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Deletion of miR-223 rendered mice highly susceptible to acute lung infection and it was suggested that miR-223 directly targets the chemoattractants CXCL2, CCL3, and IL-6 in myeloid cells. This study revealed an essential role for a single miRNA in tuberculosis and also identified new targets for and assigned biological functions to miR-223. Although in an early stage, the potential of miRs for diagnosis and therapy of tuberculosis is being considered (<xref rid="b56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). Likewise, there is discussion of the potential use of epigenetic markers as diagnostic markers in adverse immune system conditions and treatment thereof (<xref rid="b57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>), although again much is to be uncovered as to the specificity and effectiveness of such approaches. Recent studies on epigenetic programming in differentiation of mononuclear phagocytes point to a role of epigenetics in innate immunity, which has been claimed to play a role in the non-specific prevention of morbidity and mortality by the tuberculosis vaccine BCG (<xref rid="b58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>What did we learn about the immune response from the transcriptomic analysis of active TB?</title><p>Although TNF, IL-12, and the Th1 axis have shown to be important in both mouse and human for protection against tuberculosis and other mycobacterial diseases (reviewed in <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), it remains unclear what constitutes a protective immune response (<xref rid="b61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>) and what factors contribute to the development and progress of active tuberculosis disease.</p><p>Transcriptomic analyses of blood from patients with tuberculosis has revealed a dominant signature of IFN-inducible genes, including those down-stream of type I and type II (IFN-&#x003b3;) signaling (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), upregulation of complement related genes (<xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) and those associated with myeloid function and inflammation (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="b62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>) (<italic>Fig</italic>.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">6</xref>). In addition, the signature reflects downregulation of genes encoding B and T-cell functions (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) (<italic>Fig</italic>.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">6</xref>), the latter accounted for by decreased numbers of T cells in the blood of active tuberculosis patients (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). This perhaps reflects apoptosis of such cells in the blood or their migration to the infected tissue (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><fig id="fig06" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Modular and pathway analysis reveal a dominant IFN-inducible signature in tuberculosis. Modular analysis reveals overabundance of IFN-inducible genes (M3.1) and myeloid genes (M1.5 and M2.6) and under abundance of B (M1.3) and T cell (M2.8) related genes (A) (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>); (B) (From Cliff <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>., Distinct phases of blood gene expression pattern through tuberculosis treatment reflect modulation of the humoral immune response. <italic>J Infect Dis</italic> 2013; 207(<xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>): pp. 18&#x02013;29, by permission of Oxford University Press). (<xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). (C) The canonical pathway for IFN signaling from Ingenuity Pathways Analysis; with transcripts over-represented in test set patients with active tuberculosis (<xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) shaded red. GAS, Gamma-activated site; ISRE, IFN-sensitive element. Modified from (<xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Transcript abundance in whole blood and (c) separated blood leucocyte populations of representative IFN-inducible genes (from top to bottom: OAS1, IFI6, IFI44, IFI44L, OAS3, IRF7,IFIH1, IFI16, IFIT3, IFIT2, OAS2, IFITM3, IFITM1, GBP1, GBP5, STAT1, GBP2, TAP1, STAT1, STAT2, IFI35, TAP2, CD274, SOCS1, CXCL10, IFIT5) in active tuberculosis. Transcript abundance/expression is normalized to the median of the healthy controls. Modified from (A and C modified from Berry <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>., <italic>Nature</italic> 2010) (<xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="imr0264-0088-f6"/></fig><sec><title>Potential mechanisms whereby type I IFN contributes to pathogenesis in tuberculosis and other mycobacterial diseases</title><p>The blood transcriptomic approach identified a previously unappreciated signature of tuberculosis dominated by type I IFN, suggesting a potential role of Type I IFN in contributing to active tuberculosis disease (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). This was supported by the observations that the signature correlated with the radiographic extent of disease (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) and was diminished upon treatment (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Through microarray analysis of human tissue from patients with the mycobacterial disease leprosy (<xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) and comparison with deposited data on the blood transcriptional signature of active tuberculosis (<xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>), IFN-inducible transcripts have also been reported in leprosy. Using these expression data and supported by <italic>in vitro</italic> models, this study suggested that in leprosy the balance of type I and type II IFNs determines a protective or susceptible host immune responses (<xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Likewise, in experimental models of tuberculosis, type I IFN has been shown to have adverse effects (<xref rid="b63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>), although there are conflicting reports (<xref rid="b67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>). It is of note that adverse effects of Type I IFN&#x000a0;were invariably reported in experimental models of tuberculosis where mice were infected with clinical isolates of <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> as opposed to the laboratory strain H37Rv that is largely used. In addition, the experimental mouse models were on a genetic background other than the C57Bl/6 or BALB/c that are widely used as experimental models of tuberculosis (<xref rid="b63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="b68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). Elevation of type I IFN by <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> infection of mice in the context of Poly(I)C (<xref rid="b69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="b70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>) or during coinfection with influenza (<xref rid="b71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>) or through genetic manipulation removing negative regulation of type I IFN expression by the MAP-kinase TPL-2 (<xref rid="b72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>) results in exacerbated disease and increased bacterial load, all via a type I IFN-dependent mechanism.</p><p>The mechanisms that mediate IFN&#x003b1;/&#x003b2;-driven disease exacerbation are not fully understood and will undoubtedly be complex. Data from investigations of hyper-virulent strains initially suggested suppression of pro-inflammatory cytokines and Th1-type immunity (<xref rid="b63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="b65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). Recent data suggest that type I IFN enhanced migration of inflammatory monocytes and neutrophils to the lung in <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis-</italic>infected mice (<xref rid="b68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). In keeping with effects on myeloid cells, recent mechanistic studies have shown that type I IFN can induce the suppressive cytokine IL-10 (<xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="b70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="b73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>) and inhibit the production of the cytokines IL-12 and TNF important for protection against <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> infection (<xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="b70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="b73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>). Cell-intrinsic type I IFN signals additionally suppressed iNOS production by pulmonary myeloid cells (<xref rid="b70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). The induction of immune suppressive IL-10 (reviewed in <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="b74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>) and IL-1RA by IFN&#x003b1;/&#x003b2; may be part of the mechanism for this suppression of protective pro-inflammatory cytokines (<xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="b70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="b72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>, <xref rid="b73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>). Additionally, type I IFN can block the ability of IFN-&#x003b3; (type II IFN) to activate macrophages to control bacterial growth or produce the protective cytokine IL-12 (<xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="b73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>), and hence, the balance of induction of these two cytokines is critical for the outcome in infection (<xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="b73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>). Finally, polarization toward myeloid-derived suppressor cells, which counteract protective immune responses against <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic>, needs to be considered (<xref rid="b75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). Ablation of myeloid-derived suppressor cell effects by all-trans-retinoic acid in a susceptible mouse model of tuberculosis points to the potential of host-directed therapy of aberrant myeloid-derived suppressor cell responses as an adjunct to conventional drug treatment of tuberculosis (<xref rid="b75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>).</p><p>IL-1&#x003b1; and IL-1&#x003b2; have been shown recently to inhibit type I IFN induction in mouse and human macrophages, and when IL-1 was present in type I IFN-treated cultures, it also suppressed the pro-bacterial effects downstream of IFN&#x003b2;. IL-1-induced prostaglandin E2 (PGE2) was also able to potently inhibit type I IFNs in this context (<xref rid="b76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>). Moreover, targeting PGE2 during <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> infection, either via direct administration of the prostanoid or enhancement by 5-lipoxygenase blockade with zileuton reversed polyI:C-mediated type I IFN-driven mortality (<xref rid="b76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>). This has major implications for the use of zileuton for host-directed therapy to improve and possibly speed-up the current drug treatment of tuberculosis (<xref rid="b76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>). The use of the blood transcriptome (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) to monitor effective treatment is likely to be a good supportive approach in clinical trials that utilize these immunomodulators.</p><p>Although high levels of type I IFN may be detrimental to the outcome of <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> infection, it is likely that low levels at the initiation of an immune response, or in particular settings, may be protective against this pathogen. For example, in experiments using <italic>Ifngr</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup><italic>Ifnar1</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, IFN&#x003b1;/&#x003b2; is suggested to contribute to host protection in the absence of the IFN&#x003b3; pathway (<xref rid="b77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>). Furthermore, naturally occurring mutations in host-protective <italic>ISG15</italic> in humans suggests that IFN&#x003b1;/&#x003b2; can induce host-protective responses to mycobacterial infection, although it is not clear under what circumstances IFN&#x003b1;/&#x003b2; induces this gene during <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> infection (<xref rid="b78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>). Regardless, many studies demonstrate a dominant IFN-inducible signature of active tuberculosis (<xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="b63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="b70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>, <xref rid="b76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>), and it is possible that Type I IFN may contribute to disease progression, since it is higher in patients with the greatest radiographic lung disease (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) and is diminished upon effective treatment (<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Concluding remarks</title><p>Evidence to date demonstrates that blood transcriptomics present a robust approach for studying the immune response in tuberculosis and other diseases, as similar findings have now been reported from various groups in different geographical locations. The findings offer information as to the immune response underlying the pathogenesis of tuberculosis and may provide tools toward diagnosis, treatment monitoring, and in the development of host-directed therapy regimens to support drug treatment. The potential use of blood transcriptomics in the clinical management of tuberculosis is likely to support current diagnostic tests and may help to speed up diagnosis and treatment, thus reducing transmission. The development of clinic-friendly tools for supporting the diagnosis of tuberculosis and treatment monitoring have been suggested to rely on a set of discriminant classifiers (consisting of between 12 and 100 genes) that would be easily convertible into a PCR-based affordable assay, allowing its development in the clinic for tuberculosis diagnosis. Meta-analyses of diverse studies on the blood transcriptome of tuberculosis, in the context of other infectious or non-communicable diseases, are required to determine the unifying signature reflecting tuberculosis versus other diseases and the blood signature for tuberculosis treatment success. It is possible with advancing technology and decreasing pricing that a composite whole genome expression profile, obtained using either microarray or in the future RNA-Seq, may be useable rather than discriminant classifiers. This will require the development of sophisticated tools for rapid integration of complex host transcriptional signatures, the clinical data and the pathogen identification, and storage and easy access to such data. Advancement of bioinformatics tools (<xref rid="b37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) will also help in uncovering biological pathways underlying disease susceptibility, including co-infection, and also help to uncover the comorbidities caused by infectious and non-communicable diseases. This will require iterative research approaches between experimental models and human disease (<xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="b79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>) (<italic>Fig</italic>.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig07">7</xref>) to establish the function of immune and inflammatory pathways and molecules in resistance or susceptibility to <italic>M.&#x000a0;tuberculosis</italic> infection.</p><fig id="fig07" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Using a systems biology approach in infectious diseases. This figure defines the strategy for elucidating determinants of protection or disease in tuberculosis: an iterative process between human disease and experimental models. Modified from O'Garra <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>., 2013 (<xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>); O'Garra <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>., 2013 (<xref rid="b80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>); Berry <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>., 2013 (<xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>); Blankley <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>., 2014 (<xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="imr0264-0088-f7"/></fig></sec>