<p>Avian influenza A (H7N9) viruses emerged as a zoonotic respiratory disease in China in early 2013 [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. From February 2013 to October 2017, 1564 patients with H7N9 disease were reported, 612 of whom died, resulting in an overall case-fatality ratio of around 38% [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The infection can rapidly progress to severe pneumonia and acute respiratory distress syndrome. H7N9 virus pathogenesis was caused by multiple factors, including high viral replication, virus tropism for the lower respiratory tract, and dysregulation of the host innate immune responses [<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4&#x02013;6</xref>]. The measurement of blood oxygen levels reflects the extent of pulmonary dysfunction and is used by clinicians to assess disease severity [<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>Several studies have characterized peripheral blood transcriptional profiles of humans infected with influenza viruses and rhinoviruses, as well as respiratory syncytial viruses (RSV) [<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], and determined the relevant biological functions. Two similar studies have recently been carried out in patients with H7N9 virus infection. However, these studies were limited by the small numbers of samples studied (4 and 8 samples) and by a lack of association with detailed clinical parameters including viral load [<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>We aimed to identify host transcriptome responses associated with clinical and virological outcomes in patients with influenza A H7N9 infection in comparison with healthy controls. We adopted a novel strategy for transcriptomic analysis to identify genes that are strongly correlated with the Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> ratio (an indicator that reflects oxygen levels in the blood and lung function) and the viral load at the lower respiratory tract. Our results analyzed the regulation of systemic biological functions and pathways during acute and recovery phases of infection.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s5"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s6"><title>Patients</title><p>Eight patients with laboratory-confirmed low pathogenic avian influenza A (H7N9) virus infection admitted for care at the First Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University, from 2014 to 2016, were included in this study. The clinical history, physical examination, radiological findings, and hematological, biochemical, and microbiological investigations were recorded. Day 1 of clinical onset was defined as the first day of the appearance of clinical symptoms. The dates of admission, age, and clinical outcomes of these patients are tabulated in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>; and clinical and immunological features of some of these patients have been reported previously [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Approval for the study was obtained from the ethics committee of the First Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University (No: 2016&#x02013;78) and informed consent was obtained from the patients or their family members.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Detection of Virus Infection and Viral Load</title><p>Serial throat swabs, bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BALF), sputum, and endotracheal aspirates were collected, as clinically appropriate, throughout the period of hospitalization. The viral RNA from the samples was extracted and measured as previously described [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>RNA Purification From Peripheral Whole Blood</title><p>The peripheral whole blood samples (3 mL) were collected into Tempus tubes (Applied Biosystems) and the RNA was purified according to manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Gene Expression Profiling</title><p>Gene expression from whole blood samples was determined using Affymetrix Human Gene 2.0 ST following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Arrays were scanned by Affymetrix GeneChip Scanner 3000 (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA). Command Console Software (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA) was used to control the scanner and summarize probe cell intensity data (CEL file generation) with default settings. The raw data were then normalized by Expression Console. All raw and normalized microarray data has been deposited into the NCBI GEO database (Accession number: GSE114466).</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Data Analysis</title><p>The raw microarray data were normalized using robust multiarray average [<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Genes with expression that correlated with clinical measurement were identified using significance analysis of microarrays [<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], with a false discovery rate of 0.01 and a <italic>q</italic> value cutoff of 0.01. Calculation of molecular distance to health (MDTH) was adapted from a previously described methodology on a gene-by-gene basis [<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. MDTH outliers were defined as being 3 standard deviations away from the median. Outlier identification was performed iteratively until no further outliers could be identified. Gene ontology enrichment (GO) and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) pathways analysis was performed using the web interfaces <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geneontology.org">http://www.geneontology.org</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/kegg">http://www.genome.jp/kegg</ext-link>, respectively [<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. For computing the gene expression change per unit of clinical parameter, linear regression was performed to fit the clinical parameter of interest to the expression level of each gene using linregress function in Python library SciPy. The slope of the linear regression was taken as the gene expression change per unit of clinical parameter.</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Wilcoxon rank sum test was employed to compute the <italic>P</italic> value of the difference in MDTH between week 0 and week 2, 3, and 4. The default function cor.test in R software was employed to compute the <italic>P</italic> value of the Pearson correlation.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s12"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s13"><title>Demographics of the Patients With H7N9 Virus Infection</title><p>Eight patients who were admitted to the hospital from 2013 to 2016 were enrolled in this study. Clinical, virologic, and immunological features of each patient were recorded in detail. Six patients (No. 2, 4, 6, 7, 8, and 9) were discharged and 2 patients (No. 3 and 10) had a fatal outcome. Patients No. 1 and 5 were excluded as no sample was available for the transcriptomic study. All patients had laboratory-confirmed infection with low pathogenic influenza A (H7N9) viruses by reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction using specific HA primers. The demographic and clinical characteristics of the patients during their hospitalization are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>. Clinical parameters that were used by the clinicians to assist the diagnosis and treatment were recorded on the indicated days. Viral copy numbers were determined from the throat swab (defined as an upper respiratory tract specimen) and from BALF or endotracheal aspirate (defined as lower respiratory tract). Bacteria were identified from the sputum samples in each of the patient to investigate possible bacterial coinfection. Fifteen healthy donors served as controls where we assumed the viral loads in the upper and lower respiratory tracts were zero and their Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> values were 450.</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Differential Gene Expression Profile Between H7N9-Infected Patients and Healthy Controls</title><p>The gene expression profiles of the total RNA collected from the peripheral blood of the patients, each with multiple time points from the second to fourth week after disease onset (27 samples), were quantified by microarray analysis together with the samples of healthy individuals (15 samples). An overview of the data using principal component analysis showed that the gene expression profiles from the H7N9-infected patients formed a distinct cluster compared to the healthy control group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A&#x02013;</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>). The difference can be readily observed in the first 3 components, which together account for &#x0003e;50% of the variance of the data. We next computed the MDTH from each sample to see if it can be used to assess the clinical severity of the H7N9-infected patients (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1D</xref>). MDTH is a computational score derived from the full gene set of a blood transcriptomic profile and can provide a summary of overall deviation of gene expression compared to healthy controls. The use of MDTH score has been demonstrated previously to differentiate the severity of the disease in the studies such as pulmonary tuberculosis, septicemic melioidosis, and RSV infection [<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. We found that the MDTH scores derived from all patients&#x02019; samples were all higher than the normal controls. When we grouped the samples based on week after disease onset, the MDTH score from each week was also significantly higher than the control (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1E</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Overview of the microarray data. <italic>A</italic>&#x02013;<italic>C</italic>, First 3 components (PC1&#x02013;3) from principal component analysis of the gene expression profile are plotted. Ellipses represent 0.7 standard deviation from the mean value for the indicated categories (patient and control). <italic>D</italic>, The molecular distance to health (MDTH) for each sample is shown. <italic>E</italic>, Samples are categorized by week. The distribution of MDTH for each category is shown as a box plot. ** indicates a significant difference (<italic>P</italic> value &#x0003c; 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>, Wilcoxon rank sum test) compared to the control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jiy31701"/></fig></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Correlation Between the Blood Transcriptomic Profiling and Clinical Parameters of H7N9-Infected Patients</title><p>We then investigated if MDTH is associated with specific clinical parameters in the H7N9-infected patients. The correlations of MDTH with the values of different clinical parameters, including Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> ratio, viral loads in the upper (URT) and lower respiratory tract (LRT), procalcitonin (PCT), white cell count, neutrophil count, hemoglobin, aspartate aminotransferase, lactate dehydrogenase, creatine kinase, d-dimer, and urea, which were recorded on the same day as sampling, were examined by Pearson correlation test. We found that the MDTH correlated with most of the parameters except creatine kinase and viral load in the URT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). Among all the tested parameters, Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> ratio (Pearson correlation, &#x02212;0.73; <italic>P</italic> value 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup>) and viral load in LRT (Pearson correlation 0.51; <italic>P</italic> value .0012) were clearly known to associate with the pathogenesis of H7N9 virus during infection. We further aimed to identify genes from the blood transcriptomic profiles that were associated with the Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> ratio and viral load in LRT. We first examined whether there were any genes in the profile that showed a positive or negative correlation to the Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> ratio or viral load in LRT. Positive correlation means the expression of the gene increased when the value of the parameter increased, while negative correlation means the change in gene expression level was opposite to the change in the parameter. From our analysis, we found that there were 4788 and 2189 genes that were positively or negatively correlated with the Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> ratio, respectively. Similarly, 565 and 1845 genes were positively or negatively correlated with the viral load in the LRT, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>). During infection, the lung pathology could be caused by diverse factors, including replication of the virus, immune dysregulation, or bacterial coinfection. To specifically determine the host responses that were related to both H7N9 replication and lung dysfunction, we further identified 2 sets of genes with contrasting correlation to both Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> ratio and viral load in LRT : (1) negatively correlated to Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> ratio and positively correlated with viral load in LRT; and (2) positively correlated to Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> ratio and negatively correlated with viral load in LRT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>). This was based on the hypothesis that increasing viral load was likely to be associated with impaired lung function, that is decreased Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> ratio. Set 1 represents the genes activated during the acute phase of infection (oxygen level in blood decreased and viral load at the LRT increased) or deactivated during the recovery phase (oxygen level in blood increased and viral load at the LRT decreased). On the contrary, set 2 represents the opposite condition, that is genes deactivated during the acute phase of infection or activated during the recovery phase. From our analysis, 541 and 1803 genes corresponded to sets 1 and 2, respectively.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Correlation between molecular-distance-to-health (MDTH) and clinical parameters: <italic>A</italic>, Pao<sub>2</sub>/Fio<sub>2 ratio</sub>; <italic>B</italic>, lower respiratory tract (LRT) titer; <italic>C</italic>, upper respiratory tract (URT) titer; <italic>D</italic>, procalcitonin; <italic>E</italic>, hemoglobin; <italic>F</italic>, d-dimer. Control samples are blue; patient samples red. Pearson correlation and the corresponding <italic>P</italic> value are indicated. For controls, Pao<sub>2</sub>/Fio<sub>2</sub> was assumed to be 450; viral titer at the upper and lower respiratory tracts were set as 0. MDTH values of 4 data points, namely patient No. 2 (day 13), patient No. 2 (day 15), Patient No. 3 (day 21), and patient No. 3 (day 28), were identified as outliers (see Materials and Methods) and were excluded from this analysis. Therefore, each plot includes a total of 15 control samples and 23 patient samples.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jiy31702"/></fig><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.
</label><caption><p>Identification of genes with expression levels that correlated with clinical parameters. <italic>A</italic>, Number of genes identified with expression that showed a negative or positive correlation with clinical parameters of interest. <italic>B</italic>, Venn diagram showing numbers of genes which were identified from both the gene sets of Pao<sub>2</sub>/Fio<sub>2</sub> ratio and viral titer at the LRT.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jiy31703"/></fig></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Differential Systemic Host Responses at the Acute and Recovery Phase of H7N9 Infection</title><p>We further performed GO analysis to investigate the biological and functional processes that were associated with the 2 overlapping gene sets. The genes which were identified from both the gene sets of negative Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> and positive viral load in LRT correlation (set 1) could be clustered into 2 groups of biological processes: cell cycle regulation and leukocyte functions (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). On the other hand, T-cell&#x02013;related functions and metabolic processes were the top ranks of GO terms in the overlapping gene set with positive Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> and negative viral load at LRT correlation (set 2) (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Interestingly, few interferon-activated gene expression functions were identified from our data sets, although there was strong evidence of virus shedding in the LRT at the day of sampling. Because a recent study has shown that expression of the gene <italic>IFI27</italic> is upregulated in seasonal influenza infection and is a biomarker that discriminates influenza from bacterial infections, we specifically looked its expression in our data set [<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. <italic>IFI27</italic> and the related <italic>IFI27L1</italic> were two of the interferon pathway-associated genes upregulated in our patients; they were negatively correlated with Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> and positively correlated with higher virus load in the LRT, but were not correlated with PCT, which has been suggested as a biomarker for bacterial infection.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Gene Ontology (GO) Functional Enrichment of Genes With Negative Correlation to Pao<sub>2</sub>/Fio<sub>2</sub> Ratio and Positive Correlation to Viral Load in the Lower Respiratory Tract</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO Term</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO Biological Process</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold Enrichment</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leukocyte-related functions</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0043299</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leukocyte degranulation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.99</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.09E-31</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0043312</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophil degranulation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.81E-30</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0002275</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myeloid cell activation involved in immune response</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.87</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.37E-30</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0002283</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophil activation involved in immune response</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.36E-30</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0002446</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophil mediated immunity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.92</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15E-29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0042119</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophil activation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.93</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04E-29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0002444</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myeloid leukocyte mediated immunity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.77</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75E-29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0036230</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Granulocyte activation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59E-29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0002274</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myeloid leukocyte activation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.14E-29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0002366</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leukocyte activation involved in immune response</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13E-28</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell cycle-related functions</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0031536</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive regulation of exit from mitosis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.92</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.000838</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0031577</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spindle checkpoint</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.27</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00000545</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0007094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitotic spindle assembly checkpoint</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0000366</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0071174</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitotic spindle checkpoint</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0000366</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0071173</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spindle assembly checkpoint</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0000366</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0051782</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative regulation of cell division</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.96</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.000891</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0045841</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative regulation of mitotic metaphase/anaphase transition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.96</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0000449</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:1902100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative regulation of metaphase/anaphase transition of cell cycle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.52</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0000547</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0030071</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of mitotic metaphase/anaphase transition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0000000152</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0090307</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitotic spindle assembly</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0000000646</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-01"><p>Top 10 processes were selected from each group.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Gene Ontology (GO) Functional Enrichment of Genes With Positive Correlation to Pao<sub>2</sub>/Fio<sub>2</sub> Ratio and Negative Correlation to Viral Load in the Lower Respiratory Tract</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO Term</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO Biological Process</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold Enrichment</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolic-related functions</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0016070</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNA metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13E-28</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0090304</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleic acid metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48E-28</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0044260</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular macromolecule metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03E-26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006139</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleobase-containing compound metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66E-25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0046483</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterocycle metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11E-24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006725</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular aromatic compound metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.81E-24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0043170</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Macromolecule metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71E-23</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0060255</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of macromolecule metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77E-23</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0034641</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular nitrogen compound metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74E-23</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0044237</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellular metabolic process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.69E-23</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-cell&#x02013;related functions</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0045061</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thymic T-cell selection</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000658</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0043368</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive T-cell selection</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000154</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0045058</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-cell selection</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000000144</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0002293</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpha-beta T-cell differentiation involved in immune response</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000211</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0002287</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpha-beta T-cell activation involved in immune response</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000211</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0046632</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpha-beta T-cell differentiation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000000944</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0031295</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-cell costimulation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00000000399</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0042093</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-helper&#x02013;cell differentiation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000642</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0002294</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD4-positive, alpha-beta T-cell differentiation involved in immune response</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000642</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0031294</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphocyte costimulation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00000000503</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0002"><p>Top 10 processes were selected from each group</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Our results illustrated the differential systemic host responses in the 2 phases of H7N9 infection. In the acute stage (Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> decreased and viral load increased) the cell cycle regulation and leukocyte functions were activated, while T-cell&#x02013;related functions and metabolic processes were deactivated. In the recovery stage (Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> increased and viral load decreased) T-cell responses and metabolic processes were dominant but the cell cycle and leukocyte functions were suppressed. Overlapping gene sets were also identified between Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> and either procalcitonin, d-dimer, or hemoglobin using a similar analysis. Interestingly, although differential biological processes were found from these gene sets in the acute phase of infection, T-cell&#x02013;related functions and metabolic processes were both enriched at the recovery phase (data not shown).</p><p>We then performed KEGG pathway analysis from the 2 overlapping gene sets between Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> and viral load in LRT to identify the pathways that involve products of these genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). Interestingly, pathways related to systemic lupus erythematosus and alcoholism were strongly enriched (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>). The cell cycle pathway was consistently identified from the overlapping gene set of negative Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> and positive viral load in LRT (set 1) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4C</xref>). On the other hand, the pathways related to the different immune responses, especially those associated with adaptive immunity, were significantly enriched in the overlapping gene set of positive Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> and negative viral load at LRT (set 2) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Top 20 Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) pathways for each of the gene sets. Negative log-transformed adjusted <italic>P</italic> values for each of the top 20 KEGG pathways are plotted for (<italic>A</italic>) the overlapping gene set with negative Pao<sub>2</sub>/Fio<sub>2</sub> and positive viral load at LRT correlation; and (<italic>B</italic>) the overlapping gene set with positive Pao<sub>2</sub>/Fio<sub>2</sub> and negative viral load at LRT correlation. Red lines indicate an adjusted <italic>P</italic> value cutoff of 0.05. Bars are arranged in a descending order of negative log-transformed adjusted <italic>P</italic> values. A higher negative log-transformed adjusted <italic>P</italic> value indicates greater change in the corresponding pathway. Schematic gene pathways of (<italic>C</italic>) cell cycle and (<italic>D</italic>) T-cell receptor signaling with genes identified from our analysis marked with yellow.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jiy31704"/><graphic xlink:href="jiy31704a"/></fig><p>Finally, we identified genes from sets 1 and 2 that were significantly sensitive to the change in Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> ratio and viral load in LRT. A linear regression analysis was performed to compute the change in gene expression level per unit of the 2 parameters. Genes with <italic>R</italic> values higher than 0.4 and <italic>P</italic> value lower than .05 were considered as significant. The selected genes that were related to our identified biological processes are shown in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. In the gene group represented by the acute stage of infection, <italic>CD177</italic> and <italic>MMP9</italic> were found to be the most sensitive genes to those parameters. Consistent with the results from GO and KEGG analysis, a group of T-cell&#x02013;related genes, including <italic>TRAV12-2</italic>, <italic>TRAJ17</italic>, <italic>CD28</italic>, <italic>TRAT1</italic>, and <italic>THEMIS</italic>, were mainly activated during the improvement of Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> ratio and viral load in LRT. Interestingly, genes related to natural killer cell-mediated cytotoxicity, including <italic>KLRB1</italic>, <italic>KLRF1</italic>, <italic>KLRD1</italic>, <italic>KLRC3</italic>, <italic>KLRG1</italic>, and <italic>KLRC1</italic>, were identified, which was in line with the results of KEGG analysis.</p><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Sensitivity of Genes to Pao<sub>2</sub>/Fio<sub>2</sub> and Viral Load in the Lower Respiratory Tract (LRT)</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Description</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Change per Unit of Pao<sub>2</sub>/Fio<sub>2</sub></th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pearson Correlation <italic>R</italic></th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> Value</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Change per Unit of Viral Load in LRT</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pearson Correlation <italic>R</italic></th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="8" rowspan="1">Genes with negative correlation to Pao<sub>2</sub>/Fio<sub>2</sub> and positive correlation to viral load in LRT (set 1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>CD177</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD177 molecule</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.67E-31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9987</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78E-22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>MMP9</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matrix metallopeptidase 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0120</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.74E-08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8881</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.98E-06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>ALPL</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alkaline phosphatase, liver/ bone/kidney</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0088</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43E-05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6733</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62E-04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>IL1R2</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interleukin 1 receptor, type II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0092</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.94E-07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6154</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28E-04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>MGAM2</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maltase-glucoamylase 2 (putative)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34E-65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5873</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.49E-33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>TNFAIP6</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor necrosis factor, alpha-induced protein 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0072</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.55E-06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5779</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30E-05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>MMP8</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matrix metallopeptidase 8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.87E-08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.04E-03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>ARG1</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arginase 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0087</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.51E-09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4739</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.40E-04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>CXCR1</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chemokine (C-X-C motif) receptor 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13E-03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4281</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38E-03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>MMP25</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matrix metallopeptidase 25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0052</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34E-05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3748</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.30E-04</td></tr><tr><td colspan="8" rowspan="1">Genes with positive correlation to Pao<sub>2</sub>/Fio<sub>2</sub> and negative correlation to viral load in LRT (set 2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>KLRB1</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Killer cell lectin-like receptor subfamily B, member 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0088</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.02E-13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.5407</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.98E-06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>KLRF1</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Killer cell lectin-like receptor subfamily F, member 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0089</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.60E-12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.4472</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.77E-04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>TRAV12-2</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-cell receptor alpha variable 12-2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0062</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74E-06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.3893</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.84E-04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>KLRD1</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Killer cell lectin-like receptor subfamily D, member 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0070</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.52E-13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.3847</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.99E-05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>KLRC3</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Killer cell lectin-like receptor subfamily C, member 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0073</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95E-10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.3836</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.83E-04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>TRAJ17</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-cell receptor alpha joining 17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0060</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14E-07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.3760</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12E-04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>KLRG1</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Killer cell lectin-like receptor subfamily G, member 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0064</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.01E-11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.3714</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25E-05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>CD28</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD28 molecule</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0061</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.55E-10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.3632</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05E-04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>TRAT1</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-cell receptor associated transmembrane adaptor 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0053</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.45E-09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.3428</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.60E-05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>CD3G</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD3g molecule, gamma (CD3- TCR complex)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0053</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.57E-08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.3421</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.12E-05</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s17"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Traditionally, biological functions were determined from blood transcriptomic analysis using the whole gene set identified from the sample. The results were then correlated with &#x0201c;time&#x0201d; and the changes were characterized during the disease progression. However, we believed that phenotypic measurements (ie, clinical parameters) are a more reliable assessment for the condition of a patient because one could expect that progression of a disease is likely to vary among individuals. In respiratory infection, the Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> ratio measured in the blood and the viral load in the respiratory tract are both useful quantitative parameters to determine disease severity [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. One technical advantage of our approach is that samples do not need to be collected at fixed time points after admission, which is anyway not correlated with the time after onset of disease. Instead, the use of clinical parameters can enable a correlation analysis by pulling together all time points from all individuals. Two patients had a fatal outcome and both of them required extracorporeal membrane oxygenation. However, we did not find genes or MDTH that were associated with, or predictive of, this outcome. Indeed, the disease outcome of a patient can be affected by multiple factors, including the clinical practice, response to the treatment, secondary infections, or unexpected complications. The transcriptomic host responses associated with a fatal outcome need to be identified by a larger cohort with similar sample collection criteria. Our analysis, therefore, has the limitation that it does not provide predictive host responses that are associated with an adverse outcome. Instead, our approach analyzed and identified gene expression associated with 2 key clinical parameters: Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> and viral load in the LRT, which are closely related to disease severity but may not invariably be linked to disease outcome (recovered patients can also have low Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> value and high viral load at some stages of their illness). We found that MDTH correlated well with viral load at the LRT but not in the URT, which is understandable for a virus such as H7N9 that causes a primary viral pneumonia. Because dysregulation of proinflammatory cytokines has been shown to be associated with the pathogenesis of avian influenza H7N9 in humans and experimental animal models, it would be interesting to examine possible correlations between cytokine responses in plasma and gene expression levels (as well as MDTH) in blood in future studies [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21&#x02013;24</xref>].</p><p>Our data showed that the activities of neutrophil during the acute phase of infection were associated with the viral infection. Neutrophils are involved in various lung diseases [<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. A neutrophil response has long been considered a marker of bacterial infection [<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. However, rapid recruitment of neutrophils to the lung was seen in naive mice after nasal inoculation with avian influenza viruses [<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. These results suggest that infection with avian influenza viruses can also lead to recruitment and activation of neutrophils in the lung. Our study found that <italic>CD177</italic> was the most sensitive to both the Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> ratio and the viral load in LRT. CD177 (NB-1) is a glycophosphatidylinositol-anchored protein, which is responsible for mediating the migration, degranulation, and superoxide generation by neutrophils during inflammation [<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Activation of matrix metalloproteinase (MMP) 8, 9, and 25 were also found during the acute phase of H7N9 infection. A case-control study indicated that mRNA levels of MMP8 and MMP9 in peripheral blood mononuclear cells increased in children with LRT infection compared to healthy subjects [<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. It has been shown that MMP9 plays a role in regulating phagocytosis and reactive oxygen species production in neutrophils [<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. It is also interesting that cell cycle-related processes were strongly associated with the change in viral load in the lower lung during H7N9 infection. A previous transcriptomic study also noted cell cycle perturbations in the peripheral blood specimens collected from patients with severe seasonal influenza infection [<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Although cell cycle pathways were also found to be activated in other studies, their significance was masked by other biological processes such as bacteria-related or immunological pathways when the data were analyzed without association with specific clinical parameters, as has been done in this study [<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Our results suggest that activation of cell cycle processes maybe a hallmark of severe influenza virus infection.</p><p>Interferons and interferon-activated pathways are important to control viral infection. A clinical study in seasonal influenza virus infections showed that activation of these pathways was reduced dramatically at around day 6 after disease onset [<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Our study could not identify significant activation of interferon related pathways (with the exception of IFI27) even though we could still clearly observe virus shedding in the lower lung. Thus, our findings are compatible with interferon pathways being activated at early stages of infection but being downregulated fairly quickly. However, it should be noted that we did not have specimens available for transcriptomic analysis in the first week of illness. Specimens collected earlier in the course of illness will be needed in order to test this hypothesis. Interestingly, a previous blood transcriptomic study from 4 H7N9 patients (with 1 sample from each patient) showed a GO enrichment of &#x0201c;Suppression by virus of host interferon receptor activity (GO:0039511)&#x0201d; [<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. However, that study did not provide details on day of illness in relation to sampling and data on severity of illness were lacking. Thus we could not make a direct comparison with our data. While studies using animals such as mice and macaques all showed that H7N9 could effectively trigger the interferon pathways in the lung during the early stage of infection [<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37&#x02013;39</xref>], it is also possible that interferon activities were only localized in the lung of the patients during the H7N9 infection.</p><p>A recent study has shown that the expression of the gene <italic>IFI27</italic> is upregulated in seasonal influenza infection and is a biomarker that discriminates influenza from bacterial infections [<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. We therefore specifically looked for the expression of <italic>IFI27</italic> in our data set. Expression of <italic>IFI27</italic> and the related <italic>IFI27L1</italic> were two of the interferon pathway-associated genes that were upregulated in our cohort of H7N9 infected patients. It was negatively correlated with Pao
<sub>2</sub>/Fio
<sub>2</sub> (gene expression increases with lower lung oxygenation) and a positively correlated with higher virus load in the LRT. Interestingly, the expression of <italic>IFI27</italic> was not correlated with PCT. <italic>ILI27</italic> has been reported to be expressed primarily by plasmacytoid dendritic cells in response to viral infection [<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>It has been shown that patients with H7N9 disease who were discharged earlier from hospital had better T-cell and natural killer (NK) cell recruitment and antibody induction [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Our transcriptomic analysis supported their findings in that T-cell processes including selection, differentiation, and stimulation were activated during the recovery phase of H7N9 infection. Other than T-cells&#x02013;specific genes, a group of genes from the killer cell lectin-like receptor subfamily, which are expressed on the surface of T and NK cells, were also activated during the recovery stage. These proteins have been shown to regulate diverging functions of T, NK, and &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T cells during infection. For example, previous study have showed that V&#x003b3;9V&#x003b4;2 T cells, which express KLRG1, can effective kill influenza virus-infected cells [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s18"><title>Supplementary Data</title><p>Supplementary materials are available at <italic>The Journal of Infectious Diseases</italic> online. Consisting of data provided by the authors to benefit the reader, the posted materials are not copyedited and are the sole responsibility of the authors, so questions or comments should be addressed to the corresponding author.</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1"><label>Supplementary Table 1</label><media xlink:href="jiy317_suppl_sup_table1.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup2"><label>Supplementary Fig 1</label><media xlink:href="jiy317_suppl_sup_fig1.jpeg"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup3"><label>Supplementary Figure Legend</label><media xlink:href="jiy317_suppl_supplementary_figure_legend.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec>