
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">1287506</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16336051</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0030422</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Evolution</subject><subject>Zoology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Molluscs</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>DNA Barcoding: Error Rates Based on Comprehensive Sampling </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Barcoding Error Rates</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>Christopher P</given-names></name><email>cmeyer@flmnh.ufl.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Paulay</surname><given-names>Gustav</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><bold>1</bold>Florida Museum of Natural History, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, United States of America</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Godfray</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><institution>Imperial College at Silwood Park</institution><country>United Kingdom</country></aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e422</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>7</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2005 Meyer and Paulay.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e126" related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pbio.0030435" xlink:title="synopsis" vol="3" page="e435">
<article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>DNA Barcodes Perform Best with Well-Characterized Taxa </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title>
</related-article><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>DNA barcoding has attracted attention with promises to aid in species identification and discovery; however, few well-sampled datasets are available to test its performance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>We provide the first examination of barcoding performance in a comprehensively sampled, diverse group (cypraeid marine gastropods, or cowries). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>We utilize previous methods for testing performance and employ a novel phylogenetic approach to calculate intraspecific variation and interspecific divergence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Error rates are estimated for (1) identifying samples against a well-characterized phylogeny, and (2) assisting in species discovery for partially known groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We find that the lowest overall error for species identification is 4%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>In contrast, barcoding performs poorly in incompletely sampled groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Here, species delineation relies on the use of thresholds, set to differentiate between intraspecific variation and interspecific divergence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Whereas proponents envision a “barcoding gap” between the two, we find substantial overlap, leading to minimal error rates of ~17% in cowries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Moreover, error rates double if only traditionally recognized species are analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Thus, DNA barcoding holds promise for identification in taxonomically well-understood and thoroughly sampled clades. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>However, the use of thresholds does not bode well for delineating closely related species in taxonomically understudied groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The promise of barcoding will be realized only if based on solid taxonomic foundations. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>An examination of the efficacy of barcoding using a comprehensive sample of marine gastropods reveals that the method performs poorly for identifying closely related species in taxonomically understudied groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s1a"><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The Controversy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>DNA barcoding, the recently proposed DNA-based project for species identification, has attracted much attention and controversy [1–6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Proponents envision that a short fragment of DNA can be used to diagnose taxa, increasing the speed, objectivity, and efficiency of species identification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Initial tests of genetic barcoding using mitochondrial markers on animals reported near-100% accuracy, indicating that the method can be highly accurate under certain conditions [1,7,8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Accurate species identification—assignment of an unknown to a known—requires a comprehensive comparative molecular database against which unknowns can be compared. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>However, it is clear that most of the biological diversity in the world is undocumented [9,10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Therefore, a stated second goal of DNA barcoding is to facilitate the species-discovery process [11–13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Such a proposal has raised the concern of the systematics community, which claims that adopting barcoding would be a step backwards [14–16], returning taxonomy to typology [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Opponents also note that mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) sequences alone may be insufficient to diagnose species, because genetic differentiation does not necessarily track species boundaries [18,19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Thus, Funk and Omland [20] found that ca. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>23% of surveyed metazoan species are genetically polyphyletic or paraphyletic, implying that they would not be differentiable by barcoding techniques. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s1b"><title><text><SENT sid="26" pm="?"><plain>What Does Accuracy Depend on? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The Barcoding “Gap” </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The critical issue in barcoding is accuracy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="?"><plain>How well does a single gene sequence perform in delineating and identifying species? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Accuracy depends especially on the extent of, and separation between, intraspecific variation and interspecific divergence in the selected marker. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The more overlap there is between genetic variation within species and divergence separating sister species, the less effective barcoding becomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Initial efforts to test barcoding suggested a significant barcoding “gap” between intra- and interspecific variation, but these efforts have greatly undersampled both intraspecific variation (mostly 1–2 individuals per species sampled) and interspecific divergence (because of incomplete or geographically restricted sampling) [1,7,8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s1c"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Overlap between Intra- versus Interspecific Variation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>When the coalescent has yet to sort between incipient species (ancestral polymorphism), intraspecific variation overlaps with interspecific divergence and gives rise to genetically polyphyletic or paraphyletic species (Figure 1) [18,21,22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>When such overlap is real (i.e., not the result of poor taxonomy), then that marker cannot reliably distinguish among those species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Overlap between intraspecific and interspecific variation can also occur broadly within a tree, even when each species is reciprocally monophyletic to all others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>This occurs when intraspecific variation in parts of the tree exceeds interspecific divergence in other parts of the tree—i.e., when the range of intra- and interspecific variation overlaps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Such overlap will not affect identification of unknowns in a thoroughly sampled tree, where they should fall within the coalescent of already characterized species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>However, such overlap can have a substantial impact during the discovery phase (i.e., in an incompletely sampled group), as the status of unknowns that fall outside the coalescent of previously sampled species is problematic to evaluate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pbio-0030422-g001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic Relationships and Terminology </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>(A) Reciprocal monophyly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Members of each species share a unique common ancestor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>For each species, the white star represents the coalescent, the point at which all extant haplotypes share a common ancestry. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>(B) Paraphyly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>One species (Y), is monophyletic, but nests within another recognized species (X). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Thus, the coalescent of species Y (small star) is contained within the coalescent of species X (large star). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>(C) Polyphyly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Neither species X or Y are monophyletic, and both coalesce to the white star. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0030422.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s1d"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Gap versus Overlap: The Efficacy of Thresholds </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The proposed mechanism for the evaluation of unknowns within a partially sampled phylogeny is through the implementation of thresholds, chosen to separate intraspecific variation from interspecific differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>An unknown differing from an existing sample by less than a threshold value is assumed to represent that species, but one differing from existing sequences by more than the threshold value is assumed to represent a new taxon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>This method is vulnerable to both false positives and false negatives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>False positives are the identification of spurious novel taxa (splitting) within a species whose intraspecific variation extends deeper than the threshold value; false negatives are inaccurate identification (lumping) within a cluster of taxa whose interspecific divergences are shallower than the proposed value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The accuracy of a threshold-based approach critically depends upon the level of overlap between intra- and interspecific variation across a phylogeny. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>While Hebert et al. [7] suggest that a wide gap between intra- and interspecific variation makes a threshold approach promising (Figure 2A), Moritz and Cicero [23] argue that the overlap is considerably greater when a larger proportion of closely related taxa are included, making the method problematic (Figure 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the performance of this method, we need to assess the extent of and overlap between intra- and interspecific genetic variation comprehensively, within a thoroughly sampled clade [23,24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pbio-0030422-g002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Schematic of the Inferred Barcoding Gap </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The distribution of intraspecific variation is shown in red, and interspecific divergence in yellow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>(A) Ideal world for barcoding, with discrete distributions and no overlap. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>(B) An alternative version of the world with significant overlap and no gap. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0030422.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Here we present the first dataset sufficiently comprehensive to robustly evaluate the efficacy of DNA barcoding: the cowrie genetic database [25,26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>This dataset includes sequences from &gt;2,000 individuals in 263 taxa, representing &gt;93% of recognized cowrie (marine gastropods of the family Cypraeidae) species worldwide, with multiple individuals from &gt;80%, and at least five individuals from &gt;50% of the taxa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>These data provide near comprehensive sister-species coverage, and a broad survey of intraspecific variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>We use this dataset to address several questions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="?"><plain>How accurate is molecular identification of unknowns in a thoroughly sampled tree? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="?"><plain>What are the reasons for failures in such identifications? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="?"><plain>How much do intraspecific variation and interspecific divergence overlap across this well-sampled phylogeny? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="?"><plain>How much error is associated with threshold-based identifications, and what threshold value minimizes this error? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Finally we use data from two smaller but similarly exhaustively sampled clades (of limpets [27] and turbinid gastropods [28]), to evaluate the generality of these patterns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Cowries encompass a diversity of species attributes: recent versus ancient, planktonic versus direct development, common versus rare, and large Indo-west Pacific-wide ranges versus single island endemics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>All cowries have internal fertilization, mostly with feeding larvae, whereas limpets and turbinids are external fertilizers, with non-feeding larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>While all three examples are gastropods, their range of species attributes implies that these findings are likely applicable to a wide range of taxa. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The effectiveness of barcoding is critically dependent upon species delineation: splitting decreases while lumping increases both intraspecific variation and interspecific divergence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Taxonomically, cowries are one of the most extensively studied marine gastropod families, both morphologically [29–33] and genetically [25,26], thus their species are well circumscribed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>We analyze and compare barcoding performance for two types of species-level taxa based on different levels of taxonomic analysis: (1) traditional, morphological species, as defined by the most recent morphology-based revision [33], and (2) evolutionary significant units (ESUs), as defined through an integrative taxonomic analysis of combined and extensively sampled genetic and morphological data (slightly modified from [25,26]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>We thus compare the efficacy of barcoding across a 2 × 2 matrix: performance with traditional species versus ESUs in an identification versus discovery setting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Traditional species provide a test of barcoding when substantial morphological information is available, but remain untested with genetic tools. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>This level of knowledge is comparable to biotic checklists, which are often used to guide sampling in barcoding efforts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>In contrast, ESUs provide the best of integrative taxonomy, a system where population-level and geographically extensive genetic sampling has tested species-level boundaries described by extensive morphological studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Because ESUs are defined as reciprocally monophyletic units, they exclude the possibility of, and errors associated with, paraphyletic or polyphyletic species, and thus provide the optimal units for barcoding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Given that at present their reciprocal monophyletic status is based on the same genetic marker used for barcoding, they should lead to 100% accuracy in species identification tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Presently, cowrie ESUs exclude potentially valid, young species that are not reciprocally monophyletic in cytochrome c oxidase I (COI) sequences; however, additional work may demonstrate some of these to be valid species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>ESUs fulfill the phylogenetic species concept; however, we choose to recognize them only as ESUs, to emphasize that although they are genetically divergent and distinctive, they all are not, or destined to become, biological species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The correspondence between ESU definitions and traditional morphological taxonomy is high. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, 255 ESUs (97%) have been recognized previously at either the specific or subspecific level and are therefore supported by independent morphological criteria in addition to molecular data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Only eight ESUs are genetically distinct but have not been previously recognized by traditional taxonomy; all of these are allopatric, genetically divergent lineages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>So defined, the 263 ESUs sampled include &gt;93% of the 233 recognized cowrie species and 56 recognized subspecies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>From here on, we use “ESU” to denote taxa recognized through an integrated approach with the aid of molecular criteria, and “species” to refer to taxa recognized at that level in traditional cowrie taxonomy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The same definition led to the recognition of 12 ESUs in the Patelloida profunda group of limpets [27] and 30 ESUs in the Astralium rhodostomum complex of turbinid gastropods [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>In both groups traditional taxonomic study lags substantially behind cowries, and many ESUs represent undescribed, but morphologically recognizable, species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Results/Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Accuracy in Thoroughly Sampled Phylogenies: Identification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Identification of unknowns against a thoroughly sampled phylogeny was prone to error when traditional species were utilized, but accurate when ESUs formed the basis of the phylogeny. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Assignment of unknowns to a phylogeny comprised of exemplars of every traditional species was correct 80% of the time using a neighbor-joining approach (see Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Eight percent of the assignments were incorrect, while 12% were ambiguous, with the unknown falling as sister to a clade comprised of its species plus its sister species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Parsimony analyses were unambiguously correct 79%, incorrect 7%, and ambiguous 10% of the time, while the correct placement was one of multiple, equally parsimonious placements in 4% of the cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Ambiguous assignments also represent failures of the barcoding method, as although the unknowns “belong” to sampled species, they fall outside of that species as characterized by an exemplar approach, and could represent a novel taxon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>This approximately 20% failure rate at the species level is consistent with Funk and Omland's [20] assessment that 23% of metazoan species are not monophyletic. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>In contrast, identification of unknowns was 98% accurate with a neighbor-joining approach against an ESU phylogeny. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Similar analyses of turbinid and limpet datasets had success rates of 100% and 99%, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>These results are not unexpected, however, as the reciprocal monophyly criteria for circumscribing units predisposed the system for success. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>More surprising is the 2% failure rate (1% each from incorrect assignment and ambiguity). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>In these incorrect identifications, improper assignment involved a recently derived sister ESU. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>These failures occur because only a single exemplar was used to define ESUs in the phylogenies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The rooting of the three-taxon arrangement between the sample, correct ESU, and sister ESU is tenuous, and vulnerable to artifacts of incomplete sampling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>If all sequenced haplotypes were included in the analyses, the unknown would have been correctly assigned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, these high success rates are encouraging, particularly since only a single exemplar was used for comparison [34], and many of the divergences between sister taxa are shallow. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="?"><plain>What are the sources for the 20% failure rate in species-level analyses? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Non-monophyly at the species level leads to barcoding failure both in thoroughly sampled and threshold approaches, and represents the greatest challenge for the method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Funk and Omland [20] recognize five reasons for species-level non-monophyly; two of these account for most non-monophyly in cowries: imperfect taxonomy and incomplete lineage sorting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Imperfect taxonomy can cause non-monophyly either through lack of recognition of multiple taxa within a traditional species (overlumping) or when morphotypes are inappropriately recognized as species (oversplitting). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Overlumping is common in cowries and readily identified via thorough genetic sampling: 16 recognized cowrie species (7%) are nested ESUs within other, paraphyletic species comprised of multiple ESUs (e.g., Palmadusta artuffeli within P. clandestina; Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Oversplitting is more difficult to resolve because young species that remain within their sister species' coalescent lead to the same polyphyletic, genetic signature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Of 218 traditional cowrie species tested [25,26], 18 (8%) are polyphyletic with respect to another recognized species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>These are either young species (incomplete lineage sorting), or artificially split forms (imperfect taxonomy); additional research is needed to resolve their status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Note that such young species are also neglected by the ESU approach and represent the ultimate limit for barcoding: non-monophyly that cannot be eliminated at the marker (COI) used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pbio-0030422-g003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Intraspecific and Interspecific Estimations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>A subclade of five cowrie ESUs shows how both coalescent and divergence depths are generated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The two most disparate individuals are culled from within each ESU (left—red) and used in a constrained phylogeny with a molecular clock enforced (right) to recover both the maximum coalescent depth (red) and the divergence depths between sisters (yellow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Two young ESUs (stars) would be missed (false negatives) if a 3% threshold cutoff (shown) was employed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Note that Palmadusta artuffeli, a Japanese endemic species, is nested among monophyletic subspecies of the paraphyletic species P. clandestina. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The black circle indicates the coalescent for the species P. clandestina, and the black star indicates the interspecific divergence for species-level analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0030422.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Using the ESU concept in hindsight, we can ascribe the failures in our species-level test to artifacts of paraphyly or polyphyly (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Ten percent of the failures can be attributed to overlumped, paraphyletic species, while nine percent are the results of either oversplit or young (incompletely sorted) polyphyletic species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The remaining 1% is real error based on single exemplars of the type mentioned previously. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The other three causes of species non-monophyly (inadequate phylogenetic information, unrecognized paralogy, and introgression) identified by Funk and Omland [20] are of minor importance in these studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Since all three gastropod datasets are well circumscribed using morphological, anatomical, geographic, and molecular attributes, we have minimized the problems of inadequate phylogenetic information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>We can estimate error rates associated with paralogy and the presence of nuclear copies of mtDNA (NUMTs; [35]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>In generating sequence data for 2,026 cowrie individuals, seven sequences (0.3%) have been generated that are thought to be NUMTs, all within three species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Low levels of NUMTs (&lt;1%) were also reported by Hebert et al. [12] in their study of Astraptes butterflies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>NUMTs can be problematic in some taxa (e.g., [36]), but their presence is usually ascertained by translation shifts in amino acid patterns or signal deterioration in electropherograms derived from non-cloned products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The final source of non-monophyly is introgression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Hybrid individuals have been reported within cowries, and indeed, mtDNA data reveal that individuals assigned conchologically to certain species or subspecies possess haplotypes of closely related lineages, indicating some past introgressive or hybridization event. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Using only mtDNA sequences, these individuals would be identified incorrectly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="?"><plain>How frequently does this occur? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Less than 2% of cowrie individuals, 1% of turbinids, and 0% of limpets possess COI sequences inconsistent with their morphology, indicating that the impact of introgression has been minor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, this low frequency should be included in error estimation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Therefore, our overall empirical error in the best of situations (ESUs) for species identification is 4%–12%: 2% because of the use of single exemplars, 2% from introgression, and 0%–8% from polyphyletic species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Accuracy in Undersampled Phylogenies Using Thresholds: Discovery </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the efficacy of thresholds for species delineation in a partially sampled clade, we examined the overlap between intra- and intertaxon divergences at both ESU and species levels using a phylogenetic approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Three different metrics were used to characterize intraspecific variation: (1) average pairwise intraspecific difference (K2P distance) between all individuals sampled within species/ESU, as employed by previous researchers [7,8]; (2) average theta (θ), where theta is the mean pairwise distance within each taxon, thereby eliminating bias associated with uneven sampling among taxa; and (3) average coalescent depth, the depth of the node linking all sampled extant members of a taxon, bookending intraspecific variability (see Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Genetic distance between terminal taxa and their closest sister was used to characterize interspecific divergence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>A wide range of intraspecific variation was encountered among ESUs in all three datasets, with generally less variation in turbinids and limpets than cowries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Sampling effort was designed to capture the greatest intraspecific variation by targeting the most disparate populations in a taxon, whenever possible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Thus, while coalescent depths generally increase with sample size (Figure 4A), they are variable, and ESUs with n ≥ 2, n ≥ 5, and n ≥ 10 samples overlap broadly (Figure 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The distribution of all intraspecific, pairwise genetic distances approximates a Poisson distribution (Figure 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Calculated values of theta for cowrie ESUs with ≥ten samples are normally distributed, and are highly correlated with estimated coalescent depth (Figure 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>All three measures of intraspecific variability (average pairwise distances, theta, and coalescent depth) are substantially higher in cowries than in turbinids or limpets (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>This may be a result of smaller effective population sizes in the latter two groups [37], reflecting their poor dispersal abilities because of non-feeding larvae, and resultant narrow ESU ranges. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>A similar pattern is evident within cowries: taxa that lack planktonic larvae and consequently have restricted dispersal and narrow ranges, have a smaller mean theta (0.0029) than cowries that possess planktonic larvae (0.0070). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pbio-0030422-g004" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Sample Size Effect on Intraspecific Variation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Coalescent depth vs. sample size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Histograms for coalescent depths of various sample size classes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Mean coalescent depth increases with increased sample size, from 0.0049 for n ≥ 2, to 0.0057 for n ≥ 5, to 0.0068 to 0.0070 for n ≥ 10. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0030422.g004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pbio-0030422-g005" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Alternative Metrics for Intraspecific Variation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>(A) Distribution of all intraspecific pairwise K2P distances for cowrie ESUs with n ≥ 10, turbinids and limpets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Left y-axis for cowries; right y-axis for others. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>(B) Comparison between estimated theta versus estimated maximum coalescent for each cowrie ESU with n ≥ 10; r2 = 0.837. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>(C) Distribution of theta values for cowrie (n ≥ 10), turbinid and limpet ESUs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0030422.g005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pbio-0030422-t001" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Intraspecific Variation </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0030422.t001"/></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>As with intraspecific variation, a wide range of interspecific differences is found in all three gastropod groups, indicating that divergences are spread out over time (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>It is interesting to note that intraspecific variation (as measured by coalescent depth) is not correlated with interspecific divergence for ESUs ≥ five individuals (p = 0.12), indicating that older species (those without close extant relatives) do not have more intraspecific variation than younger species (those with close relatives). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pbio-0030422-g006" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Interspecific Variation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Distribution of divergence depths between terminal ESUs and their sister ESU(s) in cowries, turbinids and limpets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0030422.g006"/></fig></SecTag><sec id="s2b1"><title><text><SENT sid="167" pm="?"><plain>Gap or overlap? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Efficacy of thresholds with ESUs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>We found broad overlap between levels of intraspecific variation and interspecific divergence at the ESU level in cowries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Intraspecific variation is well constrained: only five ESUs (2%–3% of ESUs with n ≥ 10, n ≥ 5, and n ≥ 2 samples/ESU) have coalescent depths &gt;1.5% (=3% threshold), and none have &gt;2% (=4% threshold) (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Coalescent depths are recorded as nodal depths, and thus are half the value of pairwise distances commonly reported for threshold values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Therefore, if an unknown was &gt;3% divergent from all other samples, we could say with ~98% confidence that it represents an independent evolutionary lineage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Such false-positive errors become rapidly more common at lower thresholds, as 20%, 15%, 11% of ESUs (with n ≥ 10, n ≥ 5, and n ≥ 2 samples/ESU) have coalescent depths &gt;1% (=2% threshold). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>In turbinids and limpets, all coalescent depths are &lt;1%, thus none yield a false positive at even a 2% threshold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Because these error rates are determined by maximum coalescent depth, this assessment of performance is conservative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Two randomly chosen individuals within an ESU will likely be less divergent than the two most disparate individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>For direct comparison with Hebert et al. [7] and Barrett and Hebert [8], examination of all intraspecific pairwise distances (Figure 5A) yields 99% and 95% confidence values at thresholds set at 2.85% and 1.99% in cowries, 1.12% and 0.81% for turbinids, and 1.38% and 0.52% for limpets, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pbio-0030422-t002" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>False-Positive Error Rates </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0030422.t002"/></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>In contrast, interspecific ESU divergences are much less constrained, extending at their lower end well into the range of intraspecific variation (Figure 7A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Thus, high divergence thresholds miss many young ESUs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Of the 263 cowrie ESUs sampled, 16% would be artificially lumped with another ESU at a 3% threshold, and 8% would be lumped even at a 2% cutoff (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Most (79% at the 3% threshold) of the lumped ESUs are allopatrically distributed sister taxa, yet more than half (22 of 42) are traditionally recognized species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>A similar percentage of taxa would be overlooked at a 3% cutoff in turbinids (20%) and limpets (17%) (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>This high incidence of false negatives reflects both the comprehensive phylogenetic sampling and increased taxonomic scrutiny these taxa have received. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pbio-0030422-g007" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Barcoding Overlap: Cowrie ESUs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>(A) Relative distributions of intraspecific variability (coalescent depth—red) and interspecific divergence between ESUs (yellow), demonstrating significant overlap and the lack of a barcoding gap. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Note that the x-axis scale shifts to progressively greater increments above 0.02. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>(B) Cumulative error based on false positives plus false negatives for each threshold value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The optimum threshold value is 0.013 (2.6%), where error is minimized at 17%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0030422.g007"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pbio-0030422-t003" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>False-Negative Error Rates </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0030422.t003"/></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="?"><plain>How high should thresholds be set to minimize error? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>False-positive and false-negative error rates can be totaled for any threshold value across the phylogeny, and combined error minimized (Figure 7B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>In cowries the lowest overall error (17%) was at a threshold values of 2.6%, and error varied little (17%–19%) between 2.4%–3.4% thresholds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Errors at these levels are largely the result of missing young taxa, not of false recognition of additional species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>In turbinids, as in cowries, the distribution of intra- and interspecific divergences overlap, and combined error is lowest (7%) at thresholds values of 1.2%–1.6% (Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>In contrast, thresholds are effective and error can be entirely eliminated in limpets: there is no overlap at a threshold of 1.7% (Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The better performance of turbinids and limpets is likely in part the result of their shallower coalescents and lower diversity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>A 3% threshold has been cited as sufficient genetic disparity to characterize different species [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The actual threshold value that researchers would be willing to accept as indicative of a new taxon, if any, varies depending upon philosophy, marker choice, and group of organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>For our three datasets, a 3% threshold would work well at minimizing false positives, but it would create many false negatives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, Hebert et al. [7], in order to screen for novel taxa, proposed to set a standard sequence threshold value that minimizes false positives at ten times the mean intraspecific variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>This would set the threshold at around 8% in cowries (based on 60 ESUs with n ≥ 10; Table 1), well above the 4% level where all false positives are eliminated, considerably above the optimum (2.6%), and leading to a 34% error rate (all false negatives). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Substantial variation in the relationship between intraspecific variation and optimal threshold values to either minimize combined error or to eliminate all false positives makes setting the latter on the former problematic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>The optimum threshold values to minimize total error correspond to 3.2–4.1 times the level of intraspecific variation in cowries, depending on which measure is used (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The factors range from 4.9–6.3× if one were to use a conservative threshold that eliminates false positives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The corresponding ranges for turbinids are 4.8–7.8×, while for limpets it is at 5.7–6.8× (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The range of values among these gastropods and Hebert et al.'s [7] bird samples indicate that no simple formula based on intraspecific variation will yield a robust threshold to minimize error across groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pbio-0030422-t004" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Threshold Correction Factors </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0030422.t004"/></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Thresholds can be used to either minimize total error or to cleanly screen for novel taxa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Our results imply that they serve poorly for the former, as high error rates remain at even optimal threshold values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>However thresholds can certainly be set in a way to guarantee that sequences beyond them represent novel taxa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>In cowries, a 4% screening threshold eliminates all known intra-ESU variants, and guarantees that such divergent taxa are novel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>However the same threshold will also miss 21% of novel taxa, as they will register less divergent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Thus, thresholds can assist in the species discovery process by guaranteeing the distinctiveness of genetically deep variants, at some cost. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b2"><title><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Efficacy of thresholds with traditional taxonomy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Error rates almost double if we replace cowrie ESUs with the currently recognized species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>This increase in error is the result of a simultaneous increase in the range of intraspecific variation and interspecific divergence, creating a wider overlap between the two in species than in ESUs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Intraspecific variability is substantially higher in traditional species than ESUs for all three metrics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The distribution of all intraspecific pairwise comparisons is multi-modal, reflecting the lumping of discrete ESUs (Figure 8A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The means of all intraspecific pairwise distances and theta are both three times as high within species (2.97%, θ = 1.86%) than within ESUs (0.81%, θ = 0.63%) (Figure 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The range of interspecific divergence is also increased because numerous traditionally recognized cowrie species are not monophyletic in their COI, either because their coalescents have not sorted, or because they represent forms recognized by splitters that are not based on biological species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>As a result, overlap between intra- and interspecific differences and error rates associated with thresholds both are greater when traditional species are used (Figure 9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The optimal threshold for recognized species is 5%, with an error rate of 33%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The 2.6% threshold, optimal for ESUs, yields a 37% error rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Thus, thresholds fare poorly even in a thoroughly sampled phylogeny, if the basis for sampling is traditionally recognized species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>This result is a strong warning against limited sampling to exemplars for taxa based on species checklists, even for relatively well-known groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Had we not sampled the various subspecies of cowries and geographic locations as in the turbinids and limpets, we would have had a very different perspective on intra- and interspecific divergences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pbio-0030422-g008" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Intraspecific Variation Based on Recognized Species </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>(A) The distribution of all intraspecific pairwise distances for traditionally recognized cowrie species with n ≥ 10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>The white bars represent intraspecific distances where the two specimens compared fall into separate ESUs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>(B) Theta values for traditionally recognized cowrie species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Black bars are species that correspond to an ESU; white bars are species that include multiple ESUs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0030422.g008"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pbio-0030422-g009" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Barcoding Overlap: Cowrie Species </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Data are presented as in Figure 7; however, estimates of intraspecific variation and interspecific divergence are based on traditionally recognized cowrie species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>(A) Relative distributions of intraspecific variability (coalescent depth—red) and interspecific divergence between species (yellow), demonstrating a more pronounced overlap than when utilizing ESUs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Note that the x-axis scale shifts to progressively greater increments above 0.02. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>(B) Cumulative error based on false positives plus false negatives for each threshold value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>The optimum threshold value is 0.025 (5%), where error is minimized at 33%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0030422.g009"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2b3"><title><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Global versus regional sampling </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>This broad overlap contrasts with Hebert et al.'s [7] and Barrett and Hebert's [8] findings of a wide separation between intraspecific variation and interspecific divergence in a sample of North American birds and spiders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="?"><plain>What causes this difference? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>This difference likely reflects differential intensity (number of samples per species/ESU) and scale (regional versus global) of sampling, rather than differences among birds, spiders, and snails. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>First, Hebert et al.'s [7] appraisal of intraspecific variation was limited, and thus they underestimated intraspecific variation [23,24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Second, they substantially undersampled true sister species pairs [23,24,38], and thus overestimated interspecific divergence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Regional studies [1,7,8] undersample the most closely related species, which are frequently allopatric, and thus underestimate global error rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>The purported barcoding “gap” reported in these studies is the best-case scenario, and can only get worse (decrease or disappear) with increased intraspecific and interspecific sampling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Error rates are lower in regionally scaled analyses if the geographic scale of the study excludes allopatric sister taxa, thus artificially increasing observed interspecific divergence levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>For instance, a barcoding gap does exist if only cowries from the island of Moorea were investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>The geographic scale where such reduction in error occurs is dependent on the geographic mode and scale of speciation of the group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>While marine gastropods sampled at a single island would generally not include any allopatric sister taxa, terrestrial gastropods sampled at that same island may include many shallow sisters, if the landsnail group has undergone in situ radiation [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Consequently, error rates can be high even in geographically restricted analyses if diversification is local—through fine-scale allopatric speciation, sympatric speciation, polyploidy, or rapid attainment of sympatry following allopatry—or when invasive species homogenize the biota. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Two principal elements are proposed in DNA barcoding: (1) the ability to assign an unknown sample to a known species, and (2) the ability to detect previously unsampled species as distinct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The prospect of assigning an unknown to a known is promising especially for well-known, comprehensively sampled groups that have been extensively studied by genetic and morphological taxonomy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>In such globally comprehensive and well-circumscribed datasets, the majority of individuals (&gt;96% in these snails) may be successfully identified by a short fragment of mtDNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>However, even in such extensively studied taxa, a certain percentage of young species (0%–8% in cowries) will not be discernable because of ancestral polymorphism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>DNA barcoding is much less effective for identification in taxa where taxonomic scrutiny has not been thorough, and species recognition is limited to a few traditional character sets, untested by additional studies and tools. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>In such modestly known groups, which represent the bulk of life on Earth, many species will appear to be genetically non-monophyletic because of imperfect taxonomy [20], contributing to a high error rate for barcode-based identification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Thus, to create an effective environment for identification through barcoding, comprehensive, taxonomically thoroughly studied, comparative databases are necessary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>The barcoding movement will play a leading role in generating the standards and protocols for establishing these databases, and facilitating their development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>The promise of barcoding for species discovery based on methodologies currently proposed should be tempered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>The use of thresholds for species delineation is not promising and is strongly discouraged, as levels of overlap between intra- and interspecific differences are likely to be significant in most major clades, particularly within diverse yet poorly documented groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Thresholds can be effective in screening for substantially divergent novel taxa, but our data indicate such use will overlook at least one-fifth of life's forms that are distinct but less divergent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>More elegant methodologies will be required that incorporate principles of population genetics, knowledge of intraspecific variability, and sister group attributes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Identifications or discoveries may be placed within a statistical framework [40], allowing statements such as “based on the data at hand, sample X is 83% likely to be a member of taxon A.” The Data Analysis Working Group (DAWG) associated with the Consortium for the Barcoding of Life (CBOL) is pursuing these analytical challenges. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>While the barcode is certainly a link out and can provide access to life's encyclopedia, this book needs to be written in collaboration with taxonomists, systematists, and ecologists, in an integrative taxonomic framework [17,41,42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Barcoding on a global scale can only achieve high accuracy once the majority of evolutionary units have been sampled and taxonomically assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>This critical first step was achieved for the studied gastropod taxa by centuries of careful, traditional taxonomic consideration (cowries) and large sample sizes (for all three). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Without this initial phase, a threshold approach is likely to fail for ~20% of the taxa and individuals at the species discovery phase. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>We sequenced 2,026 cowries for 614 bp of COI mtDNA, the traditional Folmer primer region proposed for barcoding most metazoans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Two or more individuals were sequenced from 82% (216) of ESUs, ≥5 from 54% (143), and ≥10 from 23% (60). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>To maximize recovery of the greatest intraspecific variation and test for geographical structuring, sequences were generated from the most geographically distant populations available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Molecular methods followed standard procedures and are reviewed in Meyer [25,26], Kirkendale and Meyer [27], and Meyer et al. [28]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>We used standard, tree-based methods to address accuracy of identification in a thoroughly sampled phylogeny using both a species-level and ESU approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>One exemplar from each recognized species (the nominal subspecies if the species included multiple subspecies) or each identified ESU was used as the reference “barcode” exemplar in topological comparisons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>We randomly selected 1,000 sequences from the cowrie COI dataset, excluding barcode exemplars, and limiting representation of each species or ESU to 15 or ten sequences, respectively, to minimize bias toward well-sampled taxa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Hybrid individuals (see above) were excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>These 1,000 sequences were tested one at a time, and their placement relative to the barcoding exemplars evaluated in both neighbor-joining (K2P) and parsimony phylogenies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Identification was considered correct if the sister taxon of the test sequence was the exemplar sequence of its corresponding species or ESU. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Identification was considered incorrect if the sister taxon was wrong. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>If the random sequence fell below a node linking two recognized sister taxa including the corresponding species, the identification was considered ambiguous, as assignment to one or the other is equivocal, as the unknown could also represent a novel taxon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Similar analyses were performed with the turbinid (n = 200 from 278) and limpet (n = 100 from 125) datasets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Pairwise K2P distances, theta, and coalescent depth were used to characterize intraspecific variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Genetic distance between terminal taxa and their closest sister was used to characterize interspecific divergence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>While the phylogenies used are based upon sequence data from two mtDNA markers (16S and COI: [26–28]), only COI was used for these analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The two most genetically distant individuals within each ESU (based on pairwise comparisons) were chosen to bookend genetic diversity and recover coalescent depth (maximum intra-ESU variability). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>These two individuals replaced the exemplar taxon used to construct the overall phylogeny (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>A likelihood ratio test (GTR + G with and without a clock enforced) was used to test for clock-like behavior (using only COI) in the resulting tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>A clock could not be falsified for turbinids and limpets (p &gt; 0.05); but was falsified (p = 0.007) for cowries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Coalescent depths and interspecific divergence estimates throughout are based on topologies with a molecular clock enforced, although the overall cowrie data marginally rejected rate constancy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>We estimated theta by calculating the average intraspecific difference using K2P distances. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>All analyses were conducted using PAUP* version 4.0b10 [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>A listing of ESUs, number of individuals examined, interspecific divergence, and intraspecific metrics can be found in the supporting information for cowries (Table S1), turbinids (Table S2), and limpets (Table S3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sg001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Barcoding Overlap in Turbinids </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>(A) Relative distributions of intraspecific variability (coalescent depth—red) and interspecific divergence between ESUs (yellow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Note that the x-axis scale shifts to progressively greater increments above 0.01. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>(B) Cumulative totals of false positives plus false negatives for each threshold value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>The optimum threshold value is between 0.005 or 0.007 (1.0%–1.4%), where error is minimized at 7%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>(169 KB EPS). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0030422.sg001.eps"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sg002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Barcoding Gap in Limpets </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>(A) Relative distributions of intraspecific variability (coalescent depth—red) and interspecific divergence between ESUs (yellow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Note that the x-axis scale shifts to progressively greater increments above 0.01. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>(B) Cumulative totals of false positives plus false negatives for each threshold value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>A gap exists at a threshold of 0.0085 (1.7%), where error is eliminated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>(166 KB EPS). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0030422.sg002.eps"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="st001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>ESU Listing for Cowries </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>The table contains the taxon name, number of individuals sequenced, interspecific divergence (lineage) depth (GTR + G), coalescent depth (GTR + G), and estimated theta value (K2P). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Asterisk (*) denotes direct developers, lacking planktonic larvae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>(343 KB DOC). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0030422.st001.doc"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="st002"><label>Table S2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>ESU Listing for Turbinids </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>The table contains the taxon name, number of individuals sequenced, interspecific divergence (lineage) depth (GTR + G), coalescent depth (GTR + G), and estimated theta value (K2P). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>(55 KB DOC). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0030422.st002.doc"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="st003"><label>Table S3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>ESU Listing for Limpets </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>The table contains the taxon name, number of individuals sequenced, interspecific divergence (lineage) depth (GTR + G), coalescent depth (GTR + G), and estimated theta value (K2P). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>(36 KB DOC). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0030422.st003.doc"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Accession Numbers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>The GenBank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Genbank">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Genbank</ext-link>) accession numbers for sequences discussed in this paper are: cowrie (AY161637–AY161846, AY534433–AY534503, and DQ206992–DQ207351), limpet (AY628240–AY628327), and turbinid (AY787233–AY787400). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>The complete datasets are available also by request from CPM or at the Cowrie Genetic Database Web site (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.flmnh.ufl.edu/cowries">http://www.flmnh.ufl.edu/cowries</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><ack><p>Funding for these studies was provided by grants from the National Science Foundation (DEB-9807316/0196049 and OCE-0221382) to GP; and grants from Conchologists of America, the University of California Museum of Paleontology, and the National Institutes of Health (training grant in genetics) to CPM. Over 100 persons and many institutions contributed tissue samples for this study. They are acknowledged at the CGDP Web site. We would like to thank Brent Mishler, Craig Moritz, Mark Stoeckle, Kevin Omland, Felix Sperling, and two anonymous reviews for helpful comments or discussion on earlier drafts of this manuscript.</p><p>
<bold>Competing interests.</bold> The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><fn id="n1" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Author contributions. CPM conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, and analyzed the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>CPM and GP contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools and wrote the paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="n2" fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Citation: Meyer CP, Paulay G (2005) DNA barcoding: Error rates based on comprehensive sampling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>PLoS Biol 3(12): e422. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pbio-0030422-b001"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>HebertPDNCywinskaABallSLDeWaardJRBiological identifications through DNA barcodesProc R Soc Lond B Biol Sci2003270313321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b002"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>WillKWRubinoffDMyth of the molecule: DNA barcodes for species cannot replace morphology for identification and classificationCladistics2004204755 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b003"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>MarshallETaxonomy—Will DNA bar codes breathe life into classification?Science2005307103715718446 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b004"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>EbachMCHoldregeCDNA barcoding is no substitute for taxonomyNature2005434697 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b005"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>SchindelDEMillerSEDNA barcoding a useful tool for taxonomistsNature200543517 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b006"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>GregoryTRDNA barcoding does not compete with taxonomyNature20054341067 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b007"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>HebertPDNStoeckleMYZemlakTSFrancisCMIdentification of birds through DNA barcodesPLoS Biol20042e31210.1371/journal.pbio.002031215455034 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b008"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>BarrettRDHHebertPDNIdentifying spiders through DNA barcodesCan J Zool200583481491 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b009"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>WilsonEOThe encyclopedia of lifeTrends Ecol Evol2003187780 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b010"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>MayRMRavenPHThe dimensions of life of earthNature and human society: The quest for a sustainable world1997Washington, D.CNational Academy Press3045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b011"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>StoeckleMTaxonomy, DNA, and the bar code of lifeBioscience200353796797 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b012"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>HebertPDNPentonEHBurnsJMJanzenDHHallwachsWTen species in one: DNA barcoding reveals cryptic species in the neotropical skipper butterfly Astraptes fulgerator Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A2004101148121481715465915 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b013"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>JanzenDHNow is the timePhilos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci200435973173215253359 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b014"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>MalletJWillmottKTaxonomy: Renaissance or Tower of Babel?Trends Ecol Evol2003185759 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b015"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="?"><plain>SebergOHumphriesCJKnappSStevensonDWPetersenGShortcuts in systematics? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>A commentary on DNA-based taxonomyTrends Ecol Evol2003186365 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b016"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>LipscombDPlatnickNWheelerQThe intellectual content of taxonomy: A comment on DNA taxonomyTrends Ecol Evol2003186566 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b017"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>WillKWMishlerBDWheelerQDThe perils of DNA bar-coding and the need for integrative taxonomySyst Biol20055484485116243769 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b018"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>AviseJCPhylogeography: The history and formation of species2000Cambridge (Massachusetts)Harvard University Press447 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b019"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>AviseJCMolecular markers, natural history and evolution2004Sunderland (Massachusetts)Sinauer Associates541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b020"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>FunkDJOmlandKESpecies-level paraphyly and polyphyly: Frequency, causes, and consequences, with insights from animal mitochondrial DNAAnnu Rev Ecol Evol Syst200334397423 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b021"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>RosenbergNAThe shapes of neutral gene genealogies in two species: Probabilities of monophyly, paraphyly, and polyphyly in a coalescent modelEvolution2003571465147712940352 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b022"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>NeigelJEAviseJCNevoEKarlinSPhylogenetic relationships on mitochondrial DNA under various demographic models of speciationEvolutionary processes and theory1986New YorkAcademic Press515534 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b023"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>MoritzCCiceroCDNA barcoding: Promise and pitfallsPLoS Biol20042e35410.1371/journal.pbio.002035415486587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b024"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>PrendiniLComment on “Identifying spiders through DNA barcodes”Can J Zool200583498504 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b025"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>MeyerCPMolecular systematics of cowries (Gastropoda: Cypraeidae) and diversification patterns in the tropicsBiol J Linn Soc Lond200379401459 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b026"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>MeyerCPToward comprehensiveness: Increased molecular sampling within Cypraeidae and its phylogenetic implicationsMalacologia200446127156 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b027"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>KirkendaleLAMeyerCPPhylogeography of the Patelloida profunda group (Gastropoda: Lottidae): Diversification in a dispersal-driven marine systemMol Ecol2004132749276215315686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b028"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>MeyerCPGellerJBPaulayGFine scale endemism on coral reefs: Archipelagic differentiation in turbinid gastropodsEvolution20055911312515792232 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b029"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>SchilderFASchilderMProdrome of a monograph on living CypraeidaeProc Malacol Soc Lond193822–23119231 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b030"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>SchilderMSchilderFAA catalogue of living and fossil cowries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Taxonomy and bibliography of Triviacea and Cypraeacea, Gastropoda ProsobranchiaMemoires Institut Royal des Sciences Naturelles de Belgique, Deuxième Série1971851246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b031"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>BurgessCMCowries of the world1985Cape Town (South Africa)G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Verhoef Seacomber Publications288 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b032"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>LorenzFHubertAA guide to worldwide cowries1993Wiesbaden (Germany)C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Hemmen571 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b033"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>LorenzFNew worldwide cowries2002Hackenheim (Germany)ConchBooks292 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b034"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>ZwicklDJHillisDMIncreased taxon sampling greatly reduces phylogenetic errorSyst Biol20025158859812228001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b035"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>BensassonDZhangDXHartlDLHewittGMMitochondrial pseudogenes: Evolution's misplaced witnessesTrends Ecol Evol20011631432111369110 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b036"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>WilliamsSTKnowltonNMitochondrial pseudogenes are pervasive and often insidious in the snapping shrimp genus Alpheus Mol Biol Evol2001181484149311470839 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b037"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>TajimaFEvolutionary relationship of Dna-sequences in finite populationsGenetics19831054374606628982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b038"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>JohnsonNKCiceroCNew mitochondrial DNA data affirm the importance of Pleistocene speciation in North American birdsEvolution2004581122113015212392 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b039"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>PaulayGMeyerCPDiversification in the tropical Pacific: Comparisons between marine and terrestrial systemsAm Zool20014115501551 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b040"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>MatzMVNielsenRA likelihood ratio test for species membership based on DNA sequence dataPhilos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci20053601969197416214754 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b041"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>DayratBTowards integrative taxonomyBiol J Linn Soc Lond200585407415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b042"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>de QueirozKHowardDJBerlocherSHThe general lineage concept of species, species criteria, and the process of speciation: A conceptual unification and terminological recommendationsEndless forms: Species and speciation1998Oxford University Presspp57 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pbio-0030422-b043"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>SwoffordDLPAUP*: Phylogenetic Analysis Using Parsimony (*and Other Methods), version 4.0b10 [computer program]2002Sunderland (Massachusetts)Sinauer </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>COI</term><def><p>cytochrome <italic>c</italic> oxidase I</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ESU</term><def><p>evolutionary significant unit</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>mtDNA</term><def><p>mitochondrial DNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NUMT</term><def><p>nuclear copy of mtDNA</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag></back></article>
