
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2699550</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19564920</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">09-PONE-RA-09368R1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006096</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subject>Microbiology/Cellular Microbiology and Pathogenesis</subject><subject>Microbiology/Microbial Evolution and Genomics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Bacterial Ortholog of Mammalian Translocator Protein (TSPO) with Virulence Regulating Activity </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">TSPO in Bacteria</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chapalain</surname><given-names>Annelise</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chevalier</surname><given-names>Sylvie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Orange</surname><given-names>Nicole</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Murillo</surname><given-names>Laurence</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>Vassilios</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Feuilloley</surname><given-names>Marc G. J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory of Cold Microbiology UPRES EA4312, University of Rouen, Evreux, France</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>ADIPpharm, Evreux, France</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>The Research Institute of the McGill University Health Centre &amp; Department of Medicine, McGill University, Montreal, Quebec, Canada</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>Christophe</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Baylor College of Medicine, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>marc.feuilloley@univ-rouen.fr</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: SC MGJF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: AC LM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: SC MGJF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: NO VP MGJF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: AC NO VP MGJF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>6</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e6096</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Chapalain et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The translocator protein (TSPO), previously designated as peripheral-type benzodiazepine receptor, is a protein mainly located in the outer mitochondrial membrane of eukaryotic cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>TSPO is implicated in major physiological functions and functionally associated with other proteins such as the voltage-dependent anionic channel, also designated as mitochondrial porin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, a TSPO-related protein was identified in the photosynthetic bacterium Rhodobacter sphaeroides but it was initially considered as a relict of evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>In the present study we cloned a tspO gene in Pseudomonas fluorescens MF37, a non-photosynthetic eubacterium and we used bioinformatics tools to identify TSPO in the genome of 97 other bacteria. P. fluorescens TSPO was recognized by antibodies against mouse protein and by PK 11195, an artificial ligand of mitochondrial TSPO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>As in eukaryotes, bacterial TSPO appears functionally organized as a dimer and the apparent Kd for PK 11195 is in the same range than for its eukaryotic counterpart. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>When P. fluorescens MF37 was treated with PK 11195 (10−5 M) adhesion to living or artificial surfaces and biofilm formation activity were increased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Conversely, the apoptotic potential of bacteria on eukaryotic cells was significantly reduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>This effect of PK11195 was abolished in a mutant of P. fluorescens MF37 deficient for its major outer membrane porin, OprF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The present results demonstrate the existence of a bacterial TSPO that shares common structural and functional characteristics with its mammalian counterpart. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>This protein, apparently involved in adhesion and virulence, reveals the existence of a possible new inter kingdom signalling system and suggests that the human microbiome should be involuntarily exposed to the evolutionary pressure of benzodiazepines and related molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>This discovery also represents a promising opportunity for the development of alternative antibacterial strategies. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Benzodiazepines are among the most widely prescribed drugs in the world [1] and are known as sedative-hypnotic agents efficient against anxiety, sleep disorders and related troubles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The first identified target of benzodiazepines, designated as central benzodiazepine receptor, is corresponding to a secondary site of subtype A γ-aminobutyric acid receptors (GABAA receptors) expressed in neurons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>However, a second type of benzodiazepine receptor was identified in mammals in 1977. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>This binding site was named peripheral-type benzodiazepine receptor (PBR) [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>As the structure of this receptor is complex and variable there was rapidly a large confusion, the same word being used to designate the multimeric assembling or the benzodiazepine binding protein itself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>For that reason, on the basis of its identified functions in eukaryotes it was proposed to designate this benzodiazepine binding protein as “Translocator Protein” (TSPO) [2]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>For a receptor, the sub-cellular localization of TSPO is original since it is essentially present in the outer mitochondrial membrane [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>As it has also been found in nuclear and cytoplasmic membranes it was proposed to distinguish mitochondrial TSPO and nuclear TSPO [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In the mitochondrial membrane, TSPO is functionally associated with a Voltage Dependant Anionic Channel (VDAC), also designated as mitochondrial porin, and with an Adenine Nucleotide Translocase (ANT) essentially associated with inner membrane [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>TSPO is present in all mammalian tissues with the exception of neurons, but differently expressed according to the cellular function [2], [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>TSPO has a major role in steroidogenesis and is also implicated in porphyrin biosynthesis, cell proliferation and apoptosis [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Natural ligands of TSPO are cholesterol, Diazepam Binding Inhibitor (DBI) or protoporphyrin IX; principal artificial ligands are isoquinoline carboxamide, such as PK 11195, and benzodiazepines, such as Ro5-4864. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>However, benzodiazepine binding requires the presence of VDAC, whereas PK 11195 binding does not require the presence of other proteins [5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>TSPO was mostly studied in mammals but this protein is also expressed in invertebrates [6] and vegetal [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, a functional homologue of TSPO has been identified in the photosynthetic bacterium, Rhodobacter sphaeroides [8], [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>In this prokaryote, TSPO negatively regulates pigment biosynthesis and photosynthesis in response to light and oxygen modifications [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>TSPO-related proteins have been identified later in the cyanobacterium, Fremyella diplosiphon [10] and in the non-photosynthetic bacterium, Sinorhizobium meliloti [11]. R. sphaeroides and S. meliloti are both members of the alpha subdivision of purple bacteria, the organisms that likely gave rise to the endosymbiont at the origin of mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the existence of TSPO in these micro-organisms was considered to be a relict of evolution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Here we show that a functional ortholog of tspO, i.e. a gene that has evolved from a common ancestor, is expressed in Pseudomonas fluorescens, a ubiquitous micro-organism of the gamma-proteobacteria subdivision of eubacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The distribution of homologous genes in different bacterial species or strains covering most taxonomic groups was established. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>In addition to structural homology to mitochondrial TSPO, P. fluorescens TSPO has common pharmacological properties, as demonstrated by its high affinity for PK 11195. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The use of PK 11195 revealed that this bacterial TSPO is involved in the regulation of adhesion and virulence and, as a mitochondrial TSPO should be, functionally associated with a membrane porin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that natural ligands of TSPO, that remain to be identified, should be involved in inter-kingdom communication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Moreover, it appears that the behavior of bacteria in the human microbiome can be modulated by current pharmaceutical agents like benzodiazepines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>On another side, these results suggest a new strategy for the development of bacterial inhibitors of virulence usable in complement or in place of antibiotics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>A tspO gene is present in the γ-proteobacterium Pseudomonas fluorescens </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>In order to investigate the presence of a tspO gene in non-photosynthetic and typical eubacterium, the published genome of the environmental and widespread micro-organism Pseudomonas fluorescens (strain SBW25) was screened by BlastP against the TSPO sequence of R. sphaeroides 2.4.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>A sequence encoding a protein with 50% identity to 2.4.1 TSPO of R. sphaeroides was detected in silico in the genomic sequence of P. fluorescens SBW25. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>In order to verify experimentally the presence of this gene in P. fluorescens, primers were designed from the P. fluorescens SBW25 tspO gene sequence and used in our reference strain, P. fluorescens MF37. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>A PCR-amplified fragment of 438 bp, encoding 146 amino acids was produced from P. fluorescens MF37 (NCBI accession number FJ185105). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The fragment was cloned into the pMOSBlue plasmid and sequenced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>A BlastP search of the full fragment sequence confirmed that it was a TSPO-like protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Calculation of the topological structure of this protein by TopPred revealed a five transmembrane helix structure analogous to that of R. sphaeroides 2.4.1 [12] and mitochondrial TSPO [13], though the extracellular N-terminus is absent and the C-terminus shortened ( Fig. 1 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The first cytoplasmic loop is highly conserved (80% similarity including 46.7% identity) between R. sphaeroides 2.4.1 and P. fluorescens MF37. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Moreover, Lys21 and Lys31 (corresponding to residues 26 and 36 in R. sphaeroides 2.4.1.) are fully conserved in both amino acid identity and the distance between the two residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The software PSORTb indicated with high probability association of TSPO with the inner bacterial membrane and it was interesting to note that it was not possible to extract TSPO from the sub-fraction corresponding to the outer membrane of the bacterium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>In agreement with its probable membrane localization, a peptidoglycane-binding domain signature was detected between residues 66 and 81 in the third transmembrane helix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Using specific primers designed from the P. fluorescens MF37 tspO gene sequence, we successfully amplified homologous sequences in other strains of P. fluorescens, including the biovar V strain, MF0, as well as the clinical biovar I and II strains, MFY70, MFY162, and MFN1032 ( Fig. 2 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Intriguingly, a tspO fragment could be amplified from the MFN3597 strain, previously identified as P. putida [14], but not from the clinical strain, P. fluorescens MFY63 (biovar II). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Sequencing and alignment of the translated TSPO sequences from the amplified fragments revealed 90% similarity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>An unexpected result was the impossibility to amplify a tspO gene in Pseudomonas aeruginosa PAO1 (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0006096-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006096.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the putative topological organization of bacterial and mitochondrial TSPO. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>(a) Pseudomonas fluorescens MF37 bactTSPO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>(b) BactTSPO from Rhodobacter sphaeroides 2.4.1 recalculated from Yeliseev and Kaplan [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>(c) Mitochondrial TSPO [13]. P. fluorescens MF37 bactTSPO has a typical five transmembrane helix structure, a larger L1 intra-cytoplasmic loop, and an extended cytoplasmic C-terminal end. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the extracellular N-terminal end is absent, and a peptidoglycane binding domain signature is present between the L2 loop and H3 transmembrane domain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006096.g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0006096-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006096.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Identification of tspO genes in fluorescent Pseudomonas. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>PCR amplification of tspO-encoding sequences in the biovar V strains Pseudomonas fluorescens MF37 and MF0, the clinical biovar II strain Pseudomonas fluorescens MFY70, the biovar B strain Pseudomonas putida MFN3597, and the biovar I strains, Pseudomonas fluorescens MFY162 and MFN1032. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The biovar II strain, Pseudomonas fluorescens MFY63, lacks tspO-related sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Std: Molecular mass standards. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006096.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>TspO orthologs are widely, but heterogeneously distributed in eubacteria </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Since our results suggested a broader distribution of TSPO than expected, the TSPO sequence from P. fluorescens MF37 was used to search for homologous proteins in sequenced bacterial genomes available in the NCBI databank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>We found that 97 different eubacterial species or strains encompassing most of the different taxonomic groups contained a TSPO-related protein that we propose to designate as bacterial TSPO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Bacterial TSPO appears to be widely distributed in eubacteria, including human pathogens such as Bacillus anthracis, Legionella pneumophila, Staphylococcus haemolyticus, and Clostridium perfringens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>A cladogram was constructed based on the 97 bacterial TSPO sequences ( Fig. 3 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Although the sequence of human mitochondrial TSPO was included in the series, the tree remained unrooted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>In addition, it was not possible to distinguish any specific clusters grouping homogenous bacteria, with the single exception of a cluster of fluorescent Pseudomonas that included P. fluorescens MF37 and SBW25, as well as the P. syringae pathovars phaseolicola, syringae, and tomato. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>In fact, this cluster was certainly an artifact due to the presence of several identified sequences from closely related bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Even the P. fluorescens Pf0-1 strain remained separate from the cluster of other fluorescent Pseudomonas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The absence of tspO in P. aeruginosa was confirmed by BlastP search in the strain PAO1 and in all genomic sequences available on the site Pseudomonas.com, i.e. strains PA7, PA14 and LESB58. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>In contrast, homologous sequences were found in different archaeal prokaryotes (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The genomic environment of tspO in fluorescent Pseudomonas was analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The sequences flanking tspO in P. fluorescens MF37 were sequenced and those in P. fluorescens Pf0-1, SBW25, P. syringae pv. phaseolicola 1448A, pv. syringae B728a, and pv. tomato DC3000 were retrieved from the NCBI databank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The sense, size, and putative functions of the genes in the flanking regions of tspO were different in the six bacterial types but we observed that the tspO environment was particularly rich in transposase genes ( Fig. 4 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>In P. syringae pv. phaseolicola, a gene encoding a transposase lies immediately upstream of tspO (position 1) with four additional transposase genes lying upstream (position 14) or downstream (positions 15, 16 and 17) of tspO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Sequences encoding transposases were also observed near tspO in another two strains of P. syringae (DC3000 strain: upstream gene positions 16 and 17 and downstream positions 23, 24, 25, 26, and 29; B728a strain: upstream position 31 and downstream position 17 and 31) and in P. fluorescens Pf0-1 (upstream position 17). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The GC content of the upstream and downstream sequences was determined in the different Pseudomonas whose genomic environment was studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Differences between the GC contents of the tspO gene in a same bacterial species were generally lower than 3% (maximum 5%) whereas inter-species variations reached 9%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0006096-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006096.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Amino acid sequence cladogram showing the relationships between bacterial TSPO. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Bacterial names, accession numbers, and taxonomic groups are indicated for each branch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Bold characters indicate γ-proteobacteria, and the black arrow indicates the position of TSPO expressed in human mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The two dotted boxes indicate fluorescent Pseudomonas strains containing a bactTSPO gene (P. fluorescens and P. syringae). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The degree of statistical support for branches was determined with 1000 bootstrap replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>All branches showed less than 30% divergence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006096.g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0006096-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006096.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Comparison of tspO genomic environments among Pseudomonas. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Physical maps of the regions upstream and downstream of tspO are shown for P. fluorescens strains MF37, SBW25, and Pf0-1 as well as P. syringae strains 1448A (pathovar phaseolicola), DC3000 (pv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>tomato), and B728a (pv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>syringae). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>ORF: non-identified putative protein, ¤ Data obtained from Blast, * Protein putative function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Black areas represent intergenic regions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006096.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>TspO is differently expressed in fluorescent Pseudomonas </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>As the presence of a gene is not a warranty of its functionality, expression of the tspO gene was studied in P. fluorescens MF37 and related strains by RT-PCR and western blot analysis of total protein extracts using an antibody raised against mouse TSPO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>RT-PCR revealed the expression of mRNA coding TSPO in extracts from P. fluorescens MF37 grown in normal or in reduced oxygen conditions without visible difference (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Western blot analysis of P. fluorescens MF37 extracts allowed to detect a TSPO immunoreactive band corresponding to a 37 kDa protein ( Fig. 5a ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>This mass was double what was theoretically expected for bacterial TSPO (17 kDa) but ESI-MS/MS analysis ( Fig. 5b ) indicated a 92% recovery between experimental and theoretical masses and confirmed that this immunoreactive band was actually bacterial TSPO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>A same protein was detected in extracts of P. fluorescens MF0, the strain from which MF37 was produced [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In contrast, although PCR allowed us to amplify TSPO homologous sequences in P. fluorescens MFY70, MFY162, MFN1032, and in P. putida MFN3597, western blot analysis did not detect the expression of bacterial TSPO-like immunoreactive proteins in these micro-organisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0006096-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006096.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Expression of TSPO in fluorescent Pseudomonas. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>(a) Western blot analysis of total proteins extracts from the biovars V Pseudomonas fluorescens MF37 and MF0, the clinical strains of Pseudomonas fluorescens MFY70, MFY162, and MFN1032, and Pseudomonas putida MFN3597. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>(b) Alignment of the fragments obtained by ESI-MS/MS analysis of the TSPO immunoreactive bands extracted from MF37 and showing 92% recovery with the theoretical sequence of the protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Std: Molecular mass standards. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006096.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Bacterial TSPO expressed in Pseudomonas fluorescens MF37 shares pharmacological properties with eukaryotic mitochondrial TSPO </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The pharmacological properties of P. fluorescens MF37 bacterial TSPO were investigated using a specific ligand of eukaryotic mitochondrial TSPO, PK 11195 [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>A total protein extract of MF37 was separated by SDS-page electrophoresis, transferred onto nitrocellulose membrane, and hybridized with tritiated PK11195 ([3H]-PK 11195). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The main binding peak of [3H]-PK 11195 was detected at the position of the 37 kDa band identified by western blot as containing MF37 bacterial TSPO ( Fig. 6a ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Secondary binding peaks were observed on proteins of higher molecular mass that were not recognized by the TSPO antiserum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>A Scatchard study was then performed using the same tracer and membranes purified from P. fluorescens MF37. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The Kd determined under these conditions (0.92 nM) in the same range as what has been previously established for PK 11195 binding to mammalian mitochondrial TSPO (1.5 nM) [17] ( Fig. 6b ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that P. fluorescens MF37 bacterial TSPO recognizes PK 11195 as a ligand, and we decided to use this molecule to investigate the functional role of MF37 TSPO. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0006096-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006096.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Binding of PK 11195 to bacterial TSPO of Pseudomonas fluorescens MF37. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>(a) Demonstration of the binding of [3H] PK 11195 at the position of the TSPO-immunoreactive band visualized by western blots in P. fluorescens MF37 extracts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>(b) Scatchard plot showing the binding characteristics of PK 11195 to TSPO of P. fluorescens MF37. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The maximal binding potential (Bmax) is 0.087 pmole.µ g−1 bacterial protein and the Kd is 0.92 nM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006096.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Bacterial TSPO regulates the adhesion and cytotoxic activity of Pseudomonas fluorescens </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Owing to the role of TSPO in the adaptation of R. sphaeroides to changes in oxygen concentrations [9], we first investigated the effect of PK 11195 on the growth kinetics of P. fluorescens MF37 cultured under normal aerobic or low oxygen conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Exposure of the bacteria to PK 11195 (10−5 M) at any time of the growth phase (i.e., at the onset of growth, mid-exponential growth phase, or at the beginning of stationary phase) did not alter the growth kinetics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Since, in Pseudomonas, mobility is indirectly controlled by oxygen concentration [18], we investigated the effect of PK11195 on bacterial mobility and adherence potential. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Treatment with PK 11195 did not alter the swimming or swarming mobilities of P. fluorescens MF37. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the adhesion potential of bacteria on glass and on eukaryotic (glial) cells was markedly increased (+168±69% and +70±9%, respectively) by PK 11195 exposure ( Fig. 7 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The ability of P. fluorescens MF37 to form biofilms on polystyrene was also significantly increased, albeit to a limited degree (+16±4%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>However, these changes in the adhesion potential of P. fluorescens were not associated with global variations in surface polarity, as demonstrated by measuring the bacterial affinity to solvent. P. fluorescens MF37 is non-invasive on glial cells and PK 11195 does not modify this behavior (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Given that bacterial adhesion and virulence are linked, we investigated the effect of PK 11195 on the cytotoxicity of P. fluorescens MF37 using the release of nitrites and lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) as markers of apoptosis and necrosis, respectively [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>In these experiments, bacteria were grown with PK 11195 (10−5 M, 24 h) and carefully rinsed to remove any trace of ligand before transferring them to the growth medium of eukaryotic (glial) cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Under these conditions, the apoptotic-like effect of P. fluorescens MF37 was strongly decreased (−49±18%) ( Fig. 8 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Similar results were observed at doses of PK 11195 ranging from 10−6 to 10−8 M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The same experiment was repeated using P. fluorescens 373, a mutant of MF37 lacking the gene for OprF (the major porin of the bacterium) and P. fluorescens 373O, the oprF-complemented mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The apoptotic-like effect of the mutant 373 was identical to that of MF37 but its necrotic-like activity was significantly reduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>PK 11195 had no effect on the cytotoxicity of this oprF deleted mutant of P. fluorescens. OprF-transcomplementation allowed partial reversion of the phenotype with almost total restoration of the original necrotic-like activity of bacterium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>However to the apoptotic-like activity was reduced in the OprF-complemented mutant 373O and it was not possible to visualize restoration of the sensitivity to PK 11195. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0006096-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006096.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Effect of PK 11195 on Pseudomonas fluorescens MF37 adhesion to glass or eukaryotic cells, and on biofilm formation on PVC. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Results are expressed as percentages of the values measured in the absence of treatment (100%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>These changes were not associated with variations in the global surface polarity of bacteria. ***P&lt;0.001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006096.g007"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0006096-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006096.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Effect of PK 11195 on the cytotoxicity of Pseudomonas fluorescens MF37 and its OprF-deficient (373) and complemented OprF-deficient (373O) mutants. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>(a) Effect of PK 11195 (10−5 M) on the apoptotic-like activity of the bacteria determined by measuring nitrite production (NO2 −) resulting from NO biosynthesis by eukaryotic cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>(b) Effect of PK 11195 (10−5 M) on necrotic-like effect of P. fluorescens MF37, 373 and 373O determined by lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) activity released by eukaryotic cells. ***P&lt;0.001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>NS: not significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006096.g008"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The results of the present study demonstrate the existence of a tspO gene in a wide variety of bacterial species and its expression as bacterial TSPO protein in the micro-organism Pseudomonas fluorescens, where its role in virulence regulation appears to be entirely different than initially proposed for Rhodobacter sphaeroides and α-proteobacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>As observed in the case of other proteins [20], [21] whose structures were strongly preserved during evolution, functions can evolve independently and the present results reveal that it is necessary to reconsider the way we interpret the presence of TSPO in bacteria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Pseudomonas, and particularly Pseudomonas fluorescens, are ubiquitous and non-photosynthetic micro-organisms that diverged long time ago from the ancestor of Rhodobacter sphaeroides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Because of the high versatility of this micro-organism [22] we conducted most of our bioinformatic studies on the basis of the bacterial TSPO sequence from the reference strain, P. fluorescens MF37. P. fluorescens MF37 is a typical psychrotrophic bacterium member of the biovar V subdivision of the species and its physiological characteristics have been extensively investigated in our laboratory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In addition to cloning of the tspO gene of P. fluorescens MF37, we attempted to produce a deletion mutant by different techniques ranging from simple crossing over and cloning in pMOS, pME3087 or pKNOCK suicide vectors to double crossing over using the Cre-lox system but we never succeeded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>In eukaryotes deletion of the tspO gene is lethal [23] suggesting involvement of TSPO in essential physiological functions and our observations indicate that it should be also the same in P. fluorescens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>We propose to designate this protein as “bacterial TSPO” in accordance with the names of “mitochondrial TSPO” and “nuclear TSPO” in eukaryotes [2]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The topological structure deduced from the TSPO sequence of P. fluorescens MF37, characterized by a five transmembrane helix, is analogous to that of R. sphaeroides 2.4.1 and mitochondrial TSPO [12], [13], though it appears to be partially or completely truncated at the N- and C-terminus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The structure of the TSPO molecule is particularly well preserved in the regions essential for its function, such as the first cytoplasmic loop, considered to be the main ligand-binding domain of the protein [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>However, there is a divergence of orientation between bacterial and mitochondrial TSPO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In mitochondria, the N-terminus of TSPO is oriented in direction of the matrix [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>In contrast, in R. sphaeroides bacterial TSPO appears inserted in the opposite sense, i.e. with the N-terminus exposed to the extracellular side [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>A same orientation was predicted by TopPred for TSPO in P. fluorescens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The origin of this inversion of orientation should be ascribed to the fact that in eukaryotes TSPO is encoded in the nuclear genome and translocated to the outer membrane of the mitochondrium [24] whereas in bacteria, which synthesise TSPO in their cytoplasm, the protein has to be inserted from the inside of the prokaryotic cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The localization of TSPO in the membranes of P. fluorescens is apparently different from that previously found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>In R. sphaeroides [12], as in mitochondria [2], TSPO is shown associated to the outer membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>In contrast, calculations using the software PSORTb and extraction tests on bacterial sub-membrane fractions both suggest association of TSPO to the inner membrane of P. fluorescens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>In support of this hypothesis it is known that in Gram-negative bacteria, proteins folded in α-helixes are essentially, if not exclusively, associated to the inner membrane [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The presence of a peptidoglycan binding domain in the C terminal region of P. fluorescens TSPO is consistent with association of this protein to the bacterial membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>A similar peptidoglycan binding signature was also observed in the porin OprF of Pseudomonas aeruginosa [26] and OmpA of Erwinia carotovora [27] but the role of this hidden domain in TSPO is unexplained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Experimental studies could reveal differences with predictive model, as described for mammalian TSPO by Murail et al. [28] making possible that the peptidoglycan domain of TSPO was more exposed to the surface and have same function of anchoring to periplasmic peptidoglycan as described for the C terminal region of P. aeruginosa OprF [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Since we have collected strains of P. fluorescens from diverse environments, including from clinical origins, where they were identified as opportunistic pathogens [14], we searched for the presence of a tspO gene in various biovar and temperature variants of the species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Primers derived from the MF37 tspO gene sequence revealed that homologous sequences are indeed present, not only in the genomes of biovar I, II, and V of the species, but also in a closely related species, Pseudomonas putida. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The high degree of similarity of the translated sequences (90%) suggests that the structure of TSPO is conserved between these bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we were particularly surprised by our failure to detect a tspO-like sequence in one clinical strain of P. fluorescens and in Pseudomonas aeruginosa PAO1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>As confirmed later in an in-silico study on all eubacterial sequences available in the NCBI databank, the distribution of the tspO gene is wide but very irregular. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>In addition, although we could build a cladogram over 97 bacterial TSPO sequences, it was impossible to define specific clusters corresponding to sub-types of this protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The irregular presence of TSPO in eubacteria can not be simply explained by a lack of homogeneity of the species whose genomes were registered in the NCBI data-bank or by an insufficient volume of data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>In contrast, as suggested by the detailed study of the genomic environment of tspO in fluorescent Pseudomonas, this situation probably reflects an original mechanism of acquisition of TSPO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Indeed, in the different genomes of Pseudomonas where TSPO was detected, we noted at the vicinity of the tspO gene the presence of genes encoding transposases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>This topographical organization should favor gene exchange and, consequently, the irregular distribution of the protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Although, there is no precise limit values for differences between CG contents in individual genes, the low level of variations of the GC contents between tspO and the neighboring genes in each individual species or strains [29] suggests that tspO does not results from a recent gene transfer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>In addition, as indicated from our western blot studies, TSPO expression is precisely regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Whereas a tspO gene was detected in 5 of the 6 strains of P. fluorescens studied and alignment of the translated sequences suggested a high degree of homology of the protein, the TSPO protein was only detected in MF37 and in its parental strain, MF0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The identity of the protein was confirmed by ESI-MS/MS analysis, although the apparent mass of the protein was double what was predicted, suggesting that, as shown by Yeliseev &amp; Kaplan [12] and Delavoie et al. [30], bacterial TSPO exists as a dimer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Secondary binding peaks for the specific ligand of TSPO PK 11195 were observed but they should not represent trimers or tetramers of TSPO since they were not recognized in western blot by the antiserum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The disparities between the results of PCR and western blot analysis could result either from conformational variations making TSPO undetectable by the antiserum (an unlikely situation because the polyclonal antiserum shows cross reactivity with different forms of TSPO, including those of vegetal origin [7]), or from the existence of specific regulatory mechanisms in the different strains which could repress TSPO expression in our experimental conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Altogether, these results suggest that bacterial TSPO is a protein whose acquisition and expression is precisely regulated, as is normally observed for molecules with important physiological functions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>In the bacterial TSPO of MF37, the high degree of conservation in the region considered to be the ligand-binding domain of the protein is consistent with our observation that PK 11195, a high-affinity ligand of mitochondrial TSPO, was also recognized by this protein with nanomolar affinity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>This observation provided an opportunity to directly probe the function of bacterial TSPO in P. fluorescens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>PK 11195 did not modulate bacterial growth and mobility, and this result was independent of the oxygenation conditions of the bacterium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>This is different from what has been observed in R. sphaeroides, where TSPO is considered to be an oxygen sensor [9], and is not surprising considering P. fluorescens is not a photosynthetic bacterium and that the metabolism, structural, and even genomic organization of the two micro-organisms have very few common points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The observation that PK 11195 increases the adhesion of P. fluorescens on diverse surfaces ranging from glass to eukaryotic cells and also stimulates the biofilm formation potential of bacteria on polystyrene is essential, since bacterial adhesion is considered a key point in virulence expression [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Bacterial adhesion is mediated by at least three types of forces generated by surface polarity, pili and flagella, or specific membrane proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>As PK 11195 has the same effect on bacterial adhesion to polar (glass), complex (eukaryotic cells), and hydrophobic surfaces (polystyrene) and does not modify the affinity to solvents of the bacteria, global variations of surface polarity can be excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Considering that the flagellar-dependent mobility of P. fluorescens was not influenced by PK 11195 treatment, our results suggest that this molecule acts on the configuration and/or activity of a specific membrane adhesin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>In P. fluorescens, the porin OprF is the major outer membrane protein and implication of this molecule in adhesion to living cells [32], matrix protein [33], and abiotic surfaces [34] has already been demonstrated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>As we did not observe any binding of PK 11195 to OprF by western blot, we can only postulate an indirect action of the drug on this protein, a hypothesis that was tested in the last part of the study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>When P. fluorescens MF37 was pre-treated with PK 11195, its apoptotic-like effect on eukaryotic cells (glial cells) was significantly reduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the necrotic-like effect of the bacterium was not changed, suggesting that PK 11195 was not acting on the release of enzymes and/or soluble toxins, but was modulating a specific apoptotic signal generated by the bacterium, and probably associated with outer membrane surface components. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The same experiment was conducted in a P. fluorescens OprF-deficient mutant derived from MF37 (MF373). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The apoptotic-like effect of MF373 was identical to that of its parent strain whereas its necrotic activity was markedly reduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>This difference should be ascribed to the absence of OprF which is an adhesin required for contact mediated cytotoxicity [32], [33] and has intrinsic cytotoxic potential [35], [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>In this oprF-deleted strain, PK 11195 does not modules the apoptotic-like activity of the bacterium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that PK 11195 acts on a process that regulates the virulence of P. fluorescens and requires expression of OprF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The necrotic-like activity of P. fluorescens was almost completely restored in the oprF-transcomplemented strain P. fluorescens 373O whereas its apoptotic effect was reduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>In these conditions it was not possible to observe a restoration of the inhibitory activity of PK 11195 on apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>This partial phenotypic reversion in the complemented strain can be explained by the fact that plasmidic oprF-transcomplementation does not fully reproduces the regulation exerted over the endogenous chromosome-bound gene and underlines the phenotypic sensitivity of Pseudomonas to plasmidic of chromosomal transformations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>From these results, it is tempting to speculate that, as is the case of mitochondrial TSPO and VDAC in peripheral-type benzodiazepine receptors, dimers of bacterial TSPO interact with a porin, namely OprF, and form hyper-structures in the membrane of P. fluorescens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The degree of homology of mitochondrial and bacterial TSPO is consistent with evolution from a common ancestor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>In contrast, although VDAC and OprF are both porins, structural similarities between the two proteins are very low. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Therefore, functional association between bacterial TSPO and OprF appears more as the result of evolutionary convergence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>We should be then in this unique hyperstructure in the presence of a double and opposite evolutionary mechanism. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Although the natural ligand(s) of TSPO remains controversial, even in mammals, a first consequence of the present work is that it is highly probable that such molecules should be detected both by bacteria and eukaryotes and participate to inter-kingdom signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Communication between bacteria and eukaryotes using common molecules was only recently explored under the general identification of Microbial Endocrinology [37] but the consequences of such mechanisms are multiple. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Indeed, since benzodiazepines are widely prescribed in medicine, these drugs are certainly exerting a continuous pressure on the physiology of the bacterial species of the human intestinal microflora. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The resulting effect of these chronic and unsuspected interactions between benzodiazepines and the commensal microbiome remains to be investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>On another side, this study suggests new hypothesis for the development of antibacterial molecules acting as virulence inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Indeed, by reducing the virulence of germs, PK 11195 or related molecules may allow the host to clear an infection without generating resistant forms of bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>This strategy is a new path to find alternative solutions to antibiotics as urgently requested by the World Heath Organization [38]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>(Use of PK11195 and derived molecules as inhibitors of virulence is covered by the French Patent No. 2 894 478 and is the property of ADIPpharm). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Bacterial strains and culture conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>P. fluorescens MF37 (biovar V) is a spontaneous mutant of the MF0 strain isolated from raw milk [15]. P. fluorescens clinical strains, MFY162 and MFN1032, are biovar I [14], whereas MFY63 and MFY70 are biovar II [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Clinical strain, MFN3597 is a P. putida biovar B [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>For all strains, cultures were grown in Nutrient Broth (NB; Merck) medium (28°C, 180 rpm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Cultures were inoculated at an initial OD580 nm of 0.08 and harvested in early stationary phase. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Cloning and sequencing of bacterial tspO in MF37 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The nucleotide sequence of MF37 bacterial tspO gene was deposited in the Gen-Bank database under accession number FJ185105. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Primers 392-1 (CCGACCATGACCTTCTTCAT) and 392-1′ (GCCAGGTAAGGGAACAGGAT) were designed from the P. fluorescens SBW25 tspO genomic sequence (Sanger Institute <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sanger.ac.uk">http://www.sanger.ac.uk</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Purified chromosomal DNA was PCR amplified using 35 cycles of denaturation (30 s, 94°C), hybridization (1 min, 60°C) and elongation (1 min, 72°C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The PCR fragment was cloned into the pMOSBlue vector, according to the supplier's protocol (pMOSBlue Blunt ended kit, Roche). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Positive colonies were confirmed by PCR using the plasmidic universal primers, T7 and U19. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Recombinant plasmids were extracted using the QIAprep Spin Miniprep (Qiagen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Plasmids were sequenced on both strands by Genomexpress (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome-express.com">www.genome-express.com</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>In-silico analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The localization of TSPO and the predicted transmembrane structure were determined using the TopPred (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mobyle.pasteur.fr/cgi-bin/MobylePortal">http://mobyle.pasteur.fr/cgi-bin/MobylePortal</ext-link>) and PSORTb v2.0.4 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.psort.org">http://www.psort.org</ext-link>) programs [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>The predicted structure of MF37 TSPO was compared to that of R. sphaeroides 2.4.1, recalculated from Yeliseev &amp; Kaplan [12] and mitochondrial TSPO [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Existence of a peptidoglycan-binding signature (NXXLSXXRAXXVXXXL), based on the sequence of OmpA [27], was investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Homologies between the sequence of MF37 TSPO and those of other eubacteria were determined by searching the NCBI databank using the BLASTP program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Sequences were aligned using the multiple protein alignment algorithm, Clustal W [41], and analyzed using Philip version 3.5 (DNA parsimony program). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The degree of statistical support for branches was determined with 1000 bootstrap replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>The cladogram was visualized by Treeview 1.6.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>For analysis of the tspO genomic environment, flanking sequences in strains P. fluorescens Pf0-1 and P. syringae pv.syringae (B728a), phaseolicola (1448A), and tomato (DC3000) were retrieved from the Pseudomonas Genome Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pseudomonas.com">http://www.pseudomonas.com</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>For SBW25, 5,000 bp upstream and downstream of tspO were retrieved from the Sanger Institute (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sanger.ac.uk">http://www.sanger.ac.uk</ext-link>) and translated into protein sequence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://insilico.ehu.es">http://insilico.ehu.es</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>The hypothetical gene sequences were blasted against the prokaryotic NCBI database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>) and for each one, the most likely homologue was included in the map of the genomic environment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>PCR, Western blot and ESI MS-MS analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>For PCR analysis, chromosomal bacterial DNA was extracted and subjected to PCR using primers designed from MF37 tspO to allow amplification of the last 363 bp ( Tav363F:AAA GGA TCC GGT ACG AAT CCC TGG TCA AA and Tav363R: AAA AAG CTT TCT TAT TCC GCA GGA TCG AG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>PCR was performed using 30 cycles of denaturation (30 s, 94°C), hybridization (45 s, 60°C) and elongation (45 s, 72°C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>For Western blot studies, proteins (40 µg), obtained from MF37 in early stationary phase, were separated by SDS-PAGE on a 15% acrylamide gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Proteins were transferred for 30 min (490 mA) onto nitrocellulose membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Membranes were saturated for 1 h at 20°C in Tris-buffered saline (TBS: 20 mM Tris pH 7.5; 500 mM NaCl) containing 2% skim milk and 0.5% bovine serum albumin (BSA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Membranes were then incubated overnight at 4°C with rabbit anti-mouse mitochondrial TSPO [42] in blocking solution (1∶2,000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Membranes were rinsed twice with TBS containing 0.1% Tween 20 (TTBS) and incubated for 1.5 h at 20°C with alkaline phosphatase-conjugated goat anti-rabbit antibody (Biorad) in TTBS-1% BSA (1∶3,000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The colorimetric reactions were developed according to the instructions of the provider (BioRad). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>For electron spray ionization tandem mass spectrometry (ESI MS-MS), total bacterial proteins were extracted, as previously described [43], and an equivalent of 80 µg protein was separated by SDS-PAGE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The gel was cut vertically into two parts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>One side was used for western blot analysis, while the other was stained with coomassie blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The band containing TSPO-like immunoreactive protein was processed for ESI MS-MS analysis (UMR INRA1253, Rennes, France). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>The resulting peptide sequences were analyzed using “Findpeptool” software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.expasy.org/tools/">http://www.expasy.org/tools/</ext-link> findpept.html) to compare theoretical and experimental masses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Radioligand binding studies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Tritiated PK 11195 (3H-PK 11195; 73.6 Ci/mmole) was obtained from Perkin Elmer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Proteins were transferred onto nitrocellulose membranes and saturated for 1 h in the blocking solution already described. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Membranes were rinsed twice in TBS and incubated for 30 min at 20°C in TBS containing 2.5 µCi/mL 3H-PK 11195. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Membranes were then rinsed two times for 10 min in TBS and cut into 3 mm fragments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Each fragment was transferred to minivials containing 5 mL of scintillation liquid (Perkin-Elmer). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>For Scatchard studies, bacterial membranes were obtained by sonication on ice (four cycles of 30 s followed by microscopic control), adjusted to a final concentration of 60 µg membrane proteins/250 µl Tris-HCl buffer (50 mM, pH = 7.4), and incubated with 3H-PK 11195 at concentrations ranging from 0.6 to 59 nM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Mixtures were subjected to three steps of centrifugation (10 min, 10,500×g, 4°C) to remove membrane-bound tracer and rinsed with 0.5 mL ice-cold Tris-HCl buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Non-specific binding was determined by repeating the experiment in the presence of non-radioactive PK 11195 (30 µM). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Biophysical studies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Due to its hydrophobicity, PK 11195 was dissolved in ethanol before mixing with culture medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The final ethanol concentration was kept to 0.01%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>All control experiments were performed in the presence of a same percentage of ethanol (0.01%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>In normal oxygenation conditions, the culture medium corresponded to one-tenth of the volume of the culture vial volume, and one-half for reduced oxygenation conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Growth kinetics were determined by measuring OD580 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Swimming mobility was evaluated by puncture inoculation of plates containing NB supplemented with 0.3% agar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Swarming mobility tests were performed using an identical protocol, except that bacteria were deposited at the surface of NB supplemented with 0.5% agar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Bacterial adhesion to glass surfaces was studied using microscopic slides cleaned with ethanol and TFD4 detergent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Adhesion tests were performed by immersing slides for 2 h at 28°C in bacterial culture (108 CFU/mL) and staining with acridine orange (0.01%, 20 min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>For biofilm formation studies, bacteria were resuspended in NB at an OD595 nm of 0.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>A constant volume of 100 µL of suspension was laid in a 96 well-plate and incubated at 28°C for 24 h in a water-saturated atmosphere. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Each well was then rinsed and incubated in 0.1% crystal violet in water for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>The excess of dye was removed and the crystal violet-stained biofilm was then dissolved with sodium dodecyl sulfate (1%), and the OD595 nm of the extract was measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Possible variations in the surface polarity of the bacteria were investigated using the microbial adhesion to solvent technique described by Bellon-Fontaine et al. [44] and hexadecane as hydrophobic solvent. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Cell adhesion/invasion assays and cytotoxicity tests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Primary cultures of glial cells were obtained from newborn Wistar rats according to the recommendations of the French Ethics Committee (Agreements AGEXP27.01 and 27.06). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>The culture medium consisted of DMEM and Ham's medium (2∶1) supplemented with 10% fetal calf serum, 2 mM glutamine, 0.001% insulin, 5 mM HEPES, 0.3% glucose, and 1% antibiotic-antimycotic solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Cells were allowed to grow for 12 days to reach confluence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Just before the infection test, bacteria harvested by centrifugation (6,000 rpm, 10 min) were resuspended in glial cell culture medium without antibiotics to a final concentration of 106 CFU/mL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Effect of PK 11195-treatment on adhesive and invasive behaviors of bacteria was evaluated using the gentamicin survival assay [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>The effect of PK 11195 on the cytotoxicity of P. fluorescens MF37 was determined through measurement of nitrite (NO2 −) and lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) release by glial cells following a 24 h incubation in culture medium with bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The use of these indirect methods for the study of apoptosis and necrosis has been previously validated [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Control studies were performed to verify the absence of nitrite or LDH production by bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>The concentration of nitrites in the incubation medium was determined using the Griess reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>The concentration of LDH in the medium was determined using the Cytotox 96® enzymatic assay (Promega, France). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>LDH release was expressed as a percentage of the total amount of the enzyme generated through complete cellular lysis using Triton X-100 (9% [v/v]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>The assays were sensitive enough to detect 0.5 µM NO2 − and a concentration of LDH equivalent to the lysis of 1% of the cell population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Values (mean±SEM) were calculated over a minimum of six independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Authors wish to thank Dr. P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Barbey, IMOGERE University of Caen, for giving access to his radioactivity laboratory and Dr. D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Mollé, UMR 1253 INRA-Agrocampus, for ESI MS-MS analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Funding: This work was supported by grants from the Communaute d'Agglomeration d'Evreux and the Conseil General de l'Eure (CG27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>VP was supported by NIH grant ES007747 and a Canada Research Chair. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0006096-TheU.S.SleepMarket1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>1 The U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Sleep Market 2008 Marketdata Enterprises Inc. 145  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Papadopoulos1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>2 PapadopoulosVBaraldiMGuilarteTRKnudsenTBLacapèreJ-J 2006 Translocator protein (18kDa): new nomenclature for the peripheral-type benzodiazepine receptor based on its structure and molecular function. Trends Pharmacol Sci 27 402 409 16822554 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Zisterer1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>3 ZistererDMWilliamsDC 1997 Peripheral-type benzodiazepine receptors. Gen Pharmacol 29 305 314 9378234 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-McEnery1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>4 McEneryMWSnowmanAMTrifilettiRRSnyderSH 1992 Isolation of the mitochondrial benzodiazepine receptor: association with the voltage-dependent anion channel and the adenine nucleotide carrier. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 89 3170 3174 1373486 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Veenman1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>5 VeenmanLPapadopoulosVGavishM 2007 Channel-like functions of the 18-kDa translocator protein (TSPO): regulation of apoptosis and steroidogenesis as part of the host-defense response. Curr Pharm Des 13 2385 2405 17692008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Snyder1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>6 SnyderMJVan AntwerpenR 1998 Evidence for a diazepam-binding inhibitor (DBI) benzodiazepine receptor-like mechanism in ecdysteroidogenesis by the insect prothoracic gland. Cell Tissue Res 294 161 168 9724466 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Lindemann1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>7 LindemannPKochADegenhardtBHauseGGrimmB 2004 A novel Arabidopsis thaliana protein is a functional peripheral-type benzodiazepine receptor. Plant Cell Physiol 45 723 733 15215507 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Yeliseev1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>8 YeliseevAAKaplanS 1995 A sensory transducer homologous to the mammalian peripheral-type benzodiazepine receptor regulates photosynthetic membrane complex formation in Rhodobacter sphaeroides 2.4.1. J Biol Chem 270 21167 21175 7673149 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Yeliseev2"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>9 YeliseevAAKruegerKEKaplanS 1997 A mammalian mitochondrial drug receptor functions as a bacterial “oxygen” sensor. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 94 5101 5106 9144197 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-StoweEvans1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>10 Stowe-EvansELFordJKehoeDM 2004 Genomic DNA microarray analysis: identification of new genes regulated by light color in the cyanobacterium Fremyella diplosiphon. J Bacteriol 186 4338 4349 15205436 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Davey1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>11 DaveyMEDe BruijnFJ 2000 A homologue of the tryptophan-rich sensory protein TspO and FixL regulate a novel nutrient deprivation-induced Sinorhizobium meliloti locus. Appl Environ Microbiol 66 5353 5359 11097914 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Yeliseev3"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>12 YeliseevAAKaplanS 2000 TspO of Rhodobacter sphaeroides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>A structural and functional model for the mammalian peripheral benzodiazepine receptor. J Biol Chem 275 5657 5667 10681549 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-JosephLiauzun1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>13 Joseph-LiauzunEDelmasPShireDFerraraP 1998 Topological analysis of the peripheral benzodiazepine receptor in yeast mitochondrial membranes supports a five-transmembrane structure. J Biol Chem 273 2146 2152 9442055 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Chapalain1"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>14 ChapalainARossignolGLesouhaitierOMerieauAGruffazC 2008 Comparative study of 7 fluorescent pseudomonad clinical isolates. Can J Microbiol 54 19 27 18388968 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Burini1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>15 BuriniJ-FGugiBMerieauAGuespin-MichelJF 1994 Lipase and acidic phosphatase from the psychrotrophic bacterium Pseudomonas fluorescens: two enzymes whose synthesis is regulated by the growth temperature. FEMS Microbiol Lett 122 13 18 7958764 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-LeFur1"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>16 Le FurGGuillouxFRufatPBenavidesJUzanA 1983 Peripheral benzodiazepine binding sites: effect of PK 11195, 1-(2-chlorophenyl)-N-methyl-(1-methylpropyl)-3 isoquinoline carboxamide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>II. In vivo studies. Life Sci 32 1849 1856 6300589 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Lacapre1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>17 LacapèreJ-JDelavoieFLiHPéranziGMaccarioJ 2001 Structural and functional study of reconstituted peripheral benzodiazepine receptor. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 284 536 541 11394915 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Wyckoff1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>18 WyckoffTJThomasBHassettDJWozniakDJ 2002 Static growth of mucoid Pseudomonas aeruginosa selects for non-mucoid variants that have acquired flagellum-dependent motility. Microbiology 148 3423 3430 12427934 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Picot1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>19 PicotLChevalierSMezghani-AbdelmoulaSMerieauALesouhaitierO 2003 Cytotoxic effects of the lipopolysaccharide from Pseudomonas fluorescens on neurons and glial cells. Microb Pathog 35 95 106 12927517 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Baughn1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>20 BaughnADMalamyMH 2002 A mitochondrial-like aconitase in the bacterium Bacteroides fragilis: implications for the evolution of the mitochondrial Krebs cycle. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 99 4662 4667 11880608 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Schleiff1"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>21 SchleiffESollJ 2005 Membrane protein insertion: mixing eukaryotic and prokaryotic concepts. EMBO Rep 6 1023 1027 16264426 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Mackenzie1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>22 MackenzieCErasoJMChoudharyMRohJHZengX 2007 Postgenomic adventures with Rhodobacter sphaeroides. Annu Rev Microbiol 61 283 307 17506668 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Papadopoulos2"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>23 PapadopoulosVAmriHBoujradNCascioCCultyM 1997 Peripheral benzodiazepine receptor in cholesterol transport and steroidogenesis. Steroids 62 21 28 9029710 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Otera1"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>24 OteraHTairaYHorieCSuzukiYSuzukiH 2007 A novel insertion pathway of mitochondrial outer membrane proteins with multiple transmembrane segments. J Cell Biol 179 1355 1363 18158327 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Klebba1"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>25 KlebbaPE 2005 The porinologist. J Bacteriol 187 8232 8236 16321927 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Sugawara1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>26 SugawaraESteiertMRouhaniSNikaidoH 1996 Secondary structure of the outer membrane proteins OmpA of Escherichia coli and OprF of Pseudomonas aeruginosa. J Bacteriol 178 6067 6079 8830709 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-ElHamel1"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>27 El HamelCChevalierSDeEOrangeNMolleG 2001 Isolation and characterisation of the major outer membrane protein of Erwinia carotovora. Biochim Biophys Acta 1515 12 22 11597348 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Murail1"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>28 MurailSRobertJCCoicYMNeumannJMOstuniMA 2008 Secondary and tertiary structures of the transmembrane domains of the translocator protein TSPO determined by NMR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Stabilization of the TSPO tertiary fold upon ligand binding. Biochim Biophys Acta 1778 1375 1381 18420025 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Vandamme1"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>29 VandammePPotBGillisMDe VosPKerstersK 1996 Polyphasic taxonomy, a consensus approach to bacterial systematics. Microbiol Rev 60 407 438 8801440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Delavoie1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>30 DelavoieFLiHHardwickMRobertJCGiatzakisC 2003  In vivo and in vitro peripheral-type benzodiazepine receptor polymerization: functional significance in drug ligand and cholesterol binding. Biochemistry 42 4506 4519 12693947 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Pimenta1"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>31 PimentaALDi MartinoPBlightMA 2006 Positive correlation between in vivo and in vitro assays for the evaluation of Pseudomonas virulence. Res Microbiol 157 885 890 16901681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Azghani1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>32 AzghaniAOIdellSBainsMHancockRE 2002  Pseudomonas aeruginosa outer membrane protein F is an adhesin in bacterial binding to lung epithelial cells in culture. Microb Pathog 33 109 114 12220987 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-RebireHut1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>33 Rebière-HuëtJGuérillonJPimentaALDi MartinoPOrangeN 2002 Porins of Pseudomonas fluorescens MFO as fibronectin-binding proteins. FEMS Microbiol Lett 215 121 126 12393211 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Hemery1"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>34 HemeryGChevalierSBellon-FontaineM-NHarasDOrangeN 2007 Growth temperature and OprF porin affect cell surface physicochemical properties and adhesive capacities of Pseudomonas fluorescens MF37. J Ind Microbiol Biotechnol 34 49 54 16932888 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Cusumano1"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>35 CusumanoVTufanoMAMancusoGCarboneMRossanoF 1997 Porins of Pseudomonas aeruginosa induce release of tumor necrosis factor alpha and interleukin-6 by human leukocytes. Infect Immun 65 1683 1687 9125547 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Buommino1"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>36 BuomminoEMorelliFMetaforaSRossanoFPerfettoB 1999 Porin from Pseudomonas aeruginosa induces apoptosis in an epithelial cell line derived from rat seminal vesicles. Infect Immun 67 4794 4800 10456933 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Freestone1"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>37 FreestonePPLyteM 2008 Microbial endocrinology: experimental design issues in the study of interkingdom signaling in infectious disease. Adv Appl Microbiol 64 75 105 18485281 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Cegelski1"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>38 CegelskiLMarshallGREldridgeGRHultgrenSJ 2008 The biology and future prospects of antivirulence therapies. Nat Rev Microbiol 6 17 27 18079741 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Bodilis1"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>39 BodilisJCalbrixRGuérillonJMerieauAPawlakB 2004 Phylogenetic relationships between environmental and clinical isolates of Pseudomonas fluorescens and related species deduced from 16S rRNA gene and OprF protein sequences. Syst Appl Microbiol 27 93 108 15053326 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Gardy1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>40 GardyJLLairdMRChenFReySWalshCJ 2005 PSORTb v.2.0: expanded prediction of bacterial protein subcellular localization and insights gained from comparative proteome analysis. Bioinformatics 21 617 623 15501914 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Thompson1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>41 ThompsonJDGibsonTJPlewniakFJeanmouginFHigginsDG 1997 The CLUSTAL_X windows interface: flexible strategies for multiple sequence alignment aided by quality analysis tools. Nucleic Acids Res 25 4876 4882 9396791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-Li1"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>42 LiHYaoZDegenhardtBTeperGPapadopoulosV 2001 Cholesterol binding at the cholesterol recognition/interaction amino acid consensus (CRAC) of the peripheral-type benzodiazepine receptor and inhibition of steroidogenesis by an HIV TAT-CRAC peptide. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 98 1267 1272 11158628 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-GonzalezMarquez1"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>43 Gonzalez-MarquezHPerrinCBracquartPGuimontCLindenG 1997 A 16 kDa protein family overexpressed by Streptococcus thermophilus PB18 in acid environments. Microbiology 143 1587 1594 9168610 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-BellonFontaine1"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>44 Bellon-FontaineM-NRaultJVan OssCJ 1996 Microbial adhesion to solvents: a novel method to determine the electron-donor/electron-acceptor or Lewis acid-base properties of microbial cells. Colloids Surf B Biointerfaces 7 47 53  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0006096-MezghaniAbdelmoula1"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>45 Mezghani-AbdelmoulaSKhemiriALesouhaitierOChevalierSOrangeN 2004 Sequential activation of constitutive and inducible nitric oxide synthase (NOS) in rat cerebellar granule neurons by Pseudomonas fluorescens and invasive behaviour of the bacteria. Microbiol Res 159 355 363 15646382 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
