
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><?epub September-22-2009?><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2790905</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19773421</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkp792</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkp792</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Computational Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Universal function-specificity of codon usage </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 00, No. 0</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 00, No. 0</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Najafabadi</surname><given-names>Hamed Shateri</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goodarzi</surname><given-names>Hani</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Salavati</surname><given-names>Reza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Institute of Parasitology, McGill University, 21111 Lakeshore Road, Ste. Anne de Bellevue, Montreal, Quebec, H9X3V9, <sup>2</sup>McGill Centre for Bioinformatics, McGill University, Duff Medical Building, 3775 University Street, Montreal, Quebec, H3A2B4, Canada, <sup>3</sup>Department of Molecular Biology and Lewis-Sigler Institute for Integrative Genomics, Princeton University, Princeton NJ 08544, USA and <sup>4</sup>Department of Biochemistry, McGill University, McIntyre Medical Building, 3655 Promenade Sir William Osler, Montreal, Quebec, H3G1Y6, Canada</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 514 398 7721; Fax: +1 514 398 7857; Email: <email>reza.salavati@mcgill.ca</email></corresp><fn><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>37</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>7014</fpage><lpage>7023</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>8</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>9</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2009. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/uk/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Synonymous codon usage has long been known as a factor that affects average expression level of proteins in fast-growing microorganisms, but neither its role in dynamic changes of expression in response to environmental changes nor selective factors shaping it in the genomes of higher eukaryotes have been fully understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Here, we propose that codon usage is ubiquitously selected to synchronize the translation efficiency with the dynamic alteration of protein expression in response to environmental and physiological changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Our analysis reveals that codon usage is universally correlated with gene function, suggesting its potential contribution to synchronized regulation of genes with similar functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We directly show that coexpressed genes have similar synonymous codon usages within the genomes of human, yeast, Caenorhabditis elegans and Escherichia coli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>We also demonstrate that perturbing the codon usage directly affects the level or even direction of changes in protein expression in response to environmental stimuli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Perturbing tRNA composition also has tangible phenotypic effects on the cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>By showing that codon usage is universally function-specific, our results expand, to almost all organisms, the notion that cells may need to dynamically alter their intracellular tRNA composition in order to adapt to their new environment or physiological role. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide analysis of gene expression has been extensively used to study the mechanisms underlying the dynamic regulation of gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Simultaneous changes in transcript levels across different conditions (i.e. environmental as well as spacio-temporal and genetic variables) have been widely used as a proxy for identifying sets of coregulated genes, thus revealing the common regulatory elements underlying these observed correlations (1,2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>These regulatory elements can act at both transcriptional and post-transcriptional levels including mechanisms such as localization and stability of the transcript and enhancement or suppression of translation (3,4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Most studies have focused on the non-coding genome for finding such regulatory elements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>While coding sequences have also been shown to contain elements that contribute to regulation of expression for a minority of genes (5–7), the relationship between the dynamic regulation of expression and the sequence of coding regions is not considered widespread among and within organisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>A novel relationship between coding sequence and dynamic regulation of protein expression can be readily hypothesized from the observed variations in patterns of isoacceptor tRNA abundance and tRNA charging in different conditions and tissues (8–10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>For example, during amino acid starvation, unlike common tRNA species, the charged level of certain isoacceptor tRNAs cognate to rare codons remains high (8,11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, these rare codons are used in higher frequencies among genes involved in amino acid biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the high charged level of their cognate tRNA species can boost the amino acid biosynthesis pathway by supporting the high expression level of its enzymes (11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Methylation of the wobble base of a tRNA in yeast has also been shown to affect its codon preference, enhancing levels of certain proteins (12). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Congruent with the observed tissue-specificity of tRNA composition (10), Plotkin et al. (13) report the presence of a tissue-specific codon usage in human genes, although Sémon et al. (14) reject their hypothesis using a different statistical analysis and a richer database of tissue-specific genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>However, many other studies indirectly suggest the act of selection on synonymous codons in human genome (15); these models propose translational efficiency (16–18), mRNA stability (19–21) and splicing control (22) as mechanisms underlying such selection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Despite all these studies, factors shaping codon usage of genes in many organisms, including human, are still not completely understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>For example, no significant evidence for the presence of selection on codon usage was found in 30% of the bacteria that were examined using a population genetics-based model (23). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>A recent study has profoundly added to this complication by reporting that it is not the codon usage, but rather RNA structure that affects expression level of a protein (24). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>More than 30 years ago, Garel (25) reported that the tRNA composition of silk gland in silkworm changes during the development of this organ in order to accommodate for the high rate of synthesis of fibroin which is rich in glycine, alanine, serine and tyrosine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In other words, silk gland cells try to synchronize the translation efficiency of fibroin with its required amount at each time by providing the tRNAs that carry these four amino acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Matching tRNA composition with coding sequence may extend beyond amino acid usage of the proteins and include synonymous codon usage as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Here, based on several rigorous statistical analyses of coding sequences from almost all available genomes, we suggest function-specificity of synonymous codon usage in a wide range of organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>This implies that functional adaptation of tRNA content (25) may be a universal mechanism for synchronizing the translation efficiency with the dynamic, function-specific alteration of protein expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In other words, rather than having a single set of optimal codons, organisms could harbor different sets that change depending on environmental conditions or physiological roles and are related to the functions that are most expressed at each of these conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>We show that this hypothesis best explains the synonymous codon usage of genes across all domains of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>It also explains our recent observation that in three different organisms, Saccharomyces cerevisiae, E. coli and Plasmodium falciparum, genes whose products interact either physically or functionally use similar codons (26). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Although not as comprehensive as our computational analysis, we also provide limited experimental data showing that differences in codon usage or variations in the tRNA content of the cell can result in varied responses to environmental changes, in terms of regulation of protein expression and cell phenotype. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Analysis of correlation between codon usage and function/expression pattern </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Normalized frequency of each codon in each gene ( fc) was calculated as the usage of that codon divided by the usage of the amino acid it codes for. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>For each gene, we calculated the normalized frequencies of codons of an amino acid only if the usage of that amino acid was higher than a defined cutoff, in order to remove noisy measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The distance of normalized frequencies of each codon in each pair of genes was calculated, and the relationship between this distance value and likelihood of functional linkage/coexpression was assessed by Pearson correlation coefficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Recently duplicated genes have high sequence identity and, thus, similar codon usages that may not necessarily reflect act of selection on gene sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In addition, these genes tend to cross-hybridize on expression arrays and appear as coexpressed genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Therefore, to avoid biased analysis, paralogous genes were removed from each genome prior to calculating Pearson correlation coefficients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>This was done by sequentially selecting two paralogous genes and randomly removing one of them, until the remaining genes contained no paralogs in the dataset (2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Non-random distribution of fc in each functional cluster or cluster of coregulated genes was assessed by mutual information of fc across the genes of that cluster, with high mutual information values indicating non-random distribution and low mutual information values indicating random distribution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Evaluating the effect of codon usage on the pattern of translation efficiency </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The effect of codon usage on protein expression profile was assessed by measuring the amount of expression of two lacZ variants under 16 different conditions in yeast cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>One of these two lacZ variants was the genomic lacZ from E. coli K12-MG1665, and the other variant was a synthetic gene with the same protein sequence but extensively different codon usage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Both of these variants were inserted in pBridge (Clontech), and cloned in AH109 yeast strain (Clontech), thus having the same upstream and downstream sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The expression of each variant of lacZ in each growth condition was measured by a β-galactosidase assay using ortho-nitrophenyl-β-galactoside (ONPG) as substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The rate of conversion of ONPG to ortho-nitrophenol was measured by absorbance at 405 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>This rate, normalized for cell density (estimated by OD600), was considered as the expression level of lacZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Each of the experiments was performed in hexaplicate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Evaluating the ability of tRNA composition in conferring new phenotypes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>A tRNA library was constructed with random combinations of 25 E. coli tRNA genes cloned into pBAD18 in E. coli host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>This library was exposed to different stress conditions, including 6.7 µg/ml kanamycin, 0.5 µg/ml tetracycline, 2.0 µg/ml chloramphenicol, 5.5% ethanol, pH 4.5 and 7.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The enrichment and/or depletion of particular constructs were assessed through cloning site amplification of the pool of plasmids and visualization on agarose gels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Competition assays were performed by mixing equal volumes of E. coli cells carrying tRNA-containing plasmids in a ΔlacZ background and lacZ+ E. coli cells carrying empty plasmids, inoculating the stress-delivering culture with this mixture, and counting the red and white colony forming units (CFUs) on MacConkey plates after incubating overnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Selection index R was defined as the ratio of logarithm of growth of tRNA-containing cells over logarithm of growth of cells carrying empty plasmids. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>See ‘Methods’ section in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link> for detailed description of mathematical and experimental procedures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Software packages developed and used in this work are available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://webpages.mcgill.ca/staff/Group2/rsalav/web/ICodPack.zip">http://webpages.mcgill.ca/staff/Group2/rsalav/web/ICodPack.zip</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>A universal correlation between codon usage and function </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>We examined the relationship between codon usage and function in 785 organisms (including 72 eukaryotes, 661 bacteria and 52 archaea), the sequences and functions of whose genes were retrieved from Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes—KEGG (27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Since paralogous duplicates usually have the same function as well as similar synonymous codon usages, their presence might result in over-estimating the similarity of codon usage among proteins of similar function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Therefore, duplicates were removed within each genome using nucleotide BLAST as described before (2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>In this work, we used a relatively large E-value cutoff of 0.001 to make sure that all duplicates were removed and the results are unbiased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>For each gene, the usages of synonymous codons were calculated and normalized over the usages of their corresponding amino acids, here referred to as fc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>We applied suitable filters to reduce random fluctuations and obtain a robust measure of synonymous codon usage (see ‘Methods’ section in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The distance of a pair of genes i and j regarding the usage of codon c was calculated as dij (c) = | fc,i – fc,j | (26). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>If genes with similar functions use similar frequencies of synonymous codons, we shall expect a negative correlation between dij (c) and the likelihood of sharing a biological function; i.e. the more dissimilar the synonymous codon usages of two genes, the less likely they participate in the same pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>We observed significantly negative linear correlations between d and likelihood of functional linkage in almost all the examined genomes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>), indicating a universal pattern in which genes of similar functions have similar usages of synonymous codons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Our set of genomes covered all taxonomic domains, although, in particular, negative correlations were highly significant in eukaryotes (Figure 1). Figure 1.A heat map illustrating the significance of the negative correlations between d and likelihood of functional linkage in 72 eukaryotes and 59 codons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Each row represents one organism in the same order as the top 72 rows of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Table S1</ext-link>, while each column represents one codon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Stop codons, AUG and UGG are omitted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The P-values of the correlations are shown by a color gradient on log scale (left bar), with yellow color standing for small P-values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Significant correlations (P ≤ 1 × 10−4) are highlighted by red frames, indicating that the corresponding codons are used similarly among the proteins that share the same function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The expected value of false discovery rate (FDR) is &lt;4 × 10−4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>White regions stand for cases in which the correlation coefficient could not be calculated due to lack of enough functional linkages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Refer to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link> for the correlation between codon usage and function in all the 785 organisms studied in this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that our previously observed pattern (26) in which functionally interacting proteins use similar codon usages is not restricted to a few organisms; rather, it is a universal characteristic of the genomes across all domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>We will investigate the cause of this pattern in the next section. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Genes with similar expression patterns have similar synonymous codon usages </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>In the classic view on the relationship between codon usage and protein expression, a constant set of optimal codons is assumed for an organism over different life stages and conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>This model implies that genes with a particular codon usage should have a translation efficiency that remains constant across different conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Assuming that this constant translation efficiency is selected based on the overall expression level of each gene (28), genes with similar codon usages should have similar ‘average’ expression levels, but not necessarily similar expression ‘patterns’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>An alternative, unexplored hypothesis can be that the set of optimal codons is not constant, and changes from one condition to another. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>In this case, the translation efficiencies of genes that have similar codon usages do not remain constant, but change in a synchronized manner in response to the changes of the set of optimal codons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Thus, it is reasonable to assume that such genes would have similar expression ‘patterns’. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Knowing that genes with similar functions have similar expression patterns [(29) and the references within], the observed similarity between codon usages of functionally linked proteins led us to reevaluate the two abovementioned hypotheses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>We tested these hypotheses on four divergent organisms with available genome-wide expression profiles, human, yeast, E. coli and C. elegans (30–33). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>In each organism, clusters of coexpressed genes (i.e. genes with similar expression patterns) were analyzed in the same way as we analyzed the clusters of functionally linked genes in the previous section. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Similarly, we also clustered the genes in each organism according to their average expression level, and performed the same analysis. Figure 2 shows that in all of the tested genomes, codon usage has the strongest correlation with expression pattern rather than average expression level, corroborating the ‘variable set of optimal codons’ hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Strikingly, this correlation is most obvious for the human genome, where most of the correlations are between −0.80 and −0.90 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>) and, with only one exception (correlation between CGU and coexpression), all of them are highly significant (P ≤ 1 × 10−4). Figure 2.The significance of correlation between codon usage and clusters of genes according to different properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Genes were clustered according to either function, expression profile (resulting in clusters of coexpressed genes) or average gene expression level (resulting in clusters of genes with similar average expression levels). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Functional clusters were obtained from KEGG pathway database (27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Coexpression clusters for S. cerevisiae, Homo sapiens and C. elegans were derived from (2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>For E. coli, expression profiles of the genes were obtained from (32) and were clustered using Iclust (37). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Average gene expression levels were obtained by averaging the expression profile of each gene, except for S. cerevisiae where a previously reported reference mRNA level dataset was used (38). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The correlation between d and the likelihood of occurrence in the same cluster was assessed for each property in each organism for all codons, excluding stop codons, AUG and UGG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Significantly negative correlations are indicated by light-red frames (P ≤ 1 × 10−4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Refer to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link> for the values associated with this figure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>We further analyzed the codon usage of each coexpression cluster in human, following the same methodology that has been used before for finding informative regulatory elements (2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>We calculated the mutual information of the usage of each codon for each expression profile, and assessed whether the observed mutual information was significantly higher than expected by chance (see ‘Methods’ section in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link> for details). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>A high mutual information value signifies a non-random usage of the corresponding codon among genes within the corresponding coexpression cluster. Figure 3 shows that, in many different coexpression clusters, synonymous codons are used non-randomly; in other words, specific frequencies of synonymous codons are preferred for each expression pattern, resulting in similar synonymous codon usages among the genes that are coregulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Moreover, this non-random distribution of synonymous codon usage is not merely a result of similar GC content as reported before (14). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>This is particularly obvious in coexpression clusters whose genes occur in genomic isochores with different GC contents but still show significantly similar synonymous codon usages (the lower half of Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>It should be noted that non-random usage of a codon can be due to either preference for using that codon or preference for not using it (both resulting in high mutual information values). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>An example is shown in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Figure S1</ext-link>, where some coexpression clusters are over-represented among genes with high frequencies of codon UUU, while some other clusters are over-represented among genes that have low frequencies of UUU. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Clustering the human genes based on their ‘average’ expression level instead of expression pattern, we performed the same analysis and found no significant mutual information values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>We also found no significant mutual information between expression pattern and the usage of any amino acid, indicating that the non-randomness of codon usage among coexpressed genes is independent of the amino acid context. Figure 3.Mutual information of synonymous codon usage in human coexpression clusters is significantly higher than expected from a random distribution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Each row represents a coexpression cluster, while each column, except for the first one from left, represents a codon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Stop codons, AUG and UGG are omitted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Significant mutual information (MI) values are shown by red frames (P ≤ 1 × 10−4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Therefore, a red frame around a square indicates that the genes within the corresponding coexpressoin cluster use similar frequencies of the corresponding codon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The expected value of FDR is 1 × 10−3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>MI of regional GC content in each coexpression cluster was assessed similarly (shown in the first column from left). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Regional GC content was calculated as the GC content of the 50 kb genomic region surrounding each gene, similar to (14). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Coexpression clusters are sorted according to the descending order of the MI of regional GC content; thus, the upper rows represent clusters whose genes have significantly similar regional GC contents, while the lower rows correspond to clusters whose genes occur in different GC contexts. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>As a complementary method, we also clustered human genes just based on their synonymous codon usage (using 59 codons), and examined whether different coexpression groups show non-random distribution among these clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>It is shown in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Figure S1</ext-link> that many coexpression groups show significantly non-random distribution; each coexpression group is specifically enriched within certain codon usage clusters, while significantly under-represented in other clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>A similar analysis on S. cerevisiae also reveals coexpressed genes with significantly similar synonymous codon usages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, these coexpression clusters do not always consist of the most abundant genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Instead, there exist many low-abundance coexpressed genes that show significant similarities regarding the usage of several synonymous codons (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Figure S2</ext-link>), although it is not as noticeable as in human. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Difference in codon usage directly affects regulation of protein expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>We examined whether modification of the codon usage of a gene can change the response of this gene to environmental conditions in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>To this end, we constructed a modified version of lacZ from E. coli K12-MG1655, in which the codon usage was changed considerably while keeping the original protein sequence (see ‘Methods’ section in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The original lacZ [GenBank:U00096, region 362455–365529] and the modified lacZ [GenBank:FJ839685] were cloned in yeast, and the expression pattern of LacZ was assessed in 16 different growth and stress conditions, using a quantitative β-galactosidase assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Although the CAI values of these two genes were different (0.649 for modified lacZ compared to 0.213 for original lacZ), their average expression levels were not significantly different (paired Student’s t-test score 0.86, P &lt; 0.25). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>However, as we expected, there were several conditions in which the protein expression was significantly different between the two variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Particularly, three conditions yielded significantly higher galactosidase activities of the modified lacZ compared to the original lacZ, while two conditions yielded significantly higher activities of the original lacZ (Figure 4). Figure 4.Expression pattern of lacZ gene differs as a result of codon usage modification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Two different lacZ sequences, i.e. the original gene from E. coli K12-MG1665 and a variant with modified codon usage, were expressed in yeast in different conditions, and galactosidase activity was measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The two yeast strains carrying the two lacZ variants did not show any significant differences in their growth pattern (estimated by OD600). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>However, the galactosidase activity was significantly different between the two strains in several conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Galactosidase activity was measured as the rate of increase in OD405 in a reaction containing cell extract and ONPG substrate, normalized for cell densitity (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Methods</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The unit of galactosidase activity in this figure is OD405 × s−1 × (OD600)−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Blue circles indicate higher expression of original lacZ, while red circles indicate higher expression of modified lacZ (P &lt; 0.05 with Bonferroni correction for 16 experiments). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Experiment conditions: (i) YPDA: 37°C; (ii) YPDA: 30°C; (iii) DTT shock: 30°C; (iv) 2% sucrose: 37°C; (v) DTT shock: 37°C; (vi) 2% ethanol: 37°C; (vii) 2% glucose: 37°C; (viii) 2% glucose: 30°C; (ix) hyper-osmotic shock: 37°C; (x) SD: 37°C; (xi) 2% ethanol: 30°C; (xii) steady 1 M sorbitol: 37°C; (xiii) 2% sucrose: 30°C; (xiv) SD: 30°C; (xv) hyper-osmotic shock: 30°C; (xvi) steady 1 M sorbitol: 30°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Each experiment was performed in hexaplicate; the standard deviations are depicted by error bars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Quantile and median normalization of expression values do not change the results (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>We propose that codon usage affects the regulation of protein expression by linking it to the regulation of tRNA composition in the cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>In other words, as in different conditions different proteins are required, tRNA composition of the cell may change accordingly in order to accommodate the changing demands for synthesis of new proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The response of genes to the new tRNA composition depends on their codon usages; hence, the translation efficiencies of genes with different codon usages change differently, causing the observed difference between the patterns of expression of the two lacZ variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>It has to be emphasized that this is a very likely, yet indirect conclusion from our experiment and we did not measure the tRNA content of yeast in the examined 16 conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>In the next section, we hypothesize that not only the tRNA content may change according to the expression demands of the cell, but also we can change the cell phenotype by engineering the tRNA content. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Changes in tRNA abundance confer adaptative capacity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The results of the previous analyses and experiments suggest indirectly that the tRNA composition of the cell may follow its expression demands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="?"><plain>But is tRNA composition also able to push the expression profile of the cell to a different state in order to cause a particular phenotype? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>We examined this by looking for phenotypic changes that might occur in the cell as a result of perturbation of its tRNA content. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Briefly, we constructed a plasmid library in pBAD18 backbone, each carrying a random selection of 25 tRNA genes from E. coli (see ‘Methods’ section in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>From each tRNA gene, a plasmid could have zero, one, or multiple copies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Each copy could be oriented randomly in forward or reverse direction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The rational for this approach was that those sequences cloned in the forward orientation result in an overabundance of the tRNA, while those cloned in reverse most likely decrease the tRNA concentration through double-strand formation with the tRNA transcribed in the cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>This library was transformed into E. coli, and the pool of transformed cells was grown under different environmental stresses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The initial frequency of constructs was visualized through cloning site amplification (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Figure S3</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>After one or two rounds of selection, the plasmid population was visualized to see whether certain constructs were enriched upon selection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>We found two selection conditions in which particular plasmids had highly significant adaptive consequences in a short time-scale (∼10 generations): sub-inhibitory concentrations of kanamycin (6.7 μg/ml) and tetracycline (0.5 μg/ml). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In the case of kanamycin-containing medium, the enriched plasmid (named pBAD-tKAN) contained one copy of glyT tRNA gene in forward direction and one copy of serW tRNA gene in reverse direction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, growth in the presence of tetracycline results in the enrichment of a plasmid containing ileX tRNA gene in forward direction, designated pBAD-tTET (in each case, 10 clones were randomly selected for sequence analysis; see ‘Methods’ section in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Repeating the experiment on the library resulted in selection of the same plasmids, indicating that the observed enrichment is selective and is not due to drift. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>We also confirmed that the selection of these particular tRNA isoacceptors was not a result of bias in the original library; all tRNA isoacceptors of Gly, Ser and Ile were represented in the library in both forward and reverse directions at different combinations (see ‘Methods’ section in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Data and Supplementary Figure S3</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>This shows that, for example, in the presence of tetracycline, ileX has a significant fitness advantage over ileT since only ileX was selected. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Using a competition assay, we observed that in kanamycin-containing medium, E. coli cells freshly transformed with pBAD-tKAN have a selection index of about 1.5 over wildtype E. coli (MG1655) carrying an empty pBAD18 plasmid (P &lt; 0.025; for definition of selection index, see ‘Methods’ section). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>pBAD-tKAN confers no growth advantage over empty pBAD18 in tetracycline-containing medium (negative control). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Similarly, pBAD-tTET-carrying cells with clean genomic background have a selection index of ∼2 in tetracycline-containing medium (P &lt; 0.001), and no growth advantage in kanamycin-containing medium, indicating that each plasmid specifically increases the fitness in the medium at which it is selected. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>We showed that there is a universal correlation between codon usage and gene function, and that this correlation is even more obvious if we consider, instead of function, expression pattern as the basis for clustering the genes within each genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The best hypothesis that can explain this observation as well as the results of our experiments is that the tRNA composition follows the expression demands of the cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>In other words, if in a particular condition a set of proteins with a particular function are needed and thus are expressed at high levels, tRNA composition changes accordingly to provide the required material. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Since this adaptation would best work if in each condition the expressed genes had similar codon usages, a universal function-specificity has emerged in the codon usage within each genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The new hypothesis postulates that genes with similar expression patterns, even though having different average expression levels, should have similar codon usages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>This is most obvious in organisms with complex developmental and physiological circuits such as human and C. elegans (34), in which there is a very strong correlation between codon usage and expression pattern but almost no correlation between codon usage and average expression level (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>In the case of simpler, fast-growing organisms such as yeast and E. coli, it is more difficult to discriminate between our new hypothesis and the conventional view, since there is a high correlation between average expression level and expression pattern: in these organisms, genes that have similar expression patterns usually show similar average expression levels as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>It is reasonable to think that in microorganisms with high growth rate, both the overall expression level of proteins and the dynamic pattern of expression may contribute to shaping the coding sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>This is supported by the observation that in many cases the correlation coefficient of codon usage with expression pattern is still significant after correcting for the confounding effect of average expression level and vice versa (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Figure S4</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>However, the effect of expression pattern seems to be more profound than average expression level. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>There have been previous reports suggesting that, via regulation of tRNA activity, genes with certain codon usages may be regulated in particular conditions (12,35). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>In this work, we showed that codon usage may have a wider effect on the response of a protein to environmental stimuli: in five out of 16 environmental conditions that we examined, a change in codon usage alters the extent and sometimes even the direction of LacZ response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Since both lacZ variants that we used had the same regulatory sequences in their upstream and downstream regions, the simplest explanation for the differences in their expression patterns is a difference in translation efficiency: while in some conditions the original lacZ showed greater translation efficiency, in some other conditions the modified lacZ exhibited greater translation efficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>This corroborates the ‘variable optimal codon set’ hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>This is not however the only explanation; for example, the translation efficiency of LacZ may be affected by, in addition to codon usage, the structure of its mRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>To examine the latter case, we studied the free folding energy for the critical regions of mRNAs of the two lacZ variants, and found no significant differences (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Figure S5</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Our results are congruent with a recent report that the folding energy affects overall expression level (24): indeed the average expression levels of the two lacZ variants were similar; rather, the expression patterns were different. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, there is no known mechanism based on which mRNA structure, without involvement of regulated trans-acting factors, could affect the expression pattern. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>We also showed that changes in tRNA composition may bring about significant adaptive consequences, such as higher resistance to particular antibiotics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>This means that changes in tRNA composition results in tangible phenotypic effects, thus suggesting the possibility that tRNA composition not only follows the expression demands of the cell, but may also change the expression profile of the cell on its own. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The antibiotics that we examined suppress cell growth by inhibition of translation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Thus, it might be argued that the plasmids pBAD-tKAN and pBAD-tTET confer resistance to these antibiotics by overexpression of tRNAs and, hence, generally enhancing translation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>However, this scenario seems unlikely due to the nature of the tRNAs that these plasmids carry: both glyT and ileX encode tRNAs that recognize rare codons in E. coli (36) (GGA/G and AUA, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>This is while the overall rate of translation would be enhanced much more efficiently if tRNAs that could recognize abundant codons were overexpressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>In fact, overexpression of glyT and ileX has no direct effect on translation efficiency of many highly demanded genes in E. coli, as these genes lack the cognate codons of these tRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, selection of the reverse complement of serW cannot be explained by enhancement of translation: the reverse complement of serW is assumed to inhibit Seryl-tRNA 5 through direct binding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Specificity of pBAD-tKAN and pBAD-tTET in conferring resistance towards only kanamycin and tetracycline, respectively, and not vice versa, adds to the above reasons to conclude that the mechanism of action of these constructs is not through a general enhancement of translation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>It is interesting to see that the combination of glyT in forward direction (glyTf) and serW in reverse direction (serWr), and not glyTf or serWr alone, was selected in the presence of kanamycin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>This indicates that the combination of these two is much stronger in conferring kanamycin resistance than any of them alone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Assuming that such cooperative action of tRNAs can have beneficial effects on cell fitness in other situations as well, a regulatory network that manages and synchronizes the activity of different tRNAs can be readily hypothesized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>This also suggests that usages of different codons may have coevolved. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Although in this experiment we tested the effect of tRNA concentration on phenotype, cells may potentially change the activity profiles of tRNAs in ways other than changing the concentration as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>For example, enzymatic modification of tRNA has been shown to change the codon preference (12). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>This mechanism especially seems possible since even for amino acids that have only two codons there is an expression pattern-specific codon usage (Figures 2 and 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>In most organisms, there is only one kind of tRNA for each of the amino acids with two U/C-ending codons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>It is thus not possible to change which codon is preferred by varying the concentration of this tRNA, as this tRNA recognizes both of the codons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>However, enzymatic modification of tRNA can result in a change in its preference towards its two cognate codons (12), which can describe expression pattern-specificity of codon usage for two-codon amino acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>This indicates that variation of tRNA composition may extend beyond concentration and may include variation of tRNA activity by means such as enzymatic modification as well. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The above experiments suggest a novel approach for modulating functions with applications in biology and biotechnology: we showed that perturbations to a single tRNA gene may change the survival of the cell in certain conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>It can also be anticipated that certain metabolic pathways will be enhanced by overexpression of tRNAs that recognize the specific codons of those pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Also, pathway engineering may benefit from more careful design of coding sequences regarding their codon usage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Last but not least, the above observations lead to a novel method for prediction of gene expression profiles and gene functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>We employed a naïve Bayesian network to construct a classifier that is able to predict expression profile or the function of a gene solely based on its codon usage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Using this classifier, we were able to achieve a high sensitivity and specificity in predicting many human coexpression clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, applying the same classifier on functional groups instead of coexpression clusters showed that some functions can be reliably predicted based on synonymous codon usage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Figure S6</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>We anticipate that this method can considerably enhance homology-independent annotation of genes, especially for genomes whose genes are not conserved in well-studied model organisms (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Figure S6</ext-link> for a few examples in Trypanosoma brucei, the causative agent of human African trypanosomiasis). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>ACCESSION NUMBER </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>FJ839685. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp792/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NAR Online. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>FUNDING </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR) grant #94445 and Leaders Opportunity Fund (LOF) grant #12573 to R.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Research at the Institute of Parasitology is supported by the Centre for Host-Parasite Interactions and Le Fonds quebecois de la recherche sur la nature et les technologies (FQRNT), Quebec. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Lloyd Carr-Harris Fellowship to H.S.N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Funding for open access charge: Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR) (grant #94445). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Conflict of interest statement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>None declared. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag>
<SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>[Supplementary Data] </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="gkp792_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="gkp792_1.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="gkp792_2.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="gkp792_3.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="gkp792_4.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="gkp792_5.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="gkp792_6.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="gkp792_7.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="gkp792_8.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword" xlink:href="gkp792_nar-01747-s-2009-File014.doc"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword" xlink:href="gkp792_nar-01747-s-2009-File015.doc"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></SecTag>
</body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>1BeerMATavazoieSPredicting gene expression from sequenceCell200411718519815084257 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>2ElementoOSlonimNTavazoieSA universal framework for regulatory element discovery across all genomes and data typesMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Cell20072833735017964271 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>3dos SantosGSimmondsAJKrauseHMA stem-loop structure in the wingless transcript defines a consensus motif for apical RNA transportDevelopment200813513314318045835 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>4HaileSPapadopoulouBDevelopmental regulation of gene expression in trypanosomatid parasitic protozoaCurr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Opin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Microbiol.20071056957718177626 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>5MerriamLCChessAcis-Regulatory elements within the odorant receptor coding regionCell200713184484618045531 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>6LinXParselsLAVoellerDMAllegraCJMaleyGFMaleyFChuECharacterization of a cis-acting regulatory element in the protein coding region of thymidylate synthase mRNANucleic Acids Res.2000281381138910684933 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>7WenzPSchwankSHojaUSchullerHJA downstream regulatory element located within the coding sequence mediates autoregulated expression of the yeast fatty acid synthase gene FAS2 by the FAS1 gene productNucleic Acids Res.2001294625463211713312 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>8SorensenMAElfJBouakazETensonTSanyalSBjorkGREhrenbergMOver expression of a tRNA(Leu) isoacceptor changes charging pattern of leucine tRNAs and reveals new codon readingJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Mol Biol.2005354162416236318 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>9DittmarKASorensenMAElfJEhrenbergMPanTSelective charging of tRNA isoacceptors induced by amino-acid starvationEMBO Rep.2005615115715678157 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>10DittmarKAGoodenbourJMPanTTissue-specific differences in human transfer RNA expressionPLoS Genet.20062e22117194224 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>11ElfJNilssonDTensonTEhrenbergMSelective charging of tRNA isoacceptors explains patterns of codon usageScience20033001718172212805541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>12BegleyUDyavaiahMPatilARooneyJPDiRenzoDYoungCMConklinDSZitomerRSBegleyTJTrm9-catalyzed tRNA modifications link translation to the DNA damage responseMol. cell20072886087018082610 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>13PlotkinJBRobinsHLevineAJTissue-specific codon usage and the expression of human genesProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>USA2004101125881259115314228 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>14SemonMLobryJRDuretLNo evidence for tissue-specific adaptation of synonymous codon usage in humansMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Evol.20062352352916280544 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>15ChamaryJVParmleyJLHurstLDHearing silence: non-neutral evolution at synonymous sites in mammalsNature Rev.2006798108 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>16LavnerYKotlarDCodon bias as a factor in regulating expression via translation rate in the human genomeGene200534512713815716084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>17ComeronJMSelective and mutational patterns associated with gene expression in humans: influences on synonymous composition and intron presenceGenetics20041671293130415280243 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>18KotlarDLavnerYThe action of selection on codon bias in the human genome is related to frequency, complexity, and chronology of amino acidsBMC Genomics200676716584540 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>19ChamaryJVHurstLDEvidence for selection on synonymous mutations affecting stability of mRNA secondary structure in mammalsGenome Biol.20056R7516168082 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>20DuanJWainwrightMSComeronJMSaitouNSandersARGelernterJGejmanPVSynonymous mutations in the human dopamine receptor D2 (DRD2) affect mRNA stability and synthesis of the receptorHuman Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Genet.20031220521612554675 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>21CaponFAllenMHAmeenMBurdenADTillmanDBarkerJNTrembathRCA synonymous SNP of the corneodesmosin gene leads to increased mRNA stability and demonstrates association with psoriasis across diverse ethnic groupsHuman Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Genet.2004132361236815333584 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>22CartegniLChewSLKrainerARListening to silence and understanding nonsense: exonic mutations that affect splicingNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Rev.20023285298 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>23SharpPMBailesEGrocockRJPedenJFSockettREVariation in the strength of selected codon usage bias among bacteriaNucleic Acids Res.2005331141115315728743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>24KudlaGMurrayAWTollerveyDPlotkinJBCoding-sequence determinants of gene expression in Escherichia coliScience200932425525819359587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>25GarelJPFunctional adaptation of tRNA populationJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Theor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Biol.1974432112254591738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>26NajafabadiHSSalavatiRSequence-based prediction of protein-protein interactions by means of codon usageGenome Biol.20089R8718501006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>27KanehisaMGotoSKawashimaSOkunoYHattoriMThe KEGG resource for deciphering the genomeNucleic Acids Res.200432D277D28014681412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>28SharpPMLiWHThe codon Adaptation Index–a measure of directional synonymous codon usage bias, and its potential applicationsNucleic Acids Res.198715128112953547335 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>29van NoortVSnelBHuynenMAPredicting gene function by conserved co-expressionTrends Genet.20031923824212711213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>30SuAIWiltshireTBatalovSLappHChingKABlockDZhangJSodenRHayakawaMKreimanGA gene atlas of the mouse and human protein-encoding transcriptomesProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>USA20041016062606715075390 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>31GaschAPSpellmanPTKaoCMCarmel-HarelOEisenMBStorzGBotsteinDBrownPOGenomic expression programs in the response of yeast cells to environmental changesMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Cell2000114241425711102521 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>32FaithJJHayeteBThadenJTMognoIWierzbowskiJCottarelGKasifSCollinsJJGardnerTSLarge-scale mapping and validation of Escherichia coli transcriptional regulation from a compendium of expression profilesPLoS Biol.20075e817214507 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>33KimSKLundJKiralyMDukeKJiangMStuartJMEizingerAWylieBNDavidsonGSA gene expression map for Caenorhabditis elegansScience20012932087209211557892 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>34DunnRKKingstonREGene regulation in the postgenomic era: technology takes the wheelMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Cell20072870871418082595 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>35KuharIvan PuttenJPZgur-BertokDGaastraWJordiBJCodon-usage based regulation of colicin K synthesis by the stress alarmone ppGppMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Microbiol.20014120721611454213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>36BacaAMHolWGOvercoming codon bias: a method for high-level overexpression of Plasmodium and other AT-rich parasite genes in Escherichia coliInt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Parasitol.20003011311810704592 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>37SlonimNAtwalGSTkacikGBialekWInformation-based clusteringProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>USA2005102182971830216352721 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>38JansenRBussemakerHJGersteinMRevisiting the codon adaptation index from a whole-genome perspective: analyzing the relationship between gene expression and codon occurrence in yeast using a variety of modelsNucleic Acids Res.2003312242225112682375 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
