
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Endocrinol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JOE</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Endocrinology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0795</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1479-6805</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioScientifica</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Bristol</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2710976</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JOE090066</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1677/JOE-09-0066</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Regular papers</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Localisation of GPR30, a novel G protein-coupled oestrogen receptor, suggests multiple functions in rodent brain and peripheral tissues </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hazell</surname><given-names>Georgina G J</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Song T</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roper</surname><given-names>James A</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prossnitz</surname><given-names>Eric R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>O'Carroll</surname><given-names>Anne-Marie</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lolait</surname><given-names>Stephen J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>LINE</institution><institution>University of Bristol</institution><addr-line>Dorothy Hodgkin Building, Whitson Street, Bristol BS1 3NY</addr-line><country>UK</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>University of New Mexico</institution><addr-line>Albuquerque, New Mexico, 87131</addr-line><country>USA</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">(Correspondence should be addressed to S J Lolait; Email: <email>s.j.lolait@bristol.ac.uk</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epreprint"><day>5</day><month>5</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>202</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><history><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>1</day><month>5</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>5</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2009 Society for Endocrinology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://www.endocrinology.org/journals/reuselicence/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.endocrinology.org/journals/reuselicence/">Society for Endocrinology's Re-use Licence</ext-link> which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Recently, the G protein-coupled receptor GPR30 has been identified as a novel oestrogen receptor (ER). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The distribution of the receptor has been thus far mapped only in the rat central nervous system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>This study was undertaken to map the distribution of GPR30 in the mouse brain and rodent peripheral tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemistry using an antibody against GPR30 revealed high levels of GPR30 immunoreactivity (ir) in the forebrain (e.g. cortex, hypothalamus and hippocampus), specific nuclei of the midbrain (e.g. the pontine nuclei and locus coeruleus) and the trigeminal nuclei and cerebellum Purkinje layer of the hindbrain in the adult mouse brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>In the rat and mouse periphery, GPR30-ir was detected in the anterior, intermediate and neural lobe of the pituitary, adrenal medulla, renal pelvis and ovary. In situ hybridisation histochemistry using GPR30 riboprobes, revealed intense hybridisation signal for GPR30 in the paraventricular nucleus and supraoptic nucleus (SON) of the hypothalamus, anterior and intermediate lobe of the pituitary, adrenal medulla, renal pelvis and ovary of both rat and mouse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Double immunofluorescence revealed GPR30 was present in both oxytocin and vasopressin neurones of the paraventricular nucleus and SON of the rat and mouse brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The distribution of GPR30 is distinct from the other traditional ERs and offers an additional way in which oestrogen may mediate its effects in numerous brain regions and endocrine systems in the rodent. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Wellcome Trust</funding-source></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Oestrogen (17-β-oestradiol or E2) affects a variety of physiological processes including fertility, immune function, cardiovascular homeostasis, mood, locomotion, neuroprotection and cognition (Watson &amp; Gametchu 2001, McEwan 2002, de Ronde et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>E2 effects are typically mediated through two structurally related oestrogen receptors, the α and β (ERα and ERβ) subtypes that function as ligand-activated transcription factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>On activation ERs can either bind directly to their target DNA sequences in the nucleus or interact with other nuclear proteins to alter gene activation, and this genomic action occurs slowly (hours–days). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>However, it is well documented that E2 can also provoke many fast ‘non-genomic’ effects e.g. activation of large conductance calcium-activated potassium channels (Kca1·1; Valverde et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>1999), and these could be mediated by extranuclear ERs or by non-classical membrane bound receptors (Levin 2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>GPR30, a G protein-coupled receptor (GPCR) specifically binds E2 with high (nanomolar) affinity and evokes rapid effects (Revankar et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>2005, Thomas et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>2005), including stimulating Ca2+ mobilisation from intracellular stores directly or via epidermal growth factor receptor transactivation, c-fos expression, adenylyl cyclase and cAMP mediated signalling and ERK-1/2 in a variety of cell types (Prossnitz et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Intriguingly, only a small fraction of total cellular GPR30 appears to be expressed on the cell surface with most of the receptor located intracellularly in the endoplasmic reticulum (Revankar et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>GPR30 acts as an atypical GPCR, in that, it is activated intracellularly by E2 which readily diffuses across cell membranes (Revankar et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>2007). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Recent studies in GPR30 knockout mice have indicated that GPR30 mediates E2 stimulated insulin release in females, reduces blood pressure and is involved in bone development, but is not essential for reproduction (Mårtensson et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>2009, Otto et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In addition, GPR30 is expressed in oxytocin (OXT) neurones of the rat hypothalamic paraventricular nucleus (PVH) and supraoptic nucleus (SON), implicating a role for GPR30 in the fast, non-genomic actions of E2 on OXT release (Wang et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>1995, Revankar et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Whether or not GPR30 is expressed in vasopressin (AVP) neurones remains unclear as one study found co-expression (Brailoiu et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>2007) while another did not (Sakamoto et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>2007), both these studies used the same antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>A role for E2 in regulating OXT and/or AVP release is supported by studies showing that administration of E2 to postmenopausal women increases circulating levels of OXT and AVP (Bossmar et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>1995), and E2 rapidly stimulates intrahypothalamic and peripheral OXT and possibly AVP release (Wang et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>1995, Burbach et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>2001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>As GPR30 provides an alternative model for E2 signalling, and possibly E2 stimulated release of OXT and AVP, the present study was undertaken to clarify the distribution of GPR30 in the rodent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>As GPR30 provides an alternative model for E2 signalling, and possibly E2 stimulated release of OXT and AVP, the present study was undertaken to clarify the distribution of GPR30 in the rodent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>We aimed to 1) map the distribution of GPR30 in the mouse brain to determine whether there are differences to that shown in the rat 2) identify and highlight regions that express high levels of GPR30 mRNA and protein in the rodent periphery, to provide additional insights into the role of GPR30. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Adult male and female Sprague–Dawley rats, weighing 200–250 g (Harlan, Bicester, UK), and adult (10–12 week) male and female wild-type mice (25–30 g) from our AVP V1b receptor knockout colony (Wersinger et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>2002) were used in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>For each separate experiment (immunohistochemistry, double immunofluorescence or in situ hybridisation histochemistry) three mice or rats of each gender were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Animals were housed under a constant temperature (21±2 °C), light (lights on from 0700 to 1900 h) and humidity (45–50%) regimens with access to food and water ad libitum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Animal care, maintenance and surgery were performed in accordance with the Animal Scientific Procedures Act (1986) United Kingdom and the appropriate University of Bristol ethical review process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemistry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Animals were anaesthetised with sodium pentobarbital (100 mg/kg i.p.) and intracardially perfused with 0·1 M PBS followed by 4% paraformaldehyde in 0·1 M PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Tissues were post fixed overnight in 20% sucrose and 4% paraformaldehyde in 0·1 M PBS solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Following overnight fixation, the tissues were rapidly frozen over liquid nitrogen and stored at −80 °C until processed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>In single staining, rat and mouse peripheral cryostat sections (12 μm) were cut and thaw-mounted onto Superfrost Plus slides, or free-floating (40 μm) mouse brain sections were cut and processed for GPR30-immunoreactivity (GPR30-ir). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Tissues were first washed in 0·1 M PBS, endogenous peroxidase activity was quenched with 3% H2O2 for 10 min, washed (3×10 min with 0·1 M PBS), and then blocked with 10% normal goat serum (NGS) and 0·3% Triton-X 100 (T-X) in 0·1 M PBS for 15 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>After washing (3×10 min with 0·1 M PBS), sections were incubated overnight in an affinity-purified rabbit antiserum against GPR30 diluted (1: 1000–1:2000) in 1% NGS/0·3% T-X in 0·1 M PBS at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The specificity of GPR30 antiserum has previously been confirmed (Revankar et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>2005), and normal rabbit IgG serum (Vector Laboratories, Peterborough, UK) was used as a control at the same concentration as the antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>After washing (3×10 min with 0·1 M PBS), sections were incubated at room temperature in secondary biotinylated affinity purified goat anti-rabbit (1:500, Vector Laboratories), in 1% NGS/0·3% T-X in 0·1 M PBS for 1 h, washed (3×10 min with 0·1 M PBS) and incubated in horseradish peroxidase streptavadin (1:500, Vector Laboratories) in 1% NGS/0·3% T-X in 0·1 M PBS for a further hour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The GPR30 signal was visualised with 3,3′-diaminobenzidine in peroxidase buffer (10 min at 1:10, Roche Diagnostics). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Mouse brain sections were mounted onto Superfrost Plus slides with 0·5% gelatin solution, and along with the pre-mounted peripheral sections were cover-slipped and viewed under a light microscope (Leica DM IRB, Milton Keynes, UK). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>For double immunofluorescence staining, hypothalamic free-floating sections (40 μm) were rinsed in 0·1 M PBS, and then blocked with 10% NGS/0·3% T-X in 0·1 M PBS for 15 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>After washing (3×10 min in 0·1 M PBS), sections were incubated overnight at 4 °C with rabbit antiserum against GPR30 (diluted 1:1000) and guinea pig antiserum against OXT or AVP (diluted 1:2000 (OXT), 1:500 (AVP); Peninsula Laboratories, San Carlos, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Sections were washed and incubated for an hour at room temperature in biotinylated goat anti-rabbit antibody (as above), and Alexa Fluor 488 goat anti-guinea pig antibody (diluted 1:500, Invitrogen) to detect OXT or AVP protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Sections were further washed and incubated for an hour in streptavadin-conjugated Alexa Fluro 594 (diluted 1:500, Vector Laboratories). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Sections were mounted onto Superfrost Plus slides, cover slipped with an antifade mounting medium (Vectashield Hard Set, Vector Laboratories) and viewed under a confocal laser scanning microscope (Leica TCS-NT microscope housing a Leica DM IRBE inverted epifluorescence with a two-line krypton/argon laser) and processed with Adobe Photoshop CS3 extended computer software. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>In situ hybridisation histochemistry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Coronal cryostat sections (12 μm) were cut, thaw mounted onto polylysine-coated slides and stored at −80 °C until use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The mouse GPR30 riboprobe was generated by PCR using ∼20 ng mouse GPR30 cDNA (cloned from a mouse AtT20 pituitary tumour cDNA library; SJL unpublished data) as template. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Primers (upstream: 5′-GAGAGGATCCGGTCAGGGGCGCAGGC-3′; downstream 5′-AAACAAGCTTTGTGAGAGGAGCATC-3′) corresponding to bp 1739–2344 of a mouse GPR30 mRNA (Genbank Accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="genbank:NM_029771">NM_029771</ext-link>) were used to generate a 606 bp product. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The primers contain the recognition sequences for the restriction endonucleases HindIII and BamH1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The rat GPR30 riboprobe was generated using ∼150 ng rat genomic DNA (Promega no. G313A) as a template. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>PCR primers (upstream: 5′-GAGAGGATCCTCCTAGAGGAAAACGGA-3′; downstream 5′-AAACAAGCTTTGTGAGAGGAGCATC-3′) corresponding to bp 15718722–15718072 of a rat GPR30 gene (Genbank Accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="genbank:NM_133573">NM_133573</ext-link>) were used to generate a 651 bp product. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The primers contain the recognition sequences for the restriction endonucleases HindIII and BamH1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Primer restriction endonuclease sites allowed subcloning into the RNA generating vector pGEM4Z (Promega), and sense and antisense probes were generated using T7 and SP6 polymerases (mouse and rat antisense: linearised with BamHI and generated with T7 polymerase; sense: linearised with HindIII and generated with SP6 polymerase) with 35S-UTP and the MAXIscript in vitro transcription kit (Ambion, Austin, TX, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The integrity of the probes was verified by DNA sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>All in situ hybridisation experiments were performed as described in detail (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://intramural.nimh.nih.gov/lcmr/snge/Protocols/ISHH/ISHH.html">http://intramural.nimh.nih.gov/lcmr/snge/Protocols/ISHH/ISHH.html</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Hybridised sections were exposed to film (Amersham Hyperfilm MP) for 8 weeks, or emulsion dipped (Ilford K5) for 24 weeks and then counterstained with toluidine blue. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Distribution of GPR30-ir in the adult mouse brain </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The data presented here are semi-quantitative assessments based on subjective judgement of three independent observers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>No apparent gender differences were observed in the distribution of GPR30 in the adult mouse brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>In most brain regions, GPR30-ir was expressed in cell bodies and fibres; in some regions mostly cell bodies (e.g. paraventricular nucleus of the thalamus, hypothalamic ventromedial nucleus (VMH)) or fibres (e.g. lateral mammillary nucleus) expressed GPR30-ir (see Table 1 and Figs 1–3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>In the forebrain GPR30-ir expression was high in the cingulate, motor (Fig. 1A) and somatosensory regions of the isocortex, piriform cortex (Fig. 1B), entorhinal cortex, the dentate gyrus hilus (Fig. 2A), and subiculum of the dorsal hippocampus formation and the zona incerta (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Moderate to high expression was identified in the mitral layer of the olfactory bulb, dorsal endopiriform nucleus, CA1–3 of the ventral hippocampal formation, the medial habenular nucleus of the thalamus, anteroventral periventricular nucleus and the medial preoptic nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The retrosplenial granular region of the isocortex, the lateral nucleus of the septal complex, the nucleus of the horizontal limb of the diagonal band of broca, the olfactory tubercle, the anterior amygdaloid area of the amygdala and the paraventricular nucleus of the thalamus (Fig. 1D), all demonstrated moderate expression of GPR30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Low to moderate staining was noted in the granular insular, perirhinal and retrosplenial agranular regions of the isocortex, medial nucleus of the septal complex and the CA2 of the dorsal hippocampal formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Expression of GPR30 was low in many areas including the glomerular layer of the olfactory bulb, islands of Calleja, claustrum, caudate putamen of the striatum, shell of the accumbens nucleus, subfornical organ, CA1 and CA3 of the dorsal hippocampal formation, bed nucleus of the stria terminalis, and amygdalohippocampal nucleus and medial nucleus of the amygdala. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The data are summarised in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>In the hypothalamus intense GPR30 expression was found in the arcuate nucleus, PVH (Fig. 1E), periventricular hypothalamic nucleus, SON (Fig. 1C), dorsomedial, central and ventrolateral divisions of the VMH with moderate to high expression in the suprachiasmatic nucleus and lateral mammillary nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>GPR30-ir was low in the dorsal–medial nucleus, medial mammillary nucleus and ventral tuberomammillary nucleus and GPR30 expression is sparse in the lateral hypothalamic area, posterior hypothalamic nucleus, subthalamic nucleus and supramammillary nucleus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>In the midbrain and pons, distinct GPR30-ir could be seen in the pontine nuclei, anterior tegmental nucleus, medioventral periolivary nucleus and superior paraolivary nucleus of the superior olive and the locus coeruleus (Fig. 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>A moderate to high expression was noted in the interpeduncular nucleus, compact region of the substantia nigra (Fig. 2E) and the reticulotegmental nucleus of pons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The dorsal medial periaqueductal grey, inferior colliculus, caudal linear raphe nuclei, oral pontine reticular nucleus, the rostal, dorsal, caudal periolivary regions and the lateral superior olivary nucleus of the superior olive, nucleus of trapezoid body, lateral nucleus of the parabrachial region and the medial vestibular nucleus all express moderate levels of GPR30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, low levels were found in areas such as the lateral and reticular regions of the substantia nigra, superior colliculus, dorsal raphe and the lateral vestibular nucleus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>In the hindbrain, high expression of GPR30 was found in the oral and dorsomedial region of the spinal trigeminal nucleus (Fig. 3C and D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>GPR30-ir was also high in the Purkinje cells of the cerebellum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Moderate expression was seen in the facial motor nucleus, principal nucleus of the inferior olive and the dorsal motor nucleus of vagus with low to moderate expression in the middle cerebellar peduncle, nucleus ambiguous and nucleus of the solitary tract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Low to moderate staining was also found in the internal granule layer and molecular layers of the cerebellum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Low expression was detected in other regions including the posterodorsal tegmental nucleus, supratrigeminal, parapyramidal, intermediate reticular, gigantocellular, lateral reticular and the rosteroventrolateral reticular nuclei and the area postrema. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>GPR30 co-localises with OXT and AVP neurones </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The results for this part of the study were obtained from three male and three female rat and mouse brains, double labelled with antibodies to GPR30 and either OXT or AVP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Pictures of GPR30 immunofluorescence were acquired and merged with the corresponding immunofluorescence pictures of OXT or AVP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Neurones containing both GPR30-ir (red) and OXT-ir or AVP-ir (green) appeared yellow (merged) and were counted, and a co-expression percentage was calculated against the total number of OXT-ir or AVP-ir neurones. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>In the rat PVH, GPR30-ir is prominent in the magnocellular PVH with low-level labelling in the parvocellular PVH (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Dual labelling of hypothalamic sections revealed that GPR30-ir was present in both OXT and AVP magnocellular neurones and 40–60% of OXT neurones and 50–70% co-expressed GPR30-ir in the PVH and SON (see Table 2 and Figs 4 and 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>In the PVH and SON of the mouse both OXT and AVP neurones were positive for GPR30-ir, with 60–80% of OXT and AVP neurones expressing the receptor (Figs 4 and 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Co-localisation of GPR30-ir with OXT and AVP was also observed in fibres in the internal zone of the median eminence of both species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Peripheral distribution of GPR30 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>In the anterior lobe of the pituitary gland, ∼50% of cells were intensely stained for GPR30-ir. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The majority of cells in the pituitary intermediate lobe stained positively and there was prominent staining of fibres in the neural lobe (Fig. 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The adrenal medulla displayed strong GPR30-ir; occasional GPR30-ir cells were also observed in the zona glomerulosa of the cortex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>In the kidney, GPR30-ir was present in the smooth-muscle cells of the pelvic region and to a lesser extent the medulla, with only a few positive cells in the cortex (Fig. 6B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>In the ovary, dense staining was found within the granulosa cells with moderate to low staining in the theca cells (Fig. 6C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Staining was absent in corpora lutea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>There were no species or gender differences observed in the peripheral distribution of GPR30 protein expression in the three male and three female rats and mice analysed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Distribution of GPR30 mRNA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>We determined the expression of GPR30 mRNA in tissues that displayed abundant GPR30-ir in tissues from three male and three female rats and mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>In the rat central nervous system, a hybridisation signal for GPR30 was detected in the PVH and SON particularly in the magnocellular region of the PVH (Fig. 7A and C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>In the pituitary gland, the intermediate lobe was intensely labelled (Fig. 7D–F) and scattered cells exhibited a moderate signal in the anterior lobe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The neural lobe was unlabelled. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>In the adrenal glands, high levels of GPR30 mRNA were present in the adrenal medulla and cells within the zona glomerulosa of the adrenal cortex (Fig. 8A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In the kidney, intense labelling was present in the smooth muscle of the renal pelvis, and to a lesser extent in the medulla, with some sparse labelling in the cortex (Fig. 8C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>A few developing follicles of the rat ovary exhibited a hybridisation signal (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>A similar distribution of GPR30 transcripts was observed in mouse tissues- the SON, the adrenal medulla and pituitary intermediate lobe expressed the highest amount of GPR30 mRNA compared with kidney, ovary and PVH based on signal intensities observed for the same film exposures. Figure 8E shows GPR30 mRNA expression in developing follicles of the mouse ovary, with silver grains accumulated mainly in the granulosa and theca cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>No signal was detected in the corpora lutea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Rat and mouse sections hybridised with sense GPR30 riboprobes as controls showed only background level of labelling (Figs 7B and 8D and E). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>GPR30 was originally cloned by us as an orphan GPCR over 10 years ago (Owman et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>1996) and subsequently identified as an ER in a number of laboratories (Filardo et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>2000, 2002, Revankar et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>2005, Thomas et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Unlike many GPCRs, GPR30 appears to be predominantly expressed and functions intracellularly at least in vitro (Revankar et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that GPR30 is also found on the plasma membrane where it appears to be functionally relevant (Filardo et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Further studies on GPR30 internalisation and trafficking are required to address this issue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The suggestion that a GPCR is primarily localised intracellulary is not without precedent- e.g. the proportion of human GnRH receptors at the cell surface is extremely low (&lt;1%; Finch et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>2008) and depends upon the cellular context (the proportion of human GnRH receptors at the cell surface is five times greater in a gonadotroph cell line (LβT2) than MCF7 breast cancer cells (Finch et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>2008)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Homologues of the human, rat and mouse GPR30 are present in many species including rhesus monkey, chimpanzee, dog, chicken and zebrafish (see NCBI or Ensembl databases at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link> or <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ensembl.org">www.ensembl.org</ext-link> respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The GPR30 gene is widely distributed in human and rat tissues as shown by northern blot and immunohistochemical analyses (Owman et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>1996, Bonini et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>1997, Carmeci et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>1997, Feng &amp; Gregor 1997, Kvingedal &amp; Smeland 1997, Brailoiu et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>2007) and see EST profile Hs.20961 in NCBI Entrez Gene database). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>We have extended these observations in the present study using immunohistochemistry and in situ hybridisation histochemistry to obtain the cellular context of GPR30 expression in mouse brain and peripheral tissues. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Distribution of GPR30-ir in the adult mouse brain </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The present study provides the first full comprehensive characterisation of GPR30 distribution in the mouse central nervous system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Previously, the distribution of GPR30 has been illustrated in the rat brain using the same GPR30 antiserum as described here (Brailoiu et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>In agreement with our findings in mice, there are no apparent gender differences in GPR30 expression in the rat and this appears common to all E2 receptors (Laflamme et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>1998). Brailoiu et al. (2007) found predominant GPR30 expression in the hypothalamic PVH and SON, hippocampal formation, substantia nigra in the rat brain and this correlates well with our observations in the mouse brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>However, GPR30 is also highly expressed in the nucleus ambiguous where only low to moderate expression is found in the equivalent area in the mouse brain, suggesting some species differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>A comparison of GPR30 mRNA versus protein localisation in both rat and mouse brains may reveal whether receptor transcription and translation coincide or whether there are mismatches. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Comparison of ER distribution in the adult mouse brain </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>There appears to be only a few brain regions that express high levels of GPR30 and high amounts of either ERα or ERβ and even fewer regions that express all three receptors (see Table 3) to a high degree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>For example, GPR30 is most abundant in the hypothalamus of the mouse, particularly the arcuate nucleus, PVH, periventricular nucleus, SON and the dorsomedial, central and ventrolateral regions of the VMH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Of these nuclei, ERα is highly expressed in the arcuate nucleus and in the ventrolateral portion of the VMH, and in rats priming the VMH with E2 over days promotes lordosis, seemingly through ERα (Pfaff &amp; Sakuma 1978). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>In the rat and mouse, hypothalamus ERβ is the predominant ER isoform found in the PVH (Mitra et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>2003, Merchenthaler et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, E2 has been shown to activate the (MAPK) ERK 1/2 pathway in the PVH and SON of the mouse (Ábrahám et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>In the PVH, this is potentially mediated via either ERβ and/or GPR30, and presumably GPR30 in the SON. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>In the forebrain, GPR30 is also highly expressed in the cingulate, motor and somatosensory regions of the isocortex, piriform cortex, the hippocampal dentate gyrus hilus, subiculum and entorhinal cortex, and the zona incerta where ERα and ERβ expression is either low or absent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, E2 has been shown to induce c-fos protein expression in some brain regions (e.g. cingulate cortex) of double ERαβ knockout mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>As GPR30 is abundant in this region, GPR30 or another E2-binding protein may mediate the effects of E2 (Dominguez-Salazar et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, ERα and β are both highly expressed in the bed nucleus of the stria terminalis and the medial nucleus of the amygdala, where only minimal amounts of GPR30 can be detected. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>In the midbrain and pons, high expression of GPR30 is found in the pontine nuclei, anterior tegmental nucleus, the medioventral periolivary nucleus and superior paraolivary nucleus of the superior olive, and the locus coeruleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Of these, only the locus coeruleus contains high levels of the ERs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Interestingly in the mouse, noradrenaline neurones of the locus coeruleus have been shown to be responsive to E2 stimulation with an upregulation in tyrosine hydroxylase transcription in females, and attenuation of transcription in males (Thanky et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>This gender difference could be indicative of the varying roles of all the three ERs that are highly expressed in this brain region. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>GPR30 co-localises with OXT and AVP neurones </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The present study also aimed to clarify the inconsistencies in the literature regarding the distribution of GPR30 in hypothalamic magnocellular neurones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Our findings confirm that in the rat and mouse hypothalamus both OXT and AVP neurones express GPR30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>This is in agreement with observations of Brailoiu et al. who found co-localisation of GPR30 with OXT and AVP in magnocellular neurones of the rat PVH and SON, but contrast with those of another study that detected GPR30 only in OXT neurones of the PVH and SON of the same species (Brailoiu et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>2007, Sakamoto et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The reasons for these discrepancies are not readily apparent, especially since all three studies used the same antiserum directed against the GPR30 protein (Revankar et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>To confirm the specificity of GPR30-ir in the present study we substituted normal rabbit IgG serum for primary antibody at the same concentration, and did not observe any staining (Fig. 1F). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>E2 mediates the release of OXT and AVP in vivo and in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>It rapidly stimulates intrahypothalamic OXT and AVP release and rapid peripheral OXT and possibly AVP release (Wang et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>1995, Burbach et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>In addition, E2 inhibits the release of both peptides from hypothalamo-neurohypophysial explants stimulated hyperosmotically via a non-genomic action (Swenson &amp; Sladek 1997) and rapidly alters the electrophysiological properties of OXT cells in the SON of lactating or morphine-dependent rats (Israel &amp; Poulain 2000, Brown et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>OXT and AVP neurones of the rat PVH and SON, express ERβ (Hrabovszky et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>It is well established that ERs can stimulate second messenger pathways, perhaps via receptors tethered to the plasma membrane, as well as alter gene activation in the nucleus, suggesting that the rapid E2 effects on OXT/AVP synthesis and release could be modulated through extranuclear ERβ at the level of the hypothalamus (Razandi et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>2003, 2004, Levin 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, E2 could regulate AVP and OXT neuronal activity by indirectly activating ERα/β-expressing neurones that project to the PVH and SON (Shughrue et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>1997, Hrabovszky et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>2004, Sladek &amp; Somponpun 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The relative contribution of GPR30 in E2 effects on hypothalamo-neurohypophysial activity is not known. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>However, ERβ immunoreactivity is absent from the neural lobe suggesting that E2 does not directly mediate peripheral release of OXT and AVP at the level of the pituitary via this receptor (Pelletier et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Interestingly in the present study, we found high levels of GPR30-ir in the neural lobe, indicating that E2 could modulate the peripheral release of OXT and AVP through GPR30 signalling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>As we were unable to detect GPR30 mRNA in the neural lobe, it can be assumed that the receptor had been transported, presumably from the magnocellular neurones in the PVH and SON, as we also observed co-localisation of GPR30 with OXT and AVP fibres in the internal zone of the median eminence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>It is possible that GPR30 regulates OXT and AVP synthesis in PVH and SON magnocellular cell bodies, and/or modulates OXT and AVP release from PVH and SON magnocellular neurone dendrites or from fibres that terminate in the posterior pituitary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Our studies also suggest that GPR30 could mediate E2 effects on the hypothalamic–pituitary adrenal axis by modulating the release of OXT, AVP or perhaps CRF into portal blood from neurones originating from the parvocellular region of the PVH. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Peripheral distribution of GPR30 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The present study demonstrates high expression of GPR30 mRNA and protein in the pituitary gland, adrenal medulla, renal pelvis and ovary of the rat and mouse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>There is a strong correlation between the tissue distribution of both GPR30 mRNA and protein, apart from that in the neural lobe of the pituitary. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>While GPR30 protein is expressed in all three lobes of the pituitary with the highest mRNA expression was observed in the intermediate lobe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>ERα and ERβ are also expressed in the anterior and intermediate lobes, but are absent from the posterior lobe of the pituitary (Mitchner et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>1998, Pelletier et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>2000, González et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>It is well established that the anterior pituitary is a target tissue for E2, regulating gonadotrophin and prolactin (PRL) secretion from gonadotrophs and lactrotrophs, and this response can be rapid, with E2 increasing excitability in PRL-secreting pituitary cell lines within minutes (Dufy et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>1979). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>High expression of GPR30 mRNA and protein in the intermediate lobe and the presence of the traditional E2 receptors suggests a possible role for E2 in pro-opiomelanocortin synthesis and α-melanocyte stimulating hormone (α-MSH) and ACTH-like peptide release. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>A previous study has shown that E2 stimulates the release of α-MSH from the intermediate lobe which in turn appears to exert a rapid stimulatory effect on PRL secretion (Ellerkmann et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>1992). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>In agreement with the present study, GPR30 has been reported to be strongly expressed in the zona glomerulosa and the medulla of the human adrenal glands (Baquedano et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The fast effects of E2 have previously been described in primary cultures of bovine adrenal medullary cells with an up regulation in catecholamine synthesis within 20 min of E2 stimulation (Yanagihara et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>This suggests a role for GPR30 in E2 signalling either independently or synergisitically with extranuclear ERβ which is also expressed in cells of the rat adrenal cortex and medulla (Saunders et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>1997). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>In the kidney, ERα/β are found mainly in the glomeruli and arterioles of the renal cortex where E2 treatment has been shown to upregulate angiotensin type II receptors that regulate sodium and water reabsorption, renal blood flow and glomerular filtration rate (Baiardi et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>2005, Oestreicher et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>We found high expression of GPR30 mRNA and protein in the contracting muscle of the pelvis and to a moderate extent in the medulla. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>In the renal pelvis, the role of E2 is presently unclear but there are suggestions that prolonged E2 administration can encourage renal pelvic tumour growth (Oberley et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>1991, Adsay et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>In other carcinomas (e.g. breast, endometrial), GPR30 expression has been demonstrated (Filardo et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>2006, Smith et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Taken together, it is tempting to speculate that GPR30 is an alternative oestrogen responsive receptor in the production and maintenance of renal pelvic tumours. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>E2 has been shown to promote cell division and survival of granulosa cells in developing follicles of the ovary (Adashi 1994). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>E2 also induces rapid (s) increases in cytosolic calcium concentration of human granulosa cells in vitro (Younglai et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>While this could be mediated through the ERβ which has been shown to be highly expressed within the granulosa cells of developing follicles and corpora lutea of the rat (Saunders et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>1997), our results also indicate a role for GPR30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>GPR30 mRNA and protein have been found in both granulosa and theca cells of the hamster and expression is sensitive to cyclic changes in FSH and LH (Wang et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>It has also been suggested that GPR30 is required for primordial follicle formation (Wang et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>These observations have been appeared to contradict a recent report which concluded that GPR30 did not mediate E2 responses in reproductive organs owing to the fertile phenotype of the GPR30 knockout mice (Otto et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>In GPR30 knockout animals, the normal phenotypes in E2 responsive tissues such as the ovary, uterus and mammary gland does not necessarily preclude the possibility that GPR30 binds E2 in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>For example, in the knockout model, ERα and/or ERβ may compensate for the loss of GPR30 especially in tissues of co-expression where there is potential for receptor cross-talk (Sirianni et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>In addition, it is well known that ERβ knockouts remain fertile; it is only the deletion of ERα which appears to create the infertile phenotype (Walker &amp; Korach 2004). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>While this manuscript was in preparation, four papers relevant to the possible function of GPR30 in the brain and adrenal have been published online. Isensee et al. (2009) analysed the distribution of GPR30 using GPR30-LacZ reporter mice and found predominant expression in sub populations of cells in the cortex and the dentate gyrus of the brain, in the intermediate and anterior lobe of the pituitary gland and in the adrenal medulla. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>As shown in Table 1, GPR30-ir is also highly expressed in regions of the cortex and in the dentate gyrus of the adult mouse brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Our results also confirm the presence of GPR30 mRNA in the anterior and intermediate lobes of the pituitary and the adrenal medulla. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>However, in contrast to our data that clearly demonstrate both GPR30 mRNA and protein in the PVH and SON, GPR30 was only identified in the hypothalamic vasculature and not neurones in the GPR30-LacZ reporter mice (Isensee et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Xu et al. implicate a role for GPR30 in the rat hypothalamus based on the selective GPR30 agonist G-1 attenuating 5-HT1A signalling within the PVH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>They also confirmed GPR30 expression in OXT neurones (Xu et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Another recent study has shown that GPR30 may have been mediated E2-stimulated release of LHRH in primate neurones (Noel et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>In the rodent brain, co-localisation of GPR30 with LHRH neurones or a possible role of GPR30 in E2-stimulated LHRH release has yet to be described. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Finally, the expression of GPR30 in the adrenal medulla of the rat has been confirmed by Dun et al. (2009) with GPR30 located in tyrosine hydroxylase-positive chromaffin cells, further suggesting a likely role for GPR30 in E2-mediated noradrenaline release from the adrenal glands. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>The distribution of GPR30 in the adult mouse brain appears distinct from ERα and ERβ receptors and offers an additional site for E2 action. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>The expression of GPR30 in OXT and AVP neurones in the PVH, SON and in the median eminence, and its presence in the pituitary gland provides a likely means by which E2 can modulate fast ‘non-genomic’ effects on these specific neuropeptide systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>In the periphery, GPR30 may be involved in multiple functions including hormone release and development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Whether E2 initiates responses through GPR30 alone or in concert with the other E2 receptors (e.g. in regions of co-expression) has yet to be investigated, but the cellular distribution of GPR30 in the brain and peripheral tissues provides a basis for further studies on E2 mediated signalling. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Declaration of interest </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest that could be perceived as prejudicing the impartiality of the research reported. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Funding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>G G J H is the recipient of a BBSRC PhD studentship. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>S J L was supported by a grant from the Wellcome Trust (UK), and A M O'C was also funded by the Wellcome Trust (UK) and the BBSRC. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>These results were presented in part at the British Society for Neuroendocrinology meeting in Bristol (September, 2008) and the Winter Neuropeptide Conference in Colorado (February, 2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>ÁbrahámITodmanMGKorachKSHerbisonAECritical in vivo roles for classical estrogen receptors in rapid estrogen actions on intracellular signalling in mouse brainEndocrinology14520043055306114976146 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib2"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>AdashiEYEndocrinology of the ovaryHuman Reproduction919948158277929728 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib3"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>AdsayNVEbleJNSrigleyJRJonesECGrignonDJMixed epithelial and stromal tumor of the kidneyAmerican Journal of Surgical Pathology24200095897010895818 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib4"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>BaiardiGMacovaMArmandoIAndoHTyurminDSaavedraJMEstrogen upregulates renal angiotensin II AT1 and AT2 receptors in the ratRegulatory Peptides15200571715544836 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib5"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>BaquedanoMSSaracoNBerenszteinEPepeCBianchiniMLevyEGoñiJRivarolaMABelgoroskyAIdentification and developmental changes of aromatase and estrogen receptor expression in prepubertal and pubertal human adrenal tissuesJournal of Clinical Endocrinology and Metabolism9220072215222217405842 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib6"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>BoniniJAAndersonSMSteinerDFMolecular cloning and tissue expression of a novel orphan G protein-coupled receptor from rat lungBiochemical and Biophysical Research Communications819971901939168987 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib7"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>BossmarTForslingMAkerlundMCirculating oxytocin and vasopressin is influenced by ovarian steroid replacement in womenActa Obstetricia et Gynecologica Scandinavica7419955445487618454 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib8"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>BrailoiuEDunSLBrailoiuGCMizuoKSklarLAOpreaTIProssnitzERDunNJDistribution and characterization of estrogen receptor GPR30 in the rat central nervous systemJournal of Endocrinology193200731132117470522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib9"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>BrownCHBruntonPJRussellJARapid estradiol-17β modulation of opioid actions on the electrical and secretory activity of rat oxytocin neurons in vivoNeurochemistry Research332008614623 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib10"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>BurbachJPHLuckmanSMMurphyDGainerHGene regulation in the magnocellular hypothalamo-neurohypophysial systemPhysiological Reviews81200111981266 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib11"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>CarmeciCThompsonDARingHZFranckeUWeigelRJIdentification of a gene (GPR30) with homology to the G-protein-coupled receptor superfamily associated with estrogen receptor expression in breast cancerGenomics119976076179367686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib12"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Dominguez-SalazarEShettySRissmanEFRapid neural Fos responses to oestradiol in oestrogen receptor αβ double knockout miceJournal of Neuroendocrinology18200619520216454803 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib13"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>DufyBVincentJDFleuryHDu PasquierPGourdjiDTixier-VidalAMembrane effects of thyrotropin-releasing hormone and estrogen shown by intracellular recording from pituitary cellsScience41979509511107590 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib14"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>DunSLBrailoiuGCGaoXBrailoiuEArterburnJBProssnitzEROpreaTIDunNJExpression of estrogen receptor GPR30 in the rat spinal cord and in autonomic and sensory gangliaJournal of Neuroscience Research1520091610161919125412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib15"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>EllerkmannENagyGMFrawleyLSα-Melanocyte-stimulating hormone is a mammotrophic factor released by neurointermediate lobe cells after estrogen treatmentEndocrinology13019921331381309322 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib16"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>FengYGregorPCloning of a novel member of the G protein-coupled receptor family related to peptide receptorsBiochemical and Biophysical Research Communications2419976516549070864 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib17"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>FilardoEJQuinnJABlandKIFrackeltonARJrEstrogen-induced activation of Erk-1 and Erk-2 requires the G protein-coupled receptor homolog, GPR30, and occurs via trans-activation of the epidermal growth factor receptor through release of HB-EGFMolecular Endocrinology1420001649166011043579 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib18"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>FilardoEJQuinnJAFrackeltonARJrBlandKIEstrogen action via the G protein-coupled receptor, GPR30: stimulation of adenylyl cyclase and cAMP-mediated attenuation of the epidermal growth factor receptor-to-MAPK signaling axisMolecular Endocrinology162002708411773440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib19"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>FilardoEJGraeberCTQuinnJAResnickMBGiriDDeLellisRASteinhoffMMSaboEDistribution of GPR30, a seven membrane-spanning estrogen receptor, in primary breast cancer and its association with clinicopathologic determinants of tumor progressionClinical Cancer Research120066359636617085646 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib20"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>FilardoEQuinnJPangYGraeberCShawSDongJThomasPActivation of the novel estrogen receptor G protein-coupled receptor 30 (GPR30) at the plasma membraneEndocrinology14820073236324517379646 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib21"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>FinchASedgleyKCauntCMcArdleCPlasma membrane expression of GnRH receptors: regulation by antagonists in breast, prostate, and gonadotrope cell linesJournal of Endocrinology196200835336718252959 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib22"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>GonzálezMReyesRDamasCAlonsoRBelloAROestrogen receptor α and β in female rat pituitary cells: an immunochemical studyGeneral and Comparative Endocrinology12008857868 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib23"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>HrabovszkyEKallóISteinhauserAMerchenthalerICoenCWPetersenSLLipositsZEstrogen receptor-β in oxytocin and vasopressin neurons of the rat and human hypothalamus: immunocytochemical and in situ hybridization studiesJournal of Comparative Neurology31200431533315116394 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib24"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>IsenseeJMeoliLZazzuVNabzdykCWittHSoewartoDEffertzKFuchsHGailus-DurnerVBuschDExpression pattern of Gpr30 in LacZ reporter miceEndocrinology15020091722173019095739 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib25"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>IsraelJ-MPoulainDA17β-Oestradiol modulates in vitro electrical properties and responses to kainate of oxytocin neurones in lactating ratsJournal of Physiology524200045747010766926 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib26"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>KvingedalAMSmelandEBA novel putative G-protein-coupled receptor expressed in lung, heart and lymphoid tissueFEBS Letters407199759629141481 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib27"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>LaflammeNNappiREDroletGLabrieCRivestSExpression and neuropeptidergic characterization of estrogen receptors (ERα and ERβ) throughout the rat brain: anatomical evidence of distinct roles of each subtypeJournal of Neurobiology519983573789733072 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib28"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>LevinERIntegration of the extranuclear and nuclear actions of estrogenMolecular Endocrinology1920051951195915705661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib31"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>MårtenssonUESalehiSAWindahlSGomezMFSwärdKDaszkiewicz-NilssonJWendtAAnderssonNHellstrandPGrändePODeletion of the G protein-coupled receptor GPR30 impairs glucose tolerance, reduces bone growth, increases blood pressure, and eliminates estradiol-stimulated insulin release in female miceEndocrinology150200968769818845638 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib32"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>McEwanBEstrogen actions throughout the brainRecent Progress in Hormone Research57200235738412017552 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib33"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>MerchenthalerILaneMVNumanSDellovadeTLDistribution of estrogen receptor alpha and beta in the mouse central nervous system: in vivo autoradiographic and immunocytochemical analysesJournal of Comparative Neurology24200427029115101093 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib34"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>MitchnerNAGarlickCBen-JonathanNCellular distribution and gene regulation of estrogen receptors alpha and beta in the rat pituitary glandEndocrinology1391998397639839724053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib35"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>MitraSWHoskinEYudkovitzJPearLWilkinsonHAHayashiSPfaffDWOgawaSRohrerSPSchaefferJMImmunolocalization of estrogen receptor beta in the mouse brain: comparison with estrogen receptor alphaEndocrinology14420032055206712697714 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib36"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>NoelSDKeenKLBaumannDIFilardoEJTerasawaEInvolvement of G-protein coupled receptor 30 (GPR30) in rapid action of estrogen in primate LHRH neuronsMolecular Endocrinology23200934935919131510 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib37"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>OberleyTDGonzalezALauchnerLJOberleyLWLiJJCharacterization of early kidney lesions in estrogen-induced tumors in the Syrian hamsterCancer Research11991192219292004377 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib38"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>OestreicherEMGuoCSeelyEWKikuchiTMartinez-VasquezDJonassonLYaoTBurrDMayoralSRoubsanthisukWEstradiol increases proteinuria and angiotensin II type 1 receptor in kidneys of rats receiving L-NAME and angiotensin IIKidney International7020061759176817021606 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib39"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>OttoCFuchsIKauselmannGKernHZevnikBAndreasenPSchwarzGAltmannHKlewerMSchoorMGPR30 does not mediate estrogenic responses in reproductive organs in miceBiology of Reproduction802008344118799753 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib40"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>OwmanCBlayPNilssonCLolaitSJCloning of human cDNA encoding a novel heptahelix receptor expressed in Burkitt's lymphoma and widely distributed in brain and peripheral tissuesBiochemical and Biophysical Research Communications22819962852928920907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib41"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>PelletierGLabrieCLabrieFLocalization of oestrogen receptor α, oestrogen receptor β and androgen receptors in the rat reproductive organsJournal of Endocrinology165200035937010810300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib42"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>PfaffDWSakumaYFacilitation of the lordosis reflex of female rats from the ventromedial nucleus of the hypothalamusJournal of Physiology2881978189202469715 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib43"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>ProssnitzERArterburnJBSmithHOOpreaTISklarLAHathawayHJEstrogen signalling through the transmembrane G protein-coupled receptor GPR30Annual Review of Physiology702008165190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib44"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>RazandiMPedramAParkSTLevinERProximal events in signaling by plasma membrane estrogen receptorsJournal of Biological Chemistry27820032701271212421825 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib45"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>RazandiMPedramAMerchenthalerIGreeneGLLevinERPlasma membrane estrogen receptors exist and functions as dimersMolecular Endocrinology1820042854286515231873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib46"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>RevankarCMCiminoDFSklarLAArterburnJBProssnitzERA transmembrane intracellular estrogen receptor mediates rapid cell signallingScience30720051625163015705806 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib47"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>RevankarCMMitchellHDFieldASBuraiRCoronaCRameshCSklarLAArterburnJBProssnitzERSynthetic estrogen derivatives demonstrate the functionality of intracellular GPR30ACS Chemical Biology17200753654417655271 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib48"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>de RondeWPolsHAPvan LeeuwenJPTMde JongFHThe importance of oestrogens in malesClinical Endocrinology58200352954212699432 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib49"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>SakamotoHMatsudaKHosokawaKNishiMMorrisJProssnitzERKawataMExpression of G protein-coupled receptor-30, a G protein-coupled membrane estrogen receptor, in oxytocin neurons of the rat paraventricular and supraoptic nucleiEndocrinology14820075842585017872373 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib50"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>SaundersPTMaguireSMGaughanJMillarMRExpression of oestrogen receptor beta (ERβ) in multiple rat tissues visualised by immunohistochemistryJournal of Endocrinology15419971316 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib51"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>ShughruePJLaneMVMerchenthalerIComparative distribution of estrogen receptor-α and -β mRNA in the rat central nervous systemJournal of Comparative Neurology38819975075259388012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib52"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>SirianniRChimentoARuggieroCDe LucaALappanoRAndòSMaggioliniMPezziVThe novel estrogen receptor, G protein-coupled receptor 30, mediates the proliferative effects induced by 17beta-estradiol on mouse spermatogonial GC-1 cell lineEndocrinology14920085043505118566133 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib53"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>SladekCDSomponpunSJOestrogen receptor β: role in neurohyphyseal neuronesJournal of Neuroendocrinology16200436537115089976 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib54"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>SmithHOLeslieKKSinghMQuallsCRRevankarCMJosteNEProssnitzERGPR30: a novel indicator of poor survival for endometrial carcinomaAmerican Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology1962007386.e1386.e9(discussion 386.e9–386.e11)17403429 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib57"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>SwensonKLSladekCDGonadal steroid modulation of vasopressin secretion in response to osmotic stimulationEndocrinology1381997208920979112409 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib58"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>ThankyNRSonJHHerbisonAESex differences in the regulation of tyrosine hydroxylase gene transcription by estrogen in the locus coeruleus of TH9-LacZ transgenic miceMolecular Brain Research15200222022612225877 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib59"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>ThomasPPangYFilardoEJDongJIdentity of an estrogen membrane receptor coupled to a G protein in human breast cancer cellsEndocrinology146200562463215539556 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib60"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>ValverdeMARojasPAmigoJCosmelliDOrioPBahamondeMIMannGEVergaraCLatorreRAcute activation of Maxi-K channels (hSlo) by estradiol binding to the beta subunitScience1719991929193110489376 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib61"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>WalkerVRKorachKSEstrogen receptor knockout mice as a model for endocrine researchILAR Journal45200445546115454684 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib62"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>WangHWardARMorrisJFOestradiol acutely stimulates exocytosis of oxytocin and vasopressin from dendrites and somata of hypothalamic magnocellular neuronsNeuroscience681995117911888544991 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib63"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>WangCProssnitzERRoySKExpression of G protein-coupled receptor 30 in the hamster ovary: differential regulation by gonadotropins and steroid hormonesEndocrinology14820074853486417640985 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib64"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>WangCProssnitzERRoySKG protein-coupled receptor 30 expression is required for estrogen stimulation of primordial follicle formation in the hamster ovaryEndocrinology14920084452446118499747 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib65"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>WatsonCSGametchuBMembrane estrogen and glucocorticoid receptors – implications for hormonal control of immune function and autoimmunityInternational Immunopharmacology120011049106311407301 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib66"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>WersingerSRGinnsEO'CarrollA-MLolaitSJYoungWSIIIVasopressin V1b knockout reduces aggressive behaviour in male miceMolecular Psychiatry7200297598412399951 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib67"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>XuHQinSCarrascoGADaiYFilardoEJProssnitzERBattagliaGDoncarlosLLMumaNAExtra-nuclear estrogen receptor GPR30 regulates serotonin function in rat hypothalamusNeuroscience15820091599160719095043 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib68"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>YanagiharaNLiuMToyohiraYTsutsuiMUenoSShinoharaYTakahashiKTanakaKStimulation of catecholamine synthesis through unique estrogen receptors in the bovine adrenomedullary plasma membrane by 17beta-estradiolBiochemical and Biophysical Research Communications13200654855316307725 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib69"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>YounglaiEVWuYJKwanTKKwanCYNon-genomic action of estradiol and progesterone on cytosolic calcium concentrations in primary cultures of human granulosa-lutein cellsHuman Reproduction2020052383239015932916 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Immunoreactivity for GPR30 in the adult male or female mouse brain: labelled cells in the supplementary motor cortex (A), piriform cortex (B), labelled cells and fibres in the SON (C), with moderate labelling of cells in the paraventricular nucleus of the thalamus (D), labelled cells and fibres in the PVH (E) with an absence of labelling in the PVH with a section incubated with IgG in place of GPR30 antiserum (F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>M2, supplementary motor cortex; PIR, piriform cortex; SON, supraoptic nucleus of the hypothalamus; PVT, paraventricular nucleus of the thalamus; PVH, paraventricular nucleus of the hypothalamus; OC, optic chiasm; 3V, third ventricle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Scale bars, 100 μm in (A–B and E–F); 50 μm in (C–D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>A lower magnification of the PVT is inserted in (D) (Scale bar=100 μm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>D3V, dorsal third ventricle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JOE090066f01"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Immunoreactivity for GPR30 in the adult male or female mouse brain: labelled cells and fibres in the dentate gyrus of the hippocampus (A), zona incerta (B), arcuate nucleus and cell bodies of the ventromedial hypothalamic nucleus (C), GPR30-ir in cells and fibres of the lateral mamillary nucleus of the hypothalamus (D), labelled cells and fibres of the pars compacta of the substantia nigra (E) and labelled cells of the pontine nuclei (F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>DG, dentate gyrus of the hippocampus; ZI, zona incerta; Arc, arcuate nucleus of the hypothalamus; VMH, ventromedial hypothalamic nucleus; LM, lateral mamillary nucleus of the hypothalamus; SNC, pars compacta of the substantia nigra; Pn, pontine nuclei; 3V, third ventricle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Scale bars, 100 μm in (A–D); 50 μm in (E–F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>In E and F, lower magnifications of the SNC and Pn respectively, are shown (scale bars=200 μm). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JOE090066f02"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Immunoreactivity for GPR30 in the adult male or female mouse brain: labelled cells of the Purkinje cell layer of the cerbellum (A), locus coeruleus (B) and sensory trigeminal nucleus (C) enlarged in (D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>pcL, Purkinje cell layer of the cerbellum; lc, locus coeruleus; PrS, sensory trigeminal nucleus; 4V, fourth ventricle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Scale bars, 100 μm in (A–C); 50 μm in (D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>In (C), a lower magnification of Pr5 is shown (scale bar=200 μm). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JOE090066f03"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Double label immunofluorescence for GPR30 and AVP in the adult rat PVH (A–C), SON (D–F) and median eminence (G–I), and GPR30 and OXT in the adult mouse PVH (J, K and L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Immunoreactivities against GPR30 (A, D, G and J; red) and AVP (B, E and H; green) or OXT (K; green) were merged in each right panel (C, F, I and L; overlap yellow) respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>G–L were captured using a laser confocal microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>3V, third ventricle; OC, optic chiasm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Scale bars, 100 μm in (A–F); 80 μm in (G–L). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JOE090066f04"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Double label immunofluorescence for GPR30, OXT and AVP in the adult rat SON and mouse PVH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Immunoreactivities against GPR30 (A, D and G; red) and OXT (B; green) or AVP (E and H; green) were merged in each right panel (C, F and I; overlap yellow) respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Arrows indicate OXT or AVP immunoreactive cell bodies that also contain GPR30-immunoreactivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Note that some GPR30-ir cells (arrowhead) do not express OXT-ir or AVP-ir. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>In addition to staining of cell bodies, there also appears to be co-expression of GPR30-ir and OXT-ir in processes (that may be axons or dendrites), suggesting that the receptor may be axo-dendritically transported, as has been well-established for the neuropeptide (see open arrows). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>The presence of possible intracellular staining of GPR30 within OXT and AVP neurones which is consistent with the predominantly cytoplasmic distribution of GPR30 that has been observed in various cell types in vitro (see discussion for details). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Pictures captured at the same low magnification using a laser confocal microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Scale bars, 10 μm in (A–I). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JOE090066f05"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemical analysis of GPR30 in rodent peripheral tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>(A) GPR30-ir in rat pituitary is prominent in the nerve terminals of the neural (posterior) lobe (NL) and is present in most melanotrophs of the intermediate lobe (IL) (e.g. indicated by arrows). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>GPR30-ir is also found in scattered (∼50%) cells in the anterior pituitary (AP) lobe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Whether these represent endocrine cells (e.g. prolactotrophs and corticotrophs) was not determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>(B) High levels of GPR30-ir are present in the rat renal pelvis (RP), an extension of the ureter, with projections into the renal inner medulla (IM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>(C) In the rat ovary, GPR30-ir is found mainly in the granulosa cells (G), with some staining of theca cells (T) of the developing follicle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Scale bars, 400 μm in (B); 50 μm in (A and C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JOE090066f06"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>In situ hybridisation of GPR30 mRNA in the rodent PVH, SON and pituitary gland: reversed image of emulsion dipped section of the rat PVH the GPR30 hybridisation grains appear white in the picture (A) (but black on the actual slide); the corresponding sense slide is absent of black GPR30 hybridisation grains (B); low-magnification photographs of film autoradiographic images of a slide mounted hypothalamic section hybridised with a GPR30 probe, with signal in the PVH and SON of the rat brain (C), and pituitary sections hybridised with a GPR30 probe in rat (D) and mouse (E) with intense signal in both intermediate lobes; emulsion dipped section of the mouse pituitary, hybridisation signal for GPR30 mRNA appears as black grains (E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>3V, Third ventricle; PVH, paraventricular nucleus; SON, supraoptic nucleus; AP, anterior pituitary; IL, intermediate lobe of the pituitary; NL, neural lobe of the pituitary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Scale bars, 1 mm in (C–E); 100 μm in (A and F); 50 μm in (B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JOE090066f07"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>In situ hybridisation of GPR30 mRNA in rodent peripheral tissues: low-magnification photograph of a film autoradiographic image of a slide mounted, rat adrenal section hybridised with a GPR30 probe (A); emulsion dipped section of the mouse adrenal medulla-hybridisation signal for GPR30 mRNA appears as black grains on toluidine blue counterstained cells (B); low-magnification photograph of a film autoradiographic image of a slide mounted, rat kidney section hybridised with a GPR30 probe (C), with an absence of signal in the sense control (D); low-magnification photograph of a film autoradiographic image of a slide mounted, mouse ovary section hybridised with a GPR30 probe, with signal localised predominantly in the developing follicles (E), with an absence of signal in the sense control (F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>AM, adrenal medulla; ZG, zona glomerulosa; RP, renal pelvis; IM, renal medulla; DF, developing follicle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Scale bars, 1 mm in (A and C–F); 25 μm in (B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JOE090066f08"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Summary of the distribution of GPR30 immunoreactivity (ir) in the adult brain, determined using three males and three females. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Data presented here are of semi-quantitative assessments and the intensity of staining is based on the subjective judgement of three observers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>No apparent gender differences were detected </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Intensity of label: +++, intense; ++, moderate; +, low; −, absent; (c), cells; (f), fibres; all other regions contain both immunoreactive cells and fibres.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Summary of GPR30 co-localisation with oxytocin and vasopressin neurones in the rodent paraventricular (PVN) and supraoptic nuclei (SON) of the hypothalamus </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Values represent the total number of OXT and AVP neurones counted in sections of PVN and SON obtained from three male and three female animals, and the average percentage (±<sc>s.d.</sc>) that also express GPR30-ir. There was no apparent difference in the number of co-expressing neurones between the anterior, middle and posterior PVN in either rat or mouse.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>An overall comparison of the distribution of GPR30, oestrogen receptors (ER) α and β, in the mouse brain (Results for ERα and β are a summary of the mouse brain atlases from Mitra et al. (2003) and Merchenthaler et al. (2004) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Intensity of label: +++, intense; ++, moderate; +, low; −, abs.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
