
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Biomed Biotechnol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JBB</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Biomedicine and Biotechnology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1110-7243</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1110-7251</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2946600</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2010/108159</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Expression of a Novel Chimeric Truncated t-PA in CHO Cells Based on in Silico Experiments </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Davami</surname><given-names>Fatemeh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sardari</surname><given-names>Soroush</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Majidzadeh-A</surname><given-names>Keivan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hemayatkar</surname><given-names>Mehdi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barkhrdari</surname><given-names>Farzaneh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Omidi</surname><given-names>Maryam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Azami</surname><given-names>Mehrnaz</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Adeli</surname><given-names>Ahmad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Davoudi</surname><given-names>Noushin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mahboudi</surname><given-names>Fereidoun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1">Biotechnology Research Center,  Pasteur Institute of Iran (IPI),  no. 69,  Pasteur Avenue,  Tehran 1316943551, Iran</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Fereidoun Mahboudi: <email>mahboudi_f@pasteur.ac.ir</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editor: Saulius Butenas </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>2010</volume><elocation-id>108159</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>1</day><month>8</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>8</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2010 Fatemeh Davami et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Tissue plasminogen activator (t-PA) is one of the fibrin-specific serine proteases that play a crucial role in the fibrinolytic system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The rapid clearance of the drug from the circulation, caused by its active uptake in the liver, has lead to complicated clinical applications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Different forms of plasminogen activators have been developed to treat thrombotic disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Deletion of the first three domains of t-PA by gene manipulation techniques has shown a significant increase in its plasma half life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>In order to compensate the disadvantage of higher bleeding risk, a novel chimeric truncated form of t-PA with 394 amino acids and more fibrin affinity compared to the truncated form was designed to be expressed in Chinese Hamster Ovarian (CHO) cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The recombinant chimeric plasminogen activator consists of kringle 2 and serine protease (K2S) domains of t-PA, namely GHRP-SYQ-K2S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The level of expression was found to be 752 IU/ml with 566,917 IU/mg specific activity, based on amidolytic activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The fibrin binding of this novel chimeric truncated t-PA was 86% of the full length t-PA at a fibrinogen concentration of 0.2 mg/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>This could be a promising approach with more desirable pharmacodynamic properties compared to existing commercial forms. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="section" id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Myocardial infarction (MI) is an irreversible necrosis or death of heart muscles due to prolonged ischemia [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>According to the third monitoring report of the World Health Organization, cardiovascular diseases cause 12 million deaths throughout the world each year [2, 3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Thrombolytic drugs play a crucial role in the management of patients with acute myocardial infarction, pulmonary embolism, deep vein thrombosis, arterial thrombosis, acute thrombosis of retinal vessel, extensive coronary emboli, and peripheral vascular thromboembolism [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Recognition of the importance of fibrinolytic system in thrombus resolution has resulted in the development of various fibrinolytic agents and plasminogen activators (PAs) with different pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic properties [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Three different generations of PAs have been introduced to the market. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The first generation agents are Streptokinase and Urokinase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The second generation agents are Alteplase and Acylated plasminogen streptokinase activator complex (APSAC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The third generation agents are Vampire bat plasminogen activator (BatPA), Reteplase, Tenecteplase, Lanatoplase, and Staphylokinase [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Tissue-type plasminogen activator (t-PA) is the dominant PA involved in fibrinolysis [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>T-PA is a glycoprotein with 67 kDa, 527 amino acids, which promotes conversion of plasminogen to plasmin in the presence of fibrin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The protein molecule is divided into five structural domains: finger domain (F) followed by a growth factor domain (EGF) near the N-terminal region and the two kringle 1 (K1) and kringle 2 (K2) domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Next to kringle 2 domain is the serine protease domain with the catalytic site at the C terminus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Both finger and kringle 2 bind to the fibrin and accelerate t-PA activation on plasminogen [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>However, full length t-PA has some major disadvantages among which the rapid clearance from plasma due to the recognition of structural elements on first three N-terminal domains by certain hepatic receptors is the most important [7–9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, prokaryotic production and refolding process of full length form is challenging [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>These two substantial reasons, have lead to synthesis of the smallest active molecule such as Reteplase and Lanatoplase that are commercially available [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Reteplase is a deletion mutant of t-PA with prolonged half-life, in which the F, EGF, and K1 region of wild type t-PA molecular have been deleted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Finger domain is the responsible domain for fibrin affinity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Therefore, Reteplase has weaker affinity for fibrin and causes more fibrinogen depletion than full length forms [4, 11, 12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The chimeric tetrapeptide selection was based on following evidences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Human fibrinogen can be converted to fibrin through thrombin-catalyzed release of small peptides from the amino-terminal segments of the K and L chains that are named fibrinopeptides A and B, respectively [13, 14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The tetrapeptide GHRP can interact with a complementary site on the L lobe of fibrin monomers and prevent polymerization [13, 14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, it has been reported that histidine-16 of the BL chain plays an important role in the association of fibrin [14–16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In this study, the first three domains of t-PA were deleted in order to increase half life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The other crucial change made to the protein was that a chimeric tertapeptide Gly-His-Arg-Pro (GHRP) with high fibrin affinity, was added upstream of K2S to compensate for diminished fibrin affinity due to F domain deletion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Therefore, a novel truncated form t-PA was designed to be expressed in Chinese hamster ovarian (CHO). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>This experiment was primarily designed and analyzed based on in silico analysis of the molecule. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="section" id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>DG44 transfection kit and Zeocin selection marker were obtained from Gibco-Invitrogen cooperation (CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Plasminogen was received from Sigma (MO, USA); Chromolize t-PA Assay Kit was purchased from Biopool (Trinity Biotech plc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Ireland). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Rabbit polyclonal antibody to t-PA was supplied by Abcam (MA, USA) and goat anti rabbit IgG-HRP conjugated was purchased from Santa Cruz biotechnology (CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>All reagents for SDS/polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis were from Bio-Rad, (CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>In Silico Predictions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>All of the molecular modeling and structure visualizations were done on a dual processor windows-based platform, workstation using the Deepview/Swiss PDB viewer program version 3.7, 2001 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.expasy.org/spdbv">http://www.expasy.org/spdbv</ext-link>) and VMD 1.8.7 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ks.uiuc.edu">http://www.ks.uiuc.edu</ext-link>), DPM (double prediction Method) algorithm [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Secondary structure prediction was used to predict the secondary structure of our novel protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Atomic coordinates of kringle 2 and serine protease domain of t-PA were retrieved from the Protein Data Bank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org/pdb/cgi">http://www.rcsb.org/pdb/cgi</ext-link>) [entries 1tpk and 1bda, resp.] and 1fzv and 2flh both were used as templates for the 7 amino acid chimeric part: GHRP-SYQ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The 1fzv and 2flh entries were chosen since they had GDRPSY and PSYQ in their sequence, respectively, and their pdb files did not cause any problem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>To produce theoretical chimeric truncated t-PA using above templates a model was designed by Modeller 9v1, via automodel package. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Energy minimization was done by GROMOS96 implementation of Swiss-Pdbviewer <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.igc.ethz.ch/GROMOS/index">http://www.igc.ethz.ch/GROMOS/index</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The Ramachandran plots analysis was performed by RAMPAGE online Ramachandran plot analysis software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mordred.bioc.cam.ac.uk/~rapper/rampage">http://mordred.bioc.cam.ac.uk/~rapper/rampage</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Construction of Desired Gene Cassette Using Splicing by Overlap Extension PCR (SOEing-PCR) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Full-length human t-PA (GenBank accession number 101047) was amplified using the CHO 1–15 cell line (ATCC-CRL 9606) genomic DNA and cloned into pTZ57R during our previous work [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The general mechanism of SOE is illustrated in (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The segments to be joined; fragment AB: signal sequence from upstream of t-PA full length gene and fragment CD: K2S from downstream of the gene) are amplified in separate PCRs (“1” and “2”). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The primers used to be “SOEn” (B: CGGCCTATGACCTCTAGCTCCTCTTCTGAATCGGG and C: GGTCATAGGCCGTCATATCAAGGAAACAGTG) are made partially complementary to one another and also include nucleotides to be inserted (GHRP-SYQ) between signal sequence and K2S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Forward and reverse primers are as follows: A, GATCTGCCACCATGGATG, and D, TGGTCTAGATCACGGTCGCATGTTG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The PCR products of these first reactions overlap via their homologous sequences at the ends which contain the desired insertion (GHRP-SYQ) as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The three domains were deleted and a 21 bp fragment was inserted simultaneously. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The products of the first step are mixed in a SOE reaction (reaction 3), and subjected to repeated rounds of denaturation, reannealing, and primer extension by DNA polymerase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>By presence of the appropriate primers (“A” and “D”) in the reaction, the recombinant product is formed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The first step PCR reactions was done in the following conditions for AB and CD fragments: first reaction: 1 μL t-PA DNA (22.7 ng/μL), 0.2 mM DNTP, 1 μL primer A (0.4 μM), 2 μL primer B (0.4 μM), 21 μL Buffer, and 2 mM MgSO4; Second reaction: 1 μL t-PA DNA (26 ng/μL), 0.2 mM DNTP, 1 μL primer D (0.4 μM), 2 μL primer C (0.4 μM), 21 μL Buffer, and 2 mM MgSO4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The SOEing PCR reaction was as follows: Fragment AB as the first template 1 μL (54 ng/μL) and fragment CD as second template 1 μL (58 ng/μL) were combined and the PCR reaction was run without the presence of primers for 3 cycles (94°C, 4 min, 94°C, 1 min, and 72°C 1 min), then the procedure completed in 94°C 1 min, 68°C 1 min, 72°C 1 min for 30 cycles, and a final 5 min 72°C extension time in the presence of A and D primers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.3"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Construction of Expression Vector pTracer-SV40-GHRP-SYQ-K2S </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>After performing SOEing PCRs, the SOEn 1200 bp gene was cleaned up by a QIAquick PCR Purification kit (Qiagen Germany), cloned in an intermediate vector pJET1.2/blunt Cloning Vector via CloneJET PCR Cloning Kit (Fermentas, Vilnius, Lithuania) based on the manufacturer's procedures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>After confirming the proper sequence arrangement by bidirectional sequencing, two upstream and downstream BglII restriction sites of pJET were used due to accomplish cloning into CHO expression vector, EcoRV site in pTracer-SV40's. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>BglII sticky ends were converted to blunt ends using CloneJET PCR Cloning Kit DNA blunting enzyme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The recombinant pTracer-SV40-chimeric-truncated-t-PA plasmid was purified by EndoFree Plasmid Mega kit (Qiagen Germany) and the presence and right orientation of the gene was confirmed by SmaI restriction enzyme digestion (results not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.4"><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>CHO Transfection and Transient Expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>DG44 Transfection Kit (GIBCO Invitrogen USA) was utilized to transfect DG44 CHO cells by LIPOFECTAMINE 2000 CD, based on manufacturer's 12 well plate's protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Transfected cells were examined under fluorescent microscope GFP filters with excitation wavelength of 400 nm and emissions wavelength of 510 nm for transient expression of pTracer_SV40 GFP protein which is partially correlated with t-PA gene expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.5"><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>2.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Stable Expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Zeocin sensitivity of CHO DG44 cells was determined based on pTracer-SV40 manual guide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The pTracer-SV40-chimeric-truncated t-PA was linearized from BglII restriction site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Linierized plasmid was then transected to the cells by DG44 transfection kit, and stable integrants were selected above the predetermined Zeocin sensitivity concentration (500 μg/mL). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.6"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>2.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>SDS-PAGE and Western Blot Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Supernatants from stable transfected CHO culture medium were harvested and concentrated using Amicon filtering system (Millipore, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>SDS-PAGE was carried out in a 12% resolving polyacrylamide gel according to the Laemmli method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Western blot analysis of culture media was performed according to Sambrook et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Electroblotting was performed in a semidry blotting system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Proteins were transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane, and antigen-antibody complexes were visualized by DAB-HRP system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Primary polyclonal rabbit anti-t-PA antibody (Abcam. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>USA) were diluted 1/1000, the secondary antibody, peroxidase conjugated goat antirabbit antibody (Santa Cruz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>USA) was used in a 1/1500 dilution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.7"><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>2.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Copolymerized Plasminogen Polyacrylamide Gel Electrophoresis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>An 11% resolving polyacrylamide gel was copolymerized with plasminogen and gelatin as previously described by Heussen and Dowdle [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The stacking gel was prepared as 4% concentration without plasminogen and gelatin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Electrophoresis was performed at 40°C at a constant current of 8 mA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The residual SDS in gel slab was removed after a gentle shaking at room temperature for 1 h in 2.5% Triton X-100. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Then, the gel slab was incubated in 0.1 M glycine-NaOH, pH 8.3, for 5 h at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Finally, the gel slab was stained and destained by standard Coomassie brilliant blue (R-250) dying system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The location of the peptide harboring enzymatic activity was not stained by dye in contrast to blue-paint background. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.8"><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>2.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Purification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The one-step purification procedure was performed using HiTrap Benzamidine FF (high sub) column. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The column is specified for the purification of serine proteases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The buffers referred to are as follows: 0.05 mMTris-HCL, 0.5 M NaCl, PH 7.4 was used as binding and wash buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Elution buffers were performed using a step gradient of 0.5 M NaCl, 10 mM HCl, and PH 2.0, and 1 M NaCl, 10 mM HCl, and PH 2.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Affinity bound substances were eluted by increasing the salt concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Step 1: after washing the column with 5 columns of distilled water to remove storage buffer, the column was equilibrated with 5-column volumes of binding buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Step 2: cell culture conditioned media was filtered through a 0.45 μm filter and loaded to the column at the same flow rate (1 mL/min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Step 3: the column was again washed with 10 column volumes of binding buffer until no material appeared in eluted fraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Step 4: the t-PA was eluted from the column with 5 mL of each salt concentration (0.5 and 1 M NaCl ) of elution buffers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The pH and conductivity of the buffers were such that the t-PA bound selectively to the column electrostatically while the bulk of the other nonserine protease proteins material did not bind to the resin and were removed in the column flow through. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.9"><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>2.9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Quantification (Amidolytic Activity Test) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Biopool Chromolize t-PA Assay Kit is a biofunctional immunosorbent assay based on capturing t-PA by sp-322 monoclonal antibodies coated on the microtest wells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>After fulfilling, the steps from the kit's manual samples were read at 405 nm and 492 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Absorbance at 492 nm is measured and subtracted from 405 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Various dilutions of each sample were assayed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The amount of developed colour is proportional to the amount of t-PA activity in the sample. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec2.10"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>2.10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Fibrin Binding Assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The binding of t-PAs was assessed by previously reported methods [20–22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Briefly, various concentrations of fibrinogen (0–0.3 mg/mL) were mixed with bovine thrombin (0.5 U/mL) in buffer (0.05 M Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 0.12 M NaCl, 0.01% Tween 80, and 1 mg/mL bovine serum albumin) to form fibrin clots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>After incubating the mixture for 30 min at 37°C equal units (3000 unit) of truncated or full length t-PA were added. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The mixture was incubated for 30 min at 37°C, and the clot was removed by centrifugation (15 min, 13 000 rpm, 4°C; Sigma 202 MD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The amount of enzyme bound to fibrin was calculated from the difference of the total amount of enzyme and the free enzyme in the supernatant, as determined by ELISA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>In the ELISA assay, 100 microliters of full length and truncated t-PA are pipetted into each well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The covered plate is incubated for 15 minutes at 37°C, and the reaction is started by the addition of 100 microliters of a plasminogen/S-2251 mixture which contains two parts 10 mM S-2251, one part plasminogen solution (1 mcg/mL), and seven parts assay buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The mixture is prepared immediately prior to use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>(Assay buffer is Tris saline prepared by dissolving 605 mg Tris in 800 mL distilled water and adjusting the pH to 8.8 with 6 normal HC1, then dissolving 5.84 grams NaCl and 0.1 grams Triton X-100 into the buffer and diluting to 1000 mL.) The absorbance (405 nm) is then measured at 20, 40, and 60 minutes [17, 23, 24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="section" id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>In Silico Predictions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec sec-type="subsubsection" id="sec3.1.1"><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>3.1.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Secondary Structure Prediction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Double prediction method (DPM) algorithm [17] was used to predict secondary structure of the chimeric truncated t-PA and full length protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Percentage of alpha helix, extended strand, beta turn and random coil were 27.66, 26.9, 13.45, and 31.9 in chimeirc-truncated t-PA and 26.87, 26.69, 15.84, and 30.6 in full-length t-PA, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>As could be expected, no significant differences in secondary structure were detected between chimeric truncated t-PA and full-length protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsubsection" id="sec3.1.2"><title><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>3.1.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Tertiary Structure Prediction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Chimeric-truncated-t-PA (GHRP-SYQ-K2S) was successfully modeled via MODELLER 9V1 automodel package using templates mentioned in Section 2 (Figures 2(a) and 2(b)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>We superimposed chimeric-truncated model both on K2 (1TPK) and S (1BDA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The predicted model for chimeric-truncated t-PA in this study showed desirable calculated RMSDs after superimposing to the 1tpk (2.79, 2.64, and 2.94 for A, B, and C chains, resp.) and also 0.53 after superimposing to the 1bda structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>As RMSD values below 2 were acceptable in our criteria, the results of 1bda superimposing which represents functional domain of t-PA showed that the mentioned genetic manipulations do not change the main structure drastically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is predicted that designed novel molecule would not loose thrombolytic activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The results of Ramachandran plot analysis showed desirable results of almost 1% of residues in outliner region for both K2S and chimeric form which is acceptable in this software's criteria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Preparing Desired Cassette Gene </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec sec-type="subsubsection" id="sec3.2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>3.2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>SOEing PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>We succeeded in deleting the first three domains of t-PA (Finger, EGF, and K1), and juxtaposing signal peptide upstream of K2S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>A 21 base pare DNA sequence, related to GHRP-SYQ amino acids, was inserted between signal sequence and K2S domains by using 2 sets of primers in one SOEing reaction, simultaneously. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The PCR products for the forward and reverse reactions which were used to generate the chimeric-truncated gene are shown in Figure 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The PCR products with 134 bp (lane1), 1089 bp (lane3), and 1223 bp (lane4) represent signal sequence-GHRP, GHRP-SYQ-K2S and full-length mutated sequence (signal sequence + GHRP + SYQ + K2S), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>These findings are in accordance with the theoretical calculated lengths. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsubsection" id="sec3.2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>3.2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Construction of Truncated-t-PA-pTracer-SV40 Fusion Plasmid </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The full-length fused fragment was successfully amplified and ligated into the pTracer-SV40 vector (Invitrogen-USA) using EcoR-V and BglII restriction enzyme sites on vector and inserted gene, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, ligation was confirmed by digestion with restriction endonucleases (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>To confirm absence of any kind of mutation during gene manipulation and also to determine desired chimeric conjunction, the cloned gene was sequenced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The sequence showed the desired chimeric conjunction at the 36th to the 39th residue, and first 3 amino acids of native t-PA, exactly before K2S fragment and just after signal sequence (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec3.3"><title><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Transfections </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec sec-type="subsubsection" id="sec3.3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>3.3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Transient Expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>After transfection of CHO cells with nonlinear plasmid, the cells were allowed to recover for 24 to 48 hours and then assayed by fluorescence microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The results showed 10%–20% transfection efficiency (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsubsection" id="sec3.3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>3.3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Stable Transfection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>As mentioned in Section 2, chimeric truncated t-PA was cloned in pTracer-SV40 expression vector for transformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The positive clones were selected based on Zeocin resistance and PCR amplification of the integrated t-PA gene was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The proper band related to chimeric truncated t-PA gene is shown in Figure 4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec3.4"><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>3.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Expression Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Expression of chimeric truncated t-PA gene is shown in Figure 5(a); a 43 kd protein bond is shown in lane 1 Figure 5(a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>This band is related to chimeric truncated t-PA based on theoretical calculations, 359 amino acid sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The full-length t-PA protein is shown in lane 2, 65 kDa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>This finding was confirmed using antibody against t-PA protein in Western blot analysis, Figure 5(b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Lane 1 and 2 in Figure 5(b) belong to different clones of the chimeric truncated t-PA, and lane 3 is commercially available t-PA, Actylase. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec3.5"><title><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>3.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Electrophoretic Activity Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Using the standard electrophoretic procedure as described in Section 2, the supernatants of cultured media of transfected CHO cells showed enzymatic activity as clear zones of proteolysis against a blue background of undegraded stained gelatin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 6, clear zone for truncated form is similar to what is demonstrated in the positive control well, commercial t-PA medicine. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec3.6"><title><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>3.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Quantitative Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Our utilized affinity purification procedure resulted in more than 80% purified samples (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>For quantitative determination of human tissue plasminogen activator activity in purified supernatant samples of transfected CHO cell, a biofunctional immunosorbent assay was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Based on Biopool's Chromolize t-PA assay kit, amidolytic unit on days 7 and 9 of culture was found to be 540 unit/mL and 752 unit/mL, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>This expression is much higher than what has been shown previously in E. coli, 7 unit/mL [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The estimated specific activity was 566,917 unit/mg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>This activity is comparable to what is reported for full length t-PA: 580,000 unit/mg and truncated form: 575,000 unit/mg. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="subsection" id="sec3.7"><title><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>3.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Fibrin Affinity Assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>As it is illustrated in Figure 7, in 0.2 mg/mL fibrinogen concentration the chimeric truncated protein (GHRP-SYQ-t-PA) showed a fibrin affinity of 38%, compared to full length form with 44%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>In 0.3 mg/mL fibrinogen, chimeric-truncated form had 46% affinity to fibrin compared to full-length form with the value of 53%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Therefore, assuming that the control full-length form has 100% of fibrin affinity, the chimeric-truncated form represented 86% of fibrin affinity of full length protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="section" id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Plasminogen activators (PAs) are used in treating cardiovascular and cerebrovascular obstructions [12, 26–28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Apart from laborious production and refolding process, short plasma half life has complicated full-length t-PA's clinical application [8, 29, 30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Deletion-variants of t-PA such as Lanotaplase and Reteplase are nonglycosylated truncated forms constructed to increase plasma half life [4, 31, 32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>It seems that deletion of these regions could be an advantage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>In addition, presence of GHRP amino acids sounds beneficial for improving fibrin affinity [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Taking advantage of these two factors a chimeric truncated form of t-PA was designed based on in silico analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The analysis showed that the molecule preserves the crucial regions of full length t-PA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>As previously reported the first 3 amino acids of t-PA (SYQ) are important for the protein activity, and we decided to conjugate this part to the K2S (functional domain) the same as what is done in Reteplase (truncated form of t-PA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>This truncated form has proven to be active while SYQ is juxtaposed to K2S domain without any other interfering amino acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>So, we proposed that SYQ-K2S arrangement is responsible for the serine protease activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the aim of this study was to improve some pharmacodynamic properties of an existing truncated t-PA (Reteplase). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>So, in order to compare our proposed form with the previous one we should keep all other parts intact; that is, SYQ-K2S should have been persevered to observe the sole effect of GHRP addition in fibrin-binding affinity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The chimeric GHRP was designed to increase fibrin affinity compared to Reteplase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>We proposed that in order to have better access to fibrin cloths in purpose of improved interaction of the chimeric protein with fibrin cloths it is better to have the chimeric GHRP situated in the N-terminus and not between other residues the same as what is done in Jiao et al.'s article. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Apart from cell line development [33] and synergism strategies [33–35] improving efficacy by protein engineering is greatly promising. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Principal focus of these efforts is eliminating regions to reduce the size of molecule and increase half life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Deleting F, E, and k1 domains reduces both fibrin binding and fibrin enhancement of plasminogen activator [36, 37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>In order to compensate this disadvantage, inserting additional fibrin-binding sites into the molecule enhances specifity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Our chimeric-truncated form showed desirable protein stability based on Ramachandran plot predictions and RSMD values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>In Ramachandran plot analysis, nearly, 1% of the residues, including residues 4 and 5 were found to be in outliner region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Given that the residues 4 and 5 are representing an unnatural, chimeric junction, less than 1% of residues are not modeled well which is favorable compared to similar strategies [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the best RMSD value was the result of superimposing our model on 1BDA template which consists of 300 amino acids; 76% of total protein residues and the active site as well. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The experimental analysis confirmed our in silico analysis findings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Chimeric-truncated t-PA was expressed in CHO DG44 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The level of expression was found to be 752 IU/mL in optimized condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>This level of expression is promising compared to enzymatic activity of produced t-PA in E. coli (3–7 IU/mL) [10], nonmodified rCHO (50 IU/mL) [37], Aspergillus nidulans (0.1 μg/mL) [39], or Leishmania tarentolae (70 IU/mL) [18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Enhancing productivity of cell lines is crucial for reducing costs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Among nonrecombinant mammalian cell producers Bowes melanoma cell line is perhaps the best choice with the productivity more than 30 IU per 106 cells per day (0.1 mg/L conditioned medium) [37, 40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Epithelial cells like guinea pig ear keratocytes (GPK) have yields of production ranged over 5–10 mg/L from perfusion cultures with (7–10)×106 anchored cells per milliliter [37, 40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Between recombinant mammalian cells with inserted copies of human t-PA gene, mouse C127 fibroblasts (with 55 mg/L production rate ), rat myeloma (with 52 mg/L production rate), and CHO cells (with 65 mg/L production rate) in perfused or fed-batch systems are worth mentioning [37, 41]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Considering other recombinant cultures, Saccharomyces cervisiae has a low yield of production with extensive hyper glycosylated and heterogenic forms [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Bacterium Escherchia coli produces t-PA as inclusion bodies consisting 5%–10% of cell proteins [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Because of low recovery of active t-PA from inclusion bodies, bacterial production process does not seem feasible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>In one study, coexpressing of native or heterologous cysteine oxidoreductases increased expression levels to 180 μg/L [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Despite the complexity of renaturation from inclusion bodies [45], E. coli fermentation is far less demanding than animal cell culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, glycosylation is not necessary for biological activity; also nonglycosylated forms show increased plasma half lives, hence, t-PA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Production in bacteria is still desirable and perhaps become feasible either with advances in renaturation methods or with reduction in number of disulfide bonds via protein engineering. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The suggested chimeric-truncated form is promising due to potential of production in prokaryotic systems similar to its nonglycosylated commercial relative, Reteplase. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>We designed our cassette gene by having t-PA signal sequence upstream of chimeric-truncated molecule via SOEing PCR in order to take advantage of proper folding and glycosylation in CHO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Different sizes of templates is a problematic matter in applying SOEing PCR procedure and closer template sizes are preferred in this strategy [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Here, owing to appropriate primer design, two remarkably different sizes of templates, 134 bp and 1089 bp, were successfully sued by using sensible molar ratios of both templates and primers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>In addition, deletion and insertion were performed concurrently. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The protein migrated with an apparent molecular mass of 43 kDa on SDS-PAGE; also, an 86 kDa bond was obvious while western blotting was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>All the dimer form was converted to monomer form by dissolving the protein in 8 M urea, and just one bond at 43 KD was observed on Western Blot (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>These data confirmed that the doubled molecular mass size could be due to aggregation of truncated t-PA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Biological activity was tested with electrophoretic zymography analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown that the main extracellular protease band secreted by the CHO was approximately 92 or 95 KDa [47, 48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>This indicates that the extra higher size bonds are probably from CHO itself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>However, presence of an obvious band of almost 43 KDa and its drastic diminish after inhibition by antibody confirms that the proteolytic activity was exclusively due to t-PA and not other probably existing serine proteases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>As it is shown in Section 3, (lane 5 of Figure 6), significant decline of proteolytic zone in the presence of special t-PA antibody is apparent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The degree of inhibition by antibody is dependent upon the t-PA concentration, but is nevertheless dramatically reduced when compared to the equivalent concentration in samples without antibody [19, 48]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Both fibrin specifity and fibrin affinity are touted as desirable properties in PAs [21, 23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The fibrin-specific agents are much more likely to bind to fibrin bound plasminogen as opposed to free plasminogen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the lack of systemic plasminemia limits systemic fibrinogenolysis, which is associated with bleeding complications [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Reteplase was initially thought to have desired fibrin-specifity [32], but in practice it was less fibrin specific than full-length form [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, higher frequency of bleeding was reported by Reteplase [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Previous studies showed that Reteplase has the in vitro fibrin binding equal to 30% of that of full-length form [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>The fibrin-binding experiment demonstrated that chimeric-truncated t-PA had 86% of fibrin-binding capacity of full-length form, Actylase, suggesting that our novel protein could be targeted to fibrin clot with GHRP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>However, considering controversies now besetting advantages of fibrin affinity, to what extent this increase of fibrin affinity is beneficial for drug is now under investigation in our group for further steps of research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, as the chimeric protein has yet less fibrin affinity than full-length one, it can be said that this degree of increase is not at least pernicious. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>This paper was supported by a grant from the Pasteur Institute of Iran. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>1BoersmaEMercadoNPoldermansDGardienMVosJSimoonsMLAcute myocardial infarctionThe Lancet20033619360847858 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>2BeagleholeRSaracciRPanicoSCardiovascular diseases: causes, surveillance and preventionInternational Journal of Epidemiology2001301S1S411759844 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>3Health system:Improving performanceThe World Health Report2000Geneva, SwitzerlandWorld Health Organiztion </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>4BaruahDBDashRNChaudhariMRKadamSSPlasminogen activators: a comparisonVascular Pharmacology20064411916275118 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>5CamioloSMThorsenSAstrupTFibrinogenolysis and fibrinolysis with tissue plasminogen activator, urokinase, streptokinase-activated human globulin, and plasminProceedings of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine197113812772805125527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>6RijkenDCRelationships between structure and function of tissue-type plasminogen activatorKlinische Wochenschrift198866supplement 1233393126346 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>7KuiperJVan’t HofAOtterMBiessenEALRijkenDCvan BerkelTJCInteraction of mutants of tissue-type plasminogen activator with liver cells: effect of domain deletionsBiochemical Journal199631337757808611154 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>8EmeisJJvan den HoogenCMJenseDHepatic clearance of tissue-type plasminogen activator in ratsThrombosis and Haemostasis19855436616643937264 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>9HotchkissARefinoCJLeonardCKThe influence of carbohydrate structure on the clearance of recombinant tissue-type plasminogen activatorThrombosis and Haemostasis19886022552612851193 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>10PennicaDHolmesWEKohrWJCloning and expression of human tissue-type plasminogen activator cDNA in E. coliNature198330158972142216337343 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>11PhilippeCBiotechnology for cardiovascular diseases2007, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.bioimpact.org">www.bioimpact.org</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>12WeaverWDThe role of thrombolytic drugs in the management of myocardial infarction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Comparative clinical trialsEuropean Heart Journal1996179158960443 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>13BaileyKBettelheimFRLorandLMiddlebrookWRAction of thrombin in the clotting of fibrinogenNature1951167424123323414806439 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>14HasegawaNSasakiSLocation of the binding site “b” for lateral polymerization of fibrinThrombosis Research19905721831952315883 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>15PandyaBVGabrielJLO’BrienJBudzynskiAZPolymerization site in the βchain of fibrin: mapping of the B β 1–55 sequenceBiochemistry19913011621681988018 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>16JiaoJYuMRuBCharacterization of a recombinant chimeric plasminogen activator with enhanced fibrin bindingBiochimica et Biophysica Acta20011546239940511295444 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>17DeleageGRouxBAn algorithm for protein secondary structure prediction based on class predictionProtein Engineering1987142892943508279 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>18SoleimaniMMahboudiFDavoudiNExpression of human tissue plasminogen activator in the trypanosomatid protozoan Leishmania tarentolaeBiotechnology and Applied Biochemistry2007481556117371294 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>19HeussenCDowdleEBElectrophoretic analysis of plasminogen activators in polyacrylamide gels containing sodium dodecyl sulfate and copolymerized substratesAnalytical Biochemistry198010211962027188842 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>20van ZonneveldA-JVeermanHPannekoekHOn the interaction of the finger and the kringle-2 domain of tissue-type plasminogen activator with fibrin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of kringle-2 binding to fibrin by ε-amino caproic acidThe Journal of Biological Chemistry19862613014214142183021732 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>21NesheimMFredenburghJCLarsenGRThe dissociation constants and stoichiometries of the interactions of Lys-plasminogen and chloromethyl ketone derivatives of tissue plasminogen activator and the variant Δ FEIX with intact fibrinThe Journal of Biological Chemistry19902653521541215482123871 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>22HigginsDLVeharGAInteraction of one-chain and two-chain tissue plasminogen activator with intact and plasmin-degraded fibrinBiochemistry19872624778677912962641 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>23Green GeorgeDJpurified type I and type II t-PAUS Patent WO 89/09820, 1989 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>24KohnertURudolphRVerheijenJHBiochemical properties of the kringle 2 and protease domains are maintained in the refolded t-PA deletion variant BM 06.022Protein Engineering199251931001321420 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>25ManosroiJMAMethods for large scale protein production in prokaryotesWO/2002/040696, 2002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>26LevineGNAliMNSchaferAIAntithrombotic therapy in patients with acute coronary syndromesArchives of Internal Medicine2001161793794811295956 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>27OhmanEMHarringtonRACannonCPAgnelliGCairnsJAKennedyJWIntravenous thrombolysis in acute myocardial infarctionChest2001119supplement 1253S277S11157653 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>28RussellDMaddenKPClarkWMZivinJATissue plasminogen activator cerebrovascular thrombolysis in rabbits is dependent on the rate and route of administrationStroke19922333883931542901 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>29TopolECaliffRVan de WerfFAn international randomized trial comparing four thrombolytic strategies for acute myocardial infarctionThe New England Journal of Medicine1993329106736828204123 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>30CollenDTowards improved thrombolytic therapyThe Lancet199334288623436 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>31BhanaNSpencerCMLanoteplaseBioDrugs200013321722418034526 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>32OurielKKatzenBMewissenMReteplase in the treatment of peripheral arterial and venous occlusions: a pilot studyJournal of Vascular and Interventional Radiology200011784985410928520 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>33KlausnerAResearchers probe second generation t-PABiotechnology19864706711 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>34NollGLammleBDuckertFTreatment with stanozolol before thrombolysis in patients with arterial occlusionsThrombosis Research19853745295323983908 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>35PierardLQLSpierREGriffithsJBStephenneJCrooyPJSecretion of recombinant hybrid plasminogen activator by mouse myeloma cellsAdvances in Animal Cell Biology and Technology for Bioprocesses1989London, UKButterworths475480 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>36CartwrightTSpierREGriffithsJBStephenneJCrooyPJProduction of t-PA from animal cell cultureAnimal Cell Biotechnology1992New York, NY, USAAcademic Press217245 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>37RoufSAMoo-YoungMChistiYTissue-type plasminogen activator: characteristics, applications and production technologyBiotechnology Advances199614323926614537155 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>38BagchiPMaheshMSomashekharRPharmaco-informatics: homology modelling of the target protein (GP1, 2) for Ebola hemorrhagic fever and predicting an Ayurvedic remediation of the diseaseJournal of Proteomics and Bioinformatics200927287294 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>39UpshallAKumarAABaileyMCSecretion of active human tissue plasminogen activator from the filamentous fungus Aspergillus nidulansBio/Technology198751213011304 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>40DatarRVCartwrightTRosenC-GProcess economics of animal cell and bacterial fermentations: a case study analysis of tissue plasminogen activatorNature Biotechnology1993113349357 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>41LubinieckiAArathoonRPolastriGSpierREGriffithsJBStephenneJCrooyPJSelected strategies for manufacture and control of recombinant tissue plasminogen activator prepared from cell cultureAdvances in Animal Cell Biology and Technology for Bioprocesses1990London, UKButterworths442451 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>42LemonttJFWeiCMDackowskiWRExpression of active human uterine tissue plasminogen activator in yeastDNA1985464194283937715 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>43GriffithsJBElectricwalaAProduction of tissue plasminogen activators from animal cellsAdvances in Biochemical Engineering198734147166 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>44ManosroiJTayapiwatanaCGötzFWernerRGManosroiASecretion of active recombinant human tissue plasminogen activator derivatives in Escherichia coliApplied and Environmental Microbiology20016762657266411375177 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>45ChistiYMoo-YoungMSeparation techniques in industrial bioprocessingJournal Institution of Chemical Engineers Symposium Series1994137135146 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>46LiXQiuYShenYSplicing together different regions of a gene by modified polymerase chain reaction-based site-directed mutagenesisAnalytical Biochemistry2008373239840018022376 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>47ElliottPHohmannASpanosJProtease expression in the supernatant of Chinese Hamster Ovary cells grown in serum-free cultureBiotechnology Letters200325221949195214719832 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>48OpdenakkerGMMProtease inhibitors, a DNA construct for the expression of a protease and a process for measuring proteases and/or protease inhibitors, EP0736302, 1996 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Schematic overview of primer designed for SOEing PCR process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JBB2010-108159.001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Cartoon Ribbon display in VMD 1.8.7 program for two different views of GHRP-SYQ-K2S modeled with MODELLER 9V1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>(a) Left back view for a ribbon model of GHRP-SYQ-K2S modeled with MODELLER 9V1 automodel package (chimeric part shown in orange). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>(b) Left bottom view for a ribbon model of GHRP-SYQ-K2S modeled with MODELLER 9V1 automodel package; purple: alpha helix, blue: 3_10 helix, yellow: extended beta, tan: bridge beta, cyan: turn, and white: coil. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JBB2010-108159.002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Gel-electrophoresis analysis of PCR-products of chimeric truncated t-PA on 1% agarose gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Lane 1: 134 bp forward PCR product; signal sequence + GHRP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Lane 3: 1089 bp Reverse PCR product; GHRP-SYQ-K2S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Lane 4: 1223 bp full-length SOEn PCR product signal sequence + GHRP-SYQ-K2S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Lane 2&amp;5: 1 kb ladder. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JBB2010-108159.003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Gel-electrophoresis analysis of PCR products performed on stable transfected CHO cells and control cell line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Lane 1: PCR product from nontransfected CHO genomic DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Lane 2: PCR product from transfected CHO genomic DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Lane 3: PCR product from another transfected CHO genomic DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Lane 4: 1 kb ladder </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JBB2010-108159.004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>(a) SDS-PAGE analysis from supernatant of transfected CHO cells, 12% gel-coumasei blue stained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Right line: truncated t-PA CHO cell culture medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Middle line: full length t-PA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Left line: protein marker. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>(b) Western Blot analysis from supernatant of transfected CHO cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Lane 1&amp;2: chimeric truncated t-PA CHO cell culture medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Lane 3: full length t-PA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JBB2010-108159.005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Identification of plasminogen activators and proteases in 11% polyacrylamide gel containing gelatin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>The gel contains 11% polyacrylamide, 0.1% SDS, 0.1% copolymerized gelatin and 13 μg/ml plasminogen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Samples were electrophoresed at a constant current of 8 mA in 4°C temperature as follows: Lane3 Reference protein mixture lane 1: Actylase (full length t-PA), lane 2: Actylase +polyclonal anti-t-PA rabbit antibody, lane 4: negative control, lane 6: transfected CHO cells supernatant, lane 5: transfected CHO cells supernatant+anti-t-PA antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>After electrophoresis the gels were washed in Triton X-100, incubated in glycine-NaOH buffer at 37°C for 3 h and fixed, stained, and destained as described under Method. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JBB2010-108159.006"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Binding to fibrin clots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Different concentrations of fibrin were incubated with full length (♦) or chimeric-truncated t-PA (∗) Data represent means obtained from three experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JBB2010-108159.007"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
