
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2579334</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18997871</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">08-PONE-RA-04464R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003686</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Critical Care and Emergency Medicine</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Bioinformatics</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Comparative Genomics</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Disease Models</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Functional Genomics</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Gene Expression</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Genomics</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Physiogenomics</subject><subject>Physiology/Genomics</subject><subject>Critical Care and Emergency Medicine/Sepsis and Multiple Organ Failure</subject><subject>Nutrition/Malnutrition</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Dysregulation of Mitochondrial Dynamics and the Muscle Transcriptome in ICU Patients Suffering from Sepsis Induced Multiple Organ Failure </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Mechanisms of Muscle Wasting</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fredriksson</surname><given-names>Katarina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tjäder</surname><given-names>Inga</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>Pernille</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Petrovic</surname><given-names>Natasa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ahlman</surname><given-names>Bo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schéele</surname><given-names>Camilla</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wernerman</surname><given-names>Jan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Timmons</surname><given-names>James A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rooyackers</surname><given-names>Olav</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Anesthesiology and Intensive Care, Karolinska Institute, Karolinska University Hospital, Stockholm, Sweden</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Translational Biomedicine, Heriot-Watt University, Edinburgh, Scotland, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Surgery, CLINTEC, Karolinska Institute, Ersta hospital, Stockholm, Sweden</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>The Wenner-Gren Institute, The Arrhenius Laboratories, Stockholm University, Stockholm, Sweden</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bozza</surname><given-names>Patricia</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Instituto Oswaldo Cruz and FIOCRUZ, Brazil</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>olav.rooyackers@ki.se</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: KF IT JW OR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: KF IT PK NP BA CS JW JAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: KF IT PK NP CS JW JAT OR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: NP BA JW JAT OR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: KF IT PK NP BA CS JW JAT OR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e3686</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>4</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Fredriksson et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Septic patients treated in the intensive care unit (ICU) often develop multiple organ failure including persistent skeletal muscle dysfunction which results in the patient's protracted recovery process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>We have demonstrated that muscle mitochondrial enzyme activities are impaired in septic ICU patients impairing cellular energy balance, which will interfere with muscle function and metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Here we use detailed phenotyping and genomics to elucidate mechanisms leading to these impairments and the molecular consequences. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Methodology/Principal Findings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Utilising biopsy material from seventeen patients and ten age-matched controls we demonstrate that neither mitochondrial in vivo protein synthesis nor expression of mitochondrial genes are compromised. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Indeed, there was partial activation of the mitochondrial biogenesis pathway involving NRF2α/GABP and its target genes TFAM, TFB1M and TFB2M yet clearly this failed to maintain mitochondrial function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>We therefore utilised transcript profiling and pathway analysis of ICU patient skeletal muscle to generate insight into the molecular defects driving loss of muscle function and metabolic homeostasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Gene ontology analysis of Affymetrix analysis demonstrated substantial loss of muscle specific genes, a global oxidative stress response related to most probably cytokine signalling, altered insulin related signalling and a substantial overlap between patients and muscle wasting/inflammatory animal models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>MicroRNA 21 processing appeared defective suggesting that post-transcriptional protein synthesis regulation is altered by disruption of tissue microRNA expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Finally, we were able to demonstrate that the phenotype of skeletal muscle in ICU patients is not merely one of inactivity, it appears to be an actively remodelling tissue, influenced by several mediators, all of which may be open to manipulation with the aim to improve clinical outcome. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Conclusions/Significance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>This first combined protein and transcriptome based analysis of human skeletal muscle obtained from septic patients demonstrated that losses of mitochondria and muscle mass are accompanied by sustained protein synthesis (anabolic process) while dysregulation of transcription programmes appears to fail to compensate for increased damage and proteolysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Our analysis identified both validated and novel clinically tractable targets to manipulate these failing processes and pursuit of these could lead to new potential treatments. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Yearly about 750,000 people develop severe sepsis in the USA and probably the same amount in Europe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Total mortality for these patients is about 30–35%, however for those patients with persistent sepsis mortality is &gt;50%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Most patients with persistent sepsis develop multiple organ failure, a syndrome in which several organ systems are malfunctioning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In order for these patients to survive their vital organs need to be supported in the hospitals intensive care unit (ICU). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Septic patients treated in the intensive care unit develop skeletal muscle dysfunction which is part of the multiple organ failure syndrome, and this persists after ICU discharge [1], [2], [3], [4], [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The nature of this muscle dysfunction includes weakness due to a severe loss of muscle mass and muscle fatigue which is most apparent during weaning of the mechanical ventilation and results in impaired physical capacity during the patient's protracted recovery process [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In addition to the long term failure of skeletal muscle function, rapid degeneration in the ICU also impacts on patient acute energy metabolism and this directs the need for concurrent interventions, such as insulin and glucocorticoid therapy, which are principally aimed at improving patient survival [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In a previous study [8] we demonstrated that mitochondrial content was 30–40% lower and cellular adenine nucleotide homeostasis disrupted (lower ATP and creatine phosphate concentrations) in skeletal muscle of ICU patients suffering from sepsis induced multiple organ failure (MOF). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Mitochondria are the major mechanism for ATP generation in humans and the observed lower mitochondrial content and cellular energy status will accelerate muscle fatigue and possibly cell death in these septic patients [9], [10], [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Indeed, mitochondrial derangements and the subsequent disruption in energy metabolism are associated with multiple organ failure and an increased mortality in critically ill patients [12], [13], [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In addition, several animal models of sepsis and critical illness have shown mitochondrial derangements in skeletal muscle and other tissues [11], [15], [16], [17], [18] confirming the generality of these observations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Skeletal muscle phenotype and mitochondrial content depend on the coordinated expression of nuclear and mitochondrial encoded genes, as well as the synthesis and degradation of proteins to maintain normal muscle function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial protein synthesis and degradation have to be in equilibrium in order for the cell to maintain a constant number of well functioning mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In this study we hypothesize that the lower mitochondrial content, we found in skeletal muscle of septic patients, is caused by a lower mitochondrial protein synthesis and this would be regulated by lower mitochondrial gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Thus, we examined in vivo mitochondrial protein synthesis in skeletal muscle of patients treated in the ICU for sepsis induced MOF and compared this to age matched control subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Targeted analysis of gene expression of mitochondrial oxidative phosphorylation (OXPHOS) enzymes (both nuclear and mitochondrial encoded), mitochondrial proteases and master transcriptional regulators of mitochondrial biogenesis presented us with a complex picture, where selective transcriptional activation of mitochondrial biogenesis was clearly evident. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Finding clear evidence for disrupted coordination of mitochondrial gene expression led us to carryout a global analysis of skeletal muscle phenotype using microarray technology to determine the extent of altered muscle phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Informatic analysis yielded profound evidence for degeneration and loss of muscle specific genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Subjects </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Seventeen patients admitted to the general Intensive Care Unit (ICU) at Karolinska University Hospital Huddinge were included in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The same ICU patients were also included in another study [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Patients were septic according to the Bone criteria [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Patients younger than 18 years of age, patients with severe liver failure, undergoing dialysis, and patients with impaired coagulation were excluded from the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>As a control group 10 patients undergoing elective surgery at Ersta Hospital (Stockholm) were included. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>All patients or close relatives gave informed consent to participate in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The study protocol conformed to the ethical guidelines of the 1975 declaration of Helsinki and had received an a priori approval by the Ethical committee of Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden and local ethics approval for gene expression analysis at Heriot-Watt University, Edinburgh, Scotland. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Study protocol </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>In order to determine the mitochondrial protein synthesis rates an intravenous bolus injection of L- [2H5] phenylalanine was given to the patients over a period of 10 minutes (45 mg×kg−1 body weight, 10 atom% excess (APE)) [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Blood samples were taken before (time 0) and at 5, 10, 15, 30, 50,70 and 90 minutes after the phenylalanine injection for determination of the L- [2H5] phenylalanine enrichment in plasma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Muscle biopsies were obtained from the lateral portion of the vastus lateralis muscle, 10–20 cm above the knee, at 90 and 92 minutes after the bolus injection on the left and right leg respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The biopsies were obtained using a Bergström biopsy needle after local anaesthesia in the ICU patients and just after sedation in the control patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The biopsies were divided into smaller portions, frozen into liquid nitrogen and stored at −80°C until analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The muscle biopsies were analyzed for in vivo mitochondrial protein synthesis rate, mitochondrial enzyme activities (citrate synthase and complex I and IV of the mitochondrial respiratory chain) and a marker of oxidative stress capacity (Superoxide dismutase (SOD)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>In addition, mRNA levels were measured using real time qPCR and Affymetrix micro-array analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>From our previous study it is clear that the between-patient variation of the mitochondrial enzyme measurements is high, therefore measurements in the present study were carried out in both legs to further examine this issue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>For the mRNA analyses limited material was available and therefore only one leg was studied in 24 patients (16 septic and 8 controls) for the qPCR and 21 patients (13 septic and 8 controls) for the micro-array analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Measurements of enzyme activities </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Muscle samples were homogenized in a KCL buffer (100 mM KCl, 50 mM Tris/HCl, 5 mM MgCl2, 1.8 mM ATP and 1 mM EDTA) to obtain a 5% homogenate [8], [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Part of the homogenate was stored frozen at −80°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The remaining homogenate was used to isolate mitochondria by subsequent centrifugations [8], [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The mitochondrial pellet intended for enzyme activity measurements was suspended in SET buffer (0.25 M sucrose, 2 mM EDTA, 10 mM Tris, pH 7.4) and stored frozen until analysis at −80°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Activities of citrate synthase, mitochondrial respiratory chain complexes I and IV and superoxide dismutase (SOD) were analyzed in both total homogenate and isolated mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>All assays were spectrophotometric and performed on a Konelab 20 Analyzer (Thermo electron corporation, USA) at 37°C as described previously [8], [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>SOD activity was analysed using a Ransod kit (Randox Laboratories Ltd, UK). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial protein synthesis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Mitochondria were isolated as described above, but the mitochondrial pellet were dissolved and washed twice with 4% sulfosalicylic acid (SSA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The pellets were subsequently dissolved in 0.3 M NaOH and the protein concentrations of the samples were determined using a DC-protein assay kit (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The proteins were then precipitated and washed twice in 4% (w/v) SSA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The remaining pellets were hydrolyzed at 110°C for 24 hours in 6 M HCl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>After cooling, the samples were dried by vacuum centrifugation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The dried samples were prepared for gas chromatography-mass spectrometry analysis as described previously [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The dried protein hydrolysates were dissolved in 220 µl of 0.5 M sodium citrate buffer (pH 6.3) and filtered through a 0.22 µm centrifugal tube. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Phenylalanine standards containing 0–0.114 APE (atom percent excess) were dissolved in the same amount of the sodium citrate buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Samples and standards were decarboxylated in L-tyrosine decarboxylase to convert phenylalanine into phenylethylamine at 50°C over night. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, 100 µl of 6 M NaOH was added and after centrifugation at 16,000×g, the samples were extracted in ether and then in 0.1 M HCl and dried. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The samples were derivatized in 25 µl MTBSTFA [N-methyl-N-(t-butyldimethylsilyl)trifluoroacetamide]/ethyl acetate(1/1, v/v) at 60°C for 1 hour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The ratio of [2H5]-phenylethylamine and phenylethylamine was determined by GC-MS (Agilent 5973n; Agilent technologies, Stockholm, Sweden). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Ions m/z 180 (m+2) and m/z 183 (m+5) were analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Plasma free phenylalanine was prepared and analyzed by GC-MS as described previously [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The enrichment of [2H5]-phenylalanine in plasma was determined by monitoring the ions m/z 336 and 341. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The enrichment of protein-bound [2H5] phenylalanine was calculated from the ratio of m+5/m+2 using the standard curves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The protein synthesis rate was calculated as:Where FSR is the fractional protein synthesis rate, Ep is the protein-bound enrichment of [2H5] phenylalanine (APE), A is the area under the curve for [2H5] phenylalanine enrichment (APE) in plasma over time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real-time PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The transcript levels of several mitochondrial protein subunits encoded by either nuclear or mitochondrial DNA were measured by real-time (RT)-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The nuclear encoded subunits of mitochondrial enzymes citrate synthase (CS var1 and 2), complex IV (COXIV) and succinate dehydrogenase (SDHA) were measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>For the mitochondrial-encoded genes, subunits of complex I (mtND4, mtND6) and complex IV (mtCO1) and cytochrome B (mtCYB) were measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>In addition, transcription factors NRF-1 and NRF-2α/GABP as well as coactivators PGC-1α and -1β were quantified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>These transcriptional regulators control the expression of nuclear encoded mitochondrial proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>To further examine factors which directly regulate mtDNA encoded genes, we determined TFAM, TFB1M and TFB2M expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>In addition, given our previous data, we quantified several mitochondrial protease genes, two that are part of the AAA proteases family and located in the inner membrane of the mitochondria (YME1L1 and SPG7/paraplegin) and two located in the mitochondrial matrix (LON and CLPP). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was isolated from muscle samples using TRIzol (Invitrogen, Stockholm, Sweden) and quantified using a Nano-drop spectrophotometer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>cDNA was prepared from 1 µg of RNA using random hexamer primers and reverse transcription reagents (Applied biosystems) in a final volume of 40 µl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Gene expression was quantified in triplicates as previously described [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Oligonucleotide primers were designed using a primer design centre (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.probelibrary.com/">http://www.probelibrary.com/</ext-link>) and synthesized by Invitrogen (Stockholm, Sweden). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>To avoid amplification of nuclear DNA the primers were designed to amplify across exon-exon boundaries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial DNA contamination can not be excluded using this procedure and a ‘contamination test’ was therefore performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was utilized instead of cDNA using primers towards a mitochondrial-encoded gene (MTCO1) and the resulting amplification plot was used to indicate the amount of mtDNA contamination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The mtDNA contamination was negligible (less than 3%) and thus had no impact on the analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The delta CT (cycle threshold) values, calculated based on correction to 18sRNA, were calculated for each sample and statistical analysis was applied to this raw data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The linear value of each patient was then compared to the mean of all the control values to get an estimate of the mean increase/decrease and the variation between the samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Affymetrix Microarray </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Hybridization, washing, staining and scanning of the arrays were performed according to manufacturer's instructions (Affymetrix, Inc. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.affymetrix.com/">http://www.affymetrix.com/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The Array design can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.affymetrix.com">https://www.affymetrix.com</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>We utilized the Affymetrix U133+2 array platform with RNA preparations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Data presented in the paper was quality controlled using the Microarray Suite software (MAS 5.0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>All array data were normalized through implementations of the MAS5 algorithm, to a global scaling intensity of 100. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>As a mean to control the quality of the individual arrays, all arrays were examined using hierarchical clustering to identify outliers prior to statistical analysis in addition to the standard quality assessments including scaling factors and housekeeper 5′/3′ ratios. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>No array failed these standard quality assessment procedures although patient 9 was a clear ‘outlier’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, patient 9 did not influence the global gene expression analysis, while for the qPCr analysis (using a separate RNA/Analysis technology) patient 9 did demonstrate the highest expression value for NRF2 (See results) indicating that this patient's gene expression status was genuinely altered to a much greater extent. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Array analysis strategies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>We have previously demonstrated that it can be difficult to predict the impact of applying arbitrary filtering criteria prior to statistical analysis [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>We therefore relied on several statistical models to present, analyze and interpret our data with and without arbitrary pre-filtering of gene lists. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The microarray data was subjected to global normalization using the Robust Multi-Array Average expression measure (RMA) Bioconductor (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioconductor.org">www.bioconductor.org</ext-link>) and the output compared with MAS5.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>On this occasion 90% of RMA identified genes were found in the MAS5 data set while analysis of the smaller RMA data set provided a very similar result (in terms of Gene ontology analysis of differentially expressed genes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Thus, we used MAS5.0 for the remaining analysis as the point of array analysis is to generate a large yet robust data set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>There is some argument that using the MAS5.0 generated present-absent calls can improve the sensitivity of the differential gene expression analysis [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>We chose to remove probe sets where they were declared ‘absent’ across all chips. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The normalized log2-file was analyzed with the Significance Analysis of Microarray (SAM) in R (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www-stat.stanford.edu/~tibs/SAM/">http://www-stat.stanford.edu/~tibs/SAM/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>SAM provides a list of “significant” genes and attempts to estimate of the false discovery rate (FDR), which represents the percentage of genes that could be identified by chance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>SAM assign a score to each gene/probe set as an index of relative difference between groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>For the data presented in the manuscript, genes were considered significantly changed in ICU patients, when a delta value corresponding to the number of false significant genes of 5% (q-value), and an average fold change of 2, was achieved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>For the pathway analysis a stricter statistical cut-off was utilized (1% FDR), while presented pathways were colored by 1.5 FC and 5% FDR so that the robust trends within pathways could be visualized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Finally, due to lack of sufficient RNA please note we did not profile the two patients with the very high protein synthesis rates on Affymetrix arrays and thus these patients did not drive nor inform the array analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>We used the web-based bioinformatics tool, Ingenuity pathway analysis (IPA, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ingenuity.com">http://www.ingenuity.com</ext-link>), which is based on &gt;1.7 Million published articles, to discover networks regulated in the skeletal muscle of ICU patients, compared with age matched controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>IPA is a knowledge database generated from the peer-reviewed scientific publications that enables discovery of biological networks in gene expression data, determining the functions most significant to those networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Gene name identifiers or Affymetrix probe set ID's were uploaded into IPA and queried against all other genes stored in the IPA knowledge database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Each Affymetrix probe set ID was mapped to its corresponding gene identifier in the IPA knowledge database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Probe sets representing genes having direct interactions with genes in the IPA knowledge database are called “focus” genes, which were then used as a starting point for generating functional networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Each generated network is assigned a score according to the number of differentially regulated focus genes in our dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>These scores are derived from negative logarithm of the P indicative of the likelihood that focus genes found together in a network due to random chance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Scores of 14 or higher have 99.9% confidence level of significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>In reporting our findings we focus on networks with a substantially higher confidence limit and thus represent strong evidence for a given biological pathway being activated in ICU patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>It should be noted however that while the database extends the interpretation beyond mRNA transcript levels (as network genes don't have to be differentially expressed at the mRNA level) the database is finite and reflects current knowledge. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Detection of microRNA hsa-mir-21 expression by using real-time PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>MicroRNA expression was analysed using the Taqman® MicroRNA assays developed by Applied Biosystems that detects mature miRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>A microRNA-specific looped primer is used for the reverse transcription, thus extending the microRNA sequence enabling detection with Taqman® real-time PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Samples were analysed for the expression of hsa-mir-21 (4373090, Applied Biosystems) and the endogenous reference, RNU48 (4373383, Applied Biosystems), which is a small nuclear RNA (which we have found to be stable in human muscle through comparison with 18s). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Ten ng of total RNA was reverse transcribed using the TaqMan® MicroRNA Reverse Transcription Kit (Applied Biosystems, PN 4366597) according to instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>In short, a mastermix was prepared resulting in a final concentration in a 15-µl volume of 1 mM dNTP, 50 U MuLV Multiscribe reverse transcriptase, 1× reverse transcription buffer and 3.8 U RNase Inhibitor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>RNA was added, and aliquots made followed by addition of the microRNA-specific reverse transcription looped primer to a final concentration of 1× RT-primer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The reactions were gently mixed and briefly spun down and run in a PTC-100™(MJ Research Inc.) with conditions at 16°C for 30 min, 42°C for 30 min, and 85°C for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>For the real-time PCR, the TaqMan® 2× Universal PCR Master Mix, No AmpErase® UNG was used (Applied Biosystems, PN 4324020). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The samples were run on a 7900HT Fast Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems) on the 9600 emulation mode in triplicates of 20 µl per well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Real-time PCR conditions were; 95°C for 10 minutes followed by 50 cycles of 95°C for 15 sec and 60°C for 1 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>All reactions were run singleplex and analysed and quantified using the ΔΔCt method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Data are expressed as fold change from controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>miRNA target prediction and Gene Ontology Class </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The binding of the miRNA to the target mRNA occurs in the “seed” region of the miRNA, representing nt 2–7 of the 5′end of the mature miRNA and the 3′ untranslated region (UTR) of the mRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>We used Gene Ontology analysis to obtain an overview of the main classes of biological functions of genes predicted to be targets for miRNA-21 and thus we are able to apply a degree of statistical rigor beyond predicted target lists only. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>For miRNA target prediction categorized by Gene Ontology, we used EASE (Version 2 with updated annotation files, 2006) and a miRNA target gene list (representing target genes conserved across murine and human genes) developed based on Ensemble and miRNA sequences obtained from the Sanger Institute (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://microrna.sanger.ac.uk/sequences/">http://microrna.sanger.ac.uk/sequences/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>EASE analysis predicts biological functions of target genes for the miRNA of interest and enlists a false discovery rate (FDR) and an EASE score, which we calculated using 500 permutations/iterations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>For prediction of miRNA-21 target sites we used Targetscan (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.targetscan.org/">http://www.targetscan.org/</ext-link>, release 4.0). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Statistics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Most measurements were normally distributed according to the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test (Statistica, Softstat, Tulso, OK, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Since not all parameters were normally distributed we analysed all data (except the micro-array data) both using the Student's t-test and Mann-Whitney U-test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Data are presented as means and standard deviation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis for the micro-array is described in detail above. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Included patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>ICU patient characteristics are given in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Despite their initial diagnosis all included patients were diagnosed with severe sepsis/septic shock [20] sometime during their disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>At the time of the biopsy, all patients were circulatory stable and not suffering from severe sepsis/septic shock. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>At the time of biopsy all patients were considered to suffer from multiple organ failure, although three patients had SOFA score below 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>All but one patient received intravenous insulin (20–260 IE per day of Actrapid, Novo Nordisk) to control hyperglycemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Glucose levels were between 3 and 12 mM on the day of the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>As controls, 1 woman and 9 men were included, the median age was 70 (range 48–76) and median body mass index (BMI) was 27.4 kg×m−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The control subjects underwent elective surgery for either gallbladder disease or inguinal hernia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0003686-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003686.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Patient characteristics. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0003686-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0003686.t001"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>SOFA; Sequential Organ Failure Assessment score, AMI; Acute Myocardial Infarction; COPD; Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disorder, PN; parenteral nutrition, EN; Enteral nutrition, S; Survivor, D, death, d; day, surg; surgery * Days spent in the ICU at the time of muscle biopsy ** APACHE II score at admission to the ICU*** Nutrition was given at 20–25 kcal/kg/day including supplementation of glutamine. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Muscle mitochondrial enzyme activities are decreased with sepsis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>There were no significant differences between left and right legs in any of the enzyme and in vivo protein synthesis analyses such that all results are presented as the mean value obtained from two muscle biopsies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The activity of citrate synthase was 25% lower in the septic patients as compared to the controls (p = 0.0003; t-test) (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial respiratory chain complexes I and IV were respectively 49% and 33% lower in the patients when expressed per muscle weight (complex I p = 0.0002, complex IV p = 0.0003; t-test) (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>However, no statistically significant difference was observed when expressed per citrate synthase activity (p = 0.10 and 0.13 respectively; t-test) suggesting that it was the total mitochondrial content that had declined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>In isolated mitochondria, the activity of complex I was not statistically significantly different between controls and patients (p = 0.11; t-test), while intriguingly the activity of complex IV was 60% greater in the patients (p = 0.0003; t-test) (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Superoxide dismutase activity in muscle homogenate was not different between the patients and the controls (p = 0.79; t-test), yet the activity in isolated mitochondria was 100% higher in the patients (p = 0.011; t-test) (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>We carried out protein and gene expression analysis to investigate the cause of these alterations in enzyme capacity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0003686-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003686.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Enzyme activities. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0003686-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0003686.t002"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Mean and standard deviation of mitochondrial enzyme activity measurements in leg muscle from ICU patients with sepsis induced multiple organ failure. * p&lt;0.05 (both for Student's t-test and Mann Whitney U-test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>ICU intensive care unit patient, ww wet weight, CS citrate synthase, SOD superoxide dismutase </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The decreased mitochondrial function is not due to a decreased in vivo protein synthesis rate </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The amount of mitochondrial protein and therefore muscle mitochondrial content is the balance between mitochondrial synthesis and breakdown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>To establish whether the decreased mitochondrial function in muscle of septic patients is due to a decreased synthesis of mitochondrial proteins, in vivo protein synthesis rates of mitochondrial protein was determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>No significant difference in mitochondrial protein synthesis was obtained between the patients and controls (p = 0.35; t-test) (Figure 1A) albeit the patients did demonstrate a greater variability in synthesis rates, where some appeared to have a substantially elevated fractional synthesis rate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0003686-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003686.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Protein synthesis and gene expression of mitochondria in muscle of septic and age-matched control subjects. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>In vivo fractional synthesis rate (FSR) of mitochondrial protein in skeletal muscle from ICU patients with sepsis induced multiple organ failure and age-matched control subjects are expressed in %/day (top left panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Each dot represents one patient and the bar represents the mean value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>mRNA level of subunits of nuclear and mitochondrial encoded enzymes (top right panel), transcription factors controlling expression of nuclear encoded proteins (lower left panel) and transcription factors regulating the transcription of mitochondrial DNA (lower right panel) in skeletal muscle of septic patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The changes in mRNA levels are expressed in percent of controls (n = 8) and are presented as mean and standard deviation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The genes marked with mt are mitochondrial encoded. *p&lt;0.05 (both for Student's t-test and Mann-Whitney U-test). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0003686.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>The decreased mitochondrial function may reflect incomplete mitochondrial biogenesis and increased expression of mitochondrial protease genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>To specifically address whether transcriptional activation of mitochondrial related genes was suppressed we utilised real time qPCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>None of the mitochondrial and nuclear genes, encoding for mitochondrial related enzymes were significantly different between patients and controls (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Further, while there was greater variation for the mtDNA-encoded genes than for the nuclear encoded oxidative phosphorylation (OXPHOS) genes the tendency was for up regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Assembly of mitochondria networks involves hundreds of gene products and while OXPHOS related mRNA expression may have been stable in patients, disruption of regulators of mitochondrial organelle/network formation could also result in loss of function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, the proposed master regulators of mitochondrial biogenesis; NRF1, PGC1α and PGC1β were unchanged, however NRF2α/GABP expression was 67% higher in the septic patients (p = 0.0163; t-test) (Figure 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Convincingly, the mtDNA regulating factors TFAM, TFB1M and TFB2M were all increased significantly (by 109, 108 and 72% respectively) and these nuclear encoded genes are regulated by NRF2α/GABP (Figure 1D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Thus while we clearly demonstrated decreased mitochondrial enzyme activities, this was not due to lack of mRNA coding for OXPHOS proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Rather, increased expression of several of the transcriptional regulators of biogenesis suggests that there was a clear yet partially effective stimulus for mitochondrial biogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>This did not, however, result in an increased synthesis of mitochondria but rather only selective activation of NRF2α/GABP and NRF2α/GABP target genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>However, the ICU patients were treated with insulin therapy to overcome hyperglycemia [7] and experimental hyperinsulinaemia has been shown to increase the expression of some oxidative phosphorylation genes [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>It therefore occurred to us that the insulin therapy may be responsible for alterations in NRF2α/GABP and that such changes were not specific to MOF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>We analysed the response of NRF2α/GABP to exogenous insulin in vivo in humans and using a muscle cell line model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>First we examined the expression of NRF2α/GABP in the C2C12 muscle cell line, exposed to supra-physiological levels of insulin and we could not detect any induction of NRF2α/GABP expression or its target genes TFB1M and TFB2M (Supplemental Figure S1), suggesting that increased NRF2α/GABP and NRF2α/GABP target gene expression in the ICU patients was not a consequence of the insulin therapy but rather some more specific response to altered mitochondrial function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>We also observed a reduction in PGC1α mRNA in insulin treated C2C12 cells, consistent with the in vivo study by Southgate et al [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>In addition, to verify that insulin would not increase NRF2α/GABP in vivo we utilised RNA derived from a previously published [29] hyperinsulineamia clamp study in healthy volunteers (5 hrs, 149.2+/−6.9 mIU×l−1) and we found that NRF2α/GABP and PGC1α mRNA expression was unaltered compared with control (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>It appears unlikely that the robust activation of NRF2α/GABP and target genes in ICU patients reflects the insulin therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Connectivity analysis was carried out using NRF2α (GABPA and GABPB) and Affymetrix data (See below) further illustrates the response of some NRF2α/GABP related genes (Supplemental Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>We also evaluated if mitochondrial located proteases were activated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Genes encoding for the mitochondrial proteases LON and CLPP demonstrated an increase in the patients compared to controls of 48 and 39% respectively (P = 0.0029 and 0.0166 respectively; t-test) while the AAA metalloprotease subunits paraplegin (SPG7) and YME1L1 genes did not differ between the patients and controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>These results support the idea that in muscle of patients with sepsis, deregulated mitochondrial biogenesis may promote mitochondrial proteases expression to cope with failure in coordinated protein formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>However, the substantial loss of skeletal muscle mitochondrial content appears disproportionate compared with the global yet incomplete activation of biogenesis (See below) and thus it was important to identify the molecular signals coordinating these gross alterations in muscle phenotype. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Affymetrix analysis of ICU patient skeletal muscle shows a large number of genes that are differentially expressed, with the majority up regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>To establish a more global analysis of muscle phenotype we subjected the muscle samples to Affymetrix gene array analysis followed by our comparative array analysis strategy [30], [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The data discussed in this publication have been deposited in NCBI's Gene Expression Omnibus and are accessible through GEO Series accession number GSE13205 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?accGSE13205">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?accGSE13205</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The micro-array analyses were initially used to obtain a more global picture of the mitochondrial genes in skeletal muscle during sepsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>In addition, this allowed us to generate a detailed picture of ICU patient muscle status and also facilitated a direct comparison with various animal models which have been developed to study muscle wasting and inflammation [32], [33] to aid future drug discovery efforts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>This later analysis allows us to infer associations between changes in patient muscle with specific programmes activated by muscle wasting or muscle disuse - data that would otherwise not be possible to generate, given the critical status of such individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>This enormously valuable analysis should also help further validate these animal models for drug target validation purposes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>We found that 2080 probe sets (corresponding to 1457 unique genes/identifiers) were up-regulated in ICU patients, compared with control subjects (&gt;2 fold change with a 5% FDR (Supplemental data sheet S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>We found fewer down regulated genes, with 783 significant probe sets representing 525 unique genes/identifiers (&gt;2 fold change with a 5% FDR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Examination of the Affymetrix expression data allowed us to take a more global view on the regulation of mitochondrial gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>From a list of 342 genes annotated as being ‘mitochondrial’ on the U133+2 micro-array chip, expression of 82 genes were regulated in muscle of the septic patients (Supplemental data sheet S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Of these 82 genes, only 8 were down regulated and remarkably 74 were up regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>From the down regulated genes only one was a specific component of the OXPHOS machinery (NADH dehydrogenase 1 subunit C1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Within the up regulated genes, the largest change observed was for the mitochondrial superoxide dismutase gene, with a 16-fold increased expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>This result is remarkably consistent with the increased activity of the mitochondrial superoxide dismutase protein activity (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Thus analysis of the mitochondrial gene responses, as detected using the Affymetrix platform, strongly supports our conclusion that activation of many but not all mitochondrial genes occurred; a potentially adaptive, yet clearly ineffective, reponse at maintaining mitochondrial capacity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3f"><title><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Gene ontology analysis of Affymetrix analysis identifies broad molecular programmes activated in ICU patient skeletal muscle </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>To capture a broad assessment of the molecular processes represented by the ∼2000 modulated genes, we utilised gene ontology (GO) analysis [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>We found that regulation of apoptosis, proteosome function, ion homeostasis and kinase signalling were modulated and these appeared to us as rather predictable findings (Supplemental data sheet S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Gene ontology analysis of the down regulated list indicated that there was a dramatic loss of unique muscle related gene expression demonstrating that the patient muscle tissue was undergoing a de-differentiation process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Down regulated genes also indicated a loss of expression of numerous extracellular matrix gene ontology groups, which are known to be central to skeletal muscle remodelling and gain in physiological capacity [30], [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Thus, despite the lack of change in global protein synthesis, the types of protein being synthesised are most probably extremely different in the skeletal muscle of ICU patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>As we wish to intervene to prevent the loss of muscle tissue function, it is important to determine which biological pathways were regulating this shift in muscle phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>To examine this question, we took a number of approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Using a multiple array analysis strategy [30], [31] we utilised the extensive animal models of muscle wasting, inactivity and inflammation from the Goldberg laboratory [32], [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>While it is implausible to directly assess muscle function in the ICU setting, this comparative analysis allows us to contrast ICU patients with models of muscle atrophy, muscle inflammatory and muscle inactivity along the lines presented by Sacheck et al [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>It also facilitates discussion of the utility of such models and whether they accurately represent human muscle wasting disorders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Secondly, we utilised Ingenuity pathway analysis to establish which signalling processes or unique gene-networks may be coordinating the altered tissue phenotype (Ingenuity IPA, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ingenuity.com">http://www.ingenuity.com</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3g"><title><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Altered atrogen expression, described in catabolic animal models, are similar in the septic patients, except for the energy metabolism genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>In two recent publications, common genes up regulated or down regulated in animal models with muscle wasting have been identified [32], [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>In the first study animal models for fasting, cancer cachexia, uremia and diabetes mellitus identified 120 unique genes involved in catabolism, and the authors named these ‘atrogens’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>In a second paper these genes were compared with two animal models of disuse induced muscle wasting, leading to 53 commonly changed genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>We compared these results to our data from MOF patients and found good agreement, with the exception of the genes involved in energy metabolism (Supplemental data sheet S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>As described above, the majority of mitochondrial genes involved in energy production are either unchanged in muscle of the septic patients or modestly increased, and this agrees with our previous conclusions that in humans, mitochondrial related mRNAs are not highly responsive to alterations in muscle usage in humans [24], [30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>When comparing the septic patient responses in gene expression, with animal models of disuse, in general a much poorer agreement is observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>This indicates that muscle inactivity, inevitable in the septic ICU patients, doesn't dominate the muscle phenotype seen in these patients, while the in vivo disuse phenotype observed in the various model systems is highly reproducible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Pathway analysis revealed that the animal model atrogens formed several networks, of which estradiol was highlighted as a molecular regulator (Supplemental Figure S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>In support of this novel re-analysis of the data from the Goldberg laboratory, it has been demonstrated that estrogen status regulates muscle recovery from atrophy [36] and in the ICU patients ERS1 (estrogen receptor 1) was 3-fold down regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Notably estrogen receptors are present also in male skeletal muscle [37] and are proposed to attenuate atrophy [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Based on our analysis of the Goldberg laboratory models, and the fact that our patients present a similar muscle gene expression profile, interventions which promote muscle estrogen receptor activation may be worth investigating in the ICU setting. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3h"><title><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Pathway analysis identifies modulation of key canonical pathways and networks in MOF ICU patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>We found several significantly modulated canonical signalling pathways which understandably linked with sepsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Nuclear Factor Erythroid 2-like-2 is a transcription factor (Nrf2, not to be confused with mitochondrial related gene NRF2α/GABP), which responds to a variety of mediators including inflammation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>The Nrf2 mediated oxidative stress response pathway was highly regulated in ICU patients (Figure 2, p = 1.4×10-5 and supplemental data set S4) and recently it was shown that in Nrf2 -/- mice, mortality and inflammation is greatly enhanced in response to sepsis [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Nrf2 appears important for the regulation of glutathione synthesis and cellular detoxification processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Restoration of glutathione levels in muscle of septic patients seems to be a prioritised system [40] that could be regulated via Nrf2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Our data suggests that Nrf2 plays a major role in muscle tissue during sepsis, perhaps coordinating the oxidative stress response. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0003686-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003686.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Nuclear Factor Erythroid 2 canonical pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Ingenuity analyses of micro-array data indicated a canonical pathway around nuclear Factor Erythroid 2 (Nrf2) as one of the most significantly (p = 1.4×10-5) changed in muscle of the septic patients in comparison with the age-matched controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Gene descriptions can be found in supplemental data sheet S5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Red (and pink) means significantly increased gene expression and blue decreased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>The ‘strength’ of the colour is an indication of how up regulated the gene was (with darker red being more up-regulated). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Grey is a highly connected gene (to the transcript network that is altered) but itself is not altered at the mRNA level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Blue/Red hybrids are genes identified in the data base where the protein is actually at least two different genes and 1 sub-unit is down, while the other is up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0003686.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>We found that insulin receptor signalling pathway was significantly modulated in the patients (Figure 3 and supplemental data set S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Given the critical role of insulin resistance in these patients [41] it was informative in that molecules immediately down stream of the insulin receptor appeared to be down regulated, such as IRS1, CD36 and JAK1/2 (a tyrosine kinase associated with cytokine and metabolic signalling). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>The exception was suppressor of cytokine signalling 3 (SOC3) which was 7 fold increased in expression (Figure 3 and supplemental data set S4) and this would be consistent with attempts to suppress the deleterious impact of MOF induced cytokine signalling [42] on insulin action as SOC3 can oppose inflammatory IL6 signalling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>More distal insulin targets, such as mTOR and hormone sensitive lipase were up-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>These responses would suggest to us that the exogenous insulin interacts with excessive cytokine signalling to influence skeletal muscle gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Additional canonical systems appeared activated such as JAK/Stat signalling and PPARα/RXRα. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>With respect to the later, AMPK and adiponectin expression was both elevated (both also associated with aspects of mitochondrial biogenesis), while in the same PPARα/RXRα influenced signalling system, down regulation of Stat5b indicated a potentially negative interaction between growth hormone action on muscle and PPARα. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Activation of PPARα by using an agonist has been shown to improve mitochondrial content and function in skeletal muscle of children with severe burn injury [43], [44] providing a second example of where our data directs us to a drug target. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0003686-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003686.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Insulin signalling canonical pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Ingenuity analyses of micro-array data indicated a canonical pathway involving insulin signalling as significantly changed in muscle of the septic patients in comparison with age-matched controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Gene descriptions can be found in supplemental data sheet S5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Red (and pink) means significantly increased gene expression and blue decreased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>The ‘strength’ of the colour is an indication of how up regulated the gene was (with darker red being more up-regulated). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Grey is a highly connected gene (to the transcript network that is altered) but itself is not altered at the mRNA level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Blue/Red hybrids are genes identified in the data base where the protein is actually at least two different genes and 1 sub-unit is down, while the other is up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0003686.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Finally, Gene Network analysis (based on gene expression changes and nearest molecular neighbours) demonstrated a large number of regulated gene expression networks in skeletal muscle of septic patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>The nuclear phosphoprotein MYC (V-MYC avian myelocytomatosis viral oncogene homolog) was 9 fold induced and was central to the highest scored network that included induction of 3 subunits of eukaryotic translation initiation factor 3 (Supplemental figure S4 and supplemental data set S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Additional significant networks included ESR1 (down regulated) and genes associated with the atrogen analysis and TGFβ connected genes known to be important for muscle tissue remodelling (Supplemental figure S5, supplemental data set S4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3i"><title><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Protein synthesis and altered processing of microRNAs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, given that global protein synthesis rates were unchanged in the patients, 27 translation related genes were up-regulated (e.g. Supplemental figure S4), while perhaps critically this up-regulated functional family did not include the rate-limiting translation initiation 5′ cap-binding protein, EIF4E [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Unchanged expression of EIF4E was found in an IL-6 influenced network demonstrating evidence for vastly up regulated IL-6 receptor and STAT3 (Fig. 4 and supplemental data set S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Intriguingly, this network analysis of the Affymetrix array also included a 5-fold increase of the pri-microRNA transcript of mir-21 in ICU patients and microRNAs are selective regulators of protein synthesis [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>In addition, XPO5, the exportin responsible for transporting the mature miRNA from the nucleus, was also increased substantially in the patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>We therefore went on to analyse the abundance of the mature and active microRNA, mir-21 in ICU patients and controls using real time qPCR method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>The ICU patients displayed a variable and non-significant 50% increase in the mature mir-21 expression levels (p = 0.13), see Figure 4 insert, contrasting with the primary transcript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>This suggests to us that suppressed microRNA processing or export may be occurring, representing a plausible mechanism explaining global loss of coordinated muscle gene expression and thus worthy of further investigation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>This is especially plausible as Gene ontology analysis of the predicted targets of mir-21 suggest it should inhibit genes involved in ubiquitin ligase and JAK-STAT activity, both which were processes shown to be significantly up regulated in the transcriptomes of the patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Thus failure to produce sufficient mir-21 may well have contributed to the activation of these pathways. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0003686-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003686.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Interleukin- 6 and micoRNA –mir 21- related network. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Ingenuity analysis indicated a network including interleukin-6 and the microRNA mir21 to have many significantly changed genes in the septic patients compared with the controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Data in the micro-array is of pre-microRNA of mir-21 where as the qPCR data (insert) is of the mature and active microRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Data in the insert are fold change in mir-21 in septic patients compared with controls and are presented as means±SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Gene descriptions can be found in supplemental data sheet S4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Red (and pink) means significantly increased gene expression and blue decreased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>The ‘strength’ of the colour is an indication of how up regulated the gene was (with darker red being more up-regulated). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Grey is a highly connected gene (to the transcript network that is altered) but itself is not altered at the mRNA level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Blue/Red hybrids are genes identified in the data base where the protein is actually at least two different genes and 1 sub-unit is down, while the other is up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0003686.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>In this study we investigated the nature of the mitochondrial dysfunction found in intensive care using enzymology, protein flux analysis and transcriptomics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>While some mitochondrial enzymes activities were 25–49% lower in skeletal muscle of patients treated in the ICU for sepsis induced multiple organ failure in comparison with a control group of similar age it was abundantly clear that this was not due to either a global reduction in mitochondrial gene transcripts or to impaired in vivo total mitochondrial protein synthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Our initial analysis demonstrated a selective activation of NRF2α/GABP and its target genes suggesting partial activation of mitochondrial biogenesis, while global analysis of 342 mitochondrial genes supported this interpretation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Comparative array analysis discovered that while many atrophy and inflammation responses are conserved across species, the metabolic gene responses in rodent models do not represent a response seen in ICU patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>This is particularly important, as gene expression profiling without consideration of physiological context can produce misleading conclusions [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Finally, network analysis was able to pin-point oxidative stress related pathway activation, modulation of the insulin signalling pathway and indicated that skeletal muscle in ICU patients was undergoing a de-differentiation process regardless of duration in the ICU. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Metabolic homeostasis and mitochondrial dynamics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>In our previous study, as well as in the present one, we found low activities of mitochondrial respiratory chain complexes I and IV, and citrate synthase when expressed per muscle weight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>However, the low activities of complexes I and IV were not present when expressed per citrate synthase activity, indicating a net decrease in mitochondrial content had occurred. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Low activities of mitochondrial enzymes in skeletal muscle have been shown before in animal models for sepsis [11], [15], [16], [17], [18] and in critically ill patients [12], [14], [47], [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Most patient studies included patients in the acute septic or cardiogenic shock [14], [47], [48] whereas our patients have been stabilized in the ICU and have developed multiple organ failure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>During the acute critical phase results indicate a decreased function of the respiratory chain enzymes whereas the later phase of sepsis is characterized by a general decrease in mitochondrial content [49], [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>One might assume that the loss of mitochondrial content reflects muscle inactivity resulting in decreased gene activation [24] or sepsis induced atrophy disrupting mitochondrial biogenesis [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>However, neither appears to be true. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Firstly, the in vivo mitochondrial protein synthesis in the septic ICU patients was not different from that in the control subjects, indicating that sufficient mRNA template existed for translation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Secondly, targeted qPCR analysis demonstrated that the expression of several nuclear encoded oxidative phosphorylation genes did not differ between the groups, while there was a trend for up-regulation of mtDNA encoded oxidative phosphorylation genes and global analysis identified &gt;80 modestly up regulated nuclear encoded mitochondrial related genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Critically, this pattern of gene expression differs markedly from muscle unloading in humans [24] and from animal models of atrophy-sepsis, indicating that our findings are not driven by inactivity nor are they adequately represented by preclinical models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>These results indicate for the first time, that the observed lower mitochondrial content in muscle of septic ICU patients with multiple organ failure is not due to a general decrease in mitochondrial gene expression or failure in the protein synthesis process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>The balance between the biogenesis pathways and the rate of mitochondrial protein degradation regulates tissue mitochondrial content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>The coordinate gene expression for the estimated 1500 or so mitochondrial proteins, is under tight control by these different transcriptional regulators [51], [52], [53], [54], [55], [56], [57], [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>The nuclear encoded mitochondrial proteins are regulated by NRF1, NRF2α/GABP as well as PGC1α and β, while mitochondrial DNA replication and transcription is greatly influenced by TFAM, TFB1M and TFB2M [56], [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>In the present study we found high mRNA levels of all three transcriptional regulators that act on mitochondrial DNA, and intriguingly selectively high NRF2α/GABP levels, a transcription factor that regulates the nuclear encoded TFAM; TFB1M and TFB2M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>We also determined that the selective activation of NRF2α/GABP was unlikely to be caused by exogenous insulin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>The inability of mitochondrial protein synthesis to sustain mitochondrial capacity may therefore reflect a lack of coordinated expression of all the transcription factors needed for an increased mitochondrial biogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>The reason for the lack of coordinated increase in mitochondrial biogenesis genes in these patients needs to be elucidated and may ultimately be manipulated to improve patient outcome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Regulation of protein synthesis and potential alterations in microRNA processing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>It has previously been reported that mitochondrial protein synthesis and gene expression are decreased in septic rats [11], [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Like our present comparative analysis, this supports the idea that rodent models may be inappropriate for studying mitochondrial dynamics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>The unchanged mitochondrial protein synthesis rates are in line with the synthesis rates of other muscle proteins in the septic ICU patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>The very characteristic loss of total muscle protein in these patients is also accompanied by normal synthesis rates of total muscle protein [19] while our transcriptomics indicates that the actual proteins being made, will clearly be substantially different from control skeletal muscle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Future detailed proteomic analyses combined with ribosomal RNA analysis [60] will allow us to define which proteins are now being synthesised. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>The translational initiation factors (EIFs) are central components of the protein translation machinery and EIF4 is the proposed rate limiting factor for protein translational. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>While the partners of EIF4E, EIF4A1 (Helicase), EIF4G1 (scaffold protein) and EIF3S10 were all up-regulated in the ICU patients, EIF4E is unchanged at the mRNA level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>In combination with the increased expression of the tRNA synthetases, MARS, LARS and RARS it would appear that a substantial yet incomplete attempt was made to promote muscle protein synthesis, similar to that observed for the mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>This appears to have failed perhaps reflecting a lack of up-regulation of EIF4E, however, EIF4E is not considered to be regulated to a great extent, at the mRNA level [61], and thus further analysis is merited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Overall, it is clear that the lack of gross changes in in vivo protein dynamics must obscure critical alterations in specific protein formation, such that combing protein measurements with global transcriptomics provides a powerful solution to understanding the nature of tissue remodelling in multiple organ failure patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>When looking for novel regulators of altered protein production from mRNA, microRNA's as global regulators of protein synthesis are of great interest [62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>In the ICU patients, we found a compelling 500% increase in the precursor for mir-21 (pri-mir-21). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>When we measured the mature form of mir-21, we observed no significant change in mir-21 levels (50% increase, p = 0.13) in skeletal muscle of ICU patients when compared with controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>This is important as it has been recently identified that reduction in PTEN expression could be a compensatory mechanism to prevent muscle protein degradation [63] and mir-21 is a validated target of PTEN [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Mature mir-21 is processed from a 3,433 long nucleotide pri-mir-21 [65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Thus, despite the substantial increase in the mir-21 precursor, only modest changes in mature miRNA occurred. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, IL-6 is activated in ICU patients [42] and has been reported to increase mir-21 in tumour cell lines mediated via STAT3 [66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>The IL-6 receptor increases in skeletal muscle in response to both acute [67] and chronic [68] stimuli, suggesting an increased responsiveness to IL-6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>We detected a 10-fold increase in the IL-6 receptor in skeletal muscle of ICU patients, when compared with healthy controls, along with a 1.8-fold increase in STAT-3, the intracellular mediator of IL-6 signalling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>This suggests an increased sensitivity to IL-6 and an increased IL-6 response in the ICU patients and this may explain the substantial increase in transcription of the precursor for mir-21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Whether global processing of microRNA's has been disrupted in ICU patients merits further analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>It would appear, from this initial analysis, that there is substantial transcriptional drive to promote mir-21 expression, while some aspect of the miRNA biogenesis pathway limits substantial production of this translational blocking RNA species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Clinical impact for the patient </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>The loss of muscle mass and function has a profound affect on mortality and morbidity, not only in the septic ICU patients included in this study but also in other diseases with more chronic muscle wasting e.g. cancer, kidney failure and COPD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>In the septic patients the loss of muscle mass as well as mitochondrial content are not due to an overall decrease in their synthesis rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>A obvious conclusion from this is that the losses are driven by increased degradation and that therapeutic aims should be focussed on modulating inappropriate degradation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>However the present data suggest that a different spectrum of protein will be synthesised in these patients, and this implies that the precise profile of proteins being synthesised is altered and thus targeting protein degradation is not necessarily a logical strategy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Limitations of the study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>A potential limitation of the present study is the heterogeneity of the included patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Patients were included at different days of ICU treatment (range from 1–42 days). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>It is possible that the mitochondrial derangements are different at different phases of disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>However, it is not certain that the duration of ICU stay represents different phases of the disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Often patients treated in the ICU have been ill for a while before, whereas others arrive to the ICU early after the initial insult. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>It is therefore difficult to see length of ICU stay as a measure of time of disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>However when the patient with a shorter ICU stay (&lt;6 days) were compared with those with a longer stay (≥6 days) no significant difference were observed (Table 3 and 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Also post-hoc analyses not including the 2 patients with extreme long ICU treatment (35 and 42 days) showed exactly the same changes in comparison with the controls as when including all patients (Table 3 and 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Most importantly, global transcript profiling and clustering indicates that all patients are remarkably similar and develop a specific and clear muscle phenotype. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0003686-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003686.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Post hoc analyses on enzyme activities and mitochondrial synthesis rates. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0003686-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0003686.t003"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Data is given as mean and standard deviation. p for Student's t-test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>ICU intensive care unit patient, ww wet weight, CS citrate synthase, SOD superoxide dismutase </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0003686-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003686.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Post hoc analyses on mRNA levels measured with qPCR expressed as percentage of control. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0003686-t004-4" xlink:href="pone.0003686.t004"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Data is given as mean and standard deviation. p for Student's t-test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>ICU intensive care unit patient, ww wet weight, CS citrate synthase, SOD superoxide dismutase </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>However the groups in these post-hoc analyses are rather small and studies designed to study the temporal changes are needed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>We tried to include a patient population with severe sepsis/septic shock induced multiple organ failure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Patients not recovering from an initial sepsis develop multiple organ failure requiring ICU treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>The patients we included were not in their septic shock anymore and had developed multiple organ failure making them rather comparable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>However a few patients with SOFA scores below 3 were included not fulfilling the criteria for multiple organ failure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Again post-hoc analyses comparing the ICU patients with SOFA score over 3 with the controls gave exactly the same changes and conclusions as before (Table 3 and 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>These post-hoc analyses show that this apparently heterogeneous group of ICU patients behave rather consistent with regard to mitochondrial changes and gene expression in skeletal muscle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Another possible confounding factor is the different treatments that the patients receive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>When performing studies in actual ICU patients we are dealing with reality and this can not be changed for clinical reasons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Treatment with corticosteroids is the one most discussed in relation to muscle dysfunction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>However when we compared the micro-array changes in our patients with the changes induced with methylprednisole treatment in rats only a 1–2% of the ICU regulated genes were affected in both the patients and the rat model [69], indicating that corticosteroid treatment in the ICU patients contributes little to the observed changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>However affects of other treatments can not be excluded. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Another limitation of the study is the isolation of mitochondria done for measuring the enzyme activities and the synthesis rates of mitochondrial protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>The sequential centrifugations used to isolate the mitochondria mainly isolate intact mitochondria and not the damaged mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Also this procedure isolated mainly the subsarcolemmal mitochondria from skeletal muscle and not the intramyofibrillar mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>So when measuring the enzyme activities in the isolated mitochondria this represents mainly intact subsarcolemmal mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>This selection of one subpopulation of the mitochondria is most likely also the explanation for the different values obtained for complex I and IV activities expressed per citrate synthase activity in the whole muscle and the isolated mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Also the increased complex IV activity in the isolated mitochondria and not in the whole muscle could be explained by this. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Both the fractional synthesis rates of the mitochondria and the mitochondrial SOD activity can not be measured differently than in the isolated mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>It is possible that the synthesis rates in the non-isolated mitochondria are decreased in the patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>However the gene expression data (both from the qPCR analyses and the micro-array) do support a normal synthesis as measured in the isolated mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>In summary, we demonstrated that while the skeletal muscle of septic ICU patients with multiple organ failure have reduced mitochondrial content, this is not associated with a gross failure in biogenesis of mitochondria since both in vivo protein synthesis and mitochondrial related mRNA abundance were sustained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>However, loss of coordination of key elements of mitochondrial biogenesis was apparent, such that maturation of mitochondrial and mitochondrial networks may have still been compromised, resulting in activation of some specific mitochondrial matrix proteases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Further, in this first ever analysis of the global transcriptional responses in ICU patients, we find a substantial loss of muscle specific genes, a global oxidative stress response related to most probably cytokine signalling, altered insulin related signalling and a substantial overlap between patients and muscle wasting/inflammatory animal models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Failure to process mir-21 may have contributed to the activation of these signalling pathways, while such impairment hints at a wider problem with miRNA formation and hence control of tissue phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Finally, we were able to demonstrate that the phenotype of skeletal muscle in ICU patients is not merely one of inactivity, it appears to be an actively remodelling tissue, influenced by several mediators, all of which may be open to manipulation with the aim to improve clinical outcome </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0003686.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Expression of mitochondrial transcription factors in C2C12 cells with and without insulin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Differentiated C2C12 cells were incubated with insulin from day 5 to day 6 (24 h) and expression of NRF2α, TFB1m and TFB2m were all measured by qPCR (white bars, water; grey bars, 0.6 µM insulin; black bars, 6 µM insulin). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>None of the mRNA levels were changed by insulin in relation to the controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>Values are given as mean±SEM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>(0.28 MB TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0003686.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0003686.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>NRF2α/GABP network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Ingenuity analyses of micro-array data indicated a network around NRF2α/GABP as significantly changed in muscle of the septic patients in comparison with age-matched controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Gene descriptions can be found in supplemental data sheet S4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Red (and pink) means significantly increased gene expression and blue decreased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>The ‘strength’ of the colour is an indication of how up regulated the gene was (with darker red being more up-regulated). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>Grey is a highly connected gene (to the transcript network that is altered) but itself is not altered at the mRNA level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Blue/Red hybrids are genes identified in the data base where the protein is actually at least two different genes and 1 sub-unit is down, while the other is up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>(0.72 MB TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0003686.s002.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0003686.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Comparisons of network analyses of atrogens in animal models and septic patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Ingenuity network analyses including the atrogens defined by Golberg et al [32], [22] from catabolic and disuse animal models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>The network build around these genes and related genes are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>The changes in gene expression for the animal models are shown on the left and for the human data from the septic patients on the right. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>In large changes are similar except for the energy metabolism related genes which are downregulated in the animal models and not changed in the septic patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>An interesting observation is that this network is closely regulated by estradiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Gene descriptions can be found in supplemental data sheet S3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Red (and pink) means significantly increased gene expression and blue decreased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>The ‘strength’ of the colour is an indication of how up regulated the gene was (with darker red being more up-regulated). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Grey is a highly connected gene (to the transcript network that is altered) but itself is not altered at the mRNA level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Blue/Red hybrids are genes identified in the data base where the protein is actually at least two different genes and 1 sub-unit is down, while the other is up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>(0.87 MB TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0003686.s003.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0003686.s004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>Myc network. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>Ingenuity analyses of micro-array data indicated a network around MYC as most significantly changed in muscle of the septic patients in comparison with age-matched controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>Gene descriptions can be found in supplemental data sheet S4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>Red (and pink) means significantly increased gene expression and blue decreased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>The ‘strength’ of the colour is an indication of how up regulated the gene was (with darker red being more up-regulated). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>Grey is a highly connected gene (to the transcript network that is altered) but itself is not altered at the mRNA level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>Blue/Red hybrids are genes identified in the data base where the protein is actually at least two different genes and 1 sub-unit is down, while the other is up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>(0.56 MB TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0003686.s004.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0003686.s005"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>Tissue remodelling networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>Ingenuity analyses of micro-array data indicated two network involved in tissue remodelling as highly significantly changed in muscle of the septic patients in comparison with age-matched controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>One network is build around TGFβ (a) and the other one around ESR1 (b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>Gene descriptions can be found in supplemental data sheet S4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>Red (and pink) means significantly increased gene expression and blue decreased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>The ‘strength’ of the colour is an indication of how up regulated the gene was (with darker red being more up-regulated). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Grey is a highly connected gene (to the transcript network that is altered) but itself is not altered at the mRNA level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>Blue/Red hybrids are genes identified in the data base where the protein is actually at least two different genes and 1 sub-unit is down, while the other is up. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>(0.83 MB TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0003686.s005.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0003686.s006"><label>Supplemental data sheet S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>SAM results </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>(3.61 MB XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0003686.s006.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0003686.s007"><label>Supplemental data sheet S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>Expression of mitochondrial genes from the micro-aray analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>(0.09 MB XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0003686.s007.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0003686.s008"><label>Supplemental data sheet S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>Comparison of expression of atrogens identified in muscle of catabolic and disuse animal models (common to all models) and septic patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>(0.05 MB XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0003686.s008.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0003686.s009"><label>Supplemental data sheet S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>Gene network lists. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>(0.10 MB XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0003686.s009.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0003686.s010"><label>Supplemental data sheet S5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>Canonical Network lists. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>(0.06 MB XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0003686.s010.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to thank the excellent nursing skills of Viveka Gustavsson at Karolinska University Hospital Huddinge, Nina Johansson, Ann-Sofie Andersson and Ami Bylund at Ersta Hospital. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>We also would like to thank Paul Greenhalf for the kind gift of RNA from his insulin clamp studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>Funding: These studies were supported by grants from the Swedisch Research Council (grants 04210 and 14244), Karolinska Research Foundation, Karolinska University Hospital Research Funds and Heriot-Watt University Funds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>None of the sponsors or funders were involved in design or conduct of the study or the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0003686-Banwell1"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>1 BanwellBLMildnerRJHassallACBeckerLEVajsarJ 2003 Muscle weakness in critically ill children. Neurology 61 1779 1782 14694046 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Bolton1"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>2 BoltonCF 1996 Sepsis and the systemic inflammatory response syndrome: neuromuscular manifestations. Crit Care Med 24 1408 1416 8706499 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-DeJonghe1"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>3 De JongheBCookDSharsharTLefaucheurJPCarletJ 1998 Acquired neuromuscular disorders in critically ill patients: a systematic review. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>Groupe de Reflexion et d'Etude sur les Neuromyopathies En Reanimation. Intensive Care Med 24 1242 1250 9885875 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Larsson1"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>4 LarssonLLiXEdstromLErikssonLIZackrissonH 2000 Acute quadriplegia and loss of muscle myosin in patients treated with nondepolarizing neuromuscular blocking agents and corticosteroids: mechanisms at the cellular and molecular levels. Crit Care Med 28 34 45 10667496 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Care1"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>5 CareACatalucciDFelicettiFBonciDAddarioA 2007 MicroRNA-133 controls cardiac hypertrophy. Nat Med 13 613 618 17468766 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Herridge1"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>6 HerridgeMSCheungAMTanseyCMMatte-MartynADiaz-GranadosN 2003 One-year outcomes in survivors of the acute respiratory distress syndrome. N Engl J Med 348 683 693 12594312 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-VandenBerghe1"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>7 Van den BergheG 2004 How does blood glucose control with insulin save lives in intensive care? J Clin Invest 114 1187 1195 15520847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Fredriksson1"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>8 FredrikssonKHammarqvistFStrigardKHultenbyKLjungqvistO 2006 Derangements in mitochondrial metabolism in intercostal and leg muscle of critically ill patients with sepsis induced multiple organ failure. Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab 291 1044 1050  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Dudley1"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>9 DudleyGATullsonPCTerjungRL 1987 Influence of mitochondrial content on the sensitivity of respiratory control. J Biol Chem 262 9109 9114 3597408 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Rooyackers1"><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>10 RooyackersOEHesselinkMKWagenmakersAJ 1997 Contraction failure of skeletal muscle of rats recovering from critical illness. Clin Sci (Lond) 92 189 195 9059321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Rooyackers2"><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>11 RooyackersOEAdeyDBAdesPANairKS 1996 Effect of age on in vivo rates of mitochondrial protein synthesis in human skeletal muscle. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 93 15364 15369 8986817 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Vanhorebeek1"><text><SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>12 VanhorebeekIDe VosRMesottenDWoutersPJDe Wolf-PeetersC 2005 Protection of hepatocyte mitochondrial ultrastructure and function by strict blood glucose control with insulin in critically ill patients. Lancet 365 53 59 15639679 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Fink1"><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>13 FinkMP 2004 Research: advances in cell biology relevant to critical illness. Curr Opin Crit Care 10 279 291 15258500 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Brealey1"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>14 BrealeyDBrandMHargreavesIHealesSLandJ 2002 Association between mitochondrial dysfunction and severity and outcome of septic shock. Lancet 360 219 223 12133657 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Boczkowski1"><text><SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>15 BoczkowskiJLisderoCLLanoneSSambACarrerasMC 1999 Endogenous peroxynitrite mediates mitochondrial dysfunction in rat diaphragm during endotoxemia. Faseb J 13 1637 1646 10463956 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Brealey2"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>16 BrealeyDKaryampudiSJacquesTSNovelliMStidwillR 2004 Mitochondrial dysfunction in a long-term rodent model of sepsis and organ failure. Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol 286 R491 497 14604843 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Crouser1"><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>17 CrouserEDJulianMWBlahoDVPfeifferDR 2002 Endotoxin-induced mitochondrial damage correlates with impaired respiratory activity. Crit Care Med 30 276 284 11889292 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Schumer1"><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>18 SchumerWErvePRObernolteRP 1971 Endotoxemic effect on cardiac and skeletal muscle mitochondria. Surg Gynecol and Obstetrics 133 433 436  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Tjader1"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>19 TjaderIRooyackersOForsbergAMVesaliRFGarlickPJ 2004 Effects on skeletal muscle of intravenous glutamine supplementation to ICU patients. Intensive Care Med 30 266 275 14722645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Bone1"><text><SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>20 BoneRC 1992 Editorial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>Abnormal cellular metabolism in sepsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>A new interpretation. JAMA 267 1518 1519 1538543 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-McNurlan1"><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>21 McNurlanMAEssenPThorellACalderAGAndersonSE 1994 Response of protein synthesis in human skeletal muscle to insulin: an investigation with L-[2H5]phenylalanine. Am J Physiol 267 E102 108 8048497 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Fredriksson2"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>22 FredrikssonKRadellPErikssonLIHultenbyKRooyackersO 2005 Effect of prolonged mechanical ventilation on diaphragm muscle mitochondria in piglets. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand 49 1101 1107 16095451 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Januszkiewicz1"><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>23 JanuszkiewiczAKlaudeMLoreKAnderssonJRingdenO 2005 Determination of in vivo protein synthesis in human palatine tonsil. Clin Sci (Lond) 108 179 184 15535800 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Timmons1"><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>24 TimmonsJANorrbomJScheeleCThonbergHWahlestedtC 2006 Expression profiling following local muscle inactivity in humans provides new perspective on diabetes-related genes. Genomics 87 165 172 16326070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Larsson2"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>25 LarssonOWahlestedtCTimmonsJA 2005 Considerations when using the significance analysis of microarrays (SAM) algorithm. BMC Bioinformatics 6 129 15921534 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Choe1"><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>26 ChoeSEBoutrosMMichelsonAMChurchGMHalfonMS 2005 Preferred analysis methods for Affymetrix GeneChips revealed by a wholly defined control dataset. Genome Biol 6 R16 15693945 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Stump1"><text><SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>27 StumpCSShortKRBigelowMLSchimkeJMNairKS 2003 Effect of insulin on human skeletal muscle mitochondrial ATP production, protein synthesis, and mRNA transcripts. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 100 7996 8001 12808136 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Southgate1"><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>28 SouthgateRJBruceCRCareyALSteinbergGRWalderK 2005 PGC-1alpha gene expression is down-regulated by Akt- mediated phosphorylation and nuclear exclusion of FoxO1 in insulin-stimulated skeletal muscle. Faseb J 19 2072 2074 16203862 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Stephens1"><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>29 StephensFBConstantin-TeodosiuDLaithwaiteDSimpsonEJGreenhaffPL 2005 Insulin stimulates L-carnitine accumulation in human skeletal muscle. Faseb J  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Timmons2"><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>30 TimmonsJALarssonOJanssonEFischerHGustafssonT 2005 Human muscle gene expression responses to endurance training provide a novel perspective on Duchenne muscular dystrophy. Faseb J 19 750 760 15857889 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Timmons3"><text><SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>31 TimmonsJAWennmalmKLarssonOWaldenTBLassmannT 2007 Myogenic gene expression signature establishes that brown and white adipocytes originate from distinct cell lineages. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 104 4401 4406 17360536 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Lecker1"><text><SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>32 LeckerSHJagoeRTGilbertAGomesMBaracosV 2004 Multiple types of skeletal muscle atrophy involve a common program of changes in gene expression. Faseb J 18 39 51 14718385 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Sacheck1"><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>33 SacheckJMHyattJPRaffaelloAJagoeRTRoyRR 2007 Rapid disuse and denervation atrophy involve transcriptional changes similar to those of muscle wasting during systemic diseases. Faseb J 21 140 155 17116744 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Hosack1"><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>34 HosackDADennisGJr.ShermanBTLaneHCLempickiRA 2003 Identifying biological themes within lists of genes with EASE. Genome Biol 4 R70 14519205 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Timmons4"><text><SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>35 TimmonsJAJanssonEFischerHGustafssonTGreenhaffPL 2005 Modulation of extracellular matrix genes reflects the magnitude of physiological adaptation to aerobic exercise training in humans. BMC Biol 3 19 16138928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-McClung1"><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>36 McClungJMDavisJMWilsonMAGoldsmithECCarsonJA 2006 Estrogen status and skeletal muscle recovery from disuse atrophy. J Appl Physiol 100 2012 2023 16497837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Wiik1"><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>37 WiikAGustafssonTEsbjornssonMJohanssonOEkmanM 2005 Expression of oestrogen receptor alpha and beta is higher in skeletal muscle of highly endurance-trained than of moderately active men. Acta Physiol Scand 184 105 112 15916670 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Sugiura1"><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>38 SugiuraTItoNGotoKNaitoHYoshiokaT 2006 Estrogen administration attenuates immobilization-induced skeletal muscle atrophy in male rats. J Physiol Sci 56 393 399 17052385 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Thimmulappa1"><text><SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>39 ThimmulappaRKLeeHRangasamyTReddySPYamamotoM 2006 Nrf2 is a critical regulator of the innate immune response and survival during experimental sepsis. J Clin Invest 116 984 995 16585964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Flaring1"><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>40 FlaringUBRooyackersOEWernermanJHammarqvistF 2003 Temporal changes in muscle glutathione in ICU patients. Intensive Care Med 29 2193 2198 14566458 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Thorell1"><text><SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>41 ThorellARooyackersOMyrenforsPSoopMNygrenJ 2004 Intensive insulin treatment in critically ill trauma patients normalizes glucose by reducing endogenous glucose production. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 89 5382 5386 15531485 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Leonidou1"><text><SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>42 LeonidouLMouzakiAMichalakiMDeLasticALKyriazopoulouV 2007 Cytokine production and hospital mortality in patients with sepsis-induced stress hyperglycemia. J Infect 55 340 346 17631968 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Cree1"><text><SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>43 CreeMGNewcomerBRHerndonDNQianTSunD 2007 PPAR-alpha agonism improves whole body and muscle mitochondrial fat oxidation, but does not alter intracellular fat concentrations in burn trauma children in a randomized controlled trial. Nutr Metab (Lond) 4 9 17451602 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Cree2"><text><SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>44 CreeMGZwetslootJJHerndonDNQianTMorioB 2007 Insulin sensitivity and mitochondrial function are improved in children with burn injury during a randomized controlled trial of fenofibrate. Ann Surg 245 214 221 17245174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Mamane1"><text><SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>45 MamaneYPetroulakisEMartineauYSatoTALarssonO 2007 Epigenetic activation of a subset of mRNAs by eIF4E explains its effects on cell proliferation. PLoS ONE 2 e242 17311107 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-ValenciaSanchez1"><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>46 Valencia-SanchezMALiuJHannonGJParkerR 2006 Control of translation and mRNA degradation by miRNAs and siRNAs. Genes Dev 20 515 524 16510870 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Corbucci1"><text><SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>47 CorbucciGGGasparettoACandianiACrimiGAntonelliM 1985 Shock-induced damage to mitochondrial function and some cellular antioxidant mechanisms in humans. Circ Shock 15 15 26 2983902 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Gasparetto1"><text><SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>48 GasparettoACorbucciGGCandianiAGohilKEdwardsRH 1983 Effect of tissue hypoxia and septic shock on human skeletal muscle mitochondria. Lancet 2 1486  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Helliwell1"><text><SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>49 HelliwellTRCoakleyJHWagenmakersAJMGriffithsRDCampbellIT 1991 Necrotizing myopathy in critically-ill patients. Journal of Pathology 164 307 314 1919868 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Helliwell2"><text><SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>50 HelliwellTRGriffithRDCoakleyJHWagenmakersAJMMcClellandP 1990 Muscle morphology and biochemistry in critically-ill patients. J Neurol Sci 98 suppl 329  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Robinson1"><text><SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>51 RobinsonCEWuXNawazZOnateSAGimbleJM 1999 A corepressor and chicken ovalbumin upstream promoter transcriptional factor proteins modulate peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma2/retinoid X receptor alpha-activated transcription from the murine lipoprotein lipase promoter. Endocrinology 140 1586 1593 10098492 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Scarpulla1"><text><SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>52 ScarpullaRC 2002 Transcriptional activators and coactivators in the nuclear control of mitochondrial function in mammalian cells. Gene 286 81 89 11943463 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Taivassalo1"><text><SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>53 TaivassaloTFuKJohnsTArnoldDKarpatiG 1999 Gene shifting: a novel therapy for mitochondrial myopathy. Hum Mol Genet 8 1047 1052 10332036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Kelly1"><text><SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>54 KellyMKellerCAviluceaPRKellerPLuoZ 2004 AMPK activity is diminished in tissues of IL-6 knockout mice: the effect of exercise. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 320 449 454 15219849 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Goffart1"><text><SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>55 GoffartSWiesnerRJ 2003 Regulation and co-ordination of nuclear gene expression during mitochondrial biogenesis. Exp Physiol 88 33 40 12525853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Gleyzer1"><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>56 GleyzerNVercauterenKScarpullaRC 2005 Control of mitochondrial transcription specificity factors (TFB1M and TFB2M) by nuclear respiratory factors (NRF-1 and NRF-2) and PGC-1 family coactivators. Mol Cell Biol 25 1354 1366 15684387 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-FernandezSilva1"><text><SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>57 Fernandez-SilvaPEnriquezJAMontoyaJ 2003 Replication and transcription of mammalian mitochondrial DNA. Exp Physiol 88 41 56 12525854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Falkenberg1"><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>58 FalkenbergMGaspariMRantanenATrifunovicALarssonNG 2002 Mitochondrial transcription factors B1 and B2 activate transcription of human mtDNA. Nat Genet 31 289 294 12068295 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Callahan1"><text><SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>59 CallahanLASupinskiGS 2005 Downregulation of diaphragm electron transport chain and glycolytic enzyme gene expression in sepsis. J Appl Physiol 99 1120 1126 16103521 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Larsson3"><text><SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>60 LarssonOLiSIssaenkoOAAvdulovSPetersonM 2007 Eukaryotic translation initiation factor 4E induced progression of primary human mammary epithelial cells along the cancer pathway is associated with targeted translational deregulation of oncogenic drivers and inhibitors. Cancer Res 67 6814 6824 17638893 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Richter1"><text><SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>61 RichterJDSonenbergN 2005 Regulation of cap-dependent translation by eIF4E inhibitory proteins. Nature 433 477 480 15690031 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Filipowicz1"><text><SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>62 FilipowiczWBhattacharyyaSNSonenbergN 2008 Mechanisms of post-transcriptional regulation by microRNAs: are the answers in sight? Nat Rev Genet 9 102 114 18197166 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Hu1"><text><SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>63 HuZLeeIHWangXShengHZhangL 2007 PTEN expression contributes to the regulation of muscle protein degradation in diabetes. Diabetes 56 2449 2456 17623817 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Meng1"><text><SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>64 MengFHensonRWehbe-JanekHGhoshalKJacobST 2007 MicroRNA-21 regulates expression of the PTEN tumor suppressor gene in human hepatocellular cancer. Gastroenterology 133 647 658 17681183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Lu1"><text><SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>65 LuCHeJCCaiWLiuHZhuL 2004 Advanced glycation endproduct (AGE) receptor 1 is a negative regulator of the inflammatory response to AGE in mesangial cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 101 11767 11772 15289604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Hennig1"><text><SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>66 HennigGLofflerGWielandOH 1975 Active and inactive forms of pyruvatedehydrogenase in skeletal muscle as related to the metabolic and functional state of the muscle cell. FEBS Lett 59 142 145 1227929 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Keller1"><text><SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>67 KellerPPenkowaMKellerCSteensbergAFischerCP 2005 Interleukin-6 receptor expression in contracting human skeletal muscle: regulating role of IL-6. Faseb J 19 1181 1183 15837717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Keller2"><text><SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>68 KellerCSteensbergAHansenAKFischerCPPlomgaardP 2005 Effect of exercise, training, and glycogen availability on IL-6 receptor expression in human skeletal muscle. J Appl Physiol 99 2075 2079 16099893 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0003686-Almon1"><text><SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>69 AlmonRRDuBoisDCYaoZHoffmanEPGhimbovschiS 2007 Microarray analysis of the temporal response of skeletal muscle to methylprednisolone: comparative analysis of two dosing regimens. Physiol Genomics 30 282 299 17473217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
