
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2950848</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20949082</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PONE-RA-19931R1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013159</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Biochemistry/Bioinformatics</subject><subject>Biochemistry/Molecular Evolution</subject><subject>Computational Biology/Comparative Sequence Analysis</subject><subject>Computational Biology/Sequence Motif Analysis</subject><subject>Evolutionary Biology/Bioinformatics</subject><subject>Evolutionary Biology/Evolutionary and Comparative Genetics</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Bioinformatics</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Gene Function</subject><subject>Marine and Aquatic Sciences/Bioinformatics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Characterization of the Functional Domain of β2-Microglobulin from the Asian Seabass, Lates calcarifer </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>L. calcarifer</italic> β2-Microglobulin</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mohd-Padil</surname><given-names>Hirzahida</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tajul-Arifin</surname><given-names>Khairina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mohd-Adnan</surname><given-names>Adura</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>School of Biosciences and Biotechnology, Faculty of Science and Technology, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, Bangi, Selangor, Malaysia</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Brusic</surname><given-names>Vladimir</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>kay.tarifin@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: KTA AMA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: HMP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: HMP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: HMP KTA AMA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Interpreted data: KTA AMA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>10</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e13159</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Mohd-Padil et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>β2-Microglobulin (β2M) is the light chain of major histocompatibility class I (MHC I) that binds non-covalently with the α heavy chain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Both proteins attach to the antigen peptide, presenting a complex to the T cell to be destroyed via the immune mechanism. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Methodology/Principal Findings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In this study, a cDNA sequence encoding β2M in the Asian seabass (Lates calcarifer) was identified and analyzed using in silico approaches to predict and characterize its functional domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The β2M cDNA contains an open reading frame (ORF) of 351 bases with a coding capacity of 116 amino acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>A large portion of the protein consists of the IG constant domain (IGc1), similar to β2M sequences from other species studied thus far. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Alignment of the IGc1 domains of β2M from L. calcarifer and other species shows a high degree of overall conservation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Seven amino acids were found to be conserved across taxa whereas conservation between L. calcarifer and other fish species was restricted to 14 amino acids at identical conserved positions. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Conclusion/Significance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>As the L. calcarifer β2M protein analyzed in this study contains a functional domain similar to that of β2M proteins in other species, it can be postulated that the β2M proteins from L. calcarifer and other organisms are derived from a common ancestor and thus have a similar immune function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, fish β2M genes could also be classified according to the ecological habitat of the species, i.e. whether it is from a freshwater, marine or euryhaline environment. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="7"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>β2M is the light chain component of the class I major histocompatibility complex (MHC I) molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>It consists of about 99 residues with a seven-stranded β-sandwich fold and a central disulfide bond [1] and belongs to the antibody constant domain-like family of proteins (immunoglobulin superfamily). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>At the cell surface, the MHC I complex is comprised of three extracellular domains from the α chain (α1, α2 and α3) plus the β2M protein domain. β2M ensures the proper folding and cell surface display of the MHC I molecule [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The classical MHC I molecule mainly functions as a component that binds antigenic peptides, presenting them to the T-cell receptor to trigger the cellular immune response [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that there is a high degree of conservation of β2M sequences of mammalian species as well as between mammalian and avian species [4], [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The teleost β2M sequences also exhibit high sequence similarity overall and conserved regions with warm-blooded vertebrates [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Previous phylogenetic analysis revealed the evolutionary diversion of the β2M protein in warm-blooded vertebrates and fish [7], [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, another earlier phylogenetic analysis indicated that the freshwater fish β2M gene diverged from the common ancestor gene earlier than the seawater fish β2M gene [6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In an effort to improve our understanding of the molecular biology of L. calcarifer, several thousand expressed sequence tags (ESTs) have been derived from various cDNA libraries from several tissues [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Analyses of the EST data enabled us to identify novel gene sequences, including those with significant similarity to β2M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Using the numerous β2M sequences that are available in the public databases, we analyzed the protein sequence in an effort to better understand the immune system of L. calcarifer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The cDNA sequence of L. calcarifer β2M obtained from the spleen EST library was translated into its potential open reading frame (ORF) using the ORF Finder algorithm (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gorf/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gorf/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Domain analyses were carried out using several resources, including Simple Modular Architecture Research Tools (SMART) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de/">http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de/</ext-link>) [10], Pfam 20.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pfam.wustl.edu/">http://pfam.wustl.edu/</ext-link>) [11] and Prosite 19.36 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.expasy.org/prosite/">http://www.expasy.org/prosite/</ext-link>) [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The profile of the IGc1 domain obtained from the Pfam domain database was used to search for other homologous proteins using the hmmsearch program in HMMER version 2.3.2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hmmer.janelia.org">http://hmmer.janelia.org</ext-link>) [13], [14] in both the Swiss-Prot database Release 54 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>) and the fish genomes at Ensembl database Release 49 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ensembl.org">http://www.ensembl.org</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The IGc1 domain sequences of the homologous proteins thus identified were extracted for subsequent analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The sequence alignment for the IGc1 domains was built using the hmmalign program in the HMMER package against the profile of the IGc1 domain obtained from Pfam to enable the pattern of β2M protein change across the taxa to be examined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>PHYLIP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://evolution.genetics.washington.edu/phylip">http://evolution.genetics.washington.edu/phylip</ext-link>) [15] was then used to perform phylogenetic analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>A neighbor-joining tree was built using the protdist and neighbor programs with the Jones-Taylor-Thornton substitution model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The robustness of the trees was evaluated by bootstrap analysis of 1000 random iterations using seqboot, while consense was used to generate the consensus tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>All programs used to construct the phylogenetic trees are contained in PHYLIP packages [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, MEGA4 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://megasoftware.net/">http://megasoftware.net/</ext-link>) [16] was utilized to view the resultant phylogenetic trees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The L. calcarifer β2M sequence analyzed in this study has been deposited in the GenBank database under the accession number FJ200516. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Analysis of the L. calcarifer β2M Sequence </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Analyses of the cDNA sequence of L. calcarifer β2M (clone LSE48F06) from the spleen EST library indicated the most probable ORF codes for a polypeptide of 116 amino acids in length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>A domain search revealed that a large portion of the protein sequence matched the immunoglobulin C-type (IGc1) domain in the SMART, Pfam and Prosite databases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Almost half of the amino acid residues of β2M form two large β structures, which are linked by a central disulfide bond. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Its conformation thus strongly resembles the overall tertiary structure of the Igc1 domain [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>In addition, analysis against the Prosite database showed the presence of an immunoglobulin and major histocompatibility complex protein signature, YSCRVTH, located at residues 97–103 in the L. calcarifer β2M sequence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>A total of 81 IGc1 domains contained in β2M sequences were obtained by protein search against the Swiss-Prot database (version 14 updated 23 October 2007) and the known proteins of five fish species (medaka, stickleback, zebrafish, pufferfish and spotted green pufferfish) in the Ensembl database (version 49 updated March 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Of these 81 domain sequences, only 56 were used to build the multiple sequence alignment (MSA) (see Table 1); the remaining sequences were excluded as they were considered identical, truncated or replicated between the two databases used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>As the IGc1 domain is the functional domain in all β2M sequences analyzed in this study, subsequent analyses focused on this domain as a representation of the β2M protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0013159-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013159.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>β2M sequences used in this analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0013159-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0013159.t001"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The 55 protein sequences used in this study were retrieved from the Swiss-Prot and Refseq databases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Protein ID shows the accession number of the sequence in the database while Protein Name is the protein name designated in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Equine, Rodents, Ruminants, Primates and Others are largely grouped as Eutheria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Sequence Alignment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Alignment of the IGc1 domains of β2M from L. calcarifer and other species showed a high degree of overall conservation across taxa (see Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The IGc1 domain of L. calcarifer starts with a Ser residue, which is conserved among the taxa, with the exception of domains from the Japanese flounder (Q8AYH8), Chinese hamster (Q9WV24), hispid pocket mouse (Q8CIQ3) and Australian echidna (Q864T6), in which the starting residue is a Thr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The fish sequences, with the exception of Siberian sturgeon (Q9PRF8), are two residues shorter (lacking residue-75 and residue-76) than the human (P61769) sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The deletions in the teleost sequences are located in the loop between the anti-parallel beta-strands S6 and S7 [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Seven positions or residues, Asn11, Cys15, Pro22, Asp44, Phe47, Cys70 and Val72 (numbering refers to the position in the MSA) are found to be completely conserved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>These residues or regions are believed to be in the active or binding site of the β2M protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>A previous study reported that the two cysteine residues (Cys15 and Cys70), which covalently link to form a disulfide bridge (thus connecting the two β sheets), are important elements in protein folding that contribute to stabilization of the MHC class I molecule [1]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0013159-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013159.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Multiple sequence alignment of IGc1 domains. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The alignment consists of IGc1 domain sequences from organisms of various taxa such as Eutheria, Marsupials, Monotremes, Avians, Chondrichthyes fish and Actinopterygii fishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Lca is the L. calcarifer protein sequence and the conserved residues are marked by (*). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>S1, S2, S3, S4, S5, S6 and S7 indicate the regions of seven β strands in the IGc1 domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Numbers at the top indicate amino acid positions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Information on the sequences is given in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0013159.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic tree built is an unrooted tree (see Figure 2) with two distinct clades, the mammalian β2M and fish β2M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The avian, marsupial and monotreme sequences form an intermediate group between the fish and the mammalian clades. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>All fish sequences are from the Actinopterygii class with the exception of the clearnose skate (Q8AXA0) [19], which is a cartilaginous fish (class Chondrichthyes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>In order to clarify the relationships among the β2M molecules of the Actinopterygii fish (Siberian sturgeon, channel catfish (O42197), Japanese medaka (Q90ZJ6), Japanese flounder, zebrafish (Q04475, NP_998291), common carp (Q03422) and Lake Tana barbel (P55076)), an NJ tree consisting of fish sequences only was constructed using the chicken (P21611) β2M sequence as an outgroup (see Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The β2M from L. calcarifer, which is a euryhaline and catadromous species, clustered together with Japanese medaka β2M, forming a separate clade from the freshwater fishes (common carp, Lake Tana barbel, zebrafish and channel catfish). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic trees also reveal a molecular signal of the ecological distinction between marine and freshwater fish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The Siberian sturgeon β2M sequence is the most basal lineage, which is placed outside the main cluster of teleosts in the tree (see Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0013159-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013159.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>NJ phylogenetic tree of β2M protein sequences representing whole organisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic tree shown is the collapsed tree of 55 sets of sequence data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>This tree shows that β2M sequences are clustered together according to their taxons. β2M sequences from Eutheria are clustered together and consist of sequences from Primates, Equine, Rodents, Ruminants, SscQ07717, OcuP01885 and FcaQ5MGS7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Marsupials, Monotremes and Avians are the intermediate taxons between Eutheria and Fish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Amphibian Xla protein Q9IA97 is clustered together with Actinopterygii fishes while the outgroup in this tree is a cartilaginous fish Reg Q8AXA0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The divergence of fish and mammalian β2M received a high bootstrap value (89) to support the reliability of this phylogenetic tree. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0013159.g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0013159-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013159.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>NJ phylogenetic tree of IGc1 domains present in β2M protein sequences from fish. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic tree shows that fish β2M proteins are clustered according to the fish's ecological habitat, which may be fresh water, euryhaline or marine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The chicken sequence was used as the outgroup. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Information on the sequences is given in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0013159.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Our analysis of the novel L. calcarifer β2M gene recovered in this study indicates that, overall, fish β2M sequences have high sequence similarity and share many conserved features with published sequences from mammals and birds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Using β2M as both a phylogenetic marker and a source of information, we confirmed previous studies indicating that the β2M proteins of mammals and fish represent clearly distinct evolutionary paths, with fish β2M genes more closely related to avian sequences than to those of mammals [7], [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The divergence between fish and mammals is partially a consequence of several unreversed changes in the ORF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>For example, at site-14 (S2) in all mammalian β2M sequences, the residue is Arg, whereas in Actinopteygii fish β2M sequences it is Ile. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The Ser residue in mammalian sequences is substituted by Ala at site-45 (S4) in all Actinopterygii fish, whereas Lys at position 55 (S5) in mammalian β2M is consistently replaced by Thr in all Actinopterygii fish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Although these changes of amino acids are located within the mature protein region, the residues at those sites are not involved in any important stabilizing interactions of the protein [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Our analyses of the Actinopterygii fish β2M sequences employed sequences representing two subclasses: Neopterygii (teleosts) and Chondrostei. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Within the Neopterygii, two superorders are evident: Ostariophsi and Acanthopterygii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The molecular results showed phylogenetic relationships that support those established based on fish morphology [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Ostariophsi includes two different orders (Cypriniformes and Siluriformes), whereas Acanthopterygii includes three different fish orders (Beloniformes, Perciformes and Pleuronectiformes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>With the exception of Siberian sturgeon, our results also showed that fishes included in Ostariophsi are mainly freshwater fishes, whereas those of Acanthopterygii are marine or euryhaline fishes (see Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The results reconfirm a previous paper that indicated an evolutionary divergence had occurred between freshwater and marine or euryhaline fish β2M sequences [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>At the molecular level among the Actinopterygii fishes studied, Asian seabass, Japanese medaka and Japanese flounder sequences share synapomorphic amino acids at three sites: Thr73, (S6) Gly78 (loop between S6 and S7) and Asp82 (S7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Siberian sturgeon (Chondrost) resolves as the most basal lineage in agreement with other studies [21], [18], confirming this fish is the most primitive member of the subclass Actinopterygii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Indeed, a two-codon (residues 75 and 76 in the alignment) deletion is synapomorphic in all teleost β2M sequences in contrast to Siberian sturgeon β2M. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Given the preponderance of analytical results and qualitative comparative results, we suggest that the L. calcarifer β2M gene recovered here is likely to function similarly to previously characterized β2M genes, and that the protein it encodes acts as a light chain that binds non-covalently to the heavy chain of the MHC class I molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The two proteins would then create a complex with the antigen peptide and present the antigen to T cells to be destroyed by the immune mechanism [22]. β2M is also involved in stabilizing the MHC class I molecules [23], [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Since β2M is clearly most closely related to the IGc1-type domains of MHC class I and II, its gene must have been linked to that of the MHC at some point of evolution [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the similarity between the structures of β2M and the IGc1-type domains of MHC I and II suggests that they share a common ancestor encoded in MHC genes [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>In this study, we have identified the β2M gene in L. calcarifer and confirm its phylogenetic placement within a group of related fish species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>We believe that, as more fish β2M sequences become available, reanalysis of the data may be able to better resolve the evolutionary history of the seeming ecological divergence detected among fish sequences and that of the L. calcarifer β2M gene from the rest of the β2M gene tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Again, the overall utility of our approach in the detection, recovery and delineation of genes within L. calcarifer is emphasized by its success in our study of β2M. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The authors thank Azrol Ridzuan Abd Aziz for providing the β2M nucleotide sequence, Dr. Michael R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Fortsner for helpful discussion and revision of the manuscript and Mohd. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Zulqurnain Abd. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Razak for help with the figures. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Funding: Ministry of Science, Technology and Innovation (MOSTI), Malaysia under the Top-Down program (Project no. 05-02-02-T002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The funder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0013159-Bjorkman1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>1 BjorkmanPJSaperMASamraouiBBennettWSStromingerJL 1987 Structure of the human class I histocompatibility antigen, HLA-A2. Nature 329 506 512 3309677 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Coico1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>2 CoicoRSunshineGBenjaminiE 2003 Immunology A Short Course. New Jersey John Wiley &amp; Son, Inc 361  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Collins1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>3 CollinsRW 2004 Human MHC class I chain related (MIC) genes: their biological function and relevance to disease and transplantation. Eur J Immunogenet 31 105 114 15182323 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Ono1"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>4 OnoHFigueroaFO'hUiginCKleinJ 1993 Cloning of the β2-microglobulin gene in the zebrafish. Immunogenetics 38 1 10 8462988 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Hui1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>5 HuiFHTianYYRuoQYFengSGChunX 2006 cDNA cloning and genomic structure of grass carp (Ctenophayngodon idellus) B2-microglobulin gene. Fish Shellfish Immmunol 20 118 123  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Criscitiello1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>6 CriscitielloMFBenedettoRAntaoAWilsonMRChincharVG 1998 β2-microglobulin of Ictalurid catfishes. Immunogens 48 339 343  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Stewart1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>7 StewartROhtaYMinterRRGibbonsTHortonTL 2005 Cloning and characterization of Xenopus β2-microglobulin. Dev Comp Immunol 29 723 732 15854684 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Choi1"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>8 ChoiWLeeEYChoiTJ 2006 Cloning and sequence analysis of the β2-microglobulin transcript from flounder, Paralichthys olivaceous.  Mol Immunol 43 1565 1572 16257447 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Tan1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>9 TanSLMohd-AdnanAMohd-YusofNYForstnerMRJWanK-L 2008 Identification and analysis of a prepro-chicken gonadotropin releasing hormone II (preprocGnRH-II) precursor in the Asian seabass, Lates calcarifer, based on an EST-based assessment of its brain transcriptome. Gene 411 77 86 18280674 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Schultz1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>10 SchultzJMilpetzFBorkPPontingCP 1998 SMART, a simple modular architecture research tool: identification of signaling domain. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 95 5857 5864 9600884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Robert1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>11 RobertDFJainaMBenjaminSBSamGJVolkerH 2006 Pfam: clans, web tools and services. Nucleic Acids Res 34 247 251  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Hulo1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>12 HuloNBairochABulliardVCeruttiLDe CastroE 2006 The Prosite database. Nucleic Acids Res 34 227 230  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Eddy1"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>13 EddySR 1998 Profile hidden Markov models. Bioinformatics 14 755 763 9918945 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Durbin1"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>14 DurbinREddySKroghAMitchisonG 1998 Biological sequence analysis: probabilistic models of proteins and nucleic acids. United Kingdom Cambridge University Press 95  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Felsenstein1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>15 FelsensteinJ 1996 Inferring phylogenies from protein sequences by parsimony, distance, and likelihood methods. Methods Enzymol 266 418 427 8743697 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Tamura1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>16 TamuraKDudleyJNeiMKumarS 2007 MEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0. Mol Biol Evol 24 8 1596 1599 17488738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Becker1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>17 BeckerJWReekeGN 1985 Three-dimensional structure of β2-microglobulin. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 82 4225 4229 3889925 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Lundqvist1"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>18 LundqvistMLAppelkvistPHermsenTPilstromLStetRJM 1999 Characterization of beta-2-microglobulin in a primitive fish, the Siberian sturgeon (Acipenser baeri). Immunogenetics 50 1-2 79 83 10541811 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Cannon1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>19 CannonJPHaireRNLitmanGW 2002 Identification of diversified genes that contain immunoglobulin-like variable regions in a protochordate. Nat Immunol 3 12 1200 1207 12415263 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Benyamini1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>20 BenyaminiHGunasekaranKWolfsonHNussinovR 2003 β2-Microglobulin amyloidosis: insights from conservation analysis and fibril modeling by protein docking techniques. J Mol Biol 330 159 174 12818210 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Hurley1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>21 HurleyIAMuellerRLDunnKASchmidtEJFriedmanM 2007 A new time-scale for ray-finned fish evolution. Proc Biol Sci 274 489 498 17476768 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Hansen1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>22 HansenTHLeeDR 1997 Mechanism of class I assembly with β2-microglobulin and loading with peptide. Adv Immunol 64 105 137 9100981 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Van1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>23 VanKLAshtonRPGPloeghHLTonegawaS 1992 TAP1 mutant mice are deficient in antigen presentation, surface class molecules, and CD4-8+ cells. Cell 71 1205 1214 1473153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Zijlstra1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>24 ZijlstraMBixMSimisterNLoringJRauletD 1990 β2-Microglobulin deficient mice lack CD4-8+ cytolytic T cells. Nature 344 742 746 2139497 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Shum1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>25 ShumBPAzumiKZhangSKehrerSRRaisonRL 1996 Unexpected β2-microglobulin sequence diversity in individual rainbow trout. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 93 2779 2784 8610117 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Dixon1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>26 DixonBNagelkerkeLASibbingFAEgbertsEStetRJ 1996 Evolution of MHC class II beta chain-encoding genes in the Lake Tana barbel species flock (Barbus intermedius complex). Immunogenetics 44 6 419 431 8824153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Dixon2"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>27 DixonBVanESHMRodriguesPNSEgbertsEStetRJM 1993 Fish major histocompatibility complex genes: an expansion. Dev Comp Immunol 19 109 133  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Naruse1"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>28 NaruseKFukamachiSMitaniHKondoMMatsuokaT 2000 A detailed linkage map of medaka, Oryzias latipes: comparative genomics and genome evolution. Genetics 154 4 1773 1784 10747068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Vihtelic1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>29 VihtelicTSFadoolJMGaoJThorntonKAHydeDR 2005 Expressed sequence tag analysis of zebrafish eye tissues for NEIBank. Mol Vis 11 1083 1100 16379021 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Miska1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>30 MiskaKBHellmanLMillerRD 2003 Characterization of β2-microglobulin coding sequence from three non-placental mammals: the duckbill platypus, the short-beaked echidna, and the grey short-tailed opossum. Dev Comp Immunol 27 3 247 256 12590975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Riegert1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>31 RiegertPAndersenRBumsteadNDoehringCDominguez-SteglichM 1996 The chicken beta 2-microglobulin gene is located on a non-major histocompatibility complex microchromosome: a small, G+C-rich gene with X and Y boxes in the promoter. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 93 3 1243 1248 8577748 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Welinder1"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>32 WelinderKGJespersenHMWalther-RasmussenJSkjodtK 1991 Amino acid sequences and structures of chicken and turkey β2-microglobulin. Mol Immunol 28 1-2 177 182 2011126 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Western1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>33 WesternAHEckeryDCDemmerJJuengelJLMcNattyKP 2003 Expression of the FcRn receptor (and) gene homologues in the intestine of suckling brushtail possum (Trichosurus vulpecula) pouch young. Mol Immunol 39 20 707 717 12531282 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Groves1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>34 GrovesMLGreenbergR 1982 Complete amino acid sequence of bovine β2-microglobulin. J Biol Chem 257 5 2619 2626 6174509 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Ellis1"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>35 EllisSAMartinAJ 1993 Nucleotide sequence of horse β2-microglobulin cDNA. Immunogenetics 38 5 383 8344729 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Tallmadge1"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>36 TallmadgeRLLearTLJohnsonAKGuerinGMillonLV 2003 Characterization of the β2-microglobulin gene of the horse. Immunogenetics 54 10 725 733 12557059 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Daniel1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>37 DanielFMorelloDLe BailOChambonPCayreY 1983 Structure and expression of the mouse beta 2-microglobulin gene isolated from somatic and non-expressing teratocarcinoma cells. EMBO J 2 7 1061 1065 6354707 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Cole1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>38 ColeTDicksonPWEsnardFAverillSRisbridgerGP 1989 The cDNA structure and expression analysis of the genes for the cysteine proteinase inhibitor cystatin C and for β2-microglobulin in rat brain. Eur J Biochem 186 1-2 35 42 2689174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Gastinel1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>39 GastinelLNValenteGBjorkmanPJ 1992 cDNA sequence of CHO-KI hamster beta2-microglobulin. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 89 2 638 642 1530991 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Wolfe1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>40 WolfePBCebraJJ 1980 The primary structure of guinea pig β2-microglobulin. Mol Immunol 17 12 1493 1505 6170877 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Canavez1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>41 CanavezFCLadaskyJJMunizJASeuanezHNParhamP 1998 β2-Microglobulin in neotropical primates (Platyrrhini). Immunogenetics 48 2 133 140 9634477 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Canavez2"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>42 CanavezFCMoreiraMASimonFParhamPSeuanezHN 1999 Phylogenetic relationships of the Callitrichinae (Platyrrhini, primates) based on β2-microglobulin DNA sequence. Am J Primatol 48 3 225 236 10380996 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-York1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>43 YorkIAGrantEPDahlAMRockKL 2005 A mutant cell with a novel defect in MHC class I quality control. J Immunol 174 11 6839 6846 15905525 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Gussow1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>44 GussowDReinRGinjaarIHochstenbachFSeemanG 1987 The human β2-microglobulin gene, primary structure and definition of the transcriptional unit. J Immunol 139 3132 3138 3312414 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Milland1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>45 MillandJLovelandBEMcKenzieIF 1993 Isolation of a clone for pig β2-microglobulin cDNA. Immunogenetics 38 6 464 8406623 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0013159-Gates1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>46 GatesFTColiganJEKindtTJ 1979 Complete amino acid sequence of rabbit β2-microglobulin. Biochemistry 18 11 2267 2272 87220 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
