
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2923613</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20805886</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PONE-RA-19774R1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012260</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Immunology</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Complex Traits</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Disease Models</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Genetics of the Immune System</subject><subject>Immunology/Immune Response</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Unique DNA Repair Gene Variations and Potential Associations with the Primary Antibody Deficiency Syndromes IgAD and CVID </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">DNA Repair Defects &amp; CVID/IgAD</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Offer</surname><given-names>Steven M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pan-Hammarström</surname><given-names>Qiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hammarström</surname><given-names>Lennart</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>Reuben S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biochemistry, Molecular Biology, and Biophysics, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minnesota, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Division of Clinical Immunology, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Karolinska Institutet at Karolinska University Hospital Huddinge, Stockholm, Sweden</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Unutmaz</surname><given-names>Derya</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">New York University, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>rsh@umn.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: SMO QPH LH RSH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: SMO QPH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: SMO QPH LH RSH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SMO QPH LH RSH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: SMO RSH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Edited the paper: QPH LH. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>8</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e12260</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>7</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Offer et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Despite considerable effort, the genetic factors responsible for &gt;90% of the antibody deficiency syndromes IgAD and CVID remain elusive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>To produce a functionally diverse antibody repertoire B lymphocytes undergo class switch recombination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>This process is initiated by AID-catalyzed deamination of cytidine to uridine in switch region DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, these residues are recognized by the uracil excision enzyme UNG2 or the mismatch repair proteins MutSα (MSH2/MSH6) and MutLα (PMS2/MLH1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Further processing by ubiquitous DNA repair factors is thought to introduce DNA breaks, ultimately leading to class switch recombination and expression of a different antibody isotype. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Methodology/Principal Findings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Defects in AID and UNG2 have been shown to result in the primary immunodeficiency hyper-IgM syndrome, leading us to hypothesize that additional, potentially more subtle, DNA repair gene variations may underlie the clinically related antibody deficiencies syndromes IgAD and CVID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>In a survey of twenty-seven candidate DNA metabolism genes, markers in MSH2, RAD50, and RAD52 were associated with IgAD/CVID, prompting further investigation into these pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Resequencing identified four rare, non-synonymous alleles associated with IgAD/CVID, two in MLH1, one in RAD50, and one in NBS1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>One IgAD patient carried heterozygous non-synonymous mutations in MLH1, MSH2, and NBS1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Functional studies revealed that one of the identified mutations, a premature RAD50 stop codon (Q372X), confers increased sensitivity to ionizing radiation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Our results are consistent with a class switch recombination model in which AID-catalyzed uridines are processed by multiple DNA repair pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Genetic defects in these DNA repair pathways may contribute to IgAD and CVID. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Upon antigen stimulation, the constant region exons of the expressed antibody heavy chain gene can be replaced with downstream ones that encode an alternative antibody isotype (IgM -&gt; IgG, IgE or IgA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>At the molecular level, antibody class switch recombination (CSR) occurs between C/G-rich switch regions upstream of each set of constant region exons ( Figure 1 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In recent years a consensus model has emerged whereby CSR is initiated by activation-induced deaminase (AID)-catalyzed cytidine deamination to uridine within switch region DNA [1]–[5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>These DNA uridines are subsequently recognized and removed by the base excision repair enzyme uracil DNA glycosylase 2 (UNG2) or the mismatch repair proteins MutSα and MutLα (heterodimers of MSH2/MSH6 and MLH1/PMS2, respectively) [2], [6]–[13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Additional base excision repair, mismatch repair, and recombination repair factors are then proposed to help convert these DNA repair intermediates to double-strand breaks and ultimately to CSR products [14]–[19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0012260-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012260.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>A model for DNA break generation by repair enzymes in class switch recombination. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>AID initiates CSR by deaminating switch (S) region DNA cytosines to uracils (the µ and α constant regions are depicted). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>These uracils are recognized and excised by the base excision repair enzyme UNG2 or the mismatch repair complex consisting of MutSa (MSH2/MSH6) and MutLa (PMS2/MLH1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The endonuclease activity of APEX1 or the MRN complex (MRE11-RAD50-NBS1) could then convert UNG2-generated abasic sites to single-strand breaks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The mismatch repair pathway (MSH2/MSH6, EXO1, MLH1/PMS2) could also introduce single-strand breaks at mismatched G:U bases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Opposing single-strand breaks may naturally lead to double-strand breaks, which can be further processed by non-homologous end joining factors to yield a complete CSR event. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>A switch from IgM to IgA is depicted, and the intervening switch circle is not shown. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0012260.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>A subset of primary antibody deficiency syndromes has been explained by defects in these DNA repair pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>For instance, hyper-IgM syndrome type 2 (HIGM2) is caused by mutations in AID and this disease is characterized by high levels of IgM at the expense of the other antibody isotypes ([20]; reviewed in [21]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Mutations in UNG2 lead to the less severe HIGM5 [22], and defects in PMS2 have been associated with decreased antibody production [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Varying degrees of antibody deficiency have also been noted in chromosomal instability syndromes such as ataxia-telangiectasia (A-T, ATM mutations), Nijmegen breakage syndrome (NBS, NBS1 mutations), and ataxia-telangiectasia-like disorder (ATLD, MRE11 mutations) [24]–[30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Prior studies have shown that missense mutations that impair MSH5 binding to its obligate heterodimerization partner MSH4 associate with immunoglobulin A deficiency (IgAD) and common variable immunodeficiency (CVID) [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>IgAD and CVID often occur in different individuals of the same family, suggesting a common genetic components in at least a subset of patients [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Mutations in the B cell surface receptor genes TACI [33]–[35] and CD19 [36], [37], and the T cell receptor gene ICOS [38] are also responsible for a subset of CVID cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, despite this considerable progress, the genetic causes of &gt;90% of IgAD and CVID cases have yet to be identified (reviewed in [39]–[41]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Given that defects in DNA metabolism proteins are responsible for a fraction of primary antibody deficiencies, we hypothesized that variations in DNA repair genes could also underlie additional IgAD and CVID cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>To test this hypothesis, we performed a genetic association study of 27 candidate DNA metabolism genes in IgAD/CVID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Based on those results, we sequenced selected genes in a panel of 96 IgAD/CVID patients and subsequently genotyped the non-synonymous alleles we identified in a large case-control association study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Novel coding and non-coding variations were detected in several genes, including seven rare variants found only in IgAD and two specific to CVID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Four of these mutations, MLH1-S247A, MLH1-Q409P, NBS1-P401R, and RAD50-Q372X showed significant association with IgAD/CVID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>One IgAD patient carried three previously unreported mutations, MSH2-A727S, MLH1-G638R, and NBS1-P401R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>A second IgAD patient was compound heterozygous for RAD50-P165H and the previously reported RAD50-R327H variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Two novel single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in the 3′ untranslated region of MRE11 were also associated with CVID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Finally, both patient-derived and purposefully engineered cells harboring the RAD50-Q372X mutation exhibited increased sensitivity to ionizing radiation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>IgAD/CVID association screen of 27 DNA repair genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>To screen for candidate genes in IgAD and CVID, we genotyped 140 IgAD patients, 48 CVID patients, and 92 healthy controls for SNPs selected from 26 known DNA repair genes and AID (collectively these genes define several DNA metabolism pathways). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>To test if a given SNP was associated with IgAD and/or CVID, allele frequencies were compared to the healthy control cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Significant single marker associations with IgAD and/or CVID (p&lt;0.01) were noted for SNPs in the mismatch repair complexes, MutSα, MutSβ, and MutSγ, the MRN complex, the extended RAD52 epistasis group, and AID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>A summary of single marker associations with p-values &lt;0.01 is presented in  Table 1 . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Full association data can be found in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0012260-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012260.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>SNPs in multiple DNA repair genes associate with IgAD/CVID. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0012260-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0012260.t001"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>a</label><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>) Corrected for multiple testing bias by permutation testing as described in Materials and Methods. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>b</label><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>) Corrected p-values derived using MutSα complex SNPs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>c</label><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>) No permutations exceeded those observed for SNP rs805304. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>To further refine the list of candidates, we performed a relaxed correction for multiple testing by permutation testing markers grouped by DNA repair complex or pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>After applying this statistical method, 13 SNPs remained significantly associated with IgAD/CVID ( Table 1 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Markers in RAD54B (rs3019279), AID (rs2580874 and rs714629) showed significant association with the combined IgAD/CVID cohort, and SNPs in MSH2 (rs3771276 and rs6729015), RAD50 (rs2237060), and RAD52 (rs10849605) were associated with IgAD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>In agreement with our prior studies, six markers in the MHC class III region gene MSH5 were associated with IgAD [31]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Next, we constructed multi-marker haplotypes and tested for association with IgAD and/or CVID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The markers comprising each haplotype block are listed in Table S2 and association data for haplotypes with a frequency greater than 0.1% are reported in Table S3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Significantly associated haplotypes with an uncorrected p-value less than 0.01 are summarized in  Table 2 . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>After pathway-based permutation testing, haplotypes of MLH1, MSH5, and MUS81 were associated with IgAD and the combined IgAD/CVID group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Association with CVID was noted for haplotypes of MSH2 and RAD50. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0012260-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012260.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Haplotypes blocks in MLH1, MSH2, RAD50, and RAD54B associate with IgAD/CVID. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0012260-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0012260.t002"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label>a</label><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>) Corrected for multiple testing bias by permutation testing as described in Materials and Methods. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Identification of novel IgAD/CVID alleles </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Since notable IgAD/CVID associations were observed for genes encoding DNA repair proteins that could convert AID-catalyzed uracils into DNA breaks, we resequenced select DNA repair genes in IgAD and CVID patient samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Specifically, we sequenced the MutSα genes MSH2 and MSH6, the MutLα gene MLH1, and the MRN complex genes MRE11, RAD50, and NBS1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The genes encoding AID, APEX1, ERCC1, and RAD52 were also sequenced. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>In all, 242 genetic variants were detected, of which, 93 did not have records in dbSNP or SwissProt and were therefore considered novel (Table S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>24 alleles encoded amino acid changes, 13 of which were previously unreported (all detected in a heterozygous state). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Of the remaining 80 novel SNPs, 5 were synonymous coding alleles, 31 were located in mRNA untranslated regions (UTRs), 40 were intronic, and 4 were in flanking non-transcribed regions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>We next determined the allele frequencies of identified non-synonymous alleles and selected UTR, synonymous, and intronic SNPs in a large cohort of healthy controls, IgAD patients, and CVID patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The most significant data are summarized in  Table 3 , and full datasets can be found in Table S5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>In the mismatch repair pathway, two novel MSH2 variations were discovered in IgAD samples: MSH2-T292S and MSH2-A727S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The latter variation was unique to a single IgAD patient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Four novel amino acid mutations were detected in MLH1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>MLH1-S247A and MLH1-G638R were specific to IgAD and MLH1-Q409P was specific to CVID ( Table 3 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>MLH1-H727L and the previously reported mutations MLH1-K618A, MLH1-V716M, and MLH1-I219V occurred at similar frequencies in IgAD/CVID patients and controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0012260-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012260.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Genetic association of SNPs identified by reseqencing. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0012260-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0012260.t003"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt105"><label>a</label><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>) A single IgAD patient carried all four alleles, MLH1-G638R, MSH2-A727S, NBS1-P401R, and the intronic SNP rs104895039. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The most striking variations were observed in RAD50. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>In all, 16 novel SNPs were found: 3 encoded amino acid changes, 2 were located in the 5′ UTR, 1 was synonymous, and 10 were intronic (Table S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Most notably a single CVID sample contained the heterozygous transition mutation (1114C&gt;T) that creates a premature stop codon at amino acid 372 (RAD50-Q372X,  Table 3 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>One IgAD patient carried RAD50-R1077Q and another had both RAD50-P165H and RAD50-R327H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>RAD50-R327H was also detected in our control samples, but never linked with RAD50-P165H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Pedigree analysis of the RAD50-P165H/R327H patient revealed that the two alleles were present in a compound heterozygous state. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Novel variations were also detected in the other two MRN complex genes, MRE11 and NBS1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>In MRE11, 18 novel SNPs were detected (Table S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Of these, two resulted in amino acid changes (MRE11-A492D and MRE11-E494K), eight were in the 3′ UTR, and eight were intronic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Both MRE11-A492D and MRE11-E494K were found at similar frequencies in controls and IgAD/CVID cases ( Table 3 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Two 3′ UTR SNPs, ss206257789 and ss206257804, were, however, significantly enriched in the CVID population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>In NBS1, 11 unreported SNPs were detected (Table S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Three were non-synonymous, and the remaining 8 were a mixture of synonymous, 5′ UTR, 3′ UTR, and intronic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Two novel alleles, NBS1-P401R and NBS1-D527Y, were specific to IgAD ( Table 3 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>NBS1-V210F and NBS1-L421S were detected in IgAD/CVID and control samples, as was the previously reported common polymorphism, rs1805794 (NBS1-E185Q). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>A number of previously unreported SNPs were also discovered in other genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>In AID, two novel 3′ UTR SNPs and three novel synonymous SNPs were detected (Table S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Two novel SNPs were found in APEX1, one synonymous and one in the 5′ UTR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The previously reported 5′ UTR SNP rs2307490 showed modest association with CVID ( Table 3 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>In ERCC1, one 3′ flanking SNP and five novel intronic SNPs were detected (Table S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>18 new SNPs were discovered in RAD52, 14 in the 3′ UTR, and four in introns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>No amino acid substitution mutations variations were detected in these four genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>While no patients were homozygous for any single SNP, some patients were found to carry mutant alleles in more than one DNA repair gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>An IgAD patient heterozygous for the previously reported APEX1-Q51H allele also carried three novel mutations, MLH1-G638R, MSH2-A727S, and NBS1-P401R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>One IgAD patient carried both RAD50-R1077Q and MLH1-K618A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Additionally, as described earlier, an IgAD patient was found to be biallelic for RAD50-P165H and RAD50-R327H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>These observations hint that the combinatorial effects of multiple mutations may underlie a subset of IgAD/CVID cases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>RAD50-Q372X confers sensitivity to ionizing radiation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Since CSR is likely to involve DNA breakage and end processing by exonucleases, we next decided to test the effect of one of the identified mutations (RAD50-Q372X) on cellular DNA repair capacity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>To this end, immortalized B lymphoblast lines were generated from the CVID patient carrying RAD50-Q372X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Immunoblotting experiments indicated that RAD50 protein levels were reduced approximately 2-fold compared to three similarly derived cell lines from individuals with no detected RAD50 mutation ( Figure 2a ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>MRE11 levels were also reduced approximately 2-fold, consistent with prior reports indicating that all three components of the MRN complex are subject to coordinated post-translational regulation [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Compared to a control EBV immortalized cell line, the Q372X cells were modestly, but significantly, sensitive to higher doses of ionizing radiation, but not to the extent of cells derived from an ataxia telangiectasia patient ( Figure 2b ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0012260-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012260.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Heterozygous RAD50-Q372X cells show increased sensitivity to ionizing radiation. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>(A) Immunoblot of lysates from lymphoblast cell lines derived from the CVID patient carrying RAD50-Q372X and three CVID patients with no mutations in RAD50, MRE11, or NBS1 (wildtype, wtRAD50). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>(B) Viability of patient derived cell lines after exposure to ionizing radiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Lymphoblast cell lines from the RAD50-Q372X patient (diamonds) and a CVID patient with no mutations in RAD50, MRE11, or NBS1 (triangles) were exposed to the indicated doses of ionizing radiation and cell viability was assessed by Propidium Iodide staining and flow cytometry 10 days post-exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The Coriell cell line GM08436 (filled circles), containing heterozygous truncating mutations in ATM, was included as a positive control (Coriell Cell Repositories). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Error bars denote the standard error of triplicate treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>(C) The targeting strategy used to introduce the c.1114C&gt;T mutation into the endogenous RAD50 locus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Exons 7, 8, and 9 are depicted by boxes, and the position of c.1114C&gt;T in exon 8 is marked. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>(D) Ionizing radiation sensitivity profiles of G418 resistant targeted clones with c.1114C&gt;T (diamonds) or a wildtype RAD50 exon 8 (triangles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>It is notable that both of these clones have properly integrated drug resistance cassette, and they only differ by whether or not the flanking C-to-T mutation was co-recombined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The parental HCT116 cell line shows an ionizing sensitivity profile superimposable with that of the wildtype exon 8 clone (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>DNA-PKcs-deficient cells [42] (circles) are extremely IR sensitive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent the standard error of the mean sensitivity of four independent subclones (each assayed in duplicate). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0012260.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>To overcome the natural variability associated with patient-derived cell lines, we asked if we could recapitulate the sensitivity to ionizing radiation by introducing the RAD50 c.1114C&gt;T mutation encoding for RAD50-Q372X into the endogenous locus of an immortalized human colon cancer cell line HCT116 ( Figure 2c ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>HCT116 is a near-diploid line that has been used extensively in gene targeting experiments, particularly for studies of DNA metabolism proteins [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Targeting events were identified by insertion-specific PCR and confirmed by Southern blot using a flanking probe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Specific incorporation of the c.1114C&gt;T mutation was confirmed by sequencing insertion-specific PCR products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Cells containing the heterozygous c.1114C&gt;T mutation displayed an increased sensitivity to ionizing radiation compared to the control parental line, non-targeted sister clones, or targeted sister clones in which the mutation was not integrated ( Figure 2d  and data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>In comparison, a DNA-PKcs-deficient HCT116 cell line showed higher levels of ionizing radiation sensitivity [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>These results demonstrate that the RAD50-Q372X mutation impairs the ability of the MRN complex to repair ionizing radiation-induced DNA double strand breaks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>We have shown that variations in multiple DNA repair pathways show association with the primary immunodeficiency syndromes CVID and IgAD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge this is the first report associating immunodeficiency with markers in many of these genes, notably MSH2, MLH1, and RAD50. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>We also identified new non-synonymous alleles of MSH2, MLH1, RAD50, and NBS1, and UTR SNPs in RAD50 and MRE11 that were unique to IgAD and/or CVID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Cells carrying one of these mutations, RAD50-Q372X, were incapable of wildtype levels of recombination repair, likely due to haploinsufficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Overall, these data suggest that variations in the mismatch and recombination repair pathways may underlie some IgAD and CVID cases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Mismatch repair proteins directly recognize and excise single base DNA mismatches and short patches of mismatched DNA (reviewed in [43]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Genetically, the involvement of mismatch repair in CSR has been well established in mice, with the most prominent defects observed in animals that also lack the uracil excision repair protein UNG2 [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Humans with heterozygous inactivating mutations in the mismatch repair proteins MSH2, MSH6, MLH1, or PMS2 are at increased risk for developing hereditary non-polyposis colorectal cancer (HNPCC) [44], [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>IgA deficiency has been noted in a handful of HNPCC patients, one with a homozygous MSH2 mutation [46] and three with biallelic MSH6 mutations [47], [48]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Our results are consistent with a role for mismatch repair in CSR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Most of the IgAD/CVID-specific alleles that we detected in the mismatch repair pathway are located in functionally important domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>MSH2-A727S maps to a conserved ABC domain (amino acids 718-731) that is predicted to be involved in ATP hydrolysis [49] ( Figure 3 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Two of the three IgAD/CVID specific mutations identified in MLH1 map to domains of known importance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>MLH1-S247A is located in a region that has both nucleotide hydrolysis and signal transduction functions [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Mutation of this residue to proline (S247P) has been reported in 14 HNPCC2 patients and is associated with decreased MLH1 protein expression and impaired mismatch repair activity using an in-vitro assay [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>MLH1-G638R introduces a positively charged amino acid into a neutral area of the region known to be important for interaction with PMS2, MLH1, and PMS1 [52], [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, two additional rare alleles that we detected in both IgAD/CVID cases and control samples were previously identified and characterized in HNPCC studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>MLH1-K618A was suggested to bind less efficiently to PMS2 [54], however follow-up studies with this allele found PMS2 binding and overall mismatch repair function to be normal [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The MLH1-V716M variant has been suggested to be a protective allele, as it was found enriched in controls compared to HNPCC cases [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results indicate that cancer predisposition alleles that are DNA damage sensitizing may also perturb the ability of the DNA repair pathways to elicit CSR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0012260-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012260.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Location of the amino acid variations in the mismatch repair proteins MSH2 and MLH1. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>(A) MSH2 is divided into four domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>MutSI, II, and III represent a DNA binding globular region, an RNaseH-like motif, and a major structured domain, respectively, revealed by the Thermus aquaticus MutS crystal structure [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The fourth domain is an ABC-type ATPase domain [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>(B) MLH1 has three domains, a histidine kinase-like ATPase domain (HATP), a MutL transducer domain (MutL-T), which is homologous to a domain in DNA gyrase B, and a PMS2 interaction domain (PMS2-ID). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The indicated amino acid variations lie within conserved regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Mutations associated with IgAD or CVID are denoted by †, those that were unique to the IgAD/CVID cohort but did not reach statistical significance are denoted by ‡. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The illustrated protein segments were derived from ClustalW reference sequence alignments of the human, mouse, chicken and zebrafish proteins (MSH2, NP_000242, NP_032654, XP_426110, and NP_998689; MLH1, NP_000240, NP_081086, XP_418828, and NP_956953). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0012260.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Our results are the first to implicate MRN defects in IgAD/CVID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The premature stop codon encoded by the RAD50-Q372X allele likely leads to nonsense-mediated decay of the mRNA and haploinsufficiency ( Figure 4 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Other identified mutations may slightly perturb the structure and/or function of the MRN complex, and could act as weak hypomorphic alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The RAD50-P165H mutation replaces a neutral, non-polar proline with a positively charged, polar histidine at a position that is evolutionarily conserved through vertebrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>This residue is just outside of the N-terminal NTPase-containing globular domain and at the edge of the region that is thought to be important for interaction with MRE11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>At the edge of the N-terminal MRE11-interating domain, RAD50-R1077Q replaces a conserved, positively charged arginine with a neutral glutamine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>RAD50-R327H, which by itself did not associate with IgAD/CVID, exchanges one neutral, polar residue for another in the N-terminal coiled-coil domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Neither of the additional IgAD/CVID-specific alleles detected in the MRN complex, NBS1-P401R and NBS1-D527Y, disrupt known or predicted functionally important protein domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Future studies on the detected MRN alleles will provide greater insight into how they functionally impact recombination repair and CSR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0012260-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012260.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Location of the amino acid variations in the recombination proteins MRE11, RAD50, and NBS1. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>(A) A schematic of the MRN complex, indicating two copies of each protein and the extended coil-coil and zinc hook domains of RAD50. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>(B, C, &amp; D) Schematics depicting the major protein domains of RAD50, MRE11, and NBS1, with the IgAD/CVID amino acid variations shown below aligned to the homologous regions of mouse, chicken, and zebrafish proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>RAD50 has an N-terminal Walker A-type ATPase and DNA binding domain (ABC), three coiled-coil regions (CC), a zinc-hook (Zn), and a C-terminal Walker B-type ATPase and DNA binding domain (ABC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>MRE11 has a protein phosphatase 2A-like catalytic domain (PP2AC) and a DNA binding domain (DNA BD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>NBS1 has forkhead homology region (FHA) and a BRCA1 C-terminus-like domain (BRCT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>A box in NBS1 indicates the location containing most of the mutations responsible for Nijmegen breakage syndrome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Mutations associated with IgAD or CVID are denoted by †, those that were unique to the IgAD/CVID cohort but did not reach statistical significance are denoted by ‡. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The illustrated protein segments were derived from ClustalW reference sequence alignments (RAD50, NP_005723, NP_033038, XP_414645, and XP_696859; MRE11, NP_005582, NP_061206, NP_990109, and NP_001001407; NBS1, NP_002476, NP_038780, NP_989668, and NP_001014819). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0012260.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The association noted for two markers in AID suggests that a subclass of IgAD/CVID syndromes may be due to variations at this locus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>These markers may be linked to undiscovered alleles that impact the expression of functional AID. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>This could be due to variations that create splice variants, UTR mutations that impact mRNA stability and protein expression, or mutations that impact transcription of AID, including alterations to transcription factor binding sites or sites important for epigenetic modulation of expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>In these studies, we identified two novel SNPs in the AID UTR and three novel synonymous mutations (Table S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>The further studies of these alleles may yield that some IgAD/CVID patients represent a new subclass of Hyper-IgM type 2 patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Overall, these studies suggest that, like many cancer predisposition syndromes such as HNPCC, IgAD and CVID may be a heterogeneous class of diseases due to defects in multiple pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Rather than straightforward causal alleles giving rise to disease, IgAD and CVID alleles likely represent risk factors that predispose an individual to developing immune deficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Additional studies to determine what effects these unique variations have on DNA repair and CSR are ongoing and long-term. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Ethics Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The Karolinska Institutet human subjects research review board provided written approval for the informed collection of DNA samples from CVID/IgAD patients for sequence analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The sample identities were unknown to the University of Minnesota team and therefore this arm of the project was exempt from institutional review. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Human DNA samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The initial association screen was performed in DNA from 140 IgAD patients, 48 CVID patients, and 92 healthy controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>To characterize all coding variation for the selected candidate genes in the CVID population, genomic resequencing was performed in 58 CVID DNAs, 48 from the original population and 10 that were subsequently recruited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>38 IgAD patients, each carrying at least one allele/haplotype associating with disease, were also included. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>334 IgAD patients, 108 CVID patients, and 991 healthy controls were used for the subsequent large genetic association study of detected non-synonymous SNPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Where adequate DNA was available, samples that had been used for earlier studies were utilized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>All DNA samples used in this study were collected from unrelated individuals of self-reported Swedish descent and isolated at the Karolinska Institutet (Stockholm, Sweden). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Informed consent was obtained from all subjects, and these studies were approved by the Karolinska Institutet human subjects research institutional review board. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>SNP selection and genotyping </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>For the initial association screen, tag SNPs were selected to cover the genomic locus of each gene plus an additional 10 kb upstream and 5 kb downstream using Tagger [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>As phase II hapmap data was not yet available at the time, phase I data was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Additional non-tag SNPs were included to fill out the assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Genotypes were determined using the Illumina GoldenGate platform at the Broad Institute. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Of the 384 markers genotyped, 81 failed to pass quality control tests and were not used in subsequent studies (Table S6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Two markers rs2020908 and rs689754 deviated significantly from Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium in the control DNA set (p&lt;0.001), and 79 markers had genotype call rates that were below the 90% confidence threshold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Therefore, a total of 303 SNPs passed quality control criteria and were used in the subsequent studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>For the large genetic association study, genotyping was performed by the BioMedical Genomics Center at the University of Minnesota. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Two Sequenom iPLEX gold genotyping assays were designed using Spectrodesigner, part of the MassARRAY software package, to include non-synonymous coding SNPs detected by resequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Assays were filled out by including synonymous coding SNPs, UTR SNPs, and intronic SNPs located within 10 bases of an exon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Primers were synthesized by IDT and sequences are available upon request. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>DNA repair gene resequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Primer design, sequencing, and polymorphism detection were performed by the Broad Institute Center for Genotyping and Analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Briefly, primers were designed for each target gene to sequence the known exons, the 5′ UTR, and the 3′UTR, with at least 100 nucleotides of flanking sequence on each side. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Genetic variants were identified by a combination of the PolyPhred and PolyDhan programs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Primer sequences for each assay are available upon request. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>To increase the power to detect informative alleles, the sample set was enriched for DNAs that carried disease-associated single markers and haplotypes as determined in the initial genotyping screen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>In all, 3,086,784 nucleotides were examined, with average 1× coverage of 92.0% and 2× coverage of 88.4% (Tables S7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>All novel non-synonymous SNPs were confirmed by fluorescence-based Sanger di-deoxy sequencing at either the University of Minnesota Sequencing and Analysis Facility or the Macrogen Company (South Korea). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Data processing and statistical analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>For both genotyping studies, allele calls were made using the appropriate built-in automatic allele calling specific to each platform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Call clustering was inspected manually and adjusted when obvious calling errors were made by the software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>For genetic association studies, we required that each SNP have a missing genotype rate &lt;10% and, in controls, have a Hardy-Weinberg p-value &gt;0.001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Samples were excluded if genotyping failed for &gt;50% of markers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Haploview was used to determine haplotype structure from control genotypes and to perform association testing for both single markers and haplotypes [57]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>To correct for multiple testing bias, association results were subjected to 100,000 permutation tests by pathway using Haploview. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>For this analysis, genes were grouped based on functional pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Each group that contained at least one marker or haplotype with an uncorrected p-value &lt;0.01 was permuted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>These pathways were MutSα (MSH2 and MSH6), MutSβ (MSH2 and MSH3), MutLα (MLH1 and PMS2), MRN (MRE11, RAD50, NBS1), MutSγ (MSH4 and MSH5), and RAD51-mediated homologous recombination (RAD51, RAD52, RAD54B, DMC1, and BLM). AID and MUS81 were permuted on an individual gene basis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Permutation testing was conducted for SNPs and haplotypes independently. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>RAD50-Q372X heterozygous cell lines </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>EBV-immortalized lymphoblast lines were generated at the Karolinska Institutet (Stockholm, Sweden). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>The HCT116-RAD50-c.1114C&gt;T (Q372X) knock-in cell line and a wildtype knockin control line were generated using recombinant adeno-associated virus (rAAV)-assisted gene targeting, as previously described [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Briefly, targeting arms were amplified from genomic DNA by PCR and cloned into pJET1.2 (CloneJet PCR kit, Fermentas). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Site directed mutagenesis was used to introduce the RAD50 c.1114C&gt;T stop mutation and targeting arms were assembled into pNeDaKO [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>rAAV was produced in HEK-293T cells and used to transduce HCT116 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>The resulting G418-resistant clones were screened for targeted insertion by PCR and confirmed by Southern blotting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>The introduction of the mutation was confirmed by sequencing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Immunoblots and ionizing radiation sensitivity experiments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Cell extracts were prepared using RIPA buffer, fractionated by SDS PAGE, and transferred to PVDF membrane for immunoblotting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The membranes were probed with antibodies to RAD50 (Novus), MRE11 (Genetex), or tubulin (Bethyl) followed by appropriate HRP-conjugated secondary antibodies (BioRad). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Radiation sensitivity assays were conducted exposing cultures in a cesium irradiator for the indicated doses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Cell viability was assayed by Propidium Iodide staining and flow cytometry (lymphoblasts) or crystal violet colony staining of plated dilutions (HCT116 cells) [42]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0012260.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>(0.12 MB PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0012260.s001.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0012260.s002"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>(0.04 MB PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0012260.s002.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0012260.s003"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>(0.09 MB PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0012260.s003.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0012260.s004"><label>Table S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>(0.07 MB PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0012260.s004.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0012260.s005"><label>Table S5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>(0.05 MB PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0012260.s005.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0012260.s006"><label>Table S6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>(0.11 MB PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0012260.s006.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0012260.s007"><label>Table S7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>(0.04 MB PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0012260.s007.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>We thank T.W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Behrens, R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Ferreira, and R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Graham for initiating aspects of these studies, A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Kotnis for confirming some of the rare alleles, the Broad Institute for Illumina genotyping and DNA sequencing, the University of Minnesota Biostatistics and Informatics Shared Resource for statistical support, the University of Minnesota Supercomputing Institute for computational support, and the University of Minnesota BioMedical Genomics Center for Sequenom genotyping. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Funding: This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health (U19 AI067152 to L.H., R21 AI079743 and R01 GM80437 to R.H.) and by Swedish Cancerfound (to Q.P.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>S.M.O. was also supported in part by a University of Minnesota Graduate School Doctoral Dissertation Fellowship and by the Curtis L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Carlson University of Minnesota/Karolinska Institutet Medical Research and Education Program Award. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0012260-Muramatsu1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>1 MuramatsuMKinoshitaKFagarasanSYamadaSShinkaiY 2000 Class switch recombination and hypermutation require activation-induced cytidine deaminase (AID), a potential RNA editing enzyme. Cell 102 553 563 11007474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-PetersenMahrt1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>2 Petersen-MahrtSKHarrisRSNeubergerMS 2002 AID mutates E. coli suggesting a DNA deamination mechanism for antibody diversification. Nature 418 99 103 12097915 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Bransteitter1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>3 BransteitterRPhamPScharffMDGoodmanMF 2003 Activation-induced cytidine deaminase deaminates deoxycytidine on single-stranded DNA but requires the action of RNase. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 100 4102 4107 12651944 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Chaudhuri1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>4 ChaudhuriJTianMKhuongCChuaKPinaudE 2003 Transcription-targeted DNA deamination by the AID antibody diversification enzyme. Nature 422 726 730 12692563 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Rada1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>5 RadaCDi NoiaJMNeubergerMS 2004 Mismatch recognition and uracil excision provide complementary paths to both Ig switching and the A/T-focused phase of somatic mutation. Mol Cell 16 163 171 15494304 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Rada2"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>6 RadaCWilliamsGTNilsenHBarnesDELindahlT 2002 Immunoglobulin isotype switching is inhibited and somatic hypermutation perturbed in UNG-deficient mice. Curr Biol 12 1748 1755 12401169 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Schrader1"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>7 SchraderCELinehanEKMochegovaSNWoodlandRTStavnezerJ 2005 Inducible DNA breaks in Ig S regions are dependent on AID and UNG. J Exp Med 202 561 568 16103411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Ehrenstein1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>8 EhrensteinMRNeubergerMS 1999 Deficiency in Msh2 affects the efficiency and local sequence specificity of immunoglobulin class-switch recombination: parallels with somatic hypermutation. EMBO J 18 3484 3490 10369687 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Ehrenstein2"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>9 EhrensteinMRRadaCJonesAMMilsteinCNeubergerMS 2001 Switch junction sequences in PMS2-deficient mice reveal a microhomology-mediated mechanism of Ig class switch recombination. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 98 14553 14558 11717399 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Li1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>10 LiZSchererSJRonaiDIglesias-UsselMDPeledJU 2004 Examination of Msh6- and Msh3-deficient mice in class switching reveals overlapping and distinct roles of MutS homologues in antibody diversification. J Exp Med 200 47 59 15238604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Martin1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>11 MartinALiZLinDPBardwellPDIglesias-UsselMD 2003 Msh2 ATPase activity is essential for somatic hypermutation at A-T basepairs and for efficient class switch recombination. J Exp Med 198 1171 1178 14568978 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Martomo1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>12 MartomoSAYangWWGearhartPJ 2004 A role for Msh6 but not Msh3 in somatic hypermutation and class switch recombination. J Exp Med 200 61 68 15238605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Schrader2"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>13 SchraderCEEdelmannWKucherlapatiRStavnezerJ 1999 Reduced isotype switching in splenic B cells from mice deficient in mismatch repair enzymes. J Exp Med 190 323 330 10430621 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Honjo1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>14 HonjoTMuramatsuMFagarasanS 2004 AID: how does it aid antibody diversity? Immunity 20 659 668 15189732 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Chaudhuri2"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>15 ChaudhuriJAltFW 2004 Class-switch recombination: interplay of transcription, DNA deamination and DNA repair. Nat Rev Immunol 4 541 552 15229473 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Maizels1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>16 MaizelsN 2005 Immunoglobulin gene diversification. Annu Rev Genet 39 23 46 16285851 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Longerich1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>17 LongerichSBasuUAltFStorbU 2006 AID in somatic hypermutation and class switch recombination. Curr Opin Immunol 18 164 174 16464563 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Stavnezer1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>18 StavnezerJGuikemaJESchraderCE 2008 Mechanism and regulation of class switch recombination. Annu Rev Immunol 26 261 292 18370922 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Neuberger1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>19 NeubergerMS 2008 Antibody diversification by somatic mutation: from Burnet onwards. Immunol Cell Biol 86 124 132 18180793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Revy1"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>20 RevyPMutoTLevyYGeissmannFPlebaniA 2000 Activation-induced cytidine deaminase (AID) deficiency causes the autosomal recessive form of the Hyper-IgM syndrome (HIGM2). Cell 102 565 575 11007475 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Durandy1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>21 DurandyAPeronSFischerA 2006 Hyper-IgM syndromes. Curr Opin Rheumatol 18 369 376 16763457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Imai1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>22 ImaiKSlupphaugGLeeWIRevyPNonoyamaS 2003 Human uracil-DNA glycosylase deficiency associated with profoundly impaired immunoglobulin class-switch recombination. Nat Immunol 4 1023 1028 12958596 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Peron1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>23 PeronSMetinAGardesPAlyanakianMASheridanE 2008 Human PMS2 deficiency is associated with impaired immunoglobulin class switch recombination. J Exp Med 205 2465 2472 18824584 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Concannon1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>24 ConcannonPGattiRA 1997 Diversity of ATM gene mutations detected in patients with ataxia-telangiectasia. Hum Mutat 10 100 107 9259193 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Savitsky1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>25 SavitskyKBar-ShiraAGiladSRotmanGZivY 1995 A single ataxia telangiectasia gene with a product similar to PI-3 kinase. Science 268 1749 1753 7792600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Pan1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>26 PanQPetit-FrereCLahdesmakiAGregorekHChrzanowskaKH 2002 Alternative end joining during switch recombination in patients with ataxia-telangiectasia. Eur J Immunol 32 1300 1308 11981817 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Stewart1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>27 StewartGSMaserRSStankovicTBressanDAKaplanMI 1999 The DNA double-strand break repair gene hMRE11 is mutated in individuals with an ataxia-telangiectasia-like disorder. Cell 99 577 587 10612394 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Varon1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>28 VaronRVissingaCPlatzerMCerosalettiKMChrzanowskaKH 1998 Nibrin, a novel DNA double-strand break repair protein, is mutated in Nijmegen breakage syndrome. Cell 93 467 476 9590180 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Carney1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>29 CarneyJPMaserRSOlivaresHDavisEMLe BeauM 1998 The hMre11/hRad50 protein complex and Nijmegen breakage syndrome: linkage of double-strand break repair to the cellular DNA damage response. Cell 93 477 486 9590181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Lahdesmaki1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>30 LahdesmakiATaylorAMChrzanowskaKHPan-HammarströmQ 2004 Delineation of the role of the Mre11 complex in class switch recombination. J Biol Chem 279 16479 16487 14747472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Sekine1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>31 SekineHFerreiraRCPan-HammarströmQGrahamRRZiembaB 2007 Role for Msh5 in the regulation of Ig class switch recombination. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 104 7193 7198 17409188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Vorechovsky1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>32 VorechovskyIZetterquistHPaganelliRKoskinenSWebsterAD 1995 Family and linkage study of selective IgA deficiency and common variable immunodeficiency. Clin Immunol Immunopathol 77 185 192 7586726 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Salzer1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>33 SalzerUChapelHMWebsterADPan-HammarströmQSchmitt-GraeffA 2005 Mutations in TNFRSF13B encoding TACI are associated with common variable immunodeficiency in humans. Nat Genet 37 820 828 16007087 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Castigli1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>34 CastigliEWilsonSAGaribyanLRachidRBonillaF 2005 TACI is mutant in common variable immunodeficiency and IgA deficiency. Nat Genet 37 829 834 16007086 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-PanHammarstrm1"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>35 Pan-HammarströmQSalzerUDuLBjorkanderJCunningham-RundlesC 2007 Reexamining the role of TACI coding variants in common variable immunodeficiency and selective IgA deficiency. Nat Genet 39 429 430 17392797 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-vanZelm1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>36 van ZelmMCReisliIvan der BurgMCastanoDvan NoeselCJ 2006 An antibody-deficiency syndrome due to mutations in the CD19 gene. N Engl J Med 354 1901 1912 16672701 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Kanegane1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>37 KaneganeHAgematsuKFutataniTSiraMMSugaK 2007 Novel mutations in a Japanese patient with CD19 deficiency. Genes Immun 8 663 670 17882224 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Grimbacher1"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>38 GrimbacherBHutloffASchlesierMGlockerEWarnatzK 2003 Homozygous loss of ICOS is associated with adult-onset common variable immunodeficiency. Nat Immunol 4 261 268 12577056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-PanHammarstrm2"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>39 Pan-HammarströmQHammarströmL 2008 Antibody deficiency diseases. Eur J Immunol 38 327 333 18200502 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Schaffer1"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>40 SchafferAASalzerUHammarströmLGrimbacherB 2007 Deconstructing common variable immunodeficiency by genetic analysis. Curr Opin Genet Dev 17 201 212 17467261 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Yong1"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>41 YongPFCheeRGrimbacherB 2008 Hypogammaglobulinaemia. Immunol Allergy Clin North Am 28 691 713, vii 18940570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Ruis1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>42 RuisBLFattahKRHendricksonEA 2008 The catalytic subunit of DNA-dependent protein kinase regulates proliferation, telomere length, and genomic stability in human somatic cells. Mol Cell Biol 28 6182 6195 18710952 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Kunz1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>43 KunzCSaitoYScharP 2009 DNA Repair in mammalian cells: Mismatched repair: variations on a theme. Cell Mol Life Sci 66 1021 1038 19153655 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Lynch1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>44 LynchHTde la ChapelleA 2003 Hereditary colorectal cancer. N Engl J Med 348 919 932 12621137 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Watson1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>45 WatsonPLynchHT 1994 The tumor spectrum in HNPCC. Anticancer Res 14 1635 1639 7979199 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Whiteside1"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>46 WhitesideDMcLeodRGrahamGSteckleyJLBoothK 2002 A homozygous germ-line mutation in the human MSH2 gene predisposes to hematological malignancy and multiple cafe-au-lait spots. Cancer Res 62 359 362 11809679 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Ostergaard1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>47 OstergaardJRSundeLOkkelsH 2005 Neurofibromatosis von Recklinghausen type I phenotype and early onset of cancers in siblings compound heterozygous for mutations in MSH6. Am J Med Genet A 139A 96 105; discussion 196 16283678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Scott1"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>48 ScottRHMansourSPritchard-JonesKKumarDMacSweeneyF 2007 Medulloblastoma, acute myelocytic leukemia and colonic carcinomas in a child with biallelic MSH6 mutations. Nat Clin Pract Oncol 4 130 134 17259933 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Fuellen1"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>49 FuellenGSpitzerMCullenPLorkowskiS 2005 Correspondence of function and phylogeny of ABC proteins based on an automated analysis of 20 model protein data sets. Proteins 61 888 899 16254912 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Ban1"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>50 BanCJunopMYangW 1999 Transformation of MutL by ATP binding and hydrolysis: a switch in DNA mismatch repair. Cell 97 85 97 10199405 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Raevaara1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>51 RaevaaraTEKorhonenMKLohiHHampelHLynchE 2005 Functional significance and clinical phenotype of nontruncating mismatch repair variants of MLH1. Gastroenterology 129 537 549 16083711 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Guerrette1"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>52 GuerretteSAcharyaSFishelR 1999 The interaction of the human MutL homologues in hereditary nonpolyposis colon cancer. J Biol Chem 274 6336 6341 10037723 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Kondo1"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>53 KondoEHoriiAFukushigeS 2001 The interacting domains of three MutL heterodimers in man: hMLH1 interacts with 36 homologous amino acid residues within hMLH3, hPMS1 and hPMS2. Nucleic Acids Res 29 1695 1702 11292842 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Liu1"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>54 LiuTTannergardPHackmanPRubioCKressnerU 1999 Missense mutations in hMLH1 associated with colorectal cancer. Hum Genet 105 437 441 10598809 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Barnetson1"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>55 BarnetsonRACartwrightNvan VlietAHaqNDrewK 2008 Classification of ambiguous mutations in DNA mismatch repair genes identified in a population-based study of colorectal cancer. Hum Mutat 29 367 374 18033691 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-deBakker1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>56 de BakkerPIYelenskyRPe'erIGabrielSBDalyMJ 2005 Efficiency and power in genetic association studies. Nat Genet 37 1217 1223 16244653 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Barrett1"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>57 BarrettJCFryBMallerJDalyMJ 2005 Haploview: analysis and visualization of LD and haplotype maps. Bioinformatics 21 263 265 15297300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Kohli1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>58 KohliMRagoCLengauerCKinzlerKWVogelsteinB 2004 Facile methods for generating human somatic cell gene knockouts using recombinant adeno-associated viruses. Nucleic Acids Res 32 e3 14704360 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0012260-Obmolova1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>59 ObmolovaGBanCHsiehPYangW 2000 Crystal structures of mismatch repair protein MutS and its complex with a substrate DNA. Nature 407 703 710 11048710 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
