
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><?epub May-27-2009?><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2709589</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19474344</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkp413</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkp413</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Methods Online</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Methylation detection oligonucleotide microarray analysis: a high-resolution method for detection of CpG island methylation </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kamalakaran</surname><given-names>Sitharthan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kendall</surname><given-names>Jude</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Xiaoyue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Chunlao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Sohail</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ravi</surname><given-names>Kandasamy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Auletta</surname><given-names>Theresa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Riggs</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Helland</surname><given-names>Åslaug</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Naume</surname><given-names>Bjørn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dimitrova</surname><given-names>Nevenka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Børresen-Dale</surname><given-names>Anne-Lise</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>Jim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lucito</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Philips Research North America, Briarcliff Manor, NY 10510, USA, <sup>2</sup>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, Cold Spring Harbor, NY 11724, <sup>3</sup>Department of Genetics, Institute for Cancer Research, <sup>4</sup>Department of Oncology, Norwegian Radium Hospital, Rikshospitalet University Hospital and <sup>5</sup>Faculty Division, The Norwegian Radium Hospital Faculty of Medicine, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: <phone>+1 516 422 4138</phone>; Fax: <fax>+1 516 422 4109</fax>; Email: <email>lucito@cshl.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>5</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>5</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>37</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e89</fpage><lpage>e89</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>29</day><month>4</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2009 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Methylation of CpG islands associated with genes can affect the expression of the proximal gene, and methylation of non-associated CpG islands correlates to genomic instability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>This epigenetic modification has been shown to be important in many pathologies, from development and disease to cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>We report the development of a novel high-resolution microarray that detects the methylation status of over 25 000 CpG islands in the human genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Experiments were performed to demonstrate low system noise in the methodology and that the array probes have a high signal to noise ratio. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Methylation measurements between different cell lines were validated demonstrating the accuracy of measurement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>We then identified alterations in CpG islands, both those associated with gene promoters, as well as non-promoter-associated islands in a set of breast and ovarian tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We demonstrate that this methodology accurately identifies methylation profiles in cancer and in principle it can differentiate any CpG methylation alterations and can be adapted to analyze other species. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>It has become increasingly clear how epigenetic modification can affect the structure and the expression of genes encoded in the DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>One such modification is the methylation of cytosines that are 5′ to guanines, so-called CpG dinucleotides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Found scattered across the genome, although at a lower than expected frequency, CpG dinucleotides also cluster into what have been termed CpG islands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The definition of a CpG islands differs somewhat based on the algorithm used for identification, two commonly used algorithms being Gardiner-Garden and Frommer (1) and Takai-Jones (2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The islands identified can be classified as falling into two distinct classes, those that are overlapping or proximal (within 2000 bp) to the transcription start site (TSS) of genes and those that are not associated with any transcription start site (non-TSS) for an obvious gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Most CpG islands proximal to the TSS of genes (TSS–CGIs) are largely unmethylated normally, and methylation of these islands, as can occur during tumorigenesis, has been shown to correlate highly to the suppression of transcription (3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Of the non-TSS CpG islands (non-TSS–CGIs) in the genome, many of these are proximal or inclusive to repetitive sequences, and are generally heavily methylated in normal tissue (4,5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>However, during tumorigenesis hypomethylation occurs at these islands (4,5), which can result in the expression of certain repeats (6,7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, this hypomethylation correlates to the severity of some cancers (8,9) and DNA breakage and genome instability (10). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Under certain circumstances, which can occur in pathologies such as cancer, imprinting, development, tissue specificity and X-chromosome inactivation, TSS–CGIs can be heavily methylated (11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Specifically, in cancer, methylation of islands proximal to tumor suppressor genes such as p16, RASSF1A, BRCA1, is a frequent event (12–14). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Since the analysis of such genes was previously done one at a time using bisulfite sequencing, the value of accurate high-throughput methods is obvious. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Several higher throughput methods, many array based, have been developed to identify CpG methylation in the genome for several different species including human and plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>An indirect approach compares expression analysis of 5-aza-cytidine treated to untreated cells (15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Early methods utilized fragments cloned from CpG island libraries (16). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Illumina Inc. has developed an array-like procedure based on their bead platform (17). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Several other approaches have adopted more standard array platforms utilizing DNA precipitations for human and arabidopsis with either methyl-binding proteins or antibodies that recognize methyl cytosine (ChIP-chip) (18–21). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Other methods utilize methylation sensitive restriction endonucleases with or without fractionation of the genome (22–25). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>More recently, sequencing methods have been developed using the newest generation sequencers such as the Roche Genome Sequencer FLX (454 Lifesciences technology) (26). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Although these methods are likely to replace array-based method they are presently prohibitively expensive to analyze the entire genome of large sets of samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>It is more likely that for the time being, many islands will be analyzed for few samples or few islands will be analyzed for many samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>We have developed a method to profile genome-wide methylation that is similar to the HpaII tiny fragment Enrichment by Ligation-mediated PCR (HELP) assay (27) and MASS, which utilizes the enzyme McrBC (28), but we have made modifications to increase the methylation detection limits as well as the classes of islands analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>We have analyzed cell lines and validated measurements of methylation with bisulfite sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>We then went on to develop methods, which allow us to analyze tumors with unmatched normals, thereby accessing any samples in our tumor collection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>This methodology will be useful to identify methylation events in the field of cancer as well as other fields such as development, aging, imprinting, etc. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec sec-type="materials"><title><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Enzymes, MspI, McrBC, T4 DNA ligase, were supplied by new England Biolabs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Primers were supplied by Sigma Genosys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Cot1 DNA and tRNA were supplied by invitrogen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The Megaprime−labeling kit, Cy3-conjugated dCTP, and Cy5-conjugated dCTP were supplied by Amersham-Bioscience. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Taq polymerase [Eppendorf mastermix (2.5X)] was supplied by Eppendorf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Centricon YM-30 filters were supplied by Amicon and formamide was supplied by Amresco. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Phenol:chloroform was supplied by Sigma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>NimbleGen photoprint arrays were synthesized by NimbleGen Systems Inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Design of the array was described previously (29). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Cell lines, SKBR3, Huh7, PANC1, were acquired through ATCC and grown according to specified conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The cell line chp-skn-1 is a primary fibroblast cell line cultured from a skin sample provided by an anonymous donor, cultured under the following conditions: DMEM + 20% FBS, Penn/Strep, and non-essential amino acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Tumor DNA from 11 patients with advanced ovarian carcinomas who were treated at the Department of Gynecological Oncology at The Norwegian Radium Hospital (NRH) during the period May 1992 to February 2003 were included in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The collection is approved by the Regional ethical review board (Reference No: S-01127). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Tumor DNA from 28 patients treated for localized breast cancer at the Norwegian Radium Hospital (NRH) from 1995 to 1998 was included in this project. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The samples were collected under an informed consent and the project approved by the local REK/IRB (30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>A small number of samples 12 breast tumors and 12 normals and 7 ovarian normals were obtained from The Cooperative Human Tissue Network, a repository of tumor material run by the National Institutes of Health. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Methylation array and detection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Coverage </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Our approach to map genome-wide methylation involves tiling all the predicted CpG islands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>All annotated CpG islands were obtained from the UCSC genome browser. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>These islands were predicted using the published Gardiner-Garden and Frommer (1) definition and involves the following criteria: length ≥200 bp, %GC ≥ 50%, observed/expected CpG ≥ 0.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>There are ∼26 219 CpG islands in the range of 200–2000 bp in the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>These islands are well covered by Msp I restriction fragmentation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Arrays were manufactured by Nimblegen Systems Inc. using the 390K format to the following specifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The CpG island annotation from human genome build 33 (hg17) was used to design a 50-mer tiling array. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The 50 mers were shifted on either side of the island sequence coordinates to evenly distribute the island. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The 390 K format has 3 67 658 available features which would not fit all islands with a 50-mer tiling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we made a cutoff on the islands to be represented based on size, with only CpG islands of size 200–2000 bp being assayed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The array represents classical CpG islands and does not include imprint control regions or other non-island promoters known to be methylated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Background hybridization signal could be high with probes of high GC content since by definition these probes will be. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Therefore, control probes, which are not in an MspI representation, were designed to represent background signal, and these probes were used to calculate signal to noise (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp413/DC1">Supplementary Figure 2</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Array design, probe sequences and further annotation are available on line <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>, dataset number GSE15801. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Sample preparation and hybridization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Representations have been described previously (29), with the following changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The primary restriction endonuclease used is MspI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>After the digestion the following linkers were ligated (MspI24mer CAGCATCGAGACTGAACGCAGCAG, and MspI12mer CGCTGCTGCGTT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The 12 mer is not phosphorylated and does not ligate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>After ligation the material is cleaned by phenol chloroform, precipitated, centrifuged and resuspended. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The material is divided in two, half being digested by the endonuclease McrBC and the other half being mock digested according to specification by New England Biolabs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The digestion time is 3 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>As few as four 250 μl tubes were used for each sample pair for amplification of the representation each with a 100 μl volume reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The cycle conditions were 95°C for 1 min, 72°C for 3 min, for 15 cycles, followed by a 10-min extension at 72°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The contents of the tubes for each pair were pooled when completed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Representations were cleaned by phenol:chloroform extraction, precipitated, resuspended and the concentration determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Representations were run on a gel to check for content, the McrBC digested representation being ∼100–150 bp shorter on average than the Mock. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>DNA was labeled as described with minor changes (29). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Briefly, 2 μg of DNA template was placed (dissolved in TE at pH 8) in a 0.2 ml PCR tube. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Five microliters of random nonomers (Sigma Genosys) were added brought up to 25 μl with dH2O, and mixed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The tubes were placed in Tetrad at 100°C for 5 min, then on ice for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>To this 5 μl of NEB Buffer 2, 5 μl of dNTPs (0.6 nm dCTP, 1.2-nm dATP, dTTP, dGTP), 5 μl of label (Cy3-dCTP or Cy5-dCTP) from GE Healthcare, 2 μl of NEB Klenow fragment and 2 μl dH2O were added. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Procedures for hybridization and washing were followed as reported previously (29) with the exception that oven temperature for hybridization was increased to 50°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>In general two hybridizations were performed for all samples (carried out as dye swaps to decrease variation of labeled nucleotide incorporation) with the exception for samples analyzed in Figure 2 where four hybridizations were performed. Figure 1.Schematic of the procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Shown at the top is genomic DNA with a CpG island that is methylated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The DNA is cleaved with the restriction endonuclease MspI and adaptors ligated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The ligated material is divided evenly, one half being digested with McrBC and the other half being mock digested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>This material is used as template for PCR amplification and the resulting product is used for microarray comparison. Figure 2.Comparison of methylation analysis of cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>(A–C) shows the comparison of a normal fibroblast used to produce representations from two separate aliquots of DNA and the representations were analyzed and the intensity compared to each other by scatter plot; the intensities of each being on one and the other axis, and the correlation calculated: (A) being replicate hybs, (B) being technical replicates and (C) being biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>(D) The comparison of the breast cancer cell line SKBR3 and the normal female fibroblast cell line as a scatter plot of the intensities from the SKBR3 experiment as the y-axis and the intensities of chp-skn-1 on the x-axis, and the correlation shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>(E) An example of bisulfite validation for a fragment found methylated in the tumor and not in the normal at a CpG island at chr 9:2197965–21980065, which lies upstream of the p14 gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The original data showing the ratio differences is shown with the position of the fragment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>To the right is the electropherogram identifying a region of cytosines that do not convert and at the bottom is a short table identifying the genomic position and number of McrBC site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>(F) shows data for the cell line Huh7 compared to the normal cell line chp-skn-1 for the p16 gene CpG island graphed by genomic position. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The x-axis is the genomic position of the probes and the y-axis is the ratio of two experiments, blue being chp-skn-1 and orange being Huh7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Inset above is shown is the relation of the transcript and inset below is the relation of the CpG island to the probes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Data analysis and statistics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Microarray images were scanned on GenePix 4000B scanner and data extracted using Nimblescan software (Nimblegen Systems Inc.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>For each probe, the geometric mean of the ratios (GeoMeanRatio) of McrBc and control treated samples were then calculated for each experiment and its associated dye swap. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The GeoMeanRatios of all the samples in a dataset were then normalized using quantile normalization method (31). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The normalized ratios for each experiment were then collapsed to get one value for all probes in every MspI fragment using the median polish model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The collapsed data were then used for further analysis (32). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Collapsed fragment data were then subjected to Welch's two-sample t-test for identifying significant differences between tumors and normals. P-values were corrected for multiple testing by controlling false discovery rate (FDR) (Benjamini-Hochberg algorithm) (33) implemented in R [multitest package (34)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Significance threshold was set at 0.001 for breast and 0.05 for the smaller ovarian set. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>General computations and statistics were performed in Python (35), S-Plus and R (32). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Bisulfite sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Probes were identified with differing methylation between the two samples, SKBR3 and chp-skn-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>DNAs from the two samples were treated with bisulfite using the EZ DNA Methylation-Gold Kit (Zymo Research, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>PCR primers were designed to flank the corresponding MspI fragments using MethPrimer (36). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>For two fragments, the PCR-amplified fragments were ligated and transformed using the TOPO-TA Cloning kit (Invitrogen, CA, USA); the transformant clones were picked for plasmid extraction, which were then sequenced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>To increase throughput, the remaining 32 were sequenced as PCR products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Results for subcloning and direct sequencing were compared to determine the peak heights required to call heterozygotes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>McrBC PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The sequence of the MTSS1 CpG island was obtained, including sequence beyond the ends of the island to aid in the design of PCR primers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA was digested with McrBC or mock digested followed by heat killing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Ten nanograms of DNA was used for PCR with Qiagen Taq polymerase for 30 cycles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Ten microliters of this product was then used as template for an additional 15 cycles of PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Products were run on 2% agarose gel, and pictures were taken to illustrate the fragments that were methylated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>In order to further investigate the role that CpG island methylation plays in cancer, we have designed a new comprehensive CpG island microarray and have developed robust methods for its use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>While sharing some similarities to previously developed methylation arrays (22,27,37), our method has several features that allow for increased CpG-island coverage and sensitivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>First, we utilized high-density oligonucleotide arrays with close to 400K features that allowed us to maximize tiling coverage of 26 219 out of 27 801 (HG17) annotated CpG islands (which includes non-promoter islands), while other CpG island arrays only contain selected promoter sequences (22,37). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Second, our hybridization target, because it is made from MspI representations, enriches for CpG island sequences by 10-fold relative to total genomic DNA (based on the size or the MspI amplifiable fragment) and thus provides superior hybridization specificity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>In addition since this method is representational based, very little DNA is required (as little as 50 ng) which makes this method well suited to the analysis of primary tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Third, each island generally corresponds to multiple MspI fragments, yielding positional information of which portion of an island is methylated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Finally, our method is based on enzymatic depletion of methylated sequences with fewer steps than other methods (37,38); having fewer steps may be less prone to variability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The enzyme chosen for depletion, McrBC, has the unusual recognition site A/GCm(N40–3000)A/GCm and has been used by others to analyze methylation including its application to arrays (39,40). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>This enzyme recognizes two methyl groups and because of the varied distance and that the methyl groups can be on the same or both strands (41), a type of combinatorial recognition and cleavage occurs, which greatly increases the number of potentially methylated CpG dinucleotides that can be queried. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Using in-silico analysis we calculate using McrBC (specifically the preferred distance for recognition between methyl cytosines of 40–150 bp) our methodology queries over 1 million of the 1.7 million CpG dinucleotides occurring in CpG islands, much more than can be queried by other techniques that utilize different enzymatic depletions such as HpaII and MspI (∼225 000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>This gives our methodology a 4-fold increase in potential coverage over other methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>According to these calculations combined with the increased array coverage (where we include non-promoter sequences and do not discriminate against any other promoter sequences except for larger islands, see ‘Methods for array design’ section) we will have increased the level of DNA methylation that can be measured in the genome over other methods which either use restriction enzymes or limited array coverage (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The procedure as schematized in Figure 1 involves digesting the genome with a restriction endonuclease with a CG-rich recognition sequence (MspI), and ligation of adaptors for use in a subsequent step of reducing genomic complexity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>We next divide the ligation in half and deplete one-half of its methylated sequences by digestion with the methylation-specific endonuclease, McrBC (37), and mock treat the other half. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>In both cases, we use carefully balanced PCR conditions to size select MspI fragments and reduce the overall genome complexity as previously described (29). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The McrBC-treated representation is compared to the mock-treated sample that serves as the reference for comparative hybridization to the designed oligonucleotide array. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>To determine if our method accurately identifies the methylation state of CpG islands, we first performed initial experiments with cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>To determine the level of noise in the system we performed analysis on a normal fibroblast cell line (chp-skn-1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Two cultures of chp-skn-1 were grown and DNA prepared. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Representations were prepared and were used to compare hybridization results from the same representations, representation from the same sample prepared separately, as well as the chp-skn-1 grown separately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Generally two hybridizations are performed one being a dye swap to decrease variation but in this case four hybridizations were performed for all conditions; however to demonstrate how little noise there is in the system, results and correlation from a single hybridization were compared graphically shown in Figure 2A–C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The close correlation demonstrates the small variation in the representational process, the labeling and the hybridization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>We also found little variation among different lots of McrBC (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Included on the array are probes that are not in a representation but have moderate CpG density. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Using the average intensity for these probes in the mock channel as the background component we measured signal to noise for the probes on the array. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The average signal to noise for probes on the array was 10.39. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>We then performed a comparison of the breast cancer cell line SKBR3 with chp-skn-1, shown in Figure 2D (with a correlation of 0.831, which demonstrates that there are differences detected between two different samples as compared to the control experiments shown in Figure 2A–C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>In the scatter plot (Figure 2D), points off the central diagonal represent fragments detecting differential methylation between the two samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the accuracy of measurements 25 fragments identified with methylation differences between chp-skn-1 and SKBR3, and nine fragments with no detection of methylation were selected for validation by sodium bisulfite sequencing (42). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Analysis of one representative fragment is shown in Figure 2E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>In each of the 28 fragments sequenced CpG dinucleotides inclusive ofo McrBC sites were mapped and their methylation state identified in the two samples (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp413/DC1">Supplementary Figure 1</ext-link> for five non-gene islands, five non-CpG island regions and 10 gene-associated islands; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp413/DC1">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link> which has data for all 28 fragments). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Fragments were selected based on varying the difference in the array ratios measured for both samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>By doing so we were able to determine at what level accurate measurements of methylation can be determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>At a difference around 0.3 the measurements may be incorrect as can be seen by two fragments, which had a difference in ratio of 0.317. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Any ratio difference above this level was found to be methylated in one of the samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>To determine if our method could accurately identify known tumor suppressor CpG island methylation, we then analyzed the hepatocellular cancer cell line HuH7 with known methylation of the p16 promoter (43). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>In Figure 2F we show the detection of methylation of the region of the p16 gene CpG island commonly methylated and correlated with decreased gene transcription. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Finally, we compared the results of our methodology on the two cell lines HPDE and PANC1 with results from the same two cell lines reported by Sato and colleagues using a different method and different array design (44). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Although there were some differences in detection between the two methods they were in good agreement (68%) for islands methylated in the samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Of the 34 interesting islands listed and validated, 26 were represented on our array (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp413/DC1">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link>, panel A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Of the 26, 17 regions were properly identified with methylation in PANC1 or both. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Four regions identified as methylated by Sato and colleagues were not detected in our assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>There was disagreement in four regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>One gene RELN, which was reported as not methylated in either sample by Sato and colleagues, was found methylated in PANC1 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, this gene is frequently methylated and silenced in pancreatic tumors (45), suggesting that our cell line may have genetically drifted over time apart from that used by Sato and colleagues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>With our method we can obtain positional information for the region of the CpG island methylated and for all methylation events the region is very close to the TSS, the region critical for suppression of transcription. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>To determine the accuracy of methylation detection as well as the positional prediction we performed sodium bisulfite sequencing on the fragment, which was detected as methylated in the RELN CpG island in the PANC1 cell line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we found that the CpG island fragment at position chr7:103223731–103223823 is methylated (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp413/DC1">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link>, panel B) demonstrating that the method can accurately identify methylation and that positional information is also available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>In addition we have determined that our line of PANC1 cells has deviated from the line used by SATO and colleagues. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The standard method to analyze tumor-methylation profiling is to utilize matched normal-tumor samples, and we have done this for 12 breast tumor and normal pairs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>As with many tumor banks, ours contain many unmatched tumor samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>To determine if unmatched tumor-normal pairs could be analyzed first we compared our results obtained with matched samples to those obtained with unmatched samples as a set and measured the degree of common alterations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>We developed statistical criteria for identifying CpG-islands most significantly altered between tumor and normal (see ‘Methods for details’ section). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Our analysis identified considerable overlap (30%) of CpG-islands significantly altered (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp413/DC1">Supplementary Table 3</ext-link>) between a matched tumor-normal set (12 normals, 12 tumors) compared to an unmatched set (12 normals, 28 tumors). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Since all tumor samples are different, similarity among a set could be a measure of tumor selection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>We determined how different all 40 tumors were from the normal samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>We computed pair-wise correlations between each normal sample and the other normals and each tumor sample to each normal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>From this data we then computed the mean correlation between each sample and the normal samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The mean correlation from normals to normals is 0.93, from tumors to normals is .88 (P &lt; 10E–017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>These data (plotted in Figure 3) show that tumors are different from matched or unmatched normals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>However, while some tumors are vastly different from normal several are more normal like in their methylation profile. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>In the future it will be interesting to have more detailed clinical information to determine if methylation profile can determine specific clinical parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Thus, we moved on to the analysis of a larger set of unmatched tumors and normals. Figure 3.The mean correlation for each sample with the normal samples (mean of 12 correlations for each tumor and 11 correlations for each normal) is shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The 12 samples to the left of the vertical line are the normals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The 40 to the right are tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The horizontal line is drawn at the minimum mean correlation for the normals with normals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>It is apparent that the tumors are on the whole distinct from the normals in comparison with each other (P &lt; 10E–017). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>We then examined the set of 40 breast tumors, compared to 12 normal breast samples and 11 ovarian tumors compared to 7 normal ovarian samples (33). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Using the statistical criteria developed (detailed in the ‘Methods’ section) we obtained a list of 916 significant alterations in breast cancer and 151 in ovarian cancer and have listed these by their genomic location (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp413/DC1">Supplementary Table 4</ext-link> for entire list and Table 2 for a summary of whether the alterations were found with more methylation or less methylation than normal, based on specific classes, non-promoter associated or promoter associated as well as non-island regions). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>In Table 1 we highlight genes selected based on functional information, many of which have previously been documented to alter methylation in cancer again demonstrating the ability of this methodology to detect CpG methylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Genes identified hypermethylated in both ovarian and breast tumors include several HOX genes and protocadherins, known to be methylated in many tumor types (46–49). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>In addition to genes known to undergo methylation we have found new targets of methylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>For example, we detected for promoter methylation of a micro-RNA gene has-mir-9-3, occurring in more than half the breast tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>This miRNA has been shown to be downregulated transcriptionally in thyroid cancers (50). Table 1.Short list of genes selected from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp413/DC1">Supplementary Table 4</ext-link> with altered CpG islandsaaGenes of possible functional interest were tabulated from the two categories based on TSS association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>The gene abbreviation, full gene name, fragment location, and description of the gene are given. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Summary of significant methylation changes listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp413/DC1">Supplementary Table 4</ext-link> for breast cancera </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF2"><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>aAll methylation and demethylation events from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp413/DC1">Supplemental Table 4</ext-link> were broken down into categories of associated to a gene (TSS associated) or not (Non-TSS associated), and methylated or demethylated within each of these groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Finally the probes are divided based on inclusiveness to a CpG island or the probes that are non-CGI probes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The total number is given for breast cancer comparison as well as the conversion to percentages in parentheses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Another gene identified as methylated in the breast tumors, MTSS1 (metastasis suppressor 1) (Table 1) is known to be preferentially methylated in several cancers including breast cancer (51–53). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>To determine if our analytical methods identified this gene accurately, two primary tumors were identified with methylation from the dataset for further validation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Being that they were not cell lines we only had 25 ng of material that we wanted to check multiple times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Although bisulfite sequencing is generally used for validation we wished to use an alternative due to the small amount of genomic DNA remaining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Others have utilized McrBC combine with PCR to study methylation (39,54). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Due to the constraints on us we chose to perform McrBC PCR (40) to validate the region of the island detected as methylated (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The island was broken down into five fragments where fragment one overlaps the TSS up to fragment five that is the farthest away from the TSS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>For tumors that were suspect to have methylation, fragment 1, which overlaps the gene TSS could not be amplified in the tumor samples (due to digestion by McrBC demonstrating methylation) as compared to the normal, which was not digested by McrBC (no methylation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Fragment 5 that is far from the TSS is amplified in all samples including McrBC digested due to a lack of methylation and no cleavage by McrBC, demonstrating that the MTSS1 CpG island is methylated in primary tumors. Figure 4.McrBC PCR of two different fragments of the MTSS1 CpG island for tumors identified of having methylation of this island compared to matched normal samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Fragment 1 encompasses the MspI fragment we have identified as being methylated and overlaps the gene TSS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Fragment 5, we do not detect methylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Both Normal and Tumor were digested with McrBC or mock digested for both matched pairs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>We have designed a methylation array and developed methods to detect CpG methylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>This methodology was performed on cell lines and measurements validated with more standard methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Comparing the analysis of two cell lines by our methodology allowed us to test the accuracy by bisulfite sequencing fragments with differential methylation between the two cell lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>We found no errors except for one fragment that was methylated but was not detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>This could have been a failure of the McrBC or the array detection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>We suspect the oligonucleotide probe since as in all hybridization-based method, there are bound to be probes that do not report well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>In comparison of our method with another array-based methods for the analysis of the same samples, we found good correspondence between the two methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>One gene we found particularly interesting, RELN, is frequently silenced in pancreatic cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Sato and colleagues demonstrate that it is not methylated in this particular pancreatic cancer cell line but our measurements suggest that it is methylated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Judging from its frequency of silencing and our success in validation of our measurements it is likely that our version of the cell line has genetically, or in this case, epigenetically drifted from that used by Sato and colleagues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>To determine if this was the case we validated our findings by bisulfite sequencing and determined that our version of the cell line had deviated and the array was correct in its measurement. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>In our analysis of tumors versus normal, as expected, the tumors had more variation than the normals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>However, some tumors were remarkably similar while others very different from their matched normal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>More importantly, the unmatched tumors were for the most part similar in variation to normal as the matched tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Three breast tumors out of 40 and 2 ovarian tumors out of 11 were extremely different from the normals, which could be interesting in reference to clinical parameters or genome structure and we are investigating this further with sample sets of a larger size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>We then developed statistical methods that could be used to identify those CpG islands that differ in their methylation status in the tumors as compared to the normals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>We have identified a number of CpG islands, both associated with gene TSSs or islands far from the TSS for any genes, which have altered methylation from both breast and ovarian tumors as compared to normal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>However, we did not identify well-known tumor suppressors in the primary tumor dataset such as p16. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The lack of known tumor suppressors could be a fault in our analysis or our methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>However, the frequency of methylation for many classically known tumor suppressors varies widely, some being as low as 15% (55–58). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Using p16 as an example, analysis of the tumor samples with matched normals did not uncover tumor suppresors such as p16 and since we demonstrate the ability to detect p16 methylation in the cell line HuH7 (43) with known methylation it is likely that none of the tumors had methylation of p16. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Therefore, although improvements are always possible, we feel that our technical and analytical methods are sound. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, the tumor suppressor Rassf1a that is a common target of methylation in cancer is not measurable with the current array. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The next generation array will include better design of CpG islands such as those proximal to the Rassf1A. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>One disadvantage of our method of analysis is that those genes whose CGIs are found with altered methylation in few samples may not be identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>The MiR-196 loci on chromosome 17 is methylated in several of the breast cancers in our study as compared to matched normals but overall is not significant in the larger set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>It has been previously shown that the miR-196 directs the cleavage of HoxB8 mRNA (59), which appears to function in myeloid differentiation (60,61), however it is possible that it plays a role in the deregulation of breast cells in becoming cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Presently we are further developing our statistical methods to improve our level of detection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Of the islands associated with gene TSSs identified as methylated there are a number that have been found altered and/or have been shown by other to decrease in expression in cancer, such as MTSS1 (51–53). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>We found this island methylated in a number of the primary breast tumors and verified by McrBC PCR (54) that it was methylated in two of these (one such sample shown in Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Tumor suppressors that are methylated are often found in regions of loss of heterozygosity (LOH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>It will be interesting to determine which of the genes found methylated are in regions of LOH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>It is interesting that MTSS1 is found on the q arm of chromosome 8, which is amplified very frequently in breast cancer and ovarian tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>It is possible that MTSS1 loss is important to the tumor growth as suggested by its role in cytoskeletal rearrangement (62) and its correlation with the disease state (51), so that in order to ensure lack of transcription within a region of genomic amplification the gene is silenced by methylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>It will be interesting to associate CGH data with methylation data and incorporate expression analysis to identify genes that are methylated and suppressed and determine if they are amplified or deleted genomically. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Of the genes identified, those that are functionally interesting should have their methylation validated by other means such as bisulfite sequencing or McrBC PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Those that pass can be functionally validated as candidates with possible tumor-suppressive activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, we have developed a powerful method to profile genome-wide DNA methylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>We have demonstrated that there is very low system noise from either the representational process or the labeling and hybridization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>We then legitimatized the method's ability to detect methylation by bisulfite sequence validating over 15 fragments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>We went on to analyze a number of samples that have been analyzed by others either by bisulfite sequencing or by other genome-wide approaches for methylation detection (43,45). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>In the case of Maeta et al., we have validated specific methylation events and in the case of Sato et al. we have reproduced the majority of their findings using our methodology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>We then used this method to develop methods for the analysis of tumors with unmatched normals, which will be of interest to the greater community since many tumor banks do not have matched normals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>We plan on using this methodology to identify methylation events that correlate to clinical parameters to determine if tumor sub-classification can be achieved, markers from this type of analysis being very valuable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>In addition, this methodology will have utility in the study of other pathologies, such as imprinting, development, or tissue specificity, which all are affected by epigenetic modifications. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp413/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NAR Online. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>FUNDING </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>National Institutes of Health and National Cancer Institute [K01CA93634-01 to R.L.]; Department of Defense [W81XWH-05-1-0068 to R.L.] as well as by grants awarded to Michael Wigler from the Simons Foundation and the Breast Cancer Research Foundation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Funding for open access charge: awarded to to RL and Michael Wigler from Philips Research North America. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Conflict of interest statement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>None declared. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag>
<SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>[Supplementary Data] </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="gkp413_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="gkp413_nar-02106-met-k-2008-File008.tif"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="gkp413_nar-02106-met-k-2008-File009.tif"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="gkp413_nar-02106-met-k-2008-File010.xls"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="gkp413_nar-02106-met-k-2008-File011.xls"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="gkp413_nar-02106-met-k-2008-File012.xls"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="gkp413_nar-02106-met-k-2008-File013.xls"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="gkp413_nar-02106-met-k-2008-File014.xls"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword" xlink:href="gkp413_nar-02106-met-k-2008-File015.doc"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></SecTag>
</body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>We thank Scott Powers, Scott Lowe, Michael Wigler and Michael Zhang for critical comments on the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>We also thank Christopher Johns for assistance in design of the arrays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Some tumor samples were supplied by the Cooperative Human Tissue Network, which is funded by the National Cancer Institute. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Other investigators may have received samples from these same tissues. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>1Gardiner-GardenMFrommerMCpG islands in vertebrate genomesJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Biol.19871962612823656447 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>2TakaiDJonesPAComprehensive analysis of CpG islands in human chromosomes 21 and 22Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>USA2002993740374511891299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>3HermanJGBaylinSBGene silencing in cancer in association with promoter hypermethylationN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Engl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Med.20033492042205414627790 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>4BaylinSBHermanJGGraffJRVertinoPMIssaJPAlterations in DNA methylation: a fundamental aspect of neoplasiaAdv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Cancer Res.1998721411969338076 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>5BirdAPThe relationship of DNA methylation to cancerCancer Surv.199628871018977030 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>6LavieLKitovaMMaldenerEMeeseEMayerJCpG methylation directly regulates transcriptional activity of the human endogenous retrovirus family HERV-K(HML-2)J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Virol.20057987688315613316 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>7Roman-GomezJJimenez-VelascoAAgirreXCervantesFSanchezJGarateLBarriosMCastillejoJANavarroGColomerDPromoter hypomethylation of the LINE-1 retrotransposable elements activates sense/antisense transcription and marks the progression of chronic myeloid leukemiaOncogene2005247213722316170379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>8ChoNYKimBHChoiMYooEJMoonKCChoYMKimDKangGHHypermethylation of CpG island loci and hypomethylation of LINE-1 and Alu repeats in prostate adenocarcinoma and their relationship to clinicopathological featuresJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Pathol.200721126927717139617 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>9SmithIMMydlarzWKMithaniSKCalifanoJADNA global hypomethylation in squamous cell head and neck cancer associated with smoking, alcohol consumption and stageInt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Cancer20071211724172817582607 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>10EhrlichMDNA hypomethylation, cancer, the immunodeficiency, centromeric region instability, facial anomalies syndrome and chromosomal rearrangementsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Nutr.20021322424S2429S12163705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>11BirdADNA methylation patterns and epigenetic memoryGenes Dev.20021662111782440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>12MerloAHermanJGMaoLLeeDJGabrielsonEBurgerPCBaylinSBSidranskyD5′ CpG island methylation is associated with transcriptional silencing of the tumour suppressor p16/CDKN2/MTS1 in human cancersNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Med.199516866927585152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>13DammannRLiCYoonJHChinPLBatesSPfeiferGPEpigenetic inactivation of a RAS association domain family protein from the lung tumour suppressor locus 3p21.3Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Genet.20002531531910888881 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>14RiceJCMassey-BrownKSFutscherBWAberrant methylation of the BRCA1 CpG island promoter is associated with decreased BRCA1 mRNA in sporadic breast cancer cellsOncogene199817180718129778046 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>15ShamesDSMinnaJDGazdarAFDNA methylation in health, disease, and cancerCurr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Med.200778510217311535 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>16EstecioMRYanPSIbrahimAETellezCSShenLHuangTHIssaJPHigh-throughput methylation profiling by MCA coupled to CpG island microarrayGenome Res.2007171529153617785535 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>17BibikovaMLinZZhouLChudinzEGarciaEWWuBDoucetDThomasNJWangYVollmerEHigh-throughput DNA methylation profiling using universal bead arraysGenome Res.20061638339316449502 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>18WeberMDaviesJJWittigDOakeleyEJHaaseMLamWLSchubelerDChromosome-wide and promoter-specific analyses identify sites of differential DNA methylation in normal and transformed human cellsNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Genet.20053785386216007088 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>19BallestarEPazMFValleLWeiSFragaMFEspadaJCigudosaJCHuangTHEstellerMMethyl-CpG binding proteins identify novel sites of epigenetic inactivation in human cancerEMBO J.2003226335634514633992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>20ZhangXYazakiJSundaresanACokusSChanSWChenHHendersonIRShinnPPellegriniMJacobsenSEGenome-wide high-resolution mapping and functional analysis of DNA methylation in arabidopsisCell20061261189120116949657 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>21ZilbermanDGehringMTranRKBallingerTHenikoffSGenome-wide analysis of Arabidopsis thaliana DNA methylation uncovers an interdependence between methylation and transcriptionNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Genet.200739616917128275 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>22AdrienLRSchlechtNFKawachiNSmithRVBrandwein-GenslerMMassimiAChenSPrystowskyMBChildsGBelbinTJClassification of DNA methylation patterns in tumor cell genomes using a CpG island microarrayCytogenet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Genome Res.2006114162316717445 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>23BalogRPde SouzaYETangHMDeMasellisGMGaoBAvilaAGabanDJMittelmanDMinnaJDLuebkeKJParallel assessment of CpG methylation by two-color hybridization with oligonucleotide arraysAnal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Biochem.200230930131012413464 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>24HatadaIFukasawaMKimuraMMoritaSYamadaKYoshikawaTYamanakaSEndoCSakuradaASatoMGenome-wide profiling of promoter methylation in humanOncogene2006253059306416407832 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>25YanPSPerryMRLauxDEAsareALCaldwellCWHuangTHCpG island arrays: an application toward deciphering epigenetic signatures of breast cancerClin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Cancer Res.200061432143810778974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>26TaylorKHKramerRSDavisJWGuoJDuffDJXuDCaldwellCWShiHUltradeep bisulfite sequencing analysis of DNA methylation patterns in multiple gene promoters by 454 sequencingCancer Res.2007678511851817875690 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>27KhulanBThompsonRFYeKFazzariMJSuzukiMStasiekEFigueroaMEGlassJLChenQMontagnaCComparative isoschizomer profiling of cytosine methylation: the HELP assayGenome Res.2006161046105516809668 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>28IbrahimAEThorneNPBairdKBarbosa-MoraisNLTavareSCollinsVPWyllieAHArendsMJBrentonJDMMASS: an optimized array-based method for assessing CpG island methylationNucleic Acids Res.200634e13617041235 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>29LucitoRHealyJAlexanderJReinerAEspositoDChiMRodgersLBradyASebatJTrogeJRepresentational oligonucleotide microarray analysis: a high-resolution method to detect genome copy number variationGenome Res.2003132291230512975311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>30NaumeBZhaoXSynnestvedtMBorgenERussnesHGLingjærdeOCStrømbergMWiedswangGKvalheimGKåresenRPresence of bone marrow micrometastasis is associated with different recurrence risk within molecular subtypes of breast cancerMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Oncology20071160171 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>31BolstadBMIrizarryRAAstrandMSpeedTPA comparison of normalization methods for high density oligonucleotide array data based on variance and biasBioinformatics20031918519312538238 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>32R Development Core TeamR: A Language and Environment for Statistical ComputingR Foundation for Statistical Computing2007Vienna, Austria </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>33BenjaminiYHochbergYControlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testingJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Roy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Stat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Ser. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>B199557289300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>34PollardKDudoitSvan der LaanMJUCMultiple testing procedures: r multtest package and applications to genomicsBerkeley Div Biostat Working Paper Ser2004164 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>35Van RossumGDrakeFLJrThe Python Language Reference Manual2003UKNetwork Theory Ltd144 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>36LiLCDahiyaRMethPrimer: designing primers for methylation PCRsBioinformatics2002181427143112424112 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>37GebhardCSchwarzfischerLPhamTHSchillingEKlugMAndreesenRRehliMGenome-wide profiling of CpG methylation identifies novel targets of aberrant hypermethylation in myeloid leukemiaCancer Res.2006666118612816778185 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>38CostelloJFSmiragliaDJPlassCRestriction landmark genome scanningMethods20022714414912095273 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>39ChotaiKAPayneSJA rapid, PCR based test for differential molecular diagnosis of Prader-Willi and Angelman syndromesJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Genet.1998354724759643288 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>40YamadaYWatanabeHMiuraFSoejimaHUchiyamaMIwasakaTMukaiTSakakiYItoTA comprehensive analysis of allelic methylation status of CpG islands on human chromosome 21qGenome Res.20041424726614762061 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>41SutherlandECoeLRaleighEAMcrBC: a multisubunit GTP-dependent restriction endonucleaseJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Biol.19922253273481317461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>42FrommerMMcDonaldLEMillarDSCollisCMWattFGriggGWMolloyPLPaulCLA genomic sequencing protocol that yields a positive display of 5-methylcytosine residues in individual DNA strandsProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Sci.USA199289182718311542678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>43MaetaYShiotaGOkanoJMurawakiYEffect of promoter methylation of the p16 gene on phosphorylation of retinoblastoma gene product and growth of hepatocellular carcinoma cellsTumour Biol.20052630030516254459 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>44OmuraNLiCPLiAHongSMWalterKJimenoAHidalgoMGogginsMGenome-wide profiling of methylated promoters in pancreatic adenocarcinomaCancer Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Ther.200871146115618535405 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>45SatoNFukushimaNChangRMatsubayashiHGogginsMDifferential and epigenetic gene expression profiling identifies frequent disruption of the RELN pathway in pancreatic cancersGastroenterology200613054856516472607 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>46ImotoIIzumiHYokoiSHosodaHShibataTHosodaFOhkiMHirohashiSInazawaJFrequent silencing of the candidate tumor suppressor PCDH20 by epigenetic mechanism in non-small-cell lung cancersCancer Res.2006664617462616651412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>47StrathdeeGHolyoakeTLSimAParkerAOscierDGMeloJVMeyerSEdenTDickinsonAMMountfordJCInactivation of HOXA genes by hypermethylation in myeloid and lymphoid malignancy is frequent and associated with poor prognosisClin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Cancer Res.2007135048505517785556 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>48WahaAGuntnerSHuangTHYanPSArslanBPietschTWiestlerODWahaAEpigenetic silencing of the protocadherin family member PCDH-gamma-A11 in astrocytomasNeoplasia2005719319915799819 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>49YingJGaoZLiHSrivastavaGMurrayPGGohHKLimCYWangYMarafiotiTMasonDYFrequent epigenetic silencing of protocadherin 10 by methylation in multiple haematologic malignanciesBr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Haematol.200713682983217341268 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>50HeHJazdzewskiKLiWLiyanarachchiSNagyRVoliniaSCalinGALiuCGFranssilaKSusterSThe role of microRNA genes in papillary thyroid carcinomaProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>USA2005102190751908016365291 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>51HicksDGYoderBJShortSTarrSPrescottNCroweJPDawsonAEBuddGTSizemoreSCicekMLoss of breast cancer metastasis suppressor 1 protein expression predicts reduced disease-free survival in subsets of breast cancer patientsClin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Cancer Res.2006126702670817121889 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>52UtikalJGratchevAMuller-MolinetIOertherSKzhyshkowskaJArensNGrobholzRKannookadanSGoerdtSThe expression of metastasis suppressor MIM/MTSS1 is regulated by DNA methylationInt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Cancer20061192287229316921485 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>53WangYLiuJSmithEZhouKLiaoJYangGYTanMZhanXDownregulation of missing in metastasis gene (MIM) is associated with the progression of bladder transitional carcinomasCancer Invest.200725798617453818 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>54TryndyakVKovalchukOPogribnyIPIdentification of differentially methylated sites within unmethylated DNA domains in normal and cancer cellsAnal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Biochem.200635620220716824473 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>55AgathanggelouAHonorioSMacartneyDPMartinezADallolARaderJFullwoodPChauhanAWalkerRShawJAMethylation associated inactivation of RASSF1A from region 3p21.3 in lung, breast and ovarian tumoursOncogene2001201509151811313894 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>56BrennerAJPaladuguAWangHOlopadeOIDreylingMHAldazCMPreferential loss of expression of p16(INK4a) rather than p19(ARF) in breast cancerClin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Cancer Res.19962199319989816158 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>57DammannRYangGPfeiferGPHypermethylation of the cpG island of Ras association domain family 1A (RASSF1A), a putative tumor suppressor gene from the 3p21.3 locus, occurs in a large percentage of human breast cancersCancer Res.2001613105310911306494 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>58SilvaJSilvaJMDominguezGGarciaJMCantosBRodriguezRLarrondoFJProvencioMEspanaPBonillaFConcomitant expression of p16INK4a and p14ARF in primary breast cancer and analysis of inactivation mechanismsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Pathol.200319928929712579530 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>59YektaSShihIHBartelDPMicroRNA-directed cleavage of HOXB8 mRNAScience200430459459615105502 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>60FujinoTYamazakiYLargaespadaDAJenkinsNACopelandNGHirokawaKNakamuraTInhibition of myeloid differentiation by Hoxa9, Hoxb8, and Meis homeobox genesExp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Hematol.20012985686311438208 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B61"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>61KnoepflerPSSykesDBPasillasMKampsMPHoxB8 requires its Pbx-interaction motif to block differentiation of primary myeloid progenitors and of most cell line models of myeloid differentiationOncogene2001205440544811571641 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B62"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>62MattilaPKSalminenMYamashiroTLappalainenPMouse MIM, a tissue-specific regulator of cytoskeletal dynamics, interacts with ATP-actin monomers through its C-terminal WH2 domainJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Chem.20032788452845912482861 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
