<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Antimicrob Chemother</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jac</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jac</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-7453</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2091</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2724981</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19578178</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkp237</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">dkp237</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Resistant mutants of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> selected <italic>in vitro</italic> do not reflect the <italic>in vivo</italic> mechanism of isoniazid resistance</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bergval</surname><given-names>Indra L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schuitema</surname><given-names>Anja R. J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Klatser</surname><given-names>Paul R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Anthony</surname><given-names>Richard M.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff><addr-line>KIT Biomedical Research</addr-line>, <institution>Royal Tropical Institute</institution>, <addr-line>Amsterdam</addr-line>, <country>The Netherlands</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Tel: <phone>+31-(0)20-5665448</phone>; Fax: <fax>+31-(0)20-6971841</fax>; E-mail: <email>i.bergval@kit.nl</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>7</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>4</day><month>7</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>64</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>3</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="rev-request"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author 2009. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the British Society for Antimicrobial Chemotherapy. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oxfordjournals.org</copyright-statement><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/"><license-p>The online version of this article has been published under an open access model. Users are entitled to use, reproduce, disseminate, or display the open access version of this article for non-commercial purposes provided that: the original authorship is properly and fully attributed; the Journal and Oxford University Press are attributed as the original place of publication with the correct citation details given; if an article is subsequently reproduced or disseminated not in its entirety but only in part or as a derivative work this must be clearly indicated. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oxfordjournals.org</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>The high prevalence of isoniazid-resistant <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> is often explained by a high mutation rate for this trait, although detailed information to support this theory is absent. We studied the development of isoniazid resistance <italic>in vitro</italic>, making use of a laboratory strain of <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Spontaneous isoniazid-resistant mutants were characterized by molecular methods allowing identification of the most commonly encountered resistance-conferring mutations. Additionally, we determined the <italic>in vitro</italic> mutation rates for isoniazid and rifampicin resistance, and characterized the genome of a triple-resistant strain.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Results confirm that the <italic>in vitro</italic> mutation rate for isoniazid resistance (3.2&#8202;&#215;&#8202;10<sup>&#8722;7</sup> mutations/cell division) is much higher than the rate for rifampicin resistance (9.8&#8202;&#215;&#8202;10<sup>&#8722;9</sup> mutations/cell division). However, in the majority of the <italic>in vitro</italic> mutants <italic>katG</italic> was partially or completely deleted and neither of the two most common <italic>in vivo</italic> mutations, <italic>katG</italic>-S315T or <italic>inhA</italic>-C(-)15T, were found in 120 isogenic mutants. This implies that clinically prevalent resistance mutations were present in &lt;0.8% of isoniazid-resistant strains selected <italic>in vitro</italic> (95% CI 0%&#8211;2.5%). The triple-resistant strain had acquired isoniazid resistance via a 49 kbp deletion, which included <italic>katG</italic>. Apart from previously identified resistance-conferring mutations, three additional point mutations were acquired during sequential selection steps.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>These outcomes demonstrate that the <italic>in vivo</italic> mechanism of isoniazid resistance is not reflected by <italic>in vitro</italic> experiments. We therefore conclude that the high <italic>in vitro</italic> mutation rate for isoniazid resistance is not a satisfactory explanation for the fact that isoniazid monoresistance is significantly more widespread than monoresistance to rifampicin.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>tuberculosis</kwd><kwd>drug resistance</kwd><kwd>mutation rate</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Although the global incidence of tuberculosis (TB) is declining, drug resistance is rapidly emerging and spreading.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C1">1</xref></sup> Insufficient control measures have led to a drastic increase in the prevalence of drug-resistant strains and, more importantly, the degree of drug resistance; in certain high-burden countries the nature of multidrug-resistant TB (MDR-TB) has rapidly evolved from incidental to epidemic.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C1">1</xref></sup></p><p>The production of new and more effective antibiotics partially addresses this problem, but without a more detailed comprehension of the molecular mechanisms that lead to successful (M)DR strains, these new compounds may also be quickly rendered ineffective by the generation of extensively drug-resistant TB (XDR-TB).</p><p>Isoniazid and rifampicin are the two most commonly used anti-TB drugs and the backbone of any successful TB treatment programme. MDR-TB is consequently defined as TB that is resistant to at least isoniazid and rifampicin. Monoresistance to isoniazid is significantly more prevalent than monoresistance to rifampicin and MDR-TB; based on the most recent data it is estimated that 13.3% of all TB cases globally involve isoniazid monoresistance, versus 0.6% rifampicin monoresistance and 5.3% MDR-TB cases.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C1">1</xref></sup></p><p>Shortly after the introduction of isoniazid in the 1950s, the first resistant <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> mutants were isolated and it was observed that many of these strains had reduced catalase activity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C2">2</xref></sup> It was first assumed that deletion of <italic>katG</italic>, coding for the only identified catalase&#8211;peroxidase in <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>, was the main mechanism responsible for resistance to isoniazid.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C3">3</xref></sup> However, subsequent studies demonstrated that, although conferring high levels of resistance, this is not the primary mechanism.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C4">4</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C7">7</xref></sup> Although any mutation reducing KatG activity results in resistance, relatively few mutations in <italic>katG</italic> account for the majority of isoniazid resistance in clinical isolates; resistance to isoniazid is primarily conferred by the mutations <italic>katG</italic>-S315T (45%&#8211;75%) and <italic>inhA</italic>-C(-)15T (15%&#8211;25%).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C8">8</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C13">13</xref></sup></p><p>Biochemical and <italic>in vitro</italic> studies have shown that the most prevalent mutant, <italic>katG</italic>-S315T, still retains a significant part of its catalase activity,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C14">14</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C17">17</xref></sup> which appears to be sufficient for the preservation of virulence.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C19">19</xref></sup> Strains carrying this mutation typically have an intermediate (1&#8211;5 mg/L) level of resistance to isoniazid,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C21">21</xref></sup> since KatG has reduced abilities to activate isoniazid, but has not completely lost this function. Mutations in the regulatory region of <italic>inhA</italic> usually lead to a low-level resistance (0.2&#8211;1.0 mg/L).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C21">21</xref></sup></p><p>Mutations that lead to complete loss of function of KatG, such as deletions, insertions or other frameshifts, are found in a small proportion of the isoniazid-resistant strains.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C22">22</xref></sup> On average, partial or complete <italic>katG</italic> deletion mutants are reported in only &#8764;5% of resistant isolates,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C24">24</xref></sup> but higher proportions have been reported on occasion.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C6">6</xref></sup> Additionally, strains with isoniazid resistance due to deletion of the <italic>katG</italic> gene are less likely to be clustered than strains with the <italic>katG</italic>-S315T mutation, a mutation significantly associated with successful dissemination.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C26">26</xref></sup></p><p>Isolates resistant due to inactivation of KatG often have additional mutations in the regulatory region or coding sequence of <italic>ahpC</italic>, coding for an alkylhydroperoxidase.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C28">28</xref></sup> Originally, researchers assumed these mutations were alternative mechanisms of isoniazid resistance,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C30">30</xref></sup> but subsequent studies showed that the majority of the mutations in <italic>ahpC</italic> or the intergenic region <italic>oxyR-ahpC</italic> were compensating for the loss of <italic>katG</italic> function.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C32">32</xref></sup></p><p>It is frequently assumed that the mutation rate for isoniazid resistance is &#8764;100 times higher than for rifampicin and, consequently, that isoniazid resistance precedes resistance to rifampicin in the development of MDR-TB. However, there are no empirical grounds for these assumptions. We therefore studied the emergence of isoniazid resistance <italic>in vitro</italic>, making use of well-characterized <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> laboratory strains. We determined the <italic>in vitro</italic> mutation rate to isoniazid and characterized spontaneous isoniazid-resistant mutants by sequencing, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C33">33</xref></sup> and comparative genome hybridization (CGH).</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Growth of bacteria</title><p>The <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> parent strains that all experiments were conducted with, MTB72 (ATCC 35801) and H37Rv (ATCC 27294), were initially susceptible to all antimicrobials used in this study. Bacteria were cultured in Middlebrook medium 7H9 (Difco, BD, Sparks, MD, USA), supplemented with oleic acid/albumin/dextrose/catalase (OADC Enrichment, BD, Sparks, MD, USA), in a shaking incubator at 37&#176;C. A liquid starting culture was made by inoculating pure colonies from L&#246;wenstein&#8211;Jensen or Coletsos slopes into 10 mL of culture medium. When these cultures reached the logarithmic growth phase, 0.5 mL was transferred to 9.5 mL of fresh, non-selective medium and bacteria were cultured until mid-logarithmic growth. Oxidative stress was applied by addition of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (31% solution Ultrapur, Merck KGaA, Darmstadt, Germany) at a subinhibitory concentration of 50 mM, 24 h before the bacteria were harvested. All procedures with live mycobacteria were performed in a Biosafety Level III laboratory.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Growth in macrophages</title><sec id="s2b1"><title>THP-1 cells</title><p>Human macrophage-like THP-1 cells (ATCC TIB-202) were grown in 8 mL of RPMI 1640 medium supplemented with 5% fetal bovine serum, 1% HEPES and 1% <sc>l</sc>-glutamine (all from Gibco, Invitrogen, Breda, The Netherlands). The cells were grown in 75 cm<sup>2</sup> flasks at 37&#176;C in a humidified chamber with a 5% CO<sub>2</sub> atmosphere. When a density of &#8764;1&#8202;&#215;&#8202;10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL was reached, cells were treated with 16 nM phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate (PMA; Sigma&#8211;Aldrich Chemie, Zwijndrecht, The Netherlands). After 1 h, <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> bacteria were added and after 5 h the PMA and bacteria that were not phagocytosed were washed away with medium twice.</p></sec><sec id="s2b2"><title>M. tuberculosis</title><p>Log-phase cultures of <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> strain MTB72 were allowed to stand for 5 min and then the upper 500 &#181;L was filtered with a 5 &#181;m filter (Millipore). After filtration, the concentration of the dispersed bacterial suspensions was determined by measuring the absorbance at 420 nm, an <italic>A</italic><sub>420</sub> of 0.15 corresponding to 1&#8202;&#215;&#8202;10<sup>8</sup> bacteria/mL. Bacteria were added to the macrophages in such a way that a multiplicity of infection of &#8764;1/10 was maintained. An acid-fast stain was made and analysed by light microscopy (magnification: &#215;100) in order to determine if bacteria were properly associated with the macrophages.</p></sec><sec id="s2b3"><title>Selection of isoniazid-resistant mutants</title><p>In three experiments, intracellular isoniazid-resistant bacteria were selected by addition of 1 mg/L isoniazid to the flasks after 3 days growth of macrophages&#8202;+&#8202;bacteria. After 4 h of incubation with isoniazid, the supernatant was discarded and cells were washed with fresh medium. Macrophages were scraped off the bottom of the flask with a cell scraper and taken up in 2 mL sterile water in a new tube. The macrophages were disrupted by application of osmotic stress and sonication in a water bath, and bacteria were subsequently plated on solid Middlebrook medium (MB7H11) containing 1 mg/L isoniazid.</p><p>In one experiment, the pre-selection of resistant mutants in the cells was omitted and after disruption of the macrophages an aliquot of the bacteria was used for determination of cfu. From this experiment, the mutation frequency in macrophages was calculated.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Proportion of mutants</title><p>To determine the mutation frequency (i.e. the proportion of resistant mutants), four 0.5 mL aliquots of log-phase cultures were plated onto solid MB7H11 medium (Difco, BD, Sparks, MD, USA) containing 0.4, 1.0 or 20 mg/L isoniazid (Sigma&#8211;Aldrich Chemie). Serial dilutions of the cultures were plated on non-selective medium to determine the cfu present. The mutation frequency was calculated by dividing the number of resistant colonies by the cfu plated. From each experiment, a number of resistant mutants were picked from the antibiotic-containing plates and DNA was isolated for further molecular characterization.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Fluctuation assay</title><p>The mutation rates (i.e. the chance of a mutation occurring per generation) for isoniazid and rifampicin were determined by performing a fluctuation assay, making use of the <italic>p</italic><sub>0</sub>-method.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C34">34</xref></sup></p><p>A 10 mL starting culture was prepared by inoculating strain MTB72 from a slope, to minimize the presence of spontaneous mutants. When bacterial growth reached mid-logarithmic phase, the culture was vortexed vigorously to homogenize the bacterial suspension. Clumped cells were allowed to settle for 3 min and 55 new 1 mL cultures were made by transferring 1 &#181;L of this cell suspension (&#8764;1000 bacteria) to a 2 mL screwcap tube containing 1 mL of MB7H9 medium&#8202;+&#8202;OADC. Two to three sterile glass beads were added to each culture, to ensure a continuous homogeneous suspension. The 1 mL cultures were incubated in a shaking incubator at 37&#176;C for &#8764;10 generations (&#8764;8 days), ensuring a &#8805;1000-fold increase in cell number. The cultures were then centrifuged at 5000 <bold>g</bold> for 8 min and 850 &#181;L of supernatant was discarded. For each culture the remaining 150 &#181;L was plated in one well of a square 25-well replica plate (Greiner, Germany) containing 3 mL of MB7H11 supplemented with either 8 mg/L rifampicin (Sigma&#8211;Aldrich Chemie) or 1.0 mg/L isoniazid. The number of cfu plated in each well was estimated by making serial dilutions of the five remaining 1 mL cultures and plating onto non-selective MB7H11. The two 25-well replica plates were allowed to dry in a biosafety laminar flow cabinet, until all liquid was absorbed into the solid medium. The plates were then sealed and incubated at 37&#176;C. After 3&#8211;4 weeks incubation, the proportion of squares without growth was counted and the mutation rate was calculated.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C34">34</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>DNA isolation</title><p>Separate mutant colonies, selected on isoniazid-containing solid medium, were picked and suspended in 150 &#181;L of Tris/EDTA buffer containing 1% Triton X-100 (BDH Laboratory Supplies, Poole, England) and then heated at 95&#176;C for 30 min. After lysis, cells were centrifuged at 5000 <bold>g</bold> for 3 min and 130 &#181;L of the supernatant was collected as a DNA sample.</p><p>For the experiment using pooled isolates, four separate colonies were suspended in a single tube and DNA was extracted simultaneously.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>PCR and sequencing</title><p>A 233 bp fragment, surrounding codon 315 of <italic>katG</italic>, was amplified from selected isolates by PCR using forward primer katG-315_FW 5&#8242;-CATGAACGACGTCGAAACAG-3&#8242; and reverse primer katG-315_RV 5&#8242;-CGAGGAAACTGTTGTCCCAT-3&#8242;. In addition, a 300 bp fragment of <italic>katG</italic> surrounding codon 463 was amplified using forward primer katG-463_FW 5&#8242;-TCCCGTTGCGAGATACCTT-3&#8242; and reverse primer katG-463_RV 5&#8242;-AGGGTGCGAATGACCTTG-3&#8242;. Isolates were scored as &#916;<italic>katG</italic> if one or both of the PCR products were absent. From a proportion of the strains that were positive for the katG-315 PCR, the PCR fragment was sequenced in both directions according to protocols previously published.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C35">35</xref></sup></p><p>From another subselection of our isoniazid-resistant isolates, a 251 bp fragment spanning the intergenic region of <italic>oxyR-ahpC</italic> was amplified and sequenced, using forward primer oxyR-ahpC_FW 5&#8242;-TGCTGAACCACTGCTTTGC-3&#8242; and reverse primer oxyR-ahpC_RV 5&#8242;-GGTCACCGCCGATGAGAGC-3&#8242;.</p><p>Results of all PCRs were analysed by agarose gel electrophoresis using a 2% agarose gel (Multi-Purpose agarose, Roche Diagnostics GmbH, Mannheim, Germany).</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>MLPA</title><p><italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>-specific MLPA was performed as previously published,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C33">33</xref></sup> except in the present study only four probes were included (Table&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB1">1</xref>), allowing results to be easily interpreted on an agarose gel. The 16S rRNA probe (202 bp) targets a region specific for members of the MTB complex and was used as internal control. Probes katG-315 (160 bp) and inhA-15 (178 bp) identify the two most prevalent isoniazid resistance-conferring mutations. Probe katG-463 targets a point mutation in codon 463 of <italic>katG</italic> specific for principal genotypic groups (PGGs) 2 and 3 that was present in all strains used in this study. The absence of the <italic>katG</italic>-463 or <italic>katG</italic>-315 products identified a deletion of these regions.</p><table-wrap id="DKP237TB1" position="float"><label>Table&#160;1</label><caption><p>MLPA probes used in this study to screen isoniazid-resistant mutants</p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Indicated are the name of the probe, the region or point mutation it targets, the length of the ligated probes and the phenotype that is associated with the point mutation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>CGH</title><p>Strain RB14, a rifampicin- and rifabutin-resistant isolate derived from MTB72,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C36">36</xref></sup> was plated on solid medium containing 20 mg/L isoniazid. Upon growth of isoniazid-resistant mutants, 13 colonies were picked, purified and analysed by PCR and MLPA, as described in this study. Seven out of 13 (54%) were negative for both the <italic>katG</italic>-315 and the <italic>katG</italic>-463 PCR, indicating a substantial deletion of the <italic>katG</italic> region. We selected one of these deletion mutants of RB14, RB14H5, for further analysis. In order to determine the exact size of the deletion, the genomes of strain RB14H5 and MTB72, its wild-type parent, were compared by CGH (NimbleGen CGH Whole-Genome Tiling Arrays, Roche NimbleGen, Madison, WI, USA). DNA was extracted from liquid cultures and processed, purified and shipped according to the company's requirements. Data obtained from the CGH experiment was interpreted and analysed with SignalMap v1.9 and Microsoft Excel. Primers were designed to amplify likely regions of difference identified and any mutations present were confirmed by cycle sequencing [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jac.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/dkp237/DC1">Table S1, available as Supplementary data at <italic>JAC</italic> Online (http://jac.oxfordjournals.org/)</ext-link>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Deletions in katG are the most common mechanism of resistance to isoniazid in vitro</title><p>Two initial independent experiments with MTB72 were performed, using 20 mg/L isoniazid to select resistant mutants. Mutation frequencies of 4.40&#8202;&#215;&#8202;10<sup>&#8722;6</sup> and 7.56&#8202;&#215;&#8202;10<sup>&#8722;6</sup> were measured, and PCR assays targeting the regions flanking codons 315 and 463 of <italic>katG</italic> identified deletions in 4/20 and 18/20 mutants, respectively (Table&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB2">2</xref>). None of the mutants with an intact <italic>katG</italic> gene carried a mutation, as determined by sequencing, except for one strain that had acquired a TGG(W)&#8594;CGG(F) mutation in codon 321. Deletions in <italic>katG</italic> were confirmed by MLPA, as well as the absence of typical mutations <italic>katG</italic>-S315T or <italic>inhA</italic>-C(-)15T in all the characterized mutants.</p><table-wrap id="DKP237TB2" position="float"><label>Table&#160;2</label><caption><p>Characterization of the spontaneous isoniazid-resistant mutants derived from strain MTB72</p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>INH, isoniazid; RIF, rifampicin; THP1, macrophage; MTB, <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>.</p></fn><fn><p>The concentration of isoniazid was the concentration in the solid medium on which the bacteria were selected. The selection conditions are additional criteria to select against &#916;<italic>katG</italic> mutants, in an attempt to favour the selection of clinically relevant mutants. Mutation frequency is the proportion of mutants. Mutation rate is the estimated number of mutants per generation. No. of &#916;<italic>katG</italic> is the number of <italic>katG</italic> deletion mutants (of the characterized mutants). No. of targeted mutations is the number of <italic>katG</italic>-S315T or <italic>inhA</italic>-C(-)15T found in the characterized mutants.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>a</sup>Average of data depicted in this table.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>b</sup>Average of five independent experiments.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>We hypothesized that the high mutation frequencies and domination of <italic>katG</italic> deletions over isoniazid resistance-conferring mutations were either due to the absence of significant oxidative stress <italic>in vitro</italic> or the concentration of isoniazid used. To test the first hypothesis, the experiment was repeated after exposure to 50 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, in an attempt to select against the occurrence of <italic>katG</italic> deletions in favour of clinically relevant mutations. The mutation frequency was comparable to that obtained in previous results (3.6&#8202;&#215;&#8202;10<sup>&#8722;6</sup>, see Table&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB2">2</xref>) and 17/20 (85%) selected mutants had a deletion in <italic>katG</italic>. None of the analysed strains had acquired resistance mutations in <italic>katG</italic>-315 or <italic>inhA</italic>-(-)15.</p><p>We then lowered the concentration of isoniazid to 1 mg/L. Again, two independent experiments were performed, both resulting in average to high proportions of <italic>katG</italic> deletion mutants (13/37 and 15/20) and none of the targeted clinically prevalent mutations in 57 colonies analysed. The mutation frequencies were 1.78&#8202;&#215;&#8202;10<sup>&#8722;6</sup> and 4.17&#8202;&#215;&#8202;10<sup>&#8722;6</sup>, respectively. Addition of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> to the medium slightly increased the mutation frequency to 1.60&#8202;&#215;&#8202;10<sup>&#8722;5</sup>, but the majority (14/20) of the selected mutants had still acquired a deletion in <italic>katG</italic> (Table&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB2">2</xref>).</p><p>Five independent experiments were also conducted to determine the mutation frequency for rifampicin, resulting in an average mutation frequency of 6.86&#8202;&#215;&#8202;10<sup>&#8722;8</sup> using 8 mg/L rifampicin (Table&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB2">2</xref>). This was 43.4 times lower than the average mutation frequency observed with 1 mg/L isoniazid. In addition, fluctuation assays were performed to determine the mutation rates for isoniazid and rifampicin. The estimated mutation rate for 1 mg/L isoniazid was 3.2&#8202;&#215;&#8202;10<sup>&#8722;7</sup> mutations/cell division, 32.3 times higher than the estimated rate for 8 mg/L rifampicin (9.81&#8202;&#215;&#8202;10<sup>&#8722;9</sup> mutations/cell division, Table&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB2">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Less than 1% of in vitro selected isoniazid-resistant mutants carry a clinically prevalent mutation</title><p>Being unsuccessful in our attempt to select for isoniazid-resistant strains with either of the two most clinically prevalent mutations, we decided to screen a larger pool of isoniazid-resistant mutants derived from MTB72, in order to estimate the prevalence of the most common clinical mutations <italic>in vitro</italic>. We used the methods described above to select isoniazid-resistant mutants with 0.4 mg/L isoniazid.</p><p>The mutation frequency was 8.02&#8202;&#215;&#8202;10<sup>&#8722;6</sup> (Table&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB3">3</xref>) and an initial characterization of 29 mutants showed that 28% (8/29, Table&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB3">3</xref>) had acquired a deletion in <italic>katG</italic>. To increase the chance of finding clinically prevalent mutations, additional mutants were picked from the original plates (0.4 mg/L isoniazid) and plated in duplicate on plates containing 0.4 mg/L isoniazid and 2.0 mg/L isoniazid. Thirty colonies were picked that grew on 0.4 mg/L isoniazid but showed no growth on 2.0 mg/L isoniazid and, thus, had an MIC between 0.4 and 2.0 mg/L isoniazid. Of these 30 selected mutants, three (10%) had acquired deletions in <italic>katG</italic> (Table&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB3">3</xref>). No mutations were found in <italic>katG</italic>-315 or <italic>inhA</italic>-(-)15 by MLPA, but sequencing of <italic>katG</italic> from 10 of these low-MIC mutants with intact <italic>katG</italic> revealed an ACT(T)&#8594;ATT(I) mutation in codon 271 of <italic>katG</italic> in one of the strains.</p><table-wrap id="DKP237TB3" position="float"><label>Table&#160;3</label><caption><p>Characterization of MTB72-derived isoniazid-resistant mutants initially selected with 0.4 mg/L isoniazid</p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>A subdivision of two groups of mutants was made on the basis of their acquired isoniazid MIC, indicated in the column &#8216;acquired MIC&#8217;. MIC is expressed in terms of mg/L isoniazid. Mutation frequency is the proportion of mutants. No. of &#916;<italic>katG</italic> is the number of <italic>katG</italic> deletion mutants. No. of targeted mutations is the number of <italic>katG</italic>-S315T or <italic>inhA</italic>-C(-)15T found in the characterized mutants.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>a</sup>DNA samples were derived from mutants pooled in sets of four.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>From the panel of mutants selected with 0.4 mg/L isoniazid, an additional subpopulation with an MIC&#8202;&gt;&#8202;2.0 mg/L was analysed by MLPA, targeting the <italic>inhA</italic>-15 and <italic>katG</italic>-315 mutant alleles. In order to facilitate analysis, mutant colonies were pooled in sets of four before DNA was extracted and a total of 120 mutants were screened in this fashion. The suitability of the method for detecting a single mutant in a mixed sample using MLPA was confirmed by analysis of artificial mixtures made with wild-type <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> DNA and DNA from clinical strains carrying either the <italic>katG</italic>-S315T or <italic>inhA</italic>-C(-)15T mutation (Figure&#160;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DKP237F1">1</xref>). We were unable to measure the number and percentage of &#916;<italic>katG</italic> mutants with this method, since samples were mixtures of four colonies and only samples in which all four colonies had a deletion in <italic>katG</italic> would be detected. No mutations were found in these 120 isoniazid-resistant <italic>in vitro</italic> mutants, indicating that the prevalence of clinically relevant mutations [<italic>katG</italic>-S315T or <italic>inhA</italic>-C(-)15T] <italic>in vitro</italic> is &lt;0.8% (95% CI 0%&#8211;2.5%), under the conditions described (Table&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB3">3</xref>).</p><fig id="DKP237F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Agarose gel showing separation of MLPA products. Samples shown are artificial mixtures made with DNA from isoniazid-resistant clinical isolates and DNA from wild-type strain MTB72. From top to bottom, bands represent amplified probes targeting <italic>katG</italic>-L463R (319 bp), 16S rRNA (202 bp) and <italic>inhA</italic>-C(-)15T (178 bp, lanes 1&#8211;3) or <italic>katG</italic>-S315T (160 bp, lanes 4&#8211;6). Lane 1, 100% <italic>inhA</italic>-C(-)15T mutant; lane 2, 10% <italic>inhA</italic>-C(-)15T mutant&#8202;+&#8202;90% wild-type; lane 3, 20% <italic>inhA</italic>-C(-)15T mutant&#8202;+&#8202;80% wild-type; lane 4, 20% <italic>katG</italic>-S315T mutant&#8202;+&#8202;80% wild-type; lane 5, 10% <italic>katG</italic>-S315T mutant&#8202;+&#8202;90% wild-type; lane 6, 100% <italic>katG</italic>-S315T mutant; lane 7, 100% wild-type. M denotes a 100 bp marker, numbers on the first three bands correspond to the respective sizes (in bp).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="dkp23701"/></fig><p>Representative experiments were also performed with model strain H37Rv. Selection of spontaneous resistant mutants with 0.4 mg/L isoniazid resulted in a mutation frequency of 2.3&#8202;&#215;&#8202;10<sup>&#8722;6</sup>. From the resistant mutants, a subselection was made of strains with an MIC between 0.4 and 2.0 mg/L isoniazid. MLPA analysis of 30 of these selected strains showed that 3.3% (1/30) had acquired a deletion in <italic>katG</italic>, but no mutations were detected in <italic>katG</italic>-315 or <italic>inhA</italic>-(-)15. This indicates that also for strain H37Rv &lt;3.3% of the isoniazid-resistant H37Rv mutants carried a clinical mutation.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>No adaptive mutations were found in the oxyR-ahpC intergenic region of a random selection of &#916;katG mutants</title><p>In order to exclude the possibility that the high prevalence of &#916;<italic>katG</italic> mutants in our experiments was due to the acquisition of mutations in the <italic>oxyR-ahpC</italic> intergenic region, we sequenced a 251 bp fragment spanning the <italic>oxyR-ahpC</italic> intergenic region of a selection of our MTB72-derived isoniazid-resistant mutants. This panel of strains represented the different isoniazid concentrations and additional selection conditions used in this study, and all strains had acquired deletions in various regions of <italic>katG</italic>. In total, we screened 21 &#916;<italic>katG</italic> mutants for adaptive mutations in <italic>oxyR-ahpC</italic>. The sequence of all analysed mutants was identical to that of the wild-type parent MTB72, indicating that none of the mutants had acquired mutations in this region.</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>In vitro-selected &#916;katG mutant has a 49 kbp deletion, but is viable in vitro</title><p>The genomes of MTB72 and RB14H5 were screened by CGH, in order to obtain information about the mutations that RB14H5 acquired during the sequential selection steps. Purified DNA from both strains was compared with the sequence of strain CDC1551 (GenBank AE000516). The CGH data indicated a large deletion in the RB14H5 genome, compared with that of MTB72 [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jac.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/dkp237/DC1">Figure S1, available as Supplementary data at <italic>JAC</italic> Online (http://jac.oxfordjournals.org/)</ext-link>]. A PCR with primers targeting the flanking regions confirmed that a 49 kbp fragment spanning 47 genes (MT1928&#8211;MT1976), including the whole of <italic>katG</italic>, was deleted from the RB14H5 genome [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jac.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/dkp237/DC1">Table S2, available as Supplementary data at <italic>JAC</italic> Online (http://jac.oxfordjournals.org/), and Figure S1</ext-link>]. The exact location of the deletion, 2127129&#8211;2176164, was determined by sequencing of this PCR product.</p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Additional SNPs were accumulated during in vitro selection</title><p>With the data obtained by CGH, not only the extent of the <italic>katG</italic> deletion could be determined, but also other mutations throughout the genome of strain RB14H5 could be identified. The two previously identified mutations in <italic>rpoB</italic> conferring resistance to rifampicin and rifabutin, S522L and V176F, respectively,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C36">36</xref></sup> were confirmed by CGH. In addition, three single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) were identified in genes MT1253, MT0208 and MT0516, corresponding to genes Rv1215c, Rv198c and Rv0498 in H37Rv (GenBank AL123456), respectively. PCR and sequencing of these regions in RB14H5 confirmed a C&#8594;T mutation in MT1253, a G&#8594;A mutation in MT0208 and a C&#8594;G mutation in MT0516, of which only the mutation in MT1253 was non-synonymous (Figure&#160;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DKP237F2">2</xref>).</p><fig id="DKP237F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of the three rounds of antibiotic selection that strain MTB72 was subjected to. The selection steps finally resulted in the triple-resistant strain RB14H5. The position of the drug resistance-conferring mutations (1, 4 and 5) and additional mutations (2, 3 and 6) indicates in which selection step they were acquired. Gene ID and coordinates of mutations 2, 3, 5 and 6 are based on the annotated genome sequence of strain CDC1551 (GenBank AE000516). R190 and RB14 are the names of the intermediate strains. RIF, rifampicin; RFB, rifabutin; INH, isoniazid; kbp, kilobase pairs; del., deletion.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="dkp23702"/></fig><p>The regions where mutations were identified in RB14H5 were screened in the intermediate strains isolated after each antibiotic selection step, to determine when these additional mutations occurred. After selection with rifampicin, two SNPs, in MT1253 and MT0208, were identified in addition to the mutation in <italic>rpoB</italic>. Selection with rifabutin resulted only in a resistance-conferring mutation, <italic>rpoB</italic>-V176F, but the 49 kbp deletion was accompanied by the mutation in MT0516 after selection with isoniazid (Figure&#160;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DKP237F2">2</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Despite the increasing prevalence of resistant <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>, isoniazid remains an essential component of current TB treatment programmes. In an attempt to shed more light on the molecular mechanisms leading to the development of MDR-TB, we initially screened <italic>in vitro</italic>-selected isoniazid-resistant mutants of <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> strain MTB72, using different concentrations of isoniazid. None of the characterized strains carried the mutations that are predominantly responsible for isoniazid resistance in clinical isolates [<italic>katG</italic>-S315T or <italic>inhA</italic>-C(-)15T]. Moreover, a large proportion of the resistant clones acquired resistance to isoniazid by deletion of <italic>katG</italic>, a genotype that is rarely observed in clinical isolates. In agreement with a previous report,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C37">37</xref></sup> we measured a higher mutation rate for isoniazid resistance than for rifampicin resistance <italic>in vitro</italic>. However, the dramatic difference between the <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> spectrum of isoniazid resistance mutations suggests that an <italic>in vivo</italic> mutation rate for isoniazid resistance equal to or potentially lower than the rifampicin resistance rate (&#8764;10<sup>&#8722;8</sup> mutations/cell division) is much more feasible. These findings indicate the importance of genetic characterization of mutants before results obtained in the laboratory are extrapolated to the clinical setting.</p><p>KatG protects bacteria from the oxidative burst encountered when <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> cells reside in macrophages or granuloma.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C38">38</xref></sup> <italic>In vitro</italic> conditions are significantly less challenging, not in the least because of the extracellular catalases in the medium, protecting the bacteria from harmful reactive oxygen species. We speculated that these protective culture conditions allowed for the observed high <italic>in vitro</italic> prevalence of &#916;<italic>katG</italic> mutants, which are highly resistant to isoniazid, but susceptible to oxidative insult.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C38">38</xref></sup> However, addition of 50 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> did not alter the spectrum of mutations (Table&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB2">2</xref>). Attempts to select isoniazid-resistant mutants from mycobacteria grown in medium without added catalase have been unsuccessful, as bacterial growth of the wild-type strain MTB72 was inadequate in medium without catalase.</p><p>Conditions that seemed to have an effect on the proportion of <italic>katG</italic> deletion mutants, but not on the presence of <italic>katG</italic>-S315T or <italic>inhA</italic>-C(-)15T mutants, were selection of mutants with low levels of isoniazid (0.4&#8211;2.0 mg/L, Tables&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB2">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB3">3</xref>) and growth/selection in human macrophages. The average proportion of &#916;<italic>katG</italic> mutants selected with 20 mg/L was 65% (39/60), with 1 mg/L was 55% (42/77) and with 0.4 mg/L was 28% (8/29, Tables&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB2">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB3">3</xref>), suggesting that &#916;<italic>katG</italic> mutants are more likely to be highly resistant.</p><p>Moreover, from the mutants selected with 0.4 mg/L isoniazid that had an MIC between 0.4 and 2.0 mg/L, only 10% (3/30, Table&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB3">3</xref>) had a deletion in the <italic>katG</italic> region. Growth in THP1 cells reduced the proportion of deletion mutants, selected with 1 mg/L isoniazid, to 20% (12/59, Table&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB2">2</xref>). These results show that it is possible to reduce the proportion of deletion mutants under specific conditions, but even in strains selected under these conditions neither of the two most prevalent clinical mutations were identified.</p><p>The mutants selected with 0.4 mg/L isoniazid (Table&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB3">3</xref>) that were stratified on the basis of their MICs were all originally selected on the same plate. In total, 179 isolates selected with 0.4 mg/L isoniazid (29&#8202;+&#8202;30&#8202;+&#8202;120, Table&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB3">3</xref>) were analysed by MLPA from this plate. None of these 179 isolates acquired either of the targeted mutations; thus, the prevalence of these mutations <italic>in vitro</italic> was &lt;0.6% (&lt;1/179, 95% CI 0%&#8211;1.6%) under the conditions described. Similar results were also obtained with strain H37Rv (&lt;3.3%), suggesting that this is a general phenomenon, rather than a strain-specific effect. This observation is also supported by the absence of reports of spontaneous <italic>in vitro</italic> isoniazid-resistant mutants that carry clinical mutations. In fact, we are aware of only one study that reports the selection of an isoniazid-resistant <italic>katG</italic>-S315T mutant,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C21">21</xref></sup> but this mutant was acquired after a mouse was infected and treated with isoniazid. It is possible that none of the selection conditions we used were suitable for the selection of the targeted mutations, perhaps because further adaptation is required to obtain an MIC&#8202;&gt;&#8202;0.4 mg/L. However, this would be true for all previous reports of <italic>in vitro</italic> studies.</p><p>The general assumption is that isoniazid resistance <italic>in vivo</italic> is much more widespread due to a higher mutation rate, particularly in <italic>katG</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C39">39</xref></sup> Indeed, the <italic>M. tuberculosis katG</italic> gene is located within a genetically unstable region,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C40">40</xref></sup> suggesting an increased propensity for mutation. Based on this instability, one would expect to observe a whole spectrum of <italic>katG</italic> mutations in resistant clinical isolates, but in practice the majority of clinically resistant strains contain the same mutations. However, the genetic instability of the <italic>katG</italic> region is a likely explanation for the high prevalence of &#916;<italic>katG</italic> mutants in our and other laboratory studies.</p><p>The empirical evidence for the high mutation rate hypothesis is extracted from a few studies in which fluctuation assays with isoniazid were performed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C37">37</xref></sup> These studies report a significantly higher mutation rate for isoniazid compared with that for rifampicin, although mutants were not genetically characterized. We obtained similar results for the <italic>in vitro</italic> mutation rates when selecting with isoniazid and rifampicin (Table&#160;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKP237TB2">2</xref>). However, we suspect that this does not explain the high prevalence of isoniazid resistance <italic>in vivo</italic>, since none of the isoniazid-resistant mutants we screened carried the mutations that are most frequently observed in clinical isolates. In fact, merely two or three mutations account for isoniazid resistance in the majority of resistant clinical isolates.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C8">8</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C13">13</xref></sup> For rifampicin resistance there are three <italic>rpoB</italic> mutations that are seen in 80%&#8211;95% of clinical isolates.<sup>9,41&#8722;43</sup> The <italic>in vivo</italic> mutation rate for isoniazid resistance is therefore more likely to be similar to or lower than the rate for rifampicin resistance, as was also suggested by others.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C44">44</xref></sup> This would still lead to a higher prevalence of isoniazid-monoresistant isolates if one takes into account that isoniazid has been used to treat TB much longer than rifampicin. In addition, isoniazid has been regularly administered as monotherapy, whereas rifampicin is almost exclusively part of a combination therapy, thereby reducing the chances of drug resistance.</p><p>Previously, researchers have shown that a whole spectrum of different &#916;<italic>katG</italic> mutants can be found both <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C45">45</xref></sup> In our study, partial deletions of the <italic>katG</italic> gene close to the 5&#8242; terminus would not have been detected with the methods used, possibly resulting in an underestimation of the deletion mutants present. The few <italic>in vitro</italic> studies on isoniazid resistance that have been performed have indeed determined that the majority of the mutants were catalase-negative.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C45">45</xref></sup> Furthermore, one group of researchers have implicitly stated that almost all <italic>in vitro</italic> isoniazid mutants identified in their laboratory were &#916;<italic>katG</italic> strains, regardless of the concentrations of isoniazid used.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C44">44</xref></sup></p><p>Throughout the course of this work, only two isoniazid-resistant mutants were identified that contained point mutations in the <italic>katG</italic> gene: one mutant acquired a TGG(W)&#8594;CGG(F) mutation in codon 321; and the other an ACT(T)&#8594;ATT(I) mutation in codon 271. Neither of these mutations has been observed in clinical isolates, although other mutations in codon 321 have been reported and associated with very low quantities of KatG, and, therefore, significantly reduced catalase/peroxidase activity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C22">22</xref></sup></p><p>None of our selected isoniazid-resistant strains carried a mutation in the <italic>oxyR</italic>-<italic>ahpC</italic> intergenic region, even after exposure to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Sherman <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C28">28</xref></sup> suggested that either a second selection event or passaging was probably necessary for <italic>in vitro</italic>-generated mutants to acquire the additional mutation in <italic>oxyR</italic>-<italic>ahpC</italic>. This may, in part, explain why this mutation was not identified in any of our strains, although there is at least one report of an isoniazid-resistant mutant that had acquired a mutation in <italic>oxyR-ahpC in vitro</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C46">46</xref></sup></p><p>The failure to detect any of the clinically prevalent mutations in <italic>katG</italic>, <italic>inhA</italic> or <italic>ahpC</italic> in our study, in combination with results of others, suggests that the current <italic>in vitro</italic> model is not representative of the <italic>in vivo</italic> situation. These observations also argue against the view that the primary route to MDR-TB is invariably via isoniazid monoresistance. In fact, there is evidence that isoniazid resistance does not always precede rifampicin resistance in the development of MDR in clinical settings.</p><p>In a recent report, a rifampicin-monoresistant <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> strain was disseminated and subsequently acquired isoniazid and other drug resistance via the common resistance mechanisms, including <italic>katG-</italic>S315T.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C47">47</xref></sup> Moreover, a recent outbreak in London started with an isoniazid-resistant strain, but upon dissemination the strain acquired rifampicin resistance via unusual mutations in <italic>rpoB</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C48">48</xref></sup> This is interesting as the genetic background of bacteria probably plays a role in the evolutionary routes they can and will follow. The presence of pre-existing drug resistance mutations can be of influence on the acquisition of additional drug resistance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C36">36</xref></sup> and several studies have shown that different genotypes of <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> appear to have different preferred resistance mechanisms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C49">49</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C51">51</xref></sup> Similar observations were made in our laboratory and by others.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C52">52</xref></sup> The occurrence of atypical drug resistance mutations may therefore be an indication of suboptimal genetic routes or unusual conditions.</p><p>We used CGH to compare the genomes of triple-resistant strain RB14H5 and that of its wild-type parent strain, MTB72. Earlier, we had determined that RB14H5 has a non-functioning catalase&#8211;peroxidase in addition to a double mutation in <italic>rpoB</italic>, which moderately increases the stress levels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C36">36</xref></sup> Remarkably, strain RB14H5 had acquired a 49 kbp deletion, spanning 47 genes including the complete <italic>katG</italic> gene, but nonetheless it remained viable <italic>in vitro</italic>. We are aware of only one other report of a strain with an equally large deletion in the <italic>katG</italic> region.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C40">40</xref></sup></p><p>Strain RB14H5 acquired three other SNPs in addition to the major deletion and the drug resistance mutations (Figure&#160;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DKP237F2">2</xref>). It is unknown if these SNPs are adaptive mutations or more opportunistic &#8216;hitchhike&#8217; mutations and whether results obtained are representative of the <italic>in vivo</italic> situation.</p><p>The genetic analysis of bacteria is generally focused on previously identified targets, such as genes involved with antibiotic resistance or repetitive sequences for fingerprinting purposes. One consequence of this bias is that additional mutations elsewhere in the genome are missed. Isogenic strains generated in the laboratory may not be as isogenic as assumed and new phenotypes may consequently be attributed to the wrong mutation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C53">53</xref></sup> CGH allows the whole genome to be screened for additional mutations that may have occurred in a strain of interest compared with the wild-type template. It would be interesting to compare clinical strains in this fashion, for instance sequential isolates obtained from a single patient.</p><p>Additionally, CGH can be valuable in detecting drug resistance-conferring mutations;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C54">54</xref></sup> in some geographical locations up to 25% of clinical strains have acquired isoniazid resistance via unidentified mechanisms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKP237C43">43</xref></sup></p><p>The present study shows that characterization of <italic>in vitro</italic> mutants is essential in order to draw accurate conclusions and that results obtained in the laboratory are not automatically applicable to the <italic>in vivo</italic> situation. Combined MLPA and CGH analysis of representative clinical isolates should be used to elucidate preferred routes to MDR. Based on our results it can be concluded that the high <italic>in vitro</italic> mutation rate for isoniazid resistance is not a satisfactory explanation for the widespread isoniazid resistance found in clinical isolates, as there is no substantial evidence that the <italic>in vivo</italic> mutation rate for isoniazid resistance is significantly higher than that for rifampicin resistance. Moreover, the outcomes of our study in combination with reports of others lead us to question the current view that development of a successful MDR strain predominantly begins with isoniazid monoresistance. A more detailed study of the genetic mechanisms by which <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> strains adapt to their environment is warranted, hopefully leading to identification of genotypes or drug resistance profiles that are most likely to result in virulent strains.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was partly funded by the EU 6th Framework Programme TBAdapt (project no. 037919).</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Transparency declarations</title><p>None to declare.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Supplementary data</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jac.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/dkp237/DC1">Table S1, Table S2 and Figure S1 are available as Supplementary data at <italic>JAC</italic> Online (http://jac.oxfordjournals.org/)</ext-link>.</p></sec>
      <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
         <title>Supplementary Material</title>
         <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
            <caption>
               <title>[Supplementary Data]</title>
            </caption>
            <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="dkp237_index.html"/>
            <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="dkp237_1.pdf"/>
         </supplementary-material>
      </sec>
   </body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank MRC-Holland (Amsterdam, The Netherlands) for providing all MLPA reagents and the RIVM (Bilthoven, The Netherlands) for providing us with strain H37Rv. We also thank Dr Arend Kolk and Sjoukje Kuijper for help with the macrophage growth experiments.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="DKP237C1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Health Organization</collab><source>Anti-tuberculosis Drug Resistance in the World. Report No. 4</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name><comment>WHO/HTM/TB/2008.394</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Middlebrook</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isoniazid-resistance and catalase activity of tubercle bacilli</article-title><source>Am Rev Tuberc</source><year>1954</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13138881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Heym</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The catalase&#8211;peroxidase gene and isoniazid resistance of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1992</year><volume>358</volume><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1501713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altamirano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Marostenmaki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mutations in the catalase&#8211;peroxidase gene from isoniazid-resistant <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> isolates</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>1994</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>1162</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8169415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stoeckle</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Riegler</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Catalase&#8211;peroxidase gene sequences in isoniazid-sensitive and -resistant strains of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> from New York City</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>1993</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>1063</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8376822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tachikawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>KatG sequence deletion is not the major cause of isoniazid resistance in Japanese and Yemeni <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> isolates</article-title><source>Mol Cell Probes</source><year>1995</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8808314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rouse</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>DeVito</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Site-directed mutagenesis of the <italic>katG</italic> gene of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>: effects on catalase&#8211;peroxidase activities and isoniazid resistance</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>583</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8939440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herrera-Le&#243;n</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sa&#237;z</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>New multiplex PCR for rapid detection of isoniazid-resistant <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> clinical isolates</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2005</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15616288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Rie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mshanga</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis for a limited number of gene codons can predict drug resistance of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> in a high-incidence community</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>636</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11158121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Detection of mutations associated with isoniazid resistance in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> isolates from China</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>5477</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16272473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dalla Costa</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Correlations of mutations in <italic>katG</italic>, <italic>oxyR</italic>-<italic>ahpC</italic> and <italic>inhA</italic> genes and <italic>in vitro</italic> susceptibility in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> clinical strains segregated by spoligotype families from tuberculosis prevalent countries in South America</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>39</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19228426</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gagneux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgos</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>DeRiemer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of bacterial genetics on the transmission of isoniazid-resistant <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2006</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>e61</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16789833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hazb&#243;n</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Brimacombe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bobadilla del Valle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Population genetics study of isoniazid resistance mutations and evolution of multidrug-resistant <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2006</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>2640</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16870753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wengenack</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhl</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>St Amand</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recombinant <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> KatG(S315T) is a competent catalase&#8211;peroxidase with reduced activity toward isoniazid</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>1997</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>722</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9291321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coll</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Arag&#243;n</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alcaide</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular analysis of isoniazid and rifampin resistance in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> isolates recovered from Barcelona</article-title><source>Microb Drug Resist</source><year>2005</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15910223</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Three-dimensional model and molecular mechanism of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> catalase&#8211;peroxidase (KatG) and isoniazid-resistant KatG mutants</article-title><source>Microb Drug Resist</source><year>2004</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15650370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saint-Joanis</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Souchon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilming</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of site-directed mutagenesis to probe the structure, function and isoniazid activation of the catalase/peroxidase, KatG, from <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>1999</year><volume>338</volume><fpage>753</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10051449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pym</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Saint-Joanis</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of <italic>katG</italic> mutations on the virulence of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> and the implication for transmission in humans</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2002</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>4955</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12183541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of <italic>katG</italic> in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> is associated with its growth and persistence in mice and guinea pigs</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>1998</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>1030</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9534978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitarai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biological and molecular characteristics of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> clinical isolates with low-level resistance to isoniazid in Japan</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>2263</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18508939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Seet</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Denkin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of isoniazid-resistant clinical isolates of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> from the USA</article-title><source>J Med Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1527</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17030912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heym</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Alzari</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Honor&#233;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Missense mutations in the catalase&#8211;peroxidase gene, <italic>katG</italic>, are associated with isoniazid resistance in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7746145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single nucleotide polymorphisms in genes associated with isoniazid resistance in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2003</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1241</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12654653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marttila</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Soini</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huovinen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>katG</italic> mutations in isoniazid-resistant <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> isolates recovered from Finnish patients</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>1996</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>2187</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8878604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Soolingen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>de Haas</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>van Doorn</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mutations at amino acid position 315 of the <italic>katG</italic> gene are associated with high-level resistance to isoniazid, other drug resistance, and successful transmission of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> in the Netherlands</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2000</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>1788</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11069256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Doorn</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>de Haas</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Public health impact of isoniazid-resistant <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> strains with a mutation at amino-acid position 315 of <italic>katG</italic>: a decade of experience in The Netherlands</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>769</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16842572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouse</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of <italic>ahpC</italic> gene mutations in isoniazid-resistant clinical isolates of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>1997</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>2057</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9303417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mdluli</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>AhpC, oxidative stress and drug resistance in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Biofactors</source><year>1999</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10609885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dhandayuthapani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mudd</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress response and its role in sensitivity to isoniazid in mycobacteria: characterization and inducibility of <italic>ahpC</italic> by peroxides in <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic> and lack of expression in <italic>M. aurum</italic> and <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1996</year><volume>178</volume><fpage>3641</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8655566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>ahpC</italic>, a gene involved in isoniazid resistance of the <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> complex</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1025</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8830260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mdluli</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Compensatory <italic>ahpC</italic> gene expression in isoniazid-resistant <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Science</source><year>1996</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>1641</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8658136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sreevatsan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the <italic>oxyR-ahpC</italic> region in isoniazid-resistant and -susceptible <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> complex organisms recovered from diseased humans and animals in diverse localities</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>1997</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>600</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9056000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergval</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijzelaar</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalla Costa</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development of multiplex assay for rapid characterization of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>689</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18077627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luria</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Delbr&#252;ck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations of bacteria from virus sensitivity to virus resistance</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1943</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17247100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anthony</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuitema</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergval</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acquisition of rifabutin resistance by a rifampicin resistant mutant of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> involves an unusual spectrum of mutations and elevated frequency</article-title><source>Ann Clin Microbiol Antimicrob</source><year>2005</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>9</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15958167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergval</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Klatser</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuitema</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Specific mutations in the <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis rpoB</italic> gene are associated with increased <italic>dnaE2</italic> expression</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>2007</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>338</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17868360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probability distribution of drug-resistant mutants in unselected populations of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Appl Microbiol</source><year>1970</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>810</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4991927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manca</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>CE</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> catalase and peroxidase activities and resistance to oxidative killing in human monocytes <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>1999</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9864198</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riska</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Alland</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular determinants of drug resistance in tuberculosis</article-title><source>Int J Tuberc Lung Dis</source><year>2000</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>S4</fpage><lpage>S10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688142</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strain variation in the <italic>katG</italic> region of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7830574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Telenti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics of drug resistance in tuberculosis</article-title><source>Clin Chest Med</source><year>1997</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9098610</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sajduda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brzostek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Poplawska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of rifampin- and isoniazid-resistant <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> strains isolated in Poland</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>2425</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15184414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Musser</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular genetic basis of antimicrobial agent resistance in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>: 1998 update</article-title><source>Tuber Lung Dis</source><year>1998</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10645439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slayden</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>CE</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>The genetics and biochemistry of isoniazid resistance in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Microbes Infect</source><year>2000</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10884617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mdluli</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms involved in the intrinsic isoniazid resistance of <italic>Mycobacterium avium</italic></article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1223</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9570407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heym</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Stavropoulos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Honor&#233;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of overexpression of the alkyl hydroperoxide reductase AhpC on the virulence and isoniazid resistance of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>1997</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>1395</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9119479</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bifani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathema</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurepina</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The evolution of drug resistance in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>: from a mono-rifampin-resistant cluster into increasingly multidrug-resistant variants in an HIV-seropositive population</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2008</year><volume>198</volume><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18498237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Claxton</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Shorten</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rifampicin resistance in tuberculosis outbreak, London, England</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2005</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>931</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15963290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lipin</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Stepanshina</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Shemyakin</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of specific mutations in <italic>katG</italic>, <italic>rpoB</italic>, <italic>rpsL</italic> and <italic>rrs</italic> genes with spoligotypes of multidrug-resistant <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> isolates in Russia</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2007</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>620</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17403134</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hillemann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubica</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#252;sch-Gerdes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Disequilibrium in distribution of resistance mutations among <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> Beijing and non-Beijing strains isolated from patients in Germany</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2005</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>1229</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15728936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rinder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Disequilibria in the distribution of <italic>rpoB</italic> alleles in rifampicin-resistant <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> isolates from Germany and Sierra Leone</article-title><source>Microb Drug Resist</source><year>1997</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9185147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Sullivan</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of oxidative stress on the mutation rate of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> with impaired catalase/peroxidase function</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2008</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18577539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chakravorty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aladegbami</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Motiwala</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rifampin resistance, Beijing-W clade-single nucleotide polymorphism cluster group 2 phylogeny, and the Rv2629 191-C allele in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> strains</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>2555</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18550732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DKP237C54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manjunatha</surname><given-names>UH</given-names></name><name><surname>Boshoff</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowd</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of a nitroimidazo-oxazine-specific protein involved in PA-824 resistance in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16387854</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>