
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bioinfo</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2916718</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btq326</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Discovery Note</subject><subj-group><subject>Sequence Analysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Homology of SMP domains to the TULIP superfamily of lipid-binding proteins provides a structural basis for lipid exchange between ER and mitochondria </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kopec</surname><given-names>Klaus O.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alva</surname><given-names>Vikram</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lupas</surname><given-names>Andrei N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1">Department of Protein Evolution, Max-Planck-Institute for Developmental Biology, Spemannstr. 35, 72076 Tübingen, Germany</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">* To whom correspondence should be addressed.</corresp><fn><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Associate Editor: Alfonso Valencia </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>6</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>16</day><month>6</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>26</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>1927</fpage><lpage>1931</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>5</day><month>6</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>6</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Mitochondria must uptake some phospholipids from the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) for the biogenesis of their membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>They convert one of these lipids, phosphatidylserine, to phosphatidylethanolamine, which can be re-exported via the ER to all other cellular membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The mechanisms underlying these exchanges between ER and mitochondria are poorly understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Recently, a complex termed ER–mitochondria encounter structure (ERMES) was shown to be necessary for phospholipid exchange in budding yeast. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>However, it is unclear whether this complex is merely an inter-organelle tether or also the transporter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>ERMES consists of four proteins: Mdm10, Mdm34 (Mmm2), Mdm12 and Mmm1, three of which contain the uncharacterized SMP domain common to a number of eukaryotic membrane-associated proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Here, we show that the SMP domain belongs to the TULIP superfamily of lipid/hydrophobic ligand-binding domains comprising members of known structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>This relationship suggests that the SMP domains of the ERMES complex mediate lipid exchange between ER and mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Contact: andrei.lupas@tuebingen.mpg.de </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Supplementary information: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/btq326/DC1">Supplementary data</ext-link> are available at Bioinformatics online. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="SEC1"><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>1 INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Mitochondria are organelles of endosymbiotic origin, found in virtually all eukaryotic organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>They are the main generators of adenosine triphosphate (ATP)—the energy currency of the cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Additionally, they participate in a series of other important processes, including apoptosis, amino acid and lipid metabolism, iron–sulphur cluster assembly and the regulation of calcium levels within the cell (Lill and Kispal, 2000; McBride et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>However, only a small fraction of the biopolymers required to carry out these functions is synthesized in the mitochondria, the rest must be imported from the outside. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>For example, they only produce some of the phospholipids that make up their membranes, whereas the remainder originates from the endoplasmic reticulum (ER). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, mitochondria not only import phospholipids but also export a particular one, phosphatidylethanolamine (PtdEtn), to the ER, where it is methylated to form the phospholipid phosphatidylcholine (Voelker, 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Mitochondria synthesize PtdEtn by decarboxylating phosphatidylserine, a phospholipid imported from the ER. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The mechanisms responsible for the influx and efflux of phospholipids are unclear. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Unlike most organelles, mitochondria do not exchange phospholipids via vesicular transport. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have suggested that this exchange takes place via ER–mitochondria associations (Achleitner et al., 1999; Voelker, 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>More recently, Kornmann et al. (2009) identified a complex, the ER–mitochondria encounter structure (ERMES), that acts as a molecular tether between ER and mitochondria in Saccharomyces cerevisiae and is required for efficient inter-organelle phospholipid exchange. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>However, it remained unclear whether ERMES merely tethers these organelles together, thereby aligning proteins that carry out the actual transport, or also recruits and transfers phospholipids itself. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>ERMES comprises four proteins (Fig. 1): the mitochondrial outer membrane protein Mdm10, the putative outer membrane protein Mdm34 (Mmm2), the ER-resident Mmm1 and the cytosolic Mdm12 (Kornmann et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>These proteins have also been implicated in other mitochondrial functions, including morphology maintenance (Okamoto and Shaw, 2005) and protein import (Meisinger et al., 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Two of the ERMES components, Mmm1 and Mdm12, were reported to contain the uncharacterized SMP domain (synaptotagmin-like, mitochondrial and lipid-binding proteins), which is also present in a number of other eukaryotic membrane-associated proteins (Lee and Hong, 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>SMP domain-containing proteins have been classified into four broad groups: C2 domain synaptotagmin-like, PH domain-containing HT-008, PDZK8 and mitochondrial protein families (Lee and Hong, 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The functions of these proteins are poorly understood. Fig. 1.Domain organization of the four ERMES proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>All ERMES proteins, except the mitochondrial outer membrane protein (OMP) Mdm10, contain an SMP domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The SMP domain in Mdm34 was discovered in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In this study, we show that the SMP domain belongs to a superfamily of lipid/hydrophobic ligand-binding domains of known structure, which we call TULIP for tubular lipid-binding proteins, and propose a role for it in cellular phospholipid traffic. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods" id="SEC2"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>2 METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>All sequence similarity searches were carried out in the MPI bioinformatics toolkit (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://toolkit.tuebingen.mpg.de">http://toolkit.tuebingen.mpg.de</ext-link>; Biegert et al., 2006) using HHpred (Söding et al., 2005) and HHsenser (Söding et al., 2006) with default settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>HHpred searches were performed against a database comprising PDB70 (protein databank structures, as available on the 15th of April 2010, clustered at 70% sequence identity) and genomes of phylogenetically diverse organisms (Arabidopsis thaliana, Caenorhabditis elegans, Drosophila melanogaster, Homo sapiens and S.cerevisiae). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Representatives of the four SMP domain-containing groups from the aforementioned organisms were chosen as seeds for the searches in Figures 2 and 3, based on their presence in the core of their respective clusters in the sequence cluster map (Fig. 5). Fig. 2.Pairwise HMM comparison of SMP and TULIP domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Representatives of the four SMP domain-containing groups and of TULIP domains were chosen from Arabidopsis thaliana (At), Caenorhabditis elegans (Ce), Drosophila melanogaster (Dm), Dermatophagoides pteronyssinus (Dp), Epiphyas postvittana (Ep), Galleria mellonella (Gm), Homo sapiens (Hs) and Saccharomyces cerevisiae (Sc). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Group and protein names of these representatives, along with domain boundaries and names of source species are indicated (from left to right). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>HHpred was used to perform pairwise HMM comparisons between them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Cell color indicates the HHpred probability of the match as depicted in the scale on the right; probabilities &lt;20% are shown as white cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Proteins with known structures are marked with an asterisk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The abbreviations of the hydrophobic ligand binders are explained in the text. Fig. 3.Fold predictions for SMP domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The highest scoring PDB matches for the 16 representative SMP sequences in Figure 2 were collected with three of the top-scoring prediction servers in CASP8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Top matches to TULIP domains are shown in blue and to any other structure in red. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The color saturation is scaled linearly between the maximum and minimum scores returned by the respective method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The value ranges corresponding to pale (low confidence), medium and dark (high confidence) saturation are: Phyre-estimated precision 0–33, 34–66 and 67–100, MULTICOM e-value 7.4–5, 5.1–2.6, 2.5–0, MUSTER Z-score 0–1.8, 1.9–3.5, 3.6–5.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The number of matches to TULIP domains against the total is shown in the right-hand column. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>To identify sequences for cluster analysis, we searched the non-redundant protein sequence database (nr) at NCBI for homologs of the SMP domain from the yeast protein Mmm1 (residues 196–409), the N-terminal domain of human cholesteryl ester transfer protein (2OBD, residues 16–206), the Takeout 1 protein from Epiphyas postvittana (3E8T), and the dust mite allergen Der p 7 (3H4Z) using HHsenser. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>We pooled the permissive sets returned by HHsenser to obtain 2033 sequences, which we clustered by their pairwise BLAST P-values (Altschul et al., 1990) in CLANS (Frickey and Lupas, 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Clustering was done to equilibrium in 2D at a P-value cutoff of e-4 using default settings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="SEC3"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>3 RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The number of structural solutions available to a polypeptide chain is limited, making protein structures multiply convergent (Cheng et al., 2008; Krishna and Grishin, 2004; Salem et al., 1999), while the combinatorial possibilities in sequence space are nearly endless. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>For this reason, sequence similarity is considered the primary marker of homology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>We thus used sensitive sequence comparisons, as implemented in HHpred, to find homologs of the SMP domain in a database concatenating several complete genomes with PDB70 (see ‘Methods’ section). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The search was seeded with the SMP domain from Mmm1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The best hits were to other proteins that have previously been described to contain this domain (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>In addition, we detected a hitherto unknown SMP domain in the ERMES protein Mdm34. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>This protein has been reported as an integral outer membrane protein (Youngman et al., 2004), but we were unable to identify any sequence motifs in it that would indicate membrane insertion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>HHpred searches with other representatives and reciprocal searches with Mdm34 confirmed the presence of an SMP domain, raising the number of SMP domains in ERMES to three (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>We also found statistically significant matches to many eukaryotic proteins from the bactericidal/permeability-increasing protein-like (BPI-like) family (Fig. 2), including two with known structures: BPI (1EWF) and cholesteryl ester transfer protein (CETP; 2OBD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Other members of this family are lipopolysaccharide-binding protein (LPSBP), lipid-binding serum glycoprotein (LBSGP), phospholipid transfer protein (PLTP) and long and short paralogs of palate, lung and nasal epithelium carcinoma-associated protein (PLUNC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Some of these proteins have been shown to bind lipids, e.g. CETP facilitates lipid transport between different lipoproteins (Qiu et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>BPI and CETP have similar structures, each containing two tandem domains that adopt the same fold, comprising a long α-helix wrapped in a highly curved anti-parallel β-sheet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>All BPI-like proteins contain these two domains, the only exception being short PLUNC, which has only one. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The domains show little sequence identity (&lt;15%) and sequence comparisons do not yield significant matches between them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Instead, the C-terminal domain only shows matches to the Aha1 protein, a co-chaperone of Hsp90 in eukaryotes which shares the same fold (1USU; d.83.2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the N- and C-terminal domains of BPI-like proteins are thought to have a common ancestry based on their structural similarity (Kleiger et al., 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The Structural Classification of Proteins database (SCOP; Murzin et al., 1995) also considers them to be homologous and classifies them into the same family (d.83.1.1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>HHpred searches with SMP domains yielded many statistically significant matches to the N-terminal domain of BPI-like proteins (Fig. 2), but not to the C-terminal domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>We confirmed these findings with reciprocal searches using both domains of BPI-like proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>From the statistical significance of these matches, we conclude that SMP domains are homologous to BPI-like proteins and therefore predict that they share the same tubular fold and lipid-binding properties. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Further searches with the N-terminal domain of BPI-like proteins retrieved three more proteins of known structure: dust mite allergen Der p 7 (3H4Z), a juvenile hormone-binding protein from Galleria mellonella (JHBP, 2RCK), and a Takeout 1 protein from Epiphyas postvittana (3E8T). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>These proteins are exclusively found in arthropods and are involved in binding hydrophobic ligands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>They are composed of a single domain homologous to the N-terminal domain of BPI-like proteins (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/btq326/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link>), a relationship that has been described previously (Hamiaux et al., 2009; Kolodziejczyk et al., 2008; Mueller et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>In view of their similarities in sequence and structure, we propose to group the arthropod proteins together with the BPI-like family into the TULIP superfamily. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>To confirm the membership of SMP domains in the TULIP superfamily, we generated fold predictions for 16 representative sequences using the servers Phyre (Kelley and Sternberg, 2009), MULTICOM (Wang et al., 2010) and MUSTER (Wu and Zhang, 2008), all of which performed very well in the most recent Critical Assessment of Structure Prediction Experiment, CASP8 (Kryshtafovych et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>All three methods yielded many highest-scoring matches to TULIP domains (Fig. 3 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/btq326/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S2</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we queried the fold prediction metaserver I-TASSER (Roy et al., 2010), which was the top performing server in CASP 7 &amp; 8 (Zhang, 2007, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>This server returned a TULIP domain as the top match for 10 of 16 queries and as one of the top three matches for all but one query (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/btq326/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S3</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>These matches included both BPI-like and Takeout-like proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>A structure-assisted multiple sequence alignment of SMP domains to TULIP domains of known structure highlights the basis for these matches (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>All sequences have similar length, distribution of (predicted) secondary structure, and pattern of hydrophobic residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>However, there are no conserved sequence motifs, unsurprisingly as such motifs are not even detectable within individual families (Beamer et al., 1997; Kolodziejczyk et al., 2008). Fig. 4.Multiple sequence alignment of TULIP domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>An alignment comprising representatives of the SMP domain family and TULIP domains of known structure is shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Sequences are labeled as in Figure 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The alignment was generated by a three-step approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>First, a multiple alignment of SMP sequences was obtained using HHpred in local maximum accuracy (MAC) alignment mode. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Second, a structure-based sequence alignment of TULIP domain structures was derived from a multiple structure superimposition calculated using MAMMOTH-mult (Lupyan et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>In the final step, these two alignments were merged manually using as guide an alignment between 1EWF and Mmm1 obtained with HHpred. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The α-helices are shown in red and β-strands in blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Secondary structure predictions for the SMP domains were performed with Ali2D (Biegert et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Numbers in parentheses represent length of omitted segments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Positions in the alignments that are highly conserved or strongly hydrophobic are shown in boldface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Residues that could not be aligned in structure or sequence are shown in lower case. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>To explore the relative positions in sequence space of proteins of the TULIP superfamily, we searched for homologs of SMP domains, N-terminal domains of BPI-like proteins, as well as allergens and Takeout proteins in the nr database using HHsenser, and clustered the obtained sequences in CLANS (see ‘Methods’ section). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The resulting cluster map (Fig. 5) shows three distinct but connected regions corresponding to SMP, BPI and Takeout-like domain families, confirming the proposed homology between them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>In addition to the SMP groups described by Lee and Hong (2006) and the group of Mdm34 proteins described in this article, the clustering revealed a further SMP group, the uncharacterized transmembrane 24 proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>It also yielded a number of additional groups of BPI-like proteins, including the expression site-associated gene 5 proteins (ESAG5) from trypanosomes, whose homology to BPI-like proteins has been reported previously (Barker et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>BPI and Takeout-like domains are connected by the arthropod allergens, one form of which is unique in containing tandem domains with clear sequence similarity, indicating a domain duplication that occurred in insects (yellow and orange clusters in Fig. 5). Fig. 5.Cluster map of the TULIP domain superfamily. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>We searched for relatives of SMP domains, Takeout proteins, dust mite allergens and N-terminal domains of BPI-like proteins in the non-redundant database using HHsenser and clustered them in CLANS based on their all-against-all pairwise similarities as measured by BLAST P-values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Dots represent sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Sequences within one group are indicated by the same color; sequences that could not be assigned to a group are not colored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Line coloring reflects BLAST P-values; the darker a line, the lower the P-value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Protein families containing members with known structure are indicated with an asterisk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The lipid-binding proteins cluster (LBP) also comprises LPSBP and LPSBP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations are as in the text. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Accession details for representatives of all clusters are provided in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/btq326/DC1">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="SEC4"><title><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>4 CONCLUSIONS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>In this study, we have shown that the SMP domain belongs to the TULIP domain superfamily, a large group of proteins that bind lipids and other hydrophobic ligands within a central, tubular cavity (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>In several cases (CETP, PLTP), members of this superfamily are known to exploit this binding activity in order to mediate lipid trafficking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Given the extensive lipid exchange between the ER and the mitochondrial outer membrane and the location of the ERMES complex as a connector between them, it is attractive to consider that this exchange is mediated by the SMP domains of the ERMES subunits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>As the ERMES complex does not include a nucleotidase that could energize this process, we propose that it proceeds along an affinity gradient, amounting to facilitated diffusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Although this could be envisaged as resulting from many short, structurally unspecific contacts between the SMP domains (‘kiss-and-run’ mechanism), we prefer to consider that the domains assemble into structurally well-defined complexes, which establish a lipophilic, tubular path between the two membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Since the stoichiometry of subunits within the ERMES complex is currently unknown, it is however not possible at this time to judge on whether 1 : 1 : 1 or some other ratio would most appropriately describe the composition of such complexes. Fig. 6.View along the ligand-binding tunnel of a Takeout protein (3E8T, residues 5–211). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The ligand is shown as red sticks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Funding: This work was supported by institutional funds from the Max-Planck-Society. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Conflict of Interest: none declared. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag>
      <SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
         <title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
         <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
            <caption>
               <title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>[Supplementary Data] </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
            </caption>
            <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="btq326_index.html"/>
            <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword" xlink:href="btq326_SMP_domain_paper_revision2_SUPPLEMENT.doc"/>
         </supplementary-material>
      </sec></SecTag>
   </body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>AchleitnerGAssociation between the endoplasmic reticulum and mitochondria of yeast facilitates interorganelle transport of phospholipids through membrane contactEur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Biochem.199926454555310491102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>AltschulSFBasic local alignment search toolJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Biol.19902154034102231712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>BarkerARBioinformatic insights to the ESAG5 and GRESAG5 gene families in kinetoplastid parasitesMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Parasitol.200816211212218773926 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>BeamerLJCrystal structure of human BPI and two bound phospholipids at 2.4 angstrom resolutionScience1997276186118649188532 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>BiegertAThe MPI Bioinformatics Toolkit for protein sequence analysisNucleic Acids Res.200634W335W33916845021 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>ChengHMALISAM: a database of structurally analogous motifs in proteinsNucleic Acids Res.200836D211D21717855399 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>FrickeyTLupasACLANS: a Java application for visualizing protein families based on pairwise similarityBioinformatics2004203702370415284097 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>HamiauxCCrystal structure of Epiphyas postvittana takeout 1 with bound ubiquinone supports a role as ligand carriers for takeout proteins in insectsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Chem.20092843496350319073605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>KelleyLASternbergMJProtein structure prediction on the Web: a case study using the Phyre serverNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Protocols20094363371 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>KleigerGThe 1.7 A crystal structure of BPI: a study of how two dissimilar amino acid sequences can adopt the same foldJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Biol.20002991019103410843855 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>KolodziejczykRInsect juvenile hormone binding protein shows ancestral fold present in human lipid-binding proteinsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Biol.200837787088118291417 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>KornmannBAn ER-mitochondria tethering complex revealed by a synthetic biology screenScience200932547748119556461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>KrishnaSSGrishinNVStructurally analogous proteins do exist!Structure2004121125112715242587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>KryshtafovychAProtein structure prediction center in CASP8Proteins200977Suppl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>95919722263 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>LeeIHongWDiverse membrane-associated proteins contain a novel SMP domainFASEB J.20062020220616449791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>LillRKispalGMaturation of cellular Fe-S proteins: an essential function of mitochondriaTrends Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Sci.20002535235610916152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>LupyanDA new progressive-iterative algorithm for multiple structure alignmentBioinformatics2005213255326315941743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>McBrideHMMitochondria: more than just a powerhouseCurr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Biol.200616R551R56016860735 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>MeisingerCThe mitochondrial morphology protein Mdm10 functions in assembly of the preprotein translocase of the outer membraneDev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Cell20047617115239954 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>MuellerGAThe structure of the dust mite allergen Der p 7 reveals similarities to innate immune proteinsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Allergy Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Immunol.2010125909917e90420226507 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>MurzinAGSCOP: a structural classification of proteins database for the investigation of sequences and structuresJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Biol.19952475365407723011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>OkamotoKShawJMMitochondrial morphology and dynamics in yeast and multicellular eukaryotesAnnu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Genet.20053950353616285870 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>QiuXCrystal structure of cholesteryl ester transfer protein reveals a long tunnel and four bound lipid moleculesNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Struct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Biol.20071410611317237796 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>RoyAI-TASSER: a unified platform for automated protein structure and function predictionNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Protocols20105725738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>SalemGMCorrelation of observed fold frequency with the occurrence of local structural motifsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Biol.199928796998110222204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>SödingJThe HHpred interactive server for protein homology detection and structure predictionNucleic Acids Res.200533W244W24815980461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>SödingJHHsenser: exhaustive transitive profile search using HMM-HMM comparisonNucleic Acids Res.200634W374W37816845029 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>VoelkerDRNew perspectives on the regulation of intermembrane glycerophospholipid trafficJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Lipid Res.20034444144912562848 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>WangZMULTICOM: a multi-level combination approach to protein structure prediction and its assessments in CASP8Bioinformatics20102688288820150411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>WuSZhangYMUSTER: Improving protein sequence profile-profile alignments by using multiple sources of structure informationProteins20087254755618247410 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>YoungmanMJMmm2p, a mitochondrial outer membrane protein required for yeast mitochondrial shape and maintenance of mtDNA nucleoidsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Cell Biol.200416467768814981098 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>ZhangYTemplate-based modeling and free modeling by I-TASSER in CASP7Proteins200769Suppl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>810811717894355 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>ZhangYI-TASSER: fully automated protein structure prediction in CASP8Proteins200977Suppl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>910011319768687 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
