<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?properties manuscript?><?origin nihpa?><?iso-abbr Nature?><?submitter-system nihms?><?submitter-canonical-name Nature Publishing Group?><?submitter-canonical-id NATURE-STRUCTUR?><?submitter-userid 1045?><?submitter-authority publisher?><?submitter-login nature-structure?><?submitter-name Nature Publishing Group (obsolete)?><?domain nihpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0410462</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">6011</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nature</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nature</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0028-0836</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1476-4687</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2941915</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20844536</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09347</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">nihpa221823</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Notch and EGFR pathway interaction regulates neural stem cell number and self-renewal</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>Adan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref rid="FN2" ref-type="author-notes">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rubio</surname><given-names>Maria E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>Vittorio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label> Center for Neuroscience Research, Children&#8217;s National Medical Center, Washington, DC 20010</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label> University of Pittsburgh Medical School, Department Otolaryngology, Pittsburgh, PA 15261</aff><author-notes><corresp id="FN1"><label>*</label>Corresponding Author: Dr. Vittorio Gallo, Center for Neuroscience Research, Children&#8217;s National Medical Center, 111 Michigan Ave. NW, Washington, DC 20010, Phone: 202-476-4996, Fax: 202-476-4988, <email>vgallo@cnmcresearch.org</email></corresp><fn id="FN2" fn-type="present-address"><label>3</label><p>Present Address: SUNY at Stony Brook University, Pharmacology Department, Stony Brook, NY 11794-5140</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>19</day><month>7</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>16</day><month>9</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>467</volume><issue>7313</issue><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>327</lpage><!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1038/nature09347--><permissions><license><license-p>Users may view, print, copy, download and text and data- mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Specialized cellular microenvironments, or &#8220;niches,&#8221; modulate stem cell properties, including cell number, self-renewal and fate decisions<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>. In the adult brain, niches that maintain a source of neural stem cells (NSCs) and neural progenitor cells (NPCs) are the subventricular zone (SVZ) of the lateral ventricle and the dentate gyrus of the hippocampus<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>. The size of the NSC population of the SVZ at any time is the result of several ongoing processes, including self-renewal, cell differentiation, and cell death. Maintaining the balance between NSC and NPCs in the SVZ niche is critical to supply the brain with specific neural populations, both under normal conditions or after injury. A fundamental question relevant to both normal development and to cell-based repair strategies in the central nervous system is how the balance of different NSC and NPC populations is maintained in the niche. EGFR and Notch signaling pathways play fundamental roles during development of multicellular organisms<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>. In <italic>Drosophila</italic> and in <italic>C. elegans</italic> these pathways may have either cooperative or antagonistic functions<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>. In the SVZ, Notch regulates NSC identity and self-renewal, whereas EGFR specifically affects NPC proliferation and migration<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>. This suggests that interplay of these two pathways may maintain the balance between NSC and NPC numbers. Here we show that functional cell-cell interaction between NPCs and NSCs through epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) and Notch signaling plays a crucial role in maintaining the balance between these cell populations in the SVZ. Enhanced EGFR signaling in vivo results in the expansion of the NPC pool, and reduces NSC number and self-renewal. This occurs through a non-cell-autonomous mechanism involving EGFR-mediated regulation of Notch signaling. Our findings define a novel interaction between EGFR and Notch pathways in the adult SVZ, and thus provide a mechanism for NSC and NPC pool maintenance.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p id="P2">We examined whether changes in SVZ NPC number affect NSC properties. In the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse, the hEGFR is expressed in <italic>CNP</italic>-expressing NPCs and in NG2<sup>+</sup> progenitors<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, but not in <italic>GFAP</italic>-expressing NSCs or in neuroblasts (<xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 1a,b</xref>). EGFR overexpression enhances EGFR signaling in the adult SVZ (data not shown) and expands the NPC pool<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> (<xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 1a,b</xref>). The SVZ of <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse contains more NG2<sup>+</sup> progenitors than WT, but a reduced number of GFAP<sup>+</sup> NSCs (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1a</xref>; <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>). In WT, GFAP<sup>+</sup> cells exhibit a radial glia-like morphology (<xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 1c1</xref>), whereas in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice GFAP<sup>+</sup> cells display a morphology of protoplasmatic astrocytes (<xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 1d1</xref>)<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>. GFAP and Nestin were co-expressed in the WT SVZ, while the percentage of GFAP<sup>+</sup>Nestin<sup>+</sup> cells was reduced in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1a,b</xref>).</p><p id="P3">In SVZ cells from <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice, Lex<sup>+</sup>Nestin<sup>+</sup>GFAP<sup>+</sup> NSCs were reduced, compared to WT (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1a,b</xref>). This was not due to cell death (0.6+/&#8722;0.02 and 0.5+/&#8722;0.06% of Caspase3<sup>+</sup> cells/10<sup>6</sup> um<sup>3</sup>, WT and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR, respectively). Ultrastructural analysis<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> confirmed fewer NSCs and more neuroblasts in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice compared to WT (<xref rid="SD4" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 3</xref>).</p><p id="P4">We used LeX antibodies<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> to FACS-purify LeX<sup>+</sup><italic>CNP</italic>-EGFP<sup>neg</sup> SVZ NSCs from <italic>CNP</italic>-EGFP and <italic>CNP</italic>-EGFP/<italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice (<xref rid="SD5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 4</xref>). LeX<sup>+</sup><italic>CNP</italic>-EGFP<sup>neg</sup> cells were GFAP<sup>+</sup> (data not shown). The number of LeX<sup>+</sup><italic>CNP</italic>-EGFP<sup>neg</sup> NSCs was reduced in the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse, whereas LeX<sup>+</sup><italic>CNP</italic>-EGFP<sup>+</sup> NPCs were increased (<xref rid="SD5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 4</xref>). LeX<sup>+</sup><italic>CNP</italic>-EGFP<sup>neg</sup> NSCs from <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice displayed a reduction in LeX<sup>+</sup> neurosphere<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> number and size, compared to WT cells (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1c,d</xref>). Conversely, <italic>CNP</italic>-EGFP<sup>+</sup>LeX<sup>+</sup> NPC proliferation was increased (not shown).</p><p id="P5">In <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP/<italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice, <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup> cells with radial glia-like morphology were almost absent in the SVZ (<xref rid="SD6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 5b</xref>). Conversely, in <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP mice, GFP<sup>+</sup> cells displayed radial glia-like cell morphology throughout the SVZ (<xref rid="SD6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 5a</xref>). In FACS-purified cells from <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP and <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP/<italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice, enhanced EGFR signaling reduced the number of LeX<sup>+</sup><italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup> NSCs, whereas the number of LeX<sup>+</sup><italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>neg</sup> NPCs was increased (<xref rid="SD6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 5c,d</xref>). NSCs from <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP/<italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice displayed reduced neurosphere number and size compared to cells from <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP mice (<xref rid="SD6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 5c,d</xref>), however proliferation of LeX<sup>+</sup><italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>neg</sup> NPCs was increased (not shown). These results show that enhanced EGFR signaling and expansion of SVZ <italic>CNP</italic>-expressing progenitors<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> reduces the number, proliferation, and self-renewal of <italic>GFAP</italic>-expressing NSCs.</p><p id="P6">Notch<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, BMP<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> and Shh<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> regulate NSC properties in the SVZ. Enhanced EGFR signaling upregulated genes involved in neurogenesis [<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup. Table 1</xref> (GEO access number GSE21913) and <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a</xref>], whereas Notch signaling elements were downregulated. Shh and BMP pathways were not modified (data not shown). In WT and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR SVZ Notch1 was mainly detected in NSCs<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, whereas Dll1 and Jagged1 were detected in NPCs and in neuroblasts (<xref rid="SD7" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 6a&#8211;f</xref>; see also <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a&#8211;d</xref>). <italic>Dll</italic>-EGFP electroporation demonstrated expression in EGFR<sup>+</sup>NG2<sup>+</sup> and in Dcx<sup>+</sup> cells, but not in GFAP<sup>+</sup> cells (<xref rid="SD7" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 6g&#8211;j</xref>). Conversely, <italic>Hes1</italic> activity was mainly observed in GFAP<sup>+</sup> cells (<xref rid="SD7" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 6k&#8211;m</xref>; see also <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a&#8211;d</xref>). Notch1, NICD, Dll1, RBPJK and Hes1 proteins were decreased by 60 &#177; 3, 63 &#177; 4, 20 &#177; 2, 30 &#177; 2.5 and 40 &#177; 3% upon enhanced EGFR function, respectively (n= 3&#8211;4 each; <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a</xref>). Conversely, Numb was increased by 45 &#177; 3% (n=3). In the SVZ of the Wa2 mouse<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, NPC number and proliferation were reduced<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, and Notch1, NICD, RBPJK and Hes1 were upregulated, as compared to WT (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2b</xref>).</p><p id="P7">EGF infusion into the lateral ventricle of <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP mice increased the number of BrdU<sup>+</sup> cells in the SVZ, downregulated Notch signaling and expanded EGFR-expressing NPCs (<xref rid="SD8" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 7a-e</xref>). Proliferation and self-renewal of NSCs from EGF-infused SVZ were reduced compared to controls (<xref rid="SD8" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 7f,g</xref>).</p><p id="P8">To rescue the NSC phenotype in the postnatal <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice, we overexpressed the constitutively active form of Notch1 (Notch1 intracellular domain; NICD) in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR SVZ cells (<xref rid="SD9" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 8a</xref>). Neurosphere numbers and size were greater in <italic>NICD</italic>- than in mock-transfected cells (<xref rid="SD9" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 8b</xref>). <italic>NICD</italic> electroporation in SVZ cells of <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR<italic>/GFAP</italic>-GFP mice partially rescued the radial glia-like morphology of <italic>GFAP</italic>-expressing cells (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2c,d</xref>; see also <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a1&#8211;a3 and b1&#8211;b3</xref>), and increased neurosphere number and size (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2e,f</xref>). After adenovirus-mediated transduction of <italic>NICD</italic> (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2g</xref>) in adult WT and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice, NICD levels were higher (30 &#177; 3%) in <italic>NICD</italic>-LacZ- (ad-<italic>NICD</italic>) than in LacZ adenovirus (Ad-LacZ)-infected SVZs, whereas Numb levels were reduced (55 &#177; 4%) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2h</xref>). <italic>NICD</italic> transduction rescued NSC properties in the SVZ of <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR/<italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP mice (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2h,i</xref>).</p><p id="P9">We infused cytosine-&#946;-D-arabinofuranoside (Ara-C) into the LV to deplete dividing NPCs<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>. In saline-perfused adult mice, BrdU<sup>+</sup> cell number was significantly higher in <italic>CNP-</italic>hEGFR mice (24.1+/&#8722;2.1 cells/10<sup>6</sup> &#956;m<sup>3</sup>) compared to WT (12.4 +/&#8722;0.5 cells/10<sup>6</sup> &#956;m<sup>3</sup>) (<xref rid="SD10" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 9a,b</xref>; <italic>t</italic>-test p&lt;0.008), whereas NSC number was reduced (<xref rid="SD10" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 9a,b</xref>, and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a</xref>; <italic>t</italic>-test p&lt;0.005). Ara-C increased GFAP<sup>+</sup> cell number in the SVZ of adult <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice (<xref rid="SD10" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 9c,d</xref> and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a</xref>). We observed higher levels of Notch1 in GFAP<sup>+</sup> NSCs of Ara-C-treated <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR and WT mice, compared with saline-infused mice (not shown). In <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice, <italic>Hes1</italic> and <italic>RBPjk</italic> mRNAs and Notch1 protein levels were higher in Ara-C-treated SVZ tissues than in saline controls (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3b</xref>), whereas <italic>Numb</italic> mRNA and protein were reduced (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3b</xref>). Cell proliferation and self-renewal were enhanced in neurospheres from Ara-C-treated tissue, compared with saline (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3c</xref>). Altogether, these data indicate that NPCs regulate NSC proliferation and self-renewal in vivo.</p><p id="P10">To demonstrate that contact with NPCs regulates NSC proliferation and self-renewal through Notch, we co-cultured confluent SVZ NPCs from WT or <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice with NSCs FACS-purified from <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP mice (<xref rid="SD11" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 10</xref>). <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup> NSCs were then FACS-purified from these co-cultures. Notch signaling was downregulated in NSCs co-cultured with <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR NPCs, and cell proliferation and self-renewal were reduced (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3d</xref> and <xref rid="SD11" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 10c</xref>). NICD transduction partially rescued this phenotype (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3d</xref>). In NSCs FACS-purified from Wa2 NPC/WT NSC co-cultures Notch signaling and neurosphere formation were enhanced, as compared to WT NPC/WT NSC in NSCs (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3e</xref> and <xref rid="SD11" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 10f</xref>). These results confirm that EGFR regulates Notch through a non-cell-autonomous mechanism.</p><p id="P11">We determined whether EGFR regulates the Notch pathway and investigated the molecular mechanism. In transfected SVZ cells, <italic>CBF-1</italic> and <italic>Hes1</italic> promoter activity was higher in WT than in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR cells, even after <italic>NICD</italic> co-transfection (<xref rid="SD12" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 11a</xref>). In WT cells, <italic>Hes1</italic> activity was enhanced by <italic>NICD</italic> and reduced after <italic>hEGFR</italic> co-transfection (<xref rid="SD12" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 11b</xref>). <italic>hEGFR</italic> co-transfected with different <italic>Notch</italic> constructs (<xref rid="SD12" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 11c</xref>) reduced <italic>Hes1</italic> activation (<xref rid="SD12" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 11d</xref>), and the EGFR inhibitor PD168393<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> restored <italic>Hes1</italic> activity (<xref rid="SD12" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 11e</xref>). <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR cells plated on WT cells transfected with <italic>Hes1</italic>-luciferase suppressed basal <italic>Hes1</italic> activity; this effect was reversed by PD168393 (<xref rid="SD12" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 11f</xref>). Finally, <italic>Hes1</italic> promoter activity was higher in Wa2 SVZ cells than in WT cells (<xref rid="SD12" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 11g</xref>).</p><p id="P12">We electroporated Notch target constructs (<xref rid="SD13" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 12</xref>) to identify SVZ Notch-responsive cells and to elucidate the mechanism of Notch regulation. <italic>Hes1</italic> activity was observed in NSCs (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a-d</xref> and <xref rid="SD13" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 12m,n</xref>), and was found in a larger percentage of <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup> cells (47.8+/&#8722;3.6 cells/&#956;m3) than in <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup>/<italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR<sup>+</sup> cells (23.6+/&#8722;4.6 cells/&#956;m3, p&lt;0.01). Similar results were observed with <italic>CBFRE</italic>-GFP and <italic>Hes5</italic>-GFP (<xref rid="SD13" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 12a&#8211;l; o&#8211;r</xref>). <italic>Hes1</italic> activity in NSCs of <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP/<italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice was rescued by <italic>NICD</italic> co-electroporation (66.5+/&#8722;71 cells/&#956;m3, p&lt;0.01; n=4). In Wa2 mice, a larger percentage of SVZ NSCs displayed <italic>Hes1</italic> and <italic>CBFRE</italic> activity, compared to WT (<xref rid="SD14" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 13a&#8211;c</xref>, and not shown). shRNA-mediated knockdown of <italic>hEGFR</italic> in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice in vivo caused upregulation of Notch1 and Hes1 (<xref rid="SD14" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 13d,e</xref>). Consistent with these results, Dll-EGFP electroporation revealed a larger percentage of <italic>Dll</italic>-EGFP<sup>+</sup> cells in the SVZ of the WT mouse, compared to <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse (<xref rid="SD15" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 14</xref>). Altogether, our findings demonstrate that EGFR is an upstream regulator of Notch through a non-autonomous cellular mechanism.</p><p id="P13">Numb interacts with E3 ubiquitin ligases to regulate Notch receptor degradation<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>. Changes in Notch signaling levels directly regulate Numb expression<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>. <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4e</xref> shows that <italic>NICD</italic> overexpression reduced Numb in SVZ cells, whereas EGFR overexpression upregulated Numb, and reduced Notch1 and NICD levels. The Notch inhibitor DAPT upregulated Numb (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4f</xref>).</p><p id="P14">We determined the extent of Numb/Notch1 interaction in the SVZ by immunoprecpitation assays. Higher levels of Notch1 associated with Numb in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR samples, compared to WT (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4g1</xref>). Anti-ubiquitin immunoprecipitation followed by anti-Notch1 immunoblotting demonstrated higher levels of Notch ubiquitination in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4g2</xref>). Stereotaxic injection in WT and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice with either Ad-LacZ or <italic>NICD</italic>-LacZ adenovirus showed that both Numb/Notch interaction and Notch1 ubiquitination were reduced after NICD transduction (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4h</xref>).</p><p id="P15">To demonstrate that EGFR signaling promotes Notch ubiquitination via Numb, we performed gain- and loss-of-function experiments in SVZ cultures. After EGFR transfection, we observed increased Numb levels and reduced NICD expression, compared to the mock construct (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4i</xref>). PD168393 reversed this effect (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4i</xref>). EGFR overexpression in WT cells promoted Numb and Notch association and enhanced Notch1 ubiquitination (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4j</xref>). siRNA-mediated EGFR knock down in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR SVZ cultures reduced Numb and Notch1 interaction (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4k1</xref>), and decreased Notch1 ubiquitination (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4k2</xref>).</p><p id="P16">To confirm the role of EGFR and Numb in inhibiting Notch, we analyzed <italic>Hes1</italic> promoter activity by co-transfection in WT SVZ cells with a <italic>Hes1</italic>-luciferase reporter construct, along with <italic>hEGFR</italic> and <italic>Numb</italic> expression vectors. <italic>Hes1</italic> activity was activated only by the <italic>NICD</italic> construct (<xref rid="SD12" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 11h</xref>). However, <italic>Numb</italic> blocked <italic>NICD</italic> and reduced <italic>Hes1</italic> activity (<xref rid="SD12" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 11h</xref>). <italic>Hes1</italic> activity was further reduced by co-transfection with <italic>NICD</italic>, <italic>Numb</italic>, and <italic>hEGFR</italic> (<xref rid="SD12" ref-type="supplementary-material">Sup.Fig. 11h</xref>). Finally, siRNA mediated knockdown of <italic>Numb</italic> in vivo caused upregulation of <italic>Notch1</italic> and <italic>Hes1</italic> activity (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4l&#8211;o</xref>). Scrambled siRNA electroporation in vivo showed that <italic>Hes1</italic> activity was present in a small percentage of GFAP<sup>+</sup> and Nestin<sup>+</sup> NSCs (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4n</xref>; 3.9+/&#8722;0.51 cells/&#956;m3), however after <italic>Numb</italic> knock down <italic>Hes1</italic> activity was present in a larger percentage NSCs (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4o</xref>; 7.1+/&#8722;0.56 cells/&#956;m3, p&lt;0.01; n=4). Together, these results demonstrate that EGFR signaling reduces Notch activation through Numb-dependent Notch1 ubiquitination.</p><p id="P17">Our results point to an interaction between two signaling pathways -EGFR and Notch - that play fundamental and selective roles in the maintenance of NSCs and NPCs in the SVZ niche. This interplay occurs through the direct interaction between NPCs and NSCs, demonstrating the existence of a cellular homeostatic mechanism that involves two specific molecular pathways. Our study also proves that altering particular signaling mechanisms in selective cell types of the SVZ can cause profound changes in the overall cell composition of this neurogenic region of the adult brain. Defining interactions and homeostatic mechanisms that occur between different types of SVZ cells under normal conditions provides crucial information on possible alterations of specific signaling pathways that might occur under pathological conditions or after brain injury.</p><sec id="S1"><title>METHODS SUMMARY</title><p id="P18">Generation/genotyping of <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR, <italic>hGFAP</italic>-GFP and Wa2 mice was performed as described<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>. Wild-type C57/Bl6 and FVB/N mice were used as controls. Histology, immunohistochemistry and EM studies were performed on fresh floating or vibratome sections as described previously<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>. Immunohistochemestry and confocal imaging were used to characterize the SVZ cell composition of the postnatal and adult brain. Image analysis, three-dimensional rendering, and cell counting were done in Photoshop (Adobe) and ImageJ software. NSCs and NPCs were isolated and characterized by FACS sorting using CD15, GFAP, EGFR and NG2 antibodies. Cell proliferation, self-renewal and biochemical analysis were performed from FACS-purified cultured cells and SVZ tissue. To compare SVZ expression profiles of genes involved in NSC development/neurogenesis in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR and WT mice, we performed gene array (SuperArray, Bethesda, MD) expression on spotted cDNA fragments encoding 250 mouse genes. To monitor Notch-signaling pathway in the postnatal SVZ of the CNP- and WT mice, mouse brains were electroporated using the ECM 830 BTX electroporator (Harvard Apparatus, Holliston, MA). Each electroporation result was reproduced in multiple brains derived from at least three separate litters. SVZ NPC cell depletion using Ara-C (2%, Sigma) in vehicle (0.9% saline) or vehicle alone was performed as previously described<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>. EGF (100nm/ul, Upstate) in vehicle (0.9% saline), or vehicle alonewas infused into the LV of adult <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP and WT mice (infusion coordinates: anterioposterior, 0; lateral, 1.1; dorsoventral, 1.5 mm medial to lateral relative to bregma) for 5 days using micro-osmotic pumps (Alzet, model 1007). Brains were then processed for FACS-purification, cell culture or histology. At least 3 different brains for each strain and each experimental condition were analyzed and counted. Cell counting was performed blindly and tissue sections were matched across samples. The analysis of the SVZ was performed at different anterior-posterior and dorso-ventral levels of the lateral ventricle. Statistical analysis was performed by unpaired t-test.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="S2"><title>METHODS</title><sec id="S3"><title>Animals</title><p id="P19">Details on the generation and characterization of <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR transgenic mice have been previously reported<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>. Genotyping of the mice was performed by PCR<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>. Robust hEGFR expression was detected in total brain and spinal cord lysates from adult brain by using monoclonal anti-human EGFR antibody to probe Western blots after immunoprecipitation with a polyclonal anti-EGFR antibody<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>. Consistent with the idea that the CNP promoter drives expression in OLs, hEGFR expression was detected in OL lineage cells of the SVZ, white matter and cerebral cortex in P8-P90 CNP-hEGFR mice, and in NG2<sup>+</sup> progenitor cells of the SVZ<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>. Transgenic mice were backcrossed &gt;4 generations onto C57BL/6. In the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse strain, the <italic>CNP</italic> promoter drives expression in NPCs and in the entire oligodendrocyte lineage; hEGFR expression was detected at both P8 and P90 in NG2<sup>+</sup> progenitors of the SVZ, and in NG2<sup>+</sup> progenitors and oligodendrocytes of the white and gray matter<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>. The mouse strain expressing the <italic>hGFAP</italic>-EGFP (kind gift of F. Kirchhoff, Max Planck Institute of Experimental Medicine, Goettingen, Germany) was previously characterized<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>. The EGFR-mutant mouse (waved-2 mutation; Wa2)<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> was obtained from Jackson Labs (Bar Harbor, ME). All animalprocedures were performed according to the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Children&#8217;s National Medical Center and the National Institutes of Health &#8220;Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals.&#8221;</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Immunohistochemistry and antibodies</title><p id="P20">Freshly cut, floating tissue sections (20&#8211;40&#956;m) from P8 and P90 mice were prepared as previously described<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>. Primary antibody dilutions were: 0.5&#956;g/ml for the specific anti-hEGFR (Biofluids, Caramillo, CA); 1:500 for anti-BrdU (Accurate, Westbury, NY), anti-NG2 antibody (Chemicon, Temecula, CA), monoclonal anti-GFAP (mouse monoclonal, Sigma Aldrich, St. Louis, MO), polyclonal anti-GFAP (rabbit polyclonal, Covance, Berkeley, CA), anti-S100&#946; (DAKO, Denmark; rabbit anti-human clone A5110), and anti-Nestin (Chemicon); 1:50 for anti-LeX (MMA clone, BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA), anti-full length Notch-1, Jagged1, Delta like-1 (Dll) and anti-NICD (from Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank, Iowa, IA).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>BrdU administration</title><p id="P21">The BrdU labeling protocol was performed as previously described<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>. The number of proliferating progenitor cells in the subependyma of the lateral ventricle was determined following short-term (2h), or long-term (30d) retention. Mice were injected intraperitoneally with a single dose of BrdU (50 &#956;g/g body weight) every 3h for five injections and were sacrificed either 1h or 30d after the final injection.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Conventional transmission electron microscopy</title><p id="P22">Wild type and <italic>CNP</italic>-EGFR mice (P8, n=6 for each phenotype; adult, n=4 for each phenotype) were perfused through the heart with a mixture of 3% paraformaldehyde and 1.25% glutaraldehyde in 0.1M phosphate buffer (PB). Brains were removed and postfixed overnight with the same fixative. Brains were sectioned with a vibratome and stored in 0.1M PB. Before postfixation for 1 hour with 1% osmium tetroxide, slices were washed in 0.1M cacodylate buffer pH7.2. After, brain slices were dehydrated through a series of ethanol solutions (50%, 70%, 85%, 95% and 100%), infiltrated with epoxy resins and flat embedded. Sections with the lateral ventricle and the SVZ were trimmed and mounted on blocks and cut with an ultramicrotome. Ultrathin sections (70&#8211;80 nm in thickness) were counterstained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate and analyzed with a TECNAI G2 Spirit Biotwin TEM (FEI, Hillsboro, OR, USA). The images were captured with an AMT XR40 4 megapixel side mounted CCD camera (Danvers, MA, USA) using the electron micrograph montage option. Image processing was performed with Adobe Photoshop using only the brightness and contrast commands. The identification of cell types in the lateral wall of the lateral ventricle and SVZ was performed on electron micrographs following well-described ultrastructural criteria by Doetsch et al. (1997). Cells were false colored and were counted manually.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Microarray and PCR analysis</title><p id="P23">GEArray<sup>&#8482;</sup> expression array systems (cat #OMM-404MM and #OMM-404MM, SuperArray, Bethesda, MD) consisting of spotted cDNA fragments encoding 250 mouse genes involved in NSC development/neurogenesis and in Nocth signaling, as well as control sequences (PUC18, glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH), peptidylpropyl isomerase A (Ppia), and b-actin) were employed to compare gene expression between WT and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR SVZ tissue. Total RNA was isolated with theTrizol method (Invitrogen) and further processed for microarray hybridization according to the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions. The arrays were visualized by autoradiography and hybridization signals were scanned and analyzed for density in GEArray Expression Analysis Suite 2.0. The normalized value for each gene was calculated by dividing the value of each gene by the average value of the housekeeping genes GAPDH, Ppia, and &#946;-actin.</p><p id="P24">For RT-PCR, RNA was isolated from P8 and P90 SVZ tissue or from FACS-purified SVZ cells (WT and <italic>CNP-</italic>hEGFR mice), using Trizol (Invitrogen). RNA (1&#956;g) from each sample was reverse-transcribed using the SuperScript<sup>&#8482;</sup> First-Strand cDNA Synthesis kit (Invitrogen). The mouse gene-specific primers were obtained from Integrated DNA Technologies, Inc. (Coralville, IA). Primer sequences for PCR analysis are found in <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Experimental Procedures</xref>. Genes were amplified by denaturation at 94&#176;C for 1 min, annealing at 60&#176;C for 1 min, and extension at 72&#176;C for 1 min for 28 cycles. PCR products were resolved by 1.2% agarose gel electrophoresis and visualized by ethidium bromide staining.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>In vivo electroporation</title><p id="P25">For gene transfer into postnatal SVZ cells, <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP and <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP/<italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR P2-P3 pups were injected with 1&#8211;2&#956;g of pFLAG-NICD (gift from Dr. Raphael Kopan), shhumanEGFR (GeneCopoeia, Cat #HSH004605-LvH1, access number NM_005228.3; HSHH004605 actcactctccataaatgc; HSH004605-2 cgtcagcctgaacataaca; HSH004605-3 gaccagacaactgtatcca; HSH004605-4 ccgtcgctatcaaggaatt), <italic>CAG</italic>-GFP and <italic>Hes1</italic>-dsRED and <italic>Hes1</italic>-GFP (gift from Dr. Cepko L. Constance)<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> CBFRE-EGFP (gift from Dr. Nicholas Gaiano)<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <italic>Dll</italic>-GFP (gift from Richard Grosschedl)<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> and <italic>Hes5</italic>-GFP (gift from R. Kageyama)<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> DNA into the LV, followed by electroporation (100V/50ms, five times at 950ms intervals; the angle of the paddles was adjusted to 20&#8211;40 degrees) using an ECM 830 BTX electroporator (Harvard Apparatus, Holliston, MA).</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>In vivo viral labeling</title><p id="P26">SVZ cells were infected using a Notch Intracellular domain (Ad-NICD) or control (Ad-LacZ) construct Adenovirus (gift of Dr. Igor Prudovsky) by direct injection into the LV. Adenovirus production and titer determination were previously described<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>. P90 WT and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice were injected with the Adenovirus stock (2&#956;l; titer of 2&#8211;4 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/ml). Injections were performed stereotaxically at the following coordinates (anterioposterior relative to bregma, mediolateral, and dorsoventral from surface of the brain) for epl-SVZ (0, 1.8, 3.0mm). Brains were processed for histology at 2, 7, 14 and 28 days after infection, and sections were immunostained for NICD, GFAP, S100b, NG2 and BrdU antibodies.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>FACS sorting and cell culture</title><p id="P27">FACS-purification of LeX<sup>+</sup>NG2<sup>&#8722;</sup>/EGFP<sup>neg</sup> (NSCs) in the <italic>CNP</italic>-EGFP mouse or GFAP-GFP<sup>+</sup>LeX<sup>+</sup>NG2<sup>neg</sup> (NSCs) in the <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP mouse has been previously described<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>. Tissue from P8 <italic>CNP-</italic>hEGFR, <italic>CNP</italic>-EGFP/<italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR, <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP or <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR/<italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP mice was dissociated into single cell suspensions, followed by immunostaining for NG2 and LeX (MMA clone)<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>. SVZ neural stem cells and NPCs (after EGF or saline infusion, or 5&#8211;7days after focal demyelination of the corpus callosum) were FACS-purified using anti-LeX antibodies to purified LeX<sup>+/</sup><italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup> (NSCs) or <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>neg</sup>LeX<sup>+</sup> (NPCs) cells from the <italic>hGFAP</italic>-GFP mouse. Tissue was dissociated into single cell suspensions, followed by immunostaining for NG2 and LeX (MMA clone)<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>. To FACS-purify NSCs, antibodies were used in combination with appropriate R-PE- and PE-Cy5.5-conjugated secondary antibodies (Caltag, Burlingame, CA). Cell suspensions were analyzed for light forward and side scatter using a FACSAria instrument (BD, Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ).</p><p id="P28">Cultures of FACS-purified cells have been previously described<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>. FACS-purified NSCs were seeded at a density of 10 viable cells/&#956;l on uncoated 24-well plates (BD Falcon, Franklin Lakes, NJ), and grown in SCM for 6 days in vitro (DIV) with daily addition of 20ng/ml EGF and 10ng/ml bFGF (Upstate, Charlottesville, VA)<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>. Primary neurosphere colonies were subcloned to assay NSC self-renewal by mechanical dissociation and replated at a density of 10cells/&#956;l on uncoated 24-well plates. It is important to note that in <xref rid="SD7" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6</xref> neurosphere analysis was performed starting with the 2<sup>nd</sup> passage. This was done to overcome the experimental limitations due to low number of cells recovered after FACS.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>SVZ micro-dissection</title><p id="P29">SVZ areas were micro-dissected from 300&#956;m-thick brain coronal sections. Single cell were dissociated<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> on coated coverslips in 24-well plates (BDFalcon, Franklin Lakes, NJ). Coverslips were processed for immunocytochemistry 2h after plating.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Western blots and immunoprecipitation</title><p id="P30">SVZ tissue (WT and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice) was micro-dissected from 300&#956;m-thick coronal sections of P8 and P90 brains, and used for protein extraction using lysis buffer (50mM Tris-HCl, pH7.5, 1mM EDTA, 1mM EGTA, 1mM sodium orthovanadate, 50 mM sodium fluoride, 0.1% 2-mercaptoethanol, 1% triton X-100, plus proteases inhibitor cocktail; SIGMA). Protein samples (20&#956;g) were separated on GENE Mate express Gels 420% (ISC BioExpress, Kaysville, UT) and transferred to PVDF membranes (Millipore, Bedford MA). Numb, Notch1, NICD, Dll1, Hes1, RBPjk, ubiquitin, and actin proteins, were detected using an enhanced chemiluminescence substrate mixture (ECL Plus, Amersham, Buckinghamshire, UK). Selective primary antibodies from Santa Cruz Biotechnologies (Caramillo CA) were used at 1&#956;g/ml. Antibodies were used in combination with a secondary horseradish peroxidase-conjugate (Santa Cruz Biotechnologies).</p><p id="P31">For immunoprecipitation, SVZ tissue extracts from WT and CNP-hEGFR mice were prepared in RIPA buffer containing. Aliquots (200&#956;g protein) were incubated overnight with antibodies against ubiquitin (Santa Cruz Biotechnology), Numb or Notch1 and 15&#956;l of Agarose A (Santa Cruz Biotechnology). Immunocomplexes bound to agarose A were collected by centrifugation and washed twice in 500&#956;l RIPA buffer containing inhibitors. Precipitated proteins were analyzed by immunoblotting. Bands were detected using HRP and developed with a chemiluminescent substrate (ECL, Amersham).</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Ara-C and EGF infusion</title><p id="P32">Ara-C (2%, Sigma) in vehicle (0.9% saline) or vehicle alonewere infused onto the surface of the brain of adult mice (coordinates: anterioposterior, 0, lateral, 1.1, dorsoventral, 1.5mm medial to lateral relative to bregma) for 6 days with micro-osmotic pumps (Alzet, model 1007) as previously described by Doetsch et al. (1999). EGF (100nm/ul, Upstate) in vehicle (0.9% saline), or vehicle alone was infused into the LV in adult <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP and WT mice (infusion coordinates: anterioposterior, 0; lateral, 1.1; dorsoventral, 1.5 mm medial to lateral relative to bregma) for 5 days using micro-osmotic pumps (Alzet, model 1007). Mice were then processed for FACS-purification, cell culture or histology.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Plasmids, siRNAs, cell transfection and luciferase assays</title><p id="P33">SVZ tissue was dissected from 300&#956;m-thick brain sections prepared from P8 WT and <italic>CNP-</italic>hEGFR brains and processed for cell culture<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>. After SVZ dissection and single cell dissociation, cells were plated in 12-well cell culture dishes at a density of 50 cells/&#956;l for 24 hours. At the time of transfection, cell cultures were approximately 60% confluent. Cell transfections were performed using the NeuroPORTER Transfection reagent (Genlantis, San Diego, CA) following manufacturer&#8217;s instructions. The cell permeable, irreversible EGFR blocker (PD168393, Calbiochem, La Jolla, CA), was used 24hrs after cell transfection. Cells were pre-incubated with PD168393 (PD) for 4hrs at 37&#176;C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and then medium was changed to fresh SCM.</p><p id="P34">A commercially available siRNA directed toward the hEGFR was purchased from Dharmacon (SMARTpool Cat. No. L-003114-00, Locus NM_201283; sequence J-003114-10, CAAAGUGUGUAACGGAAUA; J-003114-11, CCAUAAAUGCUACGAAUAU, J-003114-12, GUAACAAGCUCACGCAGUU, J-003114-13, CAGAGGAUGUUCAAUAACU. and siRNA directed toward the mNumb (Santa Cruz Biotechnologies Inc. Cat. No. sc-42147; Locus NM_010949, 110 GUAGCUUCCCAGUUAAGUAtt, 412 CGAUGGAUCUGUCAUUGUUtt, 884 CCCUACGCAUCAAUGAGUUtt). siRNA transfection produced selective knockdown of the hEGFR and mNumb. Briefly, 2&#956;l of 20pM of siRNA solution and 12&#956;l of the transfection reagent were incubated in 100&#956;l of SCM for 20 minutes, in order to facilitate complex formation. The siRNA transfection mix was added to the SVZ cells cultured in 2.5% FBS. Controls consisted of non-specific siRNA. SVZ cells were transfected for 7 hours at 37&#176;C, washed with Hanks&#8217; buffer and cultured in SCM 2.5% FBS for an additional 24 hours. The medium was then changed to basal SCM (20 ng/ml EGF and 10 ng/ml FGF). After 24 or 48 hours, cells were collected and processed for RNA or protein extraction.</p><p id="P35">Transient transfections and Luciferase assays were performed in 60% confluent SVZ cell cultures (<italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR and WT) using NeuroPORTER as described above, and 1.5&#956;g of PGL3 basic, wt phEGFR (Millipore), pCBF1-Luciferase reporter plasmid (gift of Dr. Gabriel Corfas, Harvard Medical School) or <italic>Hes1</italic> Luciferase reporter plasmid, and Dll expression plasmid (gift of Dr. Alanis Israel, Unite de Biologie Moleculaire de l&#8217;Expression Genique, Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique) reporter plasmids and 0.3&#956;g of expression vectors. Notch expression vectors used were a kind gift of Dr. Raphael Kopan (Department of Molecular Biology and Pharmacology, Washington University). Luciferase assays were performed 48hr after transfection using the Dual Assay Luciferase kit (Promega). Cotransfected TK&#8211;renilla Luciferase was used to normalize samples for transfection efficiency and for sample handling. Cells were lysed, and luciferase activity was measured following the protocol recommended by the manufacturer.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Neural progenitor-neural stem cell co-cultures</title><p id="P36">NPCs were acutely dissociated from P8 <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR and WT SVZ mice and then processed for purification using anti-prominin-1 microbeads antibodies (Miltenyi Biotec, Auburn CA) following manufacturer recommendations. Purified NPCs were cultured at high density in a monolayer in the presence of EGF and bFGF, as described above. After 48 hrs, FACS-purified WT <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup>LeX<sup>+</sup> cells were plated on top of NPCs for 5 days in EGF- and bFGF-containing medium. Finally, <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup> cells were purified from the co-culture by FACS and assayed in neurosphere cultures to determine proliferation and self-renewal. FACS-purified <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup> cells were seeded at a density of 5 viable cells/&#956;l on uncoated 12mm-well plates (BDFalcon, Franklin Lakes, NJ), and maintained in SCM for 6DIV with daily addition of EGF and bFGF. Primary neurosphere colonies were subcloned by mechanical dissociation in SCM with EGF and bFGF. Cells were re-plated at a density of 5 cells/&#956;l on uncoated 24-well plates. Stem cell self-renewal was assessed after further 6 DIV.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Microscopy and cell counting</title><p id="P37">A Bio-Rad MRC 1024 confocal laser-scanning microscope (Hercules, CA) equipped with a krypton-argon laser and an Olympus IX-70 inverted microscope (Melville, NY) was used to image localization of FITC (488nm laser line excitation; 522/35 emission filter), texas red (568nm excitation; 605/32 emission filter) of Cy5 (647 excitation; 680/32 emission filter). Optical sections (Z=0.5&#956;m) of confocal epifluorescence images were acquire sequentially using a 40x oil objective (Number or aperture, NA=1.35), or a 60x oil objective (NA=1.40) with Bio-Rad <italic>LaserSharp</italic> v3.2 software. <italic>ImageJ NIH,</italic> software was subsequently used to merge images. Merge images were processed in Photoshop 7.0 with minimal manipulations of contrast. For cell counting, cells were counted in the SVZ the postnatal day 8 (P8) and adult mice P90. At least 3 different brains for each strain and each experimental condition were analyzed and counted. Cell counting was performed blindly and tissue sections were matched across samples. The analysis of the SVZ was performed at different anterior-posterior and dorso-ventral levels of the lateral ventricle. An average of 15&#8211;20 sections was quantifiedusing unbiased stereological morphometric analysis for the SVZ to obtain an estimate of the total number of positive cells. Then, percentages of cells expressing different antigens were estimated by scoring the number of cells double-labeled with the marker in question. In acute SVZ dissociated cells, 3 coverslips and 8&#8211;10 microscopic fields/coverslip were counted from 3 separate cultures. Statistical analysis was performed by unpaired t-test.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S17"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>1</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS221823-supplement-1.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1469" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>10</label><caption><title>Supplementary Figure 9. Depletion of NPCs increases NSCs in the adult SVZ niche</title><p id="P46">Timeline represents the duration of AraC or NaCl treatment (5 days), time of BrdU pulse (arrowhead), and perfusion (arrow). (a&#8211;d) Immunohistochemistry with anti-S100b, anti-GFAP, and anti-BrdU antibodies after NaCl or AraC infusion. (a and b) After NaCl infusion, a higher number of BrdU<sup>+</sup> cells were found in the SVZ of <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice; however, the number of GFAP<sup>+</sup> cells was reduced compared with WT. (c and d) In <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice, depletion of SVZ NPCs with AraC results in increased numbers of GFAP<sup>+</sup> cells compared with NaCl. Dotted lines delimit SVZ boundaries. Scale bar = 50&#956;m.</p></caption><media xlink:href="NIHMS221823-supplement-10.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1493" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><label>11</label><caption><title>Supplementary Figure 10. Cell-to-cell contact between NPCs and NSCs of the SVZ regulates Notch signaling</title><p id="P47">Co-culture experiments utilizing SVZ cells of WT (a and d), <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR (b) and Wa2 (e) mice (P8). Representative images of co-cultures after 5 DIV. FACS-purified WT <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup> NSCs (green) were cultured on top of WT, <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR or Wa2 NPCs (bright field) for 5 days in vitro. FACS-recovered <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup> NSCs were then used to purify total RNA and for neurosphere assays. (c and f) Representative agarose gels of semi-quantitative RT-PCR reactions show that the mRNA levels of <italic>Notch1, RBPjk</italic> and <italic>Hes1</italic> are downregulated in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR co-cultures, as compared with WT co-cultures. Conversely, mRNA levels of <italic>Notch1, RBPjk</italic> and <italic>Hes1</italic> are upregulated in Wa2 co-cultures. Scale bar = 50&#956;m.</p></caption><media xlink:href="NIHMS221823-supplement-11.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1536" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD4"><label>12</label><caption><title>Supplementary Figure 11. EGFR signaling is upstream of the Notch pathway in SVZ cells</title><p id="P48">(a) Reduced <italic>CBF-1</italic> promoter activity in SVZ <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR neural progenitors compared with WT. The constitutive form of activated Notch1 (ME-FNIC) maximally stimulates the <italic>CBF-1</italic> promoter in WT SVZ cells, but its effect is significantly less pronounced in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR cells (*p&lt;0.05). Data shown are means (n=4) &#177; SEM. (b) <italic>Hes1</italic> promoter activity with different expression constructs in WT SVZ cells. The <italic>EGFR</italic> and <italic>Numb</italic> constructs do not activate <italic>Hes1</italic>, but significantly reduce its basal expression levels (*p&lt;0.05). Data shown are means (n=4) &#177; SEM. (c) Diagram of <italic>Notch1</italic> expression constructs tested in WT SVZ cells. (d) Co-transfection of EGFR is sufficient to inhibit Notch1-induced <italic>Hes1</italic> promoter activity (*p&lt;0.01). (e) Incubation with the EGFR inhibitor PD168393 (PD) prevents the inhibitory effects of EGFR on Notch1-induced <italic>Hes1</italic> promoter activity (*p&lt;0.01). (f) At 24hr after transfection incubation with <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR NPCs prevents <italic>Hes1</italic> promoter activity, and incubation with PD168393 prevents this inhibition (**p&lt;0.01; *p&lt;0.03). Data shown are means (n=4) &#177; SEM. (g) <italic>Hes1</italic> promoter activity in SVZ Wa2 neural progenitors is higher compared with WT. Co-transfection with the <italic>Notch</italic> construct (EFL6MT) maximally stimulates the <italic>Hes1</italic> promoter in Wa2 SVZ cells, but its effect is significantly less pronounced in WT. Co-transfection of <italic>EGFR</italic> is sufficient to inhibit Notch1-induced <italic>Hes1</italic> promoter activity (*p&lt;0.05). Data shown are means (n=4) &#177; SEM. (h) WT SVZ cells were cotransfected with the <italic>Hes1</italic> Luciferase reporter and ME-FNIC, EGFR, and Numb expression vectors. Numb is sufficient to inhibit Notch1-induced <italic>Hes1</italic> promoter activity (*p&lt;0.01). Data shown are means (n=3) &#177; SEM. A slightly higher inhibition of Notch1-induced <italic>Hes1</italic> promoter activity was observed with <italic>Numb</italic> and <italic>EGFR</italic> coexpression. Data shown are means (n=3) &#177; SEM (**p&lt;0.05)</p></caption><media xlink:href="NIHMS221823-supplement-12.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1617" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD5"><label>13</label><caption><title>Supplementary Figure 12. Enhanced EGFR expression reduces Notch1 signaling in the SVZ</title><p id="P49">(a&#8211;l) Enhanced EGFR expression reduces Notch signaling activity in NSCs in vivo. Co-electroporation of the <italic>CBFRE</italic>-EGFP (a&#8211;f) <italic>and Hes5-</italic>GFP (g&#8211;l) and NICD constructs in the LV of P3 <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP and <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP/<italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice. At 72hrs after electroporation, a higher number of <italic>CBFRE-</italic>EGFP<sup>+</sup> cells were observed in the WT mouse (a), compared with the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse (b). Co-electroporation of the NICD construct increases the number of <italic>CBFRE</italic>-EGFP<sup>+</sup> cells both in the <italic>WT</italic> and the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse. However, NICD caused a larger increase in cell number in WT mouse compared with <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse (b, d and e). Note that electroporation efficiency was similar in WT and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice, as demonstrated by co-electroporation with <italic>CBFRE</italic>-GFP and <italic>CAG</italic>-dsRED plasmid constructs (f). At 72hrs after electroporation, a higher number of <italic>Hes5-</italic>GFP<sup>+</sup> cells were observed in the WT mouse (g and k), compared with the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse (h and k). Co-electroporation of the NICD construct increases the number of <italic>Hes5-</italic>GFP<sup>+</sup> cells both in the WT and in the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse (i-k). Note that electroporation efficiency was similar in the WT and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice, as demonstrated by co-electroporation with <italic>Hes5</italic>-GFP and <italic>CAG</italic>-dsRED plasmid constructs (l). (m&#8211;r) Hes1<sup>+</sup><italic>,</italic> CBFRE<sup>+</sup> and Hes5<sup>+</sup> cells were GFAP<sup>+</sup> and Nestin<sup>+</sup> NSCs. Scale bar = 50&#956;m.</p></caption><media xlink:href="NIHMS221823-supplement-13.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1723" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD6"><label>14</label><caption><title>Supplementary Figure 13. Downregulation of EGFR signaling activates the Notch pathway in the SVZ</title><p id="P50">(a&#8211;c) Co-electroporation of the <italic>Hes1-</italic>dsRED and <italic>CAG</italic>-GFP constructs in the LV of P3 WT and Wa2 mice. At 72hrs after electroporation, a higher number of <italic>Hes1</italic>-dsRED<sup>+</sup><italic>CAG</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup> cells were found in the Wa<italic>2</italic> mouse (b), compared with the WT mouse (a). (d,e) shRNA knockdown of hEGFR in the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse enhances Notch signaling in GFAP<sup>+</sup> NSCs in the SVZ. Total RNA (e1) and proteins (e2) were isolated from the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR SVZ 72hrs after mock or shRNA hEGFR electroporation in the SVZ of P3 mice. Representative agarose gel of semi-quantitative RT-PCR shows that mRNAs of <italic>Notch1 and Hes1</italic> are upregulated after shRNA-mediated hEGFR knockdown compared with mock. Western blot analysis reveals that Notch1 and Hes1 are upregulated, after shRNA hEGFR knockdown, compared with mock. Scale bars = 50&#956;m.</p></caption><media xlink:href="NIHMS221823-supplement-14.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1765" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD7"><label>15</label><caption><title>Supplementary Figure 14. Dll expression is regulared by EGFR signaling in the SVZ</title><p id="P51">Co-electroporation of the <italic>Dll-</italic>EGFP and <italic>CAG</italic>-dsRed constructs in the LV of P3 WT (a) and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR (b) mice. (c) At 72hrs after electroporation, a higher number of <italic>Dll</italic>-EGFP<sup>+</sup> cells were found in the WT mouse, compared with the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse. Scale bar = 50&#956;m. *p&lt;0.02)</p></caption><media xlink:href="NIHMS221823-supplement-15.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1793" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD8"><label>2</label><caption><title>Supplementary Figure 1. Reduced number of neural stem cells and increased number of NG2+ cells in the SVZ of the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse</title><p id="P38">Immunostaining of adult SVZ in WT (a,c) and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR (b,d) mice with anti-EGFR, anti-GFAP and anti-NG2 antibodies. Dotted lines delimit SVZ boundaries. SVZ= Subventricular zone, LV=Lateral ventricle, Str=striatum. Scale bar = 50&#956;m.</p></caption><media xlink:href="NIHMS221823-supplement-2.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1808" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD9"><label>3</label><caption><title>Supplementary Figure 2. Reduced number of neural stem cells in the entire SVZ of the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse</title><p id="P39">Representative confocal images taken at different anterior/posterior (rostral/caudal) levels and dorso/ventral levels of the P90 SVZ niche in WT (a,c and e) and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR (b, d and f) mice. NSCs were characterized by immunohistochemistry with anti-GFAP, anti-Nestin, and anti-S100b antibodies. A reduction of GFAP<sup>+</sup>Nestin<sup>+</sup> (NSCs) number and morphological changes were observed in the entire adult SVZ of the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse. Cell numbers and percentages are shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1e and f</xref>, and in the main text. Images were taken at different anterior/posterior and dorso/vertral levels. Stereotaxic coordinates are illustrated in the panels on the right. Dotted lines represent the level at which the images were taken. Images were acquired using Bio-Rad MRC 1024 confocal laser-scanning microscope equipped with a krypton-argon laser and an Olympus IX-70 inverted microscope using a 40x (Number or aperture, NA=1.35). Images were taken from P90 SVZ optical sections (Z=0.5&#956;m) of 20&#956;m-thick brain sections. Organization of the SVZ niche was consistently different in the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse, as compared with WT. Three brains were analyzed from 3 distinct <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse breeding cages (total brains = 9) and representative images are shown.</p></caption><media xlink:href="NIHMS221823-supplement-3.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1842" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD10"><label>4</label><caption><title>Supplementary Figure 3. Electron microscopic analysis confirms reduced number of NSCs in the postnatal and adult SVZ of the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse</title><p id="P40">Ultrastructural analysis of the SVZ niche from P8 (a, b) and P90 (c, d) WT (a, c) and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR (b, d) mice. A significant reduction in type B cells is observed throughout the entire SVZ of <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice compared to WT at both P8 and P90. In <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice, fewer type B cells are seen in contact with the subependymal layer of the SVZ, but more type A cells are observed at both P8 and P90. Scale bar (panel d) = 5&#956;m (a and b) and 10&#956;m (c and d). (e) Percentage of total cell nuclei counted in the lateral wall of the lateral ventricle. Different SVZ cell populations are identified by distinct colors. Cells were analyzed and classified as previously described by Doetsch et al., 1997. Total numbers of cells counted were 231 (WT) and 248 (<italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR) at P8, and 103 (WT) and 105 (<italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR) at P90. n=3 for each mouse strain (*p&lt;0.05).</p></caption><media xlink:href="NIHMS221823-supplement-4.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1869" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD11"><label>5</label><caption><title>Supplementary Figure 4. FACS-purification of SVZ NSCs of WT and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice</title><p id="P41">(a) Typical FACS sorting profile for Lex<sup>+</sup> cells (NSCs) from <italic>CNP</italic>-EGFP (a1) and <italic>CNP</italic>-EGFP/<italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR (a2) mice. LeX antigen (CD15 antibody) was scattered with R-phycoerythrin, R-PE. (b) Typical FACS sorting for Lex<sup>+</sup>GFP<sup>+</sup> cells (NSCs) from <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP (b1) and <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP/<italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR (b2) mice. LeX (CD15; MMA clone) antigen was scattered with R-phycoerythrin, R-PE. Events scored = 50,000.</p></caption><media xlink:href="NIHMS221823-supplement-5.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1910" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD12"><label>6</label><caption><title>Supplementary Figure 5. Reduced proliferation and self-renewal of SVZ GFAP-expressing NSCs in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice</title><p id="P42">(a,b) Confocal images of <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP (a) and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR/<italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP (b) mouse SVZ at P8 after immunostaining with anti-GFAP antibodies raised in rabbit (a2 and b2). LV = lateral ventricle. Subependymal layer of the SVZ = SEL. Dotted lines delimit the ependymal layer of the SVZ. (c,d) Reduced proliferation and self-renewal of NSCs from <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice was confirmed by directed FACS sorting of <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup>LeX<sup>+</sup> NSCs. Representative neurosphere culture from <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP (c1) and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR/<italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP (c2) mice after 7DIV shows a reduction in neurosphere number and size. (d) Histograms show neurosphere numbers (d1) and size (d2) calculated from three independent experiments; (*p&lt;0.01). Data are shown as averages &#177; SEM. Scale bars 500&#956;m (a and e) and 50&#956;m (c and d).</p></caption><media xlink:href="NIHMS221823-supplement-6.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1953" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD13"><label>7</label><caption><title>Supplementary Figure 6</title><p id="P43">In the SVZ, Notch1 is expressed in NSCs, and Notch ligands are expressed in NPCs and neuroblasts. Confocal images of <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP (a), <italic>GAD</italic>-GFP (c,d) and <italic>CNP</italic>-EGFP (e,f) mice SVZ at P40 after immunostaining with anti-Notch1 (a), with anti-Notch intracellular domain (NICD, b), anti-Jagged1 (c and e) and anti-Dll (d and f) antibodies. Notch 1 is expressed in GFAP<sup>+</sup> NSCs, and Notch ligands are expressed in <italic>CNP</italic>-EGFP<sup>+</sup> NPCs and Dcx+ neuroblasts of the adult SVZ. (g&#8211;m) Co-electroporation of <italic>Dll-</italic>EGFP and <italic>CAG-</italic>dsRED, or <italic>Hes1</italic>-dsRED and <italic>CAG-</italic>dsRED in the LV of P3 WT and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice confirmed that Notch ligands are expressed in NPCs and Notch in NSCs. <italic>Dll-</italic>EGFP<sup>+</sup> cells displayed NPC (EGFR<sup>+</sup> and NG2<sup>+</sup>; g and h) and neuroblast (Doublecortin, Dcx<sup>+</sup> cells; i) phenotypes, and were almost absent within the NSC population (GFAP<sup>+</sup>; j). The majority of <italic>Hes1</italic>-dsRED+ cells in the SVZ are NSCs (<italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup>GFAP<sup>+</sup> cells; k&#8211;m). Scale bar = 50&#956;m.</p></caption><media xlink:href="NIHMS221823-supplement-7.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e2028" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD14"><label>8</label><caption><title>Supplementary Figure 7. EGF infusion expands the pool of NPCs, and reduces NSC proliferation and self-renewal in the SVZ of WT mice</title><p id="P44">EGF was infused directly into the LV of P90 mouse brains for 5 days. (a&#8211;d) Immunohistochemistry with anti-EGFR (a,b), anti-GFAP (c,d) and anti-BrdU (c,d) antibodies after EGF infusion. After EGF infusion (b and d), a higher number of BrdU<sup>+</sup> and EGFR<sup>+</sup> cells were found in the SVZ of EGF-infused brains, as compared with BSA-infused (a and c). (e) Western blot analysis shows that Notch1, NICD, RBPjk and Hes1 are downregulated, whereas Numb is upregulated after EGF infusion, as compared with BSA infusion. (f,g) EGF or BSA were infused into the LV of the <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP mouse brain (P90) for 5 days, and SVZ tissue was dissected out for single cell dissociation and FACS purification of NSCs, as performed in <xref rid="SD5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 4b</xref>. Proliferation and self-renewal of NSCs are reduced after EGF infusion, as compared with BSA-infused brain (*p&lt;0.001). Data shown are means (n=3) &#177; SEM. Scale bar = 50&#956;m.</p></caption><media xlink:href="NIHMS221823-supplement-8.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e2049" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD15"><label>9</label><caption><title>Supplementary Figure 8. Overexpression of the constitutive active form of Notch1 (NICD) rescues proliferation and self-renewal GFAP-expressing NSCs in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice</title><p id="P45">(a,b) SVZ cells from P8 WT and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice were cultured and transfected with a control mock vector (Mock) or an NICD construct. (a1) Semi-quantitative RT-PCR shows an increase in <italic>Hes1</italic> mRNA levels in cells derived from <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice after <italic>NICD</italic> transfection, compared with mock construct. No increase was observed in WT cells. (a2) Total <italic>Hes1</italic> mRNA measured in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR cells after transfection with mock and NICD constructs. A significant 50% increase (a3) is observed only in <italic>NICD</italic>-transfected <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR cells. Data are shown as averages (n=3) &#177; SEM (*p&lt;0.05). (b) Proliferation and self-renewal of NSCs of <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice are rescued after <italic>NICD</italic> overexpression. (b1) Images of neurospheres transfected with mock or <italic>NICD</italic> constructs. (b2,b3) Neurosphere number and size in WT and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR cells show an increase only in <italic>NICD</italic>-transfected <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR cells. Data are shown as averages (n=3) &#177; SEM (*p&lt;0.01).</p></caption><media xlink:href="NIHMS221823-supplement-9.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e2105" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S19"><p>We thank Dr. Nancy Ratner (Cincinnati Children&#8217;s Hospital Research Foundation, Cincinnati, OH) for the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice. We are particularly thankful to Teresa Hawley (George Washington University) for technical advice in all FACS sorting experiments. We are grateful to Drs. Josh Corbin and Tarik Haydar for critically reading this manuscript, and to all our colleagues at the Center for Neuroscience Research for discussion and support. We are particularly thankful to Dr. Nicholas Gaiano for discussion, for providing reagents and for his continuous and generous advice on this project. We thank Drs. Gabriel Corfas (Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA), Alanis Israel (Unite de Biologie Moleculaire de l&#8217;Expression Genique, Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, Paris, France), Constance L. Cepko (Department of Genetics, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts), Raphael Kopan (Department of Molecular Biology and Pharmacology, Washington University, St. Louis), Richard Grosschedl (Max Planck Institute of Immunobiology, Department of Cellular and Molecular Immunology, Freiburg, Germany), Nicholas Gaiano (Institute for Cell Engineering, Department of Neurology, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD), and Ryoichiro Kageyama (Institute for Virus Research, Kyoto University, Kyoto, Japan) for the gift of CBF-1, <italic>Hes1</italic>-GFP, <italic>Hes1</italic>-dsRED, Notch constructs, <italic>Dll</italic>-GFP, <italic>CBFRE</italic>-EGFP and <italic>Hes5</italic>-GFP respectively. This work was supported by NIH R01NS045702 and R01NS056427 (V.G.), K99NS057944 (A.A.), ROO NS057944-03 (A.A.) and by NIH IDDRC P30HD40677 (V.G.). Electron microscopy was performed at the University of Connecticut, Department of Physiology and Neurobiology, with funding from NIH R01DC006881 to M.E.R., and from NSF DBI-0420580 for funds to purchase the Tecnai 12 Biotwin electron microscope.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN3" fn-type="con"><p><bold>Author contributions</bold></p><p>A.A. performed all the experiments. M.E.R. performed the E.M. studies. A.A and V.G. designed all experiments. V.G. supervised the entire project. A.A and V.G. wrote the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mercier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitasako</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatton</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anatomy of the brain neurogenic zones revisited: fractones and the fibroblast/macrophage network</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><volume>451</volume><fpage>170</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><year>2002</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12209835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarez-Buylla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>For the long run: maintaining germinal niches in the adult brain</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>686</lpage><year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15003168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doetsch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Caille</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Verdugo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez-Buylla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subventricular zone astrocytes are neural stem cells in the adult mammalian brain</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>97</volume><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>716</lpage><year>1999</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10380923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Willhoite</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gage</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vascular niche for adult hippocampal neurogenesis</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><volume>425</volume><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><year>2000</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10975875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Temple</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The development of neural stem cells</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>414</volume><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><year>2001</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11689956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sundaram</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The love-hate relationship between Ras and Notch</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>1825</fpage><lpage>1839</lpage><year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16103211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Moses</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The EGF receptor and notch signaling pathways control the initiation of the morphogenetic furrow during Drosophila eye development</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>128</volume><fpage>2689</fpage><lpage>2697</lpage><year>2001</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11526075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bais</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenwald</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crosstalk between the EGFR and LIN-12/Notch pathways in C. elegans vulval development</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>303</volume><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>666</lpage><year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14752159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hasson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EGFR signaling attenuates Groucho-dependent repression to antagonize Notch transcriptional output</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><volume>237</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15592470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hitoshi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Notch pathway molecules are essential for the maintenance, but not the generation, of mammalian neural stem cells</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>846</fpage><lpage>858</lpage><year>2002</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11937492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alexson</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Hitoshi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Kooy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Notch signaling is required to maintain all neural stem cell populations-irrespective of spatial or temporal niche</article-title><source>Dev Neurosci</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16508302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lillien</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Raphael</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BMP and FGF regulate the development of EGF-responsive neural progenitor cells</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>127</volume><fpage>4993</fpage><lpage>5005</lpage><year>2000</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11044412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breunig</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Silbereis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaccarino</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sestan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rakic</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Notch regulates cell fate and dendrite morphology of newborn neurons in the postnatal dentate gyrus</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>104</volume><fpage>20558</fpage><lpage>20563</lpage><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18077357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dupree</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A functional role for EGFR signaling in myelination and remyelination</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>990</fpage><lpage>1002</lpage><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17618276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rizvi</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of the epidermal growth factor receptor confers migratory properties to nonmigratory postnatal neural progenitors</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>11092</fpage><lpage>11106</lpage><year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16319309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Type-2 cells as link between glial and neuronal lineage in adult hippocampal neurogenesis</article-title><source>Glia</source><volume>54</volume><fpage>805</fpage><lpage>814</lpage><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16958090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doetsch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Verdugo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez-Buylla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cellular composition and three-dimensional organization of the subventricular germinal zone in the adult mammalian brain</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>5046</fpage><lpage>5061</lpage><year>1997</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9185542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Capela</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Temple</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lex/ssea-1 is expressed by adult mouse CNS stem cells, identifying them as non-ependymal</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>865</fpage><lpage>875</lpage><year>2002</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12372282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postnatal neurogenesis and gliogenesis in the olfactory bulb from NG2-expressing progenitors of the subventricular zone</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>10530</fpage><lpage>10541</lpage><year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15548668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jablonska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cdk2 is critical for proliferation and self-renewal of neural progenitor cells in the adult subventricular zone</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><volume>179</volume><fpage>1231</fpage><lpage>1245</lpage><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18086919</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaiano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nye</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fishell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radial glial identity is promoted by Notch1 signaling in the murine forebrain</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><year>2000</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10839358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizutani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokunaga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaiano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential Notch signalling distinguishes neural stem cells from intermediate progenitors</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>449</volume><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17721509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Noggin antagonizes BMP signaling to create a niche for adult neurogenesis</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>726</lpage><year>2000</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11163261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colak</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adult neurogenesis requires Smad4-mediated bone morphogenic protein signaling in stem cells</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>434</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18184786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaspar</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gage</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sonic hedgehog regulates adult neural progenitor proliferation in vitro and in vivo</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><year>2003</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12469128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohyama</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Visualization of spatiotemporal activation of Notch signaling: live monitoring and significance in neural development</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><volume>286</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>325</lpage><year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16153632</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced EGFR signaling in progenitor cells of the adult subventricular zone attenuates oligodendrogenesis after demyelination</article-title><source>Neuron Glia Biol</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18634612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGill</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>McGlade</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mammalian numb proteins promote Notch1 receptor ubiquitination and degradation of the Notch1 intracellular domain</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>278</volume><fpage>23196</fpage><lpage>23203</lpage><year>2003</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12682059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahlgren</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahlqvist</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lendahl</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>High levels of Notch signaling down-regulate Numb and Numblike</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><volume>175</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17116748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Role for the epidermal growth factor receptor in neurofibromatosis-related peripheral nerve tumorigenesis</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15652750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wehner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bone marrow-derived cells expressing green fluorescent protein under the control of the glial fibrillary acidic protein promoter do not differentiate into astrocytes in vitro and in vivo</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>5004</fpage><lpage>5011</lpage><year>2003</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12832523</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luetteke</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The mouse waved-2 phenotype results from a point mutation in the EGF receptor tyrosine kinase</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>413</lpage><year>1994</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8125255</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morshead</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&amp; van der Kooy, D In vivo clonal analyses reveal the properties of endogenous neural stem cell proliferation in the adult mammalian forebrain</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>125</volume><fpage>2251</fpage><lpage>2261</lpage><year>1998</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9584124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cepko</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlled expression of transgenes introduced by <italic>in vivo</italic> electroporation</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>104</volume><fpage>1027</fpage><lpage>1032</lpage><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17209010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galceran</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sustmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Folberth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosschedl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LEF1-mediated regulation of Delta-like1 links Wnt and Notch signaling in somitogenesis</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>2718</fpage><lpage>2723</lpage><year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15545629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohtsuka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Visualization of embryonic neural stem cells using Hes promoters in transgenic mice</article-title><source>Mol Cell Neurosci</source><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16214363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The intracellular domain of Notch ligand Delta1 induces cell growth arrest</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>5798</fpage><lpage>5802</lpage><year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16225865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belachew</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Postnatal NG2 proteoglycan-expressing progenitor cells are intrinsically multipotent and generate functional neurons</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><volume>161</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><year>2003</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12682089</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>EGFR overexpression reduces NSC proliferation and self renewal in the adult mouse SVZ</title><p>(a) Decreased number of GFAP<sup>+</sup>BrdU<sup>+</sup> and GFAP<sup>+</sup>Nestin<sup>+</sup> NSCs, and increased number of NG2<sup>+</sup> cells in the SVZ of the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse (*p&lt;0.05). Means &#177; SEM. (b) Decreased percentage of GFAP<sup>+</sup>Nestin<sup>+</sup>LeX<sup>+</sup> NSCs and increased percentage of GFAP<sup>+</sup>S100b<sup>+</sup> astrocytes in the SVZ of the <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mouse (**p&lt;0.02). (c) Neurospheres from WT (c1) and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR (c2) cells. (d) Reduced neurosphere numbers (d1) and size (d2) in cultures from <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice (*p&lt;0.02; **p&lt;0.001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms221823f1"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>EGFR overexpression downregulates Notch signaling in the SVZ, and NICD overexpression rescues proliferation and self-renewal of SVZ NSCs</title><p>(a) Notch signaling is downregulated, but Numb is upregulated in the SVZ of <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice. (b) NICD, RBPjk, Hes1 are upregulated in the Wa2 SVZ, and Numb is downregulated. (c-d) High NICD levels were detected after in vivo electroporation by immunostaining. (e&#8211;f) GFAP-GFP<sup>+</sup> neurosphere number (f1) and size (f2) increased after <italic>NICD</italic> electroporation. Means (n=3) &#177; SEM (*p&lt;0.01). Scale bars = 100&#956;m. (g) High b-gal expression levels in the SVZ after viral infection in WT (g1) and <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR (g2) ventricles. (h) Ad-<italic>NICD</italic> transduction increased NICD, but reduced Numb expression. (i) Ad-<italic>NICD</italic> infection increased neurosphere formation in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice, but not in WT. Means (n=3) &#177; SEM (*p&lt;0.02). Scale bars = 200&#956;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms221823f2"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>EGFR-expressing NPCs regulate NSC properties through a non-autonomous cellular mechanism</title><p>(a) Increased BrdU<sup>+</sup> cells and reduced GFAP<sup>+</sup> cells in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice (**p&lt;0.002). AraC: Increased GFAP<sup>+</sup> cells compared with NaCl in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice (**p&lt;0.002; *p&lt;0.05). (b1) AraC upregulates <italic>Hes1</italic> and <italic>RBPjk</italic> mRNAs and downregulates <italic>Numb</italic>. (b2) AraC upregulates NICD protein and downregulates Numb. (c) <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice: AraC increases NSC proliferation and self-renewal (*p&lt;0.001). Means (n=3) &#177; SEM. (d) Reduced proliferation and self-renewal in WT NSCs cultured with <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR NPCs, as compared with WT cells. Ad-<italic>NICD</italic> overexpression rescued NSC proliferation. Means (n=3) &#177; SEM (*p&lt;0.02). (e) Higher proliferation and self-renewal of NSCs cultured with NPCs of the Wa2 mouse, as compared with WT cells. Means (n=3) &#177; SEM (*p&lt;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms221823f3"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>EGFR signaling reduces Notch1 expression through Numb</title><p>(a&#8211;d) <italic>Hes1-</italic>dsRED-<italic>NICD</italic> co-electroporation in <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP and <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP/<italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR mice. More <italic>Hes1-</italic>dsRED<sup>+</sup><italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup> cells are observed in <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP mouse. <italic>NICD</italic> increases <italic>GFAP</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup><italic>Hes1</italic>-dsRED<sup>+</sup> cell number. (e) WT cells infected with: i) LacZ or <italic>NICD</italic>, or ii) GFP retrovirus (<italic>CLE</italic>-GFP) or <italic>EGFR</italic>-GFP. <italic>NICD</italic> upregulates NICD and Notch1, but downregulates Numb. <italic>EGFR</italic> reduces Notch1 and NICD, but increases Numb. (f) DAPT upregulates Numb. (g) Increased Numb/Notch1 immunoprecipitation correlates with enhanced degradation. (h) Ad-<italic>NICD</italic> reduces Notch1/Numb interaction and Notch1 degradation in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR SVZ. (i) <italic>EGFR</italic> increases Numb and reduces NICD; PD168393 prevents these effects. (j) <italic>EGFR</italic> increases Numb/Notch immunoprecipitation, and Notch1 degradation. (k) <italic>hEGFR</italic> siRNAs decrease Numb/Notch1 interaction and Notch1 degradation in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR cells. (l&#8211;o) <italic>Numb</italic> siRNA knockdown enhances Notch signaling in <italic>CNP</italic>-hEGFR NSCs. Scrab=scrambled siRNA. (l) <italic>Numb</italic> siRNA downregulates Numb and upregulates Notch1. (m) <italic>Numb</italic> siRNA decreases Numb/Notch interaction and Notch1 degradation. (n&#8211;o) Co-electroporation of Scrab or <italic>Numb</italic> siRNA, and <italic>Hes1-</italic>dsRED constructs. <italic>Numb</italic> siRNA increases the number of <italic>Hes1-</italic>dsRED<sup>+</sup><italic>CAG</italic>-GFP<sup>+</sup> cells. Scale bar = 50&#956;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms221823f4"/></fig></floats-group></article>