<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName archivearticle.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2138188</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9230079</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Human Arp2/3 Complex Is Composed of Evolutionarily
Conserved Subunits and Is Localized to Cellular
Regions of Dynamic Actin Filament Assembly</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>Matthew D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1ec5ac0N0x43bbf38">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>DePace</surname><given-names>Angela H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1ec5ac0N0x43bbf38">&#8225;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>Suzie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1ec5ac0N0x43bbf38">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iwamatsu</surname><given-names>Akihiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1ec5ac0N0x43bbf38">&#167;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>Timothy J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1ec5ac0N0x43bbf38">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x1ec5ac0N0x43bbf38">
<label>*</label>Department of Cellular and Molecular Pharmacology, <label>&#8225;</label>Department of Biochemistry and Biophysics, University of California,
San Francisco, California 94143-0450; and <label>&#167;</label>Central Laboratories for Key Technology, Kirin Brewery Company, Ltd., Yokohama,
Japan</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>1997</year></pub-date><volume>138</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>3</month><year>1997</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>3</day><month>6</month><year>1997</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>1997</copyright-year><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution&#8211;Noncommercial&#8211;Share Alike&#8211;No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution&#8211;Noncommercial&#8211;Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The Arp2/3 protein complex has been implicated in the control of actin polymerization in cells. The
human complex consists of seven subunits which include the actin related proteins Arp2 and Arp3, and
five others referred to as p41-Arc, p34-Arc, p21-Arc,
p20-Arc, and p16-Arc (<underline>Ar</underline>p <underline>c</underline>omplex). We have determined the predicted amino acid sequence of all seven
subunits. Each has homologues in diverse eukaryotes,
implying that the structure and function of the complex
has been conserved through evolution. Human Arp2
and Arp3 are very similar to family members from
other species. p41-Arc is a new member of the Sop2
family of WD (tryptophan and aspartate) repeat&#8211;containing proteins and may be posttranslationally modified, suggesting that it may be involved in regulating the
activity and/or localization of the complex. p34-Arc,
p21-Arc, p20-Arc, and p16-Arc define novel protein
families. We sought to evaluate the function of the
Arp2/3 complex in cells by determining its intracellular
distribution. Arp3, p34-Arc, and p21-Arc were localized to the lamellipodia of stationary and locomoting fibroblasts, as well to <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> assembled
actin tails. They were not detected in cellular bundles of
actin filaments. Taken together with the ability of the
Arp2/3 complex to induce actin polymerization, these
observations suggest that the complex promotes actin
assembly in lamellipodia and may participate in lamellipodial protrusion.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>T<sc>he</sc> protrusion of the cell membrane is fundamental
to cell shape change and locomotion. Actin polymerization plays a critical role in this process. The
leading edge of motile cells is dominated by thin actin-rich
structures called lamellipodia, which exhibit highly dynamic behavior characterized by rapid extension and retraction. In lamellipodia, actin filaments are oriented almost exclusively with their fast growing barbed ends
facing the membrane (for review see <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Small, 1988</xref>). Actin
polymerization adjacent to the membrane is coupled to
protrusion, and may provide the driving force for this process (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Hill and Kirschner, 1982</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Mogilner and Oster, 1996</xref>).</p><p>Many aspects of the mechanism of lamellipodial protrusion are echoed in the intracellular motility of certain bacterial and viral pathogens (for review see <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Cossart, 1995</xref>;
<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Theriot, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Higley and Way, 1997</xref>). Of these, the most
extensively studied is the bacterium <italic>Listeria monocytogenes. L. monocytogenes</italic> move in arcing trajectories within
cell cytoplasm, forming cometlike tails composed of actin
filaments oriented with their barbed ends towards the bacterium (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Tilney et al., 1992</xref>). Actin polymerization at the
bacterial surface is tightly coupled to propulsion (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Sanger
et al., 1992</xref>; <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Theriot et al., 1992</xref>), suggesting that it provides
the motile force. Although a role for myosins in bacterial
propulsion and lamellipodial protrusion cannot be definitively ruled out, the myosin inhibitor butanedione monoxime (BDM) which inhibits classic myosin-driven processes such as muscle contraction, does not affect either
process (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Cramer and Mitchison, 1995</xref>).</p><p>The central role of actin polymerization in both lamellipodial protrusion and <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> propulsion suggests that the underlying mechanisms for promoting polymerization and generating force may be similar in both
processes. Since <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> motility can be reconstituted in cell extracts (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Theriot et al., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Laurent and
Carlier, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Welch et al., 1997</xref>) understanding the biochemical mechanisms that underlie this process has
proven more tractable.</p><p>We have recently purified a multiprotein complex from
human platelets that induces actin polymerization at the
<italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> cell surface and mediates bacterial motility (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Welch et al., 1997</xref>). This complex contains actin-
related proteins in the Arp2 and Arp3 families and therefore was named the Arp2/3 complex. In addition to Arp2
and Arp3, the human complex consists of 41/40-, 34-, 21-,
20-, and 16-kD subunits, all present in approximately
equal stoichiometry. These subunits are referred to as p41-Arc, p34-Arc, p21-Arc, p20-Arc, and p16-Arc (<underline>Ar</underline>p <underline>c</underline>omplex). A similar Arp2/3 complex was first discovered by
profilin affinity chromatography of cell extracts from
<italic>Acanthamoeba castellanii</italic> (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Machesky et al., 1994</xref>). In addition, Arp2 and Arp3 proteins appear to be found in all eukaryotes (for reviews see <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Frankel and Mooseker, 1996</xref>;
<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Mullins et al., 1996</xref>), suggesting that the Arp2/3 complex
itself has been conserved through evolution. However, the
molecular identities of all but one of the non-Arp subunits
have remained undetermined. The exception is p41-Arc,
which contains WD (tryptophan and aspartate) repeats
and is similar to proteins in the Sop2 family (<underline>s</underline>uppressor <underline>o</underline>f
<underline>p</underline>rofilin; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Machesky et al., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Balasubramanian et al.,
1996</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">McCollum et al., 1996</xref>).</p><p>The mechanism by which the Arp2/3 complex promotes
actin polymerization remains enigmatic. Structural modeling of Arp2 and Arp3 proteins has led to the prediction
that the Arp2/3 complex serves as a seed for the nucleation of actin assembly (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Kelleher et al., 1995</xref>). Thus far,
only filament binding and bundling activity have been observed in vitro (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Mullins et al., 1997</xref>). Despite the lack of
detailed information regarding mechanism, several lines of
evidence indicate that the Arp2/3 complex is important for
actin function in cells. Subunits of the <italic>A. castellanii</italic> Arp2/3
complex colocalize with actin in ameba, particularly at
sites of dynamic actin assembly at the cell cortex (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Machesky et al., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Kelleher et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Mullins et al.,
1997</xref>). The <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> Arp2 and <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> Arp3 proteins are also localized to cortical actin structures. Deletions of their corresponding
genes are lethal, and temperature-sensitive mutations
cause defects in actin function (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Lees-Miller et al., 1992</xref>;
<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Schwob and Martin, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">McCollum et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Moreau
et al., 1996</xref>).</p><p>In this study we have begun to explore the function of
the Arp2/3 complex in animal cells. We have determined the
complete amino acid sequence of all seven subunits of the
human complex. Each protein has homologues in diverse
eukaryotic organisms, indicating that the subunit composition, and most likely the function of the Arp2/3 complex,
have been conserved through evolution. The ability of the
complex to promote actin assembly and mediate <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> motility suggests that it may play a corresponding role in cellular lamellipodia. In fact, multiple subunits
of the complex are localized to <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> assembled actin clouds and tails as well as to lamellipodia in stationary and motile fibroblast cells. These subunits are absent from less dynamic actin filament bundles in fibroblasts.
Our observations further strengthen the analogy between
<italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> motility and lamellipodial protrusion
and suggest that the Arp2/3 complex plays a central role in
both processes.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Protein and DNA Sequence Determination</title><p>To determine the amino acid sequence of the non-Arp polypeptide subunits of the Arp2/3 complex, the proteins were first subjected to SDS-PAGE, and then blotted to polyvinylidinedifluoride (PVDF)<sup>1</sup> membrane
(Applied Biosystems, Inc., Foster City, CA). Proteins were identified by
staining with Ponceau S (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Hirano and Watanabe, 1990</xref>). The PVDF-immobilized proteins were reduced, S-carboxymethylated, and digested in situ
with Achromobacter protease I and endoproteinase Asp-N (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Iwamatsu,
1992</xref>). Digested peptides were chromatographed by reverse-phase HPLC
using a Wakosil-II AR C18 300 &#8491; column (2.0 &#215; 150 mm; Wako Pure
Chemical Industries, Ltd., Osaka, Japan). Amino acid sequencing was
performed with a gas-phase sequencer (model PPSQ-10; Shimadzu Corp.,
Tokyo, Japan).</p><p>To identify cDNA clones encoding the individual subunits of the human Arp2/3 complex, the peptide sequences were used to search the
EMBL/GenBank/DDBJ database of expressed sequence tags (dbEST).
The following cDNA clones were identified in the database and were obtained from Genome Systems, Inc. (St. Louis, MO) (clone Id numbers are
indicated): Arp3, 328293; Arp2, 587272; p41-Arc, 527050; p34-Arc,
547253; p21-Arc, 326562; p20-Arc, 187446; and p16-Arc, 300395. In addition, a cDNA-encoding p34-Arc was isolated from a &#955; phage Uni ZAP
HeLa cell cDNA expression library (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA) by screening with anti-p34 antibody using standard procedures. The DNA sequence
of each clone was determined by sequencing both strands (performed by
the Biomolecular Resource Center Sequencing Facility at the University
of California, San Francisco, CA).</p></sec><sec><title>Protein Expression, Antibody Production,
and Immunoblotting</title><p>Polyclonal anti-peptide antibodies that recognize p34-Arc were generated
by immunizing rabbits (Berkeley Antibody Co., Richmond, CA) with the
synthetic peptide (C)KVFMQEFKEGRRASHTAPQVLFSHRE, corresponding to amino acids 179&#8211;204 of the protein. An amino-terminal cysteine was added for sulfhydryl coupling. Peptide conjugation and antibody
affinity purification were carried out as previously described (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Sawin et al.,
1992</xref>). Antibodies were concentrated by dialysis into 10 mM MOPS, pH
6.8, 150 mM NaCl, 35% glycerol.</p><p>To generate polyclonal antibodies that recognize p21-Arc (formerly referred to as the 23-kD subunit; <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Welch et al., 1997</xref>), the corresponding gene
was amplified by PCR and cloned into pGEX-3X (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Smith and Johnson,
1988</xref>) to create a glutathione S-transferase (GST) fusion protein. Purified
GST fusion protein was used to immunize rabbits (Berkeley Antibody
Co.). An affinity matrix for purification of anti-p21 antibodies was created
by cleaving p21-Arc from the GST-p21 fusion protein using Factor Xa
(<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="neb">New England Biolabs Inc.</named-content>, Beverly, MA) and covalently coupling it to affigel-10 (Bio Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA). Antibody affinity purification was performed using standard procedures (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Harlow and Lane, 1988</xref>).
Antibodies were concentrated by dialysis into 10 mM MOPS, pH 6.8, 150
mM NaCl, 35% glycerol. Immunoblotting was carried out using affinity-purified anti-Arp3 (0.4 &#956;g/ml), anti-p34 (0.04 &#956;g/ml), and anti-p21 (0.6 &#956;g/
ml) antibodies using the ECL system (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="amersham">Amersham Corp.</named-content>, Arlington
Heights, IL).</p></sec><sec><title>Cell Culture and Immunofluorescence</title><p>Swiss 3T3 fibroblasts were grown in DME-H16 medium with 10% FBS,
penicillin, and streptomycin. To create a confluent layer of cells for the
wounding experiment, cells were plated at a density of 3 &#215; 10<sup>4</sup> cells per ml
onto 22-mm diam coverslips and allowed to grow to confluence. A wound
was created using a plastic pipette tip. HeLa cells were grown in DME-H16 medium with 10% FBS, penicillin, and streptomycin. Cells were
plated onto glass coverslips 1&#8211;2 d before immunofluorescence experiments. Infection of HeLa cells with <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> strain 10403S was
carried out as previously described (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Theriot et al., 1994</xref>). Locomoting fibroblasts were prepared from heart explants from 7-d-old chick embryos
as described in <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Cramer et al., 1997</xref>. Cells were plated onto glass coverslips
treated with 1 mg/ml poly-<sc>d</sc>-lysine (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="sigma">Sigma Chemical Co.</named-content>, St. Louis, MO),
and 125 &#956;g/ml matrigel (Collaborative Research, Inc., Waltham, MA) and
were grown in DME-H16 medium with 10% FBS and 10% heat-inactivated chicken serum, penicillin, and streptomycin. Immunofluorescence
experiments were carried out within 20 h of plating, which was shown by
<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Cramer et al. (1997)</xref> to be optimal for observing rapidly locomoting cells.</p><p>For immunofluorescence experiments, cells were extracted for 30 s in
cytoskeleton buffer with 0.32 M sucrose (CBS) (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Small, 1981</xref>; <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Symons and
Mitchison, 1991</xref>) also containing 0.1% Triton X-100 and 1 &#956;g/ml phalloidin. Cells were fixed in CBS plus 4% formaldehyde for 20 min followed by
&#8722;20&#176;C methanol for 3 min (methanol fixation was necessary to observe
staining with the anti-p34 and anti-p21 antibodies, indicating that they recognize only denatured protein). Indirect immunofluorescence was performed using affinity-purified rabbit anti-Arp3 (4 &#956;g/ml), anti-p34 (0.4 &#956;g/
ml), anti-p21 (6 &#956;g/ml) and mouse anti-actin (5 &#956;g/ml; <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="boehringer">Boehringer Mannheim Biochemicals</named-content>, Indianapolis, IN) primary antibodies, and Texas red&#8211;
conjugated goat anti&#8211;rabbit and FITC-conjugated goat anti&#8211;mouse secondary antibodies (Jackson Immunoresearch Laboratories, Inc., West
Grove, PA). Fluorescent phalloidin staining of filamentous actin was carried out with 1 &#956;g/ml FITC-conjugated phalloidin (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="sigma">Sigma Chemical Co.</named-content>).
Photomicrographs were taken using a cooled CCD camera (Princeton Scientific Instruments, Inc., Princeton, NJ) on a Nikon Optiphot-2 microscope. Images were handled digitally using Adobe Photoshop (Adobe
Systems Inc., Mountain View, CA).</p></sec><sec><title>Construction of Arp3-Green Fluorescent Protein
Fusion and Cell Transfection</title><p>The gene encoding Arp3 was isolated by PCR and was cloned into
pEGFP-N1 (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="clontech">Clontech</named-content>, Palo Alto, CA) to create a fusion of Arp3 with
green fluorescent protein (EGFP) attached to its carboxy terminus
(pArp3-EGFP). (The DNA sequence of the Arp3 gene isolated by PCR
was identical to the sequence of the Arp3 cDNA clone.) pArp3-EGFP
was introduced into HeLa cells using calcium phosphate&#8211;mediated transfection as described previously (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Heald et al., 1993</xref>). To visualize Arp3-EGPF in <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic>&#8211;infected cells, HeLa cells were infected 1 d
after transfection. For fluorescence experiments, cells were extracted in
CBS with 0.1% Triton X-100 and 1 &#956;g/ml phalloidin for 30 s, and then
fixed in CBS with 3.2% formaldehyde for 10 min. To visualize polymerized actin, cells were stained with 1 &#956;g/ml 5-carboxytetramethyl
rhodamine phalloidin (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="sigma">Sigma Chemical Co.</named-content>) for 2 min. Cells were photographed as described above except that a blocking filter was used to eliminate bleed through from the rhodamine to the fluorescein channel.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>The Sequence of Human Arp2 and Arp3</title><p>To further understand the role of the Arp2/3 complex in
the control of actin assembly in cells, we determined the
predicted amino acid sequences of all of the subunits of
the human protein complex. Using peptide sequence information (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Welch et al., 1997</xref>) to search the EMBL/GenBank/DDBJ dbEST we obtained and sequenced full-length
human cDNA clones encoding Arp2 and Arp3 (these
sequence data are available from EMBL/GenBank/DDBJ
under accession numbers <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AF006082">AF006082</ext-link> for Arp2 and <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AF006083">AF006083</ext-link> for Arp3). The Arp2 cDNA encodes a predicted protein of 394 amino acids with a molecular mass
of 45 kD (43 kD as determined by SDS-PAGE; <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Welch et
al., 1997</xref>). Human Arp2 is 99% identical to chicken Arp2
(these data are available from EMBL/GenBank/DDBJ
under accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="X73971">X73971</ext-link>), and is also highly similar to Arp2 proteins from <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (81%
identical; accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="X78486">X78486</ext-link>), <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> (76% identical; accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="Z71181">Z71181</ext-link>), <italic>A. castellanii</italic> (72% identical; accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="U29609">U29609</ext-link>), and <italic>S.
cerevisiae</italic> (67% identical; accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="X61502">X61502</ext-link>). Human Arp3 is 418 amino acids in length and has a predicted
molecular mass of 47 kD (50 kD as determined by SDS-PAGE; <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Welch et al., 1997</xref>). It is identical in sequence to
bovine Arp3 (accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="D12816">D12816</ext-link>), and shows extensive similarity to Arp3 proteins from <italic>D. melanogaster</italic>
(80% identical; accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="X71789">X71789</ext-link>), <italic>A. castellanii</italic>
(70% identical; accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="U29610">U29610</ext-link>), <italic>Dictyostelium
discoideum</italic> (69% identical; accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="Z46418">Z46418</ext-link>),
<italic>Neurospora crassa</italic> (59% identical; accession number
<ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="U79737">U79737</ext-link>), <italic>S. pombe</italic> (59% identical; accession number
<ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="M81068">M81068</ext-link>), and <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (58% identical; accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="Z49565">Z49565</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec><title>p41-Arc Is a Member of the Sop2 Family of WD Repeat
Containing Proteins</title><p>We also searched the dbEST database using peptide sequences derived from the five non-Arp subunits of the
Arp2/3 complex. Full-length cDNA clones encoding each
subunit were identified, and their DNA sequences were
determined. The predicted polypeptides encoded by these
clones are similar in sequence to proteins from a wide variety of eukaryotes.</p><p>Based on its high degree of sequence similarity, the p41-Arc subunit of the platelet Arp2/3 complex is a new member of the Sop2 family of proteins. As is shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>
<italic>A</italic>,
p41-Arc is 67% identical to the previously identified human Sop2 protein Sop2Hs (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Balasubramanian et al., 1996</xref>),
making them similar but distinct members of the same
family. p41-Arc is also similar to Sop2 proteins from <italic>D.
melanogaster</italic> (49% identical; accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="L39625">L39625</ext-link>),
<italic>S. pombe</italic> (37% identical; accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="Y08998">Y08998</ext-link>), and
<italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (34% identical; accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="Z36103">Z36103</ext-link>).
Previous evidence has suggested that Sop2 family proteins
encode the 41-kD subunit of the Arp2/3 complex. The canonical member of this family, <italic>S. pombe</italic> Sop2p, associates
with Arp3 in a protein complex, and mutations in the <italic>sop2</italic>
and <italic>arp3</italic> genes interact genetically. Moreover, Sop2 proteins contain sequences that are similar to peptide sequences from the 40-kD subunit of the <italic>A. castellanii</italic> Arp2/3
complex (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Balasubramanian et al., 1996</xref>). Like previously
identified Sop2 family proteins, human p41-Arc contains
WD repeat sequences (also known as &#946;-transducin repeats). We identified seven potential WD repeats in p41-Arc (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>
<italic>A</italic>) that correspond to the consensus sequence
described by <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Neer et al. (1994)</xref> with one to five mismatches. These repeats are highly conserved in both sequence and position within p41-Arc and Sop2Hs.
</p><p>The 41- and 40-kD subunits of the platelet Arp2/3 complex (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, <italic>far left lane</italic>), which differ slightly in their mobility by SDS-PAGE, are different versions of the p41-Arc
polypeptide. Digestion of p41 and p40 with Achromobacter
protease I and endoproteinase Asp-N produced identical
peptide maps by reverse phase HPLC (not shown). This
suggests that p41 and p40 may differ in their state of posttranslational modification. Furthermore, this indicates
that the platelet Arp2/3 complex contains seven polypeptides, identical to the number found in the <italic>A. castellanii</italic>
complex. Both p41 and p40 are the only subunits of the platelet Arp2/3 complex that are present in substoichiometric
quantities, while the other six subunits are represented in
slightly larger and roughly equal amounts (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Welch et al.,
1997</xref>). However, when summed together, the quantity of
the p41 and p40 is stoichiometric with that of the other
subunits. This indicates that the seven polypeptide subunits of the complex are present in a 1:1:1:1:1:1:1 stoichiometry, similar to that found in the <italic>A. castellanii</italic> Arp2/3
complex (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Machesky et al., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Mullins et al., 1997</xref>).
</p></sec><sec><title>p34-Arc, p21-Arc, p20-Arc, and p16-Arc Define Novel
Protein Families</title><p>The four other subunits of the human Arp2/3 complex&#8212;
p34-Arc, p21-Arc, p20-Arc, and p16-Arc (formerly the 34-,
23-, 22-, and 19-kD subunits as determined by SDS-PAGE; <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Welch et al., 1997</xref>)&#8212;are similar to proteins from
diverse eukaryotic organisms. However, they do not share
similarity with any proteins of known function. These
therefore define four novel protein families, which are
shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>
<italic>B.</italic> The p34-Arc family is comprised of the
human and <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> proteins (34% identical). Furthermore, a region in p34-Arc is similar in sequence to a peptide from 35-kD subunit of the <italic>A. castellanii</italic> complex (Fig.
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>
<italic>C</italic>). A partial sequence of human p34-Arc had previously
been determined and its gene maps to chromosome 13 in
the BRCA2 region (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Couch et al., 1996</xref>). Like p34-Arc,
p21-Arc has a single homologue in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (45% identical; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>
<italic>B</italic>) and contains a region similar to a peptide in
the 18-kD subunit of the <italic>A. castellanii</italic> complex (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>
<italic>C</italic>).
The p20-Arc family has members in multiple organisms
(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>
<italic>B</italic>) including <italic>C. elegans</italic> (73% identical in its amino-terminal 168 amino acids), <italic>S. pombe</italic> (68% identical), and
<italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (67% identical). In addition, it contains a sequence that is similar to the 19-kD subunit of the <italic>A. castellanii</italic> complex (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>
<italic>C</italic>). Finally, p16-Arc resembles proteins in <italic>C. elegans</italic> (34% identical), <italic>S. pombe</italic> (26% identical),
and <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (21% identical). The <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> proteins
that share sequence similarity with human p34-Arc, p21-Arc, p20-Arc, and p16-Arc have recently been shown to
be components of the yeast Arp2/3 complex (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Winter et al.,
1997</xref>).</p><p>Although the sequences of these subunits have not provided clues to their potential function in the Arp2/3 complex, we have used the sequence information as well as the
cloned genes to generate reagents to probe the function of
the complex in cells. We have raised polyclonal antibodies
to a GST-p21 fusion protein and to a peptide from p34-Arc. Affinity-purified antibodies recognize p21-Arc and
p34-Arc in the pure Arp2/3 complex (not shown), and specifically recognize 21- and 34-kD proteins in whole cell extracts made from a variety of mammalian and avian cell
types (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). In addition, we have taken advantage of the
previously described anti-Arp3 antibody (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Welch et al.,
1997</xref>), which specifically recognizes Arp3 in the same cell
extracts (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Together, these reagents provide a means
of examining the function of the Arp2/3 complex by determining its intracellular distribution.</p></sec><sec><title>Arp3, p34-Arc, and p21-Arc Are Localized to
L. monocytogenes Assembled Actin Tails</title><p>The Arp2/3 complex promotes the assembly of actin filaments at the surface of <italic>L. monocytogenes.</italic> Moreover, the
Arp3 subunit of the complex is localized to the actin tails
assembled by moving intracellular bacteria and to actin
clouds surrounding stationary bacteria (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Welch et al.,
1997</xref>). To confirm that other subunits of the Arp2/3 complex exhibit the same localization pattern, we carried out
immunofluorescence experiments on <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic>&#8211;
infected HeLa cells using anti-p34 and anti-p21 antibodies.
As is shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>C</italic>, both p34-Arc and p21-Arc
are localized to <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> assembled actin clouds,
and throughout tails with a distribution that mirrors that
of Arp3 (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Welch et al., 1997</xref>; and see below) and polymerized actin (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, <italic>B</italic> and <italic>D</italic>). Punctate cytoplasmic staining
also was evident, and was reduced by briefly pre-extracting cells with detergent in the presence of phalloidin to
stabilize actin structures (see Materials and Methods).
</p><p>To further confirm the observed localization pattern, we
created a tagged Arp3 with green fluorescent protein
(GFP) at its carboxy terminus. We chose to create this particular fusion because <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> Arp3 tagged at its carboxy terminus can complement a null mutation in the
<italic>ARP3</italic> gene (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Winter et al., 1997</xref>). HeLa cells were transfected with pArp3-EGFP plasmid DNA, and 1 d later
were infected with <italic>L. monocytogenes.</italic> Arp3-GFP fluorescence was observed in actin clouds and tails with a distribution indistinguishable from that seen by immunofluorescence (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>
<italic>E</italic>; actin localization in <italic>F</italic>). GFP alone did
not localize to actin clouds or tails (not shown). As was
seen in the immunofluorescence experiments, cytoplasmic
Arp3-GFP fluorescence was always apparent, even in cells
expressing lower levels of the fusion protein. A brief pre-extraction of the cells before fixation significantly reduced
this cytoplasmic background.</p></sec><sec><title>The Arp2/3 Complex Is Localized to Lamellipodia in
Stationary Cells</title><p>The actin-based motility of <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> may be
mechanistically similar to actin-driven cellular movements
such as the protrusion of lamellipodia. To evaluate whether
the Arp2/3 complex may be involved in actin polymerization&#8211;driven membrane protrusion, we determined its intracellular distribution. We observed the localization of
Arp2/3 complex subunits in a variety of tissue culture lines
by immunofluorescence. Mouse Swiss 3T3 fibroblast cells
gave the most consistent results, although a similar staining pattern was evident in all cell lines tested (including
human HeLa epithelial-like cells and mouse MC7 3T3 fibroblasts). As is shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, Arp3 (<italic>A</italic>), p34-Arc (<italic>C</italic>),
and p21-Arc (<italic>E</italic>) were distributed throughout the thin actin-rich lamellipodia at the edges of Swiss 3T3 cells (actin
staining in the same cells is shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>
<italic>B</italic>, <italic>D</italic>, and <italic>F</italic>).
Staining was not observed along the entire margin of the
cell, but was confined to lamellipodia (Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Strikingly, other actin-containing structures such as stress fibers
and focal adhesions were not stained. The punctate cytoplasmic staining pattern was especially prominent in
thicker regions of the cell in the vicinity of the nucleus
(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>).
</p></sec><sec><title>The Arp2/3 Complex Is Localized to the Leading
Lamellipodia of Motile Cells</title><p>Stationary Swiss 3T3 fibroblasts produce actin-rich lamellipodia that actively protrude and retract but are not involved in directional motility. These were randomly dispersed over the cell surface as is illustrated by the
distribution of the p21 subunit of the Arp2/3 complex and
actin in these cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>). To ascertain whether
the Arp2/3 complex may be involved in membrane protrusion during cell migration, we observed the localization of
the complex in motile fibroblasts. We generated a population of moving Swiss 3T3 fibroblasts by wounding a confluent layer of cells. Cells at the margin of the wound responded immediately by generating membrane ruffles at
their edges facing the wound, indicating that they had begun to reorient their actin cytoskeleton. Within 30 min,
they began to move outwards towards the center of the
wound. p21-Arc was localized to the broad actin-rich
lamellipodia at the leading edges of these moving cells
(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>E</italic>, and actin localization in <italic>D</italic> and <italic>F</italic>).</p><p>We also generated a population of motile primary cultured fibroblasts and looked at the distribution of Arp2/3
complex subunits in these cells by immunofluorescence.
To prepare moving fibroblasts, tissue explants from the
hearts of 7-d-old embryonic chicks were plated onto coverslips. Cells migrate outward from explants within 12 h,
and continue to move rapidly for up to 20 h (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Cramer et al.,
1997</xref>). These cells assumed a morphology typical of locomoting cells, with a cone- or fan-shaped cell body and broad
lamellipodia at their leading edges (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Both Arp3
(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>
<italic>A</italic>) and p34-Arc (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>
<italic>C</italic>) were localized throughout lamellipodia. Neither protein was found in actin bundles, fully consistent with their distribution in Swiss 3T3 fibroblasts.
</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>The Arp2/3 Complex Consists of Evolutionarily
Conserved Subunits</title><p>The seven subunits of the human Arp2/3 complex define
seven protein families that are present in diverse eukaryotic organisms. Six share sequence similarity with subunits
of the <italic>A. castellanii</italic> complex (sequence information for <italic>A.
castellanii</italic> p14 is not yet available). Moreover, every subunit has a homologue <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, and the yeast equivalents of human p34-Arc, p21-Arc, p20-Arc, and p16-Arc
have recently been shown to be components of the Arp2/3
complex (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Winter et al., 1997</xref>). This indicates that the structure of the Arp2/3 complex has been conserved through
evolution and suggests a corresponding conservation of its
activity in all eukaryotic cells. The complex appears to be
essential for cell viability and actin cytoskeletal function,
as deletion of the genes encoding Arp2, Arp3, and Sop2p
is lethal in yeast, and less severe mutations cause defects in
actin organization and disrupt actin-dependent processes
(<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Lees-Miller et al., 1992</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Schwob and Martin, 1992</xref>;
<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Moreau et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">McCollum et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Balasubramanian et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Winter et al., 1997</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Sequence, Structure, and Function&#8212;the Role of the
Arp2 and Arp3 Subunits</title><p>The Arp2/3 complex induces actin polymerization at the
cell surface of <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Welch et al., 1997</xref>), suggesting that it performs a similar function in cells. It is
likely to promote actin assembly by filament nucleation.
Structural modeling of Arp2 and Arp3 proteins (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Kelleher
et al., 1995</xref>) has suggested that these subunits may serve as
a template for the nucleation of polymerization, similar to
the function performed by &#947;-tubulin in the initiation of microtubule assembly (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Moritz et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al.,
1995</xref>). Although structural considerations led <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Kelleher et
al. (1995)</xref> to propose that the Arp subunits interact with
the pointed end of the filament, interaction with the barbed
end remains a possibility. Of the Arp2/3 complex subunits,
the sequences of Arp2 and Arp3 proteins are among the
most highly conserved between species, consistent with
their proposed role in nucleating actin polymerization.</p></sec><sec><title>Sequence, Structure, and Function&#8212;the Role
of p41-Arc</title><p>The other five subunits of the Arp2/3 complex may be important for stabilizing its structure, regulating its biochemical activity, and/or determining its intracellular localization. The sequence and biochemical properties of one of
these subunits, p41-Arc, suggest that it plays an important
regulatory role. This subunit is a member of the Sop2 family of proteins and is most similar to another human protein, Sop2Hs. The similarity between these proteins suggests that they may both function as the p41 subunit of the
human Arp2/3 complex. Multiple versions of the p41 subunit may adapt the functions of the complex to different
cell types or developmental stages. Platelets appear to use
only p41-Arc since the peptides derived from the 41- and
40-kD polypeptides were all identical to it in sequence,
and clearly different from the corresponding regions in
Sop2Hs.</p><p>p41-Arc, like Sop2Hs, contains seven putative WD repeats that are evenly dispersed over the entire sequence of
the protein. The presence of WD repeats may provide
some insight into the potential functions of this subunit.
These repeats, which were first identified in the G<sub>&#946;</sub> subunit of heterotrimeric GTP-binding proteins, have since
been found in between four to ten copies in proteins with a
wide variety of functions (for review see <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Neer et al., 1994</xref>).
The repeat unit is involved in the formation of a characteristic three-dimensional structure known as a &#946;-propeller,
each repeat constituting one blade of the propeller (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Wall
et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Lambright et al., 1996</xref>; for review see <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Neer and
Smith, 1996</xref>). Because many WD repeat-containing proteins participate in the formation of multiprotein complexes, one possibility is that p41-Arc is involved in assembling and maintaining the structure of the Arp2/3 complex.</p><p>Another intriguing possibility is that p41-Arc mediates
the interaction of the complex with other molecules that
regulate its localization or activity. One known ligand of
WD repeats is the pleckstrin homology (PH) domain (for
reviews see <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Lemmon et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Shaw, 1996</xref>), which is
found in a variety of cell signaling and cytoskeletal proteins that interact with cell membranes. In addition to
binding WD repeat sequences, PH domains can simultaneously bind phosphatidyl inositol 4,5-bisphosphate, and
thus may serve as adapters that link WD repeat&#8211;containing proteins to the cell membrane. We have found that the
Arp2/3 complex is localized to the cell edges in lamellipodia. An interaction between p41-Arc in the Arp2/3 complex and a PH domain&#8211;containing protein may mediate
the recruitment of the complex to the cell membrane and
may also serve to activate the actin polymerization promoting capacity of the complex. A protein that recruits the
Arp2/3 complex to cell membranes would be functionally
similar to the <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> ActA protein, which is required for actin polymerization by bacteria in vivo (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Domann et al., 1992</xref>; <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Kocks et al., 1992</xref>) and for the activity of
the Arp2/3 complex at the bacterial surface (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Welch et al.,
1997</xref>).</p><p>Posttranslational modification of p41-Arc may also regulate the activity and intracellular distribution of the complex. We have determined that the 41- and 40-kD subunits
of the platelet Arp2/3 complex are the same polypeptide,
suggesting that they may differ in their state of posttranslational modification. However, the nature of this putative
modification and its effect on the Arp2/3 complex remain
to be determined.</p></sec><sec><title>Sequence, Structure, and Function&#8212;the Role of
p34-Arc, p21-Arc, p20-Arc, and p16-Arc</title><p>The four other subunits of the Arp2/3 complex (p34-Arc,
p21-Arc, p20-Arc, and p16-Arc) define four novel protein
families. The extent of sequence conservation between
family members from different species indicates that the
structure of these subunits has been conserved through
evolution. However, the sequences of these proteins do
not indicate what their role in the structure or regulation
of the complex may be.</p><p>Two of these subunits of the <italic>A. castellanii</italic> complex&#8212;the
35-, and either the 19-, 18-, or 14-kD subunits&#8212;were found
by chemical cross-linking to be intimately associated with
actin (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Mullins et al., 1997</xref>). The Arp3 subunit and actin
could be also cross-linked. It was suggested that these subunits mediate the ability of the <italic>A. castellanii</italic> complex to
bind the sides of actin filaments and to bundle actin filaments into parallel arrays in vitro. However, these subunits do not exhibit any similarity to known actin-binding
proteins, implying that they may possess novel actin-binding motifs.</p></sec><sec><title>Localization of the Arp2/3 Complex in Vertebrate Cells</title><p>The localization of subunits of the Arp2/3 complex in
yeast and <italic>A. castellanii</italic> is consistent with its proposed role
in promoting actin polymerization in cells. The <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> Arp2 and Arp3 proteins are found in the motile cortical actin patches, but not in cytoplasmic cables that consist
of bundled actin filaments (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Moreau et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Winter et
al., 1997</xref>). <italic>S. pombe</italic> Arp3 shares a similar distribution, and
in addition is absent from the contractile ring (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">McCollum
et al., 1996</xref>). In ameba, subunits of the complex colocalize
with actin at the cell cortex (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Machesky et al., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Kelleher et al., 1995</xref>). Staining is enriched in actin fibrils that
may represent bundles of actin filaments, in agreement
with the bundling activity exhibited by the <italic>A. castellanii</italic>
complex in vitro (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Mullins et al., 1997</xref>).</p><p>We have now determined the localization of multiple
subunits of the Arp2/3 complex in vertebrate cells. The
Arp3, p34-Arc, and p21-Arc subunits are found in the
lamellipodia of motile and stationary fibroblasts. They are
also localized to <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> assembled actin clouds
and tails in infected cells. In contrast, Arp3, p34-Arc, and
p21-Arc were not detected in cellular bundles of actin, including stress fibers in tissue culture fibroblasts and
graded polarity bundles (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Cramer et al., 1997</xref>) in primary
cultures of chick embryo fibroblasts. Moreover, they have
not been observed in filopodia, which also contain bundled actin (DePace, A., M. Welch, and T. Mitchison, unpublished results).</p><p>Actin filaments in lamellipodia and those in actin bundles differ in their spatial organization and dynamic properties. Filaments in lamellipodia are arranged as an orthogonal meshwork and are oriented at an angle of &#8764;45&#176;,
relative to the direction of protrusion (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Small et al., 1995</xref>).
They exhibit rapid polymerization dynamics, turning over
with a <italic>t</italic>
<sub>1/2</sub> of &lt;1 min in some cell types (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Theriot and Mitchison, 1991</xref>). This rapid turnover is similar to that seen for
filaments in <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> tails (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Theriot et al., 1992</xref>).
Conversely, filaments in stress fibers and other cellular
bundles are arranged in closely spaced parallel arrays.
They exhibit much slower polymerization dynamics than
filaments in lamellipodia (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Theriot and Mitchison, 1991</xref>).
We do not detect the Arp2/3 complex in actin bundles,
suggesting that the filament side-binding and bundling activity exhibited by the complex in vitro (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Mullins et al.,
1997</xref>) may not be a primary determinant of its function in
vertebrate cells. Instead, we find that the Arp2/3 complex
is present with the rapidly polymerizing and depolymerizing populations of actin filaments in lamellipodia and <italic>L.
monocytogenes</italic> tails, further strengthening the analogy between bacterial motility and lamellipodial protrusion. Together with the biochemical activity of the Arp2/3 complex, these results suggest a model in which the complex
promotes actin polymerization in the lamellipodium and
participates in lamellipodial protrusion. The ability of the
complex to bind filaments might serve to retain the complex in the lamellipodium, making it readily available for
additional rounds of polymerization.</p><p>Before we can put together a comprehensive model of
actin polymerization dynamics in lamellipodia, several
outstanding questions need to be answered. For example,
it is not clear whether actin polymerization occurs throughout the lamellipodium, matching the distribution of Arp2/3
complex, or only at the leading edge. In addition, it is not
known whether the mechanism of new actin filament polymerization involves the elongation of existing filaments or
continuous nucleation of new filaments. Finally, the mechanisms that regulate the spatial and temporal control of
actin polymerization have yet to be determined. Further
characterization of the interactions of the Arp2/3 complex
with actin filaments and with factors that regulate its activity and localization should help shed light on the answers
to these outstanding problems.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was supported by grant from the National Institutes of
Health (GM48027) to T.J. Mitchison, and a postdoctoral fellowship from
the National Institutes of Health to M.D. Welch.</p></ack><fn-group><fn><p>We want to thank all of the members of the Mitchison lab, and especially
Louise Cramer, Arshad Desai, Aneil Mallavarapu, Jody Rosenblatt, Jack
Taunton and Claire Walczak for many helpful discussions and for critically reading the manuscript. We also want to thank Dirk Winter and
Rong Li for sharing sequence information before publication.</p></fn><fn><p>Please address all correspondence to Matthew D. Welch, Department of
Cellular and Molecular Pharmacology, University of California at San
Francisco, 513 Parnassus Avenue, San Francisco, CA 94143-0450. Tel.:
(415) 476-0836. Fax: (415) 476-5233. e-mail: <email>welch@cgl.ucsf.edu</email>
</p></fn></fn-group><glossary><title>Abbreviations used in this paper</title><def-list><def-item><term>CBS</term><def><p>cytoskeleton buffer with sucrose</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>dbEST</term><def><p>database of expressed sequence tags</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EGFP and GFP</term><def><p>green fluorescent protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GST</term><def><p>glutathione S-transferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PH</term><def><p>pleckstrin homology</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Feoktistova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McCollum</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Fission yeast Sop2p: a novel and evolutionarily conserved protein that interacts with Arp3p and modulates profilin function</article-title>
<source>EMBO (Eur Mol Biol
Organ) J</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>6426</fpage>
<lpage>6437</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8978670?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8978670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cossart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Actin-based bacterial motility</article-title>
<source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>94</fpage>
<lpage>101</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 7755995?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7755995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Couch</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rommens</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuhausen</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Belanger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumont</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannon-Albright</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Generation of an integrated transcription map of the BRCA2 region on chromosome 13q12-q13</article-title>
<source>Genomics</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>86</fpage>
<lpage>99</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8812419?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8812419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Myosin is involved in postmitotic cell spreading</article-title>
<source>J Cell Biol</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>131</volume>
<fpage>179</fpage>
<lpage>189</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 7559774?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7559774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Siebert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Identification of novel graded polarity actin filament bundles in locomoting heart fibroblasts: implications for the generation of motile force</article-title>
<source>J Cell Biol</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>136</volume>
<fpage>1287</fpage>
<lpage>1305</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 9087444?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9087444</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goebel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Leimeister-Wachter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wuenscher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A novel bacterial virulence gene in <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>required for host cell microfilament interaction with homology to the proline-rich region of vinculin</article-title>
<source>EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>1981</fpage>
<lpage>1990</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 1582425?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1582425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frankel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mooseker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The actin-related proteins</article-title>
<source>Curr Opin
Cell Biol</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>30</fpage>
<lpage>37</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8791406?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8791406</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Harlow, E., and D. Lane. 1988. Antibodies: A Laboratory Manual. Cold Spring
Harbor Laboratory, Cold Spring Harbor, NY. 313&#8211;315.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heald</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McLoughlin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McKeon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Human wee1 maintains mitotic timing by protecting the nucleus from cytoplasmically activated Cdc2 kinase</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<year>1993</year>
<volume>74</volume>
<fpage>463</fpage>
<lpage>474</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8348613?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8348613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Higley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Way</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Actin and cell pathogenesis</article-title>
<source>Curr Opin Cell
Biol</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>62</fpage>
<lpage>69</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 9013675?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9013675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirschner</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Subunit treadmilling of microtubules or actin in the presence of cellular barriers: possible conversion of chemical free energy into mechanical work</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>1982</year>
<volume>79</volume>
<fpage>490</fpage>
<lpage>494</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 6952202?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6952202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Microsequencing of proteins electrotransferred onto immobilizing matrices from polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis: application to an insoluble protein</article-title>
<source>Electrophoresis</source>
<year>1990</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>573</fpage>
<lpage>580</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 2226413?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2226413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwamatsu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>S-carboxymethylation of proteins transferred onto polyvinylidene difluoride membranes followed by in situ protease digestion and amino acid microsequencing</article-title>
<source>Electrophoresis</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>142</fpage>
<lpage>147</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 1592044?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1592044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelleher</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Sequences, structural
models, and cellular localization of the actin-related proteins Arp2 and Arp3
from <italic>Acanthamoeba. </italic>
</article-title>
<source>J Cell Biol</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>131</volume>
<fpage>385</fpage>
<lpage>397</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 7593166?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7593166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kocks</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabouret</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Berche</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohayon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cossart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>
<italic>L. monocytogenes</italic>-induced actin assembly requires the actA gene product, a surface protein</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>521</fpage>
<lpage>531</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 1739966?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1739966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lambright</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sondek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Skiba</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamm</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigler</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The 2.0 &#8491; crystal structure of a heterotrimeric G protein</article-title>
<source>Nature
(Lond)</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>379</volume>
<fpage>311</fpage>
<lpage>319</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8552184?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8552184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Laurent, V., and M.-F. Carlier. 1997. Use of platelet extracts for actin-based
motility of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes. In</italic> Cell Biology: A Laboratory Handbook. J. Celis, editor. Academic Press, New York.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lees-Miller</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Helfman</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Identification of <italic>act2</italic>, an
essential gene in the fission yeast <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic>that encodes a protein related to actin</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>89</volume>
<fpage>80</fpage>
<lpage>83</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 1729722?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1729722</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemmon</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlessinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>PH domains: diverse sequences with a common fold recruit signaling molecules to the cell surface</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>85</volume>
<fpage>621</fpage>
<lpage>624</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8646770?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8646770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Machesky</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ampe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandekerckhove</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Purification of a cortical complex containing two unconventional
actins from <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic>by affinity chromatography on profilin-agarose</article-title>
<source>J Cell Biol</source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>127</volume>
<fpage>107</fpage>
<lpage>115</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 7929556?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7929556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCollum</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Feoktistova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morphew</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic>actin-related protein, Arp3, is a component of the cortical actin cytoskeleton and interacts with profilin</article-title>
<source>EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>6438</fpage>
<lpage>6446</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8978671?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8978671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mogilner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Oster</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cell motility driven by actin polymerization</article-title>
<source>Biophys J</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>71</volume>
<fpage>3030</fpage>
<lpage>3045</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8968574?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8968574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Madania</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Winsor</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The <italic>Saccharomyces
cerevisiae</italic>actin-related protein Arp2 is involved in the actin cytoskeleton</article-title>
<source>J
Cell Biol</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>134</volume>
<fpage>117</fpage>
<lpage>132</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8698808?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8698808</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Braunfeld</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sedat</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Alberts</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Agard</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Microtubule nucleation by &#947;-tubulin-containing rings in the centrosome</article-title>
<source>Nature (Lond)</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>378</volume>
<fpage>638</fpage>
<lpage>640</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8524401?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8524401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mullins</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelleher</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Actin' like actin? </article-title>
<source>Trends
Cell Biol</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>208</fpage>
<lpage>212</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 15157457?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15157457</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mullins</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Stafford</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Structure, subunit topology, and actin-binding activity of the Arp2/3 complex from <italic>Acanthamoeba.
</italic>
</article-title>
<source>J Cell Biol</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>136</volume>
<fpage>331</fpage>
<lpage>343</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 9015304?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9015304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>G protein heterodimers: new structures propel new questions</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>84</volume>
<fpage>175</fpage>
<lpage>178</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8565060?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8565060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nambudripad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The ancient regulatory-protein family of WD-repeat proteins</article-title>
<source>Nature (Lond)</source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>371</volume>
<fpage>297</fpage>
<lpage>300</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8090199?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8090199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanger</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanger</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Southwick</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Host cell actin assembly is
necessary and likely to provide the propulsive force for intracellular movement of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes. </italic>
</article-title>
<source>Infect Immun</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>3609</fpage>
<lpage>3619</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 1500169?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1500169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sawin</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wordeman</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evidence for kinesin-related proteins in the mitotic apparatus using peptide antibodies</article-title>
<source>J Cell Sci</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>101</volume>
<fpage>303</fpage>
<lpage>313</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 1629247?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1629247</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwob</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>New yeast actin-like gene required late in the cell cycle</article-title>
<source>Nature (Lond)</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>355</volume>
<fpage>179</fpage>
<lpage>182</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 1729653?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1729653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The pleckstrin homology domain: an intriguing multifunctional protein module</article-title>
<source>Bioessays</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>35</fpage>
<lpage>46</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8593162?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8593162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Organization of actin in the leading edge of cultured cells: influence of osmium tetroxide and dehydration on the ultrastructure of actin meshworks</article-title>
<source>J Cell Biol</source>
<year>1981</year>
<volume>91</volume>
<fpage>695</fpage>
<lpage>705</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 6799521?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6799521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The actin cytoskeleton</article-title>
<source>Electron Microsc Rev</source>
<year>1988</year>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>155</fpage>
<lpage>174</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 2485000?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2485000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Actin filament organization in the fish keratocyte lamellipodium</article-title>
<source>J Cell Biol</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>129</volume>
<fpage>1275</fpage>
<lpage>1286</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 7775574?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7775574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Single-step purification of polypeptides
expressed in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>as fusions with glutathoine S-transferase</article-title>
<source>Gene</source>
<year>1988</year>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>31</fpage>
<lpage>40</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 3047011?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3047011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Symons</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Control of actin polymerization in live and permeabilized fibroblasts</article-title>
<source>J Cell Biol</source>
<year>1991</year>
<volume>114</volume>
<fpage>503</fpage>
<lpage>513</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 1860882?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1860882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Theriot</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The cell biology of infection by intracellular bacterial pathogens</article-title>
<source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>213</fpage>
<lpage>239</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8689557?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8689557</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Theriot</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Actin microfilament dynamics in locomoting cells</article-title>
<source>Nature (Lond)</source>
<year>1991</year>
<volume>352</volume>
<fpage>126</fpage>
<lpage>131</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 2067574?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2067574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Theriot</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tilney</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Portnoy</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The rate of
actin-based motility of intracellular <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>equals the rate of actin polymerization</article-title>
<source>Nature (Lond)</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>357</volume>
<fpage>257</fpage>
<lpage>260</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 1589024?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1589024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Theriot</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenblatt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Portnoy</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldschmidt</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Involvement of profilin in the actin-based motility of <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic>in cells and in cell-free extracts</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>76</volume>
<fpage>505</fpage>
<lpage>517</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8313471?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8313471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tilney</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>DeRosier</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tilney</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>How <italic>Listeria</italic>exploits host cell actin to form its own cytoskeleton. I. Formation of a tail and how that tail might be involved in movement</article-title>
<source>J Cell Biol</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>118</volume>
<fpage>71</fpage>
<lpage>81</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 1618908?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1618908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Iniguez-Lluhi</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilman</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprang</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The structure of the G protein heterotrimer
Gi&#945;<sub>1</sub>&#946;<sub>1</sub>&#947;<sub>2</sub>
</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>83</volume>
<fpage>1047</fpage>
<lpage>1058</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8521505?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8521505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwamatsu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Actin polymerization is
induced by the Arp2/3 protein complex at the surface of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes. </italic>
</article-title>
<source>Nature (Lond)</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>385</volume>
<fpage>265</fpage>
<lpage>269</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 9000076?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9000076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Podtelejnikov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Purification and in vivo functional analysis of the yeast Arp2/3 complex</article-title>
<source>Curr Biol</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>519</fpage>
<lpage>529</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 9210376?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9210376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Alberts</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Nucleation of microtubule assembly by a gamma-tubulin-containing ring complex</article-title>
<source>Nature
(Lond)</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>378</volume>
<fpage>578</fpage>
<lpage>583</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 8524390?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8524390</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Predicted amino acid sequences of p41-Arc, p34-Arc,
p21-Arc, p20-Arc, and p16-Arc aligned to their homologues from
diverse organisms. (<italic>A</italic>) The sequence of p41-Arc is similar to
Sop2Hs (these data are available from EMBL/GenBank/DDBJ
under accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="Y08999">Y08999</ext-link>). Bold type indicates the location of the WD repeat sequences and underlined type indicates
the location of the peptide sequences used to determine the identity of p41. (<italic>B</italic>) The sequence of p34-Arc is similar to EMBL/
GenBank/DDBJ accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="Z71650">Z71650</ext-link> from <italic>Sc.</italic> The sequence of p21-Arc is similar to accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="U19103">U19103</ext-link> from
<italic>Sc.</italic> The sequence of p20-Arc is similar to accession numbers
<ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="U21324">U21324</ext-link> from <italic>Ce</italic>, <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="Z81317">Z81317</ext-link> from <italic>Sp</italic>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="Z28013">Z28013</ext-link> from <italic>Sc.</italic> The sequence of p16-Arc is similar to accession numbers <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="U88314">U88314</ext-link> from
<italic>Ce</italic>, <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="Z69795">Z69795</ext-link> from <italic>Sp</italic>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="Z38060">Z38060</ext-link> from <italic>Sc.</italic> Underlined type indicates the location of the peptide sequences used to determine the
identity of the proteins. (<italic>C</italic>) Sequences from within p34, p21, and
p20 are similar to peptide sequences from the 35-, 18-, and 19-kD
subunits of the <italic>Ac</italic> Arp2/3 complex (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Machesky et al., 1994</xref>), respectively. <italic>Hs</italic>, <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>, <italic>Ce</italic>, <italic>C. elegans</italic>, <italic>Ac</italic>, <italic>A. castellanii</italic>,
<italic>Sc</italic>, <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, <italic>Sp</italic>, <italic>S. pombe.</italic> The sequence data for the subunits
of the human Arp2/3 complex are available from EMBL/GenBank/DDBJ under accession numbers <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AF006084">AF006084</ext-link> for p41-Arc,
<ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AF006085">AF006085</ext-link> for p34-Arc, <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AF006086">AF006086</ext-link> for p21-Arc, <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AF006087">AF006087</ext-link> for
p20-Arc, and <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AF006088">AF006088</ext-link> for p16-Arc.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB.32814f1a"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB.32814f1b"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Immunoblots of
whole cell extracts probed
with anti-Arp3, anti-p34, and
anti-p21 antibodies. The <italic>far
left</italic> lane, which shows pure
Arp2/3 complex run on a
12% SDS-PAGE gel and
stained with Coomassie
blue, illustrates the protein
composition of the complex.
The other lanes are immunoblots of: Swiss 3T3 (<italic>S</italic>) and
chick heart fibroblast (<italic>C</italic>) extracts probed with anti-Arp3 (<italic>Arp3</italic>);
HeLa (<italic>H</italic>), Swiss 3T3 (<italic>S</italic>), and chick heart fibroblast (<italic>C</italic>) extracts
probed with anti-p34 (<italic>p34</italic>); HeLa (<italic>H</italic>) and Swiss 3T3 (<italic>S</italic>) extracts
probed with anti-p21 (<italic>p21</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB.32814f2"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Localization of Arp2/3 complex subunits in <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic>&#8211;infected HeLa cells. (<italic>A</italic>) Distribution of p34-Arc and (<italic>B</italic>)
of actin in the same cell, visualized by immunofluorescence. (<italic>C</italic>)
Distribution of p21-Arc and (<italic>D</italic>) of actin in the same cell, visualized by immunofluorescence. (<italic>E</italic>) Distribution of Arp3-EGFP
and (<italic>F</italic>) distribution of actin in the same cell, visualized by staining with rhodamine-phalloidin. Bar, 10 &#956;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB.32814f3"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Localization of Arp2/3 complex subunits in Swiss 3T3
fibroblasts by indirect immunofluorescence. (<italic>A</italic>) Distribution of
Arp3, and (<italic>B</italic>) of actin in the same cell. (<italic>C</italic>) Distribution of p34-Arc, and (<italic>D</italic>) of actin in the same cell. (<italic>E</italic>) Distribution of p21-Arc and (<italic>F</italic>) of actin in the same cell. The arrowheads indicate the
position of lamellipodia. Bar, 10 &#956;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB.32814f4"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>A comparison of
the localization of Arp2/3
complex subunits in stationary (<italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>) and moving
(<italic>C&#8211;F</italic>) Swiss 3T3 fibroblasts
by indirect immunofluorescence. (<italic>A</italic>) Higher magnification view of the distribution
of p21-Arc, and (<italic>B</italic>) of actin
in a stationary fibroblast. (<italic>C</italic>)
Lower magnification view of
the distribution of p21-Arc
and (<italic>D</italic>) of actin in fibroblasts at the edge of a wound
2 h after wounding a monolayer. Cells move in the direction of the arrows, which
point towards the center of
the wound. (<italic>E</italic>) Higher magnification view of p21-Arc
and (<italic>F</italic>) of actin in a cell from
<italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>, respectively. The
arrowheads indicate the position of the lamellipodium.
Bars, 10 &#956;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB.32814f5"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Localization of
Arp2/3 complex subunits in
primary culture fibroblasts
from embryonic chick hearts
by indirect immunofluorescence. (<italic>A</italic>) Distribution of
Arp3 and (<italic>B</italic>) of actin in the
same cell. (<italic>C</italic>) Distribution of
p34-Arc and (<italic>D</italic>) of actin in
the same cell. The arrowheads indicate the position of
the lamellipodia. Bar, 10 &#956;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB.32814f6"/></fig></floats-group></article>