
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3197592</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22028799</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-08508</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025951</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Developmental Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Toxicology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic Toxicology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Influences of DMP on the Fertilization Process and Subsequent Embryogenesis of Abalone (Haliotis diversicolor supertexta) by Gametes Exposure </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">DMP Affect Abalone Embryogenesis</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Jin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Xiao-Shan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Zhong-Hua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>Ocean Science and Technology Division, Graduate School at Shenzhen, Tsinghua University, Shenzhen, People's Republic of China</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Goldstien</surname><given-names>Sharyn Jane</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Canterbury, New Zealand</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>caizh@sz.tsinghua.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: ZHC JZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: JZ XSZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: XSZ JZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: XSZ ZHC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: JZ. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e25951</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Zhou et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Di-methyl phthalate (DMP), a typical endocrine disrupting chemical (EDC), is ubiquitously distributed in aquatic environments; yet studies regarding its impact on gametes and the resulting effects on embryogenesis in marine gastropods are relatively scarce. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>In this study, the influences of DMP on the gametes and subsequent developmental process of abalone (Haliotis diversicolor supertexta, a representative marine benthic gastropod) were assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Newborn abalone eggs and sperm were exposed separately to different DMP concentrations (1, 10 or 100 ppb) for 60 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>At the end-point of exposure, the DMP-treated eggs and sperm were collected for analysis of their ultra-structures, ATPase activities and total lipid levels, and the fertilized gametes (embryos) were collected to monitor related reproductive parameters (fertilization rate, abnormal development rate and hatching success rate). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Treatment with DMP did not significantly alter the structure or total lipid content of eggs at any of the doses tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Hatching failures and morphological abnormalities were only observed with the highest dose of DMP (100 ppb). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>However, DMP exposure did suppress sperm ATPase activities and affect the morphological character of their mitochondria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>DMP-treated sperm exhibited dose-dependent decreases in fertilization efficiency, morphogenesis and hatchability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Relatively obvious toxicological effects were observed when both sperm and eggs were exposed to DMP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, RT-PCR results indicate that treatment of gametes with DMP changed the expression patterns of physiologically-regulated genes (cyp3a, 17β-HSD-11 and 17β-HSD-12) in subsequent embryogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Taken together, this study proofed that pre-fertilization exposure of abalone eggs, sperm or both to DMP adversely affects the fertilization process and subsequent embryogenesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Over the past few decades the world's aquatic environments have been severely impacted by various contaminants from industry, agriculture, urban runoff and other sources. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>These contaminants can affect all levels of biological organization, from individuals to entire ecosystems [1], [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Consequently, decreases in biomass and biodiversity have occurred [3], [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Among these contaminants, phthalate esters (PAEs) compose one of the most persistent and widespread groups of xenobiotics in the marine ecosystem [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In addition, PAEs are typical endocrine disruptors that can interfere with the hormonal metabolism, immune responses, and reproductive functions of wildlife [6], [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The high rates of PAEs production and use have raised concerns regarding its effects on aquatic species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In the last two decades, bio-resources have reportedly declined in both number and quality, affects that could be attributed to adverse effects on the reproduction and development of aquatic animals caused by PAEs contamination [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Xenobiotics primarily target marine organisms in their early life stages because these are usually more susceptible to the toxic effects than the adult forms [9], [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Thus, great concern has arisen regarding the potential adverse effects of PAEs on the early life stages of marine animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Early embryos or larvae may be affected by two main pathways: direct exposure or indirect exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>When directly exposed to phthalate substances, embryos or larvae have demonstrated reduced fertilization rates, impaired embryogenesis and altered larval morphologies [11]–[15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Indirectly exposure is another pathway by which early embryos or larvae may be damaged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Several studies in aquatic environments have demonstrated the harmful effects of phthalate on embryo survival, growth and morphology by this way in marine organisms, including clam [16], medaka [17] and sea urchin [18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Direct or indirect exposure of embryos to xenobiotic contaminants (e.g., PAEs) during development clearly causes morphological malformations and developmental dysfunction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>However, the question remains as to whether exposure of gametes to these pollutants before fertilization would result in similar developmental defects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Most aquatic organisms release eggs or sperm into their surroundings to fuse and develop as “orphans” in direct contact with the environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Gametes, directly released into seawater, are unprotected and exposed to environmental contaminants during spawning, so the possibility for contaminants to disrupt the fertilization process and subsequent developmental events is high [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, gamete-toxicity has received relatively little attention compared to investigations involving embryos or adults. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Among the PAEs, di-methyl phthalate (DMP) is one the most frequently detected plasticizer and is a relatively stable compound in the natural environment; the hydrolysis half-life is estimated to be about 20 years [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>In the field of aquatic environments, the reported concentration of DMP ranged from 0.73 to 20 µg/L (Hu et al., 2003) [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>In this study, the abalone eggs and sperm were exposed separately or in combination to di-methyl phthalate (DMP), to study the effects of this xenobiotic agent on the gametes' fertilization behavior and the subsequent embryogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="?"><plain>The questions addressed in this paper are as follows: 1) are the reproductive parameters (fertilization efficiency, morphogenesis, and hatching behavior) adversely affected when gametes are exposed to typical concentrations of DMP found in the environment; and 2) what are the potential mechanisms affecting embryogenesis? </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The gastropod (e.g., marine abalone) was chosen as the test species in our study due to its size advantage, environmental sensitivity, short life cycle and breeding characteristics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Most importantly, abalone eggs are semi-translucent and non-sticky, allowing embryonic development to be easily observed using optical microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The species used in this study was Haliotis diversicolor supertexta, an important indigenous species in China. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>During the entire experimental period, there were no significant differences between acetone and seawater groups (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>For this reason, the acetone groups were used as controls in the following experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Effects of DMP on the total lipid levels of eggs and the ATPase activities of sperm </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>At the end of the DMP exposure period, the eggs' total lipid content and the sperm's ATPase levels were determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Total lipid measurements in DMP-treated eggs ranged from 2.69–3.43% (%, dry weight), with no significant differences in total lipid content between treatment and control groups (Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0025951-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025951.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Effects of DMP exposure on total lipid levels of eggs and ATPase activities of sperm. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>(A) total lipid levels of eggs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>(B) ATPase activities of sperm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Each bar represents the mean ± SD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Data are representative of three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Significant differences (P&lt;0.05, one-way ANOVA) in total lipid levels and ATPase activities between the experimental and control groups are indicated with different letter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0025951.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>However, spermiotoxicity experiments measured a concentration-dependent decrease in ATPase activities (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>ATPase levels significantly declined in higher DMP dose groups, diminishing to 7.65 µmol Pi/mg pro/h at the 10 ppb dose (P&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The lowest ATPase activity (41.4% of the control, P&lt;0.05) was observed when 100 ppb DMP was administered. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Effects of DMP on gamete morphologies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The basic morphologies of abalone eggs and sperm are shown in Figure 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>In this study, the basic structures of eggs showed no significant changes between the control and treatment groups (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Similarly, few apparent structural abnormalities (i.e., teratosperm) were observed in control or DMP-treated sperm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0025951-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025951.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Light microscope images of an abalone sperm (A) and egg (B). </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The full-length of the sperm is approximately 45 µm, and the diameter of the egg is approximately 150 µm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0025951.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>However, TEM analyses of DMP-treated sperm revealed ultrastructural changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Normal abalone sperm have funnel-shaped heads and whip-like tails (Figure 3A, insert). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Under control conditions, the cytoplasm and organelles (e.g., mitochondria) were clearly observed in abalone sperm (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>After exposure to DMP for 60 min (see in particular the 100 ppb results), slight swelling or eccentrically placed cristae were observed in sperm mitochondria (Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0025951-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025951.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Electron microscopic analysis of the effect of DMP treatment on abalone sperm and eggs. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>A, the ultrastructure of control sperm (the arrows indicate mitochondria, the insert picture is the full TEM image of the sperm); B, the ultrastructure of DMP-treated sperm (the mitochondria swell and secund cristae are marked by dotted line arrows); C, the ultrastructure of control eggs; and D, the ultrastructure of DMP-treated eggs (arrows denote egg envelopes). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0025951.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Likewise, the eggs exhibited relatively few morphological abnormalities in the control or DMP-treated groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The egg-envelope integrities and internal structures are similar between the control and treated groups (Figure 3 C&amp;D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Fertilization rate </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The fertilization rates obtained for the T1 samples (eggs exposed to DMP) varied between 68.5% and 79.6%, with no noticeable differences between the control and treatment groups (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>However, in T2 experiments, the fertilization capabilities were significantly impaired in DMP-treated sperm with the exception of the lowest dose (1 ppb). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The percentage fertilization values (%) decreased to 43.6% in the 10 ppb treatment groups and 38.5% in the 100 ppb treatment groups (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>For the T3 samples (both eggs and sperm exposed to DMP), the fertilization efficiencies declined more dramatically, with lower fertilization rates (approximately 40%) beginning at the 10 ppb dose (P&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The lowest fertilization rate (26.6%) was observed at 100 ppb DMP dose (P&lt;0.01). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0025951-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025951.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Effects of DMP exposure on fertilization rates (%) of abalone gametes. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The percentages of fertilization in different protocols were determined by counting approximately 100–150 randomly sampled eggs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Data are means±SD of three tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Different letters denote statistically significant differences between control and treatment groups determined by one-way ANOVA (bP&lt;0.05, cP&lt;0.01). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0025951.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Embryogenesis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2d1"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>(1) Abnormal post-fertilization development rates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Post-fertilization development was disrupted to varying degrees when gametes were exposed to DMP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Several gross morphological malformations were observed, including irregular cleavages, asymmetrical splits, yolk-sac edemas, blastula developmental arrests, and monotrochal larva stage developmental malformations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Representative photographs of the abnormal embryos are shown in Figure 5. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0025951-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025951.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Effect of PAEs on morphological development of abalone embryos. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Representative malformations in abalone embryos due to exposure of gametes to DMP (taking sperm exposed to 10 ppb DMP as a example). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Arrows point to representative abnormalities for each stage, including incomplete cleavage (1), abnormal protuberances on the embryo envelope (2), dissymmetry splits (3, 4), yolk-sac edema (5, 6) and developmental arrest (7) or monotrochal larva malformation (8). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0025951.g005"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>After statistical analysis, only eggs exposed to the highest DMP concentration (100 ppb) showed an increase in the percentage of embryos with abnormal development (approximately 17.7%, Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>In contrast, sperm displayed more susceptibility to DMP poisoning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>At 8 hpf, solvent control experiments resulted in an embryo abnormality rate of approximately 12.3%, while 1, 10 and 100 ppb DMP treatment groups showed 15.3%, 19.5% and 25.3% embryo abnormality rates, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The abnormality rates increased in a concentration-dependent manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Similar results were observed when both eggs and sperm were exposed to DMP, revealing a strong positive correlation between the percentage of abnormally developing embryos and the treatment dose (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>At the highest dose, 26.7% of embryos exhibited abnormal development and the values was significant difference compared with those of the control group (P&lt;0.01). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0025951-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025951.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Effects of DMP exposure on embryo abnormality rates (%) of abalone gametes. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Values are means±SD, and different letters denote values that are significantly different (P&lt;0.05) and the columns that share the same letter are not significantly different (P&gt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0025951.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2d2"><title><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>(2) Hatch success rates of post-fertilization development </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Hatch efficiencies were measured after exposure of eggs, sperm or both to DMP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>In T1 samples (eggs exposed to DMP), compared with the controls, hatch success rates were not significantly different from controls when eggs were exposed to low (1 ppb) or medium (10 ppb) DMP concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>However, a high dose of DMP (100 ppb) resulted in a lower number of hatching-out embryos than observed under control conditions (P&lt;0.05, Figure 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Spermiotoxicity experiments (T2 groups) demonstrated a concentration-dependent decrease in hatch rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Under control conditions, the hatch success rate was approximately 75.0%, with little difference in the percentage of hatching-out embryos compared to 1 ppb DMP conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>However, the number of hatching-out embryos was dramatically lower in the 10 and 100 ppb DMP treatment groups (a 1.41-fold and 1.85-fold decrease, respectively) (P&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>A similar trend was also observed for the T3 groups with fewer embryos hatching-out successfully at higher DMP doses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>In the 100 ppb groups, more than half the embryos lost their hatching-out competence (Figure 7). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0025951-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025951.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Effects of DMP exposure on Embryo hatching rates (%) of abalone gametes. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Values are means±SD, and different letters denote values that are significantly different (P&lt;0.05) and the columns that share the same letter are not significantly different (P&gt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0025951.g007"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>DMP exposure leads to alteration in hormonal-related genes expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>To ascertain whether DMP-induced embryotoxicity was accompanied by stress dysfunction and physiological dysregulation, the genes (cyp3a, 17β-HSD-11 and 17β-HSD-12), implicated in abalone embryo detoxification and steroid regulation were measured [15], [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 8, embryo 17β-HSD-11 and 17β-HSD-12 mRNA levels were mildly suppressed in DMP-treated eggs compared to control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Exposure of abalone eggs to DMP did not result in significant changes in cyp3a during the post-fertilization development period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>A more obvious homeostasis disruption of post-fertilization development was exhibited in spermiotoxicity experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>In these experiments, in which DMP-exposed sperm fertilized unexposed eggs, the embryo mRNA levels of 17β-HSD-11 and 17β-HSD-12 decreased significantly (1.43- and 1.67-fold, respectively) compared to control levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The similar profiles were observed when both gametes were exposed to DMP before fertilization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>In these experiments, a more obvious result was observed for these genes, and mRNA levels were altered more significantly compared to results obtained from experiments in which only one gamete was exposed to DMP (Figure 8). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0025951-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025951.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Effect of DMP on reference genes expression in abalone embryos. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Expression levels of cyp3a, 17β-HSD-11 and 17β-HSD-12 after exposure of sperm, eggs or both to DMP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Each bar represents the mean±SD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>All real-time reactions were performed three times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Significant differences among the groups were indicated with different letter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0025951.g008"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Toxicological parent to progeny developmental effects, particularly non-genetic contributions to offspring ontogenesis, has received much attention in past several decades [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>In this regard, the maternal or paternal effects of xenobiotics in aquatic animals have been widely investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The results have demonstrated that exposure of the mother or father to contaminants at environmentally relevant levels can cause gonad growth retardation, fertilization dysfunction, embryonic development defects, and transmissible damages to the offspring [24]–[30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>However, studies on gametes are relatively scarce. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Because external fertilizers (e.g., broadcast spawners) release their gametes freely into the environment, these organisms should be more vulnerable to fertilization failure as a result of point-of-contact chemical exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Thus, it is important to understand the effects of xenobiotics on gametes and subsequent reproductive processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The present study investigates the toxicity effects of DMP on germ cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, this study is the first to expose abalone gametes to DMP in order to assess the effects on the fertilization process and subsequent embryo development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The present study reveals no significant adverse effects on fertilization efficiency following exposure of eggs to DMP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>This finding is consistent with earlier studies on other marine invertebrates, in which acute exposure of eggs to contaminants had no effect on fertilization abilities [31], [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The eggs showed no significant differences between the experimental and control groups with regard to ultrastructure and total lipid levels (Figure 1A; Figure 3 C&amp;D), indicating that DMP exposure did not obviously affect the fundamental structure of the egg-envelope or the lipid content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>From these results, we speculate that, at least in the case of short-term or low-dose exposure, egg exposure to DMP alone cannot account for the fertilization defects observed in the wild [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The slight decline in fertilization rates observed in the highest-dose group is possibly due to the accumulation of high DMP concentrations in the egg envelope surfaces and micropyle blockage affecting sperm/egg fusion [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>However, further research is needed to evaluate the barrier actions of DMP on egg envelope micropores. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Sperm were more sensitive than eggs to DMP exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>DMP exerted a potent concentration-dependent inhibitory effect on sperm fertilization ability (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>These toxicological results indicate that short-term exposure to DMP may reduce sperm function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Previous literatures have also reported the influences of xenobiotic pollutants on sperm functions and fertilization processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The related mechanisms include reducing sperm swimming speed [33], damaging sperm DNA structure [8], disrupting flagellum Ca2+ signaling [19] and increasing the probability of aneuploid sperm [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we observed the declines of ATPase activity on sperm, which indicate that DMP-treated sperm have lower energy at the time of fertilization than control sperm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>As ATPase is responsible for releasing ATP (the enzymatic contents), and ATP aids sperm penetrating into the eggs [36], suppressed ATPase activity may decrease the energy for propelling the sperm to the egg, which eventually results in a diminution of the fertilization ratio. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The impaired fertilization ability of DMP-treated abalone sperm may also be explained by associated ultrastructural changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 3B, DMP caused slight mitochondrial swelling and distraction of cristae in sperm midpieces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The deformation of mitochondria may be attributed to DMP interaction with mitochondrial membrane proteins, resulting in increased membrane permeability to cations and anions [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Evidence suggests that membrane damage may correlate with altered sperm function and decrease fertility [38], [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results suggest that DMP exposure influences the sperm energy status and ultrastructure, providing possible mechanisms leading to the fertilization impairment of abalone gametes during the early phase of the fertilization process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>In addition to impacting the fertilization process, acute exposure of gametes to DMP disrupted abalone embryogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In T1 test groups (exposure of eggs), the development process was not significantly affected by low or medium concentrations of DMP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>One possible reason for this result is that the egg envelope acts as a protective layer, resisting the intrusion of DMP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, a hatching-out delay appeared at the highest dose of DMP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>High concentrations of xenobiotic may interfere with permeability of the outer membrane of egg cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Under these circumstances, fertilized eggs would suffer metabolic deactivation, ultimately affecting the morphogenesis or hatching behavior [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Significant increases in the frequencies of developmental abnormalities and hatch defects were observed in T2 compared to T1 experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Because they exhibit a limited capacity for DNA repair and antioxidant defense [41], sperm are potentially more susceptible to DMP-induced damage than oocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>In addition, we speculated that after DMP exposure, the foreign xenobiotic substance may accumulate in the sperm body, making the sperm cell act as a toxicity vector that transfers DMP into eggs, thereby forming DMP-contaminated embryos (fertilized eggs) and influenced embryonic development process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Experiments designed to detect DMP levels in sperm cells are presently underway in our laboratory to further test this hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>During the fertilization process, each gamete provides components and signals that are essential to normal embryonic development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>In many invertebrates, eggs have large stores of maternal mRNA and proteins synthesized before fertilization [42], while the sperm supplies factors that initiate the developmental program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Exposure of gametes to environmental toxicants may lead to alteration of these essential components, causing fertilization failure and/or defective development [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Among these components, the cytochrome P450 (CYP450) isoenzyme is particularly important. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>In early stages, CYP450 is responsible for the degradation of contaminants and affects cell differentiation and ontogenesis [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Previous studies report cyp3a over-expression in zebrafish and medaka embryos after exposure to TBT or TPT [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>However, the present results show no significant difference in cyp3a expression between experimental and control groups, perhaps due to the use of different exposure substances and durations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>In vertebrate, sex steroid hormones play an important role in early embryo development, including regulating differentiation, development and homeostasis [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Steroid hormones are synthesized from cholesterol through the action of steroidgenic enzymes, which are regulated primarily at the transcriptional level [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The enzymes 17β-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenases (17β-HSDs) play a key role in the cascade of steroidogenesis and the activy of these enzymes used as indicator of steroid biosynthesis [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown that these enzymes are sensitive to adverse environmental conditions during embryogenesis in various vertebrate animals, including rats [48], frog [49], and fish [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>In this study, the abnormal expression of types 11 and 12 17β-HSD mRNA was observed after abalone (an invertebrate species) gamete exposed by DMP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Despite the lack of data on steroids receptors and functional studies during embryogenesis in invertebrate, we may also hypothesize a similar role of 17β-HSD during mollusks embryonic development process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>We cannot totally rule out a role of 17β-HSD in regulating steroid biosynthesis during abalone embryo development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>In virtually, the biological function of 17β-HSD-11 [submitted manuscript] and 17β-HSD-12 [50] were verified by transiently transfecting their ORF in HEK-293 cells, which provided further support that abalone 17β-HSD may participate steroid hormone metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Besides, the physiological function of 17β-HSD involved in steroidogenesis or the cascade process has also been demonstrated in sea urchin [51], mussel [52], and dogwhelk [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Taken together, 17β-HSD may be a biomarker, at least in part, for abalone embryo developmental impairment and hatching dysfunction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>However, this cannot be extended to all mollusks as 17β-HSD receptors and binding competence are not yet fully understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Further investigations including mRNA expression and protein activity measurements are thus required to conclude on the exact physiological role(s) of these 17β hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase enzymes in steroidogenesis function during mollusks embryogenesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Clearly acute DMP exposure of abalone eggs or sperm adversely affects fertilization efficiency and subsequent embryogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Sperm were more sensitive to DMP than eggs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The results suggest that compromised sperm energy status contribute to fertilization defects in germ cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Disruption of the physiological performance of abalone embryos is a possible mechanism leading to phenotypic changes of embryogenesis, such as developmental abnormalities and decreased hatchability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>In the next step, multiple hormone-regulated genes and their interactive, simultaneous effects on morphology, physiology, and development will be examined to better understand the mechanisms of early-life-stage toxicity of plastic contaminants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Chemicals and reagents </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>DMP was obtained from Shenggong, Co., Ltd. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>(Shanghai, China, purity ≥97%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Stock solutions were prepared in acetone (Dingguo, Beijing, China), which was also used as the vehicle control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The final acetone concentrations in each treatment were the same (0.005%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Trizol, PCR reagents and supplements were obtained from Sigma (Beijing, China), Invitrogen (USA) or TaKaRa Co., Ltd. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>(Dalian, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>All other reagents were of analytical grade. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Animals and ethics statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>The abalones (two years old, average shell length 7.0±0.8 cm) were obtained from a local hatchery, Kinghaili Aquaculture Co., Ltd (Longgan District, Shenzhen city, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Abalone maturation was confirmed by gonad inspection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Fully mature males exhibited yellowish-white spermaries, whereas mature females had dark-violet ovaries (Figure 9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Gonad-outstanding individuals were selected and used in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0025951-g009" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025951.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>The experimental animals in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>A, the fully-mature abalone (shell-length near 7 cm); B, the male individual (note the yellowish-white spermary); and C, the female individual (note the dark-violet ovary). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0025951.g009"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed in compliance with the Chinese animal protection law. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The care and use of laboratory animals was approved and supervised by the Tsinghua University Animal Care and Use Committee, complying with the rules of Regulations for the Administration of Affairs Concerning Experimental Animals (Tsinghua University local representative of the animal welfare agency, approved by the State Council of P.R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The individual experiments are approved by Tsinghua University Home office inspectors (Home Office Project licenses: CGSZ10-4755). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Gametes' preparation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Female and male abalones were kept in separate rectangular tanks containing aerated sand-filtered seawater (SFS), in which they were held for up to 24 h prior to experimental treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Culture conditions were as follows: water temperature 24±2°C, salinity 30±2‰, pH 8.0±0.2, and dissolved oxygen no less than 6.0 mg/L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Abalones (♂∶♀≈1∶3) were induced to spawn in ultraviolet-radiated seawater [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Before spawning, the animals were washed several times with SFS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The newborn sperm were placed in a sperm/water mixture in a clean container (0.5 L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The newborn eggs were filtered through a 100 µm mesh nylon net, gently washed two times with SFS and re-suspended as an eggs/water mixture in 0.5 L clean seawater. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The gametes (eggs and sperm) were then used for the following experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Gametes production, artificial fertilization and embryo maintenance followed the Yang and Yan method (2006) [55]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Exposure experiments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The following three experimental designs (trials) were carried out in this study: eggs exposed to DMP but sperm unexposed (T1); sperm exposed but eggs unexposed (T2), and both sperm and eggs exposed (T3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>The abalone eggs in the T1 group were exposed to DMP at three different concentrations (1, 10 or 100 ppb) for 60 min, followed by fertilization with unexposed sperm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The abalone sperm in the T2 group were exposed to DMP at the same doses for 60 minutes and then used to fertilize unexposed eggs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>In the T3 group, both sperm and eggs were exposed to DMP using the same protocol and were then used to fertilize each other. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>In all experimental groups, the fertilized eggs (embryos) were developed in clean seawater. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The same volume of acetone solvent was used as the control, and SFS was used as the blank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Three replicates were conducted for all treatments and controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Total lipid levels of eggs and ATPase activities of sperm </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Samples of exposed eggs (after 60 min) were collected and used for total lipid content analyses performed according to the methods of Floch et al. (1957) [56]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Sperm samples for ATPase enzyme assays were obtained by homogenizing the sperm cells as described by Levine et al. (1978) [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>ATPase activities were measured using the ATPase colorimetric assay kit based on its instructions (Jiancheng Co., Ltd., Nanjing, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Briefly, 20 µl samples were added to 250 µl ATPase reaction mixtures and incubated for 30 min at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Rates of ATP hydrolysis were determined to be linear over this period of time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Unless otherwise indicated, all ATPase assays were performed in this manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>For each measurement, the extent of ATP hydrolysis was determined by measuring the amount of inorganic phosphate using the colorimetric procedure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>The protein concentration was determined using the Bradford (1976) method [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>One unit of enzyme activity is defined as the amount of enzyme resulting in a hydrolysis rate equal to 1 µmol Pi/mg pro/h. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Morphology analysis of sperm and eggs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The basic sperm morphologies were evaluated by light microscopy (Nikon, Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Sperm were fixed with 2.5% buffered glutaraldehyde. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Approximately 200–300 sperm per sample were analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Basic morphology analyses focused on detecting whether the existence or absence of teratosperm (e.g., angulated sperm or sperm suffering breakage). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>In addition to basic morphology analyses, sperm from the control groups and the DMP-treated groups were processed utilizing transmission electron microscopic (TEM) analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Briefly, samples were fixed with 2.5% glutaraldehyde in 0.1 M phosphate buffer, then washed in 0.1 M cacodylate buffer and postfixed with 1% osmium tetroxide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, the samples were washed with buffer, dehydrated, and embedded in Epon 812. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Ultrathin sections (70 to 90 nm thick) were obtained using an ultramicrotome (Lecia EM UC6, Germany) and were mounted on 150-mesh copper grids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Imaging was performed with an H-7650 transmission electron microscope (HITACHI, Japan) and a Gatan 832 CCD camera. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Egg morphologies were detected utilizing similar methods. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Fertilization rate </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>The aim of this set of experiments was to assess the fertilizing ability of gametes that had been exposed to varying DMP concentrations, not to assess how fertilization proceeds in DMP-polluted water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Therefore, prior to fertilization trials, aqueous DMP in the sperm/water (or eggs/water) mixtures required removal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, in T1 samples, the DMP-treated eggs were filtered through a 100-µm-mesh nylon net, then gently washed two times with filtered seawater before being fertilized with non-DMP-treated sperm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>In T2 samples, the DMP-treated sperm were placed in 1.5 mL Eppendorf tubes and centrifuged at low-speed for a few minutes, forming a pellet of sperm at the bottom of the tube. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>A 900 µl aliquot of the supernatant was decanted and replaced with filtered seawater. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>The resulting sperm/water solution was then used to fertilize non-DMP-treated eggs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Centrifuging the sperm/water solution did not adversely affect sperm viability, as demonstrated by a preliminary study in which centrifuged sperm exhibited motility comparable to non-centrifuged sperm and were able to successfully fertilize eggs [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The same protocol was used for T3 samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Fertilization trials were conducted by mixing sperm with eggs in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Sperm and eggs were allowed to interact in an aerated vial for 30 min, at which time 0.5 mL of buffered glutaraldehyde was added to arrest fertilization and preserve developing fertilized eggs (embryos). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Fertilization rates were determined by counting the ratio of fertilized/total eggs from a randomly selected sub-sample of at least 100 eggs (range 100–150). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Fertilized eggs exhibiting characteristic polar bodies are clearly visible under 200×magnification. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Development parameters in embryogenesis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Abnormality rate (%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>For these experiments, a multi-cell stage was adopted to determine the cleavage blocks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>The blastula stage (3 hours post fertilization (hpf)) was the starting point for detecting abnormalities, and the monotrochal larva stage (8 hpf, ready to hatch) was the end point for abnormal rates determination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Embryo samples were collected randomly, fixed with formalin, and then observed under a light microscope (Nikon, Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Each treatment was repeated three times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>For each treatment, 300 embryos (100×3 replicates) were used to measure the abnormality rate, which was calculated according to the formula below: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Hatching success rate (%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Each hatching rate was calculated at the end of the hatching-out stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>After the monotrochal larva stage (about 9 hpf), the embryo hatches and becomes a swimming veliger larva. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Embryos that exhibited developmental arrest, hatch delays or did not hatch were recorded as hatching failures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>For each treatment, 300 embryos (100×3 replicates) were chosen to measure the hatching success rate, which was calculated as follows: </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Real-time quantitative PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>At 8 hpf, samples from each treatment group were collected for reference genes' expression analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Three physiologically-related genes, cyp3a, 17β-HSD-11 and 17β-HSD-12, were selected to assess the effects of DMP on the development of abalone embryos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>The completed cDNA sequences of cyp3a, 17β-HSD-11 and 17β-HSD-12 were obtained by homology cloning in our previous work. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>The full-length cDNA sequence was submitted to GenBank, and the accession numbers were GU984784, HQ699520 and GU984783, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The gene-specific primers for cyp3a, 17β-HSD-11, 17β-HSD-12 and the internal control β-actin (accession number AAS00498) were used to amplify amplicons specific for H. diversicolor supertexta. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>The sequences of primers and the length of amplicons were shown in table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The fluorescent real-time quantitative PCR amplifications were performed according to previously described methods [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Amplification products were subjected to melting curve analysis to confirm that a single PCR product had been amplified and detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Each sample was analyzed three times to confirm reproducibility. β-actin transcript levels were used to normalize the results, and negative control reactions, in which template cDNA was omitted, were included for every primer set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Relative amounts of target genes and β-actin RNA in all cDNAs were calculated from a standard curve. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>To maintain consistency, the baseline was determined automatically using SDS software (V.1.3.0, ABI, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Target mRNA levels were expressed in relative levels (target mRNA/β-actin-RNA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0025951-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025951.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Primer sequences for real-time quantitative RT-PCR analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0025951-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0025951.t001"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>CYP3a: Cytochrome P450, family 3, subfamily A; </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>17β-HSD-11: 17β-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenases 11; </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>17β-HSD-12: 17β-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenases 12. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s4j"><title><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Data related to developmental parameters and physiological features were analyzed by one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) accompanied by Tukey's multiple comparison analysis using SPSS 11.0 software (USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>The qRT-PCR data analyses were executed by comparative CT method (2−ΔΔCT method) using SDS software V1.3.0 (ABI, USA) [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>All values are presented as mean ± SD, with P&lt;0.05 considered statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Funding: This study was supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (41106087), the PhD Start-up Fund of the Natural Science Foundation of Guangdong Province, China (10451805702004177), the International Cooperative Project of the SZSITIC Commission of Shenzhen (ZYA200903260036A), the Open Fund of the Key Laboratory of Marine Environmental Science and Engineering, SOA (MESE-2010-02), and the Open Fund of the Laboratory of Marine Ecosystem and Biogeochemistry, SOA (LMEB201105). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0025951-Fent1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>1 FentK 2004 Ecotoxicological effects at contaminated sites. Toxicology 205 223 240 15464632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Schwarzenbach1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>2 SchwarzenbachRPEscherBIFennerKHofstetterTBJohnsonCA 2006 The challenge of micropollutants in aquatic systems. Science 313 1072 1077 16931750 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-FattaKassinos1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>3 Fatta-KassinosDKalavrouziotisIKKoukoulakisPHVasquezMI 2011 The risks associated with wastewater reuse and xenobiotics in the agroecological environment. Sci Total Environ 409 19 3555 3563 20435343 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Zhou1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>4 ZhouJCaiZHZhuXS 2010 Are endocrine disruptors among the causes of the deterioration of aquatic biodiversity? Integra Environl Assess Manag 6 3 492 498  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Mackintosh1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>5 MackintoshCEMaldonadoJAIkonomouMGGobasFA 2006 Sorption of phthalate esters and PCBs in a marine ecosystem. Environ Sci Technol 40 3481 3488 16786683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Imai1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>6 ImaiYKondoAIizukaHMaruyamaTKurohaneK 2006 Effects of phthalate esters on the sensitization phase of contact hypersensitivity induced by fluorescein isothiocyanate. Clin Exp Allergy 3 1462 1468  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Oehlmann1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>7 OehlmannJSchulteOUKloasWJagnytschOLutzI 2009 A critical analysis of the biological impacts of plasticizers on wildlife. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci 364 2047 2062 19528055 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Lyche1"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>8 LycheJLGutlebACBergmanAEriksenGSMurkAJ 2009 Reproductive and developmental toxicity of phthalates. J Toxicol Environ Health B Crit Rev 12 225 249 20183522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-His1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>9 HisEBeirasRSeamanMNL 1999 The assessment of marine pollution bioassays with bivalve embryos and larvae. Adv Mar Biol 37 1 178  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Hamdoun1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>10 HamdounAEpelD 2007 Embryo stability and vulnerability in an always changing world. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 104 1745 1750 17264211 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Shioda1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>11 ShiodaTWakabayashiM 2000 Effect of certain chemicals on the reproduction of medaka (Oryzias latipes). Chemosphere 40 239 243 10665413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Wilson1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>12 WilsonJTDixonDRDixonLR 2002 Numerical chromosomal aberrations in the early life-history stages of a marine tubeworm, Pomatoceros lamarckii (Polychaeta: Serpulidae). Aquat Toxicol 59 163 175 12127734 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-ForgetLeray1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>13 Forget-LerayJLandriauIMinierCLeboulengerF 2005 Impact of endocrine toxicants on survival, development, and reproduction of the estuarine copepod Eurytemora affinis (Poppe). Ecotoxicol Environ Saf 60 288 294 15590006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-UrenWebster1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>14 Uren-WebsterTMLewisCFilbyALPaullGCSantosEM 2010 Mechanisms of toxicity of di(2-ethylhexyl) phthalate on the reproductive health of male zebrafish. Aquat Toxicol 99 360 369 20561692 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Zhou2"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>15 ZhouJCaiZHXingKZ 2011 Potential mechanisms of phthalate ester embryotoxicity in the abalone Haliotis diversicolor supertexta. Environ Pollut 159 5 1114 22 21377254 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Jiang1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>16 JiangHLiuMGouHY 2008 Effects of DOP-phthalate on the embryonic development of the clam. J Toxicol (in Chinese) 2 48 51  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Patyna1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>17 PatynaPJBrownRPDaviRALetinskiDJThomasPE 2006 Hazard evaluation of diisononyl phthalate and diisodecyl phthalate in a Japanese medaka multigenerational assay. Ecotoxicol Environ Saf 65 36 47 16029893 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Song1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>18 SongXLGeJDuW 2007 DAP inhibited the development of sea urchin embryos by maternal transfer. Fish Sci (in Chinese) 6 34 37  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Lewis1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>19 LewisCGallowayT 2010 Sperm toxicity and the reproductive ecology of marine invertebrates. Integr Environ Assess Manag 6 188 190 20821682 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Staples1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>20 StaplesCAPetersonDRParkertonTFAdamsWJ 1997 The environmental fate of phthalate esters: a literature review. Chemosphere 35 667 749  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Hu1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>21 HuXYZhangKRSunJHWuDS 2003 The review of phathalic acid esters (PAEs) pollution in China (in Chinese). Chinese J Health Lab Technol 13 1 9 14  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Zanette1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>22 ZanetteJGoldstoneJVBainyACDStegemanJJ 2010 Identification of CYP genes in Mytilus (mussel) and Crassostrea (oyster) species: first approach to the full complement of cytochrome P450 genes in bivalves. Mar Environ Res 69 Supplemental, S1 S3  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Cripe1"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>23 CripeGMHemmerBLRaimondoSGoodmanLRKulawDH 2010 Exposure of three generations of the estuarine sheepshead minnow (Cyprinodon variegatus) to the androgen, 17β-trenbolone: Effects on survival, development, and reproduction. Environ Toxicol Chem 29 2079 2087 20821666 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Westerlund1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>24 WesterlundLBillssonKAnderssonPLKysklindMOlssonPE 1999 Early life-stage mortality in zebrafish (Danio rerio) following maternal exposure to polychlorinated biphenyls and estrogen. Environ Toxicol Chem 19 1582 1588  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Nye1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>25 NyeJADavisDDMillerTJ 2007 The effect of maternal exposure to contaminated sediment on the growth and condition of larval Fundulus heteroclitus. Aquat Toxicol 82 242 250 17433459 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Ostrach1"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>26 OstrachDJLow-MarchelliJMEderKJWhitemanSJZinklJG 2008 Maternal transfer of xenobiotics and effects on larval stripped bass in the San Francisco estuary. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 105 19354 19359 19033204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Schultz1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>27 SchultzIRBrownKHNaglerJJ 2008 Effects of paternal exposure to trenbolone and the brominated flame retardant BDE-47 on fertility in rainbow trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss). Mar Environ Res 66 47 49 18397801 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Lewis2"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>28 LewisCGallowayT 2009 Reproductive consequences of paternal genotoxin exposure in marine invertebrates. Environ Sci Technol 43 928 933 19245038 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Soares1"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>29 SoaresJCoimbraAMReisHMAMonteiroNMVieiraMN 2009 Disruption of zebrafish (Danio rerio) embryonic development after full life-cycle parental exposure to low levels of ethinylestradiol. Aquat Toxicol 95 330 338 19747739 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Aluru1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>30 AluruNLeatherlandJFVijayanMM 2010 Bisphenol A in oocytes leads to growth suppression and altered stress performance in juvenile rainbow trout. PLoS One 5 5 e10741 20505776 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Eyster1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>31 EysterLSMorseMP 1984 Development of the surf clam (Spisula solidissima) following exposure of gametes, embryos, and larvae to silver. Arch Environ Contam Toxicol 13 641 646  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Hollows1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>32 HollowsCFJohnstonELMarshallDJ 2007 Copper reduces fertilization success and exacerbates Allee effects in the field. MEPS 333 51 60  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Mwatibo1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>33 MwatiboJMGreenJD 1997 Effects of methoxychlor pre-exposure on sea urchin gametes. Bull Environ Contam Toxicol 58 589 595 9060377 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Schatten1"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>34 SchattenGP 2006 Current topics in developmental biology Academic Press  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Brown1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>35 BrownKHSchultzIRCloudJGNaglerJJ 2008 Aneuploid sperm formation in rainbow trout exposed to the environmental estrogen 17α-ethynylestradiol. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 105 19786 19791 19066213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Wang1"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>36 WangKHYueHPGaoLL 2001 The role of ATPase in human sperm motility. Repro Health (in Chinese) 2 56 58  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Melnick1"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>37 MelnickRCSchillerCM 1982 Mitochondrial toxicity of phthalate esters. Environ Health Perspect 45 51 56 7140696 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Akbarsha1"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>38 AkbarshaMALathaPNMurugaianP 2000 Retention of cytoplasmic droplet by rat cauda epididymal spermatozoa after treatment with cytotoxic and xenobiotic agents. J Reprod Fertil 120 385 390 11058454 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Favret1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>39 FavretKPLynnJW 2010 Flow-cytometric analyses of viability biomarkers in pesticide-exposed sperm of three aquatic invertebrates. Arch Environ Contam Toxicol 58 973 984 19876686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Raloff1"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>40 RaloffJ 2011 PCBs may impair fertility: study finds reduced embryo implantation in women with high levels of banned chemical. ScienceNews website. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencenews.org/view/generic/id/70427/title/PCBs_may_impair_fertility">http://www.sciencenews.org/view/generic/id/70427/title/PCBs_may_impair_fertility</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2011 Feb 28  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Aitken1"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>41 AitkenRJKoopmanPLewisSE 2004 Seeds of concern. Nature 43 48 52  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Davidson1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>42 DavidsonEH 1986 Gene activity in early development, 3rd ed Academic Press  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Ioannides1"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>43 IoannidesC 2008 Cytochromes P450: role in the metabolism and toxicity of drugs and other xenobiotics. Royal Society of Chemistry Press  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Spitsbergen1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>44 SpitsbergenJMKentML 2003 The state of art of the zebrafish model foe toxicology and toxicologic pathology research-advantages and current limitations. Toxicol Pathol 31 suppl 62 87 12597434 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Lafont1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>45 LafontRMathieuM 2007 Steriods in aquatic invertebrates. Ecotoxicology 16 109 130 17238002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Hum1"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>46 HumDWMillerWL 1993 Transcriptional regulation of human genes for steroidogenic enzymes. Clinical Chem 39 333 340 8432024 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Hinshelwood1"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>47 HinshelwoodMMDemter-ArlottoMMeansGDSimpsonER 1994 Expression of genes encoding steroidogenic enzymes in the ovary. FindlayJK Molecular Biology of the Female Reproductive System Academic Press, London 129 145  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Pushpalatha1"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>48 PushpalathaTReddyPRReddyPS 2003 Effect of prenatal exposure to hydroxyprogesterone on steroidogenic enzymes in male rats. Naturwissenschaften 90 1 40 43 12545243 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Osvaldo1"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>49 OsvaldoFLucreciaCJorgeH 2004 Estradiol uptake, toxicity, metabolism, and adverse effects on cadmium-treated amphibian embryos. Environ Health Perspect 112 862 866 15175173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Zhou3"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>50 ZhouJGaoYFLiLZaiHNTanSJ 2011 Identification and functional characterization of a putative 17β-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase 12 in abalone (Haliotis diversicolor supertexta). Mol Cell Biochem 354 1–2 123 33 21479786 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Roepke1"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>51 RoepkeTAChangESCherrGN 2006 Maternal exposure to estradiol and endocrine disrupting compounds alters the sensitivity of sea urchin embryos and the expression of an orphan steroid receptor. J Exp Zool A Comp Exp Biol 305 10 830 841 16823834 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Janer1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>52 JanerGLavadoRThibautRPorteC 2005 Effects of 17beta-estradiol exposure in the mussel Mytilus galloprovincialis: a possible regulating role for steroid acyltransferases. Aquat Toxicol 75 1 32 42.47 16083976 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Castro1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>53 CastroLFCLimaDMachadoARochaEReis-HenriquesMA 2008 Molecular characterization of 17β-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase type 12 in the neogastropod Nucella lapillus. CECE 2008, 24th Conference of European Comparative Endocrinologists, September 2–6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Genoa, Italy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ciimar.up.pt/letox/images/CECE2008.pdf">http://www.ciimar.up.pt/letox/images/CECE2008.pdf</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2008 Sep 6  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Uki1"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>54 UkiNKikuchiS 1982 Technical study on artificial spawning of abalone, genus Haliotis: VIII. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Characteristics of spawning behavior of Haliotis discus hannai induced by ultraviolet irradiation stimulus. Bull Tohoku Reg Fish Res Lab 44 83 86  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Yang1"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>55 YangAGYanJP 2006 Hatchery and seed production trials of abalone and oyster (In Chinese). Published by Chinese Agriculture and Technology Publisher  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Folch1"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>56 FolchJLeesMSloane-StanleyGH 1957 A simple method for isolation and purification of total lipids from animal tissues. J Biological Chem 226 497 509  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Levine1"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>57 LevineAEWalshKAFodorEJB 1978 Evidence of an acrosin-like enzyme in sea urchin sperm. Dev Biol 63 299 306 416981 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Bradford1"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>58 BradfordMM 1976 A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye binding. Anal Biochem 72 248 254 942051 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Earnshow1"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>59 EarnshowMJWilsonSAkberaliHBButlerRDMarriottKRM 1986 Theaction of heavy metals on the gametes of the marine mussel, Mytilus edulis (L.) III. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>The effect of applied copper and zinc on sperm motility in relation to ultrastructural damage and intercellular metal localization. Mar Environ Res 20 261 278  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025951-Livak1"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>60 LivakKJSchmittgenTD 2001 Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(−Delta Delta C(T)) Method. Methods 25 402 408 11846609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
