
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plospath</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Pathogens</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7366</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7374</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3257305</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22253593</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PPATHOGENS-D-11-00168</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002445</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunity</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Model Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Models</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The Circadian Clock Protein Timeless Regulates Phagocytosis of Bacteria in Drosophila </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Phagocytosis Is Circadian-Regulated</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>Elizabeth F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>Ben O.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ayres</surname><given-names>Janelle S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">
<sup>¤a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>Linh N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ziauddin</surname><given-names>Junaid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shirasu-Hiza</surname><given-names>Mimi M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn2">
<sup>¤b</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Neurobiology and Behavior, Columbia University Medical School, New York, New York, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Genetics and Development, Columbia University Medical School, New York, New York, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Stanford University Medical School, Stanford, California, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Wessels</surname><given-names>Michael R.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Children's Hospital Boston, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>ms4095@columbia.edu</email></corresp><fn id="fn1" fn-type="current-aff"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>¤a: Current address: Department of Cell and Molecular Biology, University of California Berkeley, Berkeley, California, United States of America. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="fn2" fn-type="current-aff"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>¤b: Current address: Department of Genetics and Development, Columbia University Medical School, New York, New York, United States of America. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: MMSH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: MMSH JSA LNP JZ EFS BOF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: MMSH EFS BOF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MMSH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: MMSH EFS BOF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e1002445</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>11</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Stone et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Survival of bacterial infection is the result of complex host-pathogen interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>An often-overlooked aspect of these interactions is the circadian state of the host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Previously, we demonstrated that Drosophila mutants lacking the circadian regulatory proteins Timeless (Tim) and Period (Per) are sensitive to infection by S. pneumoniae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Sensitivity to infection can be mediated either by changes in resistance (control of microbial load) or tolerance (endurance of the pathogenic effects of infection). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Here we show that Tim regulates resistance against both S. pneumoniae and S. marcescens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>We set out to characterize and identify the underlying mechanism of resistance that is circadian-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Using S. pneumoniae, we found that resistance oscillates daily in adult wild-type flies and that these oscillations are absent in Tim mutants. Drosophila have at least three main resistance mechanisms to kill high levels of bacteria in their hemolymph: melanization, antimicrobial peptides, and phagocytosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>We found that melanization is not circadian-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>We further found that basal levels of AMP gene expression exhibit time-of-day oscillations but that these are Tim-independent; moreover, infection-induced AMP gene expression is not circadian-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>We then show that phagocytosis is circadian-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Wild-type flies exhibit up-regulated phagocytic activity at night; Tim mutants have normal phagocytic activity during the day but lack this night-time peak. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Tim appears to regulate an upstream event in phagocytosis, such as bacterial recognition or activation of phagocytic hemocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, inhibition of phagocytosis in wild type flies results in survival kinetics similar to Tim mutants after infection with S. pneumoniae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results suggest that loss of circadian oscillation of a specific immune function (phagocytosis) can have significant effects on long-term survival of infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Author Summary </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Circadian rhythms, or daily oscillations in physiological functions, are nearly ubiquitous among animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Though immune parameters are known to vary with time of day, circadian regulation of the immune system is not well understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Studies of circadian biology and innate immunity are well established in the genetically tractable model organism, the fruit fly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>We use this model to investigate the mechanisms underlying circadian-regulated immunity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>We and others have found that flies infected at different times of day exhibit different mean survival times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>There are three main components of fly immune defense against bacterial pathogens: antimicrobial peptide synthesis, reactive oxygen species generation, and phagocytosis, or the ingestion of microbes by host immune cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Of these three, we found that only the phagocytic activity of host immune cells is circadian-regulated and peaks at night, during the rest phase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>This night-time peak of phagocytosis correlates with the time of day of maximal resistance to infection by the bacteria Streptococcus pneumoniae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Mutants that lack circadian regulation also lack this night-time peak in phagocytosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of phagocytosis sensitized wild type flies to infection but did not further sensitize circadian mutants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that this night-time peak in immune system function has significant effects on survival of infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Survival of bacterial infection is the result of complex host-pathogen interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>An often-overlooked aspect of these interactions is the circadian state of the host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Most metazoans undergo daily, dynamic changes in their physiology that are regulated by well-characterized circadian machinery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>At its core, the circadian clock is composed of four transcriptional regulators paired as two distinct heterodimers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>In Drosophila, Period and Timeless form one heterodimer and Clock and Cycle form the other. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>These two heterodimers engage in an autoregulatory negative feedback loop that causes circadian oscillations in the expression levels of target genes [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Microarray analyses of different vertebrate tissues, such as heart, liver, or spleen-derived macrophages, have shown that approximately 5–10% of total gene expression in each tissue is circadian-regulated [2], [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>These oscillations in transcription are thought to underlie circadian changes in the organism's physiology and behavior. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Reflecting the pervasiveness of circadian regulation, the Drosophila circadian mutants Timeless (Tim) and Period (Per) have pleiotropic phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>They exhibit loss of circadian rhythms in locomotor activity, eclosion, male courtship, and oxidative stress response [4], [5], [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>These circadian mutants are also sensitive to infection by at least two bacterial pathogens and resistant to infection by another [7], [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The circadian-regulated mechanisms underlying these changes in immunity were not known. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Two types of mechanisms can affect survival after infection: resistance and tolerance [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Resistance mechanisms control microbial growth, while tolerance mechanisms allow the host to endure the pathogenic effects of infection, including the host's response to infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>In Drosophila, known resistance mechanisms to control microbial growth in the hemolymph include antimicrobial peptide synthesis, reactive oxygen species generation, and phagocytosis by immune cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Previously, microarray analysis comparing wild type and circadian mutants suggested that expression of immune signaling molecules that induce resistance mechanisms such as Imd (Immune deficient) may be circadian-regulated [10], [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Here we test the hypothesis that circadian mutants are sensitive to infection due to changes in mechanisms of resistance and investigate specific resistance mechanisms for circadian regulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>It has been recently shown that in mice, many immune cell functions, such as cytokine secretion by macrophages and natural killer (NK) cells, undergo oscillatory time-of-day variation [3], [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Phagocytosis by immune cells such as macrophages and neutrophils has been reported to change with time of day, though it is not clear if this oscillation is diurnal (due to photoperiod) or circadian (regulated by circadian proteins) [13], [14], [15], [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Phagocytosis of photoreceptors by pigment cells in the vertebrate retina has also been shown to be circadian-regulated [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Thus we further hypothesized that phagocytosis of bacteria by immune cells in Drosophila is also circadian-regulated and that decreased phagocytic activity may significantly contribute to the sensitivity of circadian mutants to certain types of bacterial infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Results/Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Circadian immune phenotypes are pathogen-specific </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The fly immune response to infection is highly complex and pathogen-specific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Previously, we showed that Timeless (Tim) null mutants die more quickly than wild-type flies when infected with S. pneumoniae [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Another group showed that Tim mutants die less quickly than wild-type flies when infected with P. aeruginosa, suggesting a complex immune phenotype that is pathogen-specific [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>To further understand the immune phenotype of Tim mutants, we infected Tim mutants with three other pathogenic bacteria (S. marcescens, B. cepacia, and S. typhimurium). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>We compared Tim mutant survival time with wild-type flies and confirmed a complex immune phenotype (Figure 1, A–D). Tim mutants died more quickly than wild-type flies when infected with S. marcescens and died with wild-type kinetics when infected with S. typhimurium and B. cepacia. Tim mutants showed no difference in sensitivity to wounding alone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Thus, these data suggest that Tim activity has different consequences for immunity against different pathogens. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1002445-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002445.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Tim activity has significant consequences for immunity. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Shown here are Kaplan-Meier survival curves comparing Tim null mutants (orange circles) and wild-type control flies (green squares). Tim mutants die more quickly after infection with (A) S. pneumoniae (p&lt;0.0001) or (B) S. marcescens (p&lt;0.0001). Tim mutants die at the same rate as wild-type flies after infection with (C) B. cepacia (p = 0.1001), (D) S. typhimurium (p = 0.1707), or (E) medium alone (p = 0.9836). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>p-values were obtained by log-rank analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1002445.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Tim regulates resistance to specific bacterial infection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>We next asked if Tim regulates mechanisms of resistance or tolerance against specific bacterial pathogens [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>We functionally distinguished between these two types of immune defense by comparing the bacterial loads of Tim mutant and wild-type flies after infection with four different bacterial pathogens (Figure 2, A–D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>We found that loss of Tim protein causes a loss of resistance against two pathogens. Tim mutants die faster than wild-type flies when infected with S. pneumoniae and S. marcescens and have high bacterial loads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>This suggests that Tim mutants are less able to control microbial growth and lack resistance to these two pathogens. Tim mutants had no effect on survival or bacterial growth during infection with S. typhimurium and B. cepacia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1002445-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002445.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Tim regulates resistance to infection by S. pneumoniae and S. marcescens. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Mutants lacking resistance, or bacterial killing, have shorter survival times and greater bacterial loads than wild-type flies. Tim null mutants lack resistance to (A) S. pneumoniae and (B) S. marcescens. Tim mutants have bacterial loads similar to wild-type flies when infected with (C) B. cepacia and (D) S. typhimurium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>p-values were obtained by two-tailed, unpaired t-test; all experiments were performed with day-time injections. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1002445.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>These results demonstrate that Tim regulates resistance mechanisms for specific bacterial pathogens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Different physiologies will be important for defense against each type of pathogen; thus specific microbes can be used to probe different aspects of the immune system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Circadian proteins like Tim are known to regulate many different types of behavior and up to 5–10% of the transcriptome of different tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>If specific physiologies that contribute to the defense against certain pathogens are circadian-regulated in Drosophila, then Tim mutants will present immune phenotypes when infected with those pathogens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Thus we can use our knowledge about the defenses required for different pathogens to identify those that are circadian-regulated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Light-induced degradation of Tim protein in wild-type flies causes sensitivity to S. pneumoniae </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>We chose to focus on Tim mutants and their dramatic defect in resistance against S. pneumoniae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that Tim mutants might lack resistance because of a developmental defect (such as malformation of immune tissues) or because of a direct effect of circadian disruption on immunity in the adult fly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>To distinguish between these two possibilities, we disrupted Tim protein in genetically wild-type adult flies using constant light (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Blue light (∼380 to 475 nm) causes complete and rapid ubiquitin-mediated degradation of Tim protein [20]; normally, this allows the internal molecular clock to be synchronized with external light cues [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Flies reared in constant light exhibit complete loss of circadian rhythm [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Here we use constant exposure to light to induce a Tim-null phenocopy in adult wild-type flies, circumventing any developmental requirements for Tim protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Wild-type flies were infected with S. pneumoniae and incubated either in darkness or constant light. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>We found that flies incubated after infection in constant light died faster than those incubated in darkness (p&lt;0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>As a negative control, we treated Tim null mutants and found that they were not further sensitized by constant light, suggesting that Tim is epistatic to and therefore downstream of light treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>These results are consistent with the hypothesis that Tim protein regulates resistance to S. pneumoniae in the adult fly and also demonstrate that environmental and genetic disruption of circadian regulation alters immunity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1002445-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002445.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Resistance against S. pneumonia correlates with Tim activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Shown here are Kaplan-Meier survival curves comparing wild-type flies and Tim mutants infected with S. pneumoniae and subjected to different light conditions as detailed in the schematic diagrams. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>(A) Light-induced degradation of Tim protein in wild-type flies results in increased sensitivity to S. pneumoniae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Infected wild-type flies incubated in constant light were more sensitive than wild-type flies incubated in darkness (p&lt;0.0001). Tim mutants incubated in constant light died as rapidly as did Tim mutants incubated in darkness (p = 0.3404). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>(B) Wild-type flies were more sensitive to S. pneumoniae when infected at a time of day when Tim protein is low. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Wild-type flies were less sensitive when infected 6 hours after lights off (DARK) than 6 hours after lights on, when Tim protein is minimally and maximally expressed, respectively (p&lt;0.0001). Tim mutant sensitivity was not rescued by infection 6 hours after lights off (DARK) (p = 0.4134). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>(C) Light-induced sleep-wake rhythms (a startle response called “masking”) do not rescue Tim mutant sensitivity to infection. Tim mutant sensitivity was not rescued by incubation in cycling light:dark conditions compared to incubation in the dark. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>In fact, both Tim and wild-type flies were more sensitive to infection in cycling light:dark conditions than in the dark (p = 0.0125 and p&lt;0.0001 respectively). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1002445.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Wild-type flies are more sensitive to S. pneumoniae when infected at a time of day when Tim protein expression is low </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>If Tim protein positively regulates resistance in the adult fly and if Tim protein levels oscillate over the circadian day, we predicted that the resistance of wild-type flies should also oscillate over the circadian day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>To test this, we infected two sets of flies, light-entrained in anti-phase with each other, at times that correspond to minimal and maximal Tim protein expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Tim protein levels are lowest approximately 7 hours after lights turn on (Zeitgeber 07 or ZT07/day) and highest at approximately 7 hours after lights off (ZT19/night) [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Consistent with minimal and maximal Tim expression, wild-type flies infected during the day (ZT07) died significantly faster than those infected at night (ZT19) (Figure 3B). Tim null mutants showed no difference in survival time based on time of infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that increased Tim expression at night positively regulates a mechanism(s) of resistance required to fight infection by S. pneumoniae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Loss of resistance seen in Tim mutants cannot be rescued by a sleep/wake cycle induced by environmental light cues </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>“Masking” is a phenomenon in which flies lacking endogenous circadian rhythm exhibit circadian-like, light-stimulated locomotor activity and sleep-wake patterns due to external light cues (startle response) [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Thus Tim mutants in masking light/dark conditions exhibit a locomotor response to light stimulus even in the absence of Tim protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>We set out to ask if masking would restore the immune function of Tim mutants back to that of wild-type flies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>To test this, we infected wild-type flies and Tim mutants with S. pneumoniae and incubated them either in the dark (relying on endogenous circadian rhythm) or in circadian light-dark conditions (masking) (Figure 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Masking conditions did not rescue the immune phenotype of Tim mutants infected with S. pneumoniae, suggesting that this phenotype is not rescued by light-stimulated locomotor activity but requires the normal expression of Tim protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The melanization response is not circadian-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>We next examined the three main Drosophila immune responses for circadian regulation: melanization (generation of reactive oxygen species, or ROS), anti-microbial peptide (AMP) synthesis, and phagocytosis by hemocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>We tested each immune response for time-of-day differences in wild type and Tim mutants and found evidence for circadian regulation of phagocytosis but not melanization or AMP gene induction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with our survival data for S. pneumonia, as phagocytic hemocytes are crucial to control the growth of S. pneumonia in Drosophila [24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>We first tested if the melanization response is circadian-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Insects react to injury and some bacterial infections with an enzymatic cascade that generates toxic reactive oxygen species (ROS) and results in the deposition of melanin, visible through the cuticle as dark black spots [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>If melanization is circadian-regulated, we would expect to see a difference in melanized spot formation between wild-type flies and Tim mutants as well as between wild-type flies at different times of day, but not between Tim mutants at different times of day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>We assayed melanization in wild type and Tim mutants infected with S. pneumoniae, but did not observe a systemic melanization response, consistent with published reports [24], [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>We then assayed the melanization response of flies infected with L. monocytogenes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Flies exhibit a strong melanization response after L. monocytogenes infection and require melanization enzymes for resistance against this pathogen [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>We found no significant difference in melanized spot formation between wild-type flies and Tim mutants or between wild-type flies at different times of day (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that melanization is not regulated by Tim. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1002445-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002445.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Tim protein does not regulate melanization or AMP gene expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>(A) Wild type and Tim mutants injected with L. monocytogenes at ZT07 (DAY) or ZT19 (NIGHT) have similar levels of melanization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>p-values for pair-wise comparisons were not significant: WT (DAY) vs. Tim (DAY), p = 0.3551; WT (NIGHT) vs. Tim (NIGHT), p = 1.000; WT (DAY) vs. WT (NIGHT), p = 0.4031; Tim (DAY) vs. Tim (NIGHT), p = 0.8717. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>p-values were obtained by unpaired, two-tailed t-test; n = 18–20 flies per genotype per condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>(B) Basal (uninduced) levels of Drosomycin expression were increased at ZT11 relative to ZT05, ZT17, ZT23 in both wild type and Tim mutants, suggesting that this change in expression is not mediated by Tim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>(C) Infection-induced levels of Drosomycin expression were not significantly different after injection of wild type and Tim mutants with M. luteus at ZT05 (DAY) or ZT 17 (NIGHT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Every pair-wise comparison resulted in p-values greater than 0.05 (not significant) by Mann-Whitney test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>(D) Infection-induced levels of Diptericin expression were not significantly different after injection of wild type and Tim mutants with E. coli at ZT05 (DAY) or ZT17 (NIGHT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Every pair-wise comparison resulted in p-values greater than 0.05 (not significant) by Mann-Whitney test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1002445.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>AMP gene expression induced by septic injury is not circadian-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>We next tested if antimicrobial peptide (AMP) gene expression is circadian-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Expression of AMP genes in response to infection is the best characterized immune response of Drosophila; these small peptides secreted by the fat body are thought to control microbial growth by mechanisms such as disrupting bacterial membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Previously, others had found that expression of several immunity signaling genes controlling AMP gene expression such as Rel and Imd is circadian-regulated [8], [10], [11], [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Here we measured the basal (uninduced) and pathogen-induced expression of two representative AMP genes, Drosomycin (Drs) and Diptericin (Dpt), which are widely used as reporters for induction of the Toll and imd signaling pathways, respectively [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>We first compared the basal (uninduced) expression of Drs and Dpt in wild type and Tim mutants at four time points around the circadian cycle using qRT-PCR: ZT05, ZT11, ZT17, and ZT23. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>We found that both wild type and Tim mutants exhibited higher basal expression of the Toll-regulated AMP Drs at ZT11 than other time points (Figure 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>This result suggests that basal expression of Drs varies with time of day but that this difference in expression is not mediated by Tim protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>This time-of-day difference in basal expression is statistically significant but very small relative to infection-induced expression levels (Figure 4 C, D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Basal expression of Dpt was not significantly different at any time of day in either wild type or Tim mutants (Figure S1A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>We next measured Drs and Dpt expression after S. pneumoniae infection in wild type and Tim mutants at ZT05 and ZT17, approximately when wild-type flies exhibit differences in survival and Tim mutants do not (see Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>If AMP induction were circadian-regulated, we would expect to see a difference in AMP expression between wild-type flies at ZT05 and ZT17 and between wild type and Tim mutants at ZT17 but not between Tim mutants at ZT05 and ZT17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>We found that S. pneumoniae-induced expression of Drs and Dpt was not significantly different at either time of day in either wild type or Tim mutants (Figure S1B, C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>S. pneumoniae is not typically used to induce AMP expression and did not cause the dramatic induction of AMP gene expression seen with other bacteria relative to media alone [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Thus we next examined circadian-regulation of AMP expression in response to two bacteria, M. luteus and E. coli, that have been most extensively used to probe AMP induction and more generally, to quantify signaling through the Toll pathway (activated by M. luteus) or the Imd pathway (activated by E. coli) [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>We examined Drs and Dpt induction in wild-type flies and Tim mutants infected at either ZT07 or ZT19 with either M. luteus or E. coli and collected six hours later for qRT-PCR analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Again, we found that infection-induced expression levels of Drs and Dpt were not significantly different at these time points in wild type and Tim mutants (Figure 4C,D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these data suggest that, for both Drs and Dpt, basal levels of expression and short-term expression induced by these bacteria (S. pneumonia, M. luteus, E. coli) are not circadian-regulated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Tim regulates phagocytosis of pathogens by immune cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Finally, we tested for circadian regulation of the Drosophila immune response of phagocytosis—the physical engulfment and destruction of bacteria by specialized immune cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Phagocytosis is typically assayed by measuring the internalization of fluorescently-labeled bacteria such as S. aureus or E. coli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Here, we measured phagocytic activity at different times of day in both wild-type flies and Tim mutants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>If phagocytosis is regulated by Tim protein, we predict that phagocytic activity will be high at night and low during the day in wild-type flies but will not vary with time of day in Tim mutants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>We assayed phagocytic activity in adult flies by injecting dead S. aureus labeled with pHrodo, a pH-sensitive rhodamine dye that fluoresces in acidic environments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>When pHrodo-labeled bacteria are phagocytosed and processed into acidic lysosomes, the phagocytic cell emits red fluorescence and can be imaged through the dorsal surface of live, intact flies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>We found that phagocytic activity was significantly higher at ZT19 (night) than ZT07 (day) in wild-type flies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Phagocytic activity did not vary with the circadian cycle in Tim mutants (Figure 5A, B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Thus, phagocytic activity oscillates with circadian rhythm in vivo in wild-type flies but not in Tim mutants, consistent with the hypothesis that Tim protein up-regulates phagocytosis of S. aureus at night. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>If phagocytosis is required to clear S. aureus, these data are consistent with previous studies demonstrating that wild-type flies exhibit higher rates of survival when infected with S. aureus at night than when infected during the day [18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1002445-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002445.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Tim protein regulates an early stage of phagocytosis of bacteria by hemocytes. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>(A) Wild-type flies in the night phase of the circadian cycle have more phagocytic activity than wild-type flies in the day phase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Shown here are images of the dorsal surface of representative flies after injection of dead S. aureus labeled with the fluorophore, pHrodo, which emits fluorescence in acidic environments such as the lysosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Hemocytes that have phagocytosed these bacteria become fluorescent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Dashed lines indicate the region enlarged in the inset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>(B) Phagocytic activity for wild type and Tim mutant flies was quantified by measuring areas of fluorescence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Wild-type flies exhibited significant circadian differences in phagocytosis of S. aureus (p&lt;0.001) but not E. coli (p = 0.74). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>This circadian difference is not present in Tim mutant flies with either S. aureus (p = 0.51) or E. coli (p = 0.63). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>p-values were obtained by unpaired, two-tailed t-test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1002445.g005"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>To test if circadian-regulated phagocytosis is bacteria-specific, we then assayed phagocytic activity with a different type of bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>We injected wild type and Tim mutants with pHrodo-labeled E. coli at ZT07 (day) and ZT19 (night) (Figure 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>In contrast to injections of S. aureus, wild-type flies did not exhibit a circadian difference in phagocytosis of E. coli. Tim mutants also exhibited no circadian difference in phagocytosis of E. coli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that Tim regulates bacteria-specific phagocytosis by immune cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Phagocytosis can be generally described as three steps: receptor-mediated substrate recognition and binding, particle engulfment, and phagosome maturation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Fluorescently-labeled S. aureus and E. coli have often been used in phagocytosis assays to determine whether specific phagocytic components discriminate between different types of bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Many cellular steps of phagocytosis subsequent to substrate recognition do not appear to be bacteria-specific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>For example, inhibition of β-COP, thought to be involved in phagosome maturation, leads to decreased phagocytosis of both S. aureus and E. coli [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>In contrast, some molecular components responsible for phagocyte recognition of bacteria are bacteria-specific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>For example, inhibition of the phagocytic receptor PGRP-LC leads to decreased binding and phagocytosis of E. coli but not S. aureus [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Another phagocytic receptor, PGRP-Sc1a, mediates phagocytosis of S. aureus but not E. coli [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Thus our finding that Tim up-regulates phagocytosis of S. aureus but not E. coli suggests that Tim regulates a bacteria-specific step of this process such as substrate recognition or binding. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Bead inhibition of phagocytosis eliminates the survival difference between wild type and Tim mutants after infection with S. pneumoniae </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Because phagocytosis is crucial in defense against S. pneumoniae [24], these results suggest that differences in phagocytic activity might contribute to the difference in survival after S. pneumoniae infection between wild type and Tim mutants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Thus we tested if inhibition of phagocytic activity would decrease these survival differences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Phagocytosis can be inhibited in vivo by injection of polystyrene beads; phagocytes engulf these beads and are unable to phagocytose subsequent injections of fluorescently-labeled bacteria [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Thus we compared the survival kinetics of wild type and Tim mutants infected with S. pneumoniae with or without bead pre-injection (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>As described above, Tim mutants are highly sensitive to S. pneumoniae infection relative to wild type flies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Consistent with published results, we found that bead pre-injection increased sensitivity of wild type flies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Bead pre-injection of wild type flies decreased survival rate to those similar to Tim mutants, suggesting that inhibition of phagocytosis is sufficient to recapitulate Tim mutant sensitivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this, we also found that bead pre-injection did not increase the sensitivity of Tim mutants to S. pneumoniae, suggesting that phagocytosis is already impaired in these flies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, in some experiments, bead-inhibited wild type flies appear to be more sensitive than bead-inhibited Tim mutants, suggesting that the presence of Tim protein in the absence of phagocytosis may have a negative effect on survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results suggest that Tim-mediated phagocytosis plays an important role in survival of S. pneumoniae and that loss of Tim is equivalent to total inhibition of phagocytosis, though Tim mutants are still able to phagocytose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of phagocytosis is thought to inhibit phagocytes' ability to signal the presence of infection; perhaps Tim also plays a role in these downstream signaling events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Importantly, our results do not rule out the possibility of multiple roles for Tim protein in immunity against bacterial infection, including S. pneumoniae infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1002445-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002445.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Bead inhibition of phagocytosis in wild type flies eliminates the difference in survival kinetics with Tim mutants after S. pneumoniae infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Shown here are Kaplan-Meier survival curves comparing wild-type flies and Tim mutants infected with S. pneumoniae with and without pre-injection of beads to inhibit phagocytosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Infected wild-type flies pre-injected with beads were more sensitive than wild-type flies without pre-injection (p&lt;0.0001) and had similar survival kinetics as Tim mutants (p = 0.0502). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Infected Tim mutants had identical survival kinetics with or without bead pre-injection (p = 0.1327). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>In this experiment infected, bead-injected wild-type flies were more sensitive than infected, bead-injected Tim mutants (p&lt;0.0001); however, this result varied from experiment to experiment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1002445.g006"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Circadian regulation of immunity has long been reported anecdotally in humans and other animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Here we show that Tim protein has complex, pathogen-specific effects on immunity, regulating resistance to infection in Drosophila. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Resistance against S. pneumoniae is upregulated by Tim in the adult fly and is not simply a diurnal response (i.e., activated by light/dark cycles even in the absence of circadian regulatory protein function). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>We also identified phagocytosis as a specific circadian-regulated immune mechanism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>This is the first demonstration of a link between Tim protein and the cellular immune response in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Our data suggests that circadian regulation affects phagocytic immune cells at an early stage of specific pathogen recognition and makes a significant contribution to survival of infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>This work has implications for people whose occupations disrupt their circadian regulation such as night-shift workers, flight attendants, and hospital staff. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Recently, it was shown that chronic jet lag (shifts in circadian rhythm) in mice did not cause loss of sleep or increased stress but did cause circadian dysregulation of the innate immune system and dramatic vulnerability to LPS-induced endotoxemic shock [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, mice infected with S. pneumoniae during their rest phase died significantly less quickly than mice infected during their active phase [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>In modern society, circadian dysregulation and exposure to bacterial infection at night are likely not uncommon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>This work demonstrates that disruption of circadian oscillations in phagocytosis can have significant adverse effects on resistance against infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Fly and bacterial strains </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The Canton S (CS) wild-type and CS tim01 lines have been previously described [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Infections were performed with the following bacteria as described [33]: Streptococcus pneumoniae strain SP1, a streptomycin-resistant variant of D39 and gift from Elizabeth Joyce in Stan Falkow's laboratory at Stanford University [34]; Listeria monocytogenes strain 10403S, gift from Julie Theriot at Stanford University [35]; Serratia marcescens strain DB1140, gift from Man Wah Tan at Stanford University [36]; Salmonella typhimurium strain SL1344, gift from Falkow lab at Stanford University [37]; Burkholderia cepacia ATCC strain 2541; Escheria coli strain DH5-alpha; and Micrococcus luteus ATCC strain 4698. S. pneumoniae was frozen at OD600 0.15 in 1 ml aliquots with 10% glycerol, pelleted upon thawing, rediluted three-fold in fresh BHI (Brain Heart Infusion media, Difco), and incubated (standing) for 1.5–2 hour at 37°C with 5% CO2 to OD600 0.15 for injection into flies, which were incubated at 29°C. L. monocytogenes was grown in standing BHI, overnight at 37°C, and diluted to OD600 of 0.1 for injection into flies, which were incubated at 25°C. S. marcescens was grown in shaking BHI, overnight at 37°C, and diluted to OD600 ranging from 0.1 to 0.6 for injection into flies, which were incubated at 29°C. S. typhimurium was grown in standing LB, overnight at 37°C, and diluted to OD600 of 0.1 for injection into flies, which were incubated at 29°C. B. cepacia was grown in standing BHI, overnight at 29°C, and diluted to OD600 of 0.01 to 0.001 for injection into flies, which were incubated at 18° or 25°C. E. coli was grown in shaking LB, overnight at 37°C, and diluted to OD600 0.1 for injection into flies, which were incubated at 25°C. M. luteus was grown in standing LB, overnight at 30°C, and diluted to OD600 0.1 for injection into flies, which were incubated at 25°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Injection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>All experiments, including injections, were performed with male flies, 5–7 days post-eclosion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Flies were raised at 25°C, 55–65% humidity on yeasted molasses food in a 12h light/dark cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>For injections, flies were anesthetized with CO2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Injections were carried out with a pulled glass capillary needle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>A Picospritzer III (Parker-Hannifan) or custom-made Tritech microinjector (Tritech) was used to inject 50 nL of liquid into each fly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Volume was calibrated by measuring the diameter of the expelled drop under oil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Injections comparing ZT07 (day) and ZT19 (night) were conducted in a dark room using red safety lights as light sources. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Survival assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>60–85 flies per genotype per condition were assayed for each survival curve and placed in 3 vials of dextrose food with approximately 20 flies each. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>In each experiment, 20–40 flies of each line were also injected with media as a wounding control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Death was recorded daily. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Data was converted to Kaplan-Meier format using custom Excel-based software called Count the Dead. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Survival curves are plotted as Kaplan-Meier plots and statistical significance is tested using log-rank analysis using GraphPad Prism software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed at least three times and yielded similar results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>CFU determination </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Following challenge with microbes, six individual flies were collected at each time point. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>These flies were homogenized, diluted serially and plated on appropriate media (tryptic soy blood agar for S.pneumoniae, LB for all others). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Statistical significance was determined using non-parametric two-tailed t-tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed at least three times and yielded similar results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Melanization assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Flies were injected with S. pneumoniae (OD600 0.1) or L. monocytogenes (OD600 0.1) and incubated at 29°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>On day 2 of the S. pneumoniae infection or day 3 of the L. monocytogenes infection, flies were visually inspected for deposits of melanin resulting from the proteolytic cascade that generates reactive oxygen species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Injection with media typically causes a wound-induced melanization response, a small deposit of melanin at the site of injection within 24 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Infection with certain pathogenic bacteria such as L. monocytogenes or S. typhimurium also causes a disseminated melanization response, with large spots of melanin deposition observed elsewhere than the site of injection: under the cuticle or in deeper tissue on both dorsal and ventral sides of the abdomen, thorax, and head. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Flies were quantified for both number and size of spots. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3f"><title><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Antimicrobial peptide gene expression analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Flies were injected with 50 nL of bacterial culture at OD600 0.10 (S. pneumoniae, M. luteus, or E. coli), or media alone (BHI, Difco). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Following injection, flies were placed in vials containing molasses food and incubated at 25°C for five hours at the same light: dark cycle to which they had been entrained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Three groups of six flies were homogenized in Trizol and stored at −80°C until processed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>RNA was isolated using a standard Trizol preparation and the samples treated with DNAse (Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Fermentas RevertAid First Strand cDNA synthesis kit was used to produce the cDNA following the manufacturer's protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Quantitative RT-PCR was performed using a Stratagene Mx3000 qPCR machine, with Roche FastStart Universal SYBR Green Master (Rox) mix and the following primer sets: Drosomycin, Diptericin, Rpl1 [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Total mRNA concentration was normalized using Rpl1 expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Differences in the infection-induced gene expression were calculated by normalizing to basal gene expression in uninfected CS (day sample) taken at the same time point; p-values were obtained by Mann-Whitney test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The data shown in Figures 4 and S1 pool the results of three independent trials, each having three biological replicates of six flies in each sample for each condition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3g"><title><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Phagocytosis assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>5–7 day old male flies were injected with 50 nL of 20 mg/ml pHrodo-labeled S. aureus or E. coli in water (Molecular Probes, cat# A10010 and P35361). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>The flies were allowed to phagocytose the particles for 30–60 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The wings of the flies were removed and flies were pinned with a minutien pin onto a silicon pad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Fluorescence images were taken of the dorsal surface using epifluorescent illumination with a Leica MZ3 microscope fitted with an ORCA camera (Hamamatsu). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Images were captured with Openlab (Improvision) software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>The exposure was set such that the brightest images had a very small number of saturated pixels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>The experiment was repeated three times with 6–10 flies for each treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3h"><title><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Bead inhibition of phagocytosis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Fluorescent 0.2 um polystyrene beads (Molecular Probes, cat# F13080) were injected into hemolymph to inhibit phagocytosis as previously described [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Briefly, 200 ul of beads in solution were washed three times in sterile water and resuspended in 20 ul final volume. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>5–7 day old male flies were injected with 50 nL of bead solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>To confirm that phagocytosis was inhibited with this protocol, the in vivo phagocytosis assay was performed as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Phagocytosis was completely inhibited within 2 days of bead injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Flies were then injected with S. pneumoniae at OD600 ranging from 0.05–0.15 (see Survival Assays, above). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3i"><title><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Accession numbers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Accession numbers are listed below for the following genes, which were examined in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Accession numbers were obtained from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uniprot.org">www.uniprot.org</ext-link>: Timeless (P49021); Drosomycin (P41964); Diptericin (P24492) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1002445.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Tim protein does not regulate AMP gene expression. (A) Basal (uninduced) levels of Diptericin expression were very low and not significantly different at different times of day in wild type and Tim mutants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Every pair-wise combination resulted in p-value greater than 0.05 (not significant) by Mann-Whitney test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>(B) Drosomycin expression levels induced by injection of S. pneumoniae or media (BHI) are not circadian-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Wild type and Tim mutants were injected at ZT05 (DAY) or ZT 17 (NIGHT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Pair-wise comparisons of flies injected with S. pneumoniae resulted in p-values greater than 0.05 (not significant) by Mann-Whitney test. Tim mutants injected with media during the day exhibited significantly less Drosomycin expression than wild-type flies injected with media during the day or night or Tim mutants injected at night; all other pair-wise comparisons of flies injected with media did not show significant differences by Mann-Whitney test. S. pneumoniae-infected flies exhibited higher levels of Drosomycin expression than BHI-injected controls; p&lt;0.01 by Mann-Whitney test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>(C) Infection-induced levels of Diptericin expression were not significantly different after injection of wild type and Tim mutants with E. coli at ZT05 (DAY) or ZT17 (NIGHT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Pair-wise comparisons within the set of flies injected with S. pneumoniae resulted in p-values greater than 0.05 (not significant) by Mann-Whitney test. S. pneumoniae-infected and BHI-injected flies did not exhibit significant differences in Diptericin expression; p&gt;0.05 by Mann-Whitney test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>(EPS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="ppat.1002445.s001.eps"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>We thank Elizabeth Joyce, Stan Falkow, Man Wah Tan, and Julie Theriot for providing bacteria; we thank Gerard Karsenty and the Karsenty lab for use of their qRT-PCR machine, Gary Struhl for his fluorescence microscope, and Laura Johnston and Andrew Tomlinson for microscopy equipment; and we thank Joel Shirasu-Hiza for help with computer programming. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>David Schneider, Joe Takahashi, Jen Zallen, Tarun Kapoor, and Julie Canman provided insightful comments on this manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Marc Dionne, Paul Taghert, and Amita Sehgal provided invaluable discussion, as did members of the Schneider lab and other members of the Shirasu-Hiza lab (Victoria Allen, James Cheong, Albert Kim, Paul Kim, Yang “Sunny” Li, Reed O'Connor, Adam Ryan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>We thank the reviewers for useful comments and experimental suggestions. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>This work was funded by R01AI069164 and T32AI007328. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ppat.1002445-Lowrey1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>1 LowreyPLTakahashiJS 2004 Mammalian circadian biology: elucidating genome-wide levels of temporal organization. Annu Rev Genomics Hum Genet 5 407 441 15485355 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Storch1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>2 StorchKFLipanOLeykinIViswanathanNDavisFC 2002 Extensive and divergent circadian gene expression in liver and heart. Nature 417 78 83 11967526 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Keller1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>3 KellerMMazuchJAbrahamUEomGDHerzogED 2009 A circadian clock in macrophages controls inflammatory immune responses. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 106 21407 21412 19955445 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Hardin1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>4 HardinPE 2005 The circadian timekeeping system of Drosophila. Curr Biol 15 R714 722 16139204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Beaver1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>5 BeaverLMGiebultowiczJM 2004 Regulation of copulation duration by period and timeless in Drosophila melanogaster. Curr Biol 14 1492 1497 15324667 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Krishnan1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>6 KrishnanNDavisAJGiebultowiczJM 2008 Circadian regulation of response to oxidative stress in Drosophila melanogaster. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 374 299 303 18627767 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-ShirasuHiza1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>7 Shirasu-HizaMMDionneMSPhamLNAyresJSSchneiderDS 2007 Interactions between circadian rhythm and immunity in Drosophila melanogaster. Curr Biol 17 R353 355 17502084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Williams1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>8 WilliamsJASathyanarayananSHendricksJCSehgalA 2007 Interaction between sleep and the immune response in Drosophila: a role for the NFkappaB relish. Sleep 30 389 400 17520783 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Schneider1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>9 SchneiderDSAyresJS 2008 Two ways to survive infection: what resistance and tolerance can teach us about treating infectious diseases. Nat Rev Immunol 8 889 895 18927577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-McDonald1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>10 McDonaldMJRosbashM 2001 Microarray analysis and organization of circadian gene expression in Drosophila. Cell 107 567 578 11733057 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Ceriani1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>11 CerianiMFHogeneschJBYanovskyMPandaSStraumeM 2002 Genome-wide expression analysis in Drosophila reveals genes controlling circadian behavior. J Neurosci 22 9305 9319 12417656 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-MendezFerrer1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>12 Mendez-FerrerSLucasDBattistaMFrenettePS 2008 Haematopoietic stem cell release is regulated by circadian oscillations. Nature 452 442 447 18256599 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Kondo1"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>13 KondoYCahyaningsihUAbeATanabeA 1992 Presence of the diurnal rhythms of monocyte count and macrophage activities in chicks. Poult Sci 71 296 301 1546040 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Kurepa1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>14 KurepaZRabaticSDekarisD 1992 Influence of circadian light-dark alternations on macrophages and lymphocytes of CBA mouse. Chronobiol Int 9 327 340 1394604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Hriscu1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>15 HriscuML 2005 Modulatory factors of circadian phagocytic activity. Ann N Y Acad Sci 1057 403 430 16399910 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Roy1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>16 RoyBSinghRKumarSRaiU 2008 Diurnal variation in phagocytic activity of splenic phagocytes in freshwater teleost Channa punctatus: melatonin and its signaling mechanism. J Endocrinol 199 471 480 18824520 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-NguyenLegros1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>17 Nguyen-LegrosJHicksD 2000 Renewal of photoreceptor outer segments and their phagocytosis by the retinal pigment epithelium. Int Rev Cytol 196 245 313 10730217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Lee1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>18 LeeJ-EEderyI 2008 Circadian regulation in the ability of Drosophila to combat pathogenic infections. Curr Biol 18 195 199 18261909 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Ayres1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>19 AyresJSSchneiderDS 2008 A signaling protease required for melanization in Drosophila affects resistance and tolerance of infections. PLoS Biol 6 2764 2773 19071960 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Naidoo1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>20 NaidooNSongWHunter-EnsorMSehgalA 1999 A role for the proteasome in the light response of the timeless clock protein. Science 285 1737 1741 10481010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Konopka1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>21 KonopkaRJPittendrighCOrrD 1989 Reciprocal behaviour associated with altered homeostasis and photosensitivity of Drosophila clock mutants. J Neurogenet 6 1 10 2506319 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Peng1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>22 PengYStoleruDLevineJDHallJCRosbashM 2003 Drosophila free-running rhythms require intercellular communication. PLoS Biol 1 E13 12975658 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Rieger1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>23 RiegerDStanewskyRHelfrich-FörsterC 2003 Cryptochrome, compound eyes, Hofbauer-Buchner eyelets, and ocelli play different roles in the entrainment and masking pathway of the locomotor activity rhythm in the fruit fly Drosophila melanogaster. J Biol Rhythms 18 377 391 14582854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Pham1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>24 PhamLNDionneMSShirasu-HizaMSchneiderDS 2007 A specific primed immune response in Drosophila is dependent on phagocytes. PLoS Pathog 3 e26 17352533 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Ayres2"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>25 AyresJSchneiderD 2009 The role of anorexia in resistance and tolerance to infections in Drosophila. PLoS Biol 7 e1000150 19597539 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Lemaitre1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>26 LemaitreBReichhartJMHoffmannJA 1997 Drosophila host defense: differential induction of antimicrobial peptide genes after infection by various classes of microorganisms. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 94 14614 14619 9405661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-DeGregorio1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>27 De GregorioESpellmanPTTzouPRubinGMLemaitreB 2002 The Toll and Imd pathways are the major regulators of the immune response in Drosophila. Embo J 21 2568 2579 12032070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Ramet1"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>28 RametMPearsonAManfruelliPLiXKozielH 2001 Drosophila scavenger receptor CI is a pattern recognition receptor for bacteria. Immunity 15 1027 1038 11754822 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Garver1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>29 GarverLSWuJWuLP 2006 The peptidoglycan recognition protein PGRP-SC1a is essential for Toll signaling and phagocytosis of Staphylococcus aureus in Drosophila. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 103 660 665 16407137 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-ElrodErickson1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>30 Elrod-EricksonMMishraSSchneiderD 2000 Interactions between the cellular and humoral immune responses in Drosophila. Curr Biol 10 781 784 10898983 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-CastanonCervantes1"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>31 Castanon-CervantesOWuMEhlenJCPaulKGambleKL 2010 Dysregulation of inflammatory responses by chronic circadian disruption. J Immunol 185 5796 5805 20944004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Feigin1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>32 FeiginRDSan JoaquinVHHaymondMWWyattRG 1969 Daily periodicity of susceptibility of mice to pneumococcal infection. Nature 224 379 380 5343888 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Schneider2"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>33 SchneiderDSAyresJSBrandtSMCostaADionneMS 2007 Drosophila eiger mutants are sensitive to extracellular pathogens. PLoS Pathog 3 e41 17381241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Joyce1"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>34 JoyceEAKawaleACensiniSKimCCCovacciA 2004 LuxS is required for persistent pneumococcal carriage and expression of virulence and biosynthesis genes. Infect Immun 72 2964 2975 15102809 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Mansfield1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>35 MansfieldBEDionneMSSchneiderDSFreitagNE 2003 Exploration of host-pathogen interactions using Listeria monocytogenes and Drosophila melanogaster. Cell Microbiol 5 901 911 14641175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Flyg1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>36 FlygCXanthopoulosK 1983 Insect Pathogenic Properties of Serratia marcescens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Passive and Active Resistance to Insect Immunity Studied with Protease-deficient and Phage-resistant Mutants. J Gen Microbiol 129 453 464  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Hoiseth1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>37 HoisethSKStockerBA 1981 Aromatic-dependent Salmonella typhimurium are non-virulent and effective as live vaccines. Nature 291 238 239 7015147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002445-Clark1"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>38 ClarkRIWoodcockKJGeissmannFTrouilletCDionneMS 2011 Multiple TGF-beta superfamily signals modulate the adult Drosophila immune response. Curr Biol 21 1672 1677 21962711 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
