
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bioinfo</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3463116</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22789589</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts438</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bts438</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Papers</subject><subj-group><subject>Systems Biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>iBBiG: iterative binary bi-clustering of gene sets </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gusenleitner</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="bts438-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>Eleanor A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="bts438-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="bts438-AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bentink</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="bts438-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="bts438-AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Quackenbush</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="bts438-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="bts438-AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="bts438-AFF1"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Culhane</surname><given-names>Aedín C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="bts438-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="bts438-AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="bts438-COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="bts438-AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Biostatistics and Computational Biology, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Boston, MA, USA, <sup>2</sup>Department of Statistics, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK, <sup>3</sup>Department of Biostatistics, Harvard School of Public Health, Boston, MA, USA and <sup>4</sup>Department of Cancer Biology, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Boston, MA, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="bts438-COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed.</corresp><fn><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Associate Editor: Alfonso Valencia </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>7</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>12</day><month>7</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>28</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>2484</fpage><lpage>2492</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>7</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Motivation: Meta-analysis of genomics data seeks to identify genes associated with a biological phenotype across multiple datasets; however, merging data from different platforms by their features (genes) is challenging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Meta-analysis using functionally or biologically characterized gene sets simplifies data integration is biologically intuitive and is seen as having great potential, but is an emerging field with few established statistical methods. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Results: We transform gene expression profiles into binary gene set profiles by discretizing results of gene set enrichment analyses and apply a new iterative bi-clustering algorithm (iBBiG) to identify groups of gene sets that are coordinately associated with groups of phenotypes across multiple studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>iBBiG is optimized for meta-analysis of large numbers of diverse genomics data that may have unmatched samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>It does not require prior knowledge of the number or size of clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>When applied to simulated data, it outperforms commonly used clustering methods, discovers overlapping clusters of diverse sizes and is robust in the presence of noise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>We apply it to meta-analysis of breast cancer studies, where iBBiG extracted novel gene set—phenotype association that predicted tumor metastases within tumor subtypes. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Availability: Implemented in the Bioconductor package iBBiG </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Contact: aedin@jimmy.harvard.edu </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="SEC1"><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>1 INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Genomic studies have generated vast quantities of data, including gene expression, copy number variation and single-nucleotide polymorphisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Tens of thousands of gene expression profiling experiments are stored in public repositories (Barrett et al., 2009; Parkinson et al., 2009) and are increasingly studied in aggregate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The aim of these studies is typically to discover a set of genes that participate in a pathway and are robustly predictive of a biological phenotype in a meta-analysis of multiple studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Gene set analysis (GSA) was developed to identify such gene sets whose expression distinguishes biological conditions, even if single-gene analysis fails to find significant associations with the phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The method takes advantage of a priori defined gene sets published in gene set databases (Gene Ontology, KEGG and MSigDB) or resulting from differential expression studies (MSigDB and GeneSigDB) (Culhane et al., 2009, 2012; Subramanian et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>GSA has been successfully applied to the analysis of microarray experiments (Goeman and Buehlmann, 2007; Mootha et al., 2003) and has been extended beyond transcriptomics to other areas, such as analysis of genome-wide association studies (Cantor et al., 2010; Wu et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>When compared to traditional single-gene analysis that ranks differential gene expression between two conditions, GSA produced more consistent biological results across studies even when some genes in a gene set were absent or poorly represented in a dataset (Fan et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Although GSA naturally extends to integrated meta-analysis, surprisingly few studies have applied meta-GSA to integration of multiple datasets (Segal et al., 2004; Montaner and Dopazo, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Most meta-GSA approaches are designed for the limited case, where datasets have matched samples or features (Montaner and Dopazo, 2010; Tyekucheva et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>These either create a merged dataset of features (genes) common to all datasets and perform a GSA or apply GSA on each individual datasets and then combine the resulting GSA statistics or P-values to produce a ranked list of gene sets (Montaner and Dopazo, 2010; Shen and Tseng, 2010; Tyekucheva et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>While a single ranked list of gene sets may capture the biological complexity of a simple cellular system, it is insufficient when applied to the study of complex disease or meta-analysis of large numbers of studies where different pathways are active in different subsets of samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>These limitations can be addressed using bi-clustering, a simultaneous similarity-based clustering of features and conditions, resulting in modules; subsets of features that exhibit consistent patterns over subsets of conditions (Cheng and Church, 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Numerous bi-clustering approaches have been applied to continuous (Cheng and Church, 2000; Hochreiter et al., 2010; Huttenhower et al., 2009) and discretized gene expression profiles (Prelic, 2005); however, these methods have not been applied in meta-GSA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>We introduce iterative Binary Bi-clustering of Gene sets (iBBiG), a new bi-clustering algorithm to perform meta-GSA that addresses the shortcomings of ‘ranked list’ meta-GSA approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>It scales well when applied to hundreds of datasets is tolerant to noise characteristic of genomics data and when applied on simulated data, outperforms clustering and bi-clustering methods including hierarchical and k-means clustering, FABIA (Hochreiter et al., 2010), COALESCE (Huttenhower et al., 2009) and Bimax (Prelic, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>To perform meta-GSA, we first transform ‘noisy’ gene expression profiles to simple binary gene set profiles, which simplifies the conjoint study of different studies as it negates the need to match probes across platforms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>We then apply iBBiG to extract clusters or ‘modules’ of groups of phenotypes whose gene expression profiles are enriched in similar gene sets (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary</ext-link> Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>An attractive feature of iBBiG is that it does not require prior knowledge or limit the number or size of clusters, a non-trivial requirement in cluster analysis of most large biological datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The results of iBBiG are easy to parse; iBBiG modules are ranked by an information score, and within each module, gene sets are ranked by a fitness score that measures its weight in the module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>It uses a genetic algorithm to maximize the size and entropy of each bi-cluster producing a small number of bi-clusters whose functional and phenotypic associations can be easily interpreted; eight modules were associated with known breast cancer clinical covariates in meta-GSA of 21 breast cancer gene expression datasets, and we detected 13 modules prognostic both within and across breast cancer molecular subtypes using a cluster discovery approach, which ignored a priori sample knowledge. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="SEC2"><title><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>2 MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>We tested the ability of iBBiG to discover bi-clusters in matrices of real and simulated data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Real gene expression data were transformed to gene set profiles using two different GSA approaches (i) single sample and (ii) pairwise test which were computed using the Bioconductor packages gene set variation analysis (GSVA) and GSEAlm (Oron et al., 2008), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>GSVA ranks gene sets within each individual gene expression profile to produce a gene set by sample matrix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>GSEAlm tests for enrichment of gene sets in a ranked list of genes that are differential expressed between two conditions or clinical covariates (e.g. Grade 1 versus Grade 3) resulting in a gene set by pairwise test matrix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Resulting GSA P-values are discretized generating a spare binary matrix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Columns contain ‘phenotypes’ defined by single sample or a pairwise test GSA results, in which 1 is a significant association (P &lt; 0.05) between a gene set and phenotype and 0 represents a lack of association. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="SEC2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>2.1 Datasets </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="SEC2.1.1"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>2.1.1 Single sample GSA data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Normalized gene expression of primary breast tumors was download from GEO (GSE20685, n = 327) (Kao et al., 2011) or imported from the Bioconductor data packages breastCancerNKI (n = 337) (van't Veer et al., 2002), and breastCancerVDX (n = 344) (Minn et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Data were obtained on Affymetrix U133 Plus2, Agilent and Affymetrix U133a GeneChip arrays; each contained different numbers of features. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>GSVA was applied using gene sets from C2 subset of MSigDB v3.0 to transform gene expression data into gene set x sample matrices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>No prior knowledge or covariates were used in GSVA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The resulting values were discretized (es.os≤±0.3) to produce an association matrix of sparse (11.6%, n = 1) binary data of 1008 columns (breast cancer samples) and 5098 rows (up and down-regulated results for 2459 gene sets). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>iBBiG was applied with default parameters with nModules = 20. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC2.1.2"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>2.1.2 GSEAlm data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>To discover modules associated with known breast cancer clinical covariates, 21 normalized breast cancer gene expression datasets (3875 gene expression profiles, see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>) annotated with 107 clinical covariates were obtained from the GeneChip Ontology Database (Liu et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Clinical covariates included tumor grade, stage, age or hormone status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>GSEAlm (Oron et al., 2008) was applied to all pairwise combinations of each covariate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>For example, if the covariate grade has levels 1, 2 and 3, all possible pairwise combinations would result in six phenotypes (Grades 1v2,1v3,2v1,2v3,3v1 and 3v2), therefore pairwise tests of the 107 covariates resulted in 448 phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>GSEAlm was performed independently and we did not merge studies at the probe (gene), sample or phenotype level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Gene sets from the C2 and C5 subsets of MSigDB v2.0 (n = 2293) (Subramanian et al., 2005) and GeneSigDB v1.0 (n = 560) (Culhane et al., 2009) were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Resulting P-values were corrected for multiple testing using the false discovery rate (Benjamini and Hochberg, 1995) and discretized (P &lt; 0.05), to produce an association matrix of sparse binary data with 448 columns (pairwise tests) and 2853 rows (gene sets). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>iBBiG was applied to detected 50 modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Examination of the fitness score and module size plots (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 24</ext-link>) identified eight modules that had a fitness score of over 1000 and a minimum of five pairwise tests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC2.1.3"><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>2.1.3 Simulated data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>using observations of GSA results of real data, we simulated a dataset of 400 pairwise tests by 400 gene sets in which we placed seven modules (M1–M7; Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>These were introduced by assigning associations (value of 1) to column and row pairs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>To replicate the expected properties of real data, modules were created such that they partially overlap in columns, in rows and in both directions; M1 gene sets overlapped with all modules except M3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>M2 overlapped pairwise tests with modules M4–7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Artificial modules had highly variable sizes and included ‘wide’ modules driven by a large number of pairwise tests with few gene sets and ‘tall’ modules like M1 which contained 25 pairwise tests with a large number of gene sets (n = 250). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>This latter module (with many gene sets) might represent a complex, well-characterized biological process such as proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Random background noise (at 10%), which is characteristically observed in genomics data, was also added. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>In real data the signal strength will vary both between and within modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Therefore, to simulate variance among modules, random noise (replacing values of 1 with 0) was imposed to produce modules with different signal strengths (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Within a module, we expect to see few strong signals (gene sets associated with all pairwise tests) and many weaker signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Therefore, within each module, a noise gradient was also applied so that the first gene sets had a greater number of associations (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>This within-noise gradient ranged from 10 to 60% and varied between modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The size, signal strength and signal gradient of each module are provided in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Overlaps are visualized in Figure 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>R code to generate this data (using the function makeArtificial available in our Bioconductor package iBBiG) is provided in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Materials</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>iBBiG was also applied to the 21 real datasets in which the sample labels were permuted by random shuffle, but only recovered small modules (2 and 3 pairwise tests) with low or negative weighted scores (data not shown). Fig. 1Data were simulated to represent discretized P-values from GSA of 400 pairwise tests and 400 gene sets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Associations are shown in gray, whereas non-associations are in white. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The dataset has 10% background noise and contains seven overlapping clusters of gene set modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>These include overlaps of pairwise tests (columns), overlaps of gene sets (rows) and overlaps in both dimensions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>There were different signal strength gradients with each module M1 (90–40%), M2 (80–50%), M3 (80–40%), M4 (90–50%), M5 (80–40%), M6 (90–40%) and M7 (60–50%) Table 1Module nomenclature (M1–M7) is the same as that used in Figure 1The first row indicates the dimension (number of columns and number of rows) of each module in the simulated dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The signal strength gradient within each module from the strongest to weakest signal-to-noise ratio is provided in the second row. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>For example M1 has 25 pairwise tests (columns) and 250 gene sets (rows) and a signal-to-noise is 0.9 in the first few rows which decreases to 0.4 as the number of gene sets reaches 250. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The remainder of the table shows the impact of increasing background noise (between 0 and 50%) on the mean specificity and sensitivity of 100 analyses (alpha = 0.3, selection pressure = 1.2, population size = 100, mutation rate = 0.08, success ratio = 0.6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Results in which either sensitivity or specificity drop below 50% are highlighted with a grey background. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="SEC2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>2.2 Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The iBBiG algorithm identifies bi-clusters (or modules) in a matrix of binary data and consists of three main components (i) a module fitness score (ii) a heuristic search algorithm to identify and grow modules in a high dimensional search space and (iii) an iterative extraction method to mask the signal of modules that have already been discovered. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="SEC2.2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>2.2.1 Fitness score </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The module fitness score measures both module size and homogeneity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>A module yields a high fitness score when a large group of phenotypes are associated with the same features (gene sets). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>We use the term phenotype to indicate a binary vector of discretized P-values resulting from either a pairwise test (GSEAlm) or single sample (GSVA) GSA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Module homogeneity is evaluated using Shannon's Entropy (Shannon, 1948), a standard approach to measure homogeneity, often used in cluster analysis Jenssen et al. (2003) and Li et al. (2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>An asymmetrical score was used; associations are considered and non-associations that can result from multiple technical causes are ignored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Assume a binary matrix M, with m columns (phenotypes) and n rows (features or gene sets), in which an element mij {1,0} represents an association between phenotype j and gene set i. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Given a module K with k phenotypes, where 2 ≤ k ≤ m, the probability of an association between a gene set i and the phenotypes in module K is (1) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, the entropy Hi of gene set i and phenotypes in K can be calculated (2) where 0.log2 0 = 0 (Shannon, 1948). Hi has the range 0 ≤ Hi ≤ 1, where Hi=0 when a gene set is associated (pi=1) or not associated (pi=0), with all k phenotypes. Hi=1 when associations are random pi = 0.5. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The score Si of gene set i in module K is weighted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The weight matrix W has the same dimension as matrix M and equals M on the first iteration (when finding the first module), but for subsequent iterations an element wij of W is modified if mij was included in a module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The weight Wik for gene set i in a module K is given as (3) (4) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The parameter α (range 0 &lt; α &lt; 1.0) is a weighting factor that balances module homogeneity and module size (number of phenotypes versus number of genesets). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Clearly one could have a large module with low homogeneity and vice versa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Consequently, α balances the tradeoff between specificity and sensitivity (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplemental Fig. 3</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The optimal default value (described below) was determined to be α = 0.3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link>). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplemental Figure 2</ext-link> depicts the behavior of the entropy-based score for a single gene set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>A score for an entire module S is calculated by summing up the n gene set scores Si, which can be optimized with the addition or omission of phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>A beneficial side effect of this approach is the weighting of gene sets (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Figs. 4 and 5</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The weight indicates the importance of a gene set to a module, relative to other gene sets in that module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>This ranking allows comparison of the relative importance of biological processes represented by those gene sets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC2.2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>2.2.2 Genetic algorithm </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Due to the high dimensionality of the association matrix, it is not feasible to search the solution space of all possible modules exhaustively; hence we use a genetic algorithm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Genetic algorithms (GAs) are a class of heuristic search algorithms and a particular form of optimization methods based on evolutionary concepts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>They use natural selection, recombination and sexual reproduction in order to find heuristic solutions for optimization problems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>In the GA implemented in iBBiG, a module (individual) is represented by a binary vector with length equal to the number of phenotypes, where 1 indicates membership of a phenotype within a module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>A population of such individuals is initialized by randomly selecting two phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The fitness of each individual is evaluated using the entropy-based gene set score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>High-fitness individuals are chosen as parents to create the next generation of solutions, using a linear ranking selection operator (Chakraborty and Chakraborty, 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>A single-point crossover operator is used for recombination and a bit flip operator for the mutation operator. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>An offspring selection operator is used to introduce self adaptive selection pressure (Affenzeller and Wagner, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The algorithm produces generations of solutions, until the highest fitness score in the population stagnates for a specified number of generations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC2.2.3"><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>2.2.3 Iterative module extraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The bi-clustering approach described so far is able to find one module at a time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>In order to find all possible clusters, an iterative approach similar to that described by Huttenhower et al. (2009) was applied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>After finding a module K, the weights of associations (Wik) between gene set i and phenotypes k in module K are subtracted from the weighting matrix W and the bi-clustering is applied again,  Few gene sets have associations with all k phenotypes (Hi = 0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Only the portion of the signal used to calculate the fitness score is removed, as a result a residual association signal Hi &gt; 0 remains in the weight matrix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Residual information not used in modules up to the current iteration is available for subsequent iterations, ensuring iBBiG can find true overlapping clusters. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC2.2.4"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>2.2.4 Optimization of iBBiG input parameters </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The optimal range for each parameter of the GA was tested in 100 runs on simulated data (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Tables S3–S7</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The only parameter that had an impact on the performance was the α parameter that regulates the weighting between the homogeneity and module size (number of phenotypes) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S3</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Experiments in which the α parameter was varied 0.1 &lt; α &lt; 0.9) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>) show that the clustering on the simulated datasets performs optimally (specificity 99.7% and sensitivity 90.5%) with a value of α = 0.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Most other parameters had little effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Higher population size P, which is required to establish the necessary amount of genetic diversity of solutions, shows only marginal differences in sensitivity and specificity (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S3</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The same is true for the mutation rate MR (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S4</ext-link>), the selection pressure for parent selection SP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S5</ext-link>) and the success ratio SR that determines how many children have to outperform at least one of their parents (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S6</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The optimal default settings were determined to be an α of 0.3, a population size of 100 individuals, a mutation rate of 0.08, a success ratio of 0.6, a selection pressure of 1.2 and a stop criterion of 50 iterations of stagnation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC2.2.5"><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>2.2.5 Comparison to other clustering methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>K-means clustering was performed using the ‘stats’ library in R with the parameter K = 7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Hierarchical clustering was applied to an asymmetrical binary distance matrix using Ward's minimum variance method in both dimensions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Bi-clustering methods: δ clustering (Cheng and Church, 2000), xMOTIF (Murali and Kasif, 2003), Bimax (Prelic, 2005), Plaid (Turner et al., 2005) and SPEC (Kluger, 2003) were applied using default parameters using the R packages ‘biclust’ and ‘stats’, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Over 130 runs of Bimax were performed to optimize module size parameters minr (2–26) and minc (2–20) that define module row and column size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>FABIA (Hochreiter et al., 2010) was applied using the R library ‘fabia’ to find eight clusters (p = 8) in 1000 cycles (cyc = 1000) with different spareness loading (α = 0.1, 0.2 or 0.3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>COALESCE (Huttenhower et al., 2009) available in the Sleipnir package was performed using default parameters for both initial cluster discovery and post-processing (COALESCE -j). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Each method detected different clusters, and results show the predicted clusters with maximum pairwise Jaccard similarity index (JI) to each of the ‘true’ modules M1–M7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>In <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Tables S10–16</ext-link>, JI was calculated over phenotype membership, ignoring the ranking of the gene sets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>To assess iBBiG's ability to assign gene sets to clusters (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Tables S17</ext-link>), gene set scores for each predicted module were subjected to Gaussian mixture modeling using the R function ‘mclust’ to discriminate gene sets with high scores from the background null distribution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC2.2.6"><title><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>2.2.6 Implementation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Documentation and code are available in the Bioconductor R package iBBiG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The core functions of the genetic algorithm were implemented in C to speed computation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="SEC3"><title><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>3 RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="SEC3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>3.1 Robustness of iBBiG in the presence of increasing noise </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>iBBiG maintained high performance predicting the strongest signals (M1 &gt; M2 &gt; M3) in the presence of up to 45% noise when background noise was increased in 5% increments up to 50% (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The weaker signal modules (M4–M7) show a high level of specificity but a decline in sensitivity starting at 20% noise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Increasing the α parameter (from the default of 0.3 to 0.5) increased sensitivity with a trade-off of decreased specificity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The algorithm detected M4 to M7 at 25% noise, with an α of 0.5 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S7</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>In addition, we evaluated the stability of gene set scores over 100 runs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Within each module, gene sets are ranked by a score that indicates the number of phenotypes in which a gene set is differentially regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>We observed that gene sets with high scores showed low variation among runs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>3.2 Performance of global and bi-clustering methods on simulated meta-GSA data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Global clustering methods (hierarchical clustering, k-means) had difficultly detecting overlapping modules in the simulated dataset as shown in Figure 2A and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Figures 6A and 7</ext-link>, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Although hierarchical clustering discovers M3 with high specificity and sensitivity, it was unable to detect overlapping clusters; it either identified the large clusters (M1 and M2) or the smaller clusters depending on the height of the dendrogram cut. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Figure 6B and C</ext-link> shows the maximum JI between predicted and true clusters when dendrogram was cut to give 3–15 clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>When hierarchical clustering was performed to produce the optimal number of clusters (K = 8) with the highest average JI (Figures 6B and C), it was still unable to discriminate M2 and its overlapping clusters M5 and M6 which were all contained within its cluster 3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S10</ext-link>). Fig. 2Neither (A) hierarchical clustering or (B) COALESCE could detect all seven modules (M1–M7) in cluster analysis of the simulated dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>True modules are shown in dark gray, and detected modules are colored M1–M7 as indicated. (A) Rows and columns are ordered by hierarchical cluster analysis (Wards minimum variance). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Plots of the JI, which measured similarity between the true and predicted clusters when the dendrogram was cut to give 3 ≤ K ≤ 15, are provided in the Supplement and show that K = 8 was optimal, but produced clusters that detected smaller overlapping clusters at the cost of the large clusters (M1 and M2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The larger modules could only be detected when the dendrogram was cut to produce fewer clusters. (B) Rows and columns have the same order as Figure 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>COALESCE detected five of the seven modules and had difficulty detecting M1 and M6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Bar plots show the predicted module size (number of phenotypes and gene sets) </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Most genomics bi-clustering methods are not optimized for binary data as they have been developed for gene expression data with continuous values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Only FABIA, COALESCE and Bimax discovered bi-clusters in the binary simulated data matrix, the others tested (δ-clustering, Plaid, SPEC, xMOTIF) either did not accept a binary matrix as input or failed to find clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>FABIA performed only moderately well when applied to the artificial dataset (Fig. 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>It tended to discover clusters with large numbers of phenotypes which contained many false positives (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 8</ext-link>), for example the first cluster contained almost all phenotypes (358/400) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S12</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Increasing the alpha parameters from default (α =0.1) to 0.2 or 0.3 (Supplemental Tables α =0.2:13, α =0.3: 14) did improve its ability to detect smaller clusters but still produced clusters with high numbers of phenotypes and few gene sets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The mean module specificity and precision of FABIA were 0.71, 0.71, 0.74 and 0.39, 0.38, 0.35 for alpha 0.1, 0.2, 0.3, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>COALESCE outperforms most bi-clustering algorithms when applied to gene expression data (Huttenhower et al., 2009), however only detected five of the seven clusters when applied to the simulated data (Fig. 2B, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S11</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>It was unable to discover the ‘tall’ module M1, which has few phenotypes with a large number of gene sets and the smallest module M6 which has overlaps in both M1 and M2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Binary inclusion-maximal bi-clustering (Bimax) is arguably one of the most popular binary bi-clustering algorithms, but it is not optimized to tolerate noise in the signal (Prelic, 2005) and produced small clusters with high specificity and poor sensitivity in our simulated dataset (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S16</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Bimax requires that the number and size of clusters be specified as input parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The simulated data contained modules of different sizes, therefore we tested a large range of minimum row (2 ≤ minr ≤ 26) and column size (2 ≤ minc ≤ 20), but the maximum JI to M1-M7 ranged from 0.14 (M2) to 0.68 (M1) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S15</ext-link>), the best single combination was minr = 22, minc = 4 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S17</ext-link>) but this produced clusters of only four to six phenotypes which lacked sensitivity 0.02 (M2)-0.24 (M1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>No single combination of minr and minc parameters could detect all seven modules due to their diverse sizes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementalry Table S16</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC3.3"><title><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>3.3 Performance of iBBiG on simulated meta-GSA dataset </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Next, we applied iBBiG to the simulated data (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>iBBiG does not require the number of modules to be specified and instead extracts an excess number (for example, nModules = 20); the true number clusters are easily estimated from the cluster weighted score that reflects the size and fitness scores of each module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The modules are ranked in order of decreasing score (Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Only 7/20 modules had a fitness scores above background (Fig. 3A and C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The size of modules dramatically decreases after Module 7; only low scoring groups containing two or three phenotypes are found and these do not have positive weighted scorces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Because we do not remove the entire signal on each iteration, modules (which may be artifact) will arise from remaining signal residue from stronger modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>For example, phenotypes in M8 are a subset of those in M2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Overlaps in phenotypes and gene sets of M3-M6 are detected correctly. Fig. 3iBBiG bi-cluster analysis of the simulated dataset detects all modules (M1–M7) including those with overlaps (M3–M6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Plots show the (A) fitness score (S) (B) size (k) and (C) weighted score of the first eight modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The weighted score is the log(k/m*S) where m is the total number of phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Modules M1–M7 are highlighted in (D) an image of the matrix in which rows and columns have the same order as Figure 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The eighth module (M8) contains the residues of other modules which is reflected in a low weighted score </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>To estimate the performance of iBBiG, it was applied to 100 randomly initialized artificial datasets (with k = 8) where it accurately assigned phenotypes to modules 98% of the time, with a specificity of 99%, precision of 96% and a sensitivity of 91%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>These statistics are based on correct identification of phenotypes only and ignore gene set clustering (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S8</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>We found iBBiG detected gene sets membership with high specificity (99%) and precision (92%) but lacked some sensitivity (56%) following discretization of gene set scores (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S8</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>We do not expect to observe 100% sensitive detection of gene sets in modules M1, M2, M4 or M5 as these contain gene sets with less than 50% signal (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The best performing run of 100 detected almost all module phenotypes (specificity 100% and sensitivity 98%) and more gene sets (specificity 99.7% and sensitivity 72.5%) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S9</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The performance of iBBiG gene set prediction was also assessed by calculating of the variance of the scores within 100 runs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 4</ext-link>) and calculating the ROC curves for each module on one run (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 5</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The average runtime for the 400x400 matrix was 69.3 s on an Intel Core 2 Duo (3 GHz) running Windows XP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC3.4"><title><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>3.4 iBBiG discovers 13 modules of breast cancer (GSVA analysis of three datasets) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>We can uncover gene sets associated with unknown clinical covariates using single sample GSA (e.g. GSVA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>iBBiG is optimized to find overlapping bi-clusters in these complex data which can reveal new biological pathways associated with disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>When applied to 1008 gene expression profiles of primary breast tumors from three studies (Kao et al., 2011; Minn et al., 2007: van't Veer et al., 2002) that had been obtained on different technological platforms each containing different numbers of features, iBBiG detected 13 modules with positive weighted scores (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The first four modules (M1–M4) were strongly associated with breast cancer molecular subtypes Luminal A, Basal-like, Luminal A or B and Basal like or HER2, respectively (Fig. 4, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S18</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Both M1 and M2 were enriched in cell proliferation genes and were highly predictive of tumor recurrence in all cancer subtypes and within Luminal A and Luminal B, respectively (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S18</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Figs. S11–18</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Most other modules were subsets of samples in these modules but had different gene sets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>For example, M9 contains different proliferative gene sets, and overlapped with M1 and M3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Although M11 overlapped with M4, it discovered a subset of poor prognosis basal-like patients and it was prognostic of metastases recurrence within the basal-like breast cancer (P &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>M10 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 19</ext-link>) was particularly interesting as it appears to predict patient prognosis within Luminal A and ERRB2 subtypes (DMFS, P &lt; 0.001, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Figs. S20–22</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>There were 177 gene sets in M12 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 19 and Table S19</ext-link>), which were associated with a stromal response to hypoxia and induction of angiogentic genes including TGFB1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The five top genes all contained transcription factor binding sites for V$ATF4_Q2 (GATHER, P &lt; 0.0005) and 3/5 contained sites for V$OCT1_05 (GATHER, P &lt; 0.0003) and are enriched in Gene Ontology terms GO:0045906 (negative regulation of vasoconstriction) and GO:0006701 (progesterone biosynthetic process), suggesting new avenues for research in these breast cancer subtypes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="SEC3.5"><title><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>3.5 iBBiG identifies eight modules associated with known clinical covariates in breast cancer </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>iBBiG was applied to extract 50 modules in a meta-GSA of known clinical covariates (GSEAlm) associated with 3875 gene expression profiles of breast tumors from 21 different studies obtained on diverse platforms that were available in GCOD (Liu et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>It extracted eight modules (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>S4) which had between 9 and 43 pairwise tests (total n=448) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table 20</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The largest, highest scoring module, B1, was among five modules (B1, B2, B4, B7 and B8) enriched in the phenotype (pairwise comparison) high versus low grade. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Although all associated with tumor grade, gene sets in each module represented diverse biological actions; proliferation (B1 and B8), wound healing and cell–cell communication (B2), inflammatory processes and the tumor microenvironment (B4) and extracellular matrix (B7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Module 8 (B8) is a residue of the proliferation signal of B1 and all gene sets contained in B8 are also present in B1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Modules B3, B5 and B6 were associated with hormone receptor-positive luminal breast cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The Module B3 was associated with low grade cancer or normal tissue covariate pair tests and points towards the requirement of a high grade-cancer to dedifferentiate itself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The modules B5 and B6 were associated with protein processing (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S20 and Fig. S4</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>We investigated two modules (B1 and B4) associated with p53 mutated, hormone receptor (ER-, PR-) negative, basal-like breast cancer—a poor prognosis subtype with few targeted therapies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>While the importance of proliferation (B1) is well described, module B4 was of considerable biological interest (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 25</ext-link>) as it was characterized by immune and tumor microenvironment genes sets, including cytotoxic T-cell pathway, and the cytokine pathways IL-12 and IL-17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>These genesets (B4) were associated with high-grade basal-like and luminal B tumors but were not associated with metastases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S25</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Survival analysis of a number of genes in this module in six publicly available datasets confirmed they were predictive of better outcome in Basal-like and ERBB2+ breast cancer (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S26</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="SEC4"><title><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>4 DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The iBBiG bi-clustering algorithm is optimized for module discovery in sparse noisy binary genomics data and can be used for meta-GSA of multiple genomics datasets, to discover modules: groups of phenotypes whose differential gene expression profiles are enriched in the same gene sets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Data integration is made tractable by transformation of continuous ‘noisy’ gene expression data (with different probes/genes in each study) into profiles of differentially enriched gene sets (which are common to all studies). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>We examined two GSA approaches, GSEAlm which tests for enrichment of gene sets in genes that are differentially regulated between conditions and GSVA which is single sample GSA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>The former can be applied to identifying gene sets or pathways associated with known clinical covariates, the latter is a pure discovery approach that ignores prior sample knowledge. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>We designed iBBiG to have high specificity and thereby minimize the false-positive rate when discovering new classes, but the iterative approach employed in iBBiG ensures it is sufficiently sensitive to discover weak signals, even if they are potentially masked by stronger ones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>When applied to simulated data it outperforms widely used global clustering approaches (K-means, hierarchical cluster analysis) and newer bi-clustering approaches (Bimax, FABIA and COALESCE) and is able to find overlapping gene set modules of varying sizes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>iBBiG was able to identify all clusters in a simulated meta-GSA dataset with high levels of specificity and sensitivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>An advantage of iBBiG relative to other methods is that it does not require a priori knowledge of the true number of clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Following the application of iBBiG, the number of true clusters can be estimated from the weighed scores of the extracted modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>In some cases, we observed that a module may represent the residue or remaining signal of a stronger, previously extracted module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>This residue remains because iBBiG only removes information from the data matrix that is actually used for the entropy-based score in a module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>However, we do not consider these residual modules to be a shortcoming of the method as their existence facilitates discovery of the true overlap between modules and, further, these modules can be easily detected by looking at the overlap of phenotypes and gene sets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Although iBBiG includes several parameters, we have shown that most impact only computation time and do not effect cluster discovery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The only parameter that had an impact on cluster discovery was α, which regulates the weighting between cluster homogeneity and the number of phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>This parameter is useful in fine-adjustment of the sensitivity–specificity ratio. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>One major advantage of iBBiG is its robustness in the presence of noise and its tolerance of missing data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>It can tolerate high levels of noise as the entropy derived fitness score add members to a bi-cluster once the number of associations exceeds 50%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>We demonstrate that iBBiG performs well even in the presence of false-positive associations and noise in both signal (20%) and background (40%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Second, iBBiG does not require a gene set to be associated with all phenotypes in a bi-cluster which is a attractive feature in complex biological data were biological processes maybe redundant or regulated by multiple factors concurrently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Many other bi-clustering algorithms, including Bimax and the recently described BiBiT (Rodriguez-Baena et al., 2011), discover only homogenous bi-clusters and have low tolerance to noise and missing data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Bimax identified a large number of mini-bi-clusters and was unable to identify large clusters in our simulated dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>In practice, application of Bimax to genomics data requires post-processing of bi-cluster results in order to either join or visualize overlapping bi-clusters (Santamaria et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>We applied iBBiG to discovery of new modules among 1008 primary breast tumors and discovered 13 modules in an iBBiG-GSVA analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Each module contained samples from multiple studies demonstrating successful data integration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>While the largest highest confidence modules (M1–M4) discovered breast cancer molecular subtypes known to be important in breast cancer, the smaller modules represented sub-sets of these subtypes, supporting recent evidence that there are subtypes within each of the principal breast cancer molecular subtypes (Curtis et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The module M10 was characterized by gene sets associated with angiogenesis in response to hypoxia (or HIF1A degregulation) and was a strong predictor of recurrence in Luminal and ERRB2 amplied breast cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>We uncovered different modules (n = 8) associated with pairwise tests of breast cancer clinical covariates in a meta-GSA of 21 breast cancer gene expression datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Five of the eight modules including the first and largest module was strongly associated with tumor grade. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Most high grade tumors were characterized by increased cell cycle (B1/B8) and those with fewer metastases had significant regulation of immune response genes (B4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>In a meta-analysis of two datasets, Shi et al., (2010) also reported an up-regulation of proliferation genes and down-regulation of cell adhesion genes in high-grade breast tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Although they had insufficient numbers of patients to establish statistical significance, they observed that high levels of immune genes were an indicator of good prognosis in high-grade breast cancer patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Our analysis also suggests B4 immune response is associated with better outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>When we examined which genes that most frequently appeared in module B4 GeneSigDB gene signatures, we found several chemokines including CCL5 (RANTES), a key regulators of T-cell immune response highly expressed in breast cancer and reported to be associated with metastases and progression (Soria and Ben-Baruch, 2008; Zhang et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>However, our analysis does not fit this prevailing hypothesis and suggests CCL5 is associated with good prognosis in high-grade breast cancer patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>In this study, we have used iBBiG to discover clusters in matrices of discretized P-values from GSA of gene expression data; however, the method can also be easily applied to GSA of other different data types including SNP data (Cantor et al., 2010; Raychaudhuri et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>iBBiG can be applied to non-geneset data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>For example, to demonstrate the application of iBBiG to an extremely sparse matrix (&lt;0.3% &gt; 0) in which small clusters are expected, iBBiG was applied to discretized data from the NHGRI genome-wide association study (GWAS) catalog (Hindorff et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>As the weighted scores were low for modules identified, we averaged results over 100 runs of iBBiG and chose 10 robust modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Only genes and traits that occured in at least 65/100 runs were included (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S27</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>These modules are provided in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S22</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>It discovered a possible link between triglyercides, HDL cholesterol and waist circumference with genes GCKR, LPL, BUD13 and ZNF259. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Although LPL, BUD13 and ZNF259 has been implicated previously, this module suggested a new link with an expanding waistline and GCKR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>While GSA requires input gene sets, it is not restricted to databases of curated gene sets and can use gene sets deduced through text mining from the published literature (Jelier et al., 2011; Krallinger et al., 2010; Raychaudhuri et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>We anticipate iBBiG will be useful in integrated data analysis of multiple data types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>iBBiG can be performed on any binary matrix and could be applied to binary protein–protein interaction or RNAi data; we would like to extend it to other data types, including categorical data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>An attractive feature of iBBiG compared to others methods such as the recently described logistic regression meta-GSA approach (Montaner and Dopazo, 2010) is its ability to perform integrative analysis using dozens of datasets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>In summary, iBBiG provides a simple, robust, rapid and scalable method for meta-GSA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>When applied to simulated data it outperforms commonly used clustering and bi-clustering approaches and iteratively discovers gene set modules made up of both strong and weaker signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Meta-GSA using iBBiG constitutes a new approach for discovery of pathway and gene set behavior across multiple studies and provides a higher-level understanding of gene and cellular function. Fig. 4Meta-GSA using iBBiG bi-clustering of GSVA associations between 2459 gene sets which are up- or down-regulated (n = 5098) in gene expression profiles of 1008 primary breast cancer tissue samples, obtained using different array platforms in three independent studies (KAO, NKI and VDX). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Phenotypes and the gene sets are ordered according to module membership in an image that highlights modules (n = 13) that had a weighted score greater than zero. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Color bars above the plots indicate the study, molecular subtype and distant metastases free surival events of patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>These are brown (KAO)/yellow (VDX)/green (NKI)/red (basal-like)/pink (HER2 amplified)/Luminal B (navy)/Luminal A (cyan)/no distant metastases (gray) and distant metastases (yellow), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>The largest and first four modules were strongly associated with molecular subtype across studies being enriched in Luminal A (M1), Basal-like (M2), Luminal A or B (M3) and Basal-like or HER2 (M4) respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Further details are given in the text and in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/bts438/DC1">Supplementary Table S18</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Plots below the image show the fitness size, score and weighted score of each modules </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Funding: This work was supported the Claudia Adams Barr foundation and grant 1U19CA148065 from the National Cancer Institute of the US National Institutes of Health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>We are grateful to Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Curtis Huttenhower for his invaluable expertise and generous help in running COALESCE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>We thank Benjamin Haibe-Kains and Stephan Winkler for valuable comments during the development of the algorithm, Markus Schröder for offering his expertise on implementing the R functions as C libraries and Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Daniel Silver for assistance in biological interpretation of results of the analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Conflict of Interest: none declared </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag>
<SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_28_19_2484__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_bts438_iBBiG_supplement.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_2" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_28_19_2484_v2_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_bts438_iBBiG_supplement.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></SecTag>
</body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bts438-B1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>AffenzellerMWagnerSOffspring selection: a new self-adaptive selection scheme for genetic algorithmsAdaptive and Natural Computing Algorithms2005Springer </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B2"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>BarrettTNCBI GEO: archive for high-throughput functional genomic dataNucleic Acids Res.200937 (Database) D890–D885 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B3"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>BenjaminiYHochbergYControlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testingJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Roy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Stat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Soc.199557289300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B4"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>CantorRMPrioritizing GWAS results: a review of statistical methods and recommendations for their applicationAm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Hum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Genet.20108662220074509 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B5"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>ChakrabortyMChakrabortyUAn analysis of linear ranking and binary tournament selection in genetic algorithmsProceedings of ICICS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Singapore1997Singapore407411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B6"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>ChengYChurchGMBiclustering of expression data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>InProceedings of ISMB2000893103 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B7"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>CulhaneAGenesigdb: a manually curated database and resource for analysis of gene expression signaturesNucleic Acids Res.201240D1060D106622110038 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B8"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>CulhaneACGeneSigDBa curated database of gene expression signaturesNucleic Acids Res.200938 (Database) D725–D716 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B9"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>CurtisCThe genomic and transcriptomic architecture of 2,000 breast tumours reveals novel subgroupsNature2012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B10"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>GoemanJJBuehlmannPAnalyzing gene expression data in terms of gene sets: methodological issuesBioinformatics (Oxford, England)200723980987 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B11"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>HindorffLAPotential etiologic and functional implications of genome-wide association loci for human diseases and traitsProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>USA20091069362936719474294 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B12"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>HochreiterSFABIA: factor analysis for bicluster acquisitionBioinformatics2010261520152720418340 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B13"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>HuttenhowerCDetailing regulatory networks through large scale data integrationBioinformatics2009253267327419825796 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B14"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>JelierRLiterature-aided interpretation of gene expression data with the weighted global testBrief. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatics20111251852921183478 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B15"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>JenssenRClustering using renyi's entropyProceedings of the International Joint Conference on Neural Networks, 20032003523528 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B16"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>KaoKCorrelation of microarray-based breast cancer molecular subtypes and clinical outcomes: implications for treatment optimizationBMC Cancer20111114321501481 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B17"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>KlugerYSpectral biclustering of microarray data: coclustering genes and conditionsGenome Res.20031370371612671006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B18"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>KrallingerMAnalysis of biological processes and diseases using text mining approachesMethods Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>(Clifton, NJ)2010593341382 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B19"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>LiHMinimum entropy clustering and applications to gene expression analysisCSB Conference20040142151 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B20"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>LiuFGCOD - GeneChip oncology databaseBMC Bioinformatics2011124621291543 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B21"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>MinnAJLung metastasis genes couple breast tumor size and metastatic spreadProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>USA20071046740674517420468 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B22"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>MontanerDDopazoJMultidimensional gene set analysis of genomic dataPLoS One20105e1034820436964 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B23"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>MoothaVKPGC-1-responsive genes involved in oxidative phosphorylation are coordinately downregulated in human diabetesNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Genet.20033426727312808457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B24"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>MuraliTMKasifSExtracting conserved gene expression motifs from gene expression dataPac. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Symp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Biocomput20038778812603019 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B25"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>OronAPGene set enrichment analysis using linear models and diagnosticsBioinformatics2008242586259118790795 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B26"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>ParkinsonHArrayExpress update from an archive of functional genomics experiments to the atlas of gene expressionNucleic Acids Res.200937 (Database) D868–D872 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B27"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>PrelicAA systematic comparison and evaluation of biclustering methods for gene expression dataBioinformatics2005221122112916500941 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B28"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>RaychaudhuriSIdentifying relationships among genomic disease regions: Predicting genes at pathogenic SNP associations and rare deletionsPLoS Genet.20095e100053419557189 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B29"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Rodriguez-BaenaDSA biclustering algorithm for extracting bit-patterns from binary datasetsBioinformatics (Oxford, England)20112727382745 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B30"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>SantamariaRBicOverlapper: a tool for bicluster visualizationBioinformatics2008241212121318321885 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B31"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>SegalEA module map showing conditional activity of expression modules in cancerNature Genetics2004361090109815448693 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B32"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>ShannonCEA mathematical theory of communicationBell Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Tech. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>J.194827623656 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B33"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>ShenKTsengGCMeta-analysis for pathway enrichment analysis when combining multiple genomic studiesBioinformatics2010261316132320410053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B34"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>ShiZCo-expression module analysis reveals biological processes, genomic gain, and regulatory mechanisms associated with breast cancer progressionBMC Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Biol.201047420507583 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B35"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>SoriaGBen-BaruchAThe inflammatory chemokines CCL2 and CCL5 in breast cancerCancer Lett.200826727128518439751 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B36"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>SubramanianAFrom the cover: gene set enrichment analysis: A knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profilesProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Sci.2005102155451555016199517 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B37"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>TurnerHImproved biclustering of microarray data demonstrated through systematic performance testsComput. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Stat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Data Anal.200548235254 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B38"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>TyekuchevaSIntegrating diverse genomic data using gene setsGenome Biol.201112R10522018358 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B39"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>van't VeerLJGene expression profiling predicts clinical outcome of breast cancerNature200241553053611823860 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B40"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>WuCGene set enrichment in eQTL data identifies novel annotations and pathway regulatorsPLoS Genetics20084e100007018464898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bts438-B41"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>ZhangYRole of CCL5 in invasion, proliferation and proportion of CD44+/CD24- phenotype of MCF-7 cells and correlation of CCL5 and CCR5 expression with breast cancer progressionOncol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Rep.2009211113112119288016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
