
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plospath</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Pathogens</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7366</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7374</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3219706</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22114553</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PPATHOGENS-D-11–00536</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002369</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Virology</subject><subj-group><subject>Emerging Viral Diseases</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Emerging Infectious Diseases</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Infectious Disease Control</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Metagenomic Analysis of Fever, Thrombocytopenia and Leukopenia Syndrome (FTLS) in Henan Province, China: Discovery of a New Bunyavirus </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Metagenomic Analysis: Discovery of a New Bunyavirus</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Bianli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Licheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Xueyong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Hong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Yanhua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Pengzhi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Xiaoyan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Haifeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Kai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Shiqiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Guohua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Weili</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Yinhui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Haomin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>Feng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Weijun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Center for Disease Control and Prevention of Henan Province, Zhengzhou, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Beijing Genomics Institute in Wuhan, Wuhan, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Key Laboratory of Genome Sciences and Information, Beijing Institute of Genomics, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Center for Disease Control and Prevention of Xinyang City, Xinyang, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>
<addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Pathogen and Biosecurity, Institute of Microbiology and Epidemiology, Academy of Military Medical Sciences, Beijing, China</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Palacios</surname><given-names>Gustavo</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">George Mason University, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>xubl@hncdc.com.cn</email> (BX); <email>chenwj@genomics.org.cn</email> (WC)</corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: BX WC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: XH HM YD XT HW KK SZ HC GZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: LL YZ PW YY FM WW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: WC BX. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e1002369</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>3</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Xu et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Since 2007, many cases of fever, thrombocytopenia and leukopenia syndrome (FTLS) have emerged in Henan Province, China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Patient reports of tick bites suggested that infection could contribute to FTLS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Many tick-transmitted microbial pathogens were tested for by PCR/RT-PCR and/or indirect immunofluorescence assay (IFA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>However, only 8% (24/285) of samples collected from 2007 to 2010 tested positive for human granulocytic anaplasmosis (HGA), suggesting that other pathogens could be involved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Here, we used an unbiased metagenomic approach to screen and survey for microbes possibly associated with FTLS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>BLASTx analysis of deduced protein sequences revealed that a novel bunyavirus (36% identity to Tehran virus, accession: HQ412604) was present only in sera from FTLS patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>A phylogenetic analysis further showed that, although closely related to Uukuniemi virus of the Phlebovirus genus, this virus was distinct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The candidate virus was examined for association with FTLS among samples collected from Henan province during 2007–2010. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>RT-PCR, viral cultures, and a seroepidemiologic survey were undertaken. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>RT-PCR results showed that 223 of 285 (78.24%) acute-phase serum samples contained viral RNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Of 95 patients for whom paired acute and convalescent sera were available, 73 had serologic evidence of infection, with 52 seroconversions and 21 exhibiting a 4-fold increase in antibody titer to the virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The new virus was isolated from patient acute-phase serum samples and named Henan Fever Virus (HNF virus). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Whole-genome sequencing confirmed that the virus was a novel bunyavirus with genetic similarity to known bunyaviruses, and was most closely related to the Uukuniemi virus (34%, 24%, and 29% of maximum identity, respectively, for segment L, M, S at maximum query coverage). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>After the release of the GenBank sequences of SFTSV, we found that they were nearly identical (&gt;99% identity). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>These results show that the novel bunyavirus (HNF virus) is strongly correlated with FTLS. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Author Summary </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Initially in 2007, and again between 2008 and 2010, cases of a life-threatening disease with sudden fever, thrombocytopenia, and leukopenia were reported in Henan Province, China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Patient reports of tick bites suggested that this disease could be infectious or tick-transmitted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Many patients were provisionally diagnosed with human granulocytic anaplasmosis (HGA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>However, only 24 of 285 (8%) had objective evidence of HGA, suggesting that other pathogens likely contributed to fever, thrombocytopenia and leukopenia syndrome (FTLS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Illumina sequencing was used for direct detection in clinical samples of pathogens possibly associated with FTLS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>A novel bunyavirus was found only in samples from FTLS patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Further epidemiologic and laboratory investigation confirmed that the novel bunyavirus was associated with FTLS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The results illustrate that metagenomic analysis is a powerful method for the discovery of novel pathogenic agents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Combined with epidemiologic investigation, it could assist in rapid diagnosis of unknown diseases and distinguish them from other diseases with similar symptoms caused by known pathogens. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In May 2007, a county hospital in Xinyang City, Henan Province treated three patients with fever, abdominal pain, bloating, nausea, vomiting, gastrointestinal bleeding, and elevated aminotransferases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The local hospital diagnosed the disease as acute gastroenteritis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>A family member of one patient reported the disease to the Henan Center for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), which sent a team to investigate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The investigation revealed that the disease had the following characteristics: (1) acute onset with fever; (2) low white blood cell and platelet counts; (3) high levels of alanine and aspartate transaminases; (4) positive urine protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>On the basis of these features, the Henan CDC excluded the possibility of gastrointestinal disorders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In order to identify the disease etiology, the Henan CDC team used the above clinical characteristics as the case definition to search for similar cases in local hospitals in this and neighboring counties, while establishing a disease surveillance system that required all medical institutions to report cases that met the above case definition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Altogether, 79 cases were found in 2007 in Henan, with 10 fatalities (case fatality rate, 12.7%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>All patients were farmers and resided in mountainous or hilly villages, and many had reported tick bites 7–9 days before illness, further suggesting an infectious etiology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>In recent years, patients with similar clinical symptoms were reported with human granulocytic anaplasmosis (HGA; Anaplasma phagocytophilum) in neighboring Anhui province [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In 2005, there was an epidemic of Tsutsugamushi (scrub typhus/Orientia tsutsugamushi) in this area [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Clinical investigations, epidemiological analyses, and laboratory testing prompted consideration of rickettsial diseases as possible causes, including HGA, human monocytic ehrlichiosis (HME; Ehrlichia chaffeensis), and Tsutsugamushi disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Specific methods such as polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and immunofluorescence assays (IFAs) for these pathogens were then used to determine if these cases were attributable to HGA or HME [3], [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>However, only 18 of 79 (22.7%) patients were positive for A. phagocytophilum based on serology and DNA testing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Thus, the disease was initially considered at least partly caused by A. phagocytophilum, and cases were provisionally diagnosed as suspected HGA based on clinical and epidemiological data [1]–[3], [5]–[7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>In the 3 years since 2007, 206 suspected cases have been discovered in Henan, but there was only a very low positive rate of A. phagocytophilum confirmation (6 of 206 patients) and no pathogen was isolated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Similar cases were also reported in the mountainous and hilly areas of nearby Shandong, Jiangsu, Hubei and Anhui provinces, indicating that the disease already existed for some time and was widely distributed [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>We decided to address the possible causative pathogen underlying this infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>On the basis of epidemiological and clinical characteristics, we considered two types of diseases to be possible: rickettsial and arthropod-borne viral disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Because of the low rates of A. phagocytophilum (rickettsial disease) detection, the research team intensified its virus search to take into account arthropod-borne viruses, including Flaviviridae (Dengue viruses [DENV], Japanese encephalitis virus [JEV]), Togaviridae (Chikungunya virus, Eastern equine encephalitis virus [EEEV], Western equine encephalitis virus), and Bunyaviridae (Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever virus, Hantaan virus, and Rift valley fever virus) [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Specific PCR assays for these viruses were used [9]–[16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>However, none of the patients from 2007 to 2010 was positive for these viruses, suggesting a new infectious agent, possibly a virus, remained to be discovered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Thus, the syndrome was considered an emerging infectious disease and was named fever, thrombocytopenia and leukopenia syndrome (FTLS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>To identify the etiology, the research team adopted the following strategy: 1) sequencing of randomly amplified cDNA/DNA from FTLS patient samples using high-throughput Illumina sequencing to specifically explore viral communities present in patients suffering from FTLS, 2) PCR detection of target DNA directly from clinical specimens, 3) viral culture, 4) immunodetection methods, and 5) electron microscopic study of the morphology of the cultured virus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Culture followed by serological and molecular tests is a standard approach for identifying an unknown virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>However, culture of an unknown virus is time-consuming, even taking several years to confirm a novel infection like HIV [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Otherwise, virus culture often fails because of the lack of cell lines capable of supporting propagation of viruses (e.g., hepatitis B and C virus). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Methods for cloning nucleic acids of microbial pathogens directly from clinical samples offer opportunities for pathogen discovery, thereby laying the foundation for future studies aimed at assessing whether novel or unexpected viruses play a role in disease etiology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Random PCR and subtractive cloning sequencing have identified previously unknown pathogens as etiological agents of several acute and chronic infectious diseases [18], [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Recently, high-throughput sequencing approaches have been used for pathogen detection and discovery in clinical samples [20]–[22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>We also developed a method for exploring viruses, both known and novel, using high-throughput Illumina sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>In this study, high-throughput Illumina sequencing was applied to specifically explore the viral communities in patients with FTLS, using healthy subjects as controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Here, we provide evidence for the discovery of a novel bunyavirus associated with FTLS through high-throughput sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Subsequent culture of the virus and PCR detection of the specific virus in patient specimens confirmed these findings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Ethics statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>This research was approved by the Review Board of the Center for Disease Control and Prevention of Henan Province, the Review Board of the Center for Disease Control and Prevention of Xinyang city, the Review Board of Beijing Institute of Genomics, the Review Board of Beijing Genomics Institute in Shenzhen, and the Review Board of the Institute of Microbiology and Epidemiology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>All participants gave written informed consent for use of their samples in research. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Biosafety </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Given the serious nature of FTLS, it was decided to handle all clinical specimens and perform all experiments involving live virus in a biosafety level-3 (BSL-3) facility. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Clinical samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>We studied 285 Henan province patients with FTLS whose samples were submitted to the Henan Province CDC between May 2007 and July 2010. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Acute-phase serum samples from all patients were collected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Paired convalescent sera were available from 95 patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Diagnostic testing of sera for microbial agents possibly related to FTLS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Sera were tested by reverse transcription (RT)-PCR, PCR, and/or indirect IFA serological assays for a number of microbial agents, including A. phagocytophilum, Ehrlichia chaffeensis, Dengue fever virus, Japanese encephalitis virus, Chikungunya virus, Eastern equine encephalitis virus, Western equine encephalitis virus, Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever virus, Rift Valley fever virus, Sandfly fever Naples Sabin virus, and Hantavirus [3]–[6], [9]–[16], [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Antigen slides for diagnosis of HGA (A. phagocytophilum) were purchased from Focus Diagnostics (IF1450G, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Antigen slides for diagnosis of other pathogens were prepared by our laboratories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC)-conjugated goat anti-human IgG (Fc) was purchased from Sihuan Sci-Technics Company (Beijing, China). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Sample processing for Illumina sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Equal quantities (100 µL) of acute-phase sera from 10 FTLS patients who had a history of tick bite were pooled and centrifuged at 1000 x g for 10 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was collected for DNA and RNA extraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The same was done for 10 sera from healthy subjects (control). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>DNA and RNA extraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>DNA was extracted from 140 µL of each sample using the QIAamp DNA mini Kit (Qiagen, 51304) according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>DNA was eluted from the columns with 50 µL water containing 20 µg/mL RNaseA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>After incubation at 37°C for 15 minutes to eliminate RNA, DNA was used immediately or stored at −80°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was extracted from 140 µL of each sample using the QIAamp viral RNA mini Kit (Qiagen, 52904) according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>RNA was eluted from the columns with 50 µL of diethyl pyrocarbonate (DEPC)-treated water containing 1 U DNaseI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Samples were incubated at 37°C for 15 minutes to eliminate human DNA, followed by DNase inactivation at 95°C for 10 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>RNA was used immediately or stored at −80°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Reverse transcription </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>cDNA was synthesized from 6 µL of RNA by reverse transcription at 45°C for 50 minutes in a 20-µL solution containing 50 mM Tris–HCl (pH 8.3), 75 mM KCl, 3 mM MgCl2, 10 mM DTT, 100 ng of random hexamer primers, 200 U of Superscript II (Invitrogen, 18064–014), 25 U of RNasin (Promega, N2511), and 0.5 mM dNTPs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Random hexamer PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Random hexamer PCR was carried out in a 25-µL mixture containing 4 µL of cDNA or DNA, 10 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.4), 50 mM KCl, 2.5 mM MgCl2, 100 µM dNTPs, 1 U Taq DNA Polymerase (Promega, M1661) and 100 ng of random hexamer primers containing a linker (5'-GCCGGAGCTCTGCAGAATTCNNNNNN-3'). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>After denaturing at 95°C for 5 minutes, targets were amplified by 45 cycles of 95°C for 30 seconds, 40°C for 30 seconds, 50°C for 30 seconds, and 72°C for 90 seconds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The amplified products were detected by agarose gel electrophoresis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Pure water was used as a negative control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>High-throughput sequencing by the Illumina method </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>FTLS patient and control genomic DNA/cDNA libraries were constructed according to the manufacturer's instructions (Illumina). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>In brief, RT-PCR and PCR products were roughly quantified by UV absorption and equal amounts of each sample were mixed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Nucleic acids within the mixtures were sheared by sonication, and fragments in the 150–180-bp range were collected by cutting bands from an agarose gel after electrophoresis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The sheared DNA and cDNA ends were repaired using Klenow DNA polymerase, after which 5' termini were phosphorylated and 3' termini were polyadenylated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The adaptors were added, PCR enrichment was performed, and 150–180-bp fragments were collected for sequencing by the Illumina method. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The sequencing procedure was performed according to the manufacturer's instructions (Illumina). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In this process, template library DNA was hybridized to the surface of the flow cells and multiple copies of DNA were made to form clusters using the Illumina cluster station. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Workflow steps included template hybridization, isothermal amplification, linearization, and final denaturation and hybridization of sequencing primers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Paired-end sequencing (100 cycles) was performed using a four-color DNA Sequencing-By-Synthesis (SBS) technology following the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Short Oligonucleotide Analysis Package (SOAP) was used to handle the large amounts of short reads generated by parallel sequencing [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Briefly, after filtering out highly repetitive sequences and adaptor sequences, the overlapping datasets between FTLS and healthy subjects were analyzed by subtracting fragments that mapped to both host genomic-plus-transcript and bacteria databases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The non-redundant reads were mapped onto a virus database downloaded from NCBI (<ext-link ext-link-type="ftp" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.ncbi.nih.gov/genbank/">ftp://ftp.ncbi.nih.gov/genbank/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The resulting alignments were filtered to identify unique sequences by examining alignment (identity ≥80%) and E-value scores (e≤10−2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Filtered unique alignments were examined in the taxonomy database (NCBI) using a custom software application written in Perl (BioPerl version 5.8.5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Unmapped reads were examined in GenBank nucleic acid and protein databases using BLASTn and BLASTx, respectively [25]–[27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Unique alignments were examined in the taxonomy database (NCBI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Sequences without hits were placed in the ‘‘unassigned’’ category. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Sequences were phylotyped as human, bacterial, phage, viral, or other based on the identity of the best BLAST hit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Considering misannotation and low-complexity for Illumina short reads, sequences assigned to the same virus family were further assembled into contigs with Velvet 1.1.04 (K-mer length  = 21; coverage cutoff: default 0; Insert length: PE only; minor contig length: 42) for direct comparison with GenBank nucleic acid databases using BLASTn [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Contigs were also blasted with GenBank protein databases using BLASTx [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>An E-value cutoff of 1×10−5 was applied to both BLASTn and BLASTx analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Sequences phylotyped as viral were placed in the “viral” category. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>RT-PCR detection of the bocavirus </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Our mass sequencing data revealed that some sequences showed possible infection with human bocavirus, which belongs to the Parvoviridae family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>PCR performed to detect human bocavirus tentatively identified in sera from FTLS patient samples amplified a 291-bp fragment of the NS1 gene, as described previously [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Amplified products were detected by agarose gel electrophoresis and sequenced using an ABI 3730 DNA Sequencer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2k"><title><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>RT-PCR detection of the novel bunyavirus </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Our mass sequencing data revealed a 168-bp sequence (C361, Accession: HQ412604) indicating the possible presence of a novel virus with closest identity (i.e., lowest E-value) to Tehran virus which belongs to the Phlebovirus genus of the Bunyaviridae family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>We developed a PCR strategy based on the 168-bp sequence identified in sera from FTLS patient samples to detect the novel bunyavirus using forward (PF: 5'-GAC ACG CTC CTC AAG GCT CT-3') and reverse (PR: 5'-GCC CAG TAG CCC TGA GTT TC-3') primers designed with Primer3 (Supplementary Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>PCR was carried out in a 25-µL mixture containing 4 µL of cDNA, 10 mM Tris–HCl (pH 8.4), 50 mM KCl, 2.5 mM MgCl2, 100 µM dNTPs, 1 U Taq Pol (Promega, M1661), 0.25 µM forward primer, and 0.25 µM reverse primer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Thermocycling conditions were as follows: 95°C for 4 minutes (denaturation), followed by 35 cycles of 94°C for 30 seconds, 54°C for 30 seconds, and 72°C for 30 seconds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Amplified products were detected by agarose gel electrophoresis and sequenced using an ABI 3730 DNA Sequencer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2l"><title><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Virus isolation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The Vero E6 cell line (African green monkey kidney cell) was selected for isolation of the novel bunyavirus associated with FTLS because it supports the growth of many bunyaviruses [30], [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Vero E6 cell lines were inoculated with six serum samples that contained novel bunyavirus RNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Each sample underwent at least three cell culture passages in Vero E6 cell line before being considered negative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Medium was replenished on day 7, and cultures were terminated 14 days after inoculation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>All cultures were observed daily for cytopathic effect (CPE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Virus-infected cells and uninfected cells were also examined for the novel bunyavirus by RT-PCR at each passage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Vero cell cultures with obvious CPE and containing novel bunyavirus RNA were further analyzed by morphology, genome sequencing, and serology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2m"><title><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Transmission electron microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Cells showing CPE and containing novel bunyavirus RNA were collected for thin-section electron microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>After discarding the culture supernatant, virus-infected cells (50 mL) were mixed 1∶1 with 4% glutaraldehyde (paraformaldehyde), placed onto Formvar-carbon-coated grids, and stained with 1% methylamine tungstate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Specimens for thin-section electron microscopy were prepared by dehydrating washed cell pellets with serial dilutions of acetone and embedding in epoxy resin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Ultrathin sections were cut on an Ultracut LKBV ultramicrotome, stained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate, and examined under a transmission electron microscope (JEM-1400). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2n"><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Genome sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The medium from 20 mL of novel bunyavirus-infected Vero E6 cells was centrifuged at 1,000 x g for 10 minutes and then at 4,000 x g for 10 minutes, after which the supernatant was collected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>PEG8000 was added to the supernatant at a final concentration of 10% (w/v) followed by centrifugation at 20,000 x g for 2 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The pellet was resuspended in 2 mL 1× phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) for RNA extraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Random RT-PCR was performed, and the products (500–1500 bps) were collected and ligated into the pGEM-T vector (Promega, A3600) by incubating overnight at 16°C. Escherichia coli JM109 were transformed with the ligation mixture and cultured on LB agar containing X-gal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>White clones were sequenced using an ABI 3730 DNA Sequencer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Contaminating human and extraneous sequences were eliminated using CrossMatch, and the complete sequence was assembled using Phred-Phrap-Consed [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Bridge RT-PCR was employed for gap-closure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2o"><title><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analyses were performed using the neighbor-joining method in the MEGA software package, version 4.0.2 [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Available nucleotide or protein sequences from known viruses were obtained from GenBank for inclusion in the phylogenetic trees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Selected sequences from GenBank included those with the greatest similarity to the sequence read in question based on BLAST alignments as well as representative sequences from all major taxa within the relevant Bunyaviridae family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>To further establish the relationships between the new virus and the members of the Phleboviruses genus, we included all sequences for phleboviruses available in GenBank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Branching orders of the phylograms were verified statistically by resampling the data 1,000 times in a bootstrap analysis with the branch-and-bound algorithm, as applied in MEGA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2p"><title><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Serologic detection by indirect IFA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>After successful isolation of the novel bunyavirus, we developed an indirect IFA to detect specific antibodies in patient serum specimens, as previously described [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>In brief, monolayers of virus-infected Vero E6 cells showing CPE and containing novel bunyavirus RNA were harvested, and one volume of infected cells was mixed with 0.5 volumes of non-infected cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The mixture was centrifuged at 1,000 x g for 10 minutes, after which cells were resuspended in 1× PBS, spotted onto 12-well glass slides, and fixed with acetone for 10 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Sera from patients with FTLS (including 285 acute-phase samples and 95 paired sera), patients with respiratory diseases (80 serum samples), and healthy subjects (50 serum samples) were applied to the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Samples (diluted 1∶20 in PBS) were screened by first spotting 50 µL of each serum sample per well and incubating for 30 minutes at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>After washing for 10 minutes in PBS, 20 µL of FITC-conjugated goat anti-human IgG (Sihuan Sci-Technics Company, Beijing, China) diluted 1∶40 in buffer containing Evans blue was added to each well and incubated for 30 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>After washing, slides were mounted in glycerin and examined by immunofluorescence microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>A titer of 1∶20 was considered positive. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Epidemiology and clinical features of the disease </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>All 285 patients with FTLS were from the Henan Province of China and were provisionally diagnosed as suspected HGA on the basis of similar clinical manifestations [5], [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>They represented four different epidemiologically linked sporadic cases and a few clusters of cases including 79 patients in 2007, seven patients in 2008, 47 patients in 2009, and 152 patients in 2010. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The patients presented mainly between April and October, peaking in April-May during the tea-picking season in Henan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>All patients resided in mountainous and hilly rural areas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>In our study, 238 of 285 patients tested positive for novel bunyavirus infection by RT-PCR and/or IFA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Epidemiology and clinical features of the disease in laboratory-confirmed patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The median age of patients was 57.2 years (range, 23–88) and the male-to-female ratio was 1 to 2.27; 219 patients (92.02%) were farmers and 19 (7.98%) were workers or students. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Among patients, 52 (21.85%) reported a tick bite within 2 weeks (5–14 days) before the onset of clinical manifestations; the remaining patients did not recall receiving a tick bite. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The main clinical features in confirmed patients included sudden onset of fever (&gt;37.5°C −40°C) lasting up to 10 days, fatigue, anorexia, headache, myalgia, arthralgia, dizziness, enlarged lymph nodes, muscle aches, vomiting and diarrhea, upper abdominal pain, and relative bradycardia (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>A small number of cases suffered more severe complications, including hypotension, mental status alterations, ecchymosis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, pulmonary hemorrhage, respiratory failure, disseminated intravascular coagulation, multiple organ failure, and/or death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Most patients had a good outcome, but elderly patients and those with underlying diseases, neurological manifestations, coagulopathy, or hyponatremia tended to have a poorer outcome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="ppat-1002369-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002369.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Symptoms of 238 patients with FTLS at presentation. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="ppat-1002369-t001-1" xlink:href="ppat.1002369.t001"/></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Laboratory tests showed that confirmed patients characteristically developed thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, proteinuria, and elevated serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) levels (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Biochemical tests revealed generally higher levels of lactate dehydrogenase, creatine kinase, AST and ALT enzymes, especially AST. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="ppat-1002369-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002369.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Initial laboratory findings of 238 patients with FTLS. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="ppat-1002369-t002-2" xlink:href="ppat.1002369.t002"/></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Metagenomic analysis and identification of unknown pathogen </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>One lane for each of the two sample pools (FTLS and healthy controls), each consisting of 10 samples, was sequenced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The proportions of high-quality sequences in FTLS and control pools were 98.08% (10,198,407/10,397,161) and 97.88% (10,250,809/10,472,315), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Unique, high-quality sequence reads were then classified into broad taxonomic groups based on the taxonomy of the most frequent top-scoring BLAST matches for each sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Virus sequences constituted 0.0065% (67,969) and 0.0048% (50,677) of the reads in FTLS and control libraries, respectively (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>After contig assembly, the number of sequences phylotyped as “viral” decreased to 3,163 and 2,412, respectively, in the two pools (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>To screen for possible viruses, we focused exclusively on viruses that were present in patient sera. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="ppat-1002369-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002369.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Categorization of sequence reads based on SOAP criteria. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="ppat-1002369-t003-3" xlink:href="ppat.1002369.t003"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Criteria for SOAP including ID≥80%, E-value≤1e-2 and Match query≥0.7. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>For detection of known viruses, non-redundant reads were directly aligned with the GenBank database of nucleic acids using BLASTn software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Some sequences from Adenoviridae (human adenovirus), Herpesviridae (herpesvirus), Papillomaviridae (papillomavirus) and Retroviridae (human endogenous retrovirus) were detected in both FTLS patients and healthy subject samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Some hepatitis B virus (HBV) and human bocavirus sequences were detected only in patient sera, indicating the presence of HBV and human bocavirus infections among these patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>To detect novel viruses, we examined sequence data against the GenBank protein database using BLASTx. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>An analysis of the deduced protein sequences revealed four different virus families in sera from FTLS patients (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Among these were viruses from Hepadnaviridae, which are not known to cause FTLS; Torque teno virus (TTV) from Anelloviridae, which has been reported to be associated with certain inflammatory states [34], but is not known to be transmitted by arthropods; and viruses from the Parvoviridae family, including human bocavirus, which could cause febrile illness and signs of FTLS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Although human bocaviruses are not known to be transmitted by arthropods, feline panleukopenia virus, a parvovirus, is strongly suspected to be transmitted by arthropods [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>All family Parvoviridae sequences detected in FTLS samples were also assembled and their protein sequences deduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Included among these samples were four fragments, all of which were found to be highly homologous to human bocavirus; one fragment showed the greatest similarity to human bocavirus 2 isolate 53044 (identity  = 86%) with the lowest E-value (8×10−17). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Human bocavirus was further detected by PCR in the pool of 10 serum samples, but only one individual sample within the pool tested positive for bocavirus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The final virus family detected in sera from FTLS patients was the Bunyaviridae family, which contains viruses known to cause FTLS after tick bites [8], [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>All family Bunyaviridae sequences detected in FTLS samples, including 11 fragments (1 S-segment, 2 M-segments, and 8 L-segment fragments), were assembled and their protein sequences were deduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Among these 11 novel virus fragments was a 168-bp fragment (C361, Accession: HQ412604) of the polymerase gene that showed the greatest similarity to Tehran virus (identity  = 36%) with the lowest E-value (3×10−7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>This suggested the presence of a novel virus or a known virus whose genome had not yet been sequenced. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="ppat-1002369-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002369.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>sequence reads with limited BLASTx identity to known viruses. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="ppat-1002369-t004-4" xlink:href="ppat.1002369.t004"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>*Bold indicates virus families only found in FTLS patient sera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>An E-value cutoff of 1e-5 for BLASTx was applied. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>To more accurately assess the genetic relationships to known viruses, we constructed a phylogenetic tree using a neighbor-joining method [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The result showed that the potentially novel virus clustered with Toscana virus, Uukuniemi virus, and Rift Valley fever virus of the Phlebovirus genus (Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The pools of 10 serum samples from patients and 10 serum samples from healthy subjects were also screened by PCR for the presence of the novel bunyavirus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>All 10 samples from patients tested positive for the novel bunyavirus; however, all 10 samples from healthy subjects tested negative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Thus, we further focused on the virus from the family Bunyaviridae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1002369-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002369.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis of novel bunyavirus proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic trees were generated by comparing the translated amino acid sequences of individual sequence reads to the corresponding sequences from known bunyaviruses using a neighbor-joining method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The horizontal-line distance represents the number of sites at which the two compared sequences are different. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Bootstrap values deduced from 1000 replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>A: C361 fragment (Accession number HQ412604). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>B: FTLS bunyavirus (Henan isolate), Segment L (Accession number HQ642766). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>C: FTLS bunyavirus (Henan isolate), Segment M (Accession number HQ642767). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>D: FTLS bunyavirus (Henan isolate), Segment S (Np) (Accession number HQ642768). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>E: FTLS bunyavirus (Henan isolate), Segment S (Ns) (Accession number HQ642768). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1002369.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Confirmation of the presence of the novel virus in patients' sera </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Using specifically designed RT-PCR primers, we detected viral RNA in 223 of the 285 acute serum samples tested (Table 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The specificity of the RT-PCR was confirmed by sequencing selected PCR products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>None of the 80 sera from patients with respiratory diseases or the 50 sera from healthy subjects was positive using the novel virus-specific RT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="ppat-1002369-t005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002369.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Detection of novel FTLS bunyavirus-specific IgG antibody and viral RNA by IFA and RT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="ppat-1002369-t005-5" xlink:href="ppat.1002369.t005"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label>a</label><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>: Days were counted based on the onset of symptoms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Isolation of the novel virus </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Six acute serum samples that tested positive for the novel bunyavirus by specific RT-PCR were inoculated onto Vero E6 cells, and four virus strains were isolated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The initial CPE analysis showed rounded refractile cells 2–4 days after inoculation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>CPE did not progress in the initial cultures, but appeared slightly at 24 hours in subsequent passages (Figure 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>RT-PCR revealed the presence of RNA for the novel bunyavirus in all four virus strains, and all isolates reacted with the serum of a convalescent patient in IFA (Figure 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>In addition, electron microscopy showed the presence of virus particles approximately 80–90 nm in diameter—a size compatible with a bunyavirus (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Virus particles were presumably localized to the Golgi apparatus (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1002369-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002369.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Vero E6 cells inoculated with acute serum specimens from patients with FTLS. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>The typical early CPE seen with novel bunyavirus isolates from patients with FTLS is shown in part A (×40). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Mock-inoculated Vero cells are shown in part B (×40). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Infected Vero cells reacted with the serum of a convalescent FTLS patient in an indirect IFA in part C (×400). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1002369.g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1002369-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002369.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Thin-section electron microscopy of novel FTLS-associated bunyavirus Grown in Vero E6 Cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1002369.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3f"><title><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Confirmation of the isolated virus by direct sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Genome sequencing of one isolate (HN01) revealed three segments of negative polarity, single-stranded RNA, including a large segment (L; GenBank HQ642766), a medium-sized segment (M; GenBank HQ642767), and a small segment (S; GenBank HQ642768). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The deduced amino acid sequence of the L segment had the highest homology (34%, E value  = 3×10−163) to RNA polymerase of the Uukuniemi virus of the Phlebovirus genus, whereas the M segment had the highest homology (26%, E value  = 8×10−55) to glycoprotein genes of the Punta Toro virus in the Phlebovirus genus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Of the two proteins encoded by the ambisense S segment, one had the highest homology to nucleocapsid protein (39%, E value  = 3×10−40) of the Rift Valley Fever virus, and the other had the highest homology to nonstructural protein genes (24%, E value  = 0.049) of the Punique Virus, both of which belong to the Phlebovirus genus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Collectively, these findings confirm that this virus belongs to the Phlebovirus genus of Bunyaviridae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>During the revision of this manuscript, some new sequences of SFTSV (severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome) were released. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>A comparison of these new SFTSV sequences with the sequence of this novel virus showed that they were highly homologous (&gt;99% identity). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Using sequences of Phlebovirus available in GenBank, a phylogenetic analysis showed that, although most closely related to the Uukuniemi virus of the Phlebovirus genus (34%, 24%, and 29% of maximum identity, respectively, for segment L, M, S at maximum query coverage), the three genomic segments of the novel virus, along with the SFTSV sequences, were highly divergent (Figure 1B–1E). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3g"><title><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Antibody response to the bunyavirus </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>IgG antibodies to the novel bunyavirus were detected in 80 of 285 acute-phase serum samples from patients with FTLS (Table 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Of 95 patients from whom paired acute- and convalescent-phase sera were available, 52 had seroconversions and 21 had greater than 4-fold increases in antibody titer to the virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Six had less than a 4-fold increase in antibody titer to the virus, but all paired sera tested positive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Sixteen patients tested negative to the virus, suggesting that some non-FTLS patients with similar symptoms were included in this study, a situation that is not surprising given that FTLS is a newly emerging disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>The acute-phase sera of four patients from whom the virus was isolated tested negative for IgG antibody to the virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>All convalescent sera obtained 2 months later from the same four patients contained IgG antibody to the virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>None of the 130 sera from patients with respiratory diseases or healthy subjects had detectable antibody. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Since 2007, there has been an increase in reported cases of FTLS in Xinyang City, Henan Province. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>These patients were tentatively diagnosed as having A. phagocytophilum infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>However, only a few (8.4%, 24/285) such patients had evidence for A. phagocytophilum infection, and none of the 285 patients tested positive for the many other pathogens capable of causing similar clinical and laboratory manifestations that were also investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>These findings suggested novel infectious agents, including viruses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Traditionally, virus culture is very important for identifying an unknown viral infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Before performing the Illumina sequencing strategy, we attempted viral and rickettsial culture with DH82 and BHK cell lines, but the lack of an obvious CPE led us to initially abandon this approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Here, mass sequence data obtained by Illumina sequencing revealed four virus families that appeared only in FTLS patient sera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Among these four virus families, viruses from the Parvoviridae and Bunyaviridae families reportedly can cause signs of FTLS and be transmitted by arthropods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>However, only one sample from a pool of ten samples tested positive for bocavirus by PCR, suggesting that bocavirus from the Parvoviridae is not likely involved in FTLS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>For viruses in the Bunyaviridae family, the incidence of infection is closely linked to vector activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>For example, tick-borne viruses are more common in the late spring and late summer when tick activity peaks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Human infections with certain Bunyaviridae, such as Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever virus, are associated with high levels of morbidity and mortality [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Considering the tick-bite history of many FTLS patients, we focused on Bunyaviridae family viruses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The entire Bunyaviridae family contains more than 300 members arranged in four genera of arthropod-borne viruses (Orthobunyavirus, Nairovirus, Phlebovirus and Tospovirus) and one genus (Hantavirus) of rodent-borne viruses [30], [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>The Phlebovirus genus currently comprises 68 antigenically distinct serotypes, only a few of which have been studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The 68 known serotypes are divided into two groups: the Phlebotomus fever group (the sandfly group, transmitted by Phlebotominae sandflies) comprises 55 members, and the Uukuniemi group (transmitted by ticks) comprises the remaining 13 members. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Of these 68 serotypes, eight are linked to disease in humans, including the Alenquer, Candiru, Chagres, Naples, Punta Toro, Rift Valley fever, Sicilian, and Toscana viruses [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Phleboviruses have tripartite genomes consisting of a large (L), medium (M), and small (S) RNA segment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>In screening for unknown viruses, species hits alone likely carry little weight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Thus, we used all sequences in the family Bunyaviridae for our analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>A 168-bp fragment of the polymerase gene with the lowest E-value and high sequence identity was used as the sequence of the unknown virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>This virus sequence was detected in all 10 pooled samples, indicating that the virus is involved in FTLS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>After detecting a possible novel bunyavirus through high-throughput Illumina sequencing, we inoculated Vero cell lines, which are known to be sensitive to phleboviruses, with sera from six positive patients and were subsequently able to detect the virus by RT-PCR [30], [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Although the CPE was modest, RT-PCR confirmed the infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Genome sequencing was performed and a phylogenetic analysis of the genome sequence showed that this virus clustered into the Phlebovirus branch, but was divergent from other known phleboviruses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>These results confirm the novelty of this virus within the Phlebovirus genus of the family Bunyaviridae [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, virus size and propagation in cells were similar to that of the bunyaviruses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>PCR and serological tests were performed to further test the causal link between the new virus and FTLS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Although we have not completely fulfilled Koch's postulates, evidence implicating this new bunyavirus in the outbreak of the disease among patients with FTLS is compelling. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>In view of the fact that the disease is caused by a novel bunyavirus, and taking into account that the disease was first discovered in Henan (HN), we propose the name "Henan Fever" for the FTLS disease cause by the novel virus (proposed name “Henan Fever Virus” [HNF virus]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Since the submission of this manuscript, a bunyavirus was identified as the cause of FTLS in Chinese patients from other regions of China, and the authors have named this virus “SFTSV” to indicate that it is the cause of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>After release of the GenBank sequences referred to in the Yu paper, we compared the sequences of SFTSV with those of FTLSV and found that they were nearly identical (&gt;99% identity). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>As we first identified the syndrome in 2007 and described the presence of the virus in patients between 2007 and 2010, we suggest that the name “HNF virus” should take precedence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>The most distinctive feature of the current work includes the use of an unbiased metagenomic approach for viral pathogen discovery that facilitated the rapid creation and implementation of standard culture, serological, and molecular diagnostic approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>However, there are other differences between the results described here and those reported by Yu et al; notably, we observed slight, but distinctive, CPE in Vero cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>The reason for the failure to observe CPE in Vero cells infected with the “SFTSV” bunyavirus [37], whose genome is nearly identical to that of bunyavirus isolated from our FTLS patients, is unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Perhaps this reflects the fact that the ensuing CPE is not dramatic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Alternately, this could indicate the existence of distinct viral strains that vary in pathogenicity, virulence, and possibly even disease manifestations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>This is an area of active study in our laboratories. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>The discovery of this new virus will assist in the rapid diagnosis of this disease and help to distinguish it from other diseases caused by pathogens such as A. phagocytophilum, E. chaffeensis, Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever virus, Hantavirus, dengue virus, Japanese encephalitis virus, and Chikungunya virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the availability of the new virus will facilitate the future development of new therapeutic interventions, such as vaccines and drugs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1002369.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Sensitivity and dynamic range of real-time PCR in the detection of bunyavirus RNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>To evaluate sensitivity of our RT-PCR, a real-time PCR was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Serial dilutions of in vitrobtranscribed bunyavirus RNA sequences were tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>A wide linear range (from 5 copies to 5×107 copies of control RNA per reaction) was detected in this assay. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="ppat.1002369.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>We thank Xiaohui Li and the BGI Illumina sequencing team for facilitating this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>We would like to thank Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Stephen Dumler for helpful advice regarding the identification and diagnosis of human granulocytic anaplasmosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>We thank Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Zhang Ying and Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Stephen Dumler for critical reading of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>This work was sponsored by Infectious Diseases Special Project, Minister of Health of China (2008ZX10004–001-B, 2009ZX10004–103, 2009ZX10004–109), Henan Medical Science Project (200702016) and China-Australia Health and HIV/AIDS Facility (EID35). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>Reference</title><ref id="ppat.1002369-He1"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>1 HeJGChengZXWuJBYangXXLiQ 2006 The Epidemiological Investigation on a human to human anaplasmosis infection in South Anhui Province in 2006. World J Infect 5 343 347  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Xu1"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>2 XuBLChenHMZhuQZhangJXiaSL 2006 The Epidemiological Investigation on the First Outbreak of Tsutsugamushi Disease in Henan Province. Henan J Prev Med 17 3  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Wen1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>3 WenBJianRZhangYChenR 2002 Simultaneous Detection of Anaplasma marginale and a New Ehrlichia Species Closely Related to Ehrlichia chaffeensis by Sequence Analyses of 16S Ribosomal DNA in Boophilus microplus Ticks from Tibet. J Clin Microbiol 40 3286 3290 12202567 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Du1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>4 DuP 1982 Medical experimental virology. Shanghai Shanghai Association of Microbiology 211 212  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Dumler1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>5 DumlerJSChoiKSGarcia-GarciaJCBaratNSScorpioDG 2005 Human granulocytic anaplasmosis and Anaplasma phagocytophilum. Emerg Infect Dis 11 1828 1834 16485466 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Eng1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>6 EngTRHarkessJRFishbeinDBDawsonJEGreeneCN 1990 Epidemiologic, clinical, and laboratory findings of human ehrlichiosis in the United States, 1988. JAMA 264 2251 2258 2214103 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-MOH1"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>7 MOH of the people's republic of China 2008 Guide for Human granulocytic anaplasmosis control. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.moh.gov.cn/publicfiles/business/htmlfiles/mohbgt/pw10805/200804/31429.htm">http://www.moh.gov.cn/publicfiles/business/htmlfiles/mohbgt/pw10805/200804/31429.htm</ext-link>  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Paul1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>8 PaulSDianaS 2001 Dictionary of Microbiology and Molecular Biology. Chichester John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd 1 4 3rd edition.  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Meiyu1"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>9 MeiyuFHuoshengCCuihuaCXiaodongTLianhuaJ 1997 Detection of flaviviruses by reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction with the universal primer set. Microbiol Immunol 41 209 213 9130232 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Bai1"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>10 BaiZLiuLTuZYaoLLiuJ 2008 Real-time PCR for detecting circulating dengue virus in the Guangdong Province of China in 2006. J Med Microbiol 57 1547 1552 19018028 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Xie1"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>11 XieRHXuFZhuHPChengYKFuGM 2009 Development and evaluation of TaqMan-based one-step reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction assay for the detection of Japanese encephalitis virus. Zhonghua Liu Xing Bing Xue Za Zhi 30 277 280 19642386 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Santhosh1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>12 SanthoshSRParidaMMDashPKPateriyaAPattnaikB 2007 Development and evaluation of SYBR Green I-based one-step real-time RT-PCR assay for detection and quantification of Chikungunya virus. J Clin Virol 39 188 193 17553740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Kang1"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>13 KangXLiYLiuHLinFCaiX 2010 A duplex real-time reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction assay for the detection of Western Equine Encephalitis virus and Eastern Equine Encephalitis virus. Virol J 7 284 20977706 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Chinikar1"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>14 ChinikarSGoyaMMShirzadiMRGhiasiSMMirahmadiR 2008 Surveillance and laboratory detection system of Crimean-Congo haemorrhagic fever in Iran. Transbound Emerg Dis 55 200 204 18666963 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Suzuki1"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>15 SuzukiABisordiILevisSGarciaJPereiraLE 2004 Identifying rodent hantavirus reservoirs, Brazil. Emerg Infect Dis 10 2127 2134 15663849 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Garcia1"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>16 GarciaSCranceJMBillecocqAPeinnequinAJouanA 2001 Quantitative Real-Time PCR detection of Rift Valley Fever virus and its application to evaluation of antiviral compounds. J Clin Microbiol 39 4456 4461 11724861 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Jin1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>17 JinQ 2001 Medical Molecular Virology. Beijing Science Press 1st edition. 659  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Peiris1"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>18 PeirisJSMLaiSTPoonLLGuanYYamLY 2003 Coronavirus as a possible cause of severe acute respiratory syndrome. Lancet 361 1319 1325 12711465 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Franchini1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>19 FranchiniGCollaltiEAryaSKFenyöEMBiberfeldG 1987 Genetic analysis of a new subgroup of human and simian T-lymphotropic retroviruses: HTLV-IV, LAV-2, SBL-6669, and STLV-IIIAGM. AIDS Res Hum Retroviruses 3 11 17 3040052 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-CoxFoster1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>20 Cox-FosterDLConlanSHolmesECPalaciosGEvansJD 2007 A Metagenomic Survey of Microbes in Honey Bee Colony Collapse Disorder. Science 318 283 17823314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Finkbeiner1"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>21 FinkbeinerSRAllredAFTarrPIKleinEJKirkwoodCD 2008 Finkbeiner Metagenomic Analysis of Human Diarrhea: Viral Detection and Discovery. PLoS Pathog 4 e1000011 18398449 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Palacios1"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>22 PalaciosGDruceJDuLTranTBirchC 2008 A New Arenavirus in a Cluster of Fatal Transplant-Associated Diseases. N Engl J Med 358 991 998 18256387 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-WoodsLtCol1"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>23 Woods Lt ColJB 2005 USAMRIID's Medical Management of Biological Casualties Handbook.  Fort Detrick, Maryland U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Army Medical Institute of Infectious Diseases 143 144 6th edition.  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Li1"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>24 LiRLiYKarstenKWangJ 2008 Sequence analysis SOAP: short oligonucleotide alignment program. BIOINFORMATICS 24 713 714 18227114 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Bohlander1"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>25 BohlanderSKEspinosaR3rdLe BeauMMRowleyJDDíazMO 1992 A method for the rapid sequence-independent amplification of microdissected chromosomal material. Genomics 13 1322 1324 1505965 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Altschul1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>26 AltschulSFMaddenTLSchäfferAAZhangJZhangZ 1997 Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs. Nucleic Acids Res 25 3389 3402 9254694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Li2"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>27 LiWGodzikA 2006 Cd-hit: a fast program for clustering and comparing large sets of protein or nucleotide sequences. Bioinformatics 22 1658 1659 16731699 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Huang1"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>28 HuangXMadanA 1999 CAP3: a DNA sequence assembly program. Genome Res 9 868 877 10508846 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Sloots1"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>29 SlootsTPMcErleanPSpeicherDJArdenKENissenMD 2006 Evidence of human coronavirus HKU1 and human bocavirus in Australian children. J Clin Virol 35 99 102 16257260 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Bishop1"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>30 BishopDHCalisherCHCasalsJChumakovMPGaidamovichSY 1980 Bunyaviridae. Intervirology 14 125 143 6165702 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Jin2"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>31 JinQ 2001 Medical Molecular Virology. Beijing Science Press 1st edition. 528  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Ewing1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>32 EwingBHillierLWendlMCGreenP 1998 Base-calling of automated sequencer traces using phred. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Accuracy assessment. Genome Res 8 175 185 9521921 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Swofford1"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>33 SwoffordDL 1998 PAUP*.Phylogenetic Analysis Using Parsimony (*and Other Methods).  Sunderland, Massachusettes Sinauer Associates  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Wootton1"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>34 WoottonSCKimDSKondohYChenELeeJS 2011 Viral infection in acute exacerbation of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 183 1698 1702 21471095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Greene1"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>35 GreeneCEAddieDD 2006 Feline parvovirus infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>In: Greene CE (ed). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Infectious Diseases of the Dog and Cat. St. Louis: Saunders Elsevier 78-88  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Mayo1"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>36 MayoMA 2002 Virus taxonomy-Houston 2002. Arch Virol 147 1071 1076 12021875 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1002369-Yu1"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>37 YuXJLiangMFZhangSYLiuYLiJD 2011 Fever with Thrombocytopenia Associated with a Novel Bunyavirus in China. N Engl J Med 364 1523 1532 21410387 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
