
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Parasitol Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Parasitol Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JPR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Parasitology Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2090-0023</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2090-0031</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3512318</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2012/849132</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>New Frontiers in Schistosoma Genomics and Transcriptomics </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nahum</surname><given-names>Laila A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mourão</surname><given-names>Marina M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>Guilherme</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Genomics and Computational Biology Group, Centro de Pesquisas René Rachou (CPqRR), Instituto Nacional de Ciência e Tecnologia em Doenças Tropicais, Fundação Oswaldo Cruz (FIOCRUZ), 30190-002 Belo Horizonte, MG, Brazil</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Centro de Excelência em Bioinformática (CEBio), Fundação Oswaldo Cruz (FIOCRUZ), 30190-110 Belo Horizonte, MG, Brazil</aff><aff id="I3"><sup>3</sup>Faculdade Infórium de Tecnologia, 30130-180 Belo Horizonte, MG, Brazil</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Guilherme Oliveira: <email>oliveira@cpqrr.fiocruz.br</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editor: Sergio Costa Oliveira </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>2012</volume><elocation-id>849132</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>8</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 Laila A. Nahum et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Schistosomes are digenean blood flukes of aves and mammals comprising 23 species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Some species are causative agents of human schistosomiasis, the second major neglected disease affecting over 230 million people worldwide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Modern technologies including the sequencing and characterization of nucleic acids and proteins have allowed large-scale analyses of parasites and hosts, opening new frontiers in biological research with potential biomedical and biotechnological applications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Nuclear genomes of the three most socioeconomically important species (S. haematobium, S. japonicum, and S. mansoni) have been sequenced and are under intense investigation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial genomes of six Schistosoma species have also been completely sequenced and analysed from an evolutionary perspective. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, DNA barcoding of mitochondrial sequences is used for biodiversity assessment of schistosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Despite the efforts in the characterization of Schistosoma genomes and transcriptomes, many questions regarding the biology and evolution of this important taxon remain unanswered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>This paper aims to discuss some advances in the schistosome research with emphasis on genomics and transcriptomics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>It also aims to discuss the main challenges of the current research and to point out some future directions in schistosome studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Schistosomatidae (Platyhelminthes: Digenea) includes several digenetic endoparasites with complex life cycles, whose developmental stages alternate between intermediate (freshwater gastropods) and definitive hosts (birds, reptiles, fishes, and mammals) [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>These parasites differ from other blood flukes in having separate sexes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Another important feature is the increased longevity (over 5 years) of the Schistosoma species in the human host [1]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Schistosoma, the avian and mammalian blood flukes, is the best studied genus of Schistosomatidae [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Several species are described, six of which infect humans causing schistosomiasis: S. haematobium, S. intercalatum, S. japonicum, S. malayensis, S. mansoni, and S. mekongi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Other species are known to infect a broad range of mammals such as hippopotamus, rodents, carnivores, and ruminant animals like buffalo, cattle, goat, lechwe, and sheep. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Some hybrid species are reported [1–4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>For example, S. mattheei, more commonly found in cattle, is believed to form hybrids between S. mattheei and S. haematobium thus increasing its snail and definitive host range [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Schistosomiasis, a chronic and debilitating disease, is considered by the World Health Organization as one of the most serious public health issues and the second most prevalent tropical disease with high morbidity in the world [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Schistosomiasis is endemic in 77 countries [6] and its transmission is dependent on the existence and distribution of intermediate hosts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>It is estimated that 237 million people require treatment worldwide and that 600 to 779 million people live in endemic areas, under infection risk [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Yet, exacerbating this scenario, this disease is responsible for the loss of 1.7 to 4.5 millions of years of life in the world, measured by disability-adjusted life years (DALY) [7], one of the highest indexes among all the neglected tropical diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Control of schistosomiasis represents a great challenge and it is based on drug treatment (Praziquantel), snail control, improved sanitation, and health education [5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The development of powerful and scalable methods to analyse nucleic acids and proteins has changed the way biological data is surveyed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The application of such technologies, together with the development of powerful computational tools and methods, have expanded our perspective of schistosome biology and allowed a better understanding of processes such as host-parasite interaction [8–10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>This paper aims to discuss some advances in schistosome research with emphasis on genomics and transcriptomics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>First, we summarize the current status of sequencing projects of nuclear and mitochondrial genomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>We also discuss some aspects of evolutionary genomics and biodiversity of schistosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Then, we present key findings in transcriptomic analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Finally, we point out the main challenges of the current research and suggest some future directions in Schistosoma genomic and transcriptomic studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>2. Schistosoma Genomics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In order to strengthen traditional methods and provide new information to improve success towards schistosomiasis control, the scientific community joined efforts to assess the Schistosoma genomic information, starting in 1994, as an initiative of WHO/TDR (UNICEF-UNDP-World Bank-WHO Special Programme for Research and Training in Tropical Diseases) [11, 12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>At that time, only a few hundred expressed sequence tags (ESTs) from S. mansoni were available [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The WHO/TDR support opened the possibility to generate data that could be translated into new tools for schistosomiasis diagnostics and treatment, representing the “kickoff” of Schistosoma nuclear genome studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Nuclear Genomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The karyotype of known Schistosoma species comprises seven pairs of autosomes and one pair of sex chromosomes (female = ZW, male = ZZ), ranging in size from 18 to 73 megabases (Mb) [14, 15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The nuclear genome of three Schistosoma species was sequenced (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The S. japonicum (Anhui isolate) and S. mansoni (Puerto Rico isolate) genomes were decoded and simultaneously published as an initiative of the Wellcome Trust Sanger Center Institute in collaboration with the Institute for Genomic Research (TIGR) and the Schistosoma japonicum Genome Sequencing and Functional Analysis Consortium [16, 17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Recently, the S. haematobium (Egyptian isolate) genome was sequenced opening new possibilities in comparative genomics of schistosomes [18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>S. haematobium, S. japonicum, and S. mansoni carry a nuclear genome of 385, 397, and 363 Mb composed by approximately, 13,073, 13,469, and 10,852 protein-coding genes, respectively [16–19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>It is worth to mention that the number of predicted protein-coding genes does not reflect the genome structure per se, but the actual state of analyses of the different draft genome data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The genetic linkage map of S. mansoni was obtained and allowed the refinement of the genome sequencing data providing a means for gene discovery and gene function analysis [20, 21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>More importantly, it has allowed the identification of genetic loci that determine important traits such as host specificity, virulence, and drug resistance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>In fact, although the quality and annotation of the S. mansoni genome sequence data have been greatly improved (see below); the corresponding data of S. haematobium and S. japonicum are still considered drafts [16–19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Their genome sequences are distributed in a large number of contigs; therefore extensive work is required. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Constant data refinement is necessary to provide a reliable comprehension of the genome and gene models and to provide a curated annotation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The S. mansoni genome annotation has been improved by combining different sequencing strategies [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Such strategies include new assembly of existing capillary reads supplemented with an additional ~90,000 fosmid and BAC end sequences, deep sequencing of clonal DNA (NMRI strain, Puerto Rican origin) using 108-based paired reads on Illumina Genome Analyzer IIx platform, and RNA-seq data of different parasite life stages. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Progress on the knowledge of S. mansoni genome features is still expanding, especially with the application of the next-generation sequencing platforms and single nucleotide polymorphism typing methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>For instance, 14 new microsatellite markers were recently identified by de novo assembly of massive sequencing reads; these new features can be employed for pedigree studies [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Yet, newer sequencing technologies will allow for the development of population genomics studies of field, laboratory, and clinical isolates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>As a result of the availability of the Schistosoma genome sequence data, comparative analyses across different species became possible bringing together different areas of research [21, 23, 24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Comparative genomics of three Schistosoma species revealed several conserved features such as the overall GC content, sequence identity, presence of repetitive elements, and synteny [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>This genome-wide analysis corroborates previous genetic studies and supports the evolutionary hypothesis of S. haematobium and S. mansoni as the most related species, followed by S. japonicum, to the exclusion of other Trematoda such as Clonorchis, Fasciola, and Schmidtea. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial Genomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial genes have been used as molecular markers for species and strain identification, which is key to a variety of studies such as phylogenetics, population genetics, biogeography, and molecular ecology [25–29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Besides helping to elucidate the evolutionary relationships among taxa, mitochondrial genes have been successfully applied into epidemiological studies, monitoring, and control of microbes, parasites, and vectors of medical and socioeconomic importance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The analysis of the whole mitochondrial genome of diverse taxa has changed the perspective of such studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The mitochondrial genome of six Schistosoma species was sequenced (Table 1) including S. haematobium (NC_008074), S. japonicum (NC_002544), S. mansoni (NC_002545), S. malayensis, S. mekongi (NC_002529), and S. spindale (NC_008067) [27, 30–32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>These genomes range in size from 13,503 to 16,901 bp and encode 36 genes comprising two ribosomal genes (large and small subunit rRNA genes), and 22 transfer RNA (tRNA) genes, as well as 12 protein-encoding genes (atp6, cob, cox1–3, nad1–6, and nad4L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The atp8 gene, commonly found in other phyla, is absent from Platyhelminthes, whose mitochondrial genomes have been analysed [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Moreover, each Schistosoma mitochondrial genome contains a long noncoding region that is divided into two parts by one or more tRNA genes, which is found in other Platyhelminthes and vary in length according to each taxon. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Comparative mitogenomics have revealed a highly conserved gene order among distinct Platyhelminthes with the exception of some Schistosoma species [25, 30–33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The mitochondrial genome of the Asian schistosomes, S. japonicum and S. mekongi, displays the same gene order as other Digenea and Cestoda [25, 32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the gene order in the mitochondrial genome of S. haematobium, S. mansoni, and S. spindale is strikingly different from other taxa [25, 30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The unique gene order rearrangements identified in these species constitute valuable information to the reconstruction of the phylogenetic relationships of Schistosoma and other Platyhelminthes (Section 3.1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Evolutionary Genomics and Biodiversity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Evolutionary Genomics of Schistosoma </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The use of genomic data is valuable to the understanding of the evolutionary history of Schistosoma especially due to the absence of fossil records. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Molecular markers have been used to test hypotheses in a variety of Schistosoma phylogenetic, phylogeographic and epidemiological studies [4, 25, 34–36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Traditionally, these markers include the nuclear ribosomal RNA genes (18S, 5.8S, and 28S) and the internally transcribed spacer (ITS) region besides a number of mitochondrial genes (cob, cox1–3, nad1–6, etc.). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Based on mitochondrial data from different studies, a standard phylogeny of 23 Schistosoma species was proposed [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Six clades were identified that correlate with the geographic distribution of the species analysed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>These clades include (1) the S. japonicum complex (S. japonicum, S. malayensis, S. mekongi, S. ovuncatum, and S. sinensium) found in Central and South Eastern Asia; (2) the S. hippopotami clade (S. edwardiense and S. hippopotami) distributed in Africa; (3) the proto-S. mansoni clade (S. incognitum and S. turkestanicum) in Central Asia, Near East, and Eastern Europe; (4) the S. mansoni clade (S. mansoni and S. rodhaini) found in Africa and South America; (5) the S. haematobium clade (S. bovis, S. curassoni, S. guineensis, S. haematobium, S. intercalatum, S. kisumuensis, S. leiperi, S. margrebowiei, and S. mattheei) occurring in different parts of Africa; (6) the S. indicum clade (S. indicum, S. nasale, and S. spindale) found in India and South Asia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>There are divergent opinions concerning the origin of the genus Schistosoma and its intermediate snail host [25, 37–39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The “out of Asia” hypothesis is the most generally accepted, indicating a migration followed by dispersion of these parasites from Asia to Africa [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>In this regard, studies of molecular phylogeny suggested that the genus Schistosoma had its origin in Asia and (at least two descendants) colonized the African continent independently, where they easily radiated, becoming exclusive parasites of planorbid snails. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Returning to Asia, the parasites diversified into groups of species, characterized by the position of the spike in the eggs [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The molecular phylogeny of seven Schistosoma species suggested that schistosomes were endoparasites of rodents and ruminants and were transmitted to the first hominids in Africa as a migration to savanna areas occurred [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>However, in order to better define the Schistosoma origin, there is a need to sample a broader range of species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Most of the widely accepted Schistosoma phylogenies are primarily based on sequence alignments of mitochondrial genes such as cox1–3, and nad1–6, [25, 30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Other studies use changes in the mitochondrial gene order as phylogenetic markers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Indeed, these gene rearrangements, considered to be rare evolutionary events, have been applied to an increasing number of studies (cf. [41]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>As mentioned before, major changes in the mitochondrial gene order were identified in some Schistosoma species (Section 2.2), more specifically in the African clades (S. mansoni and S. haematobium) and the S. indicum group (S. spindale). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>This provides further evidence for the Asian ancestry of schistosomes and corroborates the concept of the reinvasion of Asia by members of the S. indicum group from Africa [27, 30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Besides reconstructing the phylogenetic relationships of diverse taxa, the evolutionary framework has been applied to improve functional annotation of genes and gene products, as well as to study gene/protein family evolution [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Phylogenomics has allowed the identification and characterization of all eukaryotic protein kinases encoded in the S. mansoni genome and improved the functional annotation of over 40% of them, highlighting the molecular diversity of these enzymes [42, 43]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>A phylogenetic analysis was also employed in the classification of S. mansoni histone proteins, which play a key role in epigenetic modifications that might reflect the parasite complex lifestyle [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>By applying an evolutionary framework to analyse a large sequence dataset from a broad range of organisms, functional annotation of the S. mansoni histone proteins was improved. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Moreover, phylogenomics has unraveled the distinct evolutionary histories of three expanded endopeptidase families in S. mansoni [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>This analysis included members of the metallopeptidase M8, serine peptidase S1, and aspartic peptidase A1 families, which were originated from successive events of gene duplication followed by divergence in the parasite lineage after its diversification from other metazoans. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Other protein families such as nuclear receptors and antioxidants have been characterized in S. mansoni by applying evolutionary and functional approaches [46, 47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The identification of SmNR4A, a member of the nuclear receptor subfamily 4, and its relatedness to the human homologs were corroborated by phylogenetic analysis [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>This study also demonstrated that SmNR4A expression was regulated throughout parasite development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Thioredoxin and glutathione systems, involved in a variety of cellular processes including antioxidant defense, differ in parasitic and free-living Platyhelminthes [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>By applying different phylogenetic methods and experimental testing, it has been shown that the canonical enzymes of such systems were lost in the parasitic lineages. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>DNA Barcoding for Biodiversity Assessment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The availability of sequencing data from mitochondrial genomes from closely related taxa to Schistosoma has provided a basis for studies ranging from phylogenetic systematics to molecular ecology and so forth [27, 29, 48, 49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Importantly, it allowed the assessment of molecular markers prior to broad scale sampling by comparing data from individual genes versus completely sequenced mitochondrial genomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Data from African and Asian schistosomes were compared to an S. mansoni intraspecific dataset showing a positive correlation between polymorphism and species divergence [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>A positive correlation rather than random distribution was identified for all mitochondrial genes with the exception of cox1 and nad1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, partial sequences of cox1 have been shown not to be the ideal marker for either species identification or population studies of Schistosoma species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Instead, authors have suggested the use of cox3 and nad5 sequences for both phylogenetic and population studies of such species [27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>DNA barcoding was performed for samples of S. haematobium using cox1 and nad1 as molecular markers [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The results supported the identification of group 1 and 2 haplotypes based on phylogenetic analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Moreover, no change in genetic diversity was detected across samples collected over different time points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>This approach allowed the development of new assays based on group-specific PCR primers and SNaPshot probes to assist genetic screening of schistosome isolates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Another study employing mitochondrial sequences was performed in Schistosoma cercariae harvested from Biomphalaria choanomphala as part of parasitological and malacological surveys for S. mansoni across Lake Victoria [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>DNA barcoding of cercarial samples revealed the presence of hybrid species between S. mansoni and S. rodhaini, which is typically found in small mammals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the phylogenetic analysis identified a new sublineage within S. rodhaini. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>DNA barcoding studies are underway for an increasing number of Schistosoma species (Table 1), whose data is made available through the Barcode of Life Database (BOLD) system (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.boldsystems.org/">http://www.boldsystems.org/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>This initiative includes contributors from the Biodiversity Institute of Ontario, Canada, and the University of New Mexico, USA, among others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Other Schistosomatidae genera are subject to DNA barcoding analysis such as Allobilharzia, Austrobilharzia, Bilharziella, Bivitellobilharzia, Dendritobilharzia, Gigantobilharzia, Griphobilharzia, Heterobilharzia, Macrobilharzia, Orientobilharzia, Ornithobilharzia, Schistosomatium, and Trichobilharzia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Advances in DNA barcoding of a broader range of Schistosomatidae will create a framework for species identification from environmental and clinical samples as well as specimens deposited in biological collections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Moreover, DNA barcoding analysis will help reconstructing the evolutionary relationships across different Platyhelminthes and ultimately improve our understanding of parasite biology and evolution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>4. Schistosoma Transcriptomics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Transcriptomic analyses are valuable not only for studies of differential regulation in gene expression, but also for the identification of splicing variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>These approaches have proved to be essential in the identification of gene-coding regions during the process of genome annotation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>In this section, we aim to review the achievements in Schistosoma transcriptomic studies that range from the whole organism and tissue analyses to those performed at the cellular level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Transcriptomics in physiological conditions and in response to a variety of treatments are investigated with respect to the interaction with the host as well as other environments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>This section summarizes the accomplishments of gene function studies and the diverse techniques that are being employed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec4.1"><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>4.1. Schistosoma Transcriptomics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>A fine tuning in gene expression of parasites must occur to enable them to survive in such a complex and extremely diverse milieu, adapting to diverse environments as evading the immune system and, at the same time, exploiting different hosts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Transcriptomic studies came along allowing a temporal and quantitative analyses of gene expression, which are crucial to completely exploit different datasets and assess parasite biology at the molecular level. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Aiming to elucidate the differential regulation on the Schistosoma transcriptomics, a large number of projects employed diverse strategies, such as the ones using expressed sequence tags (ESTs) [50], open reading frame expressed sequence tags (ORESTEs) [51], and serial analysis of gene expression (SAGE) [52, 53]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The increasing number of projects resulted in the production of a vast amount of sequence data and their availability in public databases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>It is noteworthy that only S. japonicum, S. mansoni and, not until very recently, S. haematobium had some of their transcriptome explored (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>4.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Exploring the Transcriptome </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The large number of transcriptome projects accelerated the studies in this area by providing means to the use of complementary approaches, especially microarray analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Together, these approaches have been used to answer a wide range of questions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>In the early years, microarray datasets conceived the profile of gene expression between genders of Schistosoma species such as S. japonicum and S. mansoni [54–56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>This greatly extended the number of known sex-associated genes and also provided new insights into changes in gene expression promoted by parasite pairing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>In addition, gender biased alternative splicing patterns were observed, which are perhaps involved in the generation and maintenance of the sexual dimorphism [57]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Later, studies profiled the S. mansoni gene expression in different life stages broadening our understanding of factors controlling schistosome development [8, 53, 58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>While comparing different parasite life stages, information acquired from microarray datasets highlighted putative antischistosome candidate molecules to be used as vaccine targets including Dyp-type peroxidases, fucosyltransferases, G-protein coupled receptors, leishmanolysins, tetraspanins, and the netrin/netrin receptor complex [59]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Some of these candidates (fucosyltransferases, leishmanolysins, and tetraspanins) are members of protein families, which are expanded in the S. mansoni predicted proteome in comparison with other metazoans as inferred by phylogenomic analysis (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://phylomedb.org/">http://phylomedb.org/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Leishmanolysins, which are members of the metallopeptidase M8 family, were analysed in detail corroborating the potential of these enzymes as future therapeutic targets [45]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Another study identified upregulated genes during the first five days of schistosomula development in vitro that are involved in blood feeding, tegument and cytoskeletal development, cell adhesion, and stress responses [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The highly upregulated genes included a tegument tetraspanin Sm-tsp-3, a protein kinase, a novel serine protease and serine protease inhibitor, and intestinal proteases belonging to distinct mechanistic classes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Other groups have analysed immunity towards Schistosoma using protein microarrays as a vaccine discovery tool. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>They selected a subset of proteins from genomic, transcriptomic, and proteomic data to perform experimental validation aiming at identifying novel antischistosome vaccine candidates [60, 61]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Recently, an elegant approach to investigate specific tissues such as gastrodermis and both genders reproductive tissues was performed by applying laser microdissection microscopy combined to microarray. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>These studies brought the perspective of expediting tissue-specific profiling [62, 63]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Additionally, expression profiles of S. japonicum were explored in studies comparing two Chinese isolates (Anhui and Zhejiang), as well as the Anhui Chinese and Philippines isolates [55, 64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Later, an interspecies study compared the S. japonicum and S. mansoni transcriptomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, despite their large phenotypic differences, there was a reduced number of differentially expressed genes based on the expression profile, which might reflect a limitation of the technique (preferential hybridization related to species polymorphisms) [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Bypassing these pitfalls, the next generation sequencing platforms allow exploiting expression data (RNA-seq) of any organism without previous knowledge of the genome or transcriptome and, further, will reveal new features of the parasite transcriptional landscape. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The most recent achievement in this area was the refinement of the genomics and transcriptomics data using a combination of Sanger capillary sequencing, next generation DNA sequencing, genetic markers, and RNA-seq data from several S. mansoni life stages [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>A previous study, explored the transcriptome of S. mansoni adult males obtaining 11 novel microexon genes (MEGs), as well as mapping 989 and 1196 contigs to intergenic and intronic genomic regions, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>This data could represent new protein-coding genes or noncoding RNAs (ncRNAs) [65]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Together, these approaches have significantly advanced our understanding of the dynamics parasite transcriptomes [9, 65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>However, there is a need to polish and translate sequence data and gene expression profiles into functional information by computational predictions and experimental characterization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The vast amount of available data opened a myriad of possibilities towards the elucidation of gene functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>It is time for data integration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><title><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>4.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Posttranscriptional Mechanisms </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Transcriptomics is also a key approach to study posttranscriptional regulatory mechanisms such as alternative and transsplicing [57, 66–68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>It is known that schistosomes use such mechanisms to keep their intricate life cycle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Alternative splicing of transcripts of secreted proteins, like MEGs and polymorphic mucin isoforms, has been largely studied in schistosomes [51, 66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>This posttranscriptional processing has been proposed as a distinct genetic system to generate protein variation that would allow parasite adaptation to the immune response of different hosts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Additionally, alternative splicing has been shown to generate protein variation involved in transcriptional control and splicing [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>In the case of SmCA150, a spliceosome interacting transcriptional cofactor, it could impact many other transcripts leading to several effects in the parasite, especially in sexual dimorphism. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Spliced leader (SL) transsplicing has been shown to be an important posttranscriptional regulation mechanism for S. mansoni [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>At least 11% of all transcripts has been described as undergoing transsplicing in this organism [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>SL-RNAs are small ncRNAs, products of small intronless genes, transcribed by DNA polymerase II and tandemly repeated in the genome [67]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Differently from nematodes, S. mansoni carries a single SL sequence, which is composed by 36 nucleotides with an 3′-terminal AUG codon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Although the role of transsplicing is poorly understood, there is an evidence suggesting that SL transsplicing would function providing an initiator methionine for translation initiation of some recipient mRNAs in Platyhelminthes [68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>This mechanism is also involved in the resolution of polycistronic operons in monocistronic transcripts in S. mansoni [19, 70]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4.4"><title><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>4.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Transcriptome Data and Gene Function </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Despite the great potential revealed by the increasing number of genome and transcriptome studies in schistosomes, there are still several Schistosoma species that remain neglected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the vast amount of data available in public databases, limited data has been decoded in functional studies and/or in the development of successful tools to fight schistosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>This slow evolving scenery might be due to several reasons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Some of them include the convolution of schistosomes life cycle, the complex interaction with their hosts, time and labor-demand functional studies, the difficulties to nurture the complete life cycle in vitro, and the absence of immortalized cell lines, which has delayed the development of transgenesis tools and models [71]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Lately, the posttranscriptional suppression of genes through RNA interference (RNAi) techniques has been a promise to fetch progress on new interventions for schistosomiasis and other helminthiases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>In 2003, two pioneer investigations marked the use of this technique in S. mansoni research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Simultaneously gene knockdown of glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) and a glucose transporter (SGTP1) in the larval stage (sporocysts) [72] and cathepsin B in adult worms [73] of S. mansoni were reported. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Currently, this powerful technique is widely used in schistosomes and has been employed in two studies of functional screening. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The first study encompassed the exposure of sporocysts by soaking parasites to dsRNA targeting 33 genes, from calcium binding proteins, transcription factors, to receptors, and antioxidant enzymes [74]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>In this work, despite the efficacy of this tool to deliver suppression of 11 different genes, it showed that, in S. mansoni, there is a gene-to-gene variability and exposure to dsRNA could trigger gene specific upregulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Later, in a different study using electroporation to expose schistosomula to dsRNA of 11 target genes (expressed in distinct tissues), the efficiency of RNAi in a target specific fashion was observed [75]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Other issues with the use of RNAi have been widely discussed, not only in schistosomes, but also in other helminth parasites, showing that care should be taken when conducting and evaluating such experiments [76]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Despite the difficulties in exploring gene function by RNAi in schistosomes, many interesting advances have been achieved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Many proteases (cathepsins and aminopeptidases) [77–79], kinases [80], multidrug resistance transporters [81], and type V collagen [82], among other proteins have been studied in diverse life stages of S. japonicum and S. mansoni. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Recently, this tool has been described targeting tetraspanin 2 in diverse developmental stages of S. haematobium indicating the RNAi feasibility in this species [83]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Tetraspanins belong to a family of integral membrane proteins present in the outer surface membranes of the parasite tegument. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Studies have shown that tetraspanins play important roles in the tegument development, maturation, or stability [84]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Importantly, the knockdown of peroxiredoxin [85] and thioredoxin glutathione reductase [86], antioxidant enzymes, were amongst the first reports of lethality after gene silencing in the parasite, demonstrating the potential of RNAi on drug target discovery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Moreover, enzymes such as glutathione-S-transferases (GST26 and GST28), peroxiredoxins (Prx1 and Prx2), and superoxide dismutase have been shown to play important roles in the protection of S. mansoni sporocysts in the host-parasite interplay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Knockdown of those targets increased parasite susceptibility to oxidative stress and to intermediate host immune cells as described elsewhere [87]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Recently, significant progress has been made in the area of schistosome transgenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Researchers are developing new tools for the introduction and expression of homologous or heterologous gene constructs via lentiviruses, replication-defective retroviruses, transposons, retrotransposons, and DNA plasmid vectors [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Sophisticated systems applied to assess gene function in the parasite are being achieved [88–91]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>To date, eggs and miracidia are indicated as the preferred life stages for successful transformation approaches in order to enter the germline [92]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>In summary, results from such independent studies have shown that schistosome transgenesis works in all the developmental stages tested and that some success has been achieved in integrating genes into the germline [88–92]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Thus, genetic knockdown experiments in schistosomes are possible. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Genomic and Transcriptomic Databases </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Altogether, the increasing information on schistosome genomes and transcriptomes is now raising the possibilities to better explore molecular techniques in the field of parasitology, genomics, and computational biology allowing the development of approaches to unravel mechanisms of parasite infection, host-parasite interaction, and so forth [21, 23, 24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>In order to accelerate both parasite research and development of effective tools for schistosomiasis diagnostics and treatment, user-friendly databases have been created and made publicly available to the scientific community [9, 93–95]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Here, we highlight some of these major resources. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>SchistoDB integrates genome and proteome sequence data along with functional annotation of genes and gene products of S. haematobium, S. japonicum, and S. mansoni [93]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>This resource also covers results from large-scale analysis including ESTs, metabolic pathways, and candidate drug targets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>HelmCoP (Helminth Control and Prevention) integrates functional, structural, and comparative genomics data of helminths from different taxonomic groups and distinct hosts (plant, animal, and human) [94]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>HelmCoP offers a comprehensive suite of structural and functional annotations to support comparative analyses and host-parasite interaction studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>GeneDB is an annotation database that brings together data from a broad range of pathogens and closely related organisms [95]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>GeneDB offers database-driven annotation tools and pipelines and includes manually curated information maintained by computational and biological scientists. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Collectively, these computational resources support biological and biomedical research and open new frontiers in evolutionary and functional genomics, transcriptomics, and proteomics of Schistosoma species and other parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Besides biodiversity assessment at the molecular level, these resources provide a framework for the identification and prioritization of vaccine and drug targets against human diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>As the scientific community progresses in data integration and interpretation, we will meet the goals of current and future initiatives to improve human health [9, 12, 23, 24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Conclusions and Future Directions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The -omics studies came along with the aim to fill the gaps of long-established approaches, enabling the use of a broad range of experimental and computational methods and contributing to dissect the biological basis of host-parasite interaction, diagnostics improvement, and the discovery of new drug and vaccine targets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Nuclear and mitochondrial genomes of some Schistosoma species were completely sequenced opening new frontiers for comparative analyses, which will improve our understanding of parasite biology and evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Other genomes to be analysed include Schistosoma species from each of the six clades currently recognized, and other representatives of the Schistosomatidae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Improving accuracy/quality of genome assembly and annotation will be crucial for such analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Despite the efforts in the characterization of genomes and transcriptomes of distinct Schistosoma species, many questions regarding the biology and evolution of this important taxon remain unanswered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>These difficulties might be due to the size of schistosome genomes (~10-times larger compared to protozoan parasites), the complexity of its life cycle, the presence of rare features in posttranscriptional regulation (e.g., transsplicing), and little integration of the current information available, among other reasons. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>There is an urgent need for data integration to help interpreting the massive amount of data generated over the years in this and other areas or research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The need for biocuration is essential to guide this process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>We envision that, in the future, more transcriptomic and proteomic data will be used to improve the understanding of the origin and evolution of Schistosomatidae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>The analysis of structural data generated by experimental or computational approaches will also shed light in the biodiversity of schistosomes at the molecular level. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, the availability of schistosome genome and transcriptome data has provided an unprecedented resource for many research areas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Limitations do exist and should be addressed to allow advances in understanding schistosome biology and evolution and ultimately support vaccine and drug development against schistosomiasis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>The research leading to these results has received funding from the European Community's Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007–2013 FP7/2007–2011) under Grant agreement number 241865. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>This work was also partially supported by the National Institutes of Health-NIH/Fogarty International Center (TW007012 to GO), the National Council for Research and Development, CNPq (CNPq Research Fellowship 306879/2009-3 to GO, INCT-DT 573839/2008-5 to GO, CNPq-Universal 476036/2010-0 to LAN, and 480576/2010-6 to MMM), and the Research Foundation of the State of Minas Gerais (FAPEMIG) (CBB-1181/08 and PPM-00439-10 to GO and CBB-APQ-01715/11 to MMM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The authors are very grateful to Larissa Lopes Silva and two anonymous reviewers for their constructive feedback and valuable suggestions, which greatly improved this paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>List of Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>atp6:</term><def><p>ATP synthase F0 subunit6</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>atp8:</term><def><p> ATP synthase F0 subunit 8</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>bp:</term><def><p>Base pairs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>cob:</term><def><p> Apocytochrome b</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>cox1:</term><def><p> Cytochrome c oxidase subunit 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>cox1–3:</term><def><p> Cytochrome c oxidase subunit 1 to 3</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DALY:</term><def><p> Disability-adjusted life years</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>dbEST:</term><def><p> Database of expressed sequence tags</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>dsRNA:</term><def><p> Double strand DNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ESTs:</term><def><p> Expressed sequence tags</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MEGs:</term><def><p> Microexon genes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>nad1–6:</term><def><p> NADH dehydrogenase subunit 1 to 6</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>nad4L:</term><def><p> NADH dehydrogenase subunit 4L</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ncRNAs:</term><def><p> Noncoding RNAs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ORESTEs:</term><def><p> Open reading frame expressed sequence tags</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RNAi:</term><def><p> RNA interference</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RNA-seq:</term><def><p> RNA sequencing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SAGE:</term><def><p> Serial analysis of gene expression</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SL:</term><def><p> Spliced leader</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TDR:</term><def><p> Special Programme for Research and Training in Tropical Diseases</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UNDP:</term><def><p> United Nations Development Programme</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UNICEF:</term><def><p> United Nations Children's Fund</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WHO:</term><def><p> World Health Organization</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>1GryseelsBSchistosomiasisInfectious Disease Clinics of North America201226238339722632645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>2HuyseTWebsterBLGeldofSBidirectional introgressive hybridization between a cattle and human schistosome speciesPLoS Pathogens2009592-s2.0-70349655084e1000571 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>3KrugerFJEvansACDo all human urinary infections with Schistosoma mattheei represent hybridization between S. haematobium and S. mattheei?Journal of Helminthology19906443303322-s2.0-00250943662149382 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>4SteinauerMLBlouinMSCriscioneCDApplying evolutionary genetics to schistosome epidemiologyInfection, Genetics and Evolution20101044334432-s2.0-77951972821 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>5FenwickAWebsterJPSchistosomiasis: challenges for control, treatment and drug resistanceCurrent Opinion in Infectious Diseases20061965775822-s2.0-3375050814217075334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>6World Health OrganizationWeekly Epidemiological Record201287th editionWHO </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>7World Health Organization, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/healthinfo/global_burden_disease/estimates_regional_2002_original/en/">http://www.who.int/healthinfo/global_burden_disease/estimates_regional_2002_original/en/</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>8GobertGNApplications for profiling the schistosome transcriptomeTrends in Parasitology20102694344392-s2.0-7795591841620605744 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>9MourãoMMGrunauCLoverdePTJonesMKOliveiraGRecent advances in Schistosoma genomicsParasite Immunology2012342-31511622-s2.0-8485701920822145587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>10SwainMTLarkinDMCaffreyCR Schistosoma comparative genomics: integrating genome structure, parasite biology and anthelmintic discoveryTrends in Parasitology201127125555642-s2.0-8285516501422024648 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>11OliveiraGFrancoGVerjovski-AlmeidaSThe Brazilian contribution to the study of the Schistosoma mansoni transcriptomeActa Tropica20081082-31791822-s2.0-5704910574818554565 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>12LoVerdePTHiraiHMerrickJMLeeNHEl-SayedN Schistosoma mansoni genome project: an updateParasitology International20045321831922-s2.0-184273527115081950 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>13FrancoGRAdamsMDSoaresMBSimpsonAJGVenterJCPenaSDJIdentification of new Schistosoma mansoni genes by the EST strategy using a directional cDNA libraryGene199515221411472-s2.0-00289318997835692 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>14SimpsonAJGSherAMcCutchanTFThe genome of Schistosoma mansoni: isolation of DNA, its size, bases and repetitive sequencesMolecular and Biochemical Parasitology1982621251372-s2.0-00204601086182465 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>15GrossmanAIShortRBCainGDKaryotype evolution and sex chromosome differentiation in schistosomes (trematoda, schistosomatidae)Chromosoma19818434134302-s2.0-00197904497327052 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>16BerrimanMHaasBJLoverdePTThe genome of the blood fluke Schistosoma mansoni Nature200946072533523582-s2.0-6765078961819606141 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>17ZhouYZhengHChenYThe Schistosoma japonicum genome reveals features of host-parasite interplayNature200946072533453512-s2.0-6765078653019606140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>18YoungNDJexARLiBWhole-genome sequence of Schistosoma haematobium Nature Genetics20124422212252-s2.0-003568745322246508 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>19ProtasioAVTsaiIJBabbageAA systematically improved high quality genome and transcriptome of the human blood fluke Schistosoma mansoni PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases201261e14552-s2.0-84856579279 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>20CriscioneCDValentimCLLHiraiHLoVerdePTAndersonTJCGenomic linkage map of the human blood fluke Schistosoma mansoni Genome Biology2009106, article R712-s2.0-67650627644 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>21TaitAGenetics and genomics converge on the human blood flukeGenome Biology2009106, article 2252-s2.0-70349565606 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>22LepesantJMJRoquisDEmansRCombination of de novo assembly of massive sequencing reads with classical repeat prediction improves identification of repetitive sequences in Schistosoma mansoni Experimental Parasitology201213044704742-s2.0-8485910136622381218 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>23WilsonRAAshtonPDBraschiSDillonGPBerrimanMIvensAOming in on schistosomes: prospects and limitations for post-genomicsTrends in Parasitology200723114202-s2.0-3384569590817097923 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>24BrindleyPJMitrevaMGhedinELustigmanSHelminth genomics: the implications for human healthPLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases2009310, article e5382-s2.0-70350476885 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>25LawtonSPHiraiHIronsideJEJohnstonDARollinsonDGenomes and geography: genomic insights into the evolution and phylogeography of the genus Schistosoma Parasites &amp; Vectors20114, article 1312-s2.0-79960023624 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>26WaeschenbachAWebsterBLLittlewoodDTJAdding resolution to ordinal level relationships of tapeworms (Platyhelminthes: Cestoda) with large fragments of mtDNAMolecular Phylogenetics and Evolution20126338348472-s2.0-8485980743222406529 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>27ZarowieckiMZHuyseTLittlewoodDTJMaking the most of mitochondrial genomes—markers for phylogeny, molecular ecology and barcodes in Schistosoma (Platyhelminthes: Digenea)International Journal for Parasitology20073712140114182-s2.0-3454803182417570370 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>28ZhaoG-HLiJSongH-QA specific PCR assay for the identification and differentiation of Schistosoma japonicum geographical isolates in mainland China based on analysis of mitochondrial genome sequencesInfection, Genetics and Evolution2012125102710362-s2.0-84860362429 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>29StothardJRAmeriHKhamisISBlairLNyandindiUSKaneRAParasitological and malacological surveys reveal urogenital Schistosomiasis on Mafia Island, Tanzania to be an imported infectionActa Tropica. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>In press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>30LittlewoodDTJLockyerAEWebsterBLJohnstonDALeTHThe complete mitochondrial genomes of Schistosoma haematobium and Schistosoma spindale and the evolutionary history of mitochondrial genome changes among parasitic flatwormsMolecular Phylogenetics and Evolution20063924524672-s2.0-3364605514216464618 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>31LeTHBlairDMcManusDPMitochondrial genomes of parasitic flatwormsTrends in Parasitology20021852062132-s2.0-003656925411983601 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>32LeTHHumairPFBlairDAgatsumaTLittlewoodDTJMcManusDPMitochondrial gene content, arrangement and composition compared in African and Asian schistosomesMolecular and Biochemical Parasitology2001117161712-s2.0-003483976611551632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>33VallèsYBooreJLLophotrochozoan mitochondrial genomesIntegrative and Comparative Biology20064645445572-s2.0-3374735070521672765 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>34AttwoodSWStudies on the parasitology, phylogeography and the evolution of host-parasite interactions for the snail intermediate hosts of medically important trematode genera in Southeast AsiaAdvances in Parasitology2010734054402-s2.0-7795460124720627149 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>35WebsterBLSouthgateVRTimothyDLittlewoodJA revision of the interrelationships of Schistosoma including the recently described Schistosoma guineensisInternational Journal for Parasitology20063689479552-s2.0-3374711695216730013 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>36SteinauerMLMwangiINMainaGMInteractions between natural populations of human and rodent schistosomes in the lake victoria region of Kenya: a molecular epidemiological approachPLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases200824, article e2222-s2.0-48949118027 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>37AgatsumaTOrigin and evolution of Schistosoma japonicum Parasitology International20035243353402-s2.0-034423448414665391 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>38MorganJATDejongRJSnyderSDMkojiGMLokerES Schistosoma mansoni and Biomphalaria: past history and future trendsParasitology2001123supplementS211S2282-s2.0-003521609311769285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>39RollinsonDKaukasAJohnstonDASimpsonAJGTanakaMSome molecular insights into schistosome evolutionInternational Journal for Parasitology199727111282-s2.0-00309909759076525 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>40DespresLImbert-EstabletDCombesCBonhommeFMolecular evidence linking hominid evolution to recent radiation of schistosomes (Platyhelminthes: Trematoda)Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution1992142953042-s2.0-00269583821342945 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>41NahumLAPereiraSLPhylogenomics, protein family evolution, and the tree of life: an integrated approach between molecular evolution and computational intelligenceStudies in Computational Intelligence20081222592792-s2.0-44649139858 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>42AndradeLFNahumLAAvelarLGAEukaryotic Protein Kinases (ePKs) of the Helminth Parasite Schistosoma mansoni BMC Genomics201112, article 2152-s2.0-79955662226 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>43AvelarLGNahumLAAndradeLFOliveiraGFunctional diversity of the Schistosoma mansoni tyrosine kinasesJournal of Signal Transduction2011201111 pages603290 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>44AndersonLPierceRJVerjovski-AlmeidaS Schistosoma mansoni histones: from transcription to chromatin regulation; An in silico analysisMolecular and Biochemical Parasitology201218321051142-s2.0-8485959336522414701 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>45SilvaLLMarcet-HoubenMZerlotiniAGabaldónTOliveiraGNahumLAEvolutionary histories of expanded peptidase families in Schistosoma mansoni Memorias do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz201110678648772-s2.0-8225517412022124560 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>46WuWNilesEGHiraiHLoVerdePTEvolution of a novel subfamily of nuclear receptors with members that each contain two DNA binding domainsBMC Evolutionary Biology20077, article 272-s2.0-33847614245 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>47OteroLBonillaMProtasioAVFernándezCGladyshevVNSalinasGThioredoxin and glutathione systems differ in parasitic and free-living platyhelminthsBMC Genomics2010111, article 2372-s2.0-77950663440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>48StandleyCJStothardJRDNA barcoding of Schistosoma cercariae reveals a novel sub-lineage within Schistosoma rodhaini from Ngamba Island Chimpanzee Sanctuary, Lake VictoriaJournal of Parasitology20129851049105122448675 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>49WebsterBLCulverwellCLKhamisISMohammedKARollinsonDStothardJRDNA barcoding of Schistosoma haematobium on Zanzibar reveals substantial genetic diversity and two major phylogenetic groupsActa Tropica. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>In press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>50FrancoGRValadãoAFAzevedoVRabeloEMLThe Schistosoma gene discovery program: state of the artInternational Journal for Parasitology20003044534632-s2.0-003410306710731568 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>51Verjovski-AlmeidaSDeMarcoRMartinsEALTranscriptome analysis of the acoelomate human parasite Schistosoma mansoni Nature Genetics20033521481572-s2.0-014150705412973350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>52OjopiEPBOliveiraPSLNunesDNA quantitative view of the transcriptome of Schistosoma mansoni adult-worms using SAGEBMC Genomics20078, article 1862-s2.0-34547592402 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>53WilliamsDLSayedAABernierJProfiling Schistosoma mansoni development using serial analysis of gene expression (SAGE)Experimental Parasitology200711732462582-s2.0-3544893993217577588 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>54FitzpatrickJMHoffmannKFDioecious Schistosoma mansoni express divergent gene repertoires regulated by pairingInternational Journal for Parasitology20063610-11108110892-s2.0-3374711499816875694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>55MoertelLMcManusDPPivaTJYoungLMcInnesRLGobertGNOligonucleotide microarray analysis of strain- and gender-associated gene expression in the human blood fluke, Schistosoma japonicum Molecular and Cellular Probes20062052802892-s2.0-3374604598616647836 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>56WaisbergMLoboFPCerqueiraGC Schistosoma mansoni: microarray analysis of gene expression induced by host sexExperimental Parasitology200812043573632-s2.0-5504910226318822286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>57DeMarcoROliveiraKCVenancioTMVerjovski-AlmeidaSGender biased differential alternative splicing patterns of the transcriptional cofactor CA150 gene in Schistosoma mansoni Molecular and Biochemical Parasitology200615021231312-s2.0-3375062197816904200 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>58JollyERChinCSMillerSGene expression patterns during adaptation of a helminth parasite to different environmental nichesGenome Biology200784, article R652-s2.0-34548133272 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>59FitzpatrickJMPeakEPerallySAnti-schistosomal intervention targets identified by lifecycle transcriptomic analysesPLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases2009311, article e5432-s2.0-73449104210 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B61"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>60DriguezPDoolanDLLoukasAFelgnerPLMcManusDP Schistosomiasis vaccine discovery using immunomicsParasites and Vectors201031, article 42-s2.0-77649324484 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B62"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>61McWilliamHEGDriguezPPiedrafitaDMcManusDPMeeusenENTNovel immunomic technologies for schistosome vaccine developmentParasite Immunology20123452762842-s2.0-8485951702522486551 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B63"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>62GobertGNMcManusDPNawaratnaSMoertelLMulvennaJJonesMKTissue specific profiling of females of Schistosoma japonicum by integrated laser microdissection microscopy and microarray analysisPLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases200936, article e4692-s2.0-68349119283 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B64"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>63NawaratnaSSKMcManusDPMoertelLGobertGNJonesMKGene atlasing of digestive and reproductive tissues in Schistosoma mansoni PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases2011542-s2.0-79955866214e1043 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B65"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>64HopeMDukeMMcManusDPA biological and immunological comparison of Chinese and Philippine Schistosoma japonicum International Journal for Parasitology19962633253322-s2.0-00300097418786224 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B66"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>65AlmeidaGTAmaralMSBeckedorffFCFKitajimaJPDeMarcoRVerjovski-AlmeidaSExploring the Schistosoma mansoni adult male transcriptome using RNA-seqExperimental Parasitology2011132122312-s2.0-7996021515221745473 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B68"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>66Verjovski-AlmeidaSDeMarcoRGene structure and splicing in schistosomesJournal of Proteomics2011749151515182-s2.0-7995325765721440689 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B69"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>67HastingsKEMSL trans-splicing: easy come or easy go?Trends in Genetics20052142402472-s2.0-1524436300415797620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B70"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>68ChengGCohenLNdegwaDDavisREThe flatworm spliced leader 3′-terminal AUG as a translation initiator methionineThe Journal of Biological Chemistry200628127337432-s2.0-3364486264116230357 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B67"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>69DavisREHardwickCTavernierPHodgsonSSinghHRNA trans-splicing in flatworms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Analysis of trans-spliced mRNAs and genes in the human parasite, Schistosoma mansoni The Journal of Biological Chemistry19952703721813218192-s2.0-00291439297665603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B71"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>70DavisREHodgsonSGene linkage and steady state RNAs suggest trans-splicing may be associated with a polycistronic transcript in Schistosoma mansoni Molecular and Biochemical Parasitology199789125392-s2.0-177444191009297698 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B72"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>71BrindleyPJPearceEJGenetic manipulation of schistosomesInternational Journal for Parasitology20073754654732-s2.0-3394717095017280677 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B73"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>72BoyleJPWuXJShoemakerCBYoshinoTPUsing RNA interference to manipulate endogenous gene expression in Schistosoma mansoni sporocystsMolecular and Biochemical Parasitology200312822052152-s2.0-003822246512742587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B74"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>73SkellyPJDa’daraAHarnDASuppression of cathepsin B expression in Schistosoma mansoni by RNA interferenceInternational Journal for Parasitology20033343633692-s2.0-003738642212705930 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B75"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>74MourãoMMDinguirardNFrancoGRYoshinoTPPhenotypic screen of early-developing larvae of the blood fluke, Schistosoma mansoni, using RNA interferencePLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases200938, article e5022-s2.0-70449507123 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B76"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>75ŠtefanicSDvořákJHornMRNA interference in Schistosoma mansoni schistosomula: selectivity, sensitivity and operation for larger-scale screeningPLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases2010410, article e8502-s2.0-78449236012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B77"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>76GeldhofPVisserAClarkDRNA interference in parasitic helminths: current situation, potential pitfalls and future prospectsParasitology200713456096192-s2.0-3424970842717201997 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B78"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>77CorrentiJMBrindleyPJPearceEJLong-term suppression of cathepsin B levels by RNA interference retards schistosome growthMolecular and Biochemical Parasitology200514322092152-s2.0-2394449330216076506 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B79"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>78MoralesMERinaldiGGobertGNKinesKJTortJFBrindleyPJRNA interference of Schistosoma mansoni cathepsin D, the apical enzyme of the hemoglobin proteolysis cascadeMolecular and Biochemical Parasitology200815721601682-s2.0-3804914869518067980 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B80"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>79RinaldiGMoralesMEAlrefaeiYNRNA interference targeting leucine aminopeptidase blocks hatching of Schistosoma mansoni eggsMolecular and Biochemical Parasitology200916721181262-s2.0-6764936133019463860 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B81"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>80SwierczewskiBEDaviesSJA schistosome cAMP-dependent protein kinase catalytic subunit is essential for parasite viabilityPLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases200938, article e5052-s2.0-70449507606 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B82"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>81KasinathanRSMorganWMGreenbergRMGenetic knockdown and pharmacological inhibition of parasite multidrug resistance transporters disrupts EGG production in Schistosoma mansoni PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases2011512e14252-s2.0-84855290515 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B83"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>82YangYJinYLiuPRNAi silencing of type v collagen in Schistosoma japonicum affects parasite morphology, spawning, and hatchingParasitology Research20121113125112572-s2.0-8486614130622638918 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B84"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>83RinaldiGOkatchaTIPopratiloffAGenetic manipulation of Schistosoma haematobium, the neglected SchistosomePLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases2011510e13482-s2.0-80055068038 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B85"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>84TranMHFreitasTCCooperLSuppression of mRNAs encoding tegument tetraspanins from Schistosoma mansoni results in impaired tegument turnoverPLoS Pathogens201064e10008402-s2.0-77953951982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B86"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>85SayedAACookSKWilliamsDLRedox balance mechanisms in Schistosoma mansoni rely on peroxiredoxins and albumin and implicate peroxiredoxins as novel drug targetsThe Journal of Biological Chemistry20062812517001170102-s2.0-3374519548016606626 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B87"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>86KuntzANDavioud-CharvetESayedAAThioredoxin glutathione reductase from Schistosoma mansoni: an essential parasite enzyme and a key drug targetPLoS Medicine200746e206 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B88"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>87MourãoMDMDinguirardNFrancoGRYoshinoTPRole of the endogenous antioxidant system in the protection of Schistosoma mansoni primary sporocysts against exogenous oxidative stressPLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases2009311, article e5502-s2.0-73449138216 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B89"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>88AyukMASuttiprapaSRinaldiGMannVHLeeCMBrindleyPJ Schistosoma mansoni U6 gene promoter-driven short hairpin RNA induces RNA interference in human fibrosarcoma cells and schistosomulesInternational Journal for Parasitology20114177837892-s2.0-7995566994721447344 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B90"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>89DuvoisinRAyukMARinaldiGHuman U6 promoter drives stronger shRNA activity than its schistosome orthologue in Schistosoma mansoni and human fibrosarcoma cellsTransgenic Research20122135115212-s2.0-8486088156721953124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B91"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>90RinaldiGSuttiprapaSTortJFFolleyAESkinnerDEBrindleyPJAn antibiotic selection marker for schistosome transgenesisInternational Journal for Parasitology20124211231302-s2.0-8486232686222155152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B92"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>91BeckmannSGreveldingCGPaving the way for transgenic schistosomesParasitology201213956516682-s2.0-8485938486021892995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B93"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>92RinaldiGEckertSETsaiIJGermline transgenesis and insertional mutagenesis in Schistosoma mansoni mediated by murine leukemia virusPLoS Pathogens20128716 pagese10028202-s2.0-84864591486 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B94"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>93ZerlotiniAHeigesMWangHSchistoDB: a Schistosoma mansoni genome resourceNucleic Acids Research2009371D579D5822-s2.0-5814919461418842636 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B95"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>94AbubuckerSMartinJTaylorCMMitrevaMHelmCoP: an online resource for Helminth functional genomics and drug and vaccine targets prioritizationPLoS ONE2011672-s2.0-79960107786e21832 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B96"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>95Logan-KlumplerFJDe SilvaNBoehmeUGeneDB-an annotation database for pathogensNucleic Acids Research201240D1D98D1082-s2.0-8486220815122116062 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Availability of genomic and transcriptomic data for Schistosoma species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Taxid: NCBI taxonomy identifier. ncDNA: nuclear DNA genome (SchistoDB.org). mtDNA: mitochondrial DNA genome (NCBI Organelle Genome Resources). ESTs: data from NCBI dbEST (release 120701, July 1, 2012). Barcoding: DNA barcoding used on cox1 sequences (BOLD Systems). *<italic>Schistosoma</italic> sp. BH-2009.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
