
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Dis Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Infect Dis Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IDR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Infectious Disease Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2036-7430</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2036-7449</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PAGEPress Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Pavia, Italy</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3123035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">idr.2010.e3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4081/idr.2010.e3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Corynebacterium macginleyi isolated from a corneal ulcer </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ruoff</surname><given-names>Kathryn L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Toutain-Kidd</surname><given-names>Christine M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>Muthiah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lalitha</surname><given-names>Prajna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>Nisha R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zegans</surname><given-names>Michael E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartzman</surname><given-names>Joseph D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Pathology, Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center, Lebanon, NH, USA;</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Surgery (section of Ophthalmology), Dartmouth Medical School, Hanover, NH, USA, and Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center, Lebanon, NH, USA;</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Aravind Eye Care System, India;</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>F.I. Proctor Foundation, University of California, San Francisco, CA, USA;</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Department of Ophthalmology, University of California, San Francisco, CA, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="FN1">Correspondence: Kathryn L. Ruoff, <addr-line>Department of Pathology (Microbiology), Dartmouth Hitchcock Medical Center, One Medical Center Drive, Lebanon, NH 03756, USA.</addr-line> E-mail: <email>kathryn.l.ruoff@Hitchcock.org</email></corresp><fn id="FN2" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Contributions: KLR and JDS were involved in the identification of the C. macginleyi isolate; KLR prepared the manuscript; CMTK and MEZ were involved in the patient's follow-up and treatment, as well as the preparation of the manuscript; MS, PL, and NRA were involved in the design of the study and overall management of the patient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>All authors have read and approved the final version of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="FN3" fn-type="conflict"><p><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Conflict of interest: the authors report no conflicts of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>03</day><month>2</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e3</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>08</day><month>2</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>2</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>©Copyright K.L. Ruoff et al., 2010</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License (by-nc 3.0).</license-p><license-p>Licensee PAGEPress, Italy</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="idr-2010-1-e3.pdf"/><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>We report the isolation of Corynebacterium macginleyi from the corneal ulcer culture of a patient, later enrolled in the Steroids for Corneal Ulcer Trial (SCUT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge this is the first published report from North America of the recovery of C. macginleyi from a serious ocular infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><title>Key words:</title><kwd><italic>corynebacterium macginleyi</italic></kwd><kwd>cornea</kwd><kwd>ulcer.</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="CASE"><sec id="S1"><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Case Report </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>An 84-year-old man with a previous history of Fuchs' endothelial dystrophy, Parkinson's syndrome, and bilateral cataract surgery presented to the Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center ophthalmology clinic with a two-day history of decreased vision, eye pain, and tenderness in his right eye. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>He denied a history of trauma or contact lens wear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>His Snellen visual acuity using his current glasses was 3/200 in his right eye and he had an intra-ocular pressure of 19 mmHg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Slit lamp examination revealed a para-central 2.5 mm epithelial defect overlying a 3.6 mm corneal ulcer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>There was minimal thinning of the corneal stroma and no hypopyon (see Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>However, an endothelial plaque of white blood cells underlying the ulcer and +1 anterior chamber cells were present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The patient's eyelids were notable for blepharitis and meibomitis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Figure 1.Photographs of the infected eye taken on the first day of treatment (E), after 3 weeks (3W), and after 3 months of follow-up (3M). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The arrow indicates the site of the ulcer (E and 3W) and the scar (3M). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Please note that the yellow-green coloration of the ulcer in photograph E is due to fluorescein drops used during examination of the patient's cornea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Staining with fluorescein indicates disruption of the corneal epithelium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Staining with fluorescein indicates disruption of the corneal epithelium. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Corneal scrapings were obtained and inoculated onto T-soy agar containing 5% sheep blood and chocolate agar (Remel, Lenexa, KS, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Growth at each inoculation point was noted on blood agar after incubation for 48 hours at 35°C in an atmosphere containing 3–5% CO2, but no growth occurred on chocolate agar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The small, slowly growing catalase-positive colonies were gray and non-hemolytic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Gram stains showed diphtheroidal gram-positive rods. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center is a study site for the Steroids for Corneal Ulcer Trial (SCUT), which is a multicenter National Eye Institute (NEI) funded trial investigating the question of whether topical corticosteroids improve the outcome of bacterial keratitis when used in conjunction with topical antibiotics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Because this patient met the enrollment criteria for this study, participation in the study was offered to him and he elected to enroll. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Consequently, he was treated according to the study protocol with topical 0.5% moxifloxacin hydrochloride applied every hour initially and the study medication, either topical 1% prednisolone phosphate or placebo, for three weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Patient enrollment in SCUT is ongoing and thus the nature of the treatment regimen that this patient received continues to remain masked to the clinical investigators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>At the end of the three weeks of treatment, the patient's vision in his right eye had improved to 20/320, and by three months it was back to the pre-ulcer vision at 20/100. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The catalase-positive gram-positive rod isolated from the patient's culture was identified as C. macginleyi by the API Coryne identification system (BioMerieux, Durham, NC, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The organism's profile number, 1100305, was noted previously1,2 as one of the profiles exhibited by the C. macginleyi strains isolated from ocular specimens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Growth of the organism on blood but not chocolate agar suggested a lipophilic nature as previously described for C. macginleyi.1 The organism's lipophilic behavior was demonstrated with Tween 80 (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA) supplemented media. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Growth was stimulated (colony size approximately 2 mm in diameter after 48 hours of incubation) on sheep blood agar plates that had been supplemented with 0.1 mL of sterile 10% Tween 80 compared to growth on non-supplemented blood agar (colony size approximately 0.5 mm after 48 hours of incubation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Growth also occurred on Tween-supplemented but not on unsupplemented chocolate agar. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The isolate was identified further by 16S rRNA gene sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Nucleic acid was prepared with PrepMan Ultra reagent (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA) and PCR was performed with a MicroSeq 500 kit (Applied Biosystems) according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>ExoSAP-IT (USB Co., Cleveland, OH, USA) was used to purify the PCR product, which was sequenced at the Dartmouth College Molecular Biology and Proteomic Core Facility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) GenBank BLAST program was used to identify homologous sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The sequence of our isolate displayed 99% similarity to sequences from a number of previously described C. macginleyi isolates (accession numbers AB359405, AB359393, AJ439345, X80499). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The patient's isolate displayed minimum inhibitory concentrations for penicillin, ciprofloxacin, tobramycin, and vancomycin of 0.016, 0.032, 0.064, and 0.5 µg/mL, respectively, when tested by the Etest method (AB Biodisk, Solna, Sweden) on sheep blood-supplemented Mueller Hinton agar (Remel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>These observations were similar to previously reported susceptibilities of the majority of C. macginleyi strains isolated from ocular specimens,1,3,4 but a recent report5 noted fluoroquinolone and sulbenicillin resistance in two ocular strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Isolates from other body sites4,6,7 have shown more resistant phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S2"><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Few reports of C. macginleyi isolated from clinical isolates have appeared since this species was proposed by Riegel and colleagues in 1995.8 The majority of isolates described have been recovered from conjunctival swab specimens,1–3,9 and C. macginleyi is thought to be a component of normal conjunctival flora that may function as an opportunistic pathogen in conjunctivitis as well as other ocular infections. C. macginleyi has rarely been associated with more serious ocular infections such as keratitis,5,10 and endophthalmitis.11 Three case reports described C. macginleyi as an agent of infection in non-ocular sites, including the urine of a patient with a permanent bladder catheter,4 an infected intravenous catheter,6 and a case of septicemia.7 The association of C. macginleyi infections with the presence of prosthetic abiotic materials as described above, suggests that bacterial biofilm formations on these surfaces may play a role in its pathogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>However, the presence of a bacterial biofilm has been documented only in the suture-related keratitis case described by Suzuki and colleagues.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Corynebacteria, for the most part, are susceptible to a wide array of antibiotics such as penicillins, macrolides, rifampicin, gentamicin, and fluoroquinolones,1,12 although one recent report from Japan showed that 11 out of 16 C. macginleyi ophthalmic isolates were resistant to fluoroquinolones.9 It is difficult to know why no C. macginleyi case has ever been reported in North America. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Identification techniques have evolved tremendously in recent years; the API Coryne system appears to be accurate for identification of this organism,1 which may have been characterized only to the genus level in the past. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Slow growth on blood agar of lipophilic diphtheroidal organisms isolated from ocular cultures should alert microbiologists to the possible presence of C. macginleyi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>This bacterial species seems to be encountered infrequently. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>For instance, in a report studying the normal bacterial flora of the conjunctiva, only four isolates out of the 25 corynebacteria identified were C. macginleyi.13 To our knowledge, this is also the first time that this bacterium has been identified in an eye isolate at Dartmouth Hitchcock Medical Center. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Finally, it is possible that infections caused by C. macginleyi are less noticeable since they are frequently successfully treated with a standard regimen of antibiotics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Our patient had at least two distinct risk factors for bacterial keratitis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>He had Fuchs' endothelial dystrophy, a dysfunction of the corneal endothelium that can lead to corneal edema, and compromise of the corneal epithelial barrier.14 Gaps in the integrity of the corneal epithelial layer caused by excessive contact lens wear, trauma, or diseases compromising the ocular surface such as Fuchs', are well known to predispose patients to bacterial corneal infection.15 Furthermore, Parkinson's disease has been reported to alter tear function in most patients, further compromising the ocular surface.16 Thus, our patient had an impaired ocular surface likely rendering his cornea particularly permissive to infection with what is normally a commensal organism, C. macginleyi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Because of the relatively small size of the ulcer, its location, and the good response to treatment, the patient's vision in the right eye returned to its pre-keratitis level (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>All reports of isolation of C. macginleyi published to date have originated in Europe, Australia, or Japan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>We document a case of corneal ulcer yielding C. macginleyi as the sole isolate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge the case reported here represents the first published account of clinical isolation of this organism in North America. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements:</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>the SCUT study (CMTK, MS, PL, NRA, and MEZ) is supported by the National Eye Institute (NEI, U10 EY015114). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>1FunkeGPagano-NiedererMBernauerWCorynebacterium macginleyi has to date been isolated exclusively from conjunctival swabsJ Clin Microbiol199836367039817893 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R2"><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>2JoussenAMFunkeGJoussenFCorynebacterium macginleyi: a conjunctiva specific pathogenBr J Ophthalmol2000841420211090486 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R3"><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>3GiammancoGMDi MarcoVPrioloICorynebacterium macginleyi isolation from conjunctival swab in ItalyDiag Microbio Infect Dis2002442057 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R4"><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>4VillanuevaJLDominguezARiosMJCorynebacterium macginleyi isolated from urine in a patient with a permanent bladder catheterScan J Infect Dis200234699700 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R5"><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>5SuzukiTIiharaHUnoTSuturerelated keratitis caused by Corynebacterium macginleyiJ Clin Microbiol2007453833617913935 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R6"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>6DoblerGBIHighly resistant Corynebacterium macginleyi as cause of intravenous catheter-related infectionEur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis20032272312582751 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R7"><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>7Villamil-CajotoIRodriguez-OteroLVillacian-VicedoM.JSepticemia caused by Corynebacterium macginleyi: a rare form of extraocular infectionInt J Infec Dis200812333517981483 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R8"><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>8RiegelPRuimeyRdeBrielDGenomic diversity and phylogenetic relationships among lipid-requiring diphtheroids from humans and characterization of Corynebacterium macginleyi spInt J Syst Bacteriol199545128337857793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R9"><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>9EguchiHKuwaharaTMiyamotoTHigh-level fluoroquinolone resistance in ophthalmic clinical isolates belonging to the species Corynebacterium macginleyiJ Clin Microbiol2008465273218077650 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R10"><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>10LyCNPhamJNBadenochPRBacteria commonly isolated from keratitis specimens retain antibiotic susceptibility to fluoroquinolones and gentamicin plus cephalothinClin Exp Ophthalmol2006344450 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R11"><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>11FerrerCRuiz-MorenoJRodriguezAPostoperative Corynebacterium macginleyi endophthalmitisJ Cataract Refract Surg2004302441415519105 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R12"><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>12SomodevillaADomingoDMartinezMCCorynebacterium macginleyi: susceptibility to 7 usual ophthalmic antibiotics19th European Congress of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious DiseasesHelsinki, Finland2009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R13"><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>13von GraevenitzASchumacherUBernauerWThe Corynebacterial Flora of the Normal Human Conjunctiva Is LipophilicCurr Microbiol200142372411400060 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R14"><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>14BorboliSColbyKMechanisms of disease: Fuchs' endothelial dystrophyOphthalmol Clin North Am200215172512064077 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R15"><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>15KeayLEdwardsJNaduvilathTMicrobial keratitis: predisposing factors and morbidityOphthalmology20001131091616360210 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R16"><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>16TamerCMelekIDumanTTear film tests in Parkinson's disease patientsOphthalmology2005112e3e3 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
