
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Med Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJMR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Indian Journal of Medical Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0971-5916</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0971-5916</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3028944</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21150009</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJMR-132-567</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Genomic approaches to coronary artery disease </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Padmanabhan</surname><given-names>Sandosh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hastie</surname><given-names>Claire</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prabhakaran</surname><given-names>Dorairaj</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dominczak</surname><given-names>Anna F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001"><italic>Institute of Cardiovascular and Medical Sciences, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, United Kingdom</italic></aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>*</label><italic>Centre for Chronic Disease Control, New Delhi, India</italic></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><italic>Reprint requests:</italic> Dr Sandosh Padmanabhan, Institute of Cardiovascular and Medical Sciences, University of Glasgow, 126 University Place, Glasgow G12 8TA, United Kingdom e-mail: <email xlink:href="sp24g@clinmed.gla.ac.uk">sp24g@clinmed.gla.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>132</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>578</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Indian Journal of Medical Research</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Coronary artery disease (CAD) is a leading cause of death and disability worldwide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In addition to lifestyle and environmental factors which are major aetiologic determinants, there is considerable familial clustering of the disease indicating a genetic component in its causation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Although the total genetic contribution to CAD risk can be quantified, the determination of the size and number of contributing effects is impossible without identifying all CAD susceptibility genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>However, despite extensive studies, strong evidence of a molecular genetic association with coronary artery disease or myocardial infarction remains elusive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Genome wide association studies have been successful in identifying robust associations of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP) with CAD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Identifying the causal variant and dissecting pathways linking these variants to disease process is a major challenge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Technologies from whole genome sequencing, proteomics, transcriptomics and metabolomics are now available to extend analysis to a more complete range of potential susceptibility variants, and to support more explicit modelling of the joint effects of genes and environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The availability of these high throughput technologies does not diminish the importance of rigorous phenotyping and appropriate study designs in all the endeavours to understand the aetiopathogenesis of CAD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Combining classical epidemiology with modern genomics will require collaborative efforts within the cardiovascular disease community at both bench and bedside and this will have the potential to expand our understanding of CAD and translate discoveries into clinically useful applications that will have a major impact on public health. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>Candidate gene</kwd><kwd>coronary artery disease</kwd><kwd>genetic associations</kwd><kwd>metabolomics</kwd><kwd>proteomics</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Coronary arery disease (CAD) is predicted to be the most common cause of death globally, including India, by 2020, when the 10 leading causes of disability-adjusted life-years (in descending order) are projected to be ischaemic heart disease, unipolar major depression, road traffic accidents, cerebrovascular disease, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, lower respiratory infections, tuberculosis, war injuries, diarrhoeal diseases, and HIV12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In India, this epidemiological transition is attributed to recent rapid economic and social changes leading to non-communicable diseases attaining the top spot for causing death and disability, and chronic diseases contributing to an estimated 53 per cent of deaths and 44 per cent of disability-adjusted life-years lost13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>By the year 2010, it is projected that 60 per cent of the world’s patients with heart disease will be in India2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>CAD also remains the number one cause of death in industrialised countries despite collective efforts to minimize attributable risk from known contributors to CAD such as hypertension, dyslipidaemia and smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The proportion of deaths due to non-communicable disease is projected to rise from 59 per cent in 2002 to 69 per cent in 20304. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The epidemiological transition needs not only country-wide health planning and preventive strategies, but also national collaborative research into molecular and genetic causation of these diseases in India. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Advances from cardiovascular research in genetic studies, expression profiling and proteomics will not reach their full potential unless translated to care of the individual patient, and this requires combining new molecular discoveries with epidemiological and screening tools. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The focus of this review is to first present the evidence for a genetic component to coronary artery disease then, describe the recent progress in genomic and other high throughput technologies in understanding the causation of atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease, and finally present the need for further research requiring the collaboration between clinicians, basic scientists and epidemiologists (Fig.). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F0001" position="float"><label>Fig</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Integrating epidemiological and “Omics” strategies in a translational framework for coronary artery disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJMR-132-567-g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec></SecTag><sec id="sec1-2"><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Genetic Basis of CAD </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>CAD comprises a spectrum of clinical diagnoses [e.g. angina, myocardial infarction (MI)] which are caused by atherosclerosis, a pervasive degenerative condition in which lipid and fibrous matrix is deposited in arterial vessel walls to form atheromatous plaques. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Rupture of unstable plaques in coronary arteries results in the release of thrombogenic material into the lumen of the vessel leading to coronary thrombosis, vessel occlusion, and subsequent infarction of the myocardium, a critical condition with high mortality5. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec2-1"><title/><sec id="sec3-1"><title><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Familial clustering </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The key factor that indicates the presence of a genetic component to atherosclerosis is the familial clustering of CAD67. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The strength of the association between parental history and CAD is similar to that found for other standard risk factors such as systolic BP, cholesterol and cigarette smoking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>A history of early CAD in a first degree relative approximately doubles the risk of CAD (RR 1.3-11.3)689. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In the Framingham Heart Study, parental history of premature coronary, cerebral vascular or peripheral vascular disease was a strong risk factor for CAD (OR=2.0 for men and 1.7 women) after adjustment for all classical risk factors7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In the INTERHEART study, family history of CAD after adjustment for nine classical risk factors was associated with an OR of 1.459. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Additionally, there is increasing evidence that some of the classical risk factors for atherosclerosis also have independent genetic components [lipids, BMI, BP, lipoprotein(a), homocysteine, type 2 diabetes, fibrinogen, C-reactive protein (CRP)]10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The extent to which the familial clustering of CAD can be explained by heritable quantitative variation in the classical risk factors such as cholesterol and BP is contentious, and the small but significant residual familial relative risk after regression on these conventional risk factors suggests the presence of unmeasured genetic risk factors, raising the possibility of a high level of genetic control by a small number of genes that control fundamental physiological systems67911. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Heritability </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>A 36 year follow up study of 21000 Swedish twins demonstrated concordance rates for acute myocardial infarction in monozygotic (MZ) twins of 0.26 among males and 0.27 among females. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>For dizygotic (DZ) twins the concordances were 0.20 for males and 0.16 for females12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The estimated heritability was 57 per cent among male twins and 38 per cent for female twins for CAD13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Such high heritabilities are supported by adoption studies showing a relative ris k of death in adoptees of 4.5 for death from vascular disease before the age of 50 yr of a biological parent compared to a relative risk of 3.0 for death of an adoptive parent14. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Further evidence for a moderate genetic influence on the risk of dying prematurely in adulthood, with only a small effect of the family environment was shown by higher mortality among biological parents who had children dying in the age range 25 through 64 yr for death from natural causes, infectious causes, vascular causes, and from all causes combined, with no significant effects for the adoptive parents15. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Mendelian forms of CAD </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Studies of rare Mendelian forms of CAD have shown how mutations in genes [low density lipoprotein receptor (LDLR), apolipoprotein B (ApoB), proprotein convertase subtilisin/kexin type 9 (PCSK9), low density lipoprotein receptor adaptor protein 1 (ARH), ATP-binding cassette, sub-family G (WHITE), member 5 (ABCG5), cytochrome P450, family 7, subfamily A, polypeptide 1 (CYP7A1)]10 involved in low-density lipoprotein and high-density lipoprotein metabolism/homeostasis can cause premature CAD, but these mutations are thought to explain a relatively minor fraction of familial CAD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>However studies of monogenic diseases have helped to unravel the molecular pathways that regulate cholesterol metabolism, resulting in the development of HMG-CoA-reductase inhibitors16. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Also, studies of two rare genetic lipid disorders, Tangier disease and sitosterolemia, have revolutionized our understanding of sterol transport1718. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>All these point to a multifactorial polygenic causation of CAD, with evidence that susceptibility genes for CAD might exist that are independent of hypercholesterolaemia or arterial hypertension or diabetes and may act by affecting an intermediate factor such as vascular inflammation, oxidative stress, thrombogenicity, arterial calcification, etc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>It is likely that susceptibility genes might be involved in novel biological pathways or be novel genes in well known pathways such as cholesterol metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The search and identification of genetic factors contributing to CAD is important to increase our understanding of CAD pathophysiology and develop new strategies for risk prediction and intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec1-3"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Genetic Architecture of CAD </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The success of CAD gene mapping is dependent on its genetic architecture which refers to the number of disease genes that exist, their allele frequencies, the risks that they confer, and the interactions between multiple genetic and environmental factors1920. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Although the total genetic contribution to CAD risk can be quantified, the determination of the size and number of contributing effects is impossible without identifying all CAD susceptibility genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The multiple risk factors for CAD themselves have their own genetic architecture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The heritabilities of some of the risk factors for CAD are considerable - total cholesterol (40 to 60%), HDL-cholesterol (45 to 75%), total triglycerides (40 to 80%), body mass index (25 to 60%), systolic blood pressure (50 to 70%), Lp(a) levels (90%), homocysteine levels (45%), type 2 diabetes (40 to 80%), fibrinogen (20 to 50%)10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Also, as CAD is rare before the age of 50 yr, it is unlikely to have an effect on reproductive success and hence less likely to have been subject to direct evolutionary selection pressure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Variants that confer susceptibility or protection for CAD might therefore have evolved neutrally in the past, and so could present at a wide range of frequencies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>This is the basis of the Common Disease/Common Variant (CDCV) hypothesis which holds that the genetic variants underlying complex traits occur with a relatively high frequency (&gt;1%), have undergone little or no selection in earlier populations and are likely to date back to &gt;100,000 years ago21.The other competing model is the Common Disease Rare Variant hypothesis, with an inverse relationship between the magnitude of genetic effect and allele frequency22. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>This model argues that diseases are common because of highly prevalent environmental influences, not because of common disease alleles in the population19. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>A review of candidate gene associations and recent genome wide association study results support the importance of common alleles in CAD2324. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>At odds with this, rare allelic variants of three candidate genes (ABCA1, APOA1, LCAT) that influence HDL levels, were jointly found to make a substantial contribution to the population distribution of HDL levels2526. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The most likely scenario would be that the allelic spectrum of the disease variants is the same as the general spectrum of all disease variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Under this neutral model, although most susceptibility variants are rare with minor allele frequencies (MAF) &lt;1 per cent, variants with MAF&gt;1 per cent would account for more than 90 per cent of the genetic differences between individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>It is plausible that these common variants might contribute significantly to those common diseases in which susceptibility alleles might not be under intense negative selection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec1-4"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Subject ascertainment and study designs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2-2"><title/><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The common methods used in the genetic dissection of complex diseases like CAD are linkage and association studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Linkage mapping (a gene hunting technique that attempts to identify gene regions that are found in people with disease more frequently than in those without the disease, by studying genetic markers of known chromosomal location that are co-inherited with the disease in a pedigree), which is a powerful tool for finding Mendelian disease genes, often produces weak, and sometimes inconsistent, signals in complex disease studies27. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Association mapping is another study design commonly used in candidate gene studies and is based on linkage disequilibrium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Linkage disequilibrium (LD) is the non-random association of alleles at two or more loci on a chromosome and results in the greater co-occurrence of two genetic markers on the same chromosome in a population than would be expected for independent markers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>To succeed in finding complex disease genes, a study must detect a relatively weak statistical signal, and hence study design flaws can potentially have a dramatic impact on the probability of success28. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Ascertainment criteria partitioning the presence or absence of CAD are a major challenge and have major implications on the power and success of gene mapping studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Studies of asymptomatic individuals have shown that atherosclerotic CAD is pervasive, but only a fraction of them will ever develop an MI, and this is influenced by haemodynamic modifiers or individual susceptibility to inflammation and plaque progression2930. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec3-4"><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Intermediate phenotypes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Many of the known risk factors for the development of CAD are genetically determined traits - LDL and HDL levels, high blood pressure, type 2 diabetes and metabolic syndrome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>A growing number of other plasma factors have also been identified that are associated with CAD risk, many of which are also strongly genetically determined [Lp(a), homocysteine and fibrinogen]10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Combined genetic and intermediate analysis with single, large study groups provides a means of comparing the risk that is attributable to genetically determined life-long variations in the measured intermediate phenotype with the expected increment in CAD risk that is based on observational epidemiological studies5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>This approach, sometimes referred to as “Mendelian randomisation”, could potentially discriminate between causal relationships and those that are due to confounding or “reverse causality”31. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Component phenotypes of atherosclerosis can be expected to reflect the influence of a smaller number of genes that should therefore have a larger effect size and increased study power. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>These phenotypes also provide surrogate endpoints in longitudinal studies and allow the classification of patients into more homogeneous groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Examples of quantitative vascular phenotypes include carotid intima-medial thickness, non invasive measures of endothelial function or arterial stiffness5. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3-5"><title><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Cases </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The selection of cases or ‘affected’ takes into consideration not only phenotypic definition to reduce phenotypic heterogeneity, but also manoeuvres to improve study power through enrichment of specific disease-predisposing alleles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>There is an argument for using related cases, as they are more likely to share a disease-causing variant in common than randomly selected cases, provided the data are analyzed after taking into account correlation between related individuals3233. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Individuals with CAD who have low risk profiles in terms of lifestyle factors will carry greater genetic loads and thus be more informative for genetic studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>One strategy adopted by researchers is to bias their recruitment strategy towards younger patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>For the myocardial infarction phenotype prematurity refers to age less than 45 for men or less than 50 yr for women for the index event. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>However, it is important to note that in India about 50 per cent of CHD-related deaths occur in people younger than 70 yr compared with only 22 per cent in the West2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Genetic enrichment can also be achieved by enrolling individuals with first degree relatives who are affected as cases34. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>There are important factors to be considered when selecting a CAD phenotype for study34. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>It is important to note that myocardial infarction represents a very small fraction of the individuals who have the CAD phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>A large proportion of people with CAD do not have anginal symptoms and are identified only through an abnormal routine exercise test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Patients who present for a coronary angiogram represent a bias of ascertainment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Also the coronary angiogram is an incomplete assessment which only shows the accumulation of plaque that results in narrowing of the arterial lumen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The complexity increases further when one considers multiple longitudinal angiographic studies that show an individual progressing from having slight (&lt;30%) narrowing to critical (&gt;70%) stenosis over a 6 month period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Thus it is important to acknowledge that the assessment of a “case” is only relevant to the actual time in which the study was performed and that this is a dynamic phenomenon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Safeguards are therefore needed to pre-empt the potential re-categorisation of a control to a case, and ensure that the defined phenotype is homogeneous as there are vast pathophysiological differences between the chronic accumulation of arterial plaque as compared with a sudden plaque rupture event with attendant thrombosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The phenotype of myocardial infarction, one of the manifestations of CAD, is more restrictive and has thus far proven more useful in identifying susceptibility genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>However, the diagnosis of MI does not imply a uniform pathogenic process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>A significant minority of patients with MI present with sudden cardiac death and never reach the hospital, leading to a survival bias. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Also an even larger proportion of patients have an acute coronary syndrome with a normal ECG or non specific ECG abnormalities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>There are important differences between ST segment elevation myocardial infarction which involves occlusive coronary thrombosis with more extensive myocardial necrosis, and non-ST segment elevation myocardial infarction which occurs with non-occlusive thrombosis and may result from more extensive collateral flow and results in less necrosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>These phenotypic differences may be associated with differences in genetic predisposition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3-6"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Controls </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The definition of controls or ‘unaffected’ is more challenging than cases3435. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>An ideal control might be conceived as an individual who has lived to greater than 90 yr and has undergone a post-mortem that shows completely normal coronary arteries, and the issues in addition to impracticality are bias introduced in terms of longevity of the controls and the different diagnostic criteria between cases and controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>From a practical point of view, it would be ideal to identify controls without having to subject individuals to an invasive assessment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>However, stress testing, even with adjunctive nuclear or echocardiographic imaging is not sensitive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Currently the gold standard technique is an invasive diagnostic angiogram which is expensive and carries a definite albeit low risk of morbidity and death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The definition of a normal angiogram is still unclear, and the appearance of a truly “normal” angiogram is not particularly common as compared with finding individuals who have minor irregularities with no frank luminal encroachment that would approximate a 10 per cent narrowing34. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Many of the patients with true “normal” angiograms have actually presented to cardiac catheterisation for evaluation of valvular heart disease, thus introducing a confounding factor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Also a normal angiographic study does not exclude small vessel disease, and it would be inappropriate to classify them as controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>It is also important that controls should not have other forms of atherosclerotic disease such as stroke or transient ischaemic attacks or peripheral vascular disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>One of the important considerations is matching cases and controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>There exists the distinct possibility that controls may, later in life, become cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>For reasons of genetic enrichment as described above, young cases are likely to be preferentially collected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>But comparison of young cases (who are less than 55 yr old) with aged (greater than 85 yr old) controls introduces potential confounding sources. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Examples of these are differential survival due to genes that are unrelated to CAD, genetic drift and mismatching for potential covariates5. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3-7"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Case-control, cohort or family designs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Using a positional cloning approach, linkage analysis using families of multiple affected individuals was very successful in identifying genes for Mendelian diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>However, it has been less successful in identifying genes for complex diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Recently genome wide association studies which have been successful in identifying replicated loci for common diseases have predominantly used a case-control approach, where samples of unrelated affected and unaffected individuals are ascertained from the study population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>While it is extremely easy to recruit unrelated cases and control, recruitment of families is resource intensive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>But it must be recognised that population and family studies have different strengths and weaknesses and must be viewed as complementary and not competitive3536. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>A key concern with case-control design is latent population substructure that will inflate type I error and care must be taken when attempting to reproduce these results in other populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Though there are statistical methods to correct for population substructure along with information from ancestry informative markers, these are only applicable to populations of European ancestry, these will correct only for ‘average’ genome wide measures of ethnic admixture and will not always eliminate spurious associations immediately adjacent to markers that are strongly informative about ancestry3537–39. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>There is clear evidence that analysis in African-descent populations is complicated by their greater haplotypic diversity and fine-scale geographical structure40. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Recent papers have demonstrated the difficulty of genetic analysis in the Hispanic or Latino populations due to subgroups with various amounts of contribution from ancestral Native-American, West African and European populations and the Wellcome Trust genome wide association (GWA) identified a substructure within the European-Caucasian population even within the UK243541–43. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The key advantage of family studies is that they are robust to population stratification36. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Though family based design is associated with some loss of power, in populations with greater diversity and substructure, this is more advantageous. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The additional benefits of family information are that it helps to refine the genetic model and risk estimates, control for the effects of shared environment and detect heterogeneity, imprinting, and epigenetic phenomena3644. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Finally if the underlying architecture favours the rare variant hypothesis, then one can expect extensive allelic and locus heterogeneity, and in this case family studies are preferred to case control studies44. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>One option for the efficient use of family data in such a setting is to restrict high-density scanning to a subset of pedigree members and then use information on patterns of chromosomal segregation derived from low-density genotyping in the remaining members to propagate genotypes through the family45. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The successful detection of gene-gene or gene-environment interactions is dependent on recruiting adequate sample sizes in the prospective cohort studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>In contrast to case-control studies which typically begin when disease cases have occurred, prospective cohort studies avoid this inherent bias by investigating a representative sample of the population before disease onset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>In terms of genetic main effects, 5000 incident cases are needed for a minimum detectable odds ratio (MDOR) of 1.5 with 80 per cent power and MAF=5 per cent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>For genotypic and environmental prevalences of 10 per cent and above, 10,000 cases are needed to provide adequate power for interaction effects with an MDOR greater than 2354647. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>These studies promise new insights into the genetic basis of continuous traits and enhanced opportunities for revealing pleiotropy, although low power remains an issue - especially for the detection of non-additive gene-environment interactions4647. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><sec id="sec1-5"><title><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Linkage Studies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Previous methods for determining genetic linkage of a complex disease relied chiefly upon the technique of genome wide scanning of microsatellites (short tandem repeat sequences). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>This required the laborious selection of hundreds of families, particularly sib pairs with MI or CAD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Using around 400 microsatellite markers distributed evenly across the genome, the goal was to identify a significant linkage peak defined by a logarithm of odds ratio (LOD) greater than 3.5 corresponding to a p&lt;10-6 indicating a gene that is in linkage disequilibrium (LD) near or even within the microsatellite region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>However, identifying disease causing genes interspersed within microsatellites has proved to be quite difficult and studies from different centres reported varying results - Finland (2q21.2-22 and Xq23-26)48, Germany (14q32.2)49, Iceland (13q12-13)50, US (1p34-36,3q13 and 5q31)51 and UK (2p11, 17p11-17q21)5253. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Genomic regions identified in the published linkage studies as being correlated with CHF are largely non-overlapping, suggesting genetic and/or phenotypic heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Two genes, ALOX5AP and MEF2A, have been identified by fine mapping studies following the original linkage analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The Icelandic locus was replicated in population-based studies from Iceland and England, with different haplotypes of the ALOX5AP gene (encoding 5-lipoxygenase activating protein) associated with CAD in the two countries, and the Icelandic haplotype was also associated with stroke in Iceland and in Scotland5054. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>MEF2A (myocyte enhancer factor 2A) a transcription factor expressed in coronary artery endothelium was identified by linkage analysis in a pedigree in which 13 members had CAD, nine of whom had MI55. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec1-6"><title><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Candidate genes studies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Candidate gene association studies often base selection of candidate genes on assumptions about biologically relevant genes, and hence these studies are biased against identification of novel genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>An overlap in inflammatory responses observed in chronic infection and atherosclerosis led to an interest in candidate genes for CAD that are involved in innate immunity56. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Among these, CD14, toll-like receptor 4 (TLR 4), were the first genes to show variable evidence of association with CAD susceptibility57–59. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>However, large association studies showed no association with susceptibility60. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Leukotriene A4 hydrolase (LTA4H) has also been shown to be associated with CAD, with striking evidence in African American patients and modest association among Europeans61. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>In a pioneering study62 of nearly 93,000 predominantly gene based SNPs in a Japanese case control cohort, polymorphisms in the lymphotoxin-α (LTA) gene, which encodes a member of the tumour necrosis factor (TNF) ligand family were found to be associated with susceptibility to myocardial infarction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>A larger case-control study however did not find any association63. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Despite some successes, single gene association studies remain problematic, with most being poorly replicable2364. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Because only a small proportion of variants will have significant effect sizes, these studies have a low a priori likelihood of identifying the important variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>However, as small scale studies are easy to carry out these have become numerous; some, by chance, yield a false positive association and there is evidence of publication bias in the literature that might enrich for false positives. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec1-7"><title><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Genome Wide Association (GWA) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Of the 3.1 billion base pairs in our genome, our inter-individuality is determined by only 0.1 per cent or approximately 3 million of those base pairs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>GWA studies are large scale association mapping using SNPs, making no assumptions of the genomic location or function of the causal variant and are a comprehensive approach to testing the hypothesis that common alleles contribute to heritable phenotype variation33. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Because no assumptions are made about the genomic location of the causal variants, this approach could exploit the strengths of association studies without having to guess the identity of the causal genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The GWA approach, therefore, represents an unbiased yet fairly comprehensive option that can be attempted even in the absence of convincing evidence regarding function or location of the causal genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The crucial factors that have made GWA studies possible are the availability of high throughput technologies, the decreasing cost of genotyping and the determination of LD on a genome wide scale through the HapMap project40. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The recent surge in GWA studies for complex diseases, including CAD, with replicated results of SNP association show that complex diseases are finally yielding their secrets2465–69. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Most of these studies are case-control studies, where SNP frequencies are compared between the two groups, and those that differ significantly are then validated in independent samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Most of these robust associations have not been with genes previously suspected as being related to the disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Some of these associations have been found in regions not even known to harbour genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Such findings promise to open up new avenues of research, through both the discovery of new genes relevant to specific diseases and the elucidation of genetic mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The association of 9p21 locus with CAD and MI has been found in every GWA studies published including a meta-analysis which suggests, at least, that this association is widely distributed6670–72. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>However, the region on chromosome 9p21 associated with CAD is defined by two flanking recombination hotspots and contains the coding sequences of genes CDKN2A and CDKN2B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Thus a large number of SNPs in this region show highly significant association with CAD and the causally responsible variant and the related mechanism remains to be identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The CDKN2A and CDKN2B genes are cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitors which regulate cell cycle and belong to a family of genes that have been implicated in the pathogenesis of atherosclerosis through their role in transforming growth factor-β-induced growth inhibition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>However, the most strongly associated SNPs lie considerably upstream of these genes, and the nearest signal is 10 kb upstream of CDKN2B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The C-allele of the lead SNP (rs1333049) has a frequency of 0.17 in Yoruba, 0.48 in Han Chinese, 0.51 in Japanese and 0.49 in Europeans indicating that the risk of CAD and MI related to the chromosome 9p21 locus may vary among different ethnic groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>More interestingly, this same susceptibility locus was found to be independently associated with type 2 diabetes67–6973. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>It is possible that the risk allele is located within a regulatory element that controls the expression of a gene outside of the associated region, or that the functional variant itself is located outside the region that was not well covered by the genotyping platforms used in the studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Other genes associated with significantly increased risk of MI are proline/serine-rich coiled-coil 1 (PSRC1), melanoma inhibitory activity family, member 3 (MIA3) and mothers against decapentaplegic homolog 3 also known as SMAD family member 3 (SMAD3) encoding cell-growth regulators, and a locus near the gene encoding the chemokine (C-X-C motif) ligand 12 (CXCL12)71. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>There is also evidence of strong signals for intermediate phenotypes from GWA studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The Diabetes Genetics Initiative was designed to investigate type 2 diabetes, but 18 other phenotypes, including plasma lipid concentrations, were analysed as secondary traits67. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Several of the loci that are significantly associated with changes in lipid concentrations are in or near genes in which mutations have been shown to cause mendelian syndromes affecting lipid concentrations [namely genes that encode the proteins apolipoprotein E, ABCA1, apolipoprotein A-V, Cholesterylester transfer protein (CETP), lipoprotein lipase and hepatic lipase]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>In addition, a SNP in the gene glucokinase (hexokinase 4) regulator (GCKR), which encodes glucokinase regulatory protein, was found to have a highly significant association with triglyceride concentrations67. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Other loci identified are near methylmalonic aciduria type B1/mevalonate kinase (MVK-MMAB) and UDP acetylgalactosaminyltransferase 2 (GALNT2), with high-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol; near sortilin 1 (SORT1), cadherin EGF LAG seven-pass G-type receptor 2 (CELSR2) and Proline/serine-rich coiled-coil protein 1 (PSRC1) with variants primarily associated with low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol; near Tribbles homolog 1 (TRIB1), MLX interacting protein-like1 (MLXIPL) and angiopoietin-like 3 (ANGPTL3), with variants primarily associated with triglycerides; and a locus encompassing several genes near neurocan (NCAN), with variants strongly associated with both triglycerides and LDL cholesterol7475. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>For most phenotypes, genes that were previously identified by linkage analysis, however, have not been found to be associated using GWA studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>There are several explanations for this- the particular chip configuration used covered these genes poorly and so the genetic effect was missed; the quantitative contribution of the genes to the disease is lower when ranked compared with other genes; or the association was missed because it was not present to a great degree in a particular study sample354243. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>There is always the possibility that results from GWA studies are merely random because subject recruitment is in fact sampling from a population and the results are due to statistical methods. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec1-8"><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Resequencing and other ‘Omic’ approaches </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2-3"><title/><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Validating new discoveries related to atherosclerosis will require multiple complementary approaches. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec3-8"><title><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Resequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The GWA approach has been extremely successful in identifying common SNP variants with modest effect on the CAD phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>However, this does not detect whether rarer variants play a role in CAD and it is unable to explain all of the observed familial clustering. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>All these emphasize the need to extend analysis to a more complete range of potential susceptibility variants, and to support more explicit modelling of the joint effects of genes and environment35. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Also, progressing from confirmed association signal to complete enumeration of the pattern of causal variants at a given locus poses significant challenges, and to narrow down the causal variant will require fine-mapping and resequencing of the implicated region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>For example, sequence variants in the PCSK9 gene were associated with lower LDL cholesterol and protection from CVD, single gene mutations in sarcomere genes were associated with a small but significant proportion of men and women with left ventricular hypertrophy (LVH)7677. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Whole-genome resequencing78 would resolve the question regarding the relative contribution of rare and common variants to CAD, but at present whole-genome resequencing is prohibitively expensive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>An alternative option is to study different ethnicities as inter-ethnic differences in patterns of LD and mutations are extremely valuable tools for fine mapping. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3-9"><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Transcriptomics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The SNP association studies cannot determine which SNPs may affect gene expression or function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Gene expression microarray technology provides a way to scan rapidly specific tissues for patterns of expression among thousands of genes across the genome and provides both qualitative (switched on/off genes) and quantitative data (transcriptional level of single genes), so that subtle differences of gene activation can be detected79. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Although SNPs represent static information (the genome), expression profiles are dynamic (the transcriptome) and may show physiological fluctuations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, profiling cardiovascular tissue samples may generate novel hypotheses and help to identify unexpected cell components and reveal novel marker genes and may aid identification of drug targets and validation of candidate drugs for the management of atherosclerosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>As proof of principle, Tuomisto et al80 showed that HMG-CoA reductase (the target of statin drugs) increased in atherosclerotic plaque. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Studying the transcriptional effect of statin exposure on peripheral monocytes, Waehre et al81 provided evidence showing that statins inhibit expression of inflammatory cytokine interleukin-1β, normally present at high levels among subjects with CAD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3-10"><title><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Proteomics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>There are approximately ten times more proteins than genes, and expression arrays should preferably be complemented by proteomic evaluation as they cannot assess potentially important post-transcriptional variables including alternative splicing of mRNA, control subjects on protein translation, and post-translational processing of proteins8283. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Therefore, new findings discovered by transcript profiling may serve as leads but require subsequent functional characterization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Proteomic studies on isolated plasma lipid fractions have yielded new insight into the composition of LDL and high-density lipoprotein particles, identifying 3 proteins previously not associated with LDL and 2 proteins not previously associated with high-density lipoprotein and identifying unique patterns of LDL associated apolipoproteins in subjects with type 2 diabetes and subclinical peripheral atherosclerosis84–86. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Urinary proteomic studies are also useful and have been shown to identify CAD patients and help in monitoring the effects of therapeutic interventions87. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>As in the case of genomic markers, proteomic studies require rigorous validation of technology platforms and experimental results88. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3-11"><title><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Metabolomics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The study of the collection of small molecular-weight organic and inorganic species present in a biological system is defined as metabolomics, and provides a phenotypic profile either as a snapshot in time or as an integrated picture of biology over a period of time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Metabolites are the final downstream product of gene transcription and so reflect more closely the phenotype at a functional level, and the metabolome is thought to be a potentially more sensitive marker of cellular processes both in normal physiology and disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>As proof of principle, Sabatine et al89 used mass spectrometry-based technology to identify differences in plasma metabolites among 18 subjects with ischaemia induced by exercise stress testing compared with non ischaemic individuals who also exercised; specifically, changes in 6 metabolites, including citric acid, accurately differentiated cases from control subjects (P&lt;0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Analysing 4,630 participants from the INTERMAP epidemiological study, involving 17 population samples aged 40-59 in China, Japan, UK and USA, Holmes et al90 showed that urinary metabolite excretion patterns for East Asian and western population samples, with contrasting diets, diet-related major risk factors, and coronary heart disease/stroke rates were significantly differentiated (P&lt;10-16) and mean 24-hour urinary excretion of alanine (direct) and hippurate (inverse), reflecting diet and gut microbial activities, were also associated with blood pressure of these individuals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Thus metabolomic analysis may not only identify potential biomarkers for CV disease but may also provide information regarding prognosis, response to therapy, and underlying mechanisms of the disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec1-9"><title><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Rapid advances in genomic, proteomic, and metabolomic technology provide researchers with valuable tools for understanding the genetic predisposition to atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease and have led to the development of successful therapeutic interventions for atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease; for example, reducing plasma concentrations of atherogenic lipoproteins (with statins) and blocking rennin-angiotensin-aldosterone system activity (with ACE inhibitors and angiotensin-receptor blockers). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Combining classical epidemiology with modern genomics will require collaborative efforts within the cardiovascular disease community at both bench and bedside, and is likely to pay major dividends with the development of a new generation of personalised prevention and treatment interventions that will have a major impact on public health. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="CIT1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>1MurrayCJLopezADAlternative projections of mortality and disability by cause 1990-2020: Global Burden of Disease StudyLancet199734914985049167458 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT2"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>2GuptaRJoshiPMohanVReddyKSYusufSEpidemiology and causation of coronary heart disease and stroke in IndiaHeart200894162618083949 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT3"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>3SrinathRKShahBVargheseCRamadossAResponding to the threat of chronic diseases in IndiaLancet20053661744916291069 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT4"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>4MathersCDLoncarDProjections of global mortality and burden of disease from 2002 to 2030PLoS Med20063e44217132052 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT5"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>5WatkinsHFarrallMGenetic susceptibility to coronary artery disease: from promise to progressNat Rev Genet200671637316462853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT6"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>6Lloyd-JonesDMNamBHD’AgostinoRBSrLevyDMurabitoJMWangTJParental cardiovascular disease as a risk factor for cardiovascular disease in middle-aged adults: a prospective study of parents and offspringJAMA200429122041115138242 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT7"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>7MyersRHKielyDKCupplesLAKannelWBParental history is an independent risk factor for coronary artery disease: the Framingham StudyAm Heart J199012096392220549 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT8"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>8KaikkonenKSKortelainenMLLinnaEHuikuriHVFamily history and the risk of sudden cardiac death as a manifestation of an acute coronary eventCirculation20061141462717000909 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT9"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>9YusufSHawkenSOunpuuSDansTAvezumALanasFEffect of potentially modifiable risk factors associated with myocardial infarction in 52 countries (the INTERHEART study): case-control studyLancet20043649375215364185 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT10"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>10LusisAJMarRPajukantaPGenetics of atherosclerosisAnnu Rev Genomics Hum Genet2004518921815485348 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT11"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>11AllayeeHGhazalpourALusisAJUsing mice to dissect genetic factors in atherosclerosisArterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol2003231501912920046 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT12"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>12ZdravkovicSWienkeAPedersenNLDe FaireUGenetic susceptibility of myocardial infarctionTwin Res Hum Genet2007108485218179397 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT13"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>13ZdravkovicSWienkeAPedersenNLMarenbergMEYashinAIDe FaireUHeritability of death from coronary heart disease: a 36-year follow-up of 20 966 Swedish twinsJ Intern Med20022522475412270005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT14"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>14SorensenTINielsenGGAndersenPKTeasdaleTWGenetic and environmental influences on premature death in adult adopteesN Engl J Med1988318727323347221 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT15"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>15PetersenLNielsenGGAndersenPKSorensenTICase-control study of genetic and environmental influences on premature death of adult adopteesGenet Epidemiol2002231233212214306 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT16"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>16GoldsteinJLHobbsHHBrownMSScriverCRBeaudetALSlyDFamilial hypercholesterolemiaThe metabolic basis of inherited disease1995New YorkMcGraw Hill126782 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT17"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>17BurrisTPEachoPICaoGGenetic disorders associated with ATP binding cassette cholesterol transportersMol Genet Metab200277132012359125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT18"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>18RustSRosierMFunkeHRealJAmouraZPietteJCTangier disease is caused by mutations in the gene encoding ATP-binding cassette transporter 1Nat Genet199922352510431238 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT19"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>19WrightAFHastieNDComplex genetic diseases: controversy over the Croesus codeGenome Biol2001218 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT20"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>20ReichDELanderESOn the allelic spectrum of human diseaseTrends Genet2001175021011525833 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT21"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>21LanderESThe new genomics: global views of biologyScience199627453698928008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT22"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>22PritchardJKAre rare variants responsible for susceptibility to complex diseases?Am J Hum Genet2001691243711404818 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT23"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>23LohmuellerKEPearceCLPikeMLanderESHirschhornJNMeta-analysis of genetic association studies supports a contribution of common variants to susceptibility to common diseaseNat Genet2003331778212524541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT24"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>24The Wellcome Trust Case Control Consortium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide association study of 14,000 cases of seven common diseases and 3,000 shared controlsNature20074476617817554300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT25"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>25CohenJCKissRSPertsemlidisAMarcelYLMcPhersonRHobbsHHMultiple rare alleles contribute to low plasma levels of HDL cholesterolScience20043058697215297675 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT26"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>26Frikke-SchmidtRNordestgaardBGJensenGBTybjaerg-HansenAGenetic variation in ABC transporter A1 contributes to HDL cholesterol in the general populationJ Clin Invest200411413435315520867 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT27"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>27AltmullerJPalmerLJFischerGScherbHWjstMGenomewide scans of complex human diseases: true linkage is hard to findAm J Hum Genet2001699365011565063 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT28"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>28RischNMerikangasKThe future of genetic studies of complex human diseasesScience1996273151678801636 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT29"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>29GimbroneMAJrVascular endothelium, hemodynamic forces, and atherogenesisAm J Pathol19991551510393828 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT30"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>30Goldschmidt-ClermontPJCreagerMALorsordoDWLamGKWWassefMDzauVJAtherosclerosis 2005: Recent Discoveries and Novel HypothesesCirculation200511233485316301361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT31"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>31LittleJKhouryMJMendelian randomisation: a new spin or real progress?Lancet2003362930114511923 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT32"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>32FarrallMMorrisAPGearing up for genome-wide gene-association studiesHum Mol Genet200514R1576216244314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT33"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>33HirschhornJNDalyMJGenome-wide association studies for common diseases and complex traitsNat Rev Genet200569510815716906 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT34"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>34LuoAKJeffersonBKGarciaMJGinsburgGSTopolEJChallenges in the phenotypic characterisation of patients in genetic studies of coronary artery diseaseJ Med Genet200744161517158593 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT35"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>35McCarthyMIAbecasisGRCardonLRGoldsteinDBLittleJIoannidisJPGenome-wide association studies for complex traits: consensus, uncertainty and challengesNat Rev Genet200893566918398418 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT36"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>36LairdNMLangeCFamily-based designs in the age of large-scale gene-association studiesNat Rev Genet200673859416619052 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT37"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>37PriceALPattersonNJPlengeRMWeinblattMEShadickNAReichDPrincipal components analysis corrects for stratification in genome-wide association studiesNat Genet200638904916862161 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT38"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>38VoightBFPritchardJKConfounding from cryptic relatedness in case-control association studiesPLoS Genet20051e3216151517 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT39"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>39ZhengGFreidlinBGastwirthJLRobust genomic control for association studiesAm J Hum Genet200678350616400614 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT40"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>40FrazerKABallingerDGCoxDRHindsDAStuveLLGibbsRAA second generation human haplotype map of over 3.1 million SNPsNature20074498516117943122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT41"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>41PriceALPattersonNYuFCoxDRWaliszewskaAMcDonaldGJA genomewide admixture map for Latino populationsAm J Hum Genet20078010243617503322 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT42"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>42TaylorKDNorrisJMRotterJIGenome-wide association: which do you want first: the good news, the bad news, or the good news?Diabetes2007562844818042761 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT43"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>43WangWYBarrattBJClaytonDGToddJAGenome-wide association studies: theoretical and practical concernsNat Rev Genet200561091815716907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT44"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="?"><plain>44Clerget-DarpouxFElstonRCAre linkage analysis and the collection of family data dead? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Prospects for family studies in the age of genome-wide associationHum Hered20076491617476108 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT45"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>45ChenWMAbecasisGRFamily-based association tests for genomewide association scansAm J Hum Genet2007819132617924335 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT46"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>46ManolioTABailey-WilsonJECollinsFSGenes, environment and the value of prospective cohort studiesNat Rev Genet200678122016983377 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT47"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>47WongMYDayNELuanJAChanKPWarehamNJThe detection of gene-environment interaction for continuous traits: should we deal with measurement error by bigger studies or better measurement?Int J Epidemiol20033251712690008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT48"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>48PajukantaPCargillMViitanenLNuotioIKareinenAPerolaMTwo loci on chromosomes 2 and X for premature coronary heart disease identified in early- and late-settlement populations of FinlandAm J Hum Genet20006714819311078477 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT49"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>49BroeckelUHengstenbergCMayerBHolmerSMartinLJComuzzieAGA comprehensive linkage analysis for myocardial infarction and its related risk factorsNat Genet200230210411818963 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT50"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>50HelgadottirAManolescuAThorleifssonGGretarsdottirSJonsdottirHThorsteinsdottirUThe gene encoding 5-lipoxygenase activating protein confers risk of myocardial infarction and strokeNat Genet200436233914770184 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT51"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>51HauserERCrossmanDCGrangerCBHainesJLJonesCJMooserVA genomewide scan for early-onset coronary artery disease in 438 families: the GENECARD StudyAm J Hum Genet2004754364715272420 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT52"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>52FarrallMGreenFRPedenJFOlssonPGClarkeRHelleniusMLGenome-wide mapping of susceptibility to coronary artery disease identifies a novel replicated locus on chromosome 17PLoS Genet20062e7216710446 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT53"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>53SamaniNJBurtonPManginoMBallSGBalmforthAJBarrettJA genomewide linkage study of 1,933 families affected by premature coronary artery disease: The British Heart Foundation (BHF) Family Heart StudyAm J Hum Genet20057710112016380912 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT54"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>54HelgadottirAGretarsdottirSSt ClairDManolescuACheungJThorleifssonGAssociation between the gene encoding 5-lipoxygenase-activating protein and stroke replicated in a Scottish populationAm J Hum Genet200576505915640973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT55"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>55WangLFanCTopolSETopolEJWangQMutation of MEF2A in an inherited disorder with features of coronary artery diseaseScience200330215788114645853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT56"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>56CampbellLAKuoCCChlamydia pneumoniae--an infectious risk factor for atherosclerosis?Nat Rev Microbiol20042233215035006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT57"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>57AmezianeNBeillatTVerpillatPChollet-MartinSAumontMCSeknadjiPAssociation of the Toll-like receptor 4 gene Asp299Gly polymorphism with acute coronary eventsArterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol200323e61414563652 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT58"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>58Arroyo-EspligueroRAvanzasPJefferySKaskiJCCD14 and toll-like receptor 4: a link between infection and acute coronary events?Heart200490983815310678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT59"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>59KiechlSLorenzEReindlMWiedermannCJOberhollenzerFBonoraEToll-like receptor 4 polymorphisms and atherogenesisN Engl J Med20023471859212124407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT60"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>60YangIAHollowayJWYeSTLR4 Asp299Gly polymorphism is not associated with coronary artery stenosisAtherosclerosis20031701879012957699 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT61"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>61HelgadottirAManolescuAHelgasonAThorleifssonGThorsteinsdottirUGudbjartssonDFA variant of the gene encoding leukotriene A4 hydrolase confers ethnicity-specific risk of myocardial infarctionNat Genet200638687416282974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT62"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>62OzakiKOhnishiYIidaASekineAYamadaRTsunodaTFunctional SNPs in the lymphotoxin-alpha gene that are associated with susceptibility to myocardial infarctionNat Genet200232650412426569 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT63"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>63ClarkeRXuPBennettDLewingtonSZondervanKParishSLymphotoxin-alpha gene and risk of myocardial infarction in 6,928 cases and 2,712 controls in the ISIS case-control studyPLoS Genet20062e10716839190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT64"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>64Newton-ChehCHirschhornJNGenetic association studies of complex traits: design and analysis issuesMutat Res2005573546915829237 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT65"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>65FraylingTMTimpsonNJWeedonMNZegginiEFreathyRMLindgrenCMA common variant in the FTO gene is associated with body mass index and predisposes to childhood and adult obesityScience20073168899417434869 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT66"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>66HelgadottirAThorleifssonGManolescuAGretarsdottirSBlondalTJonasdottirAA common variant on chromosome 9p21 affects the risk of myocardial infarctionScience20073161491317478679 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT67"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>67SaxenaRVoightBFLyssenkoVBurttNPde BakkerPIChenHGenome-wide association analysis identifies loci for type 2 diabetes and triglyceride levelsScience20073161331617463246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT68"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>68ScottLJMohlkeKLBonnycastleLLWillerCJLiYDurenWLA genome-wide association study of type 2 diabetes in Finns detects multiple susceptibility variantsScience20073161341517463248 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT69"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>69ZegginiEWeedonMNLindgrenCMFraylingTMElliottKSLangoHReplication of genome-wide association signals in U.K. samples reveals risk loci for type 2 diabetesScience200731613364117463249 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT70"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>70McPhersonRPertsemlidisAKavaslarNStewartARobertsRCoxDRA common allele on chromosome 9 associated with coronary heart diseaseScience200731614889117478681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT71"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>71SamaniNJErdmannJHallASHengstenbergCManginoMMayerBGenomewide association analysis of coronary artery diseaseN Engl J Med20073574435317634449 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT72"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>72SchunkertHGotzABraundPMcGinnisRTregouetDAManginoMRepeated replication and a prospective meta-analysis of the association between chromosome 9p21.3 and coronary artery diseaseCirculation200811716758418362232 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT73"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>73SladekRRocheleauGRungJDinaCShenLSerreDA genome-wide association study identifies novel risk loci for type 2 diabetesNature2007445881517293876 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT74"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>74KathiresanSMelanderOGuiducciCSurtiABurttNPRiederMJSix new loci associated with blood low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol or triglycerides in humansNat Genet2008401899718193044 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT75"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>75WillerCJSannaSJacksonAUScuteriABonnycastleLLClarkeRNewly identified loci that influence lipid concentrations and risk of coronary artery diseaseNat Genet200840161918193043 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT76"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>76CohenJCBoerwinkleEMosleyTHJrHobbsHHSequence variations in PCSK9, low LDL, and protection against coronary heart diseaseN Engl J Med200635412647216554528 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT77"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>77MoritaHLarsonMGBarrSCVasanRSO’DonnellCJHirschhornJNSingle-gene mutations and increased left ventricular wall thickness in the community: the Framingham Heart StudyCirculation2006113269770516754800 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT78"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>78ChanEYAdvances in sequencing technologyMutat Res2005573134015829235 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT79"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>79SeoDGinsburgGSGoldschmidt-ClermontPJGene expression analysis of cardiovascular diseases: novel insights into biology and clinical applicationsJ Am Coll Cardiol2006482273516843168 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT80"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>80TuomistoTTKorkeelaARutanenJViitaHBrasenJHRiekkinenMSGene expression in macrophagerich inflammatory cell infiltrates in human atherosclerotic lesions as studied by laser microdissection and DNA array: overexpression of HMG-CoA reductase, colony stimulating factor receptors, CD11A/CD18 integrins, and interleukin receptorsArterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol20032322354014576072 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT81"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>81WaehreTYndestadASmithCHaugTTunheimSHGullestadLIncreased expression of interleukin-1 in coronary artery disease with downregulatory effects of HMG-CoA reductase inhibitorsCirculation200410919667215051633 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT82"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>82MayrMMadhuBXuQProteomics and metabolomics combined in cardiovascular researchTrends Cardiovasc Med20071743817292045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT83"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>83MillerDTRidkerPMLibbyPKwiatkowskiDJAtherosclerosis: the path from genomics to therapeuticsJ Am Coll Cardiol20074915899917433948 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT84"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>84DavidssonPHultheJFagerbergBOlssonBMHallbergCDahllofBA proteomic study of the apolipoproteins in LDL subclasses in patients with the metabolic syndrome and type 2 diabetesJ Lipid Res2005461999200615995172 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT85"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>85KarlssonHLeandersonPTagessonCLindahlMLipoproteomics II: mapping of proteins in high-density lipoprotein using two-dimensional gel electrophoresis and mass spectrometryProteomics2005514314515761960 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT86"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>86KarlssonHLeandersonPTagessonCLindahlMLipoproteomics I: mapping of proteins in low-density lipoprotein using two-dimensional gel electrophoresis and mass spectrometryProteomics200555516515627967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT87"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>87ZimmerliLUSchifferEZurbigPGoodDMKellmannMMoulsLUrinary proteomic biomarkers in coronary artery diseaseMol Cell Proteomics20087290817951555 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT88"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>88BerhaneBTZongCLiemDAHuangALeSEdmondsonRDCardiovascular-related proteins identified in human plasma by the HUPO Plasma Proteome Project pilot phaseProteomics2005535203016052623 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT89"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>89SabatineMSLiuEMorrowDAHellerEMcCarrollRWiegandRMetabolomic identification of novel biomarkers of myocardial ischemiaCirculation200511238687516344383 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT90"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>90HolmesELooRLStamlerJBictashMYapIKChanQHuman metabolic phenotype diversity and its association with diet and blood pressureNature2008453393400 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
