
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Mol Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijms</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1422-0067</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Molecular Diversity Preservation International (MDPI)</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3269738</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22312304</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms13011054</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ijms-13-01054</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Studies on Bioflocculant Production by Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Raats, a Freshwater Bacteria Isolated from Tyume River, South Africa </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mabinya</surname><given-names>Leonard V.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cosa</surname><given-names>Sekelwa</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nwodo</surname><given-names>Uchechukwu</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Okoh</surname><given-names>Anthony I.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1-ijms-13-01054">*</xref></contrib><aff id="af1-ijms-13-01054">Applied and Environmental Microbiology Research Group (AEMREG), Department of Biochemistry and Microbiology, University of Fort Hare, Alice 5700, South Africa; E-Mails: <email>lmabinya@ufh.ac.za</email> (L.V.M.); <email>200804075@ufh.ac.za</email> (S.C.); <email>201101482@ufh.ac.za</email> (U.N.)</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1-ijms-13-01054"><label>*</label>Author to whom correspondence should be addressed; E-Mail: <email>aokoh@ufh.ac.za</email>; Tel.: +27-406-022-365; Fax: +27-866-286-824.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1054</fpage><lpage>1065</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>06</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2012 by the authors; licensee Molecular Diversity Preservation International, Basel, Switzerland.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0"><license-p>This article is an open-access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>A bioflocculant-producing bacteria was isolated from Tyume River in the Eastern Cape Province, South Africa and identified by 16S rRNA gene nucleotide sequence to have 91% similarity to Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>5J12A, and the nucleotide sequence was deposited in GenBank as Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Raats (accession number HQ875723). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The bacteria produced an extracellular bioflocculant when grown aerobically in a production medium containing glucose as sole carbon source and had an initial pH of 7.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Influences of carbon, nitrogen and metal ions sources, as well as initial pH on flocculating activity were investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The bacteria optimally produced the bioflocullant when lactose and urea were used as sole sources of carbon and nitrogen respectively with flocculating activities of 75.4% and 83.4% respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Also, the bacteria produced the bioflocculant optimally when initial pH of the medium was 7.0 (flocculating activity 84%), and when Mg2+ was used as cation (flocculating activity 77%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Composition analyses indicated the bioflocculant to be principally a glycoprotein made up of about 56% protein and 25% total carbohydrate. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Arthrobacter</italic> sp. Raats</kwd><kwd>freshwater</kwd><kwd>bioflocculant</kwd><kwd>polyssacharide</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Presently, both organic and inorganic flocculating agents are extensively used for sedimentation of colloidal and cellular materials and thus applied in a wide range of industrial fields, such as purification of drinking water, wastewater treatment, food industries, dredging and fermentation processes [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Notwithstanding their harmfulness to humans and the environment, various chemically synthesized flocculants such as aluminum salts and polyacrylamide derivatives are commonly employed in these processes due to cost considerations and their effectiveness [1,2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>In order to circumvent the health and environmental problems attributed to inorganic and synthetic flocculants, flocculants produced by microorganisms have attracted considerable scientific and technological attention in recent years [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The industrial potential of bioflocculants has long been recognized because of their harmlessness, biodegradability and lack of secondary pollution from their degradative intermediates [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The majority of bioflocculants produced by different microorganisms are usually high molecular weight polymers such as polysaccharides, proteins, glycoproteins and nucleic acids [5,6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Although a number of microorganisms have been screened for their bioflocculant-producing capabilities, to-date, very little has been accomplished on a commercial scale [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The high cost of production coupled with low yield seem to be the major deterring factors in the advancement of research in developing bioflocculants for both scientific and commercial applications [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>However, in order to reduce costs and optimize cultivation conditions, strategies such as fed-batch production processes are being developed [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>As part of our exploration for new and novel bioflocculants that could stand as alternatives to inorganic and synthetic flocculants, the present study reports on the bioflocculant-producing potential of a freshwater bacteria identified as Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Raats which was isolated from Tyume River, South Africa. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Arthrobacter is a common genus of soil bacteria with all species being generally non-sporulating, Gram-positive and obligate aerobes that exhibit pure respiratory metabolism with the exception of at least two species, Arthrobacter globiforms and Arthrobacter nicotianae which exhibit anaerobic metabolism [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Due to their metabolic diversity, Arthrobacter species have been used in industrial applications in the bioremediation of contaminated water [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The usefulness of Arthrobacter globiformis for bioremediation of industrial wastes rich in nitrates was demonstrated by its ability to remove all nitrate from solutions containing from 100 to 150 mM NO3− [10], while Shen et al. [11] reported on an Arthrobacter nitroguajacolicus strain with the capability to transform acrylonitrile into acrylic acid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Su et al. [12] also studied the flocculability of the Arthrobacter sp. and demonstrated Arthrobacter albidus LC13T to be an effective flocculant-producing strain with high flocculating efficiency obtained for the produced bioflocculant LC13-SF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Results and Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Identity of the Bacteria </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The test bacterium was one of several isolated from Tyume River in the Eastern Cape Province of South Africa that was screened for bioflocculant-production potential. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Initial screening revealed the bacteria to be capable of flocculating kaolin clay suspension (4 g/L) at pH 7.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) amplification of the 16S rRNA gene of the bacteria produced an amplicon of expected size (approx. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>1.5 kb) (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The 16S rRNA gene nucleotide sequence analyses revealed a 91% similarity of the test bacterium to Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>5J12A, and the nucleotide sequences were deposited in GenBank as Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Raats with accession number HQ875723. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Effect of Culture Conditions on Bioflocculant Production </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Factors such as the constituents of the production medium and culture conditions have an influence on bioflocculant production [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Different key factors such as carbon source, nitrogen source, metal ions and the pH were evaluated for their effects on the flocculating activity of the bioflocculant produced by the test bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The effects of lactose, sucrose, fructose and starch on flocculation were assessed and the results are as shown in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Lactose and sucrose were favorable carbon sources with flocculating activities of 75.4% and 73.4% being attained respectively, while fructose and starch did not support any flocculating activities (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>With respect to sucrose, these results seem to support the findings reported by Li et al. [3] for bioflocculant production by Bacillus licheniformis X14. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>However, contrary to the present study, starch was found to enhance the production of the bioflocculant by Bacillus licheniformis X14 while lactose was not favored at all [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Studies carried out by Patil et al. [14] and He et al. [15] on bioflocculant production by Azotobacter indicus and Halomonas sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>V3a’ respectively, also showed a better bioflocculant recovery rate with sucrose as a carbon source. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Starch has also been reported as a poor carbon source for bioflocculant production by Bacillus sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Gilbert [16] and Virgibacillus sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Rob [17] respectively with fructose also shown not to be a favorable carbon source among sugars tested for bioflocculant production by Enterobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>BY-29 [18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The effect of nitrogen sources on biofloccdulant production was investigated by cultivating the strain in the same medium, except that the nitrogen source was varied (Table 1). Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Raats was able to utilize both organic (urea) and inorganic (ammonium sulphate) nitrogen sources with urea being more effectively used and resulting in the highest flocculating activity of 83.4%, followed by ammonium sulphate at 79% and ammonium chloride at 61% (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Patil et al. [14] assessed the influence of nitrogen sources on bioflocculant production by Azotobacter indicus and showed that in addition to yeast extract, both urea and ammonium sulphate were also effective in promoting flocculation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, ammonium chloride has been reported to be an effective nitrogen source for bioflocculant production by Halomonas sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>V3a’ and AAD6 respectively [15,19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, contrary to the present studies with Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Raats, both yeast extract and peptone were found to be key parameters influencing optimal production of the bioflocculant produced by Arthrobacter albidus LC13T [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>A number of strains have also been reported to optimally produce bioflocculants in the presence of organic nitrogen sources (or sometimes combined organic and inorganic sources) [20,21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The production of bioflocculant is influenced by the presence of cations in the culture medium [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The effects of various cations on flocculating activity were evaluated using solutions of FeCl3, MgCl2, FeSO4·7H2O and KCl as sources of cations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>As can be seen in Table 1, the addition of a divalent cation, Mg2+ enhanced flocculation when compared to the monovalent cation, K+. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Both Fe3+ and Fe2+ had no effect on flocculation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Increased flocculation in the presence of Mg2+ was also reported for Virgibacillus sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Rob [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>In contrast, for bioflocculant LC13-SF produced by Arthrobacter albidus LC13T, maximum flocculating efficiency required the presence of Ca2+ [12] A similar requirement was also reported for optimal flocculation by bioflocculant-producing Vagococcus sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>W31 and Halomonas sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>V3a’ [22,23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>For Serratia ficaria-produced bioflocculant, addition of both divalent cations, Ca2+ and Mg2+ enhanced the flocculating activity whereas the co-presence of trivalent cations Al3+ and Fe3+ negatively affected the flocculating activity [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Li et al. [24] reported a requirement for the co-presence of both monovalent and divalent cations for enhancing flocculating efficiency by Aeromonas sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Cations were often added to achieve high flocculating activity by neutralizing negatively charged functional groups of both the bioflocculant molecules and the suspended particles [1,25] and consequently weaken the static repulsive force thus enhancing the flocculating effect [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The influence of these cations on flocculating rates varies among bioflocculant-producing microorganisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The pH of the solution is also a key factor in flocculation and thus effectively influences the flocculation process [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The effect of initial pH of the medium on flocculating activity by Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Raats was investigated at pH values ranging from 3 to 11, and the flocculating activity was found to be distinctly higher (84%) in neutral pH conditions (pH 7.0) than in acidic and alkaline conditions (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Similar pH values (pH 7.2 and 7.0) were reported for optimum activity of bioflocculants ERSS-31 produced by Halomonas maura sp. nov. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>[27] and MBFW31 produced by Vagococcus sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>W31 [22] respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Bioflocculant HBF-3, produced by a mutant Halomonas sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>V3a’ also attained the highest flocculating activity at pH 7 [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>At low pH, the absorption of H+ ions tends to weaken the bioflocculant-kaolin complex formation process and a similar effect is also observed at high pH values due to OH− ions [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>According to Li et al. [25], the mediating effect of cations appears to be strongest at neutral pH values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>However, these observations are different from studies carried out by Choi et al. [28] and Zheng et al. [2] in which the maximum flocculating activities of bioflocculants produced by Anabaena sp. and Bacillus sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>F19 respectively were observed at pH 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The bioflocculant produced by Bacillus sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>PY-90 was found to be actively high in an acidic pH range of 3.0 to 5.0 [29], while Serratia ficaria produced a bioflocculant effective over a weakly acidic pH range of 5.0 to 7.0 [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Time Course Assay of Bioflocculant Production </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Figure 3 shows the time course of bioflocculant production by Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Raats in relation to optical density, pH and flocculating activity over a 10 days cultivation period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>During growth, the flocculating activity was observed to increase reaching a maximum of 87.5% in 5 days beyond which a rapid decline was noted with a complete loss of activity over the last 4 days of growth (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The observed decrease in flocculating activity might be due to the activity of deflocculation enzymes in the late phase of cell growth [20,28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>According to a study by Jang et al. [30] on bioflocculant production by fed-batch culture of Citrobacter sp., specific flocculating activity and bioflocculant production was influenced by fermentation conditions which included among other things, carbon source, inoculum size, dissolved oxygen tension (DOT) and carbon/nitrogen (C/N) source ratio. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Jang et al. [30] also noted that the initial growth rate increased with an increase in carbon source concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>However, carbon source consumption was severely limited at higher carbon source concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Inoculum size has also been reported to affect not only cell growth but also product formation with the dynamic behavior of cells of Citrobacter sp. cell cultures at different inoculum sizes affecting bioflocculant activity [30,31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The synthesis of bioflocculant and the flocculating activity were also shown to be significantly affected by the C/N ratio of the growth medium with a higher C/N ratio not necessarily translating to a higher yield of flocculant synthesis [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The influence of the initial pH of fermentation medium can determine both the electric charge of the cells and the oxidation-reduction potential which, in turn, can affect nutrient absorption and enzymatic reaction [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Thus the corresponding steady increase in cell growth (OD600) in relation to flocculating activity observed over the first 5 day growth period is possibly an indication that the bioflocculant was produced by biosynthesis during growth of the bacterium and not by cell autolysis [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>From 72 to 120 h, the pH increased steadily until optimal flocculating activity was reached at pH 7.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>After 6 days of cultivation, a complete loss of flocculating activity was observed while the pH increased sharply and remained around pH 8.2 (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The correlation between bioflocculant production and culturing times may differ among different organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Maximum production levels and a flocculating peak of 90.6% for a bioflocculant produced by Arthrobacter albidus LC13T were obtained at 72 h of fermentation time under neutral conditions (pH 7.0) [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>For Bacillus licheniforms, maximum values were obtained for both the flocculant production and cell growth during the stationary phase [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Li et al. [3] and Xia et al. [21] showed that for Bacillus licheniforms X14, and Proteus mirabilis TJ-1, maximum production of the bioflocculant was achieved in less time than required for other strains (24 h) while the flocculating activity peaked during the early stationary phase (48 h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The observed fluctuations in the pH of the medium during bacterial growth may also be attributed, according to Lors et al. [33], to two opposite phenomena: a decrease of pH due to the bacterial activity and an increase of pH due to the release of hydroxide ions associated to the cations that are leached out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these observations seem to strongly support a fed-batch culture approach in order to fully understand the dynamics involved in a growing cell culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The relationship between growth kinetics and the concentration of a substrate is fundamental in studying the enormous inconsistencies that exist especially for pure cultures growing with single substrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Confounding the problem further is the fact that microorganisms tend to change their kinetic properties in order to adapt to changing environment [34]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Chemical Analysis of Bioflocculant Composition </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>An aliquoted suspension (1 mg/mL) of the purified bioflocculant was found to contain 0.25 mg/mL total carbohydrate and 0.56 mg/mL protein respectively, thus confirming that the bioflucculant consisted primarily of a glycoprotein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Inoue et al. [35] investigated a biopolymer produced by Arthrobacter sp. and revealed it to be a heterogenous polysaccharide which was principally a galactan sulfate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>A number of other organisms have been reported to produce different kinds of glycoprotein bioflocculants [5,36]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Experimental Section </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Test Bacterium and Cultivation Conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The test bacterium was one of the bioflocculant producing bacteria isolated from Tyume River in the Eastern Cape Province of South Africa that forms part of the culture collections of the Applied and Environmental Microbiology Research Group (AEMREG), University of Fort Hare, Alice, South Africa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The bacterium was preserved on agar slants and the glycerol (20%) stocks maintained at −80 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The composition of the cultivation medium was prepared by mixing the following: glucose (10 g), MgSO4·7H2O (0.3 g), K2HPO4 (5 g), peptone (1.0 g) and KH2PO4 (0.2 g) in a litre of deionized water at pH 7.0 [15,16,36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>A loopful of colonies of the test bacterium was inoculated into 5 mL of the growth medium and incubated in a rotary shaker (160 rpm) at 28 °C for 5 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The resultant culture broth (2 mL) was centrifuged (8000× g, 15 min) and the cell-free supernatant was assayed for flocculating activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Determination of Flocculating Activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Using a suspension of kaolin clay as test material, flocculating activity was determined according to Kurane et al. [37] as modified by Gao et al. [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>A suspension of kaolin clay (4 g/L) in deionized water at pH 7 was used as a stock solution for the subsequent assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The following solutions were mixed in a test tube: kaolin clay suspension (9 mL), culture supernatant (0.1 mL) and 1% CaCl2 (0.25 mL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>A control in which the culture supernatant was replaced with deionized water was also included and measured under similar conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The final volume of all mixtures was made up to 10 mL with deionized water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The solutions were mixed gently and allowed to settle for 5 min. at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The optical density (OD) of the clarifying upper phase solution was measured at 550 nm using a ThermoSpectronic spectrophotometer (Helios Epsilon, USA) and the flocculating activity determined as follows: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><disp-formula id="FD1"><mml:math id="mm1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Flocculating activity</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>where A and B are optical densities at 550 nm of the sample and control respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Effect of Carbon and Nitrogen Sources on Bioflocculant Production </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The effects of the following carbon sources were assessed: lactose, sucrose, fructose and starch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Nitrogen source candidates included ammonium sulphate, ammonium chloride and urea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The assessments were done following the method described by Lachhwani [38]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>3.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Effect of Various Cations and pH on Bioflocculant Production </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The effect of metal ions was evaluated utilizing the procedure elaborated above, but the CaCl2 solution was replaced by various salt solutions and the flocculating activity determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Solutions of KCl, MgCl2, FeCl3 and FeSO4·7H2O were used as cation sources. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>To assess the effect of pH on flocculating activity, the initial pH of the kaolin suspension was varied between the pH range of 3–11 by adjusting with either HCl or NaOH [39]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>3.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Time Course Assay of Bioflocculant Production </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The composition of the medium for bioflocculant production was prepared according to the method described under subsection 3.1 [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The selected strain was pre-cultured in 50 mL medium contained in 50 mL flasks on a rotary shaker (160 rpm) at 28 °C for 16 h and used as seed culture for batch fermentation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Batch fermentations were carried out according to the modified method of Gao et al. [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Seed culture (10% v/v) was used to inoculate 150 mL of medium in 500 mL flasks on a rotary shaker (160 rpm) at 28 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Culture samples were withdrawn at appropriate time intervals (24 h) for a period of 240 h and monitored for growth (OD660), pH and flocculating activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Culture broth (5 mL) was centrifuged (8000× g, 15 min.) and the cell-free supernatant was used to determine the flocculating activity as previously described. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>3.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Extraction, Purification and Characterization of the Bioflocculant </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>After 5 days of fermentation, the culture broth was centrifuged (8000× g, 15 min.) to remove bacterial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>One volume of distilled water was added to the supernatant phase and centrifuged (8000× g, 15 min.) to remove insoluble substances. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was then mixed with 2 volumes of ethanol, stirred and left standing at 4 °C for 12 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was decanted and the precipitate vacuum-dried to obtain the crude biopolymer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The crude product was then dissolved in distilled water and mixed with 1 volume of chloroform/n-butyl alcohol (5:2, v/v). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>After stirring, the mixture was left standing at room temperature for 12 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The upper phase was separated, centrifuged (3000× g, 15 min.) and the supernatant concentrated at 40 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Two volumes of ethanol were added, the precipitate recovered, vacuum-dried and re-dissolved in distilled water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Thereafter, the protein content was measured using the Folin-Lowry method, and total carbohydrate was assayed using Phenol-Sulphuric acid protocol as described by Lachhwani [38]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>3.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Identification of the Bioflocculant-Producing Microorganism </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>DNA extraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>DNA extraction was conducted via the boiling method whereby 2–3 colonies were suspended in 70 μL of sterile double distilled water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The samples were heated in a water bath at 100 °C for 10 min, allowed to cool for 5 min and thereafter centrifuged at 3000 rpm for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was transferred to a clean tube and stored at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>This served as the template in the PCR assay. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>PCR Amplification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>PCR was carried out in 50 μL reaction volume containing 2 mM MgCl2, 2 U Supertherm Taq polymerase, 150 mM of each dNTP, 0.5 mM of each primer (F1: 59-AGAGTTTGATCITGGCTCAG-39; I = inosine and primer R5: 59-ACGGITACCTTGTTAC GACTT-39) and 2 μL template DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Primer F1 and R5 binds to base positions 7–26 and 1496–1476 of the 16S rRNA gene of Streptomyces ambofaciens ATCC 23877, respectively [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The primers in this study were used to amplify nearly full-length 16S rDNA sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The PCR programme used was an initial denaturation (96 °C for 2 min), 30 cycles of denaturation (96 °C for 45 s), annealing (56 °C for 30 s) and extension (72 °C for 2 min), and a final extension (72 °C for 5 min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Gel electrophoresis of PCR products were conducted on 1% agarose gels to confirm that a fragment of the correct size had been amplified. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Automated sequencing of the 16S rRNA genes of the bacterial isolates was performed using the Spectrumedix SCE2410 genetic analysis system with 24 capillaries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The sequencing reactions were performed according to the manufacturer’s instructions, using the Big Dye version 3.1 dye terminator cycle sequencing kit (Applied Biosystems) and 27F primer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The sequences were edited manually based on the most similar sequences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The bioflocculant produced by Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Raats showed good flocculating activity for kaolin suspension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Lactose and urea were preferred as sole carbon and nitrogen sources for bioflocculant production by the bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The divalent cation (Mg2+) as well as initial medium pH 7.0 resulted in optimal production of bioflocculant, and chemical analyses indicated the bioflocculant to be a glycoprotein made up of about 56% protein and 25% total carbohydrate. Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Raats appears to hold promise as a source of new bioflocculant that could stand as an alternative to inorganic and synthetic organic flocculants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>We are grateful to the University of Fort Hare, Alice, South Africa and the National Research Foundation (NRF) of South Africa for supporting this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>1SalehizadehH.ShojaosadatiS.A.Extracellular biopolymeric flocculants: Recent trends and biotechnology importanceBiotechnol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Adv20011937138514538073 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>2ZhengY.YeZ.-L.FangX.-L.LiY.-H.CaiW.-M.Production and characteristics of a bioflocculant produced by Bacillus sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>F19Bioresour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Technol2008997686769118358717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>3LiZ.ZhongS.LeiH.-Y.ChenR.-W.YuQ.LiH.-L.Production of a novel bioflocculant by Bacillus licheniformis X14 and its application to low temperature drinking water treatmentBioresour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Technol20091003650365619303286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>4WangL.MaF.QuY.SunD.LiA.GuoJ.YuB.Characterization of a compound bioflocculant produced by mixed culture of Rhizobium radiobacter F2 and Bacillus sphaeicus F6World J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol20112725592565 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>5FengD.L.XuS.H.Characterization of biofloculant MBF3-3 produced by an isolated Bacillus spWorld J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol20082416271632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>6WuJ.YeH.-F.Characterization and flocculating properties of an extracellular biopolymer produced from a Bacillus subtillis DYU1 isolateProcess Biochem20074211141123 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>7LiY.HeN.GuanH.DuG.ChenJ.A novel polygalacturonic acid bioflocculant REA-11 produced by Corynebacterium glutamicum: A proposed biosynthetic pathway and experimental confirmationAppl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol200310036503656 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>8WuH.LiQ.LuR.WangY.ZhuangX.HeN.Fed-batch production of a bioflocculant from Corynebacterium glutamicumJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Ind. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol2010371203120920589412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>9EschbachM.MöbitzH.RompfA.JahnD.Members of the genus Arthrobacter grow anaerobically using nitrate ammonification and fermentative processes: Anaerobic adaptation of aerobic bacteria abundant in soilFEMS Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Lett200322322723012829291 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>10PiñarG.RamosJ.L.A strain of Arthrobacter that tolerates high concentrations of nitrateBiodegradation19988393399 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>11ShenM.ZengY.-G.ShenY.-C.Isolation and characterization of a novel Arthrobacter nitroguajacolicus ZJUTB06-99, capable of converting acrylonitrile to acrylic acidProcess Biochem200944781785 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>12SuX.ShenX.DingL.YokotaA.Study on the flocculability of the Arthrobacter sp., an actinomycete resuscitated from the VBNC stateWorld J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol201110.1997/s11274-011-0795-2 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>13HeN.LiY.ChenJ.Production of a polygalacturonic acid bioflocculant REA-11 by Corynebacterium glutamicumBioresour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Technol20041009910515081493 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>14PatilS.V.SalunkheR.B.PatilC.D.PatilD.M.SalunkeB.K.Bioflocculant exopolysaccharide production by Azotobacter indicus using flower extract of Madhuca latifolia LAppl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol20101621095110819921493 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>15HeJ.ZhenQ.QiuN.LiuZ.WangB.ShaoZ.YuZ.Medium optimization for the production of a novel bioflocculant from Halomonas sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>V3a’ using response surface methodologyBioresour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Technol20091005922592719632109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>16PiyoN.CosaS.MabinyaV.L.OkohI.A.Assessment of bioflocculant production by Bacillus sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Gilbert, a marine bacterium isolated from the bottom sediment of Algoa BayMar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Drugs201191232124221822413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>17CosaS.MabinyaL.V.OlaniranA.O.OkohO.O.BernardK.DeyzelS.OkohA.I.Bioflocculant production by Virgibacillus sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Rob isolated from the bottom sediment of Algoa Bay in the Eastern Cape, South AfricaMolecules2011162431244221403600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>18YokoiH.HiroseJ.HayashiS.TakasakiY.Simultaneous production of hydrogen and bioflocculant by Enterobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>BY-29World J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol200117609613 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>19SamS.KucukasikF.YenigunO.NicolausB.OnerE.B.YukselenM.A.Flocculating performances of exopolysaccharides produced by a halophilic bacterial strain cultivated on agro-industrial wasteBioresour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Technol20111021788179420970999 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>20GongW.-X.WangS.-G.SunX.-F.LiuX.-W.YueQ.-Y.GaoB.-Y.Bioflocculant production by culture of Serratia ficaria and its application in wastewater treatmentBioresour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Technol2008994668467418024024 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>21XiaS.ZhangZ.WangX.YangA.ChenL.ZhaoJ.LeonardD.Jaffrezic-RenaultN.Production and characterization of bioflocculant by Proteus mirabilis TJ-1Bioresour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Technol2008996520652718155905 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>22GaoJ.BaoH.-Y.XinM.-X.LiuY.-X.LiQ.ZhangY.-F.Characterization of a bioflocculant from a newly isolated Vagococcus sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>W31J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Zhejiang Univ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>B2006718619216502504 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>23HeJ.ZouJ.ShaoZ.ZhangJ.LiuZ.YuZ.Characteristics and flocculating mechanism of a novel bioflocculant HBF-3 produced by deep-sea bacterium mutant Halomonas sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>V3a’World J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol20102611351141 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>24LiX.-M.YangQ.HuangK.ZengG.-M.LiaoD.-X.LiuJ.-J.LongW.-F.Screening and characterization of a bioflocculant produced by Aeromonas spBiomed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Sci20072027427817948760 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>25LiW.W.ZhouW.Z.ZhangW.Z.WangJ.ZhuX.B.Flocculation behaviour and mechanism of an exopolysaccharide from the deep-sea psychrophilic bacterium Pseudoalteromonas sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>SM9913Bioresour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Technol2008996893689918353634 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>26YokoiH.ArimaT.HiroseJ.HayashiS.TakasakiY.Flocculation properties of poly (γ-glutamic acid) produced by Bacillus subtilisJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Ferment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Bioeng1996828487 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>27BouchotrochS.QuesadaE.Del MoralA.LlamasI.BéjarV.Halomonas maura sp. nov., a novel moderately halophilic, exopolysaccharide-producing bacteriumInt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Microbiol2001511625163211594589 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>28ChoiC.W.YooS.-A.OhI.-H.ParkS.H.Characterization of an extracellular flocculating substance produced by a planktonic cyanobacterium, Anabaena spBiotechnol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Lett199820643646 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>29YokoiH.NatsudaO.HiroseJ.HayashiS.TakasakiY.Characteristics of a biopolymer flocculant produced by Bacillus sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>PY-90J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Ferment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Bioeng199579378380 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>30JangJ.-H.IkeM.KimS.M.FujitaM.Production of a novel bioflocculant by fed-batch culture of Citrobacter spBiotechnol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Lett200123593597 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>31KallosM.S.BehieL.A.Inoculation and growth conditions for high-cell-density expansion of mammalian neural stem cells in suspension bioreactorsBiotechnol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Bioeng19996347348310099628 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>32ShihI.L.VanY.T.YehL.C.LinH.G.ChangY.N.Production of a biopolymer flocculant from Bacillus licheniformis and its flocculation propertiesBioresour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Technol20017826727211341686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>33LorsC.ChehadeM.H.DamidotD.pH variations during growth of Acidithiobacillus thiooxidans in buffered media designed for an assay to evaluate concrete biodeteriorationInt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Biodeterior. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Biodegrad200963880883 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>34Kovárová-KovarK.EgliT.Growth kinetics of suspended microbial cells: From single-substrate-controlled growth, to mixed-substrate kineticsMicrobiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Rev1998626466669729604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>35InoueK.KorenagaH.KadoyaS.A sulfated polysaccharide produced by an Arthrobacter speciesJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Biochem198292177517846298190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>36ZhangZ.-Q.LinB.XiaS.-Q.WangX.-J.YangA.-M.Production and application of a novel bioflocculant by multiple microorganism consortia using brewery wastewater as carbon sourceJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Sci200719667673 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>37KuraneR.TakedaK.SuzukiT.Screening and characteristics of microbial flocculantsAgric. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Chem19865023012307 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>38LachhwaniP.Studies on Polymeric Bioflocculant Producing MicroorganismsMaster ThesisThapar Institute of Engineering and TechnologyPatiala, India2005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>39YimJ.H.KimS.J.AhnS.H.LeeH.K.Characterization of novel bioflocculant, p-KG03, from a marine dinoflagellate, Gyrodiumimpudicum KG03Bioresour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Technol20069836136716473007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40-ijms-13-01054"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>40CookA.E.MeyersP.R.Rapid identification of filamentous actinomycetes to the genus level using genus-specific 16 S rRNA gene restriction fragment patternsInt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Microbiol2003531907191514657122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f1-ijms-13-01054" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Agarose gel electrophoresis of PCR product of Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Raats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Lanes: 1 = Ladder; 2 = PCR product. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-13-01054f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f2-ijms-13-01054" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Effect of initial pH on flocculating activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-13-01054f2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f3-ijms-13-01054" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Time course assay of flocculant production by Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Raats. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-13-01054f3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="t1-ijms-13-01054" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Effect of constituents of culture medium on the production and flocculating activity of the bioflocculant produced by Arthrobacter sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Raats. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1-ijms-13-01054"><p>Note: - denotes no flocculating activity detected.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
