
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jexbot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3430997</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ers185</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Cell survival after UV radiation stress in the unicellular chlorophyte Dunaliella tertiolecta is mediated by DNA repair and MAPK phosphorylation </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>García-Gómez</surname><given-names>Candela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no"><name><surname>Parages</surname><given-names>María L.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no"><name><surname>Jiménez</surname><given-names>Carlos</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no"><name><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>Armando</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no"><name><surname>Mata</surname><given-names>M. Teresa</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Segovia</surname><given-names>María</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">*</xref></contrib><aff>Department of Ecology. Faculty of Sciences. University of Málaga, E-29071, Spain</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><sup>*</sup>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>candelagg@uma.es</email> or <email>segovia@uma.es</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>63</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>5259</fpage><lpage>5274</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author [2012]. Published by Oxford University Press [on behalf of the Society for Experimental Biology]. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/bync/3.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/bync/3.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Ultraviolet radiation (UVR) induces damage in a variety of organisms, and cells may adapt by developing repair or tolerance mechanisms to counteract such damage; otherwise, the cellular fate is cell death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Here, the effect of UVR-induced cell damage and the associated signalling and repair mechanisms by which cells are able to survive was studied in Dunaliella tertiolecta. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>UVR did not cause cell death, as shown by the absence of SYTOX Green-positive labelling cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Ultrastructure analysis by transmission electron microscopy demonstrated that the cells were alive but were subjected to morphological changes such as starch accumulation, chromatin disaggregation, and chloroplast degradation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>This behaviour paralleled a decrease in F v/F m and the formation of cyclobutane–pyrimidine dimers, showing a 10-fold increase at the end of the time course. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>There was a high accumulation of the repressor of transcriptional gene silencing (ROS1), as well as the cell proliferation nuclear antigen (PCNA) in UVR-treated cells, revealing activation of DNA repair mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The degree of phosphorylation of c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK) and p38-like mitogen-activated protein kinases was higher in UVR-exposed cells; however, the opposite occurred with the phosphorylated extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>This confirmed that both JNK and p38 need to be phosphorylated to trigger the stress response, as well as the fact that cell division is arrested when an ERK is dephosphorylated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>In parallel, both DEVDase and WEHDase caspase-like enzymatic activities were active even though the cells were not dead, suggesting that these proteases must be considered within a wider frame of stress proteins, rather than specifically being involved in cell death in these organisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><title>Key words</title><kwd>caspase-like enzymes</kwd><kwd>Dunaliella tertiolecta</kwd><kwd>cell death</kwd><kwd>cell survival</kwd><kwd>cellular proliferation nuclear antigen</kwd><kwd>cyclobutane–pyrimidine photodimers</kwd><kwd>DNA damage and repair</kwd><kwd>repressor of transcriptional gene silencing (ROS1)</kwd><kwd>mitogen-activated protein kinases</kwd><kwd>ultraviolet radiation</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Research on the environmental effects of UV radiation (UVR) in aquatic and terrestrial ecosystems has been widely fostered since the discovery of the ozone layer depletion over Antarctica, namely the ‘ozone hole’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Such research was initially focused on UVB radiation (280–315nm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>However, it soon became known that many of the effects of solar UVR were also caused by wavelengths corresponding to the UVA range (315–400nm) that were not affected by fluctuations in the stratospheric ozone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it was obvious that natural levels of incident UVR (i.e. in the absence of ozone reduction) were enough to cause significant negative effects on the biota. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The deleterious effects of UVR on aquatic systems are due mainly to the decrease in the carbon uptake capacity of primary producers and to DNA damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Aquatic ecosystems absorb a similar amount of atmospheric carbon dioxide as terrestrial ecosystems and produce half of the biomass of our planet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Both UVA and UVB reduce carbon incorporation rates of marine phytoplankton by modifying photosystem II (PSII) efficiency or the ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase (Rubisco) pool (Häder et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>A reduction in the performance of these targets decreases the ability of the cells to photosynthesize, thereby hampering the carboxylation process (Raven, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In addition, UVR effects on DNA include the generation of several photoproducts that affect replication and transcription of the DNA, causing mutations and/or cell death (Lo et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The two major classes of mutagenic DNA lesions induced by UVR are cyclobutane–pyrimidine photodimers (CPDs) and the 6-4 photoproducts (6-4PPs) (Van de Poll et al., 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>UVR also stimulates base substitutions, as well as duplications and deletions in the DNA (Yoon et al., 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>CPDs such as TT, CC and TC dimers may arrest cell-cycle progression by inhibiting cell division due to the obstruction of de novo synthesis of cellular components required for cell growth and maintenance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>DNA damage caused by exposure to UVR also induces the production of reactive oxygen species, which are one of the primary causes of DNA degradation in most aquatic organisms (Lesser, 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Consequently, growth is reduced or even arrested, driving the whole population into massive death, as described previously for natural phytoplankton communities (Llabrés and Agustí, 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Survival of the cells is based on the balance between damage induction rate and damage removal rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Damage will accumulate when the capacity of the repair mechanisms is overloaded and is not sufficient to reverse the harmful effects induced/caused by UVR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Therefore, repair of oxidative and mutagenic DNA lesions is essential to prevent mutations and cell death (Roldán-Arjona et al., 2000; Morales-Ruiz et al., 2006; Ponferrada-Marín et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Considerable evidence has been accrued to demonstrate that when cells are stimulated by biotic or abiotic stress, a complex network of specific protein phosphorylations and dephosphorylations takes place [by the so-called mitogen-activated protein kinases (MAPKs)], leading to the activation and/or de-activation of specific group of genes (Kyriakis and Avruch, 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>This process generally leads to a response that allows the cell either to adapt to the new conditions or to enter into a process that will end up in cell death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>MAPKs are grouped in canonic tri-modules, and three of these cascades—extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK), c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK) and p38—have been described completely in mammalian cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Recent studies indicate that MAPK signalling cascades are also present in vascular plants such as Arabidopsis, Nicotiana and Oryza (Nakagami et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>However, while the above-mentioned three MAPK subfamilies (ERK, JNK and p38) are present in animal cells, plant kinase genes appear to belong solely to the ERK subfamily (Zhang et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The presence of MAPK-like pathway components in algae has been described previously by our group (Jiménez et al., 2004, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>We reported the presence of both p38- and JNK-like MAPKs in Dunaliella viridis and their involvement in survival of hyperosmotically stressed cells, demonstrating the presence of ERK1/2 in this microalga and its participation in cell division, including a partial cloning of both MAPKs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Very recently, the expression of MAPK-like proteins in response to stress has been also shown in intertidal macroalgae (Parages et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results indicate that algae possess MAPK-like signalling components that serve to sense and respond to stress, permitting cell acclimation and survival under the new conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Thus, cells have different DNA repair mechanisms to counteract the lethal effects of abiotic injuries, allowing them to maintain their genetic integrity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The most important repair mechanisms are photoreactivation and excision repair. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>During photoreactivation, the enzyme photolyase in combination with photorepair wavelengths between 330nm and visible light are able to reverse the UVB-induced production of CPDs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Photolyase binds to CPDs in the DNA and, after absorbing a near-UV or blue light photon, it splits the cyclobutane ring to restore the pyrimidine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The photoreactivation process has been demonstrated widely in phytoplankton (Boelen et al., 2001; Yi et al., 2006), and in the particular case of Dunaliella tertiolecta we have cloned a CPD photolyase expressed in this species (García-Gómez C, Cano I, Mata MT and Segovia M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>GenBank accession no. JF260981) under chronic UVR exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In contrast, excision repair mechanisms are able to replace either the damaged base [base excision repair (BER)] or the whole damaged nucleotide [nucleotide excision repair (NER)] in the DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>During BER, different DNA N-glycosylases cleave the glycosylic bond between the target base and deoxyribose (García-Ortiz et al., 2001; Roldán-Arjona and Ariza, 2009), whilst during NER, the gap formed is replaced by DNA polymerases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The cell proliferation nuclear antigen (PCNA) is an auxiliary protein of the δ/ε DNA polymerase, which is essential for DNA synthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Its synthesis and abundance is cell-cycle dependent and it increases during the S phase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>PCNA is generally expressed, and the protein accumulated in phytoplankton under normal growth conditions, indicating cell proliferation (Carpenter et al., 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>However, previous reports have shown compelling evidence that PCNA is also expressed and the protein accumulates at high rates in cells exposed to UVR, evidencing its participation during DNA repair by both BER and NER pathways (Masih et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>A second nuclear protein, the repressor of transcriptional gene silencing (ROS1), also participates in UVR-induced repair mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>This protein was studied for its role in epigenetic control of gene expression (Gong et al., 2002), but it contains an endonuclease III domain with significant similarities to BER DNA proteins in the HhH-GPD superfamily (Ponferrada-Marín et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Such family contains a diverse range of structurally related DNA repair proteins including endonuclease III [DNA glycosylase/apurinic/apyrimidinic (AP) lyase] and MutY (A/G-specific adenine glycosylase) (Krokan et al., 1997; Scharer and Jiricny, 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The genome of Arabidopsis encodes several other proteins belonging to the HhH family of DNA glycosylases, all with similar DNA repair activities to homologues found in bacteria, fungi and animals (Roldán-Arjona et al., 2000; García-Ortiz et al., 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>All these proteins act as DNA glycosylases, removing oxidized pyrimidines from the DNA, as well as AP lyase, by cleaving the phosphodiester back-bone by β-elimination at the site where a damaged base has been removed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>In addition, genetic and biochemical studies have revealed that the Arabidopsis protein ROS1, which contains a DNA glycosylase domain, initiates the deletion of 5-methylcytosine though a BER process (Ortega-Galisteo et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>UVR is usually considered to be a stressor for phytoplankton that reduces the photosynthetic uptake of atmospheric carbon dioxide and affects species diversity, ecosystem stability, trophic interactions and global biogeochemical cycles, driving microalgae into decreased cell viability and, in most of species, leading to cell death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The occurrence of programmed cell death (PCD) as an active mechanism by which mass cell death takes place as a consequence of biotic and abiotic stress has been widely reported in unicellular chlorophytes (Segovia et al., 2003; Darehshouri et al., 2008; Zuppini et al., 2010), dinoflagellates (Vardi et al., 1999; Bouchard and Purdie, 2011), cyanobacteria (Ross and Paul, 2006), diatoms (Timmermans et al., 2007), haptophytes (Bidle et al., 2007; Franklin et al., 2012), and natural communities (Veldhuis et al., 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The mechanisms by which cell death (programmed or not) occurs, considering that cell death in unicells leads to the complete demise of the organism, are always intriguing and there are still many unanswered questions (Nedelcu et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Among these are the questions of what is the proteolytic machinery involved and how it works. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Caspase-like (CL) activities have been reported to be involved in PCD in plants, fungi, protists, and protozoa (Bonneau et al., 2008; Pérez-Martín, 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Regarding phytoplankton, the nature of CL activities remains an unrevealed question. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Although it is known that CL activities are involved in cell death, these proteases are also essential during the normal physiology of the cells with constitutive functions, as well as during growth and cell stress acclimation (Segovia and Berges, 2005; Bouchard and Purdie, 2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Microalgae from the genus Dunaliella are among the most ubiquitous eukaryotic organisms and are well known for their extraordinarily high tolerance to salinity, temperature, nutrient limitation, and irradiance (Ben-Amotz et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>These features make these microalgae perfect candidates as model organisms for the study of environmental stress responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>As such, in previous works, we have shown that survival of the halotolerant species D. viridis subjected to environmental stress was crucially dependent on phosphorylation of p38- and JNK-like MAPKs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Cell division was impaired after hyperosmotic shock, UVR, heat shock, and nutrient starvation, caused by a marked decrease in the phosphorylated form of ERK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>However, depending on the stress factor and on its intensity, cells underwent PCD, as demonstrated morphologically and by an increase in the CL activity DEVDase (Jiménez et al., 2004, 2007, 2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The aim of this work was to elucidate why D. tertiolecta cells did not die when subjected to chronic UVR exposure and the reasons for their resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>For this purpose, we studied the dynamics of DNA damage accumulation and repair, with regard to cell death and/or survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>We showed that cells survived chronic UVR exposure by activation of DNA repair mechanisms by means of PCNA and ROS1-protein accumulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Concurrently, we demonstrate that activation of MAPK-like proteins mediated the process and we have also provided evidences that CL proteins, mainly regarded as cell death proteases, are also involved in the response to stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>As such, these proteases must be considered within a wider frame of stress proteins, rather than being specifically involved in cell death in these organisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Culture conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The unicellular chlorophyte D. tertiolecta (CCAP 19/6) was used in this work. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Cells were grown in sterile acrylic cylinders (Plexiglas XT® 29080) transparent to UV, in artificial seawater (Goldman and McCarthy, 1978) f/2 enriched (Guillard and Ryther, 1962). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The cells were maintained at 16 ºC, under continuous stirring and bubbling, at an irradiance of 100 µmol quanta m–2 s–1, until they reached mid-exponential growth phase, when treatment was begun. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The treatments comprised the application of photosynthetically active radiation (PAR) or PAR+UVA+UVB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The different irradiance conditions where achieved by covering the experimental cylinders with cut-off filters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Ultraphan UBT 395 (Digefra, München, Germany) transmitted only PAR (P treatment), while Ultraphan UBT 295 (Digefra, München, Germany) transmitted PAR, UVA and UVB (PAB treatment). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>PAR was obtained by using Optimarc 250 W lamps (DuroTest, USA) and measured using an Ocean Optics SMS 500 spectroradiometer (Sphaereoptics, Contoocook, New Hampshire, USA) calibrated after National Physical Laboratory standards with a cosine-corrected sensor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>UV fluence rates were provided by Qpanel-340 lamps (9.5 Wm-2 UVA and 0.45 Wm-2 UVB, unweighted) and measured with a MACAM UV203 radiometer (MACAM Photometrics, Livingston, UK) and with the Ocean Optics SMS 500 spectroradiometer mentioned above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Spectra were measured in the range 250–800nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>All light measurements were carried out inside the cylinders once they were wrapped with the appropriate cut-off filters. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Cell abundance and cell death </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>For cell counts, 1ml of fresh cell culture was counted in a Coulter Counter (Z2 Beckman Coulter, Fullerton, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The growth rate (r) was calculated as the number of cell doublings day–1 by fitting an exponential function to the logarithmic phase of the growth curve. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Cell death was estimated using SYTOX Green (Invitrogen, OR, USA) according to the method of Segovia and Berges (2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Basically, cell pellets were resuspended in 1ml of 10mM PBS buffer (pH 7) containing SYTOX Green at a final concentration of 20 µM, incubated at 16 °C in the dark for 30min and analysed by flow cytometry using a DakoCytomation flow cytometer (MoFlo, Beckman Coulter, Fullerton, CA, USA) and under an epifluorescence microscope (Leitz, Wetzlar, Germany) at an excitation wavelength of 450–490nm and emission wavelength of 523nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Positive controls consisted of cells killed by fixation with 1% glutaraldehyde. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Samples were analysed in triplicate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>In vivo chlorophyll a fluorescence </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The optimal quantum yield of PSII fluorescence (F v/F m) was measured with a Water-PAM fluorometer (Waltz, Effeltrich, Germany) as described by Schreiber et al. (1986), considering F v/F m as (F m – F o)/F m according to Genty et al. (1989), F v is the maximal variable fluorescence of a dark-adapted sample, F m is the maximal fluorescence intensity with all PSII reaction centres closed, and F o is the basal fluorescence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>High F v/F m values indicate that cells are in a good condition, whereas a decrease in F v/F m indicates stress and photoinhibition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s6"><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>DAPI is a popular nuclear counter-stain for use in multicolour fluorescent techniques. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Its blue fluorescence stands out in vivid contrast to the green, yellow, or red fluorescent probes of other structures and it specifically stains nuclei, with little or no cytoplasmic labelling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>DAPI (Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR, USA) was added at a concentration of 1–10 µM and incubated for 5min at room temperature according to the method of Jiménez et al. (2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Samples were analysed using a DakoCytomation flow cytometer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Counts were triggered using forward scatter signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>DAPI fluorescence was observed through a 435–485nm band-pass filter and chlorophyll fluorescence through a 650–710nm band-pass filter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s7"><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Cells were harvested by centrifugation (15min at 7000 g) and fixed in cacodylate buffer (100mM, pH 7.2) containing 4% glutaraldehyde and 8.6 % sucrose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Pellets were washed in a series of cacodylate buffers with descending sucrose concentration and post-fixed in 1% osmium tetroxide dissolved in Milli-Q ultrapure water (Millipore, USA) for 2h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>After dehydration in an ascending series of ethanol (70–100%), samples were embedded in 4 % agar resin and ultrathin sections (60nm thickness) were prepared with a Reichert-Jung ultramicrotome (Leipzig, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Sections were stained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate, and observed under a Philips CM 100 transmission electron microscope at different magnifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Quantification of cells by TEM can be problematic; therefore, counting of cells showing each of the different characteristics was carried out for three fields of view for each treatment at the lowest magnification. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s8"><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>DNA damage </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>For the detection of DNA damage, 25ml of D. tertiolecta was collected by centrifugation and the pellets frozen at –80° C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>DNA was extracted following the procedure provided with the DNeasy Plant Mini kit (Qiagen, VA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The extracted DNA was quantified using the fluorescent probe Quant-iTTM PicoGreen® kit (Invitrogen, OR, USA,) and CPDs were analysed by a modification of the protocol described by Boelen et al. (1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Thirty nanograms of DNA in 200ml of TE buffer [10mM Tris/HCl (pH 7.5), 1mM EDTA final concentration] were loaded onto a nylon HybondTM-N+ membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The membrane was incubated overnight at 4 °C with a primary anti-thymine dimer H3 monoclonal antibody (Affitech, Oslo, Norway) (diluted 1:600). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>After the appropriate washes and incubation with horseradish peroxidase-conjugated anti-mouse secondary antibody (diluted 1:5000) (Abcam, Cambridge, UK), the signal was detected by chemiluminescence (ECL; GE Healthcare, Buckinghamshire, UK) and the intensity of cross-reactions was quantified using a Gel Logic Image Analyser (Eastman-Kodak, Rochester, NY, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s9"><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Western blots </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s10"><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>PCNA and ROS1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>For PCNA and ROS1 detection and protein accumulation studies, SDS-PAGE (12 % acrylamide) was performed on an equal protein concentration basis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Proteins were extracted according to the method of Segovia and Berges (2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>For PCNA immunodetection, blots were probed with anti-PCNA-at263 antibody at a 1:2000 dilution (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, California, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>For ROS1 immunodetection, blots were probed with an anti-Arabidopsis thaliana ROS1 protein polyclonal antibody (α-AtROS1) kindly provided by Professor Teresa Roldán-Arjona (Córdoba University, Spain; Gong et al., 2002; Morales-Ruiz et al., 2006) at a 1:1000 dilution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>An antigenic AtROS1 Sepharose-purified recombinant protein was also used as the antibody-blocking peptide (blockage binding-site ratio of 1:4, antibody:recombinant protein, in moles) to check for absolute specificity of the antibody, as well as for positive controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Antibodies were also blocked with Rubisco to ensure that there was no recognition of this protein, as we were using an anti-rabbit polyclonal antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Pre-immune sera were used for the appropriate non-specific ROS1-reactivity negative controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Additionally, a secondary antibody non-specific cross-reactivity control was carried out by incubating the membranes with the secondary antibody only in absence of the primary antibody. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s11"><title><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>ERK, p38, and JNK kinases </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>For MAPK extraction, 15ml of D. tertiolecta culture of each treatment were centrifuged in duplicates (1500g, 10min) at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Pellets were resuspended in 100 µl of 10 % SDS, and gently mixed with 400 µl of MAPK lysis buffer [50mM β-glycerophosphate (pH 7.2), 0.1mM sodium vanadate, 2mM MgCl2, 1mM EGTA, 1mM dithiothreitol, 2 µg ml–1 leupeptin, 4 μg ml–1 aprotinin]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Samples were placed in a pre-cooled sonicating water bath (Branson 2510; Branson Ultrasonic Corp., Danbury, CT, USA) for 5min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>A centrifugation step (4°C, 30min, 15 000 g) was applied to remove all cell debris and the supernatant was assayed for protein quantification by the BCA method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Western blots were performed by modifying the protocol described previously by Jiménez et al. (2004), in which tricine was used instead of glycine in the gels for better resolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Antibodies against the phosphorylated forms of p38, JNK, and ERK MAPKs, as well as their specific blocking peptides, were purchased from Cell Signaling Technology (Beverly, MA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The possibility of non-specific cross-reactivity with the antibodies raised against the phosphorylated forms of the MAPKs from mammalian cells was also analysed by incubating at least one lane of each treatment directly with the secondary antibodies, avoiding contact with the primary ones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Non-specific bands were not included in further analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The signal on the membranes was detected by chemiluminescence, as described above. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s12"><title><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>CL activities </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Cells were harvested by centrifugation and resuspended in lysis buffer [50mM HEPES (pH 7.3), 100mM NaCl, 10 % sucrose, 0.1 % CHAPS, 10mM dithiothreitol] and sonicated (UP50H; Hielscher GmbH, Germany) on ice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Extracts were mixed with 50 µM (final concentration) of 7-amino-4-methyl coumarin (AMC) of the labelled substrates acetyl-l-tryptophyl-l-glutamyl-l-histidyl-l-aspartic acid-AMC (WEHD) and acetyl-l-aspartyl-l-glutamyl-l-valyl-l-aspartic acid-AMC (DEVD) (Peptanova GmbH, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The fluorescence emitted as a consequence of substrate cleavage was measured for 4h at 16 °C (excitation 360nm, emission 460nm) in a microplate fluorescence reader (FL-600; Bio-Tek, Vermont, USA), according to the method of Segovia and Berges (2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s13"><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Data were checked for heterogeneity of variances and for normality using Cochran and Mann–Whitney’ U tests, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Differences due to the effect of light treatments and time were then tested by two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and ANOVA-RM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Where significant differences were detected, post-hoc multiple comparisons were applied using Holm-Sidak or Newman–Keuls tests (considering P &lt;0.05 as significant). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>To quantify the relationship between the variables, we performed Pearson’s product-moment correlations (considering P &lt;0.05 as significant). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Values are expressed as means ±standard deviation (SD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The statistical analyses were carried out using the SigmaPlot 11.0 statistical package (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s14"><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s15"><title><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Cell abundance and cell death </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The cell density of D. tertiolecta (Fig. 1A) increased in P treatment during the time course of the experiment, reaching the stationary phase at 144h, by which time the cell cultures had started to decay (r = 0.44 dd–1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Unexpectedly, we observed a net growth in UV-exposed cultures, although the cell density increase was nearly four times lower under PAB than under P treatment (r = 0.12 dd–1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1. </label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>(A) D. tertiolecta cell abundance in cultures grown under continuous P (closed symbols) or continuous PAB (open symbols) conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>(B) Changes in the optimum quantum yield (F v⁄F m) in cultures grown under P (closed symbols) or PAB (open symbols) conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Symbols are the mean ±SD of two replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The insert shows a representative epifluorescence micrograph of SYTOX Green-treated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The chlorophyll red fluorescence in cultures grown under PAB treatment demonstrates that the cells are alive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Statistically significant differences (P &lt;0.05) between treatments are indicated by asterisks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ers185_f0001"/></fig><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Cell death was checked with the fluorescent probe SYTOX Green. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>When the plasma membrane is compromised, cells incubated with this nucleic acid stain will fluoresce green, whereas living cells appear red due to the autofluorescence of chlorophyll a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Over the time course of the experiments, approximately 99% of the cells were alive and swimming in both treatments, as demonstrated by the absence of green fluorescent labelling and by the presence of chlorophyll red fluorescence (Fig. 1A, insert). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The presence of green fluorescence in the positive control corresponding to dead cells killed by fixation with glutaraldehyde (data not shown) confirmed the integrity of the cells in all treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Hence, cell death was not detected in any of the cultures stressed with UVR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s16"><title><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Photosynthetic efficiency </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The optimum quantum yield of PSII (F v/F m) was used as an indicator of stress and photoinhibition (Fig. 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The F v/F m value dropped significantly from values close to 0.6 at the beginning of the experiments to values below 0.09 in just 2h under UVRtreatment (data not shown) and to 0.2 in 24h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The values with P treatment were significantly different throughout the experiment and were about 6-fold higher than under PAB treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>UVR-exposed cells were transferred to a recovery treatment under P conditions to contrast the results obtained with SYTOX Green, indicating the absence of cell death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Under these conditions, the F v/F m value showed an increase of 200% from the minimum value in only 24h under P treatment, and these values were maintained until 72h. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s17"><title><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Cell cycle </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The results obtained for F v/F m were confirmed by flow cytometry analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry (Fig. 2A) showed that when cultures were in the mid-exponential phase (t = 0 before UVR exposure), 78 % of the cells were in the G1 phase of the cell cycle (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>However, only after 1h of PAB treatment, the number of cells in G1 decreased dramatically to 22 %, and this value did not change significantly during the rest of the experiment, with no parallel increase in counts in other stages of the cell cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>However, there was a significant increase in DAPI fluorescence (Fig. 2A, arrows), indicating chromatin disaggregation, without indicating any shift in the chromatin content as a result of the cell cycle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2. </label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>(A) Flow cytometry analysis of DAPI-labelled D. tertiolecta cells exposed to PAB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>(B) Variation in the number of cells in the G1 phase of the cell cycle with respect to the total number of cells counted during PAB treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ers185_f0002"/></fig></sec><sec id="s18"><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Cell morphology </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The cell cycle results paralleled the cell morphology observed by TEM (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Micrographs showed normal vegetative cells growing under PAR conditions, with conspicuous Golgi, mitochondria, chloroplasts, pyrenoids, and scarce starch spots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Nuclei were well defined and surrounded by the nuclear membrane, with the chromatin compacted in the nucleoli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>From 72h onwards, cells presented symptoms of senescence, and by the end of the experiment, most of the cells showed chromatin marginalization (144h) while the organelles remained intact. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>When cells were cultured under PAB conditions, their morphology was also unaltered, and the nucleolus was well structured in the nucleus; however, the chromatin started to disaggregate and formed dense spots at early stages of exposure, while the appearance of the organelles did not change. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>In addition, starch accumulation in the cytoplasm occurred from 48h onwards, coincident with slight chloroplastic degradation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The micrographs did not provide evidence for cell death indicators under UVR exposure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3. </label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Representative transmission electron micrographs showing the morphological changes in D. tertiolecta cultures exposed to P or PAB treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>C, chloroplast; N, nucleus; G, Golgi, M, mitochondria; P, pyrenoid; S, starch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Note the chromatin marginalization (arrow 1) due to natural senescence of the cultures under P treatment, and the cellular changes associated with UVR exposure such as chromatin spots (arrows 2 and 4), starch accumulation and slight chloroplastic degradation (arrow 3), and chromatin disaggregation (arrow 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Bar corresponds to 1 µm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ers185_f0003"/></fig></sec><sec id="s19"><title><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>DNA damage and repair </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The presence of CPDs is a direct indicator of DNA damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The evident effect of UVR exposure on CPD accumulation can be seen in Fig. 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Both P and PAB treatments presented a low intensity pattern for CPD accumulation at the initial time (t = 0), which was not significant (P &gt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>During the course of the experiment with P treatment, CPD accumulation did not change significantly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>However, cells exposed to UVR (PAB treatment) suffered a remarkable 5-fold increase by 24h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>From 72h onwards, there was an increase in the intensity of the dots, peaking at 144h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>At this point, differences between the two light treatments were 7-fold higher under PAB treatment and more than 8-fold when compared with the initial values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4. </label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Quantification of the intensity of the dots under P (closed symbols) or PAB (open symbols) treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Data points are the mean±SD of three replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Statistically significant differences(P &lt;0.05) between treatments are indicated by asterisks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ers185_f0004"/></fig><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>We studied two proteins directly related to DNA repair after UV stress, PCNA and ROS1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>PCNA accumulated at a high rate in cells exposed to UVR, indicating its participation during both BER and NER pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Differences in PCNA accumulation during the two light treatments were estimated by the relative intensity of the immunologically detected 36kDa band (Fig. 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>PCNA trends were highly similar to the pattern obtained for CPD formation (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The results showed a basal amount of PCNA protein with P treatment that did not change significantly over the time course of the experiment (P &gt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>However, when UVR was present, the PCNA level was slightly augmented at 24h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, at 48 and 72h its concentration increased 4 and 7-fold, respectively, compared with the P treatment and with the level at t = 0 before UVR exposure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5. </label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Western blots showing cross-reactions of protein extracts from cultures of D. tertiolecta under continuous P (closed symbols) or continuous PAB (open symbols) with two A. thaliana polyclonal antibodies raised against PCNA (A), which showed a clear 36kDa band, and ROS1 (B), which revealed a single band of 52kDa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Results are shown as the mean±SD of two replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Statistically significant differences (P &lt;0.05) between treatments and bands obtained by image analyses are indicated by asterisks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ers185_f0005"/></fig><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>ROS1 also participates during repair mechanisms caused by UVR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>It was found that the antibody against ROS1 from A. thaliana detected a 52kDa band. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>As found for PCNA, with both the P and PAB treatments, D. tertiolecta presented a basal amount of ROS1 protein at the start of the experiment (t = 0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>As before, in control cultures under P conditions, ROS1 levels did not change significantly during the course of the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>However, when cells were cultured under PAB, protein accumulation increased significantly after 48h, reaching values three to six times higher than with P treatment after 72h and 144h, respectively (Fig. 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>In order to ensure that the bands detected by the antibody corresponded to the recombinant ROS1 protein, the binding site between the protein and the primary antibody was specifically blocked as described in Materials and Methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>In the presence of the blocked antibody, a clear reduction in the intensity of the bands (&gt;90%) was seen, confirming that detection was indeed specific for ROS1 protein (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s20"><title><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>MAPK phosphorylation in response to stress </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Phosphorylation of the JNK-like MAPK in D. tertiolecta under P and PAB treatment is depicted in Fig. 6A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>It can be seen that a clear 45kDa band was detected by the antibody against the phosphorylated form of mammalian JNKs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Basal phosphorylation of this JNK-like protein occurred before the light treatments (Fig. 6A, t = 0), indicating that constitutive phosphorylation of this MAPK-like protein exists in this microalga. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>In addition, a significant increase in phosphorylation occurred over the following 48h with PAR treatment, coinciding with the time when cultures reached their loading capacity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>At 144h, during the stationary phase of growth, the degree of phosphorylation dropped off to initial levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The pattern changed when UVR was applied to the cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The degree of phosphorylation was always higher under PAB than under P treatment after 48h of culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Maximum phosphorylation was found at 72h, but a decrease to initial levels was not detected at 144h, as was found with PAR treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>To be sure that the bands detected by the specific phosphorylated JNK antibody corresponded to a JNK-like protein in D. tertiolecta, the binding site between the protein and the primary phospho-antibody was again specifically blocked by using specific blocking peptides as indicated in Materials and Methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>These peptides abolished the signals from the indicated phospho-JNK MAPK, confirming that the antibody was indeed specific for a phospho-JNK-like protein (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F6" position="float"><label>Fig. 6. </label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Western blots showing the phosphorylated forms of MAPK-like proteins in D. tertiolecta under continuous P (closed symbols) or continuous PAB (open symbols) treatment using polyclonal antibodies raised against phosphorylated JNK (A), which revealed the presence of a single band of 45kDa, phosphorylated p38 (B), which cross-reacted with a specific 40kDa protein, and phosphorylated ERK (C), which showed a clear 44kDa band. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Statistically significant differences (P &lt;0.05) between treatments and bands obtained by image analyses are indicated by asterisks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ers185_f0006"/></fig><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Phosphorylation of a p38-like MAPK was also detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The results presented in Fig. 6B show the different behaviour of phosphorylation after P or PAB treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Activation of a 40kDa p38-like MAPK was very scarce under P conditions; however, a significant increase in phosphorylation was detected in the presence of UVR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>It can be seen that the degree of phosphorylation peaked 24h after the initiation of the light treatment (band intensity was 2.5 times higher than at t = 0 and than in control PAR cultures). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>This phosphorylation was reduced to initial levels over the following 48h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>The use of p38-specific blocking peptide also greatly reduced, almost to undetectable levels, the intensity of the band of this p38-like MAPK, indicating the high degree of similarity between this protein in  D. tertiolecta and the mammalian p38. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Finally, we tested the specific phospho-ERK1/2 antibodies of mammalian origin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>It was clear that a 44kDa ERK-like MAPK was activated by P treatment to much higher levels than by PAB treatment after 24h (Fig. 6C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>From this point, the degree of phosphorylation was reduced almost to initial levels after 144h under P conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the degree of phosphorylation showed small changes under PAB treatment over the course of the experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>The use of a specific blocking peptide of mammalian ERK resulted in a total disappearance of the band, indicating that this protein is similar to a mammalian ERK1/2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s21"><title><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>CL activities </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Caspase-like activities were analysed to check whether these enzymes were present and/or active, even though the cells were not dead. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>DEVDase activities were found to be constant and lower than WEHDase activities, and did not experience any significant change during UVR exposure (P &gt;0.05) (Fig. 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>However, the pattern of DEVDase activity was different with P treatment, where the activity increased about 3-fold during the first 24h compared with PAB treatment, and finally dropping off to initial values after 72h (Fig. 7A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Under PAB treatment, no significant variation in DEVDase activity was found during the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>In contrast to DEVDase, WEHDase activity (Fig. 7B) initially increased under PAB treatment at 24h, showing a fluctuating pattern around the initial values for the rest of the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>When UVR was not present (P treatment), the enzymatic activity decreased dramatically at about 7-fold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>These results demonstrated that both pathways were active, showing a broad range of enzymatic activity depending on the treatments, even though the cells were not dead. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F7" position="float"><label>Fig. 7. </label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>DEVDase (A) and WEHDase (B) enzymatic activities in D. tertiolecta cells with P (closed symbols) or PAB (open symbols) treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Results are shown as means±SD of two replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Statistically significant differences (P &lt;0.05) between treatments are indicated by asterisks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ers185_f0007"/></fig></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s22"><title><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s23"><title><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Effects of UVR on cell death or survival, photosynthesis and cell morphology </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>When aquatic organisms are subjected to stressful irradiance, the most compelling sign of photosynthetic capacity loss due to photoinhibition is a sharp decrease in optimal quantum yield. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>When D. tertiolecta cells were exposed to PAB treatment, there was a dramatic decrease in F v/F m in just 2h of exposure from 0.6 to 0.09. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Several studies in algae have described the oxidative degradation of the D1 protein in the PSII reaction centre (Hanelt, 1998) after exposure to excess irradiance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Despite the initial decline in F v/F m in cultures under PAB treatment, the values obtained for this parameter indicated the presence of some photosynthetic activity and, consequently, that the cells were able to tolerate high UVR doses (Fig. 1B), probably due to DNA and other cellular component repair processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The decline in F v/F m in PAB cultures was due to cell damage, as demonstrated by the morphological analysis showing degradation of the chloroplasts from 48h onwards (Fig. 1B) and as also observed by Melis et al. (1992) and Bouchard et al. (2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>When UVR is added to PAR, DNA damage means that the synthesis of essential proteins does not occur (Jordan, 1996; Meador et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Thus, in addition to D1 and PSII reaction centre degradation, the electron transport chains and photophosphorylation processes are inhibited, and the electron-demanding Rubisco content also decreases (Neale et al., 1993), producing an excess of reactive oxygen species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>The slight decline in F v/F m in P-treated cultures in the long term could be attributed to senescence, which was corroborated by morphological analysis showing that chromatin marginalization started after 72h (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>As observed in plants, cell cultures and unicellular photosynthetic organisms, chromatin condensation has been found to accompany cell death after different types of induction mechanisms (Moharikar et al., 2006; Darehshouri et al., 2008; Jiménez et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>This was the only effect observed in P-treated cells, as the rest of the organelles remained intact. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>PAB exposure produced a decrease in the growth rate and carrying capacity of the cultures compared with P-treated cultures (Fig. 1A) because DNA damage arrests the cell cycle (discussed below). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>For instance, phytoplankton growth rates are inhibited by UVR, and this was found to be five times higher in UVR-excluded treatments (Llabrés and Agustí, 2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>The unavoidable consequence of these events in cell fate is death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>It is well known that, despite protective systems and repair pathways, cell death is caused by UVR exposure in phytoplanktonic organisms, as demonstrated for natural phytoplankton populations from the Atlantic Ocean (Llabrés and Agustí 2006), and in controlled culture conditions in Chlamydomonas (Moharikar et al., 2006) and Dunaliella (Jiménez et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>However, cell death was not detected in any of the D. tertiolecta cultures stressed with UVR (Fig. 1, insert), indicating that this particular species is capable of tolerating UVR for at least 6 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>The most remarkable changes observed were the rapid disaggregation of the chromatin under PAB treatment after the first hours of exposure, while other cellular structures remained unchanged after 48h, when only apparent degradation of the chloroplast began (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Hence, the nucleus suffered the effects of UVR stress in the short term, while the rest of the cell suffered it in the long term, indicating high cellular resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>These results agreed with those obtained by flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>The cytograms showed that, with the UVR treatment, the number of cells in G1 decreased exponentially due to rapid disaggregation of the chromatin (Fig. 2); therefore, the cell cycle could not be assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>This was a direct consequence of UVR confirmed by other studies in which UVB exposure induced doubling of the cell volume in Dunaliella salina, a phenomenon that has been attributed to DNA damage and consequent cessation of the processes involved in the cell cycle (Masi and Melis, 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>The same effect has been observed in other algae exposed to UVB (Behrenfeld et al., 1992) and has been attributed to direct damage to the microtubules, resulting in a slow down of the G2 phase (Zaremba et al., 1984; Staxen et al., 1993). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>In our experiments, cell-cycle arrest by DNA damage was confirmed by the detection and accumulation of CPDs (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Regarding the optimal quantum yield data, it was obvious that cells were photosynthetically active. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>This explains the high accumulation of starch that was observed (Fig. 3, see PAB panel at 24h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The energy produced by photosynthesis is not demanded by cell division, because the cell cycle is arrested due to DNA damage and the energy is stored as starch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>It is known that plant abiotic stress affects metabolism kinetics, resulting in the accumulation of starch (Muñoz et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>This accumulated energy could be advantageous for the cell if the cause of the stress disappears. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>The results showed a decrease in F v/F m and growth rates in PAB-treated cultures at the end of the experiment (Fig. 1) due to the accumulation of DNA damage caused by UVR, which results in the continuous inhibition of the synthesis of numerous proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>This has a direct consequence on cell replication, photosynthesis, and other essential processes, but it did not produce cell death, as demonstrated by the absence of green fluorescent labelling in all treatments (Fig. 1, insert). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s24"><title><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>DNA damage and repair mechanisms triggered by UVR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>DNA is a principal target of shortwave radiation in algae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>DNA predominantly absorbs in the UVB region, largely contributing to lethal damage (reviewed by Buma et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Formation of CPDs is the most common injury associated with UVB exposure, causing the disruption of DNA replication (Buma et al., 2001; Helbling et al., 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>In contrast, exposure to UVA has different effects on DNA, most of them indirectly through the formation of reactive oxygen species and the production of modified bases (Jeffrey and Mitchell, 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>However, UVA has a relevant role in the removal of CPDs through a photoreactivation mechanism that eliminates UVR-induced photoproducts through the action of a photolyase, an enzyme that uses the energy of UVR or PAR to break the dimers, restoring the DNA integrity (Britt, 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Our results showed that PAB treatment induced CPD formation after just 8h of exposure (data not shown), reaching an accumulation level ten times higher at the end of the experiments than at the beginning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>In contrast, P-treated cultures, as expected, showed no increase in the amount of CPDs during the 6 days of exposure (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>However, the damage caused by PAB treatment did not completely suppress DNA replication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Studies in macrophytes have shown that species such as Palmaria palmata, Devaleraea ramentacea, Phycodrys rubens, and Laminaria saccharina have the capacity to remove 90% of induced CPDs in just 5h, although other species such as Odonthalia dentata, Coccotylus truncates, and Monostroma arcticum did not show this capacity (Van de Poll et al., 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>These studies concluded that CPD induction is lower in the Arctic than in temperate and tropical regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>This low capacity of arctic macrophytes seemed to be enough to prevent accumulation of CPDs in their natural habitat. Boelen et al. (2001) observed these same repair mechanisms in tropical phytoplankton when the UVR dose was reduced, and also during and after exposure to UVR of bacteria and phytoplankton in the Red Sea (Boelen et al., 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, these mechanisms were not sufficient to remove DNA damage, suggesting that photomortality is responsible for the loss of the plankton community, which was not the same in our case. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Cell density increased slightly during UVR exposure, so it could be concluded that there are mechanisms for CPD removal, probably by activation of photolyases through UVA, as well as other repair mechanisms induced by the detection of DNA damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Among these, NER and BER are the most important. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>BER is a critical pathway in cellular defence against endogenous or exogenous DNA damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>This complex multistep process is initiated by DNA glycosylases that excise the damaged base and continues through the concerted action of additional proteins that finally restore the DNA to the unmodified state (Fortini and Dogliotti, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>BER has been studied in detail in eukaryotes, and Córdoba-Cañero et al. (2009) extended the biochemical analysis to plants, demonstrating that Arabidopsis cell extracts were able to fully repair U:G mismatches initiated by glycosylase activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>In vascular plants, active DNA demethylation is carried out mainly by a small group of bifunctional DNA glycosylases, including ROS1, DME, DML2, and DML3 [founding members of the DEMETER-LIKE (DML) family]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Once these DNA glycosylases remove the methylated cytosine base and create an abasic site, the gap is refilled with an unmethylated cytosine through a BER pathway (Zhu, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, our results showed an accumulation of a ROS1-like protein in response to UVR treatment from 48h of exposure to the end of the experiment (Fig. 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>A positive correlation was found between TT dimmers and ROS1 accumulation (P &lt;0.0001, r = 0.766). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>In A. thaliana, the molecular weight for ROS1 is around 160kDa, but it has been demonstrated that members of the DML family are large polypeptides that possess a discontinuous catalytic domain (Ponferrada-Marín et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>The antibody we used was raised against a 30kDa peptide, which is the specific part of the AtROS1 protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>We obtained a single 52kDa band that disappeared when the antibody was blocked with the recombinant protein, and that passed through all the non-specific binding tests performed (see Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Thus, we assumed that, in D. tertiolecta, the protein is smaller. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>In contrast, cultures without UVR exposure presented a basal amount of ROS1 throughout the experiment, without any significant change (Fig. 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>This confirmed all the previous results with regard to cell-cycle progress, morphology, and CPD accumulation, and it also confirmed all the triggered repair mechanisms such as BER and NER, which allowed the cells to survive under UVR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>This hypothesis was corroborated by PCNA accumulation, another protein involved in DNA repair. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>PCNA has received considerable attention because of its role in multiple cellular pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>In addition to DNA replication and repair events such as base excision, it is also involved in various other processes including NER (Nichols and Sancar, 1992), mismatch repair (Umar et al., 1996), cell-cycle control (Watanabe et al., 1998), apoptosis (Scott et al., 2001), and transcription (Hasan et al., 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>The primary amino acid sequences of PCNA are highly conserved across the eukaryotic kingdom and more than 90% homology has been observed among plant PCNA proteins (Bagewadi et al., 2004). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>In our experiments, it was shown that damage caused to the DNA triggers the accumulation of this protein from the start of the PAB treatment (Fig. 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>As exposure under UVR was extended, the synthesis of PCNA was higher because accumulation of damage was greater, as shown by the CPD results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>A positive correlation was found between TT dimmers and PCNA accumulation (P &lt;0.0001, r = 0.893). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>These data agree with changes in cell morphology, as detected by disaggregation of chromatin within hours after the outset of the treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>The basal amount of protein found at the beginning of the experiments is appointed to cell division, because PCNA is also involved in DNA replication (Carpenter et al., 1998), since it is a polymerase auxiliary protein and its presence in the nucleus of D. tertiolecta indicates that cells are in S phase of the cell cycle (Lin et al., 1995). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>A positive correlation was found between ROS1 and PCNA accumulation (P &lt;0.0001, r = 0.790). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s25"><title><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>MAPK phosphorylation and the response to stress </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>The presence and phosphorylation of three MAPK-like proteins was detected in D. tertiolecta in response to UVR (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>These MAPK-like proteins were most similar to mammalian p38, JNK, and ERK1/2, and showed different behaviours depending on the presence or not of UVR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Six MAPK cascades have been proposed to date in mammalian cells, in only three of which (p38, c-Jun, and ERK) all components have been completely identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>These cascades are involved in the response to a variety of stress conditions (UVR, heat, osmolarity, growth factors, hormones, etc.) and control of cell proliferation and differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>In previous studies, we demonstrated that p38-like and JNK-like MAPKs were responsible for stress adaptation inD. viridis, while ERK1/2-like protein was involved in cell division control (Jiménez et al., 2004, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>In the current study, it was found that increased phosphorylation of a 40kDa p38-like MAPK occurred in D. tertiolecta in the first 24h after exposure to UVR, and the degree of phosphorylation was progressively reduced to initial levels by 144h (Fig. 6B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>However, activation of this protein with P treatment was much lower and occurred progressively during the first 72h of exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>JNK-like MAPK was also activated with both in P and PAB treatment, but, activation was higher in the latter and the course of the activation was more extended over time (Fig. 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Finally, an ERK-like MAPK was also highly phosphorylated with P treatment during the first days (Fig. 6C), in parallel with the exponential phase of division of D. tertiolecta. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>These results indicated a relationship between UVR stress and p38 and JNK phosphorylation, and, as expected, a decrease in ERK phosphorylation in stressed cells. Jiménez et al. (2007) showed that ERK phosphorylation was mandatory for completing cell division in D. viridis, and that several environmental stresses resulted in cell division reduction or arrest due to ERK dephosphorylation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Both p38 and JNK have been extensively described to be responsible for stress adaptation in animal cells (Capasso et al., 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Among these stresses, it is worth mentioning hyperosmolarity and UVR exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>With regard to D. tertiolecta, a similar response was obtained, with a significant increase in the phosphorylation of both kinases in response to UVR stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>We have shown previously that inhibition of p38 and JNK phosphorylation in D. viridis highly impaired adaptation under stressful conditions, as was the case with D. tertiolecta. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that this microalga survives under high UVR stress conditions by activating several cell programmes, among them p38- and JNK-like MAPKs and DNA repair mechanisms such as PCNA plus ROS1 accumulation and CL activities. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s26"><title><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>CL activities as stress proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Caspase-like activities have been reported to be involved in PCD in organisms other than metazoans (Segovia et al., 2003; Deponte, 2008; Bouchard and Purdie, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>However, execution of PCD in non-metazoan organisms is morphologically different from apoptotic PCD in animals; it lacks a number of key molecular components of the apoptotic machinery and in some cases might be referred to as ‘apoptotic-like’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>With regard to phytoplankton, the nature of CL activities currently remains an unravelled question. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>There are no orthologue caspase genes reported to date in kingdoms other than that of metazoans, and metacaspases, which are distant homologues of caspases within the cysteine protease superfamily, found in fungi, vascular plants, and unicellular eukaryotes, were thought to perform similar functions to caspases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>However, their target substrates are quite distinct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>In the majority of cases, measurement of these activities in unicellular species has been carried out using the classical aspartate-containing caspase substrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Consequently, the activities measured are ‘CL’ activities and not metacaspases, as metacaspase activity has not yet been reported in phytoplankton (metacaspases are calcium-activated enzymes having target sites in P1 lysine or arginine; reviewed by Tsiatsiani et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="?"><plain>Therefore, the question is: which enzyme is responsible for the observed CL activity in phytoplankton (as well as in plants, fungi, etc.)? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Some authors have pointed to the serine protease family proteins to perform this hydrolysis in vascular plants (Bonneau et al., 2008) and/or the vacuolar processing enzyme (Hara-Nishimura and Hatsugai, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>It has also been reported that some CL activities are attributable to the plant subtilisin-like proteases—saspases and phytaspases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>These proteases hydrolyse a range of tetrapeptide caspase substrates following the aspartate residue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>Data obtained with saspases implicate them in the proteolytic degradation of Rubisco during biotic and abiotic PCD, whereas phytaspase-overproducing and silenced transgenics provide evidence that phytaspase regulates PCD during both abiotic (oxidative and osmotic stresses) and biotic (virus infection) insults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Like putative caspases, phytaspases and saspases are synthesized as pro-enzymes, which are processed autocatalytically to generate a mature enzyme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>However, unlike caspases, phytaspases and saspases appear to be constitutively processed and secreted from healthy plant cells into the intercellular space (Vartapetian et al., 2011), showing that there is specificity for aspartate residues and that traditional caspase inhibitors inhibit the above-mentioned proteinases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Even so, the discussion about whether metacaspases are caspases or not remains open (Carmona-Gutierrez et al., 2010; Enoksson and Salvesen, 2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>In any case, it is clear that further research is needed in phytoplankton and protists to unravel the nature of these proteases, which cleave after an aspartate residue in general. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>The fact is that they are present and show a ‘preference’ for this amino acid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>However, although it is known that CL activities are involved in cell death in these organisms, these enzymes are also essential during the normal physiology of the cells, involved in housekeeping functions, as well as during growth and cell stress acclimation (Segovia and Berges 2005, Bouchard and Purdie 2011; Franklin et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Our results demonstrated that DEVDase and WEHDase enzymatic activities (Fig. 7) were present and active, showing a broad range of activity depending on the treatment, even though the cells were not dead, and so they must be involved during the response to stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>The proteolytic activity may then possibly be related to a shift to the arrested state, which is a low metabolic state but retains low photosynthetic levels as indicated by Fv/Fm, in this case due to repair responses that are able to keep the cell alive, viable, and accumulating starch to be used when the stress ceases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>In this regard, a non-apoptotic-like role for CLs was proposed previously in phytoplankton. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>They were reported to be constitutive and to have housekeeping functions when D. tertiolecta cells were treated with several antibiotics that inhibited de novo protein synthesis (Segovia and Berges, 2005), and measurements of the enzymatic activities of ‘XXXDase’ demonstrated that they were active. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Thus, growing evidence suggests the participation of CLs in other cellular processes such as development, the cell cycle, and cell proliferation, in addition to their well-characterized role in cell death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>We have provided evidence that these CL proteases must be considered within a wider general meaning of stress proteins, rather than specifically being involved in cell death in phytoplankton. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s27"><title><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>UVR as a selection pressure factor for phytoplankton </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Phytoplankton is at the base of the trophic web and is an important component of biogeochemical cycles; thus, research on the ecophysiology of phytoplankton is of relevance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>On our planet, half of the organic carbon incorporation is due to phytoplankton (Raven, 2011) and evaluation of UVR effects on aquatic ecosystems is crucial to estimate carbon flux in the oceans and increase our understanding of global change (Sarmiento et al., 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>The stress caused by UV solar radiation depends on various factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>The first is that the radiation levels on the mixed layer must be high enough to produce CPDs and photoinhibition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>It is through these first few metres of the water column where UVR is able to penetrate, depending on the transparency of the water, hence causing damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>The second factor is the ability of cells to repair the damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Our data showed the capacity of D. tertiolecta to undergo DNA repair. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>This species can tolerate high doses of UVR for several days, despite damage caused to DNA and essential proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Similar data were obtained by Montero et al. (2002) in a study comparing the optimum quantum yield of seven species of microalgae from different phyla subjected to UVR treatments, in which D. salina was the most UV-tolerant among the Chlorophyta. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>The explanation for the high resilience of this species can be found in the sequence of temporal events taking place during UVR stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Biochemical responses precede any structural change or modification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>In this regard, we saw that the F v/F m value dropped off in matter of 2h as a result of photosynthetic uncoupling because of photoinhibition within the frame of ‘short-term responses’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Concurrently, the DNA was also modified by the formation of CPDs during the short-term response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>As a consequence of the UVR-induced biochemical changes, MAPKs were activated by dual phosphorylation, initiating downstream repair processes through PCNA and ROS1 accumulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>In this mid-term time frame, CL activities (which should be expected to help in dismantling the cell according to the traditional role in cell death usually attributed to these enzymes in a variety of organisms) were not related to cell death processes, indicating a role in overcoming/managing the stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>All the biochemical changes that happened during the short- and mid-term response induced structural modifications affecting the cell cycle and morphology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Our results suggest that the repair capacity of D. tertiolecta and the consequent tolerance to high UVR doses could provide a clear advantage over other phytoplankton species in the photic zone and possibly in the whole water column. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Moreover, although projections on the dynamics of the ozone holes indicate changes in distribution, geography, and size (Shanklin, 2010), the capability of D. tertiolecta to repair UV-induced damage to DNA and essential proteins would confer clear advantages to this species with regard to dominance and exclusions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>The high resilience to abiotic stress of some species such as small chlorophytes could be crucial for phytoplankton vertical community structure and biogeography within the actual global-change scenario. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>© 2011 The Authors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag>
<SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_63_14_5259__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_ers185_JXB_Lks2_Suppl_Yuo_final_12_7_16.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></SecTag>
</body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by research grants P08-03800 from the Regional Science Research Programme (Junta de Andalucía, Spain) and CTM/MAR 2010-17216 from the Ministry for Science and Innovation (MICCIN) Spain, to M.S., and CTM/ANT 2011-24007 to C.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>The authors are truly grateful to Teresa Roldán-Arjona (Córdoba University, Spain) for providing us with the AtROS1 antibodies, the recombinant proteins used as antigens and the pre-immune sera. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term>AMC</term><def><p>7-amino-4-methyl coumarin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BER</term><def><p>base excision repair</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CL</term><def><p>caspase-like</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CPD</term><def><p>cyclobutane–pyrimidine dimer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DML</term><def><p>DEMETER-LIKE</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ERK</term><def><p>extracellular signal-regulated kinase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>JNK</term><def><p>c-Jun N-terminal kinase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MAPK</term><def><p>mitogen activated protein kinase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NER</term><def><p>nucleotide excision repair</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PAR</term><def><p>PCNA, cell proliferation nuclear antigen</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PSII</term><def><p>photosystem II</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ROS1</term><def><p>repressor of transcriptional gene silencing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Rubisco</term><def><p>ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p>standard deviation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TEM</term><def><p>transmission electron microscopy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UVR</term><def><p>ultraviolet radiation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WEHD</term><def><p>acetyl-l-tryptophyl-l-glutamyl-l-histidyl-l-aspartic acid α-(4-methyl-coumaryl-7-amide)</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain> BagewadiBChenSLalSKRoy ChoudhuryNMukherjeeSK 2004 PCNA interacts with Indian mung bean yellow mosaic virus Rep and downregulates Rep activity Virology Journal 78 11890–11903  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain> BehrenfeldMJArdíJTLeeH 1992 Chronic effects of UVB on growth and cell volume of Phaeodactilum tricornutum (Bacillariophycea) Journal of Phycology 28 757–760  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain> Ben-AmotzAPolleJEWRaoDVS 2009 The Alga Dunaliella: Biodiversity, Physiology, Genomics, and Biotechnology Enfield, New Hampshire: Science Publishers  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain> BidleKDHaramatyLBarcelo eRamos JFalkowskiPG 2007 Viral activation and recruitment of metacaspases in the unicellular coccolithophore, Emiliania huxleyi  Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA 104 6049–6054  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain> BoelenPObernostererIVinkAABumaAGJ 1999 Attenuation of biologically affective UV radiation in tropical Atlantic waters, as measured with a biochemical DNA dosimeter Photochemistry and Photobiology 69 34–40  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain> BoelenPPostAFVeldhuisMJWBumaAGJ 2002 Diel patterns of UVBR-induced DNA damage in picoplankton size fractions from the Gulf of Aqaba, Red Sea Microbial Ecology 44 164–174 12060864 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain> BoelenPVeldhuisMJWBumaAGJ 2001 Accumulation and removal of UVBR-induced DNA damage in marine tropical plankton subjected to mixed and simulated non-mixed conditions Aquatic Microbial Ecology 24 265–274  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain> BonneauLGeYDruryGEGalloisP 2008 What happened to plant caspases? Journal of Experimental Botany 59 491–499 18272922 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain> BouchardJNCampellDARoyS 2005 Effects of UV-B radiation on the D1 protein repair cycle of natural phytoplankton communities from three latitudes (Canada, Brazil, and Argentina) Journal of Phycology 41 273–286  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain> BouchardJNPurdieDA 2011 Temporal variation of caspase 3-like protein activity in cultures of the harmful dinoflagellates Karenia brevis and Karenia mikimotoi  Journal of Plankton Research 33 961–972  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain> BrittAB 2004 Repair of DNA damage induced by solar UV Photosynthesis Research 81 105–112  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain> BumaAGJBoelenPJeffreyWA 2003 UVR-induced DNA damage in aquatic organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>In: HelblingEWZagareseH, eds. UV effects in aquatic organisms and ecosystemsComprehensive Series in Photochemical and Photobiological SciencesRoyal Society of Chemistry 291–327  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain> BumaAGJHelblingEWde BoerMKVillafañeVE 2001 Patterns of DNA damage and photoinhibition in temperate South-Atlantic picophytoplankton exposed to solar ultraviolet radiation Journal Photochemistry and Photobiology 62 9–18  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain> CapassoJMRivardCJBerlT 2001 The expression of the G subunit of Na, K-ATPase is regulated by osmolality and by C-terminal Jun kinase and PI3 kinase dependent mechanisms Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA 98 13414–13419  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain> Carmona-GutierrezDFröhlichKUKroemerGMadeoF 2010 Metacaspases are caspases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Doubt no more Cell Death and Differentiation 17 377–378 20154701 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain> CarpenterEJLinSChangJ 1998 Phytoplankton growth studies by cell cycle analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>In: CookseyKE, ed. Molecular approaches to the study of the ocean London: Chapman &amp; Hall 227–245  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain> Córdoba-CañeroDMorales-RuizTRoldán-ArjonaTArizaRR 2009 Single-nucleotide and long-patch base excision repair of DNA damage in plants The Plant Journal 60 716–728 19682284 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain> DarehshouriAAffenzellerMLutz-MeindlU 2008 Cell death upon H2O2 induction in the unicellular green alga Micrasterias  Plant Biology 10 732–745 18950431 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain> DeponteM 2008 Programmed cell death in protists Biochimica et Biophysica Acta Molecular Cell Research 1783 1396–1405  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain> EnokssonMSalvesenGS 2010 Metacaspases are not caspases – always doubt Cell Death and Differentiation 17 1221 20622886 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain> FortiniPDogliottiE 2007 Base damage and single-strand break repair: mechanisms and functional significance of short- and long-patch repair subpathways DNA Repair 6 398–409 17129767 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain> FranklinDJAirsRLFernandesMBellTGBongaertsRJBergesJAMalinG 2012 Identification of senescence and death in Emiliania huxleyi and Thalassiosira pseudonana: cell staining, chlorophyll alterations, and dimethylsulfoniopropionate (DMSP) metabolism Limnology and Oceanography 57 305–317  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain> García-OrtizM-VArizaRRRoldán-ArjonaT 2001 A chemiluminescent method for the detection of DNA glycosylase/lyase activity Analytical Biochemistry 298 127–129 11673906 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain> GentyBBriantaisJMBakerNR 1989 The relationship between the quantum yield of photosynthetic electron-transport and quenching of chlorophyll fluorescence Biochimica et Biophysica Acta 990 87–92  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain> GoldmanJCMcCarthyJJ 1978 Steady state growth and ammonium uptake of a fast growing marine diatom Limnology and Oceanography 23 695–703  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain> GongZMoralesRuizTArizaRRRoldánArjonaTDavidLZhuJK 2002 ROS1, a repressor of transcriptional gene silencing in Arabidopsis, encodes a DNA glycosylase/lyase Cell 111 803–814 12526807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain> GuillardRRLRytherJH 1962 Studies of marine planktonic diatoms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>I. Cyclotella nana Hustedt and Detonula confervacea (Cleve) Gran Canadian Journal of Microbiology 8 229–239 13902807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain> HäderDPKumarHDSmithRCWorrestRC 2007 Effects of solar UV radiation on aquatic ecosystems and interactions with climate change Photochemical &amp; Photobiological Sciences 6 267–285 17344962 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain> HaneltD 1998 Capability of dynamic photoinhibition in Artic macroalgae is related to their depth distribution Marine Biology 131 361–369  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain> Hara-NishimuraIHatsugaiN 2011 The role of vacuole in plant cell death Cell Death and Differentiation 18 1298–1304 21637288 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain> HasanSHassaPOImhofRHottigerMO 2001 Transcription coactivator p300 binds PCNA and may have a role in DNA repair synthesis Nature 410 387–391 11268218 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain> HelblingEWBumaAGJBoerMKVillafañeVE 2001 In situ impact of solar ultraviolet radiation on photosynthesis and DNA in temperate marine phytoplankton Marine Ecology Progress Series 211 43–49  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain> JeffreyWHMitchellDL 1997 Mechanisms of UV-induced DNA damage and response in marine microorganisms Photochemistry and Photobiology 65 260–263  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain> JiménezCBerlTRivardCJEdelsteinCLCapassoJM 2004 Phosphorylation of MAP kinase-like proteins mediate the response of the halotolerant alga Dunaliella viridis to hypertonic shock Biochimica et Biophysica Acta 1644 61–69 14741745 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain> JiménezCCapassoJMEdelsteinCLRivardCJLuciaSBreusegemSBerlTSegoviaM 2009 Different ways to die: cell death modes of the unicellular chlorophyte Dunaliella viridis exposed to various environmental stresses are mediated by the caspase-like activity DEVDase Journal of Experimental Botany 60 815–828 19251986 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain> JiménezCCossíoBRRivardCJBerlTEdelsteinCLCapassoJM 2007 Cell division in the unicellular microalga Dunaliella viridis depends on phosphorylation of extracellular signal-regulated kinases (ERKs) Journal of Experimental Botany 58 1001–1011 17220513 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain> JordanBR 1996 The effects of ultraviolet-B radiation on plants: a molecular perspective Advances in Botanical Research 22 97–162  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain> KrokanHEStandalRSlupphaugG 1997 DNA glycosylases in the base excision repair of DNA Biochemistry Journal 325 1–16  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain> KyriakisJMAvruchJ 2001 Mammalian mitogen-activated protein kinase signal transduction pathways activated by stress and inflammation Physiology Review 81 807–869  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain> LesserMP 2006 Oxidative stress in marine environments: biochemistry and physiological ecology Annual Review of Physiology 68 253–278  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain> LinSChangJCarpenterEJ 1995 Growth characteristic of phytoplankton determined by cell cycle proteins: PCNA immunostaining of Dunaliella tertiolecta  Journal of Phycology 31 388–395  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain> LlabrésMAgustíS 2006 Picophytoplankton cell death induced by UV radiation: evidence for oceanic Atlantic communities Limnology and Oceanography 51 21–29  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain> LlabrésMAgustíS 2010 Effects of ultraviolet radiation on growth, cell death and the standing stock of Antarctic phytoplankton Aquatic Microbial Ecology 59 151–160  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain> LoHLNakajimaSMaLWalterBYasuiBEthellDWOwenLB 2005 Differential biologic effects of CPD and 6-4PP UV-induced DNA damage on the induction of apoptosis and cell-cycle arrest BMC Cancer 5 135 16236176 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain> MasiAMelisA 1997 Morphological and molecular changes in the unicellular green algae Dunaliella salina grown under supplemental UVB radiation: cell characteristic and photosystem II damages and repair properties Biochimica et Biophysica Acta 1321 183–193  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain> MasihPJKunnevDMelendyT 2008 Mismatch repair proteins are recruited to replicating DNA through interaction with proliferating cell nuclear antigen (PCNA) Nucleic Acids Research 36 67 17984070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain> MeadorJABaldwinAJCatalaPJeffreyWHJouxFMossJAPakulskiJDStevensRMitchellDL 2009 Sunlight-induced DNA damage in marine micro-organisms collected along a latitudinal gradient from 70°N to 68°S Photochemistry and Photobiology 85 412–420 19161407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain> MelisANemsonJAHarrisonMA 1992 Damage to functional components and partial degradation of photosystem-II reaction center proteins upon chloroplast exposure to ultraviolet-B radiation Biochimica et Biophysica Acta 1100 312–320  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain> MoharikarSD’SouzaJSKulkarniABRaoBJ 2006 Apoptotic-like cell death pathway is induced in unicellular chlorophyte Chlamydomonas reinhardtii (Chlorophyceae) cells following UV irradiation: detection and functional analyses Journal of Phycology 42 423–433  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain> MonteroOKlischMHäderDPLubianLM 2002 Comparative sensitivity of seven marine microalgae to cumulative exposure to UVB radiation with daily increasing doses Botanica Marina 45 305–315  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain> Morales-RuizTOrtega-GalisteoAPPonferrada-MarínMIMartínez-MacíasMIArizaRRRoldán-ArjonaT 2006 DEMETER and REPRESSOR OF SILENCING 1 encode 5-methylcytosine DNA glycosylases Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA 103 6853–6858  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain> MuñozFJZorzanoMTMAlonso-CasajúsNBaroja-FernándezEEtxeberriaEPozueta-RomeroJ 2006 New enzymes, new pathways and an alternative view on starch biosynthesis in both photosynthetic and heterotrophic tissues of plants Biocatalysis and Biotransformation 24 63–76  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain> NakagamiHPitzschkeAHirtH 2005 Emerging MAP kinase pathways in plant stress signalling Trends in Plant Science 10 339–346 15953753 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain> NealePJCullenJJLesserMPMelisAYamamotoHSmithCM 1993 Physiological bases for detecting and predicting photoinhibition of aquatic photosynthesis by PAR and UV radiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>In: YamamotoHYSmithCM (eds) Photosynthetic Responses to the Environment Symposium24–27 August 1992Hawaii Institute of Tropical Agriculture and Human Resources, University of Hawaii American Society of Plant Physiology 61–77  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain> NedelcuAMDriscollWWDurandPMHerronMDRashidiA 2011 On the paradigm of altruistic suicide in the unicellular world Evolution 65 3–20 20722725 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0056"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain> NicholsAFSancarA 1992 Purification of PCNA as a nucleotide excision repair protein Nucleic Acids Research 20 2441–2446 1352873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0057"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain> Ortega-GalisteoAPMorales-RuizTArizaRRRoldán-ArjonaT 2008  Arabidopsis DEMETER-LIKE proteins DML2 and DML3 are required for appropriate distribution of DNA methylation marks Plant Molecular Biology 67 671–681 18493721 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0058"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain> ParagesMLCapassoJMMecoVJiménezC 2012 A novel method for phosphoprotein extraction from macroalgae Botanica Marina 55, doi 10.1515/bot-2011-0051 (in press). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0059"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain> Pérez-MartínJM 2008 Programed cell death in protozoa Austin, TX: Landes Bioscience  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0060"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain> Ponferrada-MarínMIMartínez-MacíasMIMorales-RuizTRoldán-ArjonaTArizaRR 2010 Methylation-independent DNA binding modulates specificity of repressor of silencing 1 (ROS1) and facilitates demethylation in long substrates Journal of Biological Chemistry 285 23032–23039 20489198 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0061"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain> RavenJA 2011 The cost of photoinhibition Physiologia Plantarum 142 87–104 21382037 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0062"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain> Roldán-ArjonaTArizaRR 2009 Repair and tolerance of oxidative DNA damage in plants Mutation Research 681 169–179 18707020 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0063"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain> Roldán-ArjonaTGarcía-OrtizM-VRuiz-RubioMArizaRR 2000 cDNA cloning, expression and functional characterization of an Arabidopsis thaliana homologue of the Escherichia coli DNA repair enzyme endonuclease III Plant Molecular Biology 44 43–52 11094978 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0064"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain> RossCRPaulVJ 2006 Signal transduction in the cyanobacteria Lyngbya confervoides and L. polychroa: ecological implications of reactive oxygen species Integrative and Comparative Biology 46 E121  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0065"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain> SarmientoJLSlaterRBarberR 2004 Response of ocean ecosystems to climate warming Global Biogeochemical Cycles 18 GB3003  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0066"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain> ScharerODJiricnyJ 2001 Recent progress in the biology, chemistry and structural biology of DNA glycosylases Bioessays 23 270–281 11223884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0067"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain> SchreiberUSchilwaUBilgerW 1986 Continuous recording of photochemical and non-photochemical chlorophyll fluorescence quenching with a new type of modulation fluorometer Photosynthesis Research 10 51–62  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0068"><text><SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain> ScottMBonnefinPVieyraDBoisvertFMYoungDBazett-JonesDPRiabowolK 2001 UV-induced binding of ING1 to PCNA regulates the induction of apoptosis Journal Cell Science 114 3455–3462  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0069"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain> SegoviaMBergesJA 2005 Effect of inhibitors of protein synthesis and DNA replication on the induction of proteolytic activities, caspase-like activities and cell death in the unicellular chlorophyte Dunaliella tertiolecta  European Journal of Phycology 40 21–30  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0070"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain> SegoviaMBergesJA 2009 Inhibition of caspase-like activities prevents the appearance of reactive oxygen species and dark-induced apoptosis in the unicellular chlorophyte Dunaliella tertiolecta  Journal of Phycology 40 21–30  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0071"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain> SegoviaMHaramatyLBergesJAFalkowskiPG 2003 Cell death in the unicellular chlorophyte Dunaliella tertiolecta: a hypothesis on the evolution of apoptosis in higher plants and metazoans Plant Physiology 132 99–105 12746516 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0072"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain> ShanklinJ 2010 Reflections on the ozone hole Nature 465 34–35 20445611 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0073"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain> StaxenIBergouniouxCBormanJF 1993 Effects of UV on cell division and microtubule organisation in Petunia hybrida protoplasts Protoplasma 173 70–76  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0074"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain> TimmermansKRVeldhuisMJWBrussaardCPD 2007 Cell death in three marine diatom species in response to different irradiance levels, silicate, or iron concentrations Aquatic Microbial Ecology 46 253–261  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0075"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain> TsiatsianiLVan BreusegemFGalloisPZavialovALamEBozhkovPV 2011 Metacaspases Cell Death and Differentiation 18 1279–1288 21597462 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0076"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain> UmarABuermeyerABSimonJAThomasDCClarkABLiskayRMKunkelTA 1996 Requirement for PCNA in DNA mismatch repair at a step preceding DNA resynthesis Cell 87 65–73 8858149 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0077"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain> Van de PollWHHaneltDHoyerKBumaAGJBreemanAM 2002 Ultraviolet-B-induced cyclobutane–pyrimidine dimer formation and repair in arctic marine macrophytes Photochemistry and Photobiology 76 493–500 12462643 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0078"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain> VardiABerman-FrankIRozenbergTHadasOKaplanALevineA 1999 Programmed cell death of the dinoflagellate Peridinium gatunense is mediated by CO2 limitation and oxidative stress Current Biology 9 1061–1064 10508616 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0079"><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain> VartapetianABTuzhikovAIChichkovaNVTalianskyMWolpertTJ 2011 A plant alternative to animal caspases: subtilisin-like proteases Cell Death and Differentiation 18 1289–1297 21546909 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0080"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain> VeldhuisMJWKraayGWTimmermansKR 2001 Cell death in phytoplankton: correlation between changes in membrane permeability, photosynthetic activity, pigmentation and growth European Journal of Phycology 36 167–177  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0081"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain> WatanabeHPanZQSchreiber-AgusNDePinhoRAHurwitzJXiongY 1998 Suppression of cell transformation by the cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor p57KIP2 requires binding to proliferating cell nuclear antigen Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA 95 1392–1397  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0082"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain> YiYCaoYQianLMinLLongCLindanBZhirongYDairongQ 2006 Cloning and sequence analysis of the gene encoding (6-4) photolyase from Dunaliella salina  Biotechnology Letters 28 309–314 16614917 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0083"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain> YoonJHLeeCSO’ConnorTRYasuiAPfeiferGP 2000 The DNA damage spectrum produced by simulated sunlight Journal of Molecular Biology 299 681–693 10835277 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0084"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain> ZarembaTGLeBonTRMillarDBSmejkalRMHawleyRJ 1984 Effects of UV on the in vitro assembly of microtubules Biochemistry 23 1073–1080 6712937 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0085"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain> ZhangTLiuYYangTZhangLXuSXueLAnL 2006 Diverse signals converge at MAPK cascades in plant Plant Physiology Biochemistry 44 274–283  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0086"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain> ZhuJK 2009 Active DNA demethylation mediated by DNA glycosylases Annual Review of Genetics 43 143–166  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0087"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain> ZuppiniAGerottoCBaldanB 2010 Programmed celldeath and adaptation: two different types of abiotic stressresponse in a unicellular chlorophyte Plant and CellPhysiology 51 884–895  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
