<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><?epub January-15-2013?><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3597645</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23325852</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks1336</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gks1336</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Gene Regulation, Chromatin and Epigenetics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Transcription profiling during the cell cycle shows that a subset of Polycomb-targeted genes is upregulated during DNA replication</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pe&#241;a-Diaz</surname><given-names>Javier</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gks1336-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hegre</surname><given-names>Siv A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gks1336-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gks1336-AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Anderssen</surname><given-names>Endre</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gks1336-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aas</surname><given-names>Per A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gks1336-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mjelle</surname><given-names>Robin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gks1336-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gilfillan</surname><given-names>Gregor D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gks1336-AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lyle</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gks1336-AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Drabl&#248;s</surname><given-names>Finn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gks1336-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Krokan</surname><given-names>Hans E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gks1336-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>S&#230;trom</surname><given-names>P&#229;l</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gks1336-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gks1336-AFF1"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="gks1336-COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="gks1336-AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Cancer Research and Molecular Medicine, Norwegian University of Science and Technology, NO-7491 Trondheim, Norway, <sup>2</sup>St. Olavs Hospital, NO-7006 Trondheim, Norway, <sup>3</sup>Department of Medical Genetics and Norwegian Sequencing Centre, Oslo University Hospital, NO-0407 Oslo, Norway and <sup>4</sup>Department of Computer and Information Science, Norwegian University of Science and Technology, NO-7491 Trondheim, Norway</aff><author-notes><corresp id="gks1336-COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: <phone>+47 735 94 796</phone>; Fax: <fax>+47 735 94 466</fax>; Email: <email>pal.satrom@ntnu.no</email></corresp><fn id="gks1336-FN1"><p>Present address: Javier Pe&#241;a-Diaz, Institute of Molecular Cancer Research (IMCR), University of Zurich, 8057 Zurich, Switzerland.</p></fn><fn id="gks1336-FN2"><p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first three authors should be regarded as joint First Authors.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>41</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2846</fpage><lpage>2856</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2013. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Genome-wide gene expression analyses of the human somatic cell cycle have indicated that the set of cycling genes differ between primary and cancer cells. By identifying genes that have cell cycle dependent expression in HaCaT human keratinocytes and comparing these with previously identified cell cycle genes, we have identified three distinct groups of cell cycle genes. First, housekeeping genes enriched for known cell cycle functions; second, cell type-specific genes enriched for HaCaT-specific functions; and third, Polycomb-regulated genes. These Polycomb-regulated genes are specifically upregulated during DNA replication, and consistent with being epigenetically silenced in other cell cycle phases, these genes have lower expression than other cell cycle genes. We also find similar patterns in foreskin fibroblasts, indicating that replication-dependent expression of Polycomb-silenced genes is a prevalent but unrecognized regulatory mechanism.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Genome-wide studies of gene expression throughout the cell division cycle have revealed several genes that are differentially expressed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B1 gks1336-B2 gks1336-B3 gks1336-B4 gks1336-B5 gks1336-B6 gks1336-B7 gks1336-B8 gks1336-B9">1&#8211;9</xref>), but have also indicated that the set of cycling genes differs between primary and cancer cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B3">3</xref>). Primary cells are, however, inherently difficult to synchronize, for example, only 40&#8211;50% of foreskin fibroblast cells in culture can be synchronized by serum starvation or double thymidine block (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B3">3</xref>). Although sophisticated statistics may partially overcome lack of synchronization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B3">3</xref>), a large population of asynchronous or arrested cells results in high background gene expression noise. Consequently, more cycling genes can be detected in a highly synchronous culture than in a culture where at most 50% of the cells are synchronized. Moreover, as the only human cell line&#8212;in addition to primary fibroblasts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B4">4</xref>)&#8212;profiled for cell cycle expression so far is the cervical cancer cell line HeLa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B5">5</xref>), it is unclear to what extent cell type-specific factors affect reported differences in cycling genes.</p><p>We have used the human keratinocyte cell line HaCaT to address this question. Specifically, by measuring the gene expression profiles of double thymidine synchronized HaCaT cells, we identified three major groups of cycling genes. First, a set of genes with housekeeping characteristics, strong enrichment for known cell cycle functions and overlap with previously identified cell cycle genes. Second, a set of genes with cell type-specific characteristics, enrichment for HaCaT-specific functions and poor overlap with previously identified cell cycle genes. Third, a set of genes that has the mark for Polycomb silencing: histone H3 lysine 27 tri-methylation (H3K27me3). We show that this third set of genes is expressed in a replication-dependent manner, as the genes are upregulated during S phase in a pattern related to DNA replication timing. Consistent with being epigenetically silenced in other cell cycle phases, these genes are generally lower expressed than are other cell cycle expressed genes. We also find similar patterns in foreskin fibroblasts synchronized by serum starvation, indicating that replication-dependent expression of Polycomb-silenced genes is a prevalent but unrecognized regulatory mechanism.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>HaCaT cell culture and synchronization</title><p>HaCaT cells were plated at 10% confluence (1 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup> cells) in 150-mm tissue culture dishes in Dulbecco&#8217;s modified Eagle&#8217;s medium (DMEM) with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS). Cells were arrested in the interphase G<sub>1</sub>/S by double thymidine block; briefly, cells were treated with 2 mM of thymidine for 18 h, released from the arrest for 10 h and arrested a second time with 2 mM of thymidine for additional 18 h. After treatment, media was replaced, and cells were collected at 3-h intervals for up to 33 h, covering approximately two cell cycles. Synchrony was monitored by flow cytometry analysis of propidium iodide-stained cells and by cell counting. Quantification of cells in each phase was done with the MultiCycle DNA cell cycle analysis software (Phoenix Flow Systems Inc., San Diego, CA, USA) combined with the cell counting results.</p></sec><sec><title>HeLa cell culture and synchronization</title><p>Adherent HeLa cells were plated in 150-mm culture dishes in DMEM with 10% of FBS, 2 mM of glutamine, 0.1 mg/ml of gentamicin and 1.25 &#181;g/ml of fungizone. Cells at 60&#8211;70% confluence were arrested in the G<sub>2</sub>/M transition with 100 ng/ml of nocodazole for 17 h. The mitotic cells were then collected by manual shake-off, washed twice and re-plated in fresh DMEM to progress through the cell cycle. Cells were harvested from culture dishes by trypsinization every 30 min for the first 2 h and then every 3 h from 3 to 24 h after release. Phosphate-buffered saline containing 3% of FBS was added to inactivate the trypsin.</p><p>HeLa cells were pelleted and resuspended in 100 &#181;l of RNAlater (Applied Biosystems/Ambion, Austin, TX, USA). All pellets were kept at 4&#176;C overnight and were stored at &#8722;80&#176;C before use. Verification of the cell cycle stage was determined by analysing the DNA content of propidium iodide-stained cells by a BD FACSAria (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA) flow cytometer. Quantification of cells in each phase was done with FlowJo (Tree Star Inc., OR, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>cRNA synthesis and microarray hybridization&#8212;HaCaT</title><p>Total RNA was extracted using the High Pure RNA Isolation Kit (Roche Applied Science, Indianapolis, IN, USA) and the manufacturer&#8217;s protocol. RNA from synchronous cells was reverse transcribed into cDNA (cDNA synthesis Kit, Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA), which was used as a template for the RNA polymerase Enzo (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA, USA) to synthesize dUTP&#8211;dCTP biotinylated cRNA. The labelled cRNA was hybridized to Affymetrix oligonucleotide arrays (HG-U133 Set) under conditions specified by the manufacturer.</p></sec><sec><title>Microarray analyses&#8212;HeLa</title><p>Total RNA was prepared using the <italic>mir</italic>Vana miRNA Isolation Kit (Ambion) according to the manufacturer&#8217;s protocol. The integrity and stability of RNA samples were assessed by Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA). We used the Illumina TotalPrep RNA amplification Kit (Ambion) to amplify RNA for hybridization on Illumina BeadChips. Total RNA from each sample was used to synthesize first strand cDNA by reverse transcription. After the second strand cDNA synthesis and cDNA purification steps, the <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription to synthesize cRNA was prepared overnight for 12 h. The gene expression profiles were measured using Illumina HumanHT-12 v3 Expression BeadChip (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Identification of periodically expressed genes&#8212;statistical analysis</title><p>Normalization across arrays was performed by robust multi-array average (RMA) from the Bioconductor package affy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B10">10</xref>). As there are no probes specific for splice variants in the arrays used, for probes that hybridized with mRNAs corresponding to the same gene, only the probe having the highest variation was used for further analyses. The normalized data were then used to identify genes that showed cyclic behaviour. Genes that matched a cell cycle profile were identified using partial least squares (PLS) regression. Specifically, the gene expression matrix was regressed on to a sine and cosine function with periods equal to the estimated duration of the cell cycle. False discovery rates were computed using a modified Hotelling&#8217;s T-square statistic and resampling. Resampling (<italic>n</italic> = 1000) was done by assigning phase angles randomly to the time-steps, thus preserving the correlation within replicates of the same time-steps.</p></sec><sec><title>Assigning cell cycle phases</title><p>Assignment of cell cycle phases used the following protocol. First, each gene in the PLS model was assigned a phase angle by computing the arctangent of the gene&#8217;s first and second principle component. Second, we used a list of genes previously published to be predominantly expressed in G<sub>1</sub>/S, S, G<sub>2</sub>, G<sub>2</sub>/M and M/G<sub>1</sub> phase [(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B2">2</xref>): Table 2 and the four M/G<sub>1</sub> associated genes from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F2">Figure 2</xref>] and identified which of these genes were significant (<italic>q</italic> &lt; 0.05) in our PLS model (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Figure S3A</ext-link>). Third, for each set of significant G<sub>1</sub>/S, S, G<sub>2</sub>, G<sub>2</sub>/M and M/G<sub>1</sub> phase genes, we computed the set&#8217;s average phase angle and the corresponding standard deviation and used these values as parameters in a normal distribution to construct a phase angle probability density function for each of the five cell cycle phases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Figure S3</ext-link>A). Fourth, we used these probability density functions to assign the most probable phase IDs to each of the significant (<italic>q</italic> &lt; 0.05) genes in the PLS model. Fifth, if necessary, the standard deviation parameters in the phase angle probability density functions were increased to ensure that the phase assignments had the same order as the average phase angles for the five groups. Specifically, if any out of order phase assignments were detected, the lowest of the five standard deviations was increased by 25%, and the phase assignments were redone. This process was repeated until all phase assignments were in the order defined by the averages.</p></sec><sec><title>Promoter CpG analyses</title><p>Gene annotations were downloaded from the refGene table in the University of California, Santa Cruz (UCSC) Genome Browser database (human genome assembly version hg18) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B11">11</xref>). Promoter regions were defined as the 1000 nt upstream of annotated transcription start sites. Overlapping regions corresponding to genes with multiple transcripts having identical or alternative start sites were merged into one region to create a non-redundant set of promoter regions. Based on this non-redundant set, CpG ratios and CpG promoter classes were calculated and assigned as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B12">12</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Promoter histone analyses</title><p>Processed peak data from chromatin immunoprecipitation sequencing (ChIP-seq) experiments of H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 in seven cell lines (GM12878, HUVEC, K562, NHEK, H1-hESC, HMEC and NHLF) were downloaded from UCSC (hg18) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B14">14</xref>). Non-redundant promoter regions that contained overlapping H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 peaks in all seven cell lines were classified as H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 enriched, respectively; promoter regions that contained both marks in all seven cell lines were classified as bivalent; and promoter regions that did not contain any of the marks or only contained the marks in some of the cell lines were classified as having no or inconsistent marks.</p><p>Processed peak data from ChIP-seq experiments of H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 in HeLa and normal adult dermal fibroblasts (NHDF-Ad) were downloaded from UCSC (hg19; Broad Histone track) and remapped to hg18 by the UCSC liftOver tool.</p></sec><sec><title>HaCaT ChIP-seq</title><p>ChIP, library preparation and sequencing were done as described in the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Methods</ext-link>. The resulting input chromatin and H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 IP libraries contained &#8764;64 million (M), &#8764;42 M and &#8764;52 M sequence reads, respectively. We used cutadapt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B15">15</xref>) to trim adapter sequences, bowtie (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B16">16</xref>) to align sequence reads from the human genome (version hg18) and discarded all reads that aligned to more than one genomic location. The &#8764;50 M, &#8764;32 M and &#8764;39 M aligned reads for the input, H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 libraries, respectively, were processed by SICER (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B17">17</xref>) to identify genomic regions that were significantly enriched for H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 in HaCaT (SICER used the input chromatin library as control to identify significant regions; see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Dataset S3</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">S4</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec><title>Gene ontology and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes analyses</title><p>Gene ontology (GO) term and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) pathway enrichment was assessed by GOstats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B18">18</xref>). For GO terms, the test was conditioned on the structure of the GO graph.</p></sec><sec><title>Data access</title><p>The microarray data from this publication have been submitted to the ArrayExpress database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress/</ext-link>) and were assigned the identifiers E-MTAB-454 (HaCaT) and E-TABM-1152 (HeLa). HaCaT ChIP-seq data are available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tang.medisin.ntnu.no/~palsat/HaCaT-ChIP.tgz">http://tang.medisin.ntnu.no/&#8764;palsat/HaCaT-ChIP.tgz</ext-link>; bed-files with significant H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 regions are available as <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Dataset S3</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">S4</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Partial least squares regression identifies cell cycle-regulated transcripts</title><p>To overcome the problem of low synchronization of primary cells and to investigate potential cell type-related differences in cycling genes, we turned to the human keratinocyte cell line HaCaT&#8212;a non-tumorigenic, spontaneously immortalized cell line that exhibits apparently normal differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B19">19</xref>). Using a double thymidine block to arrest and, subsequently, release HaCaT cells at the G<sub>1</sub>/S boundary resulted in &#8764;90% of the cells re-entering the cell cycle and continuing as a uniform cohort through the cell cycle (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Figure S1</ext-link>). Based on the DNA content profile, we estimated the cell cycle duration to be &#8764;20 h. Although the cells gradually lost synchrony, such that 70% instead of 90% of the cells were synchronously entering the second S phase, the results were reproducible across three independent experiments. We, therefore, considered synchronized HaCaT cells a good starting point for gene expression analyses.</p><p>We were primarily interested in genes that showed consistent cyclic expression with a period equal to the estimated cell cycle duration of 20 h. We, therefore, used PLS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B20">20</xref>) to identify genes that followed a sine or cosine pattern with a period of 20 h. Conceptually, this PLS analysis projects the time profile for all genes onto a plane described by the sine and cosine of the cell cycle. As a result, genes that are periodically expressed with high amplitude will be far from the origin, whereas genes that vary little or randomly will be close to the origin. Moreover, the phase angle of the cyclic variation will determine the direction from the origin such that genes that have the same temporal expression patterns will lie in the same direction from the origin on the plane.</p><p>By profiling RNA isolated from the synchronized cells at 3 h intervals for 33 h, and combining PLS analyses with resampling to compute false discovery rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B21">21</xref>), we identified 1249 Entrez genes that had significant periodic expression patterns during the HaCaT cell cycle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F1">Figure 1</xref>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Dataset S1</ext-link>). The synchronization experiments&#8217; trajectory through the PLS cell cycle plane confirmed that the three replicates gave similar and reproducible results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F1">Figure 1</xref>B). The trajectory also indicated the cells&#8217; gradual loss of synchrony, as the samples were gradually approaching the origin&#8212;especially at later time points.
<fig id="gks1336-F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>PLS regression identifies cyclic gene expression patterns. The loadings (<bold>A</bold>) and scores (<bold>B</bold>) plots show the contribution of each gene (loadings) to the location of each sample in the subspace of the PLS model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B20">20</xref>) (scores; here, sine and cosine, period of 20 h). (A) Points show significant genes [<italic>q</italic> &lt; 0.05; permutation test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B21">21</xref>)] and their contribution to the PLS cell cycle model&#8217;s first and second components (PC1 and PC2). Colours show the cell cycle phase where the gene is predominantly expressed (see &#8216;Materials and Methods&#8217; section). The circle and cell diagrams indicate early and late DNA replication, G<sub>2</sub>, mitosis and G<sub>1</sub> as determined by the scores plot (B) and flow cytometry (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Figure 1</ext-link>). (B) Points show the location of the samples from the three replicates (point, circle and cross) within the PLS model&#8217;s first and second components; the line shows the replicates&#8217; average trajectory; numbers show the sample time (h). (<bold>C&#8211;F</bold>) Expression profiles for selected genes from the loadings plot [labelled triangles in (A)]. (C) Cyclin E2 (<italic>CCNE2</italic>); (D) Cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor 2C (<italic>CDKN2C</italic>); (E) Cyclin A2 (<italic>CCNA2</italic>); and (F) Cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor 3 (<italic>CDKN3</italic>). (<bold>G</bold>) Heatmap showing the expression changes of the cell cycle genes relative to their median expression. The profiles are ordered according the genes&#8217; phase angle in the PLS model in (A). Margin colours show the genes&#8217; assigned cell cycle phase.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gks1336f1p"/></fig></p><p>To further analyse the cell cycle genes, we used existing annotations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B2">2</xref>) to subdivide the genes into five main groups that represented phases G<sub>1</sub>/S, S, G<sub>2</sub>, G<sub>2</sub>/M and M/G<sub>1</sub> of the cell cycle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F1">Figure 1</xref>; see &#8216;Materials and Methods&#8217; section). The assigned phases showed good correspondence with previously published phases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>); the genes missing from our list had expression patterns that were either inconsistent between replicates, not cyclic, or consistently expressed in the first cell cycle only (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Figures S2&#8211;S4</ext-link>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Discussion S1</ext-link>). We, therefore, concluded that our PLS model could robustly identify genes that showed consistent and reproducible cyclic expression patterns within the synchronized HaCaT cells.</p></sec><sec><title>HaCaT cell cycle genes include both generally active housekeeping and keratinocyte-specific genes</title><p>Having established a set of genes with cell cycle-dependent expression, we set out to characterize these genes further. As cell cycle control is a central housekeeping function, we expected our set of genes to be enriched for high-CpG (HCG) promoters&#8212;a hallmark of developmentally regulated genes and housekeeping genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B22">22</xref>). We also expected the cell cycle genes to be enriched for histone H3 lysine 4 tri-methylation (H3K4me3) within their promoters, as this epigenetic mark is associated with actively transcribed genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B24">24</xref>). Indeed, although the complete set of genes followed a bimodal distribution of HCG and low-CpG (LCG) promoters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B22">22</xref>), the distribution for the cell cycle genes was shifted, such that a larger percentage had HCG promoters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F2">Figure 2</xref>A and B; <italic>P</italic> = 2e-11, binomial test). Similarly, ChIP-seq of H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 marks in the HaCaT cells (see &#8216;Materials Methods&#8217; section; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Dataset S2</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">S3</ext-link>) showed that the cell cycle genes described here were enriched for H3K4me3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F2">Figure 2</xref>C). Moreover, the genes were also enriched for H3K4me3 marks that were present in and common for all of seven other cell lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B14">14</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F2">Figure 2</xref>D), which is consistent with these genes having housekeeping functions common to many cell types.</p><p>The cell cycle genes that showed inconsistent or no histone modifications within their promoters were highly enriched among LCG genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F2">Figure 2</xref>E and F). Tissue-specific genes are commonly enriched among LCGs, which suggested that this subset of cell cycle expressed genes that have LCG promoters with no or inconsistent H3K4me3 modifications might be cell type-specific for HaCaT. To test this possibility, we first investigated whether all the human LCG genes without consistent H3K4me3 within the seven cell lines (LCG/NoH3K4me3) were enriched within GO categories or KEGG pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B18">18</xref>). As expected, the set of all LCG/NoH3K4me3 genes was highly enriched for tissue specific functions, whereas the set of all HCG/H3K4me3 genes was enriched for housekeeping categories and pathways (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Figure S5</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Dataset S4</ext-link>). Second, by accounting for such background enrichment within the nine subgroups, we found both the HCG/H3K4me3 cell cycle genes and the intermediate CpG (ICG)/H3K4me3 cell cycle genes to be specifically enriched for cell cycle-related terms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F2">Figure 2</xref>G). Moreover, the LCG/NoH3K4me3 cell cycle genes were specifically enriched for the KEGG cytokine&#8211;cytokine receptor interaction pathway, which is consistent with cytokines being important regulators of wound healing in general and keratinocyte proliferation in particular (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B25">25</xref>). Thus, at least some of the cell cycle genes seem to be cell type-specific for HaCaT cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Distinct cell types have exclusive cell cycle regulated genes related to the cells&#8217; specific characteristics and functions</title><p>To further determine whether cell type-specific factors could explain differences in reported cycling genes, we analysed the overlap among the cell cycle-regulated genes identified in our and previous human studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F3">Figure 3</xref>). Although our study identified more cell cycle genes than did the foreskin fibroblast (FF) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B3">3</xref>) and HeLa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B2">2</xref>) studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F3">Figure 3</xref>A), the cell cycle genes we identified had clear cycling patterns in HaCaT. In contrast, the genes identified in the two previous studies but missed in our study had weak or inconsistent patterns in HaCaT; compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F3">Figure 3</xref>B and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F3">3</xref>C.
<fig id="gks1336-F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>HaCaT cell cycle genes include both generally active housekeeping and keratinocyte-specific genes. (<bold>A</bold>) Distributions of CpG content in promoters for all genes included in the PLS model (all, dashed line) and cell cycle expressed genes (CC, solid line). The lines are the kernel density estimates of the two CpG content distributions. (<bold>B</bold>) Fraction of LCG (black), ICG (grey) and HCG (white) promoters for the two groups in (A). Numbers above bars are the total number of non-redundant promoter regions. (<bold>C and D</bold>) Fraction of promoters that in HaCaT (C) or in seven different cell lines (D) contain exclusive H3K4me3 or H3K27me3 marks (K4, white; K27, dark grey), bivalent K4 and K27 marks (K4/K27, light grey), or no or inconsistent marks (None, diamonds). <italic>P</italic>-values are the results of binomial tests comparing the fraction of H3K4me3-marked genes in the two sets. (<bold>E and F</bold>) Fractions from (C: E) and (D: F) subdivided into LCG, ICG and HCG (black, dark grey and light grey lines) promoters. (<bold>G</bold>) GO biological process (BP) terms or KEGG pathways significantly enriched (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) among HCG, ICG or LCG cell cycle genes subdivided into promoters with consistent H3K4me3 (white) or H3K27me3 (no significant terms) marks, or no or inconsistent marks (diamonds). Horizontal axes show Benjamini&#8211;Hochberg corrected <italic>P</italic>-values (&#8211;log<sub>10</sub>); numbers on the right show the expected (E) and observed (O) number of genes and the corresponding odds ratios (OR).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gks1336f2p"/></fig>
<fig id="gks1336-F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Cell cycle genes that are common or exclusive for foreskin fibroblasts (FF) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B3">3</xref>), HeLa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B2">2</xref>) and HaCaT reveal characteristics that are specific for the three cell types. (<bold>A</bold>) Venn diagram showing the overlap in cell cycle genes between FF (BJ), HeLa (W) and HaCaT (33 h). (<bold>B</bold>) Heatmap showing the expression changes of the HaCaT cell cycle genes relative to their median expression. The genes are grouped according to their overlap with the cell cycle genes from the FF and HeLa studies and are ordered according the genes&#8217; phase angle (from &#8722;&#960; to &#960;) in the HaCaT 33 h PLS model. Margin colours show the genes&#8217; assigned cell cycle phase (red, G<sub>1</sub>/S; turquoise, S; green, G<sub>2</sub>; blue, G<sub>2</sub>/M; and pink, M/G<sub>1</sub>). (<bold>C</bold>) Heatmap showing the expression changes in HaCaT for genes identified as cell cycle regulated in FF or HeLa but not in HaCaT. The genes are grouped according to their overlap between the two studies and are ordered according to the genes&#8217; phase angle in the HaCaT 33 h PLS model. (<bold>D</bold>) Median expression level in HaCaT of the genes common and exclusive for the three studies. The genes are grouped according to their overlap between the three studies. Boxes, horizontal black line, and circles show the first and third quartiles, the median and outliers; whiskers show the most extreme data points up to 1.5 times the interquartile range from the box. (<bold>E</bold>) KEGG pathways and GO molecular function (MF), biological process (BP) and cellular component (CC) terms that are overrepresented (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) and unique for six of the seven subsets of cell cycle genes common or exclusive for FF, HeLa and HaCaT; see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link> for pathways and terms overrepresented among cell cycle genes common for FF, HeLa and HaCaT.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gks1336f3p"/></fig></p><p>Some of the differences between the studies were likely related to differences in microarray technologies and study designs. Microarray results are generally reproducible across platforms and laboratories for genes with medium and high expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B26">26</xref>), and the genes common for the three studies were generally highly expressed in HaCaT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F3">Figure 3</xref>D). These genes were also strongly enriched for cell cycle functions (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>), indicating that these common genes represent a core set of cell cycle genes. As for design, although previous studies have either not included or used poorly matched biological replicates, we included three direct biological replicates. This, combined with the reproducibly high level of synchronization for the HaCaT cells, gave our study better statistical power to identify cyclically expressed genes.</p><p>Although the cell cycle genes common for all three studies represented a core set of human cell cycle genes, the other subsets of cell cycle genes were at least partially related to cell type-specific functions and characteristics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F3">Figure 3</xref>E). To illustrate, the GO term &#8216;vitamin D receptor binding&#8217; was overrepresented among the cell cycle genes exclusive for HaCaT, which is consistent with vitamin D and the vitamin D receptor&#8217;s important functions in keratinocytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B27">27</xref>). In contrast, and consistent with HeLa&#8217;s cancer origin, &#8216;chronic myeloid leukaemia&#8217; was the only term exclusive for the HeLa cell cycle genes. Further supporting this conclusion, the KEGG pathways &#8216;nucleotide excision repair&#8217; and &#8216;base excision repair&#8217; were exclusively overrepresented among the cell cycle genes common for FF and HaCaT, which suggests that these two DNA repair pathways are partially dysregulated in HeLa. Although we cannot exclude that technical differences underlie some of the differences in gene expression (see &#8216;Discussion&#8217; section), distinct cell types do seem to have distinct cell cycle regulated genes. For some cells, such as HeLa and likely other cancers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B3">3</xref>), these distinct cell cycle genes may reflect that the cells are in an abnormal dysregulated state. Nevertheless, for more normal non-tumorigenic cells, such as HaCaT, at least some of the distinct cell cycle genes are related to the cells&#8217; specific functions.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell cycle genes marked with H3K27me3 are transcribed during DNA replication</title><p>Although the cell cycle genes were generally enriched for H3K4me3, a fraction of the cell cycle genes were marked with H3K27me3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F2">Figure 2</xref>B)&#8212;the mark for genes silenced by Polycomb group proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B29">29</xref>). Replication opens compacted chromatin, and although H3K27me3 marks are copied to daughter chromatin, the marks may initially be diluted, such that the normally silenced DNA is transiently accessible for transcription during this replication process. If this model was correct, we would expect that cell cycle genes marked with H3K27me3 were enriched among genes upregulated during DNA replication.</p><p>Indeed, the H3K27me3 marks in the HaCaT cells were differentially distributed among the cell cycle genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F4">Figure 4</xref>A). Of genes predominantly expressed in the G<sub>1</sub>/S and S phases, 37% had H3K4me3 marks and 12% had H3K27me3 marks. In contrast, of genes expressed in G<sub>2</sub>, G<sub>2</sub>/M and M/G<sub>1</sub>, 80% contained H3K4me3, whereas only 1% contained H3K27me3 marks. In total, 87% of the H3K27me3 marked cell cycle genes were expressed in G<sub>1</sub>/S or S (<italic>P</italic> = 5e-17; one-tailed binomial test). Similarly, a larger percentage of the G<sub>1</sub>/S and S phase genes was LCG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F4">Figure 4</xref>B). The enrichment of H3K27me3 was not related to CpG content, as the G<sub>1</sub>/S and S phase genes showed similar enrichment for H3K27me3 independent of CpG content (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F4">Figure 4</xref>C). These patterns were also consistent within the previously published data from seven different cell lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B14">14</xref>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Figure S6</ext-link>).
<fig id="gks1336-F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>G<sub>1</sub>/S and S phase genes are enriched for H3K27me3 marks and show replication-related expression. (<bold>A</bold>) Distribution of HaCaT H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 marks in promoters of genes upregulated in G<sub>1</sub>/S, S, G<sub>2</sub>, G<sub>2</sub>/M and M/G<sub>1</sub> phases; see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F2">Figure 2</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Fractions of LCG, ICG and HCG promoters for genes upregulated in the five cell cycle phases. (<bold>C</bold>) Distribution of histone marks from (A) subdivided by promoter CpG content. (<bold>D&#8211;F</bold>) GC% (D), replication timing (E) and expression level (F) of genes expressed in the five cell cycle phases. GC% is the GC% in the region defined by the gene&#8217;s annotated transcription start and end sites; replication timing is the median S/G<sub>1</sub> ratio within embryonic stem cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B33">33</xref>) of regions overlapping each gene, such that values close to 100 and 0 represent early and late replication, respectively; expression is the gene&#8217;s average microarray expression. Boxes, horizontal black line, and circles show the first and third quartiles, the median and outliers; whiskers show the most extreme data points up to 1.5 times the interquartile range from the box. (<bold>G</bold>) Expression levels of specific subgroups of G<sub>1</sub>/S and S phase genes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gks1336f4p"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Genes upregulated in early S-phase tend to be replicated earlier than late S-phase genes</title><p>Replication occurs in distinct domains largely characterized by differences in GC content, and although these domains are partly reorganized during development, domains with high and low GC content are generally replicated early and late in S phase, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B30 gks1336-B31 gks1336-B32 gks1336-B33 gks1336-B34 gks1336-B35">30&#8211;35</xref>). If DNA replication facilitated transient transcription of silenced genes, we would, therefore, expect the genes upregulated during G<sub>1</sub>/S to generally have a higher GC content than the S phase and other cell cycle genes. Indeed, the G<sub>1</sub>/S genes had the highest overall GC content of the cell cycle genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F4">Figure 4</xref>D; <italic>P</italic>-value of 7e-3, two-sided un-paired Student&#8217;s <italic>t</italic>-test with unequal variance of difference in mean between G<sub>1</sub>/S and S phase genes) and replication-timing data from three different cell lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B33">33</xref>) indicated that the G<sub>1</sub>/S genes on average tended to be replicated earlier than the S phase genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F4">Figure 4</xref>E, Student&#8217;s <italic>t</italic>-test <italic>P</italic>-value of 1e-3; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Figure S7</ext-link>). Importantly, 63% of the cell cycle regulated genes reside in genomic regions previously shown to have stable replication timing across multiple cell types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B31">31</xref>), and these genes had the same pattern in replication timing as the complete set of cell cycle genes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Figure S8</ext-link>).</p><p>Consistent with some of the genes residing in silenced chromatin and being transiently expressed during replication, the G<sub>1</sub>/S and S genes had a general lower expression level than the genes expressed in the other phases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F4">Figure 4</xref>F). Moreover, the genes marked with H3K27me3 in HaCaT had the lowest expression level of the G<sub>1</sub>/S and S phase genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F4">Figure 4</xref>G). The differences in expression between H3K27me3-marked genes and other subgroups were significant for all G<sub>1</sub>/S phase groups (<italic>P</italic>-values of 2e-16, 2e-9, 3e-5 and 0.01 for K4, HCG, ICG and LCG groups, respectively; two-sided un-paired Student&#8217;s <italic>t</italic>-test with unequal variance) and for the K4 and HCG S phase groups (<italic>P</italic>-values of 7e-4, 0.02, respectively; <italic>P</italic>-values of 0.1 and 0.3 for ICG and LCG groups, respectively).</p></sec><sec><title>Foreskin fibroblasts show similar replication-related expression of H3K27me3 marked genes</title><p>To investigate whether this replication-related cell cycle expression pattern could be found in other cell types, we first used our computational framework to reanalyse the previously published primary foreskin fibroblast data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B3">3</xref>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Figure S9</ext-link>). As in the HaCaT cells, the majority (64%) of the genes that had significant cell cycle expression and were marked with H3K27me3 in fibroblasts were upregulated during DNA replication (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F5">Figure 5</xref>A); the mark was especially enriched for the G<sub>1</sub>/S genes (<italic>P</italic> = 0.009; one-tailed binomial test for enrichment). In contrast to HaCaT, the majority of the fibroblast cell cycle genes marked with H3K27me3 was also marked with H3K4me3. The fibroblast cell cycle genes also showed a similar trend in GC content as the HaCaT genes, although the difference between the genes expressed early (G<sub>1</sub>/S) and late (S) during DNA replication was not significant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F5">Figure 5</xref>B; <italic>P</italic> = 0.1, Student&#8217;s <italic>t</italic>-test).
<fig id="gks1336-F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>H3K27me3 marks are enriched in genes upregulated during DNA replication in primary foreskin fibroblasts. (<bold>A</bold>) Distribution of H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 marks in promoters of genes upregulated in G<sub>1</sub>/S, S, G<sub>2</sub> and M/G<sub>1</sub> phases in primary foreskin fibroblasts synchronized by serum starvation [expression data from (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B3">3</xref>); ChIP-seq data from normal adult dermal fibroblasts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B14">14</xref>)]. (<bold>B</bold>) GC% of the genes from (A). (<bold>C</bold>) Distribution of H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 marks in promoters of genes upregulated in G<sub>1</sub>/S, S, G<sub>2</sub>, G<sub>2</sub>/M and M/G<sub>1</sub> phases in HeLa cells synchronized by nocodazole and mitotic shake-off [ChIP-seq data from HeLa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B14">14</xref>)]. (<bold>D</bold>) GC% of the genes from (C). See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F2">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F4">4</xref> for details on graphs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gks1336f5p"/></fig></p><p>Second, we measured the gene expression profiles in HeLa cells synchronized in the G<sub>2</sub>/M transition by nocodazole and mitotic shake-off and used PLS to identify genes with cell cycle-dependent expression (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Figures S10</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">S11</ext-link>). Again, the majority (52%) of the cell cycle genes that were marked with H3K27me3 in HeLa was upregulated during DNA replication, but the differences between the phases were not significant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F5">Figure 5</xref>C; <italic>P</italic> = 0.2). Moreover, the cell cycle genes again showed a similar trend in GC content as the HaCaT, such that the G<sub>1</sub>/S genes had a higher GC content than the S genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F5">Figure 5</xref>D; <italic>P</italic> = 0.01, Student&#8217;s <italic>t</italic>-test). Thus, replication-related expression of H3K27me3-marked genes does not seem to be a strong characteristic of all cell types. It is relevant to note, however, that the characteristic is absent in the most abnormal of the three cells, whereas HaCaT and the primary fibroblasts both have significant replication-related expression of H3K27me3-marked genes.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Previous studies of the gene expression patterns during the human cell division cycle have indicated marked differences between primary and cancer cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B3">3</xref>), but our results show that distinct cell types have distinct cell cycle expressed genes that are related to the cells&#8217; functions. Specifically, by profiling the gene expression in synchronized human HaCaT keratinocytes, we have identified a set of cell cycle expressed genes containing known marks for cell type-specific expression, such as low CpG content in their promoters and few or inconsistent promoter histone marks. These genes were enriched for functions important for keratinocyte proliferation, such as cytokine&#8211;cytokine receptor interaction.</p><p>Cell cycle regulation is an important housekeeping function and accordingly, most of the cell cycle expressed genes identified in our study have high CpG promoters and the active chromatin mark H3K4me3 in multiple cell lines. Nevertheless, we have also shown that some genes with low CpG promoters or the silent chromatin mark H3K27me3 have cell cycle dependent expression. These genes are mostly expressed during S phase in a replication-related pattern, which suggests that DNA replication can open some epigenetically silenced loci for transcription.</p><p>Replication-dependent transcription is a mechanism that can achieve precise transcriptional regulation during the cell cycle, as normally silenced genes will only be transcribed when their loci are replicated in S-phase. Compared with the other cell cycle genes, the Polycomb-regulated cell cycle genes in HaCaT were significantly enriched for the GO terms &#8216;GO:0007267 cell&#8211;cell signalling&#8217; and &#8216;GO:0046903 secretion&#8217; (Benjamini&#8211;Hochberg-corrected <italic>P</italic>-values of 0.007 and 0.02, respectively). In HaCaT cells, replication-dependent transcription may, therefore, be a regulatory mechanism for coordinating cell&#8211;cell signalling with the cell cycle.</p><p>Lanzuolo <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B36">36</xref>) have earlier reported that two Polycomb-repressed homeotic genes show replication-dependent expression in <italic>Drosophila</italic> S2 cells. Our results extend this observation to humans and show that many other genes with Polycomb-repressive marks have replication-dependent expression. We also note that cis-encoded RNAs do play a role in Polycomb-mediated targeting and regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B37 gks1336-B38 gks1336-B39">37&#8211;39</xref>). Given that Polycomb regulates all transcripts in targeted loci, replication-dependent expression may be a mechanism for expressing such cis-encoded Polycomb-associated RNAs at existing Polycomb-regulated loci.</p><p>When comparing our list of HaCaT cell cycle genes with the cell cycle genes from the previous HeLa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B2">2</xref>) and primary foreskin fibroblast studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B3">3</xref>), we found several differences, such that only 125 genes were common for all three studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gks1336-F3">Figure 3</xref>A). Several technical factors, such as differences in microarray technology, analytical approach and experimental design, likely contributed to these differences, for example, the genes that were common for all three studies were highly expressed, whereas the genes that were exclusive for our study were lowly expressed in HaCaT. We could detect these HaCaT-specific genes because our three matched biological replicates gave increased statistical power to identify weak, but consistent, cyclic expression patterns.</p><p>In addition to these technical differences, our results also show that underlying biological differences between the cells can explain some of the differences in cell cycle expressed genes. Specifically, our results show that in addition to the core genes that have cell cycle-dependent expression in multiple cell types, some genes related to the cell type&#8217;s specific functions and characteristics also have cyclic expression. This is in contrast to a previous report, which indicated that such cell-type specific expression mostly reflects differences between primary and cancer cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B3">3</xref>). These cancer-related differences are evident in our analyses as well, but we also find that genes and pathways important to keratinocyte function, such as cytokine&#8211;cytokine receptor interaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B25">25</xref>) and vitamin D receptor binding, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gks1336-B27">27</xref>) have cell cycle-dependent expression. Both functions are important for normal keratinocyte proliferation, which makes it unlikely that these results are an artifact of HaCaT&#8217;s transformed state or technical differences between the studies. Instead, the cell cycle-dependent expression of these genes likely reflects that processing of proliferative signals from the extracellular environment should be coordinated with the cell cycle.</p><p>We should note that as we have measured expression changes in total cellular RNA, some of the expression changes we have detected could potentially be explained by cell cycle-dependent changes in RNA processing or RNA stability instead of RNA transcription. Moreover, our approach of chemically synchronizing cells can likely explain some of the changes in gene expression in our data, as the synchronization procedure likely triggers stress-related responses that could both give false-positive cyclic profiles and mask the cell-cycle-dependent expression of some true cell cycle genes. This masking effect could potentially explain why we did not detect the known cell-cycle genes CDKN1A and VEGFC to have cell cycle-dependent expression in HaCaT (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Figure S2</ext-link>C and D). Our analyses, including the good overlap between the genes we identified and known cell-cycle-expressed genes, strong enrichment for cell-cycle-related functions and overlap with previous studies, do suggest, however, that the majority of the genes we identified are true cell cycle genes.</p><p>In summary, by combining robust statistics with the power of matched biological replicates, we have identified a set of genes that show consistent cell cycle-dependent expression in HaCaT cells. These genes include both general cell cycle genes and genes specific for HaCaT function. Some of the cell cycle genes also have H3K27me3 marks&#8212;a histone modification commonly associated with Polycomb-silenced genes. We show that in both HaCaT and primary foreskin fibroblasts, these genes are upregulated during DNA replication, which is consistent with a mechanism where DNA replication can open some Polycomb-repressed loci for transcription.</p></sec><sec><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gks1336/-/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NAR Online: Supplementary Tables 1 and 2, Supplementary Figures 1&#8211;11, Supplementary Methods, Supplementary Datasets 1&#8211;4 and Supplementary References [2,3,18,30,31,33,40].</p></sec><sec><title>FUNDING</title><p><funding-source>Norwegian Functional Genomics Program of the Norwegian Research Council</funding-source> (to H.E.K. and P.S.); <funding-source>Norwegian Cancer Association</funding-source> (to H.E.K.); <funding-source>Cancer Fund at St. Olav&#8217;s Hospital Trondheim</funding-source> (to H.E.K. and P.S.); <funding-source>Svanhild and Arne Must Fund for Medical Research</funding-source> (to H.E.K.); <funding-source>European Community</funding-source> program <award-id>IHP-MCIF-99-1</award-id>, contract <award-id>HPMF-CT-2001-01290</award-id> (to J.P.-D.). Funding for open access charge: <funding-source>Norwegian Research Council</funding-source>.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement.</italic> None declared.</p></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supplementary Data</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_41_5_2846__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_gks1336_nar-02954-x-2012-File007.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="supp_gks1336_nar-02954-x-2012-File008.xls"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="supp_gks1336_nar-02954-x-2012-File009.bed"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="supp_gks1336_nar-02954-x-2012-File010.xls"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="supp_gks1336_nar-02954-x-2012-File011.bed"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>The authors thank N.B. Liabakk for technical assistance and A.D. Riggs and O. Sn&#248;ve Jr for critical reading. The sequencing service was provided by the Norwegian Sequencing Centre (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.sequencing.uio.no">www.sequencing.uio.no</ext-link>), a national technology platform hosted by the University of Oslo and supported by the &#8216;Functional Genomics&#8217; and &#8216;Infrastructure&#8217; programs of the Norwegian Research Council and the Southeastern Regional Health Authorities of Norway.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="gks1336-B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinmetz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapinoso</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hampton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Elledge</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lockhart</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional regulation and function during the human cell cycle</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2001</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11137997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitfield</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherlock</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Saldanha</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Matese</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Perou</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurt</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of genes periodically expressed in the human cell cycle and their expression in tumors</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source><year>2002</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1977</fpage><lpage>2000</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12058064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bar-Joseph</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegfried</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandeis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brors</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Eils</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dynlacht</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide transcriptional analysis of the human cell cycle identifies genes differentially regulated in normal and cancer cells</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>955</fpage><lpage>960</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18195366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Trent</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Staudt</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>J</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Boguski</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The transcriptional program in the response of human fibroblasts to serum</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1999</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9872747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beyrouthy</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitfield</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Bass</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>McGee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurt</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of G1-regulated genes in normally cycling human cells</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2008</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e3943</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19079774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spellman</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherlock</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>MQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Futcher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive identification of cell cycle-regulated genes of the yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> by microarray hybridization</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3273</fpage><lpage>3297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9843569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Winzeler</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinmetz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wodicka</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfsberg</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabrielian</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Landsman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lockhart</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A genome-wide transcriptional analysis of the mitotic cell cycle</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9702192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laub</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>McAdams</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldblyum</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global analysis of the genetic network controlling a bacterial cell cycle</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>290</volume><fpage>2144</fpage><lpage>2148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11118148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rustici</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mata</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kivinen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Penkett</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayles</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brazma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Periodic gene expression program of the fission yeast cell cycle</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2004</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>809</fpage><lpage>817</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15195092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolstad</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Irizarry</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Astrand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Speed</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparison of normalization methods for high density oligonucleotide array data based on variance and bias</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2003</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12538238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rhead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Karolchik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinrichs</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zweig</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Diekhans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenbloom</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Raney</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The UCSC Genome Browser database: update 2010</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>D613</fpage><lpage>D619</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19906737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellmann</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Paabo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebhan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schubeler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution, silencing potential and evolutionary impact of promoter DNA methylation in the human genome</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2007</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17334365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenbloom</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreszer</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pheasant</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pohl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Raney</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinrichs</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zweig</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ENCODE whole-genome data in the UCSC Genome Browser</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>D620</fpage><lpage>D625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19920125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birney</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamatoyannopoulos</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guigo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gingeras</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Margulies</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dermitzakis</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Thurman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification and analysis of functional elements in 1% of the human genome by the ENCODE pilot project</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2007</year><volume>447</volume><fpage>799</fpage><lpage>816</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17571346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cutadapt removes adapter sequences from high-throughput sequencing reads</article-title><source>EMBnet.J.</source><year>2011</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>R25</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19261174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schones</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A clustering approach for identification of enriched domains from histone modification ChIP-Seq data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1952</fpage><lpage>1958</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falcon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentleman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using GOstats to test gene lists for GO term association</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2007</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17098774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boukamp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrussevska</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Breitkreutz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Markham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fusenig</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Normal keratinization in a spontaneously immortalized aneuploid human keratinocyte cell line</article-title><source>J. Cell Biol.</source><year>1988</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>771</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2450098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Berglund</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A multivariate approach applied to microarray data for identification of genes with cell cycle-coupled transcription</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2003</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12611801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gidskehaug</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderssen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Flatberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alsberg</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A framework for significance analysis of gene expression data using dimension reduction methods</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>346</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17877799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saxonov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Brutlag</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A genome-wide analysis of CpG dinucleotides in the human genome distinguishes two distinct classes of promoters</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>1412</fpage><lpage>1417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16432200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ku</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Issac</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Giannoukos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Brockman</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Koche</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide maps of chromatin state in pluripotent and lineage-committed cells</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2007</year><volume>448</volume><fpage>553</fpage><lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17603471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kouzarides</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromatin modifications and their function</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>693</fpage><lpage>705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17320507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grose</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of wound healing by growth factors and cytokines</article-title><source>Physiol. Rev.</source><year>2003</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>835</fpage><lpage>870</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12843410</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Trimarchi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Punzo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lombardi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Whipple</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Maysuria</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Serikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A sequence-oriented comparison of gene expression measurements across different hybridization-based technologies</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>832</fpage><lpage>840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16823376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cianferotti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Skorija</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Demay</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vitamin D receptor is essential for normal keratinocyte stem cell function</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>9428</fpage><lpage>9433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17517646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beisel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Paro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silencing chromatin: comparing modes and mechanisms</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21221116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Margueron</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Polycomb complex PRC2 and its mark in life</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2011</year><volume>469</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21248841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woodfine</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiegler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Beare</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>McCann</surname><given-names>OT</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Debernardi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mott</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunham</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replication timing of the human genome</article-title><source>Hum. Mol. Genet.</source><year>2004</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14645202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandstrom</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Canfield</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Thurman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorschner</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Gartler</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamatoyannopoulos</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequencing newly replicated DNA reveals widespread plasticity in human replication timing</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19966280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farkash-Amar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Polten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Goren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Helmstetter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yakhini</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global organization of replication time zones of the mouse genome</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1562</fpage><lpage>1570</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18669478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Desprat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Thierry-Mieg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lailler</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lajugie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schildkraut</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Thierry-Mieg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouhassira</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predictable dynamic program of timing of DNA replication in human cells</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2288</fpage><lpage>2299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19767418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costantini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernardi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replication timing, chromosomal bands, and isochores</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>3433</fpage><lpage>3437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18305168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiratani</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokochi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwaiger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Townes</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schubeler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global reorganization of replication domains during embryonic stem cell differentiation</article-title><source>PLoS Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e245</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18842067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanzuolo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo Sardo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Diamantini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Orlando</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PcG complexes set the stage for epigenetic inheritance of gene silencing in early S phase before replication</article-title><source>PLoS Genet.</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e1002370</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22072989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plath</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mlynarczyk-Evans</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Worringer</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>de la Cruz</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Otte</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Panning</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of histone H3 lysine 27 methylation in X inactivation</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>300</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12649488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polycomb proteins targeted by a short repeat RNA to the mouse X chromosome</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2008</year><volume>322</volume><fpage>750</fpage><lpage>756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18974356</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammad</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Enroth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Redrup</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Komorowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancini-Dinardo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanduri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kcnq1ot1 antisense noncoding RNA mediates lineage-specific transcriptional silencing through chromatin-level regulation</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18951091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gks1336-B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kheradpour</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoresh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Issner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mapping and analysis of chromatin state dynamics in nine human cell types</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2011</year><volume>473</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21441907</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>