
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosntds</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1935-2727</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1935-2735</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3923677</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24551254</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PNTD-D-13-01148</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002689</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Systems Biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemical Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Computational Chemistry</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Phytochemistry</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Computational Studies on Sirtuins from Trypanosoma cruzi: Structures, Conformations and Interactions with Phytochemicals </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>T. cruzi</italic> Sirtuins: Conformers and Phyto Inhibitors</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sacconnay</surname><given-names>Lionel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Angleviel</surname><given-names>Melissa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Randazzo</surname><given-names>Giuseppe Marco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marçal Ferreira Queiroz</surname><given-names>Marcos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ferreira Queiroz</surname><given-names>Emerson</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wolfender</surname><given-names>Jean-Luc</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carrupt</surname><given-names>Pierre-Alain</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nurisso</surname><given-names>Alessandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, University of Geneva, University of Lausanne, Geneva, Switzerland</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Setzer</surname><given-names>William N.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Alabama in Huntsville, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>alessandra.nurisso@unige.ch</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: LS EFQ AN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: LS MA GMR MMFQ AN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: LS MA AN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: EFQ JLW PAC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: LS MA AN. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e2689</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Sacconnay et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sacconnay et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The silent-information regulator 2 proteins, otherwise called sirtuins, are currently considered as emerging anti-parasitic targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Nicotinamide, a pan-sirtuin inhibitor, is known to cause kinetoplast alterations and the arrested growth of T. cruzi, the protozoan responsible for Chagas disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>These observations suggested that sirtuins from this parasite (TcSir2rp1 and TcSir2rp3) could play an important role in the regulation of the parasitic cell cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Thus, their inhibition could be exploited for the development of novel anti-trypanosomal compounds. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Homology modeling was used to determine the three-dimensional features of the sirtuin TcSir2rp1 from T. cruzi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The apo-form of human SIRT2 and the same structure solved in complex with its co-substrate NAD+ allowed the modeling of TcSir2rp1 in the open and closed conformational states. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Molecular docking studies were then carried out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>A library composed of fifty natural and diverse compounds that are known to be active against this parasite, was established based on the literature and virtually screened against TcSir2rp1 and TcSir2rp3, which was previously modeled by our group. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In this study, two conformational states of TcSir2rp1 were described for the first time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The molecular docking results of compounds capable of binding sirtuins proved to be meaningful when the closed conformation of the protein was taken into account for calculations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>This specific conformation was then used for the virtual screening of antritrypanosomal phytochemicals against TcSir2rp1 and TcSir2rp3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The calculations identified a limited number of scaffolds extracted from Vismia orientalis, Cussonia zimmermannii, Amomum aculeatum and Anacardium occidentale that potentially interact with both proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The study provided reliable models for future structure-based drug design projects concerning sirtuins from T. cruzi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Molecular docking studies highlighted not only the advantages of performing in silico interaction studies on their closed conformations but they also suggested the potential mechanism of action of four phytochemicals known for their anti-trypanosomal activity in vitro. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Author Summary </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>T. cruzi is a protozoan pathogen responsible for Chagas disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Current therapies rely only on a very small number of drugs, most of which are inadequate because of their severe host toxicity or because of their susceptibility to drug-resistance mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>To determine efficient therapeutic alternatives, the identification of new biotargets and detailed knowledge of their structures are essential. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Sirtuins from T. cruzi have been recently considered as promising targets for the development of new treatments for Chagas disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of their activity has been shown to significantly interfere with the life cycle of the parasite. T. cruzi possesses genes encoding two sirtuin-like proteins, TcSIR2rp1 and TcSIR2rp3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The structures of these enzymes were theoretically elucidated in this work, which also focused on the impact of their possible conformational states on computational interaction studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>A small library of phytochemicals that are active against the parasite was built and screened against the most meaningful conformations, identifying a restricted number of scaffolds that potentially interact with the modeled proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>For these hits, a mechanism of action related to interactions with sirtuins was proposed. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The authors are grateful to the Swiss National Science Foundation for financial support. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Chagas disease is caused by a flagellated protozoan belonging to the Trypanosomatidae family of the kinetoplastida order. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>This disease which is mainly localized in Central and South America, affects approximately 8 million people, causing near 14,000 deaths worldwide [1] and leading to serious medical complications such as fatal damage to the heart muscles (cardiomyopathy), central nervous system, and digestive tract (megacolon, megaesophagus) consequently resulting in death [2], [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, the two drugs used for the treatment of Chagas disease (Benznidazole and Nifurtimoz), have limited efficacy and have been associated with numerous adverse side effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the pathogen seems to be able to develop resistance against these treatments [4], [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Thus, there is an urgent need to find new biotargets for the development of compounds with low toxicity and good efficacy against this parasite [6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The silent-information regulator 2 (SIR2) proteins are currently considered as emerging anti-parasitic targets because of their nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide NAD+-dependent deacetylase activity on histones and other cellular substrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>It has been demonstrated, for example, that sirtuins from Plasmodium species are involved in the regulation of the telomere-associated var gene family members that encode for proteins responsible of host immune evasion [7], [8]. Leishmania sirtuins were found to be implicated in delaying apoptosis and providing protection from host immune responses [9], [10], [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Moreover, their species specific inhibition by bisnaphthalimidopropyl (BNIP) derivatives has exhibited robust anti-leishmanial activity [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Whereas TbSir2rp2 and TbSir2rp3 from T. brucei do not impact on parasite growth and differentiation in vitro, TbSir2rp1 has been shown to participate in DNA repair through the modification of H2A and H2B histones [13], [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>For an extensive review on this topic, please refer to [15], [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>In T. cruzi, two isoforms from the SIR2 family have been identified: TcSIR2rp1 and TcSIR2rp3 (Figure 1) [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>It was proven in cellulo that their inhibition by the well-known sirtuin inhibitor nicotinamide can cause morphologic alterations and an inhibitory growth of this parasite, suggesting a potential use of TcSIR2 proteins for the development of new drugs against Chagas disease [18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pntd-0002689-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002689.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Hypothetical roles of NAD+ dependent deacetylases (sirtuin family) in the T. cruzi parasite. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pntd.0002689.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>From a structural point of view, sirtuins are formed by a large Rossmann fold domain and by a small domain composed of a helical and a zinc-binding module. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Their catalytic pocket is conserved, from bacteria to mammals [19], [20] and it is formed by three sub-pockets that accommodate the co-substrate NAD+: the A pocket, where the adenine-ribose moiety binds; the B pocket, where the nicotinamide-ribose moiety binds; and the C pocket, where nicotinamide is supposed to bind [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Recently, crystallography identified two possible conformational states for sirtuins: an open or non-productive conformation (apo-form) and a closed or productive conformation (bound-form). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The two conformers, experimentally observed in the human sirtuin SIRT2, differ at the catalytic pocket in terms of shape and ligand accessibility [21], [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>By considering this very recent structural information, two conformers of TcSIR2rp1 have been built by homology modeling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>A molecular docking approach was then used not only for evaluating the quality of the modeled proteins but also for understanding the impact of the two conformational states on the final docking results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>It is important to note that the majority of molecular docking calculations involving sirtuins reported in the literature have been carried out using only the non-productive conformation of sirtuins [23], [24], [25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Finally, because nature is a rich source of anti-trypanosomal agents [26], [27], a database of phytochemicals with a known inhibitory activity in vitro against T. cruzi has been collected from the literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Computational interaction studies between these compounds and sirtuins in the more meaningful modeled conformation was conducted to identify a potential sirtuin-related trypanocidal activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Homology modeling </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Homology modeling was performed by using the Molecular Operating Environment MOE software package (MOE 2012.10; Chemical Computing Group, Montreal, Canada). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The primary sequence of SIR2rp1 from T. cruzi (TcSIR2rp1, sequence ID: Q4DP02) was retrieved from the Universal Protein Resource database and used as a target for the homology modeling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>To identify a template structure, the target sequence was submitted to a PSI-BLAST search (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>) against the Protein Data Bank PDB (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org/">www.rcsb.org/</ext-link>) using the BLOSUM62 matrix with an E-value cutoff of 10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The human cytosolic SIRT2 protein (hSIRT2), having ∼35% sequence identity with the target, was selected as a template for the current project. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Two conformations of hSIRT2 were found in the PDB: a non-productive conformation (PDB ID: 1J8F), that corresponds to the apo-hSIRT2 [21], and a productive one (PDB ID: 3ZGV) [22], in which hSIRT2 binds adenosine-5-diphophoribose A5dPR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Both proteins were used in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Thus, TcSIR2rp1 was modeled in the two possible conformational states by following the same strategy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The target-template sequence alignment was performed using MOE's multiple sequence alignment algorithm [28], [29] and then refined manually. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Three-dimensional model building was then carried out using the MOE homology program [30] based on a segment matching procedure [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Ten intermediate models of TcSIR2rp1 in both non-productive and productive forms were generated and successively minimized by using the Tripos force field [32] in Sybyl-×2.0 (TRIPOS Inc., St. Louis, MO). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The sequence from Trp93 to His97 of the parasitic productive form was modeled based on the productive human SIRT1 structure (PDB ID: 4I5I) due to a lack of structural information of this specific loop in hSIRT2 [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Gasteiger-Huckel charges were assigned to the proteins before starting the minimization step that was conducted using the Tripos force field [32] with 700 cycles of the Powell algorithm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Finally, the stereochemical quality of the models was assessed using Ramachandran plot analysis included in the PROCHECK validation package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nihserver.mbi.ucla.edu/SAVES/">http://nihserver.mbi.ucla.edu/SAVES/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The models with the best stereochemical quality were then selected for the interaction studies described in the next section. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Molecular docking </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The crystal structure of hSIRT2 co-crystallized with the co-substrate A5dPR (PDB ID: 3ZGV) was taken into account not only as a template for the homology modeling but also for validating the docking methodology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>This structure was prepared for docking in Sybyl-×2.0 (TRIPOS Inc., St. Louis, MO) by removing the crystallized water molecules, by adding the missing hydrogen atoms and by extracting the ligand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The re-docking was then conducted using GOLD version 5.1 (CCDC, Cambridge, UK). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The binding site was defined by a 12.5 Å radius sphere around the Ala85 residue and 100 docking solutions were generated by using 100,000 GOLD Genetic Algorithm iterations (Preset option). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Docking poses were evaluated and ranked according to the PLP score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Root-mean-square-deviation RMSD values between the docking solutions and the crystallized ligand of reference were calculated to evaluate docking performance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The homology models were then superimposed on the respective productive (PDB ID: 3ZGV) and non-productive (PDB ID: 1J8F) hSIRT2 conformations using the nicotinamide recognition sequence (TQNXD motif) as a reference for superimposition [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Further docking studies of NAD+ (co-substrate), nicotinamide (pan-sirtuin inhibitor) and AGK2 (selective hSIRT2 inhibitor) were carried out on the non-productive and productive protein forms of T. cruzi sirtuins by applying the methodology described above [18], [34], [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The binding site of the parasitic targets was defined by taking Ala38 into account as a reference for NAD+ and AGK2 docking whereas, for nicotinamide, the binding site was defined by taking into account an 8 Å radius sphere around Asp125. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>This correction was made to avoid false positive results due to the small size of this compound with respect to the sirtuin pocket. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Clustering analysis was finally performed using the RMSD analysis tool implemented in GOLD version 5.1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Library of trypanocidal natural compounds: Construction and diversity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>A library of fifty compounds with in vivo anti T. cruzi activity was created by collecting data from the literature (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Iridoids &amp; Terpenes (11 compounds), Phenolics (31 compounds) and Alkaloids (9 compounds) characterize the library. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>3D structures were generated by using Sybyl-×2.0 (TRIPOS Inc., St. Louis, MO), with particular regard to the stereochemistry and protonation states (pH = 7.4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>To display the chemical variation of data, a heat map based on the Tanimoto similarity matrix of Morgan fingerprints [36], was generated using RDKit [37], SciPy [38] and Matplotlib [39] tools. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>In silico screening of trypanocidal natural compounds against sirtuins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The database was screened against the productive form of T. cruzi sirtuins (TcSIR2rp1, TcSIR2rp3 [40]) using the previously described protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The best-ranked forms according to their PLP score were taken into account for docking evaluation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The compounds with a positive score with respect to AGK2 (potent and selective class I sirtuin inhibitor [35]) and thiobarbiturate 6 (potent and selective class III sirtuin inhibitor [41]) were selected for further structural analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Results and Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Homology modeling of Sir2rp1 from T. cruzi: Non-productive and productive conformational states </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>A rational template search was the first step for the construction of a reliable homology model of TcSIR2rp1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Through a BLAST-P search, the human histone deacetylase hSIRT2, with ∼35% of sequence identity, was determined to be the best template choice for TcSIR2rp1 modeling [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The primary sequence of the selected template was aligned with the respective target primary sequence (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The alignment showed a high number of conserved residues (∼70%) in the three catalytic sub-pockets (Table S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pntd-0002689-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002689.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Sequence alignment between TcSir2rp1 and hSIRT2. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Conserved amino acids are highlighted in yellow. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pntd.0002689.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>As reported for hSIRT2, two possible conformational states in sirtuins could exist: a so-called non-productive conformation, characterized by the absence of ligands in the catalytic site [21], and a productive one, in which the protein is found in a bound state [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The main difference between the two conformations consists of a 25° rotation of the zinc-binding domain towards the Rossmann-fold domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a high flexibility of the zinc-binding domain was observed in the productive form (Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In this study, two conformations of TcSIR2rp1 were modeled, based on hSIRT2 structural information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>After several energy minimization cycles, 98.3% and 98.6% of φ and ψ backbone dihedral angles from the non-productive and productive protein forms occupied the allowed regions of the Ramachandran plots whereas less than 1%, comprised of residues that are not part of the active site regions, occupied the disallowed ones (Figure S2).These percentages, together with the absence of clashes and anomalies in bond lengths and angles, emphasized the accuracy of the modeled proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>A productive conformational state of TcSir2rp1 is necessary for reliable molecular docking studies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>In this project, a molecular docking approach was used to verify the quality of the modeled proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the impact of the two modeled conformational states on the final docking results was also evaluated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>To validate the docking methodology, a re-docking strategy was carried out using the structure of A5dPR co-crystallized with hSIRT2 (PDB ID: 3ZGV, productive conformation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The best-ranked docking solution according to the PLP score presented an RMSD value of 0.7 Å with respect to the crystallographic pose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Contacts with the protein were mainly polar, involving Arg97, Asn286, His187 and Glu323 residues [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Hydrophobic interactions with Phe235, Val266 and Phe96 were also present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>When the same ligand was docked into the modeled productive TcSIR2rp1 binding site, a similar binding mode and interaction network were determined. Figure 3A shows the docking results, highlighting the successful reproduction of the crystallographic information in silico. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pntd-0002689-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002689.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Molecular docking results in the productive pocket of TcSIR2rp1. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>(A) Superimposition of A5dPR crystal (yellow-capped sticks) and best-ranked docking poses in hSIRT2 (green-capped sticks, cyan ribbons) and TcSIR2rp1 (white-capped sticks, dark pink ribbons). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>(B) NAD+ best-ranked docking pose in the TcSIR2rp1 productive form (purple-capped sticks, dark pink ribbons). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>(C) Nicotinamide best-ranked docking pose in the TcSIR2rp1 productive form (purple -capped sticks, dark pink ribbons). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>(D) AGK2 best-ranked docking pose in the TcSIR2rp1 productive form (purple-capped sticks, dark pink ribbons). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pntd.0002689.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>NAD+ was successively docked into the productive form of TcSir2rp1 (Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The best-ranked solution, according to the PLP score, was evaluated using the crystallographic NAD+ pose in the hSIRT1 pocket as a reference [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The hydrogen bond network described by Zhao et al. was retrieved and it involves Ala38, Phe49, Arg50, Thr214, Ser215, Asn238, and Cys308 residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Hydrophobic contacts stabilizing the nicotinamide ring were also observed (Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Nicotinamide was then docked into the productive pocket of TcSIR2rp1 [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>In agreement with the crystallographic information from the Thermotoga maritima-nicotinamide Sir2 homolog complex (PDB ID: 1YC5) [43], the inhibitor occupied the C-site of the protein, forming hydrogen bonds with the Ile124 backbone and Asp125 lateral chain. ∏-stacking interactions with Phe50 were also observed along with hydrophobic contacts involving Ile124, Ala38 and Ile46 (Figure 3C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>AGK2 was finally docked into the productive binding site of TcSIR2rp1 (Figure 3D, Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>This compound was demonstrated to have a certain degree of selectivity towards class I sirtuins [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>To date, no information about the potency of AGK2 trypanocidal activity is available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>However, due to the high identity between the catalytic pocket of hSIRT2 and TcSIR2rp1 [24], a similar binding mode was assumed in the current study (Figure 3A, Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>It has been described that AGK2 in hSIRT2 can preferentially bind the C-pocket of this protein [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>However, in the absence of crystallographic information, it can be supposed, by a structure-activity relationship, that AGK2 can assume an orientation similar to A5dPR, occupying the A and B pockets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Our docking results are seemingly in agreement with this hypothesis (Figure 3D, Figure S3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>By following the same methodology, in silico interaction studies were also carried out on the non-productive form of TcSIR2rp1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The docking analysis revealed that the NAD+ best-ranked pose occupied a different position in the active site, compared to the hSIRT1 co-crystal [25], with the adenosine-ribose moiety pointing toward the solvent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>A cluster analysis (cut-off of 2 Å) performed on the docking solutions (Table S4), indicated that 24% of the docking positions converged to this binding mode. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Moreover, numerous and diverse docking clusters, related to the high number of conformations the ligand can assume in the wide pocket, were obtained (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Conversely, cluster analysis performed on the docking solutions from the productive form highlighted a more important convergence (46%) to the correct orientation of the co-substrate in the pocket (Figure 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>In agreement with the previous findings, the docking of nicotinamide in the TcSIR2rp1 non-productive form showed that all docking poses occupied a non-crystallographic position in the pocket whereas all the docking solutions retrieved in the productive form matched the crystallographic orientation (Table S4, Figure S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Finally, the best-ranked pose of AGK2 seemed, even in the TcSIR2rp1 non-productive form, able to adopt a position similar to the one retrieved in the productive active site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>However, this specific solution belonged to a cluster populated by a small portion of docking solutions (16%) whereas, in the productive form, 27% of the docking poses converged to the expected one (Table S4, Figure S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the PLP scores obtained for all the ligands docked in the productive TcSIR2rp1 were higher if compared to the scores obtained in the non-productive form (Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>This observation can be explained by the lack of key interactions between ligands and the non-productive form of the enzyme that is unfavorable for ligand accommodation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>By considering all these observations, the productive form of TcSIR2rp1, herein modeled for the first time, will be taken into account for the interaction studies described in the following section. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pntd-0002689-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002689.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Superimposition of ten NAD+ docking poses in the TcSIR2rp1 productive (A) and non-productive (B) forms. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>NAD+ molecules are represented in brown-capped sticks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Protein structures are represented as ribbons and colored in dark pink and green representing the TcSIR2rp1 productive and non-productive form, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Pocket surfaces were generated with MOE (MOE 2012.10; Chemical Computing Group, Montreal, Canada) and are colored in gray. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pntd.0002689.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Computational interaction studies identified a possible sirtuin-related mechanism of action of four trypanocidal natural compounds </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>In silico target-fishing approaches have been reported in the past to identify the possible mechanism of actions of anti-parasitic compounds [45], [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>By following a similar strategy, with the aim of identifying a possible action related to sirtuin inhibition, fifty diverse anti-trypanosomal natural compounds were docked into the productive forms of sirtuins from T. cruzi: TcSIR2rp1 and TcSIR2rp3 [40] (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The latter has been recently modeled in a productive conformational state based on the E. coli CobB protein and A. fulgidus sirtuin in complex with NAD+ (PDB IDs: 1S5P, 1ICI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>As qualitatively demonstrated by the color of the heat map reported in Figure S5, the compounds characterizing the small dataset used in this work were diverse in terms of chemical structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The results of the screening are listed in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>PLP scores were compared to AGK2 and thiobarbiturate 6, because these compounds are selective inhibitors of sirtuin class I [35] and class III [41], respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Four compounds, according to their positive score with respect to the score obtained for the reference compounds, were selected for further structural inspections as potential sirtuin modulators: anacardic acid derivative (Cmp5), aculeatin D (Cmp33), 16-acetoxy-11-hydroxyoctadeca-17-ene-12,14-diynylethanoate (Cmp1) and vismione D (Cmp50). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>GRID surfaces were then calculated in order to better understand the interactions with the proteins [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>DRY, N1 and O probes were used to describe the hydrophobic, electron-donor and electron-acceptor properties of the pockets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the analysis of the docking poses suggested that each ligand is a competitive inhibitor for NAD+ fixation, being able to occupy the NAD+ pocket of the proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pntd-0002689-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002689.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>PLP scores for the anti-trypanosomal compounds docked into TcSIR2rp1 and TcSIR2rp3 productive forms. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pntd-0002689-t001-1" xlink:href="pntd.0002689.t001"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The compounds selected from the virtual screening for structural inspections are reported in bold. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Considering the PLP score, the anarcadic acid derivative (Cmp5) obtained from the cashew nut shell liquid exhibited the best overall docking results in both parasitic sirtuins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The best-ranked pose of this compound in the TcSIR2rp1 pocket formed hydrogen bonds between the carboxylic group of the ligand and the side chain of Arg50. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Moreover, additional hydrophobic interactions with Ala38, Phe49, Phe188 and Val218 were observed (Figure 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, in TcSIR2rp3, the best-ranked pose exhibited a shift of 180° in the binding site with the poly-carbonated chain pointing toward the A pocket. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>A hydrogen bond between the polar head of the compound and Arg60, which is known to interact with the succinyl/malonyl group of the endogenous substrate and also to be responsible for nicotinamide resistance in sirtuin class III proteins, was highlighted [15], [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Hydrophobic interactions between the lipophilic chain and Ala14, Phe24, Phe157 and Val186 residues of pocket B and C were also detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The second best-ranked pose matched the one observed in TcSIR2rp1, suggesting two possible binding modes in TcSIR2rp3 (Figure 5A, S6A, S7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>All these observations correlate well with the GRID surfaces calculated in the protein pockets, especially with the DRY surfaces, indicating the main role of hydrophobic interactions in the binding. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pntd-0002689-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002689.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Molecular docking results from the virtual screening of the productive conformational state of TcSIR2rp1. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>(A) Anacardic acid best-ranked docking pose in the TcSIR2rp1 productive form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>(B) Aculeatin D best-ranked docking pose in the TcSIR2rp1 productive form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>(C) 16-acetoxy-11-hydroxyoctadeca-17-ene-12,14-diynylethanoate best-ranked docking pose in the TcSIR2rp1 productive form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>(D) Vismione D best-ranked docking pose in the TcSIR2rp1 productive form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Protein structures are represented as dark pink ribbons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Amino acids participating in protein-ligand interactions are indicated bylight gray sticks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Ligands are represented in capped sticks and are colored in orange. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>GRID surface are also reported in the active site pockets and are colored as yellow, blue and red to highlight the hydrophobic, electron-donor and electron-acceptor properties, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pntd.0002689.g005"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Aculeatin D (Cmp33) extracted from the rhizomes of Amomum aculeatum was characterized by PLP scores of 79.7 and 90.3 in the TcSIR2rp1 and TcSIR2rp3 productive forms, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>As in the previous case, hydrophobic-driven interactions with the sirtuin pockets, also highlighted by the DRY probe, were observed (Figure 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>In addition, for TcSIR2rp3, hydrogen bonds with Val97, Arg60 and His113 were reported (Figure S6B), explaining the higher score observed for this specific isoform. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>16-acetoxy-11-hydroxyoctadeca-17-ene-12,14-diynylethanoate (Cmp1) extracted from the root bark of Cussonia zimmermannii formed similar interactions with both proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Hydrogen bonds between the hydroxyl and carbonyl group of the polar head with, respectively, Arg50 and Cys308 of TcSIR2rp1 and Asn185 and Lys224 of TcSIR2rp3 were observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Hydrophobic interactions with Ala38, Phe49, Phe188 and Val218 of TcSIR2rp1 and Ala14, Phe25, Phe157 and Val186 of TcSIR2rp3 were also detected (Figure 5C, FigureS6C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Again, GRID surface analysis highlighted a good match between DRY surfaces and the hydrophobic region of the potential inhibitor. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Vismione D (Cmp50) isolated from the plant Vismia orientalis Engl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>(Guttiferae or Clusiaceae) was the last compound that was selected from the screening, according to the PLP score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Hydrogen bonds with Ala38 (TcSIR2rp1) and Ala14 (TcSIR2rp3) backbones were detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Moreover, van der Waals contacts with the hydrophobic amino acids characterizing the pocket were retrieved in both parasitic proteins (Figure 5D, Figure S6D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>These results suggested that the possible mechanism of action of these four natural compounds, that are known to have an inhibitory activity against T. cruzi, could be related to interactions with sirtuins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the compounds identified by molecular docking are flexible molecules that would likely bind many active sites such as other NAD+ dependent enzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Additional docking studies against other enzymes (NAD+ dependent and others) would clarify this point. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Moreover, no selectivity was found when the same computational approach was performed using the homologous human enzymes hSIRT2 and hSIRT5 (Figure S8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, these quite large lipophilic compounds, displaying no selectivity for parasite protein over host, do not appear to be very drug-like starting points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Please refer to the works of Kaur et al. and Sacconnay et al. for information about structural differences in the binding pockets that could be exploited for species-specific sirtuin inhibitor design [40], [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, in this study, several goals were reached: (i) the building (in silico) and the description of the three-dimensional structure of two conformational states of TcSIR2rp1 from T. cruzi; (ii) the evaluation of their impact on docking calculations, showing the advantages of performing computational interaction studies on the productive form; and (iii) the identification of a possible sirtuin-related mechanism of action of four natural trypanocidal compounds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Indeed, such results require experimental validation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The homology models of T. cruzi sirtuins are deposited in the Protein Model Database PMDB [49] with the following IDs: PM0079211 (TcSIR2rp1, non-productive conformational state [40]), PM0079212 (TcSIR2rp1, productive conformational state), and PM0078446 (TcSIR2rp3, productive conformational state). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0002689.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Structural superimposition of the non-productive form (light pink ribbons) and productive form (purple ribbons) of TcSir2rp1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pntd.0002689.s001.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0002689.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Ramachandran plots of the non-productive (a) and productive (b) forms of Tcsir2rp1 homology models. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pntd.0002689.s002.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0002689.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>NAD+ (A), nicotinamide (B) and AGK2 (C) best-ranked docking poses in the hSIRT2 productive form. Protein is represented in deep cyan cartoon whereas the amino acids involved in the interaction with the ligands are represented as capped sticks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>NAD+, Nicotinamide and AGK2 are also represented as capped sticks and are colored in brown, orange and purple, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pntd.0002689.s003.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0002689.s004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Superposition of ten nicotinamide and AGK2 docking poses in TcSIR2rp1 productive (A–C) and non-productive (B–D) forms. Nicotinamide and AGK2 are represented by orange and purple-capped sticks respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Backbones are represented with ribbons and are colored in dark pink and green, representing the TcSIR2rp1 productive and non-productive form respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Surfaces of the protein pockets are colored in gray. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pntd.0002689.s004.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0002689.s005"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Heat map constructed from the fifty natural compounds of the library. Colors in the heat map indicate the relative similarity (brown for high similarity and white for low similarity) of the molecules in the dataset. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pntd.0002689.s005.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0002689.s006"><label>Figure S6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Molecular docking results in the productive pocket of TcSIR2rp3. (A) Anacardic acid docking pose in the TcSIR2rp3 productive form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>(B) Aculeatin D best-ranked docking pose in the TcSIR2rp3 productive form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>(C) 16-acetoxy-11-hydroxyoctadeca-17-ene-12,14-diynylethanoate best-ranked docking pose in the TcSIR2rp3 productive form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>(D) Vismione D best-ranked docking pose in the TcSIR2rp3 productive form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Protein structures are represented as light pink ribbons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Amino acids participating in protein-ligand interactions are highlighted by light gray sticks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Ligands are represented as capped sticks and are colored in orange. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>GRID surface are also reported in the active site pocket and are colored yellow, blue and red for hydrophobic, electro-donor and electro-acceptor properties, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pntd.0002689.s006.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0002689.s007"><label>Figure S7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Best-ranked docking poses for the Anacardic acid derivative in TcSIR2rp3 (A) and hSIRT5 (B) productive forms. Protein structures are represented in ribbons and colored in pink and light blue for TcSIR2rp3 and hSIRT5, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Amino acids participating in protein-ligand interactions are represented in orange capped sticks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Ligand is represented in capped stick and colored in orange. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>GRID surfaces are also reported in the active site pockets and colored as yellow, blue and red for highlighting hydrophobic, electro-donor and electro-acceptor properties, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pntd.0002689.s007.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0002689.s008"><label>Figure S8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Molecular docking results from the virtual screening in the productive conformational states of hSIRT2 and hSIRT5. Anacardic acid best-ranked docking poses in hSIRT2 (A) and in hSIRT5 (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Aculeatin D best-ranked docking poses in hSIRT2 (C) and in hSIRT5 (D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>16-acetoxy-11-hydroxyoctadeca-17-ene-12,14-diynylethanoate best-ranked docking poses in hSIRT2 (E) and in hSIRT5 (F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Vismione D best-ranked docking poses in hSIRT2 (G) and in hSIRT5 (H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Protein structures are represented as ribbons and are colored cyan and light blue for hSIRT2 and hSIRT5 respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Amino acids participating in protein-ligand interactions are represented as light gray sticks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Capped stick ligands are colored orange. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>GRID surfaces are also reported in the active site pockets and are colored yellow, blue and red to highlight hydrophobic, electron-donor and electron-acceptor properties, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pntd.0002689.s008.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0002689.s009"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Smile codes for the anti- T. cruzi  compounds characterizing the natural product library. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pntd.0002689.s009.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0002689.s010"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Summary of the residues characterizing the A–C pockets of TcSir2rp1 and hSIRT2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pntd.0002689.s010.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0002689.s011"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Best-ranked PLP docking scores of NAD+, nicotinamide and AGK2 ligands in the non-productive/productive TcSIR2rp1 conformations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pntd.0002689.s011.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0002689.s012"><label>Table S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Clustering analysis results (2 Å cut-off). Red clusters contain the best-ranked poses according to the PLP score. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pntd.0002689.s012.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>The authors thank researchers from the CHEMBIOFIGHT project (EC/FP7/269301), in particular Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Soares, for valuable scientific discussions. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pntd.0002689-Hotez1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>1 HotezPJ, BottazziME, Franco-ParedesC, AultSK, PeriagoMR (2008) The Neglected Tropical Diseases of Latin America and the Caribbean: A Review of Disease Burden and Distribution and a Roadmap for Control and Elimination. PLoS Negl Trop Dis 2 9: e300 doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000300">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000300</ext-link> 18820747 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Satoskar1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>2Satoskar AR, Simon GL, Hotez PJ, Tsuji M (2009) Medical Parasitology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Austin, Texas: Landes Bioscience. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>297p. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Menezes1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>3 MenezesC, CostaGC, GollobKJ, DutraWO (2011) Clinical aspects of Chagas disease and implications for novel therapies. Drug Dev Res 72: 471–479.22267887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Wilkinson1"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>4 WilkinsonSR, TaylorMC, HornD, KellyJM, CheesemanI (2008) A mechanism for cross-resistance to nifurtimox and benznidazole in trypanosomes. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 105: 5022–5027.18367671 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Rassi1"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>5 RassiAJr, RassiA, MarinJA (2010) Chagas disease. Lancet 375: 1388–1402.20399979 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Kappagoda1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>6 KappagodaS, SinghU, BlackburnBG (2011) Antiparasitic therapy. Mayo Clin Proc 86: 561–583.21628620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-FreitasJunior1"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>7 Freitas-JuniorLH, Hernandez-RivasR, RalphSA, Montiel-CondadoD, Ruvalcaba-SalazarOK, et al (2005) Telomeric Heterochromatin Propagation and Histone Acetylation Control Mutually Exclusive Expression of Antigenic Variation Genes in Malaria Parasites. Cell 121: 25–36.15820676 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Petter1"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>8 PetterM, LeeCC, ByrneTJ, BoysenKE, VolzJ, et al (2011) Expression of P. falciparum var Genes Involves Exchange of the Histone Variant H2A.Z at the Promoter. PLoS Pathog 7 2: e1001292 doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1001292">10.1371/journal.ppat.1001292</ext-link> 21379342 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Silvestre1"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>9 SilvestreR, Cordeiro-Da-SilvaA, TavaresJ, SerenoD, OuaissiA (2006) Leishmania cytosolic silent information regulatory protein 2 deacetylase induces murine B-cell differentiation and in vivo production of specific antibodies. Immunology 119: 529–540.17026719 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Silvestre2"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>10 SilvestreR, SilvaAM, Cordeiro-Da-SilvaA, OuaissiA (2009) The contribution of Toll-like receptor 2 to the innate recognition of a Leishmania infantum silent information regulator 2 protein. Immunology 128: 484–499.19930041 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Vergnes1"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>11 VergnesB, SerenoD, TavaresJ, Cordeiro-Da-SilvaA, VanhilleL, et al (2005) Targeted disruption of cytosolic SIR2 deacetylase discloses its essential role in Leishmania survival and proliferation. Gene 363: 85–96.16236469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Merrick1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>12 MerrickCJ, HuttenhowerC, BuckeeC, Amambua-NgwaA, Gomez-EscobarN, et al (2012) Epigenetic Dysregulation of Virulence Gene Expression in Severe Plasmodium falciparum Malaria. J Inf Dis 205: 1593–1600.22448008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Alsford1"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>13 AlsfordS, KawaharaT, IsamahC, HornD (2007) A sirtuin in the African trypanosome is involved in both DNA repair and telomeric gene silencing but is not required for antigenic variation. Mol Microbio 63: 724–736. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-GarcaSalcedo1"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>14 García-SalcedoJA, GijónP, NolanDP, TebabiP, PaysE (2003) A chromosomal SIR2 homologue with both histone NAD-dependent ADP-ribosyltransferase and deacetylase activities is involved in DNA repair in Trypanosoma brucei . EMBO J 22: 5851–5862.14592982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Zheng1"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>15 ZhengW (2013) Sirtuins as emerging anti-parasitic targets. Eur J Med Chem 59: 132–140.23220641 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Religa1"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>16 ReligaAA, WatersAP (2012) Sirtuins of parasitic protozoa: In search of function(s). Mol Biochem Parasitol 185: 71–88.22906508 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-DaliYoucef1"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>17 Dali-YoucefN, LagougeM, FroelichS, KoehlC, SchoonjansK, et al (2007) Sirtuins: The “magnificent seven”, function, metabolism and longevity. Ann Med 39: 335–345.17701476 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Soares1"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>18 SoaresMBP, SilvaCV, BastosTM, GuimarãesET, FigueiraCP, et al (2012) Anti-Trypanosoma cruzi activity of nicotinamide. Acta Tropica 122: 224–229.22281243 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Buck1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>19 BuckSW, GalloCM, SmithJS (2004) Diversity in the Sir2 family of protein deacetylases. J Leukocyte Biol 75: 939–950.14742637 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Marmorstein1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>20 MarmorsteinR (2004) Structure and chemistry of the Sir2 family of NAD+-dependent histone/protein deactylases. Biochem Soc Trans 32: 904–909.15506920 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Finnin1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>21 FinninMS, DonigianJR, PavletichNP (2001) Structure of the histone deacetylase SIRT2. Nat Struct Biol 8: 621–625.11427894 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Moniot1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>22 MoniotS, SchutkowskiM, SteegbornC (2013) Crystal structure analysis of human Sirt2 and its ADP-ribose complex. J Struct Biol 182: 136–143.23454361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Kadam1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>23 KadamRU, KiranVM, RoyN (2006) Comparative protein modeling and surface analysis of Leishmania sirtuin: A potential target for antileishmanial drug discovery. Bioorg Med Chem Lett 16: 6013–6018.16982188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Kaur1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>24 KaurS, ShivangeA, RoyN (2010) Structural analysis of trypanosomal sirtuin: an insight for selective drug design. Mol Diversity 14: 169–178. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Sakkiah1"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>25 SakkiahS, ThangapandianS, ParkC, SonM, LeeKW (2012) Molecular Docking and Dynamics Simulation, Receptor-based Hypothesis: Application to Identify Novel Sirtuin 2 Inhibitors. Chem Biol Drug Des 80: 315–327.22564257 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Kayser1"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>26 KayserO, KiderlenAF, CroftSL (2003) Natural products as antiparasitic drugs. Parasitol Res 90: S55–S62.12937967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Izumi1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>27 IzumiE, Ueda-NakamuraT, Dias FilhoBP, Veiga JúniorVF, NakamuraCV (2011) Natural products and Chagas' disease: a review of plant compounds studied for activity against Trypanosoma cruzi . Nat Prod Rep 28: 809–823.21290079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Kelly1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>28Kelly K (2013) Multiple sequence and structure alignment in MOE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Chem Comput Group 1–5. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Kelly2"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>29Kelly K, Labute P (2013) The A* search and applicatins to sequence alignment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Chem Comput Group 4. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Kelly3"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>30Kelly K (2013) 3D bioinformatics and comparative protein modeling in MOE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Chem Comput Group 1–10. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Levitt1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>31 LevittM (1992) Accurate modeling of protein conformation by automatic segment matching. J Mol Biol 226: 507–533.1640463 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Clark1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>32 ClarkM, Cramer IIIRD, Van OpdenboschN (1989) Validation of the general purpose Tripos 5.2 force field. J Comput Chem 10: 982–1012. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Zhao1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>33 ZhaoX, AllisonD, CondonB, ZhangF, GheyiT, et al (2013) The 2.5 A Crystal Structure of the SIRT1 Catalytic Domain Bound to Nicotinamide Adenine Dinucleotide (NAD+) and an Indole (EX527 Analogue) Reveals a Novel Mechanism of Histone Deacetylase Inhibition. J Med Chem 56: 963–969.23311358 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Grozinger1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>34 GrozingerCM, ChaoED, BlackwellHE, MoazedD, SchreiberSL (2001) Identification of a Class of Small Molecule Inhibitors of the Sirtuin Family of NAD-dependent Deacetylases by Phenotypic Screening. J Biol Chem 276: 38837–38843.11483616 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Outeiro1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>35 OuteiroTF, KontopoulosE, AltmannSM, KufarevaI, StrathearnKE, et al (2007) Sirtuin 2 inhibitors rescue a-Synuclein-mediated toxicity in models of Parkinson's disease. Science 317: 516–519.17588900 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Rogers1"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>36 RogersD, HahnM (2010) Extended-connectivity fingerprints. J Chem Inf Model 50: 742–754.20426451 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Landrum1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>37 LandrumG (2013) RDKit Documentation. Release 2013.03.1: 1–79. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Jones1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>38Jones, E., Oliphant, T., and Peterson, P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>(2001) SciPy: Open source scientific tools for Python. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scipy.org/">http://www.scipy.org/</ext-link> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scipy.org/Citing_SciPy">http://www.scipy.org/Citing_SciPy</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Hunter1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>39 HunterJD (2007) Matplotlib: A 2D graphics environment. Comput Sci Engin 9: 90–95. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Sacconnay1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>40 SacconnayL, SmirilisD, Ferreira-QueirozE, WolfenderJL, SoaresM, et al (2013) Structural Insights of SIR2rp3 Proteins as Promising Biotargets to Fight Against Chagas Disease and Leishmaniasis. Mol Biosyst 9: 2223–2230.23799611 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Maurer1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>41 MaurerB, RumpfT, ScharfeM, StolfaDA, SchmittML, et al (2012) Inhibitors of the NAD+-Dependent Protein Desuccinylase and Demalonylase Sirt5. ACS Med Chem Lett 3: 1050–1053.24900427 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Andrews1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>42 AndrewsKT, HaqueA, JonesMK (2012) HDAC inhibitors in parasitic diseases. Immunol Cell Biol 90: 66–77.22124373 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Avalos1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>43 AvalosJL, BeverKM, WolbergerC (2005) Mechanism of Sirtuin Inhibition by Nicotinamide: Altering the NAD(+) Cosubstrate Specificity of a Sir2 Enzyme. Mol Cell 17: 855–868.15780941 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Lawson1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>44 LawsonM, UciechowskaU, SchemiesJ, RumpfT, JungM, et al (2010) Inhibitors to understand molecular mechanisms of NAD+-dependent deacetylases (sirtuins). Biochim Biophys Acta 1799: 726–739.20601279 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Ogungbe1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>45 OgungbeIV, SetzerWN (2009) Comparative Molecular Docking of Antitrypanosomal Natural Products into Multiple Trypanosoma brucei Drug Targets. Molecules 14: 1513–1536.19384282 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Setzer1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>46 SetzerWN, OgungbeIV (2012)  In-silico Investigation of Antitrypanosomal Phytochemicals from Nigerian Medicinal Plants. PLoS Negl Trop Dis 6 7: e1727 doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0001727">10.1371/journal.pntd.0001727</ext-link> 22848767 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Goodford1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>47 GoodfordPJ (1985) A Computational Procedure for Determining Energetically Favorable Binding Sites on Biologically Important Macromolecules. J Med Chem 28: 849–857.3892003 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Newman1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>48 NewmanJC, HeW, VerdinE (2012) Mitochondrial Protein Acylation and Intermediary Metabolism: Regulation by Sirtuins and Implications for Metabolic Disease. J Biol Chem 287: 42436–42443.23086951 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Castrignan1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>49 CastrignanòT, D'Onorio De MeoP, CozzettoD, TalamoIG, TramontanoA (2006) The PMDB protein model database. Nucl Acids Res 34: D306–D309.16381873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Senn1"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>50 SennM, GunzenhauserS, BrunR, SequinU (2007) Antiprotozoal Polyacetylenes from the Tanzanian Medicinal Plant Cussonia zimmermannii . J Nat Prod 70: 1565–1569.17922552 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-CardonaZuleta1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>51 Cardona ZuletaLM, CavalheiroAJ, Siqueira SilvaDH, FurlanM, Marx YoungMC, et al (2003)  seco-Iridoids from Calycophyllum spruceanum (Rubiaceae). Phytochemistry 64: 549–553.12943773 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Wright1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>52 WrightAD, PapendorfO, KönigGM (2005) Ambigol C and 2,4-Dichlorobenzoic Acid, Natural Products Produced by the Terrestrial Cyanobacterium Fischerella ambigua . J Nat Prod 68: 459–461.15787461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Freitas1"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>53 FreitasRF, ProkopczykIM, ZottisA, OlivaG, AndricopuloAD, et al (2009) Discovery of novel Trypanosoma cruzi glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase inhibitors. Bioorg Med Chem 17: 2476–2482.19254846 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Bringmann1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>54 BringmannG, ZhangG, ÖlschlägerT, StichA, WuJ, et al (2012) Highly selective antiplasmodial naphthylisoquinoline alkaloids from Ancistrocladus tectorius . Phytochemistry 91: 220–228.22459968 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Bringmann2"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>55 BringmannG, WohlfarthM, RischerH, SchlauerJ, BrunR (2002) Extract screening by HPLC coupled to MS-MS, NMR, and CD: a dimeric and three monomeric naphthylisoquinoline alkaloids from Ancistrocladus griffithii . Phytochemistry 61: 195–204.12169315 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Tasdemir1"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>56 TasdemirD, GünerND, PerozzoR, BrunR, DönmezAA, et al (2005) Anti-protozoal and plasmodial FabI enzyme inhibiting metabolites of Scrophularia lepidota roots. Phytochemistry 66: 355–362.15680992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Fournet1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>57 FournetA, FerreiraME, Rojas de AriasA, GuyI, GuinaudeauH, et al (2007) Phytochemical and antiprotozoal activity of Ocotea lancifolia . Fitoterapia 78: 382–384.17499454 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Grael1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>58 GraelCFF, AlbuquerqueS, LopesJLC (2005) Chemical constituents of Lychnophora pohlii and trypanocidal activity of crude plant extracts and of isolated compounds. Fitoterapia 76: 73–82.15664466 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Pontius1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>59 PontiusAl, KrickA, KehrausS, BrunR, KoenigGM (2008) Antiprotozoal Activities of Heterocyclic-Substituted Xanthones from the Marine-Derived Fungus Chaetomium sp . J Nat Prod 71: 1579–1584.18683985 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Ramrez1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>60 RamírezI, CarabotA, MeléndezP, CarmonaJ, JimenezM, et al (2003) Cissampeloflavone, a chalcone-flavone dimer from Cissampelos pareira . Phytochemistry 64: 645–647.12943789 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Hay1"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>61 HayAE, IosetJR, AhuaKM, DialloD, BrunR, et al (2007) Limonoid Orthoacetates and Antiprotozoal Compounds from the Roots of Pseudocedrela kotschyi . J Nat Prod 70: 9–13.17253841 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Tarus1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>62 TarusPK, MachochoAK, Lang'at-ThoruwaCC, ChhabraSC (2002) Flavonoids from Tephrosia aequilata . Phytochemistry 60: 375–379.12031428 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Marcucci1"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>63 MarcucciMC, FerreresF, García-VigueraC, BankovaVS, De CastroSL, et al (2001) Phenolic compounds from Brazilian propolis with pharmacological activities. J Ethnopharmacol 74: 105–112.11167028 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-ErosaRejn1"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>64 Erosa-RejónGJ, Yam-PucA, Chan-BacabMJ, Giménez-TurbaxAl, SalamancaE, et al (2010) Benzochromenes from the roots of Bourreria pulchra . Phytochem Lett 3: 9–12. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Alves1"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>65 AlvesTMA, ChavesPPG, SantosLMST, NagemTJ, MurtaSMF, et al (1995) A Diterpene from Mikania obtusata Active on Trypanosoma cruzi . Planta Med 61: 85–87.7701002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Mbwambo1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>66 MbwamboZH, KapinguMC, MoshiMJ, MachumiF, ApersS, et al (2006) Antiparasitic Activity of Some Xanthones and Biflavonoids from the Root Bark of Garcinia livingstonei . J Nat Prod 69: 369–372.16562837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Paveto1"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>67 PavetoC, GüidaM, EstevaMI, MartinoV, CoussioJ, FlawiáMM, et al (2004) Anti-Trypanosoma cruzi activity of green tea (Camellia sinensis) catechins. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 48: 69–74.14693520 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Ferreira1"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>68 FerreiraME, Rojas de AriasA, YaluffG, de BilbaoNV, NakayamaH, et al (2010) Antileishmanial activity of furoquinolines and coumarins from Helietta apiculata . Phytomedicine 17: 375–378.19879121 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Abe1"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>69 AbeF, NagafujiS, OkabeH, HigoH, AkahaneH (2003) Trypanocidal Constituents in Plants 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Xanthones from the Stem Bark of Garcinia subelliptica . Biol Pharm Bull 26: 1730–1733.14646180 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-MennaBarreto1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>70 Menna-BarretoRFS, LaranjaGAT, SilvaMCC, CoelhoMGP, PaesMC, et al (2008) Anti-Trypanosoma cruzi activity of Pterodon pubescens seed oil: geranylgeraniol as the major bioactive component. Parasitol Res 103: 111–117.18343952 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Kaya1"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>71 KayaGI, SarikayaB, OnurMA, SomerNU, ViladomatF, et al (2011) Antiprotozoal alkaloids from Galanthus trojanus . Phytochem Lett 4: 301–305. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Schmidt1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>72 SchmidtTJ, BrunR, WilluhnG, KhalidSA (2002) Anti-trypanosomal Activity of Helenalin and Some Structurally Related Sesquiterpene Lactones. Planta Med 68: 750–751.12221603 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Karioti1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>73 KariotiA, SkaltsaH, KaiserM, TasdemirD (2009) Trypanocidal, leishmanicidal and cytotoxic effects of anthecotulide-type linear sesquiterpene lactones from Anthemis auriculata . Phytomedicine 16: 783–787.19200703 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Tasdemir2"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>74 TasdemirD, KaiserM, BrunR, YardleyV, SchmidtTJ, et al (2006) Antitrypanosomal and Antileishmanial Activities of Flavonoids and their Analogues: In vitro, In vivo, Structure-Activity Relationship, and Quantitative Structure-Activity Relationship Studies. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 50: 1352–1364.16569852 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Ambrozin1"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>75 AmbrozinARP, MafezoliJ, VieiraPC, FernandesJB, da SilvaMFDF, et al (2005) New pyrone and quinoline alkaloid from Almeidea rubra and their trypanocidal activity. J Braz Chem Soc 16: 434–439. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Heilmann1"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>76 HeilmannJ, BrunR, MayrS, RaliT, SticherO (2001) Minor cytotoxic and antibacterial compounds from the rhizomes of Amomum aculeatum . Phytochemistry 57: 1281–1285.11454360 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Uchiyama1"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>77 UchiyamaN, KiuchiF, ItoM, HondaG, TakedaY, et al (2006) Trypanocidal constituents of Dracocephalum komarovi . Tetrahedron 62: 4355–4359. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-daSilvaFilho1"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>78 da Silva FilhoAA, BuenoPCP, GregórioLE, SilvaMLA, AlbuquerqueS, et al (2004) In-vitro trypanocidal activity evaluation of crude extract and isolated compounds from Baccharis dracunculifolia D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>(Asteraceae). J Pharm Pharmacol 56: 1195–1199.15324490 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Bastos1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>79 BastosJK, AlbuquerqueS, SilvaMLA (1999) Evaluation of the Trypanocidal Activity of Lignans Isolated from the Leaves of Zanthoxylum naranjillo . Planta Med 65: 541–544.10483375 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Bringmann3"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>80 BringmannG, Hertlein-AmslingerB, KajahnI, DreyerM, BrunR, et al (2011) Phenolic analogs of the N,C-coupled naphthylisoquinoline alkaloid ancistrocladinium A, from Ancistrocladus cochinchinensis (Ancistrocladaceae), with improved antiprotozoal activities. Phytochemistry 72: 89–93.21047659 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Izumi2"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>81 IzumiE, MorelloLG, Ueda-NakamuraT, Yamada-OgattaSF, FilhoBPD, et al (2008)  Trypanosoma cruzi: Antiprotozoal activity of parthenolide obtained from Tanacetum parthenium (L.) Schultz Bip. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>(Asteraceae, Compositae) against epimastigote and amastigote forms. Exp Parasitol 118: 324–330.17950283 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Abegaz1"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>82 AbegazBM, BezabihM, MsutaT, BrunR, MencheD, et al (2002) Gaboroquinones A and B and 4′-O-Demethylknipholone-4′-O-β-D-glucopyranoside, Phenylanthraquinones from the Roots of Bulbine frutescens . J Nat Prod 65: 1117–1121.12193014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Ribeiro1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>83 RibeiroTS, Freire-de-LimaL, PreviatoJO, Mendonça-PreviatoL, HeiseN, et al (2004) Toxic effects of natural piperine and its derivatives on epimastigotes and amastigotes of Trypanosoma cruzi . Bioorg Med Chem Lett 14: 3555–3558.15177472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Moretti1"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>84 MorettiC, SauvainM, LavaudC, MassiotG, BravoJA, et al (1998) A novel antiprotozoal aminosteroid from Saracha punctata . J Nat Prod 61: 1390–1393.9834160 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Matsuo1"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>85 MatsuoK, ItoM, HondaG, QuiTK, KiuchiF (2003) Trypanocidal flavonoids from Sophora flavescens . Nat Med 57: 253–255. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Fournet2"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>86 FournetA, FerreiraME, deAriasAR, deOrtizST, InchaustiA, et al (1997) Activity of Compounds Isolated from Chilean lichens Against Experimental Cutaneous Leishmaniasis. Comp Biochem Physiol 116: 51–54. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-DeCarvalho1"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>87 De CarvalhoEAB, AndradePP, SilvaNH, PereiraEC, FigueiredoRCBQ (2005) Effect of usnic acid from the lichen Cladonia substellata on Trypanosoma cruzi in vitro: an ultrastructural study. Micron 36: 155–161.15629646 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pntd.0002689-Mbwambo2"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>88 MbwamboZH, ApersS, MoshiMJ, KapinguMC, Van MiertS, et al (2004) Anthranoid Compounds with Antiprotozoal Activity from Vismia orientalis . Planta Med 70: 706–710.15368649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
