
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3203153</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22046296</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-09088</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0026502</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microarrays</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene expression</subject><subj-group><subject>DNA transcription</subject><subject>RNA interference</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics of Disease</subject><subject>Genome-Wide Association Studies</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cancers and Neoplasms</subject><subj-group><subject>Lung and Intrathoracic Tumors</subject><subj-group><subject>Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>An Integrated Analysis of miRNA and mRNA Expressions in Non-Small Cell Lung Cancers </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Integrated RNA Analysis of NSCLC</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Lina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Yanyan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Wangyu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Shiquan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Jihang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Fang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Xiaoguang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yongkui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Jun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Joint Laboratory of Immunogenomics, Zhoushan Hospital-BIGCAS, Zhejiang, People's Republic of China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>CAS Key Laboratory of Genome Sciences and Information, Beijing Institute of Genomics, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, People's Republic of China</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Zhivotovsky</surname><given-names>Boris</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Karolinska Institutet, Sweden</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>lxg2004@gmail.com</email> (XL); <email>yongkuizhang53@163.com</email> (YZ); <email>junyu@big.ac.cn</email> (JY)</corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: LM XL YZ JY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: LM YH WZ SZ JZ FZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: LM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: LM JY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Directed the analyzation work: JY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Contributed materials and reagents: YZ XL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e26502</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Ma et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Using DNA microarrays, we generated both mRNA and miRNA expression data from 6 non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) tissues and their matching normal control from adjacent tissues to identify potential miRNA markers for diagnostics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>We demonstrated that hsa-miR-96 is significantly and consistently up-regulated in all 6 NSCLCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>We validated this result in an independent set of 35 paired tumors and their adjacent normal tissues, as well as their sera that are collected before surgical resection or chemotherapy, and the results suggested that hsa-miR-96 may play an important role in NSCLC development and has great potential to be used as a noninvasive marker for diagnosing NSCLC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>We predicted potential miRNA target mRNAs based on different methods (TargetScan and miRanda). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Further classification of miRNA regulated genes based on their relationship with miRNAs revealed that hsa-miR-96 and certain other miRNAs tend to down-regulate their target mRNAs in NSCLC development, which have expression levels permissive to direct interaction between miRNAs and their target mRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In addition, we identified a significant correlation of miRNA regulation with genes coincide with high density of CpG islands, which suggests that miRNA may represent a primary regulatory mechanism governing basic cellular functions and cell differentiations, and such mechanism may be complementary to DNA methylation in repressing or activating gene expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Currently, non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) is the leading cause of cancer death in the world[1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Surgical resection is mainly performed in early-stage cases and is also effective, but its effect is limited for patients with locally advanced cancers because of the high rate of distant metastasis and recurrence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Thus, chemotherapy and radiation therapy, as well as a combination of both, are always performed in the treatment of patients with locally advanced cancers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>However, the 5-year survival rate of lung cancer patients decreases dramatically with clinical stages of the disease, for instance, from an estimated 61% for patients with the stage IA disease to 38% for patients with the stage IB disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Other stage-related 5-year survival rate of the disease are 34% for patients with IIA disease, 13% for patients with stage IIIA disease, 5% for patients with stage IIIB disease, and 1% for patients with stage IV [2], [3], [4], [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Most lung cancer patients are only diagnosed after tumors have spread beyond their primary sites, and this is an important reason for the poor outcome of lung cancer treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>In addition, variation analysis among a variety of cancers suggested that lung cancer has larger number of mutated genes than other cancers [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the discovery of effective diagnostic markers and interrogating mechanisms of lung cancer development, are both necessary for improving the survival rate of lung cancer patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>miRNAs are short non-coding RNAs (∼22 nt long) that bind complementary sequences in target mRNAs, resulting in their selective degradation or selective inhibition of translation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Therefore, through regulating their target genes, miRNAs are known to be involved in a wide range of biological functions, such as cellular proliferation, differentiation, and apoptosis [7], [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Aberrant miRNAs expression has been reported to cause diseases, such as cancers [9], Alzheimer's disease [10], heart diseases [11], spinal motor neuron anomalies [12], and etc.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In NSCLC, it has been suggested that miR-31 may act as an oncogenic miRNA by repressing tumor suppressors: LATS2 and PPP2R2A [13], and expression of hsa-miR-205 has been suggested to be able to distinguish squamous from nonsquamous non-small-cell lung carcinoma [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In addition, evidences show that high hsa-mir-155 and low hsa-let-7a-2 expression correlated with poor survival of lung cancer patients [15], and has-miRNA-126 may promote NSCLC cells apoptosis induced by irradiation through the PI3K-Akt pathway [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>miRNAs are now emerging as highly tissue-specific biomarkers for discriminate cancers from noncancerous tissue, and different cancer types, as well as different prognostic results [15], [17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>mRNA profiling have revealed that transcriptional abnormality of many genes are responsible for the development of NSCLC [18], [19], and differential expression of miRNAs also have been detected between lung cancer tissues and the adjacent normal tissues [15], [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we used microarrays to measure the expression levels of miRNAs and mRNAs simultaneously in paired NSCLC and their adjacent normal tissues to investigate possible roles of miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Our analyses are both integrated and rather deep in search for possible candidate miRNAs and their mRNA targets for further investigations and clinical applications. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Differentially expressed mRNAs in NSCLC tissues compared with their paired normal tissues </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>We performed gene expression profiling for paired tumor-normal tissue samples from 6 NSCLC patients and investigated 34,694 genes/transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>We defined 581 up-regulated genes and 1, 297 down-regulated genes which were consistently up- or down-regulated in all 6 tumor tissues compared with the adjacent normal tissues (Table S2 and Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Among differentially expressed genes, we identified 2 significantly up-regulated and 22 significantly down-regulated genes at a False Discovery Rate (FDR) of 0.1 (Table S2 and Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>We subsequently performed GO enrichment analysis using hypergeometric test and multiple test adjustment method BH through WebGestalt2 [21] and defined the enriched pathways at a p value of &lt;0.001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The hypergeometric distribution is a discrete probability distribution that describes the number of successes in a sequence of n draws from a finite population without replacement, just as the binomial distribution describes the number of successes for draws with replacement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Hypergeometric test helps to find which GO terms are overrepresented in a large gene list. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>According to hypergeometric test results, the cell cycle M-phase and DNA metabolic process were predominantly activated, whereas pathways involved in immune functions were significantly repressed in NSCLC (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In addition, up-regulated genes were predominantly enriched in “chromosome” as opposed to down-regulated genes that were predominantly enriched in “cell membrane” (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0026502-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0026502.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Enriched GO terms for biological process based on variable genes in lung cancer tissues when compared with their adjacent normal tissues. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0026502-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0026502.t001"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>*The alst column lists the number of reference genes in the category (C), number of genes in the gene set and also in the category (O), expected number in the category (E), Ratio of enrichment (R), p value from hypergeometric test (rawP), and p value adjusted by the multiple test adjustment (adjP). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0026502-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0026502.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Enriched GO terms for cellular components based on variable genes in lung cancer tissues when compared with their adjacent normal tissues. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0026502-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0026502.t002"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>*The last column lists the number of reference genes in the category (C), number of genes in the gene set and also in the category (O), expected number in the category (E), Ratio of enrichment (R), p value from hypergeometric test (rawP), and p value adjusted based on the multiple test adjustment (adjP). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Differentially expressed miRNAs in NSCLC tissues compared with their paired normal tissues </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>We performed miRNA expression profiling using the same 6 paired samples of the primary tumor and its adjacent normal tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>We obtained 25 up-regulated and 24 down-regulated miRNAs which were consistently up- or down-regulated in all 6 tumor tissues compared with the adjacent normal tissues before significance test (Table S4 and Table S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Based on a more stringent analysis, we obtained a single significantly up-regulated miRNA, hsa-miR-96, at a False Discovery Rate (FDR) of 0.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>We further examined the expression level of its potential mRNA targets (These targets have conserved miRNA binding sites among vertebrates or mammals and were predicted using TargetScan): 13 out of 728 total candidate target genes (Table S2 and Table S6) (account for 2.24% of the 581 up-regulated genes) were up-regulated and 48 out of the total (Table S3 and Table S6) (account for 3.70% of the 1, 297 down-regulated genes) were down-regulated (Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>We then validated hsa-miR-96 expression based on quantitative RT-PCR in an independent set of 35 NSCLC and their serum samples (for the sera, expression values were normalized to normal people without cancer history or other illness at that time), and found hsa-miR-96 was significantly up-regulated in both tissue and serum samples from NSCLC patients (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Therefore, hsa-miR-96 may be an important factor to contribute to NSCLC development and may have great potential to be used for diagnosing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0026502-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0026502.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated target candidates of hsa-miR-96 in NSCLC. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>(A) Microarray results of the Down-regulated target candidates of hsa-miR-96 in NSCLC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>We assayed 6 paired NSCLC vs. normal tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>C and N stand for cancer and adjacent normal tissue, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The asterisk marks genes belong to the correlated group and the remaining genes are grouped into the anti-correlated group according to the expression relationship of these genes with their regulatory miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>(B) Validation of microarray results by qRT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>We selected 10 down-regulated target candidates of hsa-miR-96 and performed qRT-PCR experiments for the validation of relative mRNA expression in reference to glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The relative expression values are the means ± SE. *, P&lt;0.05 by t test; **, P&lt;0.001 by t test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0026502.g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0026502-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0026502.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Quantitative RT-PCR analysis of hsa-miR-96 expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Two groups of comparisons were performed: (1) tumor vs. adjacent normal lung tissues, and (2) cancer serum vs. non-cancer serum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Relative hsa-miR-96 expression was determined in reference to an internal U6 snRNA control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Relative expression values are the normalized mean ± SE. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0026502.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>As miRNAs always repress the expression of the target genes, the 48 down-regulated targets of hsa-miR-96 may be most likely to contribute to NSCLC development through hsa-miR-96 regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>We selected 10 down-regulated targets of hsa-miR-96 to validate their mRNA expression levels using qRT-PCR in 20 NSCLC and found that all of them were significantly down-regulated in tumor tissues when compared with the adjacent normal tissues (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>To investigate how these 48 down-regulated potential mRNA targets may affect the development of NSCLC, we classified them based on GO terms, and found that these genes were involved in a variety of basic biological process, including metabolism, biological regulation, cell communication, developmental process, immune system, and etc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>(Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Classification of mRNAs based on their relationship with miRNA regulation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>To characterize how miRNAs may regulate their target mRNAs, we performed an extensive analysis on the correlated expression of miRNAs and their target mRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>miRNAs are expressed as long precursor RNAs that are processed by a cellular nuclease, Drosha, before being transported by an Exportin-5-dependent mechanism into the cytoplasm [22], [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Once in the cytoplasm, miRNAs are cleaved further by the enzyme DICER [24], [25], and this results in 17–24 nt miRNAs that are associated with a cellular complex that is similar to the RNA-induced silencing complex that participates in RNA interference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>However, miRNAs mainly regulate mRNA translation, whereas siRNAs direct RNA destruction via the RNA interference (RNAi) pathway [8], [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the abundance of miRNAs may mainly depend on its original expression and not imported exogenously. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>In addition, several lines of evidence suggest that elevation of miRNA expression lead to down-regulation of the target genes, and reduction of miRNA expression lead to up-regulation of the target genes [13], [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>We therefore hypothesize that the effect of miRNAs on their target mRNAs is expression level-dependent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>We used a novel measure to evaluate miRNA regulation, termed regulation value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>We first assume that a regulation value of a miRNA is positively correlated with its expression level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Since a miRNA always has more than one target genes [28], we then assume that a regulation value of a given miRNA is negatively correlated with the number of its targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we define a regulation value for miRNA as the deviation in expression level for a given miRNA divided by the number of expressed mRNA targets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>During cancer development, the regulation may vary from case to control for a given miRNA and, therefore, regulation value of a given miRNA equals to the variation of miRNA expression divided by the number of expressed targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>When the expression of a miRNA is down-regulated in cancers, its regulation value becomes negative if the number of its expressed targets is not changed significantly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>For a target mRNA, its regulation value is the sum of all regulation values from its regulatory miRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Based on these definitions, we classified all differentially expressed genes in cancers into different groups based on their correlations—correlated or anti-correlated with miRNA regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Before doing this, we predicted the potential target genes of these consistently up- or down-regulated miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>We used three methods to predict the potential targets of miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The software TargetScan focuses more on miRNA seed (2-8nt in the 5′ region of mature miRNA), as evidence suggests the importance of this region for miRNA target recognition [29], [30], [31], [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>In addition, the sequence conservation of target sites has been considered as an important feature to reduce false-positive rate [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>We therefore predicted potential miRNA targets using TargetScan and conserved target sites among vertebrates or mammals using P CT method of TargetScan [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>However, seed sites do not always confer repression, and the software miRanda also takes into consideration of other region of miRNA in addition to seed sites [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>We then used miRanda as another alternative method to predict miRNA targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The two software were frequently used to predict miRNA targets, and in addition, both of them can be used to predict targets of novel miRNAs as the illuminia miRNA microarray "humanMI_V2" contains many novel miRNAs that are generated from next-generation sequencing efforts worldwide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>We obtained 16,160 conserved miRNA-target pairs among vertebrates or mammals using P CT method of TargetScan (Table S6), 70,320 miRNA-target pairs by using TargetScan without considering the conservation condition (Table S8), and 77,988 miRNA-target pairs by using miRanda (Table S10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>We observed that 48,841 miRNA-target pairs were present in both TargetScan and miRanda results (69.46% of TargetScan results, 62.63% of miRanda results), and 12,403 miRNA-target pairs of conserved TargetScan results were common with miRanda results (76.75% of conserved TargetScan results). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Therefore, there were about 70% prediction results that were common in the two different methods, and conserved prediction results of TargetScan exhibite a larger proportion of shared genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>We firstly used the conserved prediction results to classify mRNAs based on their relationship with miRNA regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>In particular, we defined 197 and 190 genes as anti-correlated and correlated, respectively, and 1,491 as “others”, whose miRNA regulation values are null (Table S7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>We further investigated the distribution of miRNA regulation value, gene expression level and the potential relationship between these two parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>In the 197 anti-correlated genes, 171 (account for 13.18% of 1, 297 down-regulated genes) were down-regulated and 26 (account for 4.48% of 581 up-regulated genes) were up-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Gene distribution based on the regulation value also suggested that the anti-correlated group were always down-regulated by miRNAs (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>In the 190 correlated genes, 140 (account for 10.79% of 1, 297 down-regulated genes) were down-regulated and 50 (account for 8.61% of 581 up-regulated genes) were up-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Gene distribution based on the regulation value suggested that the correlated group were always down-regulated (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>For 1,491 genes in “others”, 986 (account for 76.02% of 1,297 down-regulated genes) were down-regulated and 505 (account for 86.92% of 581 up-regulated genes) were up-regulated (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, these results indicate that miRNAs tend to down-regulate gene expression, especially for those of the anti-correlated group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>We also investigated potential functions of the anti-correlated group, which were supposed to be regulated by miRNAs, and found they were involved in a variety of biological processes, including metabolism, immune systems, cell killing, multicellular organismal development, and cell communication (Figure S3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0026502-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0026502.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>miRNA regulation analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>We classified all expression-variable mRNAs during lung cancer development based on their relationship with miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The results are classified into correlated, anti-correlated, and others (no correlation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The correlated mRNAs show correlated expressions to their regulatory miRNA expressions and the anti-correlated mRNAs are not. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Three different methods were used to predict potential miRNA targets: “Conserved” are those genes that have conserved miRNA binding sites among vertebrates or mammals, and these genes were predicted by using the P CT method of TargetScan; “TargetScan” are those genes that are predicted by using a perl script of TargetScan without considering conservation. “miRanda” are those genes that are predicted potential targets based on miRanda v3.3a on Linux platform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>(A) Gene distribution of the correlated and anti-correlated mRNAs was plotted based on their miRNA regulation values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>(B) Gene distribution of the three groups of mRNAs was plotted based on their expression values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The expression value was defined by referencing that of the adjacent normal tissue (log2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>(C) The relationship between gene expression and miRNA regulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0026502.g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0026502-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0026502.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Three groups of mRNAs predicted with different methods. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0026502-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0026502.t003"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>*The proportion was calculated by dividing the number of all up-regulated mRNAs or down-regulated mRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>We further verified this result using predictions of TargetScan without considering sequence conservation and predictions of miRanda. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Using miRanda, we have 482 and 294 genes as anti-correlated and correlated, respectively, and 1,102 as “others”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Using TargetScan without considering conservation, we have 472 and 285 genes as the anti-correlated and correlated, respectively, and 1,121 as “others”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>We further investigated the intersection between TargetScan and miRanda, and found that the three methods shared about 80% in the anti-correlated group; TargetScan and miRanda shared about 70% genes in the correlated group, while P CT method shared only about 50% genes with the remaining two methods in the correlated group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Consistent with the results of conserved predictions, miRNAs in the anti-correlated group seem regulate higher proportion of down-regulated mRNAs as compared to the remaining groups defined based on the following two methods (Table 3), and the anti-correlated group exhibited strikingly different distribution of regulation value as compared to the correlated group (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>We then examined target expression level of the three regulation groups and found that expression level of the anti-correlated group was higher than the remaining groups (Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Further investigation of regulation values with the expression level showed that highly-expressed genes in the anti-correlated group tended to be down-regulated by miRNAs, whereas lowly-expressed genes tended to be up-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Genes in the correlated group behave in the opposite way (Figure 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>This result suggested that highly expressed genes may contribute more to down-regulated genes in anti-correlated group than to up-regulated genes in the same group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Potential relationship of miRNAs with methylation in regulating mRNA expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>As methylation is another important mechanism to regulate mRNA expression, we further studied how it may interact with miRNA regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>We first categorized the target genes into HCG (high CpG content), LCG (intermediate CpG content), and ICG (low CpG content) classes (Table S2 and Table S3) according a method previously described [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>We found that in the conserved prediction results, both the anti-correlated and correlated groups contained more HCG genes than others or all genes (Figure 4A), and the result suggests that HCG genes are most likely to be regulated by miRNAs that have conserved target sites. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0026502-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0026502.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Potential relationship between miRNA and DNA methylation. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>(A) The distribution of CpG-density classified genes in each group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>These target genes were predicted using three different methods: “Conserved” are those genes that have conserved miRNA binding sites among vertebrates or mammals, and these genes were predicted by using the P CT method of TargetScan; “TargetScan” are those genes that are predicted by using a perl script of TargetScan without considering conservation. “miRanda” are those genes that are predicted potential targets based on miRanda v3.3a on Linux platform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>(B) Relationship between CpG island density and gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Three groups were classified: all expressed genes in NSCLC, the miRNA-regulated genes, and other genes which may not be influenced by miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0026502.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Since a large number of highly-expressed genes were found in the anti-correlated group, we further asked if these HCG genes are always highly-expressed and tend to miRNA-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>In all genes expressed in NSCLC, HCG genes were not seen as dominant in highly expressed genes as compared to LCG or ICG genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The peak expressions of HCG range from 5 to 10, whereas those of ICG or LCG genes are in a range of 2 to 7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>miRNA tends to regulate more genes at the relative expression level of 5 to 10, therefore, when regulated by miRNAs, the peak of ICG or LCG gene expressions should be in this range, and we observed that there were less LCG genes in this expression range as compared to HCG or ICG genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>However, “others” (genes with no regulation value variation) also has a peak in the expression range but there was no difference in gene density among the three CpG classes (Figure 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>In summary, HCG genes may be enriched genes that are regulated by miRNAs due to their high expression levels, but this is obviously not the only reason. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>We also performed GO analysis between the miRNA-regulated and miRNA-insensitive groups to show that their genes and functions are different from the anti-correlated and the correlated groups (Figure 5 and Figure S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>As it is shown in Figure 5, the miRNA-regulated group contains more genes in the following processes: transcription regulation, nucleic acid binding, cell communication, metabolic, and development regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>These differences demonstrate from another angle why miRNAs tend to affect HCG genes with conserved miRNA target sites as CpG island content is always correlated with gene regulation and functional differentiation, and these genes may be of importance for basic cellular functions of different vertebrates or mammals [36]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0026502-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0026502.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Different GO terms between the miRNA-regulated and miRNA-unregulated genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>P&lt;0.05 was considered as significant [67]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0026502.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>In this study, we investigated the mRNA and miRNA profiling of NSCLC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>mRNA profiling revealed that a number of differentially-expressed genes are involved in activation of cell cycle in NSCLC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>This finding is consistent with results of previous studies, which suggest that abnormal cell cycle is associated with elevated lung cancer risk [37], [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The down-regulated genes are found to be predominantly enriched in immune systems as well as those localized on cell membranes, which are usually correlated with cell-cell communication and participate in immune process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Inhibitions of these genes have been supposed to facilitate lung cancer development and progression, and this may to some extent due to the escape of cancer cells from detection and destruction by the host immune system [39], [40], [41]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>In miRNA profiling comparison, we found hsa-miR-96 was significantly up-regulated in NSCLC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>48 hsa-miR-96 potential targets were predominantly enriched in the down-regulated mRNA group and are involved in a variety of biological processes according to GO annotations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Based on regulation value estimates, we showed that 42 of them belong to the anti-correlated group (Figure 1A, Table S7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Our validation experiments revealed that the mature form of hsa-miR-96 is highly expressed not only in cancer tissues but also in sera of cancer patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>This result suggests that hsa-miR-96 has a great potential to be used as a noninvasive biomarker for NSCLC diagnosis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Our current knowledge about hsa-miR-96 is rather limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>It resides in the intergenic area between NRF1 and UBE2H on human chromosome 7 [42] and has a very broad distribution among animals, from nematodes to mammals, and is more conserved among vertebrates (Figure S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have suggested that it functions to regulate the progression of differentiation in mammalian cochlear inner and outer hair cells [43], and is associated with aggressive human behaviors [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>In the relationship with cancers, hsa-miR-96 has been reported to be highly expressed in bladder cancer [45], prostate carcinoma [46], and chronic myeloid leukemia [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>It can be detected in urine and is correlated with stage and grade based on urinary cytology of urothelial carcinoma [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Up-regulation of hsa-miR-96 results in down-regulations of transcriptional factor FOXO3a and FOXO1, and thus induces cell proliferation in human breast cancer [49], [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>In our assays, we found a set of potential targets that may correlate with the function of hsa-miR-96 in NSCLC development, but none of the potential targets have been validated by experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Therefore, further experimentation is of essence in revealing relationship between hsa-miR-96 and NSCLC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>In addition, we will increase the size of the specimen to investigate possible relationship of hsa-miR-96 expression with prognosis, and other characteristics of NSCLC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>In General, miRNAs are believed to bind the 3′ untranslated region of a target mRNA and down-regulate its expression at mRNA or protein levels but mostly at mRNA level [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Therefore, when the expression of a miRNA is elevated, mRNAs that are regulated by the miRNA is expected to be down-regulated; when the expression of miRNA is repressed, its target mRNAs should show up-regulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>However, according to our results, the anti-correlated mRNAs are always down-regulated and only a small fraction of genes are up-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Further examination suggested that in the anti-correlated group, down-regulated mRNAs are always highly expressed, and up-regulated mRNAs are always lowly expressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the existence of more highly expressed genes may be an important contributor to the effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The reason why highly-expressed mRNAs tend to be down-regulated by miRNAs and the lowly-expressed mRNAs tend to be up-regulated by miRNAs suggests an existence of a regulatory balance that functions to keep the entire transcriptome in an optimized dynamic range. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>In our analysis, we failed to find any clues that are responsible for the difference between the anti-correlate and the correlated mRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>GO classification did not show any obvious difference either (Figure S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>In addition, expression levels of the target mRNAs that have a high regulation value did not show significant variation, and vice versa (Table S2, Table S3,Table S7, Table S9, Table S11), and genes whose expression are significantly varied are not necessarily significantly regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Since a mRNA is often regulated by more than one miRNAs [28], we are still unable to know how these miRNAs interact with one another, and which kind of direct interactions are most effective. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, miRNAs may repress their target genes only at the protein level [52] and the targets may not exhibit noticeable changes at the mRNA level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>There are other factors that are involved in regulating mRNAs at epigenetic levels, such as histone methylation [53], [54] and acetylation [55], [56], and that are always capable of interfering with miRNA-centric networks [57], [58], making deciphering such networks more difficult. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Another interesting observation is that genes in either the correlated group or the anti-correlated group have a larger proportion of HCG genes than that in “others” group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Both the correlated and the anti-correlated groups are considered most likely to be influenced or possibly regulated by miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>This result suggests that miRNAs tend to regulate HCG genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Further investigation demonstrated that HCG genes tended to express at a higher level when compared with ICG or LCG genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Therefore, there may be a possibility that more HCG genes are influenced by miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>However, comparisons based on all potential targets failed to show any difference among these groups (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>As the stringent standard selected targets have conserved binding sites of miRNAs among vertebrates or mammals, more HCG target genes in miRNA-influenced group may correlate with gene evolution among vertebrates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>GO comparison between the regulated and the unregulated groups demonstrated they were quite different as the former always contains more genes involved in transcription regulation, nucleic acid binding, cell communication, metabolic, and development regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The function of genes and their expression is always correlated with the CpG island content of promoters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>It has been suggested that house-keeping functions are significantly overrepresented in the HCG class, whereas terms associated with specific functions characteristic of more differentiated or highly regulated cells are significantly overrepresented in the LCG class [36], [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>miRNA has been proposed to be a primary regulation mechanism as it is present from low to high organisms, it therefore may prefer to regulate a higher proportion of HCG genes for basic cellular functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>These are possible reasons why miRNA regulation may be more biased toward HCG genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>DNA methylation plays a role in the repression of gene expression in animal cells, but in many cells, most genes are inactive even their CpG island-containing promoters remain unmethylated [35], [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>This implies that there may be other regulatory mechanisms involved, such as histone modifications and miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Inactive HCG genes were more frequently unmathylated as compared with ICG or LCG genes, and it was most likely that the role of enriched demethylated H3K4 is to protect CpG islands from methylation [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>In addition, a broad H3 hyperacetylation in CpG islands has been reported [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Therefore, histone modifications are most likely to affect DNA methylation regulated gene repression, and an increasing number of evidence has confirmed this conclusion [62], [63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Lung cancer development is closely correlated with three most studied epigenetic phenomena including modifications in DNA and histone proteins as well as miRNAs [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The interaction between DNA methylation and histone modification have been well studied [65], while the relationship between DNA methylation and miRNAs or miRNAs and histone modification has not been elucidated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>According to our results, there may be a possibility that miRNAs play a role in bridging DNA methylation repression and histone modifications. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Ethics Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>All samples were obtained from the tissue bank of Zhoushan Hospital (city of Zhoushan, Zhejiang province, China), which assures written informed consent from all subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The Institutional Review Board of Zhoushan Hospital approved the use of samples for this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Patients and RNA extraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>We performed miRNA microarray and mRNA microarray using 3 adenocarcinomas and 3 squamous cell carcinomas of the lung as well as the paired control samples from their adjacent normal tissues, which were carefully diagnosed and pathologically defined (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Specimens were brought to pathologists immediately for diagnosis (Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Tumor tissues and the corresponding adjacent normal tissues were placed in different tubes in liquid nitrogen and subsequently stored at -180°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The Total RNA that was used to perform microarray analysis was extracted using TRIZOL (Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Since we used 3 adenocarcinomas (and controls) and 3 squamous cell carcinomas (and controls) of the lung for the microarray analysis, we chose a comparable number of corresponding NSCLC cases for validation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>We also took into consideration of the coverage of different genders, cancer stages, ages, and other characteristics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>In particular, we performed tissue qRT-PCR validation using 35 pair specimens (17 paired samples of adenocarcinomas and 18 paired samples of squamous cell carcinomas of the lung), and further examined miRNA expression abundance in the serum samples from the same 35 specimens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>There are 17 patients whose ages are more than 60 and 18 younger than 60 (including 7 males and 28 females). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>As for the grade of differentiation, the tumors are 13 well differentiated, 18 moderately differentiated, and 4 are poorly differentiated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The tumor stages are also clearly defined: 28 are at T1-T2 and 7 are in T3-T4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>In addition, lymph node metastases were found in 15 patients (8 patients are at stage I and 17 patients are higher stages; Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>We collected the sera before surgical resection and chemotherapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>We selected 20 people (9 males and 11 females; all aged below 60) without any cancer histories and other illness and collected their sera as normal controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Total RNA including miRNA from the tissue and serum samples were extracted by using a commercial kit (mirVana RNA™ Isolation kit, Applied Biosystems) according to the supplier's instruction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Quality of total RNA was determined by using Bioanalyzer (UV spectrophotometer Q3000, Quawell). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Extracted RNA samples were stored at -80°C until used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>For mRNA expression validation, we used 20 pair specimens (9 paired samples of adenocarcinomas and 11 paired samples of squamous cell carcinomas of the lung. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>12 pair were from the previous 35 patient cohort.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>In particular, There are 5 patients whose ages are more than 60 and 15 patients who are younger than 60 (17 male and 3 female). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>For the grade of differentiation, 11 and 9 are moderately differentiated and poorly differentiated, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>For tumor stages, 19 patients are at T1-T2 and one is at T3-T4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Lymph node metastases were found in 5 patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>For the tumor stage, 9 patients have stage I and 11 patients have higher stage tumors (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real-time PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>10 ng of total RNA was reverse-transcribed using the TaqMan miRNA reverse transcription kit and RT primers for miR-96 and U6 snRNA (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The cDNAs were then analyzed by real-time PCR using TaqMan probes for miR-96, and U6 snRNA (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>We reverse transcribed three micrograms of total RNA to single-stranded cDNA using Fermentas kit and then performed qRT-PCR experiments using SYBR Green (RealMasterMix(SYBR Green), TIANGEN) on Applied Biosystems 7500 Real-Time PCR System. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>We analyzed gene expression using 2ΔΔCT method [66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Relative expression of hsa-miR-96 was determined in reference to an internal U6 snRNA control, and relative mRNA expression was determined in reference to glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>We listed the primer sequences that were used in mRNA expression validation experiments in Table S12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>In the statistical analysis, we presented results as mean ± SE, and assessed differences between the groups by using paired or independent T-Test in SPSS 15.0. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Microarray hybridization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>mRNA profiling were performed by using Illuminia Technologies “HumanHT-12 v4” according to manufacturer’s protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>miRNA profiling were performed by using Illuminia Technologies “humanMI_V2” according to the manufacturer's protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>GenomeStudio 1.0 was used to perform average normalization of the results from mRNA and miRNA microarrays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>All data is MIAME compliant and that the raw data has been deposited in a MIAME compliant database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>The expression data generated by this study are available in the NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) as accession GSE29250. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Differential expression analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>In each group-based comparison, we filtered out all miRNAs or mRNAs that were not detected in any sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Considering that these samples may be too few to draw any reliable conclusions about differential expression, we only chose genes that are consistently up- or down-regulated in all the 6 NSCLC tissues compared with the adjacent normal tissues as the differential expression results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>To get the significantly differential expression results, the signal values were transformed (log2) and median centered for each array, and then two-class paired differential expression analysis was performed by using SAM (version 3.11; Stanford University). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Genes with significant differences were selected at a FDR of 0.1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>miRNA target prediction and miRNA regulation value </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>We used three methods to predict miRNA targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>UTR sequences were downloaded from the website of TargetScan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>We used perl scripts of TargetScan to predict targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>First, we predicted targets with conserved miRNA binding sites using the P CT method of TargetScan [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>We then predicted all the potential targets using TargetScan without considering sequence conservation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>At last, we run miRanda v3.3a on Linux platform as the third method to predict potential targets using default parameter settings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that the average regulation value of a miRNA is correlated with its expression level and the number of targets, and can be calculated as: the expression value variation divided by the number of expressed targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>During the process of cancer development, some miRNAs may be up-regulated in cancer as compared with the adjacent normal tissue, and in contrast, some may be down-regulated, and therefore the regulation value will become positive or negative respectively if the number of its expressed targets is not changed significantly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>For an mRNA, it can be regulated by a variety of miRNAs, so the regulation value is calculated by the addition of regulation value variations over all variable miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Histological images of lung tumor tissues and the adjacent normal lung tissues. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>GO results of the 48 down-regulated conserved targets of hsa-miR-96 (predicted using TargetScan).C </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s002.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>GO results of the anti-correlated genes (predicted using TargetScan, and the conserved target sites were chosen). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s003.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Mature sequence alignment of hsa-miR-96 in different species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s004.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s005"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Different GO terms between the anti-correlated group and the correlated group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s005.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s006"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Information for the 35 patients that were used in qRT-PCR examination and the 6 patients that were used in performing microarray. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>(XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s006.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s007"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated genes in NSCLC cancer tissue compared with the adjacent normal tissue. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>(XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s007.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s008"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated genes in NSCLC cancer tissue compared with the adjacent normal tissue. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>(XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s008.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s009"><label>Table S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated miRNAs in NSCLC cancer tissue compared with the adjacent normal tissue. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>(XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s009.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s010"><label>Table S5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated miRNAs in NSCLC cancer tissue compared with the adjacent normal tissue. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>(XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s010.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s011"><label>Table S6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Target genes (predicted using P CT method of TargetScan) which have conserved miRNA binding sites among vertebrates or mannals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>(XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s011.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s012"><label>Table S7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Target genes which have conserved miRNA binding sites. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>(XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s012.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s013"><label>Table S8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>All potential target genes that are predicted by TargetScan. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>(XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s013.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s014"><label>Table S9</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Regulation pattern based on all potential target genes that are predicted by TargetScan. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>(XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s014.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s015"><label>Table S10</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>All potential target genes that are predicted by miRanda. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>(XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s015.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s016"><label>Table S11</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Regulation pattern based on all potential target genes that are predicted by miRanda. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>(XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s016.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0026502.s017"><label>Table S12</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Primer sequences for mRNA expression validation experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>(XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0026502.s017.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Funding: This work is supported by Natural Science Foundation of Zhejiang Province (Y2110960) and Bureau of Science and Technology of Zhoushan awarded to Professor Yongkui Zhang (20081059), and the Research Fund of Zhoushan Hospital awarded to Dr. Lina Ma, and the National Basic Research Program (973 Program; 2011CB944100 and 2011CB944101) and National Natural Science Foundation of China (90919024) awarded to Professor Jun Yu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0026502-Cancer1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>1 Cancer. 2009 Cancer Geneva, Switzerland World Health Organization  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Martini1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>2 MartiniNBainsMSBurtMEZakowskiMFMcCormackP 1995 Incidence of local recurrence and second primary tumors in resected stage I lung cancer. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg 109 120 129 7815787 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Hoffman1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>3 HoffmanPCMauerAMVokesEE 2000 Lung cancer. Lancet 355 479 485 10841143 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Flehinger1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>4 FlehingerBJKimmelMMelamedMR 1992 The effect of surgical treatment on survival from early lung cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Implications for screening. Chest 101 1013 1018 1313349 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Mountain1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>5 MountainCF 1997 Revisions in the International System for Staging Lung Cancer. Chest 111 1710 1717 9187198 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Kan1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>6 KanZJaiswalBSStinsonJJanakiramanVBhattD 2010 Diverse somatic mutation patterns and pathway alterations in human cancers. Nature 466 869 873 20668451 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-LagosQuintana1"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>7 Lagos-QuintanaMRauhutRLendeckelWTuschlT 2001 Identification of novel genes coding for small expressed RNAs. Science 294 853 858 11679670 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Hutvagner1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>8 HutvagnerGZamorePD 2002 A microRNA in a multiple-turnover RNAi enzyme complex. Science 297 2056 2060 12154197 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Ruvkun1"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>9 RuvkunG 2006 Clarifications on miRNA and cancer. Science 311 36 37  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-NunezIglesias1"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>10 Nunez-IglesiasJLiuCCMorganTEFinchCEZhouXJ 2010 Joint genome-wide profiling of miRNA and mRNA expression in Alzheimer's disease cortex reveals altered miRNA regulation. PLoS One 5 e8898 20126538 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Clop1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>11 ClopA 2009 Insights into the importance of miRNA-related polymorphisms to heart disease. Hum Mutat 30: v  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Haramati1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>12 HaramatiSChapnikESztainbergYEilamRZwangR 2010 miRNA malfunction causes spinal motor neuron disease. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 107 13111 13116 20616011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Liu1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>13 LiuXSempereLFOuyangHMemoliVAAndrewAS 2010 MicroRNA-31 functions as an oncogenic microRNA in mouse and human lung cancer cells by repressing specific tumor suppressors. J Clin Invest 120 1298 1309 20237410 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Lebanony1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>14 LebanonyDBenjaminHGiladSEzagouriMDovA 2009 Diagnostic assay based on hsa-miR-205 expression distinguishes squamous from nonsquamous non-small-cell lung carcinoma. J Clin Oncol 27 2030 2037 19273703 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Yanaihara1"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>15 YanaiharaNCaplenNBowmanESeikeMKumamotoK 2006 Unique microRNA molecular profiles in lung cancer diagnosis and prognosis. Cancer Cell 9 189 198 16530703 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Wang1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>16 WangXCDuLQTianLLWuHLJiangXY 2010 Expression and function of miRNA in postoperative radiotherapy sensitive and resistant patients of non-small cell lung cancer. Lung Cancer 72 92 99 20728239 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Lu1"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>17 LuJGetzGMiskaEAAlvarez-SaavedraELambJ 2005 MicroRNA expression profiles classify human cancers. Nature 435 834 838 15944708 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Saviozzi1"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>18 SaviozziSCeppiPNovelloSGhioPLo IaconoM 2009 Non-small cell lung cancer exhibits transcript overexpression of genes associated with homologous recombination and DNA replication pathways. Cancer Res 69 3390 3396 19351853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Chang1"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>19 ChangJWYiCASonDSChoiNLeeJ 2008 Prediction of lymph node metastasis using the combined criteria of helical CT and mRNA expression profiling for non-small cell lung cancer. Lung Cancer 60 264 270 18280003 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Jeong1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>20 JeongHCKimEKLeeJHYooHNKimJK 2011 Aberrant expression of let-7a miRNA in the blood of non-small cell lung cancer patients. Mol Med Report 4 383 387  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Duncan1"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>21 DuncanDProdduturiNZhangB 2010 WebGestalt2: an updated and expanded version of the Web-based Gene Set Analysis Toolkit. BMC Bioinformatics 11 1 1 20043860 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Yi1"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>22 YiRQinYMacaraIGCullenBR 2003 Exportin-5 mediates the nuclear export of pre-microRNAs and short hairpin RNAs. Genes Dev 17 3011 3016 14681208 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Gregory1"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>23 GregoryRIShiekhattarR 2005 MicroRNA biogenesis and cancer. Cancer Res 65 3509 3512 15867338 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Lee1"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>24 LeeYJeonKLeeJTKimSKimVN 2002 MicroRNA maturation: stepwise processing and subcellular localization. EMBO J 21 4663 4670 12198168 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Lee2"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>25 LeeYAhnCHanJChoiHKimJ 2003 The nuclear RNase III Drosha initiates microRNA processing. Nature 425 415 419 14508493 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Zhang1"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>26 ZhangBWangQPanX 2007 MicroRNAs and their regulatory roles in animals and plants. J Cell Physiol 210 279 289 17096367 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Poy1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>27 PoyMNEliassonLKrutzfeldtJKuwajimaSMaX 2004 A pancreatic islet-specific microRNA regulates insulin secretion. Nature 432 226 230 15538371 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Doench1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>28 DoenchJGSharpPA 2004 Specificity of microRNA target selection in translational repression. Genes Dev 18 504 511 15014042 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Lewis1"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>29 LewisBPShihIHJones-RhoadesMWBartelDPBurgeCB 2003 Prediction of mammalian microRNA targets. Cell 115 787 798 14697198 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Lewis2"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>30 LewisBPBurgeCBBartelDP 2005 Conserved seed pairing, often flanked by adenosines, indicates that thousands of human genes are microRNA targets. Cell 120 15 20 15652477 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Brennecke1"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>31 BrenneckeJStarkARussellRBCohenSM 2005 Principles of microRNA-target recognition. PLoS Biol 3 e85 15723116 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Krek1"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>32 KrekAGrunDPoyMNWolfRRosenbergL 2005 Combinatorial microRNA target predictions. Nat Genet 37 495 500 15806104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Friedman1"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>33 FriedmanRCFarhKKBurgeCBBartelDP 2009 Most mammalian mRNAs are conserved targets of microRNAs. Genome Res 19 92 105 18955434 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Enright1"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>34 EnrightAJJohnBGaulUTuschlTSanderC 2003 MicroRNA targets in Drosophila. Genome Biol 5 R1 14709173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Weber1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>35 WeberMHellmannIStadlerMBRamosLPaaboS 2007 Distribution, silencing potential and evolutionary impact of promoter DNA methylation in the human genome. Nat Genet 39 457 466 17334365 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Saxonov1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>36 SaxonovSBergPBrutlagDL 2006 A genome-wide analysis of CpG dinucleotides in the human genome distinguishes two distinct classes of promoters. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 103 1412 1417 16432200 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Zheng1"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>37 ZhengYLKostiOLoffredoCABowmanEMechanicL 2009 Elevated lung cancer risk is associated with deficiencies in cell cycle checkpoints: genotype and phenotype analyses from a case-control study. Int J Cancer 126 2199 2210  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Wang2"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>38 WangWSpitzMRYangHLuCStewartDJ 2007 Genetic variants in cell cycle control pathway confer susceptibility to lung cancer. Clin Cancer Res 13 5974 5981 17908995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Nambu1"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>39 NambuYBeerDG 2003 Altered surface markers in lung cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Lack of cell-surface Fas/APO-1 expression in pulmonary adenocarcinoma may allow escape from immune surveillance. Methods Mol Med 74 259 266 12415701 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Shimada1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>40 ShimadaKYasudaS 1984 Studies on immune response of human lung cancer by cell surface antigen. Rinsho Kyobu Geka 4 53 60 6377454 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Huang1"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>41 HuangBSikorskiRSampathPThorneSH 2011 Modulation of NKG2D-ligand cell surface expression enhances immune cell therapy of cancer. J Immunother 34 289 296 21389869 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Mourelatos1"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>42 MourelatosZDostieJPaushkinSSharmaACharrouxB 2002 miRNPs: a novel class of ribonucleoproteins containing numerous microRNAs. Genes Dev 16 720 728 11914277 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Kuhn1"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>43 KuhnSJohnsonSLFurnessDNChenJInghamN 2011 miR-96 regulates the progression of differentiation in mammalian cochlear inner and outer hair cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 108 2355 2360 21245307 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Jensen1"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>44 JensenKPCovaultJConnerTSTennenHKranzlerHR 2009 A common polymorphism in serotonin receptor 1B mRNA moderates regulation by miR-96 and associates with aggressive human behaviors. Mol Psychiatry 14 381 389 18283276 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Han1"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>45 HanYChenJZhaoXLiangCWangY 2011 MicroRNA Expression Signatures of Bladder Cancer Revealed by Deep Sequencing. PLoS One 6 e18286 21464941 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Schaefer1"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>46 SchaeferAJungMMollenkopfHJWagnerIStephanC 2010 Diagnostic and prognostic implications of microRNA profiling in prostate carcinoma. Int J Cancer 126 1166 1176 19676045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Agirre1"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>47 AgirreXJimenez-VelascoASan Jose-EnerizEGarateLBandresE 2008 Down-regulation of hsa-miR-10a in chronic myeloid leukemia CD34+ cells increases USF2-mediated cell growth. Mol Cancer Res 6 1830 1840 19074828 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Yamada1"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>48 YamadaYEnokidaHKojimaSKawakamiKChiyomaruT 2010 MiR-96 and miR-183 detection in urine serve as potential tumor markers of urothelial carcinoma: correlation with stage and grade, and comparison with urinary cytology. Cancer Sci 102 522 529 21166959 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Lin1"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>49 LinHDaiTXiongHZhaoXChenX 2011 Unregulated miR-96 induces cell proliferation in human breast cancer by downregulating transcriptional factor FOXO3a. PLoS One 5 e15797  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Guttilla1"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>50 GuttillaIKWhiteBA 2009 Coordinate regulation of FOXO1 by miR-27a, miR-96, and miR-182 in breast cancer cells. J Biol Chem 284 23204 23216 19574223 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Guo1"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>51 GuoHIngoliaNTWeissmanJSBartelDP 2010 Mammalian microRNAs predominantly act to decrease target mRNA levels. Nature 466 835 840 20703300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Wang3"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>52 WangLObergALAsmannYWSicotteHMcDonnellSK 2009 Genome-wide transcriptional profiling reveals microRNA-correlated genes and biological processes in human lymphoblastoid cell lines. PLoS One 4 e5878 19517021 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Jin1"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>53 JinMKawakamiKFukuiYTsukiokaSOdaM 2009 Different histological types of non-small cell lung cancer have distinct folate and DNA methylation levels. Cancer Sci 100 2325 2330 19764999 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Vaissiere1"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>54 VaissiereTHungRJZaridzeDMoukeriaACueninC 2009 Quantitative analysis of DNA methylation profiles in lung cancer identifies aberrant DNA methylation of specific genes and its association with gender and cancer risk factors. Cancer Res 69 243 252 19118009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Choi1"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>55 ChoiKCLeeYHJungMGKwonSHKimMJ 2009 Gallic acid suppresses lipopolysaccharide-induced nuclear factor-kappaB signaling by preventing RelA acetylation in A549 lung cancer cells. Mol Cancer Res 7 2011 2021 19996305 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Tani1"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>56 TaniMItoJNishiokaMKohnoTTachibanaK 2004 Correlation between histone acetylation and expression of the MYO18B gene in human lung cancer cells. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 40 146 151 15101048 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Dickstein1"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>57 DicksteinJSenyukVPremanandKLaricchia-RobbioLXuP 2010 Methylation and silencing of miRNA-124 by EVI1 and self-renewal exhaustion of hematopoietic stem cells in murine myelodysplastic syndrome. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 107 9783 9788 20448201 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Roccaro1"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>58 RoccaroAMSaccoAJiaXAzabAKMaisoP 2010 microRNA-dependent modulation of histone acetylation in Waldenstrom macroglobulinemia. Blood 116 1506 1514 20519629 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Sharif1"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>59 SharifJEndoTAToyodaTKosekiH 2010 Divergence of CpG island promoters: a consequence or cause of evolution? Dev Growth Differ 52 545 554 20646027 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Bird1"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>60 BirdA 2002 DNA methylation patterns and epigenetic memory. Genes Dev 16 6 21 11782440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Roh1"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>61 RohTYCuddapahSZhaoK 2005 Active chromatin domains are defined by acetylation islands revealed by genome-wide mapping. Genes Dev 19 542 552 15706033 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Edwards1"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>62 EdwardsJRO'DonnellAHRollinsRAPeckhamHELeeC 2011 Chromatin and sequence features that define the fine and gross structure of genomic methylation patterns. Genome Res 20 972 980  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Okitsu1"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>63 OkitsuCYHsiehCL 2007 DNA methylation dictates histone H3K4 methylation. Mol Cell Biol 27 2746 2757 17242185 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-VanDenBroeck1"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>64 Van Den BroeckAOzennePEyminBGazzeriS 2010 Lung cancer: a modified epigenome. Cell Adh Migr 4 107 113 20139698 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Kondo1"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>65 KondoY 2009 Epigenetic cross-talk between DNA methylation and histone modifications in human cancers. Yonsei Med J 50 455 463 19718392 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Livak1"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>66 LivakKJSchmittgenTD 2001 Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) Method. Methods 25 402 408 11846609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0026502-Ye1"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>67 YeJFangLZhengHZhangYChenJ 2006 WEGO: a web tool for plotting GO annotations. Nucleic Acids Res 34 W293 297 16845012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
