
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Hum Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Indian J Hum Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJHG</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Human Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0971-6866</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-362X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications &amp; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3897137</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJHG-19-423</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0971-6866.124370</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Distribution and genotype frequency of the C1431T and pro12ala polymorphisms of the peroxisome proliferator activator receptor gamma gene in an Iranian population </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rooki</surname><given-names>Hassan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Haerian</surname><given-names>Monir-Sadat</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Azimzadeh</surname><given-names>Pedram</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ebrahimi</surname><given-names>Mahmoud</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mirhafez</surname><given-names>Reza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ferns</surname><given-names>Gordon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ghayour-Mobarhan</surname><given-names>Majid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zali</surname><given-names>Mohammad-Reza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Gastroenterology and Liver Diseases Research Center, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>1</label>Cardiovascular Research Center, School of Medicine, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>2</label>Institute for Science and Technology in Medicine, University of Keele, Guy Hilton Research Centre, Thornburrow Drive, Stok on Trent, Staffordshire, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Prof. Mohammad-Reza Zali, 7<sup>th</sup> Floor, Taleghani Hospital, Gastroenterology and Liver Diseases Research Center, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Velenjak, Shahid Aerabi Street, Yemen Street, Tehran, Iran. E-mail: <email xlink:href="nnzali@hotmail.com">nnzali@hotmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Oct-Dec</season><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>429</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © Indian Journal of Human Genetics</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>BACKGROUND: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Peroxisome proliferator activator receptor gamma (PPARγ) is a nuclear transcription factor regulating multiple genes involved in cell growth, differentiation, carbohydrate and lipid metabolism and energy production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Several genetic variations in the PPARγ gene have been identified to be associated with diabetes, obesity, dyslipidemia, insulin resistance, metabolic syndrome and coronary artery disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The present study was designed to explore the distribution of two common single nucleotide polymorphisms of the PPARγ gene (C1431T and Pro12Ala) in an Iranian population. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec id="st2"><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Genotype frequencies for these two polymorphisms were compared for 160 healthy Iranian individuals with reports from other populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The Genotyping was performed using real-time polymerase chain reaction. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec id="st3"><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>RESULTS: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The genotype distribution of the C1431T PPARγ polymorphism was 0.869 for the CC genotype, 0.119 for the CT genotype and 0.013 for uncommon TT genotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Allelic frequencies were 0.93 for C and 0.07 for T allele respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>For the Pro12Ala polymorphism of PPARγ gene, genotypic distributions and allelic frequencies were, 0.813 for CC, 0.181 for CG and 0.06 for GG and 0.903 for C and 0.097 for G respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Allelic and genotypic frequencies for both polymorphisms of PPARγ gene were in Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec id="st4"><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>CONCLUSIONS: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Iran is a country with an ethnically diverse population and a comparison of allelic and genotypic frequencies of PPARγ C1431T and Pro12Ala polymorphisms between our population and others showed significant differences. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>Iranian population</kwd><kwd>PPARγ gene</kwd><kwd>single nucleotide polymorphism</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1-1"><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Peroxisome proliferator activator receptor gamma (PPARγ) is a member of the nuclear receptor superfamily and is a ligand-activated transcription factor that regulates genes responsible for some very important biological functions including: Cell growth, differentiation and metabolism and acts as dietary lipid sensor.[1] </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The PPARγ gene is located on the human chromosome 3p25-24 and consists of nine exons and as a result of alternative splicing and promoter usage produces four isoforms; PPARγ1, PPARγ2, PPARγ3 and PPARγ4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>PPARγ1 is expressed by most tissues.[2] PPARγ2 is predominantly expressed in adipose tissue and regulates adipocyte differentiation.[3] PPARγ3 expression appears to be confined to macrophages, adipose tissue and the colon.[4] Primer extension studies have confirmed that PPARγ4 mRNA is present in adipose tissue suggesting that the PPARγ4 isoform has a role in adipocyte biology.[5] </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>PPARγ plays critical roles in regulating lipid and carbohydrate metabolism (energy balance), adipocyte differentiation, proliferation and insulin sensitivity and create a relationship between environmental factors and metabolic processes of the organism.[6] PPARγ also plays roles in macrophages by enhancing foam cell formation and suppressing inflammatory cytokine production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>It may also participate in controlling systemic glucose and lipid metabolism in the liver.[78] PPARγ may therefore affect processes involved in atherosclerosis.[9] </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Since PPARγ is a nuclear transcription factor regulating multiple genes involved in energy production, glucose and lipid metabolism it may be a promising candidate gene for several major common diseases including cardiovascular disease, cancer, diabetes, inflammation and polymorphisms in this receptor may influence the pathology of these diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The PPARγ gene has been reported to be associated with various metabolic disorders including diabetes,[10] obesity,[11] dyslipidemia, insulin resistance, metabolic syndrome[12] and coronary artery disease (CAD).[13] </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Several PPARγ2 gene single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) have been reported to be associated with diabetes, obesity, dyslipidemia, insulin resistance, metabolic syndrome and CAD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Several genetic variations of the PPAR gene have been found in the activation function domain 1, deoxyribonucleic acid binding domain and ligand binding domain (LBD) of the receptor and confer some conformational changes in protein structure that may affect transcriptional activity.[14] </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Among several genetic variants of the PPARγ gene, two polymorphisms Pro12Ala of the exon B (rs1801282) and the C1431T silent substitution (rs3856806) in the 6th exon are the most frequently occurring SNPs and have been associated with various diseases and extensive studies have been undertaken to assess the effects of these polymorphisms on many aspects of human physiology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The C1431T polymorphism is also known as the C161T or His477His was identified in 1998 by Meirhaeghe et al.,[15] and has been studied in relation to bone metabolism, metabolic syndrome, CAD, obesity and glucose intolerance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The Pro12Ala protein polymorphism is due to a CCA-to-GCA missense mutation and was identified by Yen et al.[16] It is associated with type-2 diabetes mellitus, insulin resistance, obesity and metabolic disorders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In addition, numerous studies have demonstrated rare alleles of these two common variants play a role in the complex pathogenetic mechanism of major diseases supposed to be useful markers to evaluate the connection between PPARγ and metabolic derived disorders. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Given the pivotal roles of PPARγ in regulating metabolism several studies in various ethnic populations including, Caucasians,[17] Mexican-Americans,[18] African-Americans,[1913] Asian,[20] Eastern Asian,[12] European,[10] Hispanic and non-Hispanic[21] have been conducted to determine allelic frequencies and genotypic distribution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>There have been no studies of the distribution of C1431T polymorphism in an Iranian population and there is some controversy about the frequency of Pro12Ala polymorphism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the present study was designed to explore the distribution of these two common variants of PPAR gene in Iranian population and compare the finding with other populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>A number of 160 healthy individuals were analyzed to evaluate the frequency of PPARγ alleles and genotypes in a healthy Iranian population. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>A total of 160 healthy volunteer subjects comprised of 70 males and 90 females, mainly people of Iranian descent (primarily Persian), were selected randomly from all parts of Mashhad as a second largest city in Iran and enrolled in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>A health questionnaire, including questions such as name, ethnicity, family history, age, sex and dietary habits, was provided to each participant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Blood was taken in accordance with the World Health Organization protocol for blood donation and the healthy state of the all the participants was determined by medical history, physical examination and blood chemistry tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Subjects were excluded from the study if they had a history of congestive heart disease, liver and/or renal disease, endocrinological abnormalities and alcohol consumption or were under medications that altered blood pressure, glucose or lipid metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The clinical and biochemical characteristics of the all the individuals enrolled into the study were normal at baseline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The protocol was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Mashhad University of Medical Science and Informed consent was obtained from all participants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Genomic deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) was extracted from whole blood using the FlexiGene DNA isolation Kit (Qiagen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>C1431T and Pro12Ala polymorphisms of the PPARγ gene were determined by a predesigned TaqMan SNP genotyping assay (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Oligonucleotides used for allelic discrimination assays for Pro12Ala and C1431T were as follows: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Context sequences for Pro/12Ala ([VIC/FAM]) (Applied Biosystems ID: C_1129864_10): AACTCTGGGAGATTCTCCTATTGAC[C/G] CAGAAAGCGATTCCTTCACTGATACPro12 Probe (Vic labeled): C_1129864_10-CAla12 Probe (Fam labeled): C_1129864_10-G. Context sequences for C1431T ([VIC/FAM]) (Applied Biosystems ID: C_11922961_30): ACCTCAGACAGATTGTCACGGAACA[C/T] GTGCAGCTACTGCAGGTGATCAAGAC1431 Probe (Vic labeled): C_11922961_30-CT1431 Probe (Fam labeled): C_11922961_30-T.  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The reaction was performed in 25 μl final volume with real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using 96-well plates on an ABI 7500 real time PCR system (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The PCR conditions were 95°C for 10 min and 40 cycles of 92°C for 15 s and 60°C for 1 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Individual genotypes identification was analyzed by SDS software version 1.3 (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>For genotyping quality control, duplicate samples and negative controls were included to ensure the accuracy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Allele frequencies of two SNPs were computed using genotype data obtained from these healthy controls and were compared with those reported in other populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Each SNP was tested for Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) conformity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The statistical significance of the differences between genotypic distributions in populations was tested by the Chi-square (χ2) or Fisher's exact test using the SPSS 16.0 statistical package. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>(SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL) P &lt; 0.05 was considered to be significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The genotype characteristics of studied individuals are shown in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Allelic and genotypic frequencies for both polymorphisms of PPARγ gene were in HWE (P ≥ 0.05) [Table 1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The genotypic distribution of the C1431T PPARγ polymorphism were 0.869 for CC, 0.119 for CT and 0.013 for TT and allelic frequencies were 0.93 for C and 0.07 for T respectively [Table 1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>For another Pro12Ala variant of PPARγ, genotypic distributions and allelic frequencies were, 0.813 for CC, 0.181 for CG and 0.06 for GG and 0.903 for C and 0.097 for G respectively [Table 1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Differences in allelic frequencies and genotype distribution of the polymorphisms between Iranian population and those reported for other populations are shown in Tables 2 and 3 respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Allelic and genotypes frequency of studied population </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJHG-19-423-g001"/></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Comparison of allelic and genotypic frequencies of PPARγ C1431T variant between our population and others </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJHG-19-423-g002"/></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Comparison of allelic and genotypic frequencies of PPARγ Pro12Ala variant between our population and others </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJHG-19-423-g003"/></table-wrap></SecTag></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The present study represents the examination of the PPARγ gene C1431T and Pro12Ala polymorphisms distribution in Iranian healthy population and comparison with other populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Several studies have demonstrated these two common polymorphisms of PPARγ gene have a relationship with some major diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>This current study is part of another study dealing with patients with metabolic syndrome and CADs (unpublished data); many studies have showed these two common variants of PPARγ are associated with decreased risk of CAD and MS in various populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, C1431T polymorphism has not been studied in our population before, so this is why we selected these two common variants to evaluate in our population. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Allelic and genotypic frequencies of PPARγ C1431T polymorphism in our population showed significant differences from other populations listed in Table 2 except for two reports from European,[3132] one from Italy,[33] two in African-American,[35] and one from sub-Saharan African population.[35] Allelic but not genotypic frequencies in one report from European,[32] one from Caucasian,[17] one from Hispanic[21] and one from Indian[28] showed significant differences from what we found in our Iranian population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>In all the populations the frequency of rare allele homozygote's (TT) was low (0-7%), but there was one exception for a Chinese population that showed more than 12% frequency that it might be due to small sample size.[24] In general, Chinese and other Asian populations showed a higher frequency than others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>In this case, our data was different from those of Asian populations and was similar to those in Australian, European and Caucasian. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>With respect to Pro12Ala polymorphism, comparison of allelic and genotypic frequencies between our data and other studies listed in Table 3 shows no significant differences with most of them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>However there were some significant differences with two reports from China (P = 0.00),[2036] one from Korea (P = 0.041),[12] one from Asia (P = 0.00),[20] and a few reports from Europe including, Italy (P = 0.003), Slovenia (P = 0.017),[39] The Czech Republic (P = 0.004),[38] France (P = 0.00)[11] and in an African-American population (P = 0.00)[40] as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>One report from Europe and one within a Caucasian population showed significance differences in allelic but not genotypic frequencies with our results.[3830] As shown in Table 3, the CC ((Pro/Pro) genotype was the predominant form in all populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Data are presented in Table 3 shows some inconsistency among different studies in the distribution of the G (12Ala) allele that might be due to the difference in racial and ethnic groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The highest distribution of the G (12Ala) allele belongs to European and Caucasian populations and the least is relate to Chinese and African-American populations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Most of the population in Iran is genetically close to Caucasian and their ancestors were the Aryans who had migrated from Central Asia to Iran. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The main reason for the significant differences between our data and other populations results from Iran as a country with an ethnically diverse population including Pars, Turk, Kurd, Tajik, Turkmen, Baloch and special religious such as Muslims, Zoroastrians, Jews, Christians and Assyrians. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>However, Iran is located along the ancient Silk Road and connected Asia to Europe and during the course of history, Iranian population has encountered foreigners including Macedonians, Arabs, Turks and Mongols on various occasion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the population living in this country might be mixed due to contacting with others and the immigration of some people from neighboring nations.[41] </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Several studies have been undertaken on the association between the Pro12Ala and C1431T mutations with numerous diseases such as cardiovascular disease, cancer, diabetes, inflammation on various populations and the results showed controversy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The controversial findings related to these polymorphisms may be attributable to genetically differences in populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is necessary to study in different populations to reach a general consensus in this field. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>An important limitation in our study is the relatively small sample size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Further association study with a larger population base is needed to confirm our results and may be useful in understanding these SNPs roles in pathology of the main disease in the future. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec1-5"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Statistical differences in the distribution of two common polymorphisms of PPARγ gene between Iranian population and others showed the importance of studying these SNPs in relation to some major diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Regards to Iranian different genetic with some other populations in Asia and other continents, it seems that our study confirms this difference concerning the two common PPARγ polymorphisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>This work was financially supported as a PhD thesis (no. 316) by Gastroenterology and Liver Disease Research Center, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Source of Support: This work was financially supported as a PhD thesis (no. 316) by Gastroenterology and Liver Disease Research Center, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Conflict of Interest: No. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>1DesvergneBWahliWPeroxisome proliferator-activated receptors: Nuclear control of metabolismEndocr Rev1999206498810529898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref2"><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>2BeamerBANegriCYenCJGavrilovaORumbergerJMDurcanMJChromosomal localization and partial genomic structure of the human peroxisome proliferator activated receptor-gamma (hPPAR gamma) geneBiochem Biophys Res Commun199723375699168928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref3"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>3AuwerxJPPARgamma, the ultimate thrifty geneDiabetologia19994210334910447513 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref4"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>4FajasLFruchartJCAuwerxJPPARgamma3 mRNA: A distinct PPARgamma mRNA subtype transcribed from an independent promoterFEBS Lett199843855609821958 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref5"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>5Al-ShaliKCaoHKnoersNHermusARTackCJHegeleRAA single-base mutation in the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma4 promoter associated with altered in vitro expression and partial lipodystrophyJ Clin Endocrinol Metab20048956556015531525 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref6"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>6González SánchezJLSerrano RíosMFernández PerezCLaaksoMMartínez LarradMTEffect of the Pro12Ala polymorphism of the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma-2 gene on adiposity, insulin sensitivity and lipid profile in the Spanish populationEur J Endocrinol200214749550112370112 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref7"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>7TontonozPNagyLAlvarezJGThomazyVAEvansRMPPARgamma promotes monocyte/macrophage differentiation and uptake of oxidized LDLCell199893241529568716 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref8"><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>8GavrilovaOHaluzikMMatsusueKCutsonJJJohnsonLDietzKRLiver peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma contributes to hepatic steatosis, triglyceride clearance, and regulation of body fat massJ Biol Chem2003278342687612805374 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref9"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>9MarxNSukhovaGMurphyCLibbyPPlutzkyJMacrophages in human atheroma contain PPARgamma: Differentiation-dependent peroxisomal proliferator-activated receptor gamma (PPARgamma) expression and reduction of MMP-9 activity through PPARgamma activation in mononuclear phagocytes in vitroAm J Pathol199815317239665460 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref10"><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>10DoneyASFischerBCecilJEBoylanKMcGuiganFERalstonSHAssociation of the Pro12Ala and C1431T variants of PPARG and their haplotypes with susceptibility to Type 2 diabetesDiabetologia200447555814730381 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref11"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>11ValveRSiveniusKMiettinenRPihlajamäkiJRissanenADeebSSTwo polymorphisms in the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma gene are associated with severe overweight among obese womenJ Clin Endocrinol Metab19998437081210523018 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref12"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>12RheeEOhKLeeWKimSYOhESBaekKHEffects of two common polymorphisms of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-γ gene on metabolic syndromeArch Med Res200637869416314192 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref13"><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>13WeiQJacobsDRJrSchreinerPJSiscovickDSSteffesMWFornageMPatterns of association between PPARgamma genetic variation and indices of adiposity and insulin action in African-Americans and whites: The CARDIA StudyJ Mol Med (Berl)2006849556516955276 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref14"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>14AgostiniMSchoenmakersEMitchellCSzatmariISavageDSmithANon-DNA binding, dominant-negative, human PPARgamma mutations cause lipodystrophic insulin resistanceCell Metab200643031117011503 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref15"><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>15MeirhaegheAFajasLHelbecqueNCottelDLebelPDallongevilleJA genetic polymorphism of the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma gene influences plasma leptin levels in obese humansHum Mol Genet19987435409467001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref16"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>16YenCJBeamerBANegriCSilverKBrownKAYarnallDPMolecular scanning of the human peroxisome proliferator activated receptor gamma (hPPAR gamma) gene in diabetic Caucasians: Identification of a Pro12Ala PPAR gamma 2 missense mutationBiochem Biophys Res Commun199724127049425261 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref17"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>17MössnerRMeyerPJankowskiFKönigIRKrügerUKammererSVariations in the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma gene and melanoma riskCancer Lett20072462182316713673 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref18"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>18ColeSAMitchellBDHsuehWCPinedaPBeamerBAShuldinerARThe Pro12Ala variant of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma2 (PPAR-gamma2) is associated with measures of obesity in Mexican AmericansInt J Obes Relat Metab Disord200024522410805513 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref19"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>19FornageMJacobsDRSteffesMWGrossMDBrayMSSchreinerPJInverse effects of the PPAR (gamma) 2 Pro12Ala polymorphism on measures of adiposity over 15 years in African Americans and whites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The CARDIA studyMetabolism200554910715988700 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref20"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>20TaiESCorellaDDeurenberg-YapMAdiconisXChewSKTanCEDifferential effects of the C1431T and Pro12Ala PPARgamma gene variants on plasma lipids and diabetes risk in an Asian populationJ Lipid Res2004456748514729856 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref21"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>21MoffettSPFeingoldEBarmadaMMDamcottCMMarshallJAHammanRFThe C161 →T polymorphism in peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma, but not P12A, is associated with insulin resistance in Hispanic and non-Hispanic white women: Evidence for another functional variant in peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gammaMetabolism2005541552616253648 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref22"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>22ZhouXChenJXuWAssociation between C1431T polymorphism in peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-γ gene and coronary artery disease in Chinese Han populationMol Biol Rep2012391863821643757 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref23"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>23WanJXiongSChaoSXiaoJMaYWangJPPARgamma gene C161T substitution alters lipid profile in Chinese patients with coronary artery disease and type 2 diabetes mellitusCardiovasc Diabetol201091320334678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref24"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>24YangLLHuaQLiuRKYangZAssociation between two common polymorphisms of PPARgamma gene and metabolic syndrome families in a Chinese populationArch Med Res200940899619237017 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref25"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>25DongxiaLQiHLisongLJinchengGAssociation of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptorgamma gene Pro12Ala and C161T polymorphisms with metabolic syndromeCirc J200872551718362424 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref26"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>26OgawaSUranoTHosoiTMiyaoMHoshinoSFujitaMAssociation of bone mineral density with a polymorphism of the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma gene: PPARgamma expression in osteoblastsBiochem Biophys Res Commun1999260122610381354 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref27"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>27SanadaKIemitsuMMurakamiHTabataIYamamotoKGandoYPPARγ2 C1431T genotype increases metabolic syndrome risk in young men with low cardiorespiratory fitnessPhysiol Genomics201143103921156835 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref28"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>28JiangJGajalakshmiVWangJKurikiKSuzukiSNakamuraSInfluence of the C161T but not Pro12Ala polymorphism in the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma on colorectal cancer in an Indian populationCancer Sci2005965071216108832 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref29"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>29WangXLOosterhofJDuarteNPeroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma C161 →T polymorphism and coronary artery diseaseCardiovasc Res1999445889410690291 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref30"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>30AndersenVChristensenJErnstAJacobsenBATjønnelandAKrarupHBPolymorphisms in NF-κB, PXR, LXR, PPARγ and risk of inflammatory bowel diseaseWorld J Gastroenterol20111719720621245992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref31"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>31PoulsenPAndersenGFengerMHansenTEchwaldSMVølundAImpact of two common polymorphisms in the PPARgamma gene on glucose tolerance and plasma insulin profiles in monozygotic and dizygotic twins: Thrifty genotype, thrifty phenotype, or both?Diabetes200352194812502512 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref32"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>32DallongevilleJIribarrenCFerrièresJLyonLEvansAGoASPeroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma polymorphisms and coronary heart diseasePPAR Res2009200954374620016803 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref33"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>33OrioFJrMatareseGDi BiaseSPalombaSLabellaDSannaVExon 6 and 2 peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma polymorphisms in polycystic ovary syndromeJ Clin Endocrinol Metab20038858879214671186 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref34"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>34KochMRettKMaerkerEVolkAHaistKDeningerMThe silent PPARgamma exon 6 CAC (His)→CAT (His) polymorphism does not affect the plasma leptin levels in a collective of first degree relatives of type 2 diabetes patients from South West GermanyExp Clin Endocrinol Diabetes2000108341610989952 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref35"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>35dbSNP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>(Database of Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms), National Center for Biotechnology Information, National Library of Medicine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>(dbSNP)2012Available from: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/2012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref36"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>36GaoLWangLYunHSuLSuXAssociation of the PPARgamma2 gene Pro12Ala variant with primary hypertension and metabolic lipid disorders in Han Chinese of Inner MongoliaGenet Mol Res2010913122020623456 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref37"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>37LiLLMaXLRanJXSunXFXuLMRenJGenetic polymorphism of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma 2 Pro12Ala on ethnic susceptibility to diabetes in Uygur, Kazak and Han subjectsClin Exp Pharmacol Physiol2008351879117941898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref38"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>38KaydashevIRasinAShlykovaOGorbasISmirnovaIPetrushovAFrequency of Pro12Ala-polymorphism of the Gene PPARγ2 in the Ukrainian population and its possible relation to the development of the metabolic syndromeCytol Genet200741297302 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref39"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>39DragojevičJOstanekBMencej-BedračSKomadinaRPreželjJMarcJPPARG gene promoter polymorphism is associated with non-traumatic hip fracture risk in the elderly Slovenian population: A pilot studyClin Biochem2011441085921756892 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref40"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>40KaoWHCoreshJShuldinerARBoerwinkleEBrayMSBrancatiFLPro12Ala of the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma2 gene is associated with lower serum insulin levels in nonobese African Americans: The Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities StudyDiabetes20035215687212765972 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref41"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>41FarjadianSMoqadamFAGhaderiAHLA class II gene polymorphism in Parsees and Zoroastrians of IranInt J Immunogenet2006331859116712649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
