
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Acta Neuropathol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Acta Neuropathol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Acta Neuropathologica</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0001-6322</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-0533</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3535372</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1024</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00401-012-1024-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Myosinopathies: pathology and mechanisms </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tajsharghi</surname><given-names>Homa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Oldfors</surname><given-names>Anders</given-names></name><address><phone>+46-31-3422084</phone><phone>+46-707338116</phone><fax>+46-31-3422886</fax><email>anders.oldfors@gu.se</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1">Department of Pathology, Institute of Biomedicine, University of Gothenburg, Sahlgrenska University Hospital, 413 45 Gothenburg, Sweden </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>8</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>5</day><month>8</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>125</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>4</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>7</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The myosin heavy chain (MyHC) is the molecular motor of muscle and forms the backbone of the sarcomere thick filaments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Different MyHC isoforms are of importance for the physiological properties of different muscle fiber types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Hereditary myosin myopathies have emerged as an important group of diseases with variable clinical and morphological expression depending on the mutated isoform and type and location of the mutation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Dominant mutations in developmental MyHC isoform genes (MYH3 and MYH8) are associated with distal arthrogryposis syndromes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Dominant or recessive mutations affecting the type IIa MyHC (MYH2) are associated with early-onset myopathies with variable muscle weakness and ophthalmoplegia as a consistent finding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Myopathies with scapuloperoneal, distal or limb-girdle muscle weakness including entities, such as myosin storage myopathy and Laing distal myopathy are the result of usually dominant mutations in the gene for slow/β cardiac MyHC (MYH7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Protein aggregation is part of the features in some of these myopathies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>In myosin storage myopathy protein aggregates are formed by accumulation of myosin beneath the sarcolemma and between myofibrils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>In vitro studies on the effects of different mutations associated with myosin storage myopathy and Laing distal myopathy indicate altered biochemical and biophysical properties of the light meromyosin, which is essential for thick filament assembly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Protein aggregates in the form of tubulofilamentous inclusions in association with vacuolated muscle fibers are present at late stage of dominant myosin IIa myopathy and sometimes in Laing distal myopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>These protein aggregates exhibit features indicating defective degradation of misfolded proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In addition to protein aggregation and muscle fiber degeneration some of the myosin mutations cause functional impairment of the molecular motor adding to the pathogenesis of myosinopathies. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Myopathy</kwd><kwd>Myosin</kwd><kwd>Myosin heavy chain</kwd><kwd>Mutation</kwd><kwd>Myosin storage myopathy</kwd><kwd>Laing distal myopathy</kwd><kwd>Protein aggregate</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg 2013</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Myosin is a highly conserved, ubiquitous protein found in all eukaryotic cells [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>It acts as a molecular motor that converts chemical energy of ATP hydrolysis into mechanical force for diverse cellular movements such as cytokinesis, phagocytosis, and muscle contraction [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Myosins constitute a diverse superfamily and are grouped into different classes including the conventional, or class II, two-headed myosins that form filaments in striated muscle, smooth muscle and non-muscle cells [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The class II conventional muscle myosin exists as a hexameric protein composed of two myosin heavy chain (MyHC) subunits and two pairs of non-identical light chain subunits [57, 64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>MyHCs associate into dimers through a coiled-coil interaction along its long tail, which is termed the rod domain (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Dimerization of two heavy chains results in a polar structure with two distinct regions, which provide the motor and filament-forming functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The amino terminus forms a globular head domain that binds to actin and ATP, which is required for motor activity [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The elongated α-helical coiled-coil C-terminal rod domain exhibits filament-forming properties that assemble into thick filaments of the sarcomeres (Fig. 1) [57].Fig. 1a Electron micrograph of a skeletal muscle sarcomere, demonstrating thick and thin filaments and the banding pattern. b Schematic drawing of the sarcomere demonstrating the thin filaments composed mainly of actin, tropomyosin and the troponin complex and the thick filaments composed mainly of myosin with the myosin heavy chain (MyHC) globular heads interacting with the thin filaments. c Illustration of the MyHC dimer with approximate binding sites for ATP, actin, myosin-binding protein C, myomesin-1, M-protein and titin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The assembly competence domain in the distal rod region is indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The different regions of the MyHC (S1, S2 and light meromyosin, LMM) are indicated by different colors </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Mutations in MyHC genes have been demonstrated to be an important cause of various myopathies, some of which are associated with protein aggregates in muscle fibers [49, 50]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Myosin heavy chain isoforms </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>There are several striated muscle MyHC isoforms encoded by different genes and expressed in a tissue and developmental specific manner [61–63, 84, 85]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In adult human limb skeletal muscle there are three major MyHC isoforms: MyHC I, also called slow/ß-cardiac MyHC, is encoded by MYH7 and is expressed in slow, type 1 muscle fibers as well as in the ventricles of the heart; MyHC IIa (MYH2) is expressed in fast, type 2A muscle fibers and MyHC IIx (MYH1) is expressed in fast, type 2B muscle fibers [66] (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The three different muscle fiber types differ in their contractile and physiological properties, which are partly determined by the different MyHCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In addition, embryonic and perinatal MyHCs, encoded by MYH3 and MYH8, are expressed during fetal development and also during muscle regeneration [24, 31].Table 1Myosin heavy chain isoforms expressed in human muscle </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In addition to the common MyHC isoforms expressed in fibers of adult human limb muscles, there are special MyHC isoforms expressed in specific muscles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Muscles of the head and neck such as the masseter muscle show a more diverse expression of MyHC isoforms than limb muscles [52] and very fast contracting fibers found in extraocular muscles express extraocular MyHC isoform (MYH13) [54]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The non-muscle conventional class II MyHC genes MYH9 and MYH10 encode the non-muscle myosins IIA (MYHIIA) and IIB (MYHIIB), whereas MYH11 encodes smooth muscle MyHC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Myosin heavy chain diseases </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The first striated muscle MyHC isoform associated with disease in humans was slow/β cardiac MyHC (MYH7) [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>More than 200 different dominant mutations in MYH7 have been associated with hypertrophic and dilated cardiomyopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Mutations in slow/α-cardiac MyHC (MYH6) have been reported to cause hypertrophic and dilated cardiomyopathy and atrial septal defect [14, 16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>MYH9-related disorders are autosomal dominant syndromes, variably affecting platelet formation, hearing, and kidney function, and result from mutations in the human nonmuscle myosin IIA heavy chain gene (MYH9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>They have previously been described as distinct disorders including Sebastian, Fechtner and Epstein syndromes and May-Hegglin anomaly [7, 27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The first pure skeletal myopathy associated with an identified MyHC mutation was a MyHC IIa myopathy, associated with a dominant MYH2 mutation that was described in 2000 [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Since then, mutations in genes encoding different MyHC isoforms (MYH2, MYH3, MYH7 and MYH8) have been associated with various skeletal muscle diseases, which are summarized in Table 2.Table 2Myopathies associated with mutations in skeletal muscle myosin heavy chainsEM Electron microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Loss of thick filaments and myosin, but preserved thin filaments can be seen as an unspecific alteration in various conditions such as dermatomyositis but more typically in critical illness myopathy [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>This loss of myosin and other proteins associated with the thick filaments is frequently triggered by systemic corticosteroid hormone treatment, postsynaptic block of neuromuscular transmission and prolonged mechanical ventilation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The loss of myosin can be identified by electron microscopy showing a characteristic disappearance of thick filaments or by measuring the ratio of myosin to actin after separation of muscle proteins by gel electrophoresis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Myopathies associated with developmental MyHC isoforms, MYH3 and MYH8 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The essential roles of embryonic and fetal MyHC isoforms for normal fetal development has been highlighted by the identification of dominant MYH3 and MYH8 mutations associated with distal arthrogryposis (DA) syndromes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>In addition to common DA manifestations such as clubfeet and clenched fists these syndromes frequently include also decreased movement of proximal joints, facial dysmorphism and other manifestations [8, 26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>At least 18 mutations in the globular head and rod domains of MYH3 have been associated with DA1, DA2A (Freeman–Sheldon syndrome) and DA2B (Sheldon–Hall syndrome) [3, 71, 79]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The amino acid at position 672 (R672) is the most frequently mutated residue associated with Freeman–Sheldon syndrome indicating a mutational hotspot of this residue [79]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>One mutation has been identified in MYH8 in several unrelated families with the trismus-pseudocamptodactyly syndrome [78, 82]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, this mutation in MYH8 affects the residue R764 (R764Q), which is paralogous to R672 in MYH3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The embryonic and fetal MyHCs are expressed during embryonic and fetal development [24, 31] and it has been suggested that mutations in MYH3 and MYH8 cause a developmental myopathy resulting in reduced fetal movement and joint contractures [71, 79]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>There are few reports on muscle pathology in distal arthrogryposis associated with MyHC mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>These reports are limited to muscle biopsies from children and adults, which show minor unspecific changes [71]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Myopathies associated with MyHC IIa, MYH2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Dominant as well as recessive mutations in MYH2 that cause myopathy have been identified. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Autosomal dominant MyHC IIa myopathy, which has also been referred to as “autosomal dominant myopathy with congenital joint contractures, ophthalmoplegia and rimmed vacuoles”, was originally identified as a muscle disorder in western Sweden [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The disease was mapped to chromosome 17p13.1 [39] and later demonstrated to be caused by a heterozygous missense mutation in MYH2 encoding MyHC IIa [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The mutation changes the highly conserved and negatively charged glutamate at position 706 to the positively charged lysine (E706K). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The mutated residue is located in the SH1 helix in the core of motor domain, which is highly conserved through evolution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>A prenatal onset of the disease was indicated by multiple joint contractures that were present at birth in the majority of the patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The joint contractures preferentially involved the fingers and/or hips and generally resolved early in childhood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Hypotonia was not a prominent feature and the early development was normal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>External ophthalmoplegia was present in all patients, ranging from a slight impairment of upward gaze in affected children to a generalized ophthalmoparesis in some adult cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The muscle weakness and atrophy predominantly involved proximal muscles of the shoulder and pelvic girdles, and also back and hand muscles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Atrophy of the quadriceps muscles was prominent in the more severely affected adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The muscle weakness was remarkably variable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Most children and adolescents and some adults were mildly affected, whereas some adults had experienced progressive muscle weakness affecting ambulation from age 30 to 50 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>While mildly affected cases had normal serum creatine kinase (s-CK) levels, it was slightly elevated in the family members showing a progressive course. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>A fine action hand tremor has been noticed in several cases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Muscle pathology was highly variable, also in different muscles of the same individual. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>A consistent finding was a predominant involvement of type 2A muscle fibers (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>In children and mildly affected adults the type 2A fibers were reduced in number, frequently smaller than normal and often demonstrating disorganization of myofibrils, similar to what is observed in multi-mini core disease [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Adults with progressive course and increased s-CK levels demonstrated dystrophic muscle pathology with increased interstitial fat and connective tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The presence of rimmed vacuoles in many fibers (Fig. 3) in the more advanced cases was the reason at that time to consider this myopathy as a variant of hereditary inclusion body myopathy (hIBM3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The number of rimmed vacuoles was variable also in the severely affected cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>These rimmed vacuoles are associated with inclusions that stain positively for ubiquitin and sequestosome 1 (SQSM1/p62) (Fig. 4a, b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>SQSM1/p62 is a component of many disease-associated intracellular multiprotein aggregates and a useful marker for the identification of inclusions in sporadic inclusion body myositis [18, 47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>A few inclusions show congophilia (Fig. 4c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Inclusions of tubulofilaments measuring 15–21 nm in diameter are present, usually in association with rimmed vacuoles (Figs. 5, 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Intranuclear filaments can also be observed (Fig. 7).Fig. 2Dominant myosin IIa myopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Biopsy of the deltoid muscle of a 38-year-old man showing alterations of the type 2A fibers (arrows). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>NADH-tetrazolium reductaseFig. 3Dominant myosin IIa myopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Biopsy of the quadriceps muscle of a 38-year-old man demonstrating variability of fiber size, increased interstitial connective tissue, and frequent fibers with rimmed vacuoles. a Hematoxylin and eosin; b Gomori trichromeFig. 4Dominant myosin IIa myopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Several muscle fibers show inclusions that are immunoreactive to antibodies against p62 (a) and ubiquitin (b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Amyloid is present in a few inclusions as revealed by Congo staining and fluorescence microscopy with Texas red filter (c)Fig. 5Dominant myosin IIa myopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Electron microscopy reveals a filamentous inclusion (arrow) associated with a rimmed vacuole with degradation productsFig. 6Dominant myosin IIa myopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Electron microscopy demonstrating an inclusion composed of 15–20 nm tubulofilamentsFig. 7Electron micrograph illustrating intranuclear filaments (arrow) in dominant myosin IIa myopathy </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The severity of the disease was apparently related to the amount of expressed MyHC IIa protein in muscle [75]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Severely affected individuals and muscles showed a large proportion of type 2A muscle fibers, and the fibers with rimmed vacuoles expressed MyHC IIa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Studies on the effects of endurance training have been performed [69, 74]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>An 8-week endurance training program on a stationary exercise bicycle had no adverse effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The peak watt and walking speed increased, but there was no significant increase in muscle strength or isometric endurance [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The training program resulted in a shift in expression from fast to slow MyHC isoforms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>There was no significant change in the MyHC IIa expression, but frequent hybrid fibers expressing more than one MyHC isoform were identified [74]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Patients with recessive MyHC IIa mutations have recently been identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The so far published cases are homozygous or compound heterozygous for truncating mutations in MYH2, accompanied by complete loss of MyHC IIa protein and absence of type 2A muscle fibers [70]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The clinical picture was surprisingly mild with minor or moderate generalized muscle weakness including facial muscle weakness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>A consistent finding was external ophthalmoplegia, which was only occasionally associated with ptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of lower limb muscles in two cases demonstrated selective involvement of certain muscles with fatty infiltration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>There was predominant involvement of medial gastrocnemius in the lower legs, combined with predominant involvement of the semitendinosus, gracilis and vastus lateralis muscles in the thigh. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Muscle biopsy demonstrated in addition to complete loss of MyHC IIa protein, unspecific myopathic changes with fiber size variability, internalized nuclei and interstitial fatty infiltration [70]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Some muscle biopsy samples demonstrated type 1 fiber uniformity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Unlike the dominant MyHC IIa myopathy, no rimmed vacuoles or protein aggregates have been identified. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Myopathies associated with slow/beta MyHC, MYH7 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Overall, mutations in MYH7 are predominantly missense mutations located in the globular myosin head, potentially affecting the binding sites for actin or nucleotides but there are also numerous mutations in the rod region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>More than 200 different mutations have been associated with either hypertrophic or dilated cardiomyopathy, but there are also pure skeletal myopathies and combination of myopathy and cardiomyopathy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Myosin storage myopathy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Myosin storage myopathy is a protein aggregate myopathy associated with myosin accumulation [76]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Mutations that cause myosin storage myopathy are located in the distal end of the tail of slow/β cardiac MyHC, corresponding to exons 37–40 of MYH7 (Fig. 8).Fig. 8Mutation in MYH7 associated with myosin storage myopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>They are all located in the distal rod region of the MyHC </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>A dominant missense mutation changing the highly conserved and positively charged arginine at position 1845 to the uncharged, aromatic tryptophan (R1845W) was the first mutation identified in myosin storage myopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>This mutation has been reported in several unrelated cases indicating that the C nucleotide at position 5533 is a mutational hotspot [32, 34, 55, 65, 76]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Two additional dominant missense mutations, H1901L [10] and L1793P [22], have later been reported to cause myosin storage myopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Recently, a heterozygous A to G transition in exon 40 of MYH7 was reported in several individuals of a five-generation family [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The mutation is predicted to change the terminal stop codon (TAG) to a tryptophan (W), resulting in an elongation of the C-terminal tail region (X1936WfsX32). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Another dominant in frame deletion of the amino acid lysine at position 1784 (K1784del) in exon 37 of MYH7 has recently been reported in a case with myosin storage myopathy [68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Myosin storage myopathy combined with cardiomyopathy was reported in three siblings homozygous for a missense mutation (E1883K), but with apparently unaffected parents [72]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Mutations in the distal rod region of slow/β cardiac MyHC associated with myosin storage myopathy may thus be either dominant or recessive. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Myosin storage myopathy was first reported as a familial myopathy with probable lysis of myofibrils in type 1 fibers by Cancilla et al. [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The inclusions were described as hyaline bodies because of their unstructured appearance at light microscopy [15], and the term hyaline body myopathy was used in some subsequent case reports. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>After the discovery that the storage material consists of mainly myosin heavy chain immunoreactive material and that the mutated gene is the slow/β cardiac MyHC gene, MYH7, the term myosin storage myopathy was introduced [76] and has been adopted and used in most subsequent reports. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The clinical manifestations are highly variable ranging from no weakness to severe impairment of ambulation [9, 11, 13, 15, 34, 42, 55, 59, 65, 68, 76, 81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>This variability can also be present within a family [11, 55, 81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Onset is usually in childhood but may be much later. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Presenting signs and symptoms are often delayed motor milestones, difficulties in climbing stairs or running and a waddling gate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The distribution of muscle weakness is usually proximal in upper extremities with difficulties in lifting the arms above the shoulder level and scapular winging has been described in many cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>In the lower extremities a distal involvement with foot drop is common and pseudo-hypertrophy of the calves is frequently encountered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Apart from a scapulo-peroneal distribution of weakness, a predominant limb-girdle weakness can be seen in some cases [13, 15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The course is usually slowly progressive and scoliosis sometimes supervenes [11, 68] and some patients need assisted ventilation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Evidence of cardiomyopathy associated with the myopathy is usually not found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>However, in one woman with muscle weakness since age 30, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy was diagnosed at age 51 [81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Her 24-year-old daughter presented with cardiac failure already at age 3 months and was diagnosed with signs of left ventricular non-compaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Three severely affected siblings homozygous for apparently recessive mutations had myosin storage myopathy and hypertrophic cardiomyopathy with cardiac failure that was lethal in two cases [72]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of muscle in myosin storage myopathy in ten individuals from one family demonstrated in the lower limbs early involvement of the biceps femoris and semimembranosus muscles and relative sparing of the semitendinosus in the posterior compartment of the thigh [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>In the distal muscles of the legs there was a predominant involvement of the medial gastrocnemius, tibialis anterior, extensor hallucis longus and extensor digitorum longus muscles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>In the upper limbs there was a predominant involvement of the deltoid muscle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>There was no asymmetry. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Muscle biopsy demonstrates the characteristic subsarcolemmal accumulation of material that is slightly eosinophilic and stains light green in trichrome but there is no NADH-tetrazolium-reductase staining (Fig. 9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>By light microscopy the material looks completely unstructured giving it a hyaline appearance (Fig. 10a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>There is no immunoreactivity of dystrophin, sarcoglycans or merosin in relation to the stored material, but immunostaining of desmin and also of αβ-crystalline may show a rim of intense staining around the stored material (Fig. 10b) [11, 55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The stored material is restricted to type 1 fibers and usually demonstrates myofibrillar ATPase activity and immunoreactivity to slow/β cardiac MyHC (Fig. 10c) [11, 51, 55, 68, 76, 81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>However, there are also reports indicating that the accumulated material may be immunoreactive to antibodies against fast myosin isoforms [15, 65]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>We have found the stored material to be immunoreactive with antibodies against ubiquitin (Fig. 10d), which is different from a previous report [11], but we have not identified any p62 positive material. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The stored material shows no cytochrome c oxidase or succinate dehydrogenase activity (Fig. 11a), but there is usually a rim of increased enzyme activity in the periphery corresponding to mitochondria (Fig. 11b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The inclusion bodies are not limited by a membrane but the stored material can be seen between partly disintegrated myofibrils in the vicinity of the main storage body (Figs. 11b, 12a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>At higher magnification the storage material has a granular appearance and a few abortive filaments can be seen (Fig. 12b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The inclusions in myosin storage myopathy differ from those in cap disease as the latter contain remnants of sarcomeres with thickened and fragmented Z-lines and thin filaments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The caps show positive immunostaining to desmin whereas the inclusions in myosin storage myopathy are unstained.Fig. 9Myosin storage myopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>There is fatty infiltration and numerous muscle fibers with subsarcolemmal accumulation of material (arrows) that stains faintly red by hematoxylin–eosin (a) is unstained by NADH-tetrazolium reductase (b) and stains light green in Gomori trichrome (c)Fig. 10Myosin storage myopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The inclusions (arrows) appear unstructured in hematoxylin-eosin (a) and are surrounded by a rim of desmin (b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The inclusions are immunoreactive with antibodies against slow/β cardiac MyHC (c) and ubiquitin (d)Fig. 11Myosin storage myopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The inclusions are surrounded by a rim of increased succinate dehydrogenase activity (arrows) (a), which corresponds to the presence of numerous mitochondria (arrows) around but not within the inclusions as revealed by electron microscopy (b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>There is also storage material between surrounding myofibrils (arrow heads)Fig. 12Myosin storage myopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Electron microscopy of storage material. a The inclusions are not limited by any membrane but instead the storage material can be seen surrounding the adjacent myofibrils (arrows). b The storage material appears granular and party filamentous and some glycogen particles are also present </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Laing (Gowers–Laing) distal myopathy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Most patients reported with Laing distal myopathy have dominant mutations in MYH7 located in exon 32-36 in the mid region of the MyHC rod including: R1500P, E1508del, L1591P, A1603P, K1617del, A1663P, L1706P and K1729del (Fig. 13) [21, 43, 44, 80]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The L1729del mutation has been identified in multiple unrelated patients [44, 45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>However, MYH7-associated distal myopathy is not restricted to mutations in this region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Three mutations have been identified in the globular head (T441M, V606M and R783P) [20, 29, 53], and three mutations have been identified in the distal rod region overlapping with the myosin storage myopathy region (E1801K, E1856K and K1784del) (Fig. 13) [77, 80]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Five of these six mutations were associated with distal myopathy and cardiomyopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Muscle morphology was not reported in the patients with the three distal mutations (K1784del, E1801K and E1856K) [77, 80] and it cannot be excluded that they were cases of myosin storage myopathy, since the K1784del mutation has been associated with myosin storage myopathy [68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>For classification of diseases, which are associated with mutations in the LMM of slow/β cardiac MyHC and may show clinical overlap, it is essential to perform muscle biopsy.Fig. 13Mutations in MYH7 associated with distal myopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>They are mainly located in mid-rod region of the MyHC, but some are located in the globular myosin head and the distal rod </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Laing distal myopathy was first linked to chromosome 14q11 [35, 83], and it was later demonstrated to be caused by mutations in MYH7 [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Most cases have presented early in childhood and hence the term “early-onset” distal myopathy has been used in several reports. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Onset is, however, not always in childhood but can occur with a range from congenital to 50 years [35, 36, 41, 44, 77, 83]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The clinical course in typical cases starts with early-onset weakness of ankle dorsiflexors and a “hanging big toe” sign. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Calf hypertrophy may be present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>During the slowly progressive course finger extensor and neck flexion weakness and later also proximal limb and facial muscle weakness supervenes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Patients usually remain ambulant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Serum CK levels are normal or moderately elevated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Cardiac involvement is usually not a feature of Laing distal myopathy but there are a few exceptions with diseases associated with MYH7 mutations and presenting with distal myopathy as well as cardiomyopathy [20, 29, 53, 80]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Muscle MRI has demonstrated early changes in the anterior compartments of the lower leg especially the extensor hallucis longus and tibialis anterior muscles [21, 44, 77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Later in the course and in more severely affected patients additional muscles in the thigh may be involved. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Muscle pathology has been reported in most case reports and more systematically in patients from a few families [36, 44, 83]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The pathological changes are, unlike those in myosin storage disease, variable and unspecific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Common findings are predominance of type 1 fibers and numerous small type 1 fibers (Fig. 14), which may appear as fiber type disproportion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Internal nuclei are usually present and structural abnormalities, especially minicores, in addition to mitochondrial abnormalities are common. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Muscle fiber necrosis can be seen but is usually not conspicuous. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The muscle may show severe atrophy with fat and connective tissue replacement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Protein aggregates are usually not seen, but rimmed vacuoles and filamentous inclusions of the same type as in MyHC IIa myopathy and inclusion body myositis have been observed [41, 77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>In one case cytoplasmic bodies and myofibrillar alterations similar to those seen in myofibrillar myopathies were reported [77].Fig. 14Tibialis anterior muscle of a 7-year-old boy with MYH7-associated distal myopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Many of the type 1 fibers are small (arrows). a Myofibrillar ATPase, pH 4.3 and b NADH-tetrazolium reductase </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Other skeletal muscle phenotypes associated with MYH7 mutations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Although the most important skeletal muscle manifestations of MYH7 mutations are referred to as either myosin storage myopathy or Laing distal myopathy several cases cannot be classified into these groups because they either do not display distal muscle weakness or do not exhibit hyaline bodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Muscle biopsy of some patients with mutations that are known to cause myosin storage myopathy may not reveal the pathognomonic changes, but instead unspecific changes [55] or alterations diagnostic for congenital fiber type disproportion [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>A few patients with MYH7 mutations that otherwise cause distal myopathy could be classified as having limb-girdle syndrome or scapuloperoneal myopathy thus overlapping with the clinical features of myosin storage myopathy [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>In some but not all patients with cardiomyopathy due to MYH7 mutations, but without overt muscle weakness, cores may be identified in skeletal muscle fibers [23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Pathogenesis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>MYH3 mutations and distal arthrogryposis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>A correct understanding of the cause of distal arthrogryposis due to MYH3 mutations would require examination of muscle pathology during the developmental period when MYH3 is expressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Since MYH3 mutations associated with distal arthtrogryposis are dominant, it may be hypothesized that they affect muscle function during early development through either haploinsufficiency with insufficient dosage of a functional embryonic MyHC or a dominant negative effect of the mutated allele. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Most of the MYH3 mutations are missense, but it is not known whether the mutant allele is expressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Although the hemizygous loss of MyHC IIa expression is tolerated well in individuals with heterozygous MYH2 null mutations [70], the situation may be different with embryonic MyHC, since it is a predominant MyHC isoform expressed during an early period of development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Another possibility would be that MYH3 mutations impose dominant negative effects by functional or structural alterations as seen in dominant mutations affecting the adult MyHC isoforms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>However, studies on disease models are needed to pinpoint the pathogenesis of developmental myopathy caused by MYH3 mutations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The MyHC IIa E706K mutation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>The E706K mutation associated with the autosomal dominant MyHC IIa myopathy has been studied at the molecular level in different systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The mutated residue is situated in the SH1 helix in the core of myosin motor domain, which is strongly conserved throughout the myosin class II family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The SH1 helix plays a central role in the conformational changes of the myosin head during the ATP cycle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Several studies have suggested impaired functional properties as the primary molecular defect of the E706K mutated MyHC protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>In vitro motility studies on myosin IIa isolated from single muscle fibers of patients carrying the E706K mutation clearly showed a marked reduction of speed [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, studies on the motor function of E683K mutant myosin of Dictyosteliumdiscoideum, which is equivalent to the human MyHC IIa E706K mutation, demonstrated a threefold reduction of the ATP hydrolysis step followed by the slower acto-myosin dissociation [87]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Consequently, these effects lead to a reduced velocity of contraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>A transgenic C. elegans was generated to simulate MyHC IIa myopathy in order to assess the functional or structural effects of the E706K mutation [73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Worms that were null mutant for UNC-54 (encoding the major C. elegans myosin heavy chain expressed in body wall muscle) were partly rescued by transfection with wild type UNC-54. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Transfection with a construct encoding UNC-54 with an E710K mutation corresponding to the human MyHC IIa E706K mutation resulted in restored thick filaments but completely paralyzed worms [73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>In addition, mutations in SH1 helix of nonmuscle class II MYHIIA, encoded by MYH9 (R702C and R705H), have been associated with a group of inherited giant-platelet disorders in several families [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Association of diseases with mutations in SH1 helix of myosin in both muscle and non-muscle MyHC illustrates the crucial role of this thiol region in the head of myosin for proper function of the protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>These different studies all point to a severe defect of the molecular motor function caused by the E706K mutation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Structural changes in the muscle fibers and muscle fiber loss are likely to be an additional mechanism causing muscle weakness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Morphological studies on muscle biopsy specimens have demonstrated a clear correlation between the expression of the mutated MyHC IIa and dystrophic changes in muscle [75]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The high expression of mutant protein combined with aging may cause defective elimination of misfolded proteins, resulting in accumulation of protein aggregates and secondary muscle fiber degeneration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>This hypothesis is supported by the accumulation of ubiquitinated and p62-labeled protein aggregates in vacuolated muscle fibers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>This mechanism could be similar to what is seen in inclusion body myositis although the upstream events are different [6, 46, 47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The same mechanism could also be involved in the muscle degeneration and protein aggregation seen in advanced cases of Laing distal myopathy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>In a recent investigation of the molecular background of the mouse mutant ariel a recessive missense mutation, L342Q, in the motor domain of Myh4 was found to cause a myofibrillar myopathy-like phenotype with protein aggregates in fast MyHC IIb fibers [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The mutant protein formed also aggregates in COS7 cells and did not incorporate into thick filaments of C2C12 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>In ariel heterozygotes, which showed no weakness or aggregates, the level of mutant protein was only 7 %, indicating efficient degradation of the defective protein prohibiting protein aggregation. MYH4 is not expressed in human limb muscle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>However, mRNA but not protein has been identified in human masseter muscle [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>A functional equivalent of mouse MyHC IIb is MyHC IIx (MYH1) in humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>So far no disease has been associated with human MYH1 mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Protein aggregation with features similar to those in myofibrillar myopathy and in the ariel mouse was identified in one patient with a mutation in the rod region of MyHC I (MYH7) mutation [77]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>MyHC IIa null mutations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>The selective muscle involvement of certain muscles with fatty infiltration and loss of type 2A muscle fibers with interstitial fatty infiltration in patients with MyHC IIa null myopathy indicate that complete loss of one adult MyHC cannot be compensated for by other MyHC isoforms [70]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>This is further supported by studies on strains of mice null for different MyHC isoforms indicating that different isoforms of MyHC are functionally unique and cannot substitute for one another [1, 2, 60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Mice MyHC IIb or IId null strains are viable but exhibit growth and muscle defects with significant decreases in body mass and mean muscle mass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Although both strains showed evidence of skeletal muscle pathology, the extent and the pattern of affected muscles did not correlate with the abundance and distribution of the two MyHC isoforms in normal mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Together these observations indicate that MyHC isoforms impose unique structural and functional roles and support the hypothesis that MyHC isoforms are unable to replace one another. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Mutations in the LMM region of slow/β-cardiac MyHC </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Mutations in the middle and distal part of the slow/β-cardiac MyHC rod (LMM) region have been associated with several distinct morphological and clinical phenotypes depending on the location of the mutated residue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The assembly of MyHC filaments involves both the proper folding of α-helices into coiled-coils, and the assembly of these coiled-coils into filaments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Defects in any of these steps, caused by mutations, may result in improper filament formation leading to pathological conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Coiled-coils are two-stranded protein motifs, where each strand is an α-helix with seven-residue repeats (a–b–c–d–e–f–g) (Fig. 15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>This heptad repeat generally has apolar residues at the a and d positions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>When the two α-helical strands wrap around one another, the a and d positions are internalized and stabilize the structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Positions b, c, e, f, g are exposed on the surface of the protein, where the side chains are available to interact with other proteins, and they may also form intra- and interchain associations that can further stabilize the structure.Fig. 15The assembly of MyHC LMM rod domain into coiled-coil α-helices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>The heptad repeat motif forms the structural basis for the LMM coiled-coil dimer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The cross-section of the double α-helix coiled-coil with the heptad repeat sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>While the residues at positions a and d form the core of the α-helix, the residues at positions b, c, e, f and g are located at the outer region of the coiled-coil </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Mutations in the LMM region can affect the ability of the protein to form stable and functional thick filaments, based on the amino acid change, the position in the heptad repeat motif and the location in the LMM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Missense mutations associated with myosin storage myopathy (L1793P, R1845W, E1883K and H1901L) are located within or closed to the 29-residue assembly competence domain, in the C-terminus coiled-coil rod region of MyHC, which is known to be critical for the proper assembly of sarcomeric myosin rod filaments [67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>These mutated residues are located either in the outer b or f position, where the side chains are available to interact with other myosin dimers or other proteins, or in the d position that stabilize the structure of the protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Mutations at outer positions may cause improper filament formation through disturbed interaction with other myosin dimers and thereby perturb thick filament assembly. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>A disturbed interaction with other sarcomeric proteins such as titin, myosin-binding proteins (MyBP) C and H, M-protein or myomesin 1, may also be considered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>In this context it is of interest to note that one patient with a mutation in the rod region of MyHC I showed cytoplasmic bodies [77], a type of protein aggregates that are otherwise typically associated with A-band titin (TTN) mutations [48]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>The aberrant accumulations of myosin in the muscle fibers of affected individuals with myosin storage myopathy might be due to improper incorporation of mutated myosin into thick filaments or disassembly of the filaments resulting in accumulation of mutant protein between the myofibrils and beneath the sarcolemma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>The observation that some of the accumulated myosin appears to be ubiquitinated indicates that it is marked to be degraded through the proteasomal pathway [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>The accumulation may be due to insufficient degradation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>It is noteworthy that the inclusion bodies are not labeled by p62, which is otherwise common in protein aggregate diseases [86]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Several in vitro studies have been performed to investigate molecular mechanisms involved in the pathogenesis of diseases caused by mutations in the rod region of muscle MyHC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Biochemical and biophysical characterization of the effects of the myosin storage myopathy mutations in the LMM region have suggested adverse effects of the mutations in the ability of the protein to form stable and functional thick filaments [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>However, analyses of different mutations demonstrated that each mutation has a unique effect on the biochemical and biophysical properties of the LMM [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The pathogenic mechanisms of the R1500P and L1706P causing Laing early-onset distal myopathy have been investigated by biochemical assays and in different cellular systems [5, 12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>By co-expression of wild-type and mutant proteins in non-muscle COS-7 cells, in the C2C12 mouse muscle cell line and in neonatal rat ventricular myocytes, dominant adverse effects could be demonstrated including formation of myosin aggregates [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Generation of transgenic C. elegans indicated that the proline mutations did not affect the thick filament formation or muscle force generation but myosin aggregates were identified in the R1500P mutants [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>It is still unclear why Laing distal myopathy and myosin storage myopathy are associated with different muscle pathologies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Myosin storage myopathy mutations are located in exons 37–40 in the LMM region of slow/β-cardiac MyHC within or close to the assembly competence domain, which is crucial for proper filament assembly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Consequently, mutations in this region may cause defective integration of dimers into the thick filament leading to accumulation of unassembled MyHC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>In contrast, mutations associated with Laing distal myopathy that are situated at distance from the assembly competence domain might cause other effects on the thick filament structure and function leading to different pathology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Further work is needed to get insight into the mechanisms governing the cardiac and/or skeletal muscle involvement as well as the pathogenesis leading to protein aggregation in some of the myosin myopathies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>For this purpose and for classification of the diseases, which may show clinical overlap, it is essential to perform morphological investigations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Based on correlations between genotype and muscle phenotype in humans, the use of animal models in combination with in vitro studies will allow investigation of the disease mechanisms and clarify the functional impact of mutations affecting different isoforms and different domains of the MyHC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the Swedish Research Council Proj. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>No. 07122 and 20628. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><sec id="d29e1797"><title>Open Access</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits any use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>1.Acakpo-SatchiviLJEdelmannWSartoriusCLuBDWahrPAWatkinsSCMetzgerJMLeinwandLKucherlapatiRGrowth and muscle defects in mice lacking adult myosin heavy chain genesJ Cell Biol19971391219122910.1083/jcb.139.5.12199382868 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>2.AllenDLHarrisonBCLeinwandLAInactivation of myosin heavy chain genes in the mouse: diverse and unexpected phenotypesMicrosc Res Tech20005049249910.1002/1097-0029(20000915)50:6&lt;492::AID-JEMT6&gt;3.0.CO;2-J10998638 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>3.AlvaradoDMBuchanJGGurnettCADobbsMBExome sequencing identifies an MYH3 mutation in a family with distal arthrogryposis type 1J Bone Joint Surg Am2011931045105010.2106/JBJS.J.0200421531865 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>4.ArmelTZLeinwandLAMutations in the beta-myosin rod cause myosin storage myopathy via multiple mechanismsProc Natl Acad Sci USA20091066291629610.1073/pnas.090010710619336582 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>5.ArmelTZLeinwandLAMutations at the same amino acid in myosin that cause either skeletal or cardiac myopathy have distinct molecular phenotypesJ Mol Cell Cardiol2010481007101310.1016/j.yjmcc.2009.10.01119854198 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>6.AskanasVEngelWKSporadic inclusion-body myositis: conformational multifactorial ageing-related degenerative muscle disease associated with proteasomal and lysosomal inhibition, endoplasmic reticulum stress, and accumulation of amyloid-beta42 oligomers and phosphorylated tauPresse Med201140e219e23510.1016/j.lpm.2010.11.02421392932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>7.BalduiniCLPecciASavoiaARecent advances in the understanding and management of MYH9-related inherited thrombocytopeniasBr J Haematol201115416117410.1111/j.1365-2141.2011.08716.x21542825 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>8.BamshadMJordeLBCareyJCA revised and extended classification of the distal arthrogryposesAm J Med Genet19966527728110.1002/(SICI)1096-8628(19961111)65:4&lt;277::AID-AJMG6&gt;3.0.CO;2-M8923935 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>9.BarohnRJBrumbackRAMendellJRHyaline body myopathyNeuromuscul Disord1994425726210.1016/0960-8966(94)90027-27522681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>10.BohlegaSAbu-AmeroSNWakilSMCarrollPAl-AmrRLachBAl-SayedYCuplerEJMeyerBFMutation of the slow myosin heavy chain rod domain underlies hyaline body myopathyNeurology2004621518152110.1212/01.WNL.0000123255.92062.3715136674 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>11.BohlegaSLachBMeyerBFAl SaidYKambourisMAl HomsiMCuplerEJAutosomal dominant hyaline body myopathy: clinical variability and pathologic findingsNeurology2003611519152310.1212/01.WNL.0000096022.09887.9D14663035 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>12.BuvoliMBuvoliALeinwandLAEffects of pathogenic proline mutations on Myosin assemblyJ Mol Biol201241580781810.1016/j.jmb.2011.11.04222155079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>13.CancillaPAKalayanaramanKVerityMAMunsatTPearsonCMFamilial myopathy with probable lysis of myofibrils in type I fibersNeurology19712157958510.1212/WNL.21.6.5794104682 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>14.CarnielETaylorMRSinagraGLenardaAKuLFainPRBoucekMMCavanaughJMiocicSSlavovDGrawSLFeigerJZhuXZDaoDFergusonDABristowMRMestroniLAlpha-myosin heavy chain: a sarcomeric gene associated with dilated and hypertrophic phenotypes of cardiomyopathyCirculation2005112545910.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.104.50769915998695 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>15.CeuterickCMartinJJMartensCHyaline bodies in skeletal muscle of a patient with a mild chronic nonprogressive congenital myopathyClin Neuropathol19931279837682901 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>16.ChingYHGhoshTKCrossSJPackhamEAHoneymanLLoughnaSRobinsonTEDearloveAMRibasGBonserAJThomasNRScotterAJCavesLSTyrrellGPNewbury-EcobRAMunnichABonnetDBrookJDMutation in myosin heavy chain 6 causes atrial septal defectNat Genet20053742342810.1038/ng152615735645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>17.CiechanoverAIntracellular protein degradation: from a vague idea thru the lysosome and the ubiquitin-proteasome system and onto human diseases and drug targetingBiochim Biophys Acta2012182431310.1016/j.bbapap.2011.03.00721435401 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>18.D’AgostinoCNogalskaAEngelWKAskanasVIn sporadic inclusion body myositis muscle fibres TDP-43-positive inclusions are less frequent and robust than p62 inclusions, and are not associated with paired helical filamentsNeuropathol Appl Neurobiol20113731532010.1111/j.1365-2990.2010.01108.x20626631 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>19.DarinNKyllermanMWahlstromJMartinssonTOldforsAAutosomal dominant myopathy with congenital joint contractures, ophthalmoplegia, and rimmed vacuolesAnn Neurol19984424224810.1002/ana.4104402159708547 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>20.DarinNTajsharghiHOstman-SmithIGilljamTOldforsANew skeletal myopathy and cardiomyopathy associated with a missense mutation in MYH7Neurology2007682041204210.1212/01.wnl.0000264430.55233.7217548557 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>21.DubourgOMaisonobeTBehinASuominenTRaheemOPenttilaSPartonMEymardBDahlAUddBA novel MYH7 mutation occurring independently in French and Norwegian Laing distal myopathy families and de novo in one Finnish patientJ Neurol20112581157116310.1007/s00415-011-5900-921279644 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>22.DyeDEAzzarelliBGoebelHHLaingNGNovel slow-skeletal myosin (MYH7) mutation in the original myosin storage myopathy kindredNeuromuscul Disord20061635736010.1016/j.nmd.2006.03.01116684601 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>23.FananapazirLDalakasMCCyranFCohnGEpsteinNDMissense mutations in the beta-myosin heavy-chain gene cause central core disease in hypertrophic cardiomyopathyProc Natl Acad Sci USA1993903993399710.1073/pnas.90.9.39938483915 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>24.FeghaliRLeinwandLAMolecular genetic characterization of a developmentally regulated human perinatal myosin heavy chainJ Cell Biol19891081791179710.1083/jcb.108.5.17912715179 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>25.Geisterfer-LowranceAAKassSTanigawaGVosbergHPMcKennaWSeidmanCESeidmanJGA molecular basis for familial hypertrophic cardiomyopathy: a beta cardiac myosin heavy chain gene missense mutationCell199062999100610.1016/0092-8674(90)90274-I1975517 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>26.HallJGReedSDGreeneGThe distal arthrogryposes: delineation of new entities—review and nosologic discussionAm J Med Genet19821118523910.1002/ajmg.13201102087039311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>27.HanKHLeeHKangHGMoonKCLeeJHParkYSHaISAhnHSChoiYCheongHIRenal manifestations of patients with MYH9-related disordersPediatr Nephrol20112654955510.1007/s00467-010-1735-321210153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>28.HeathKECampos-BarrosATorenARozenfeld-GranotGCarlssonLESavigeJDenisonJCGregoryMCWhiteJGBarkerDFGreinacherAEpsteinCJGlucksmanMJMartignettiJANonmuscle myosin heavy chain IIA mutations define a spectrum of autosomal dominant macrothrombocytopenias: May-Hegglin anomaly and Fechtner, Sebastian, Epstein, and Alport-like syndromesAm J Hum Genet2001691033104510.1086/32426711590545 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>29.HomayounHKhavandgarSHooverJMMohsenAWVockleyJLacomisDClemensPRNovel mutation in MYH7 gene associated with distal myopathy and cardiomyopathyNeuromuscul Disord20112121922210.1016/j.nmd.2010.12.00521211974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>30.HortonMJBrandonCAMorrisTJBraunTWYawKMScioteJJAbundant expression of myosin heavy-chain IIB RNA in a subset of human masseter muscle fibresArch Oral Biol2001461039105010.1016/S0003-9969(01)00066-811543711 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>31.Karsch-MizrachiITravisMBlauHLeinwandLAExpression and DNA sequence analysis of a human embryonic skeletal muscle myosin heavy chain geneNucleic Acids Res1989176167617910.1093/nar/17.15.61672771643 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>32.KiphuthICNeuen-JacobEStruffertTWehnerMWallefeldWLaingNSchroderRMyosin storage myopathy: a rare subtype of protein aggregate myopathiesFortschr Neurol Psychiatr20107821922210.1055/s-0029-124514520376763 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>33.KurapatiRMcKennaCLindqvistJWilliamsDSimonMLeProustEBakerJCheesemanMCarrollNDennyPLavalSLochmullerHOchalaJBlancoGMyofibrillar myopathy caused by a mutation in the motor domain of mouse MyHC IIbHum Mol Genet2012211706172410.1093/hmg/ddr60522199023 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>34.LaingNGCeuterick-de GrooteCDyeDELiyanageKDuffRMDuboisBRobberechtWSciotRMartinJJGoebelHHMyosin storage myopathy: slow skeletal myosin (MYH7) mutation in two isolated casesNeurology20056452752910.1212/01.WNL.0000150581.37514.3015699387 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>35.LaingNGLaingBAMeredithCWiltonSDRobbinsPHoneymanKDoroszSKozmanHMastagliaFLKakulasBAAutosomal dominant distal myopathy: linkage to chromosome 14Am J Hum Genet1995564224277847377 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>36.LamontPJUddBMastagliaFLVisserMHederaPVoitTBridgesLRFabianVRozemullerALaingNGLaing early onset distal myopathy: slow myosin defect with variable abnormalities on muscle biopsyJ Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry20067720821510.1136/jnnp.2005.07382516103042 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>37.LarssonLAcute quadriplegic myopathy: an acquired “myosinopathy”Adv Exp Med Biol2008642929810.1007/978-0-387-84847-1_819181096 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>38.LiMLionikasAYuFTajsharghiHOldforsALarssonLMuscle cell and motor protein function in patients with a IIa myosin missense mutation (Glu-706 to Lys)Neuromuscul Disord20061678279110.1016/j.nmd.2006.07.02317005402 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>39.MartinssonTDarinNKyllermanMOldforsAHallbergBWahlstromJDominant hereditary inclusion-body myopathy gene (IBM3) maps to chromosome region 17p13.1Am J Hum Genet1999641420142610.1086/30237510205275 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>40.MartinssonTOldforsADarinNBergKTajsharghiHKyllermanMWahlströmJAutosomal dominant myopathy: missense mutation (Glu-706 to Lys) in the myosin heavy chain IIa geneProc Natl Acad Sci USA200097146141461910.1073/pnas.25028959711114175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>41.MastagliaFLPhillipsBACalaLAMeredithCEgliSAkkariPALaingNGEarly onset chromosome 14-linked distal myopathy (Laing)Neuromuscul Disord20021235035710.1016/S0960-8966(01)00287-512062252 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>42.MasuzugawaSKuzuharaSNaritaYNaitoYTaniguchiAIbiTAutosomal dominant hyaline body myopathy presenting as scapuloperoneal syndrome: clinical features and muscle pathologyNeurology19974825325710.1212/WNL.48.1.2539008527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>43.MeredithCHerrmannRParryCLiyanageKDyeDEDurlingHJDuffRMBeckmanKVisserMGraaffMMHederaPFinkJKPettyEMLamontPFabianVBridgesLVoitTMastagliaFLLaingNGMutations in the slow skeletal muscle fiber myosin myosin chain gene (MYH7) cause Laing early-onset distal myopathy (MPD1)Am J Hum Genet20047570370810.1086/42476015322983 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>44.MuelasNHackmanPLuqueHGarces-SanchezMAzorinISuominenTSevillaTMayordomoFGomezLMartiPMaria MillanJUddBVilchezJJMYH7 gene tail mutation causing myopathic profiles beyond Laing distal myopathyNeurology20107573274110.1212/WNL.0b013e3181eee4d520733148 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>45.MuelasNHackmanPLuqueHSuominenTEspinosCGarces-SanchezMSevillaTAzorinIMillanJUddBVilchezJSpanish MYH7 founder mutation of Italian ancestry causing a large cluster of Laing myopathy patientsClin Genet20128149149410.1111/j.1399-0004.2011.01667.x21395566 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>46.NeedhamMMastagliaFLInclusion body myositis: current pathogenetic concepts and diagnostic and therapeutic approachesLancet Neurol2007662063110.1016/S1474-4422(07)70171-017582362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>47.NogalskaATerraccianoCD’AgostinoCKing EngelWAskanasVp62/SQSTM1 is overexpressed and prominently accumulated in inclusions of sporadic inclusion-body myositis muscle fibers, and can help differentiating it from polymyositis and dermatomyositisActa Neuropathol200911840741310.1007/s00401-009-0564-619557423 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>48.OhlssonMHedbergCBradvikBLindbergCTajsharghiHDanielssonOMelbergAUddBMartinssonTOldforsAHereditary myopathy with early respiratory failure associated with a mutation in A-band titinBrain2012135Pt 61682169410.1093/brain/aws10322577218 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>49.OldforsAHereditary myosin myopathiesNeuromuscul Disord20071735536710.1016/j.nmd.2007.02.00817434305 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>50.OldforsALamontPJThick filament diseasesAdv Exp Med Biol2008642789110.1007/978-0-387-84847-1_719181095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>51.OrtolanoSTarrioRBlanco-AriasPTeijeiraSRodriguez-TrellesFGarcia-MuriasMDelagueVLevyNFernandezJMQuintansBMillanBSCarracedoANavarroCSobridoMJA novel MYH7 mutation links congenital fiber type disproportion and myosin storage myopathyNeuromuscul Disord20112125426210.1016/j.nmd.2010.12.01121288719 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>52.OsterlundCThornellLEErikssonPODifferences in fibre type composition between human masseter and biceps muscles in young and adults reveal unique masseter fibre type growth patternAnat Rec (Hoboken)20112941158116910.1002/ar.2127221634018 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>53.OvereemSSchelhaasHJBlijhamPJGrootscholtenMILaakHJTimmermansJWijngaardAZwartsMJSymptomatic distal myopathy with cardiomyopathy due to a MYH7 mutationNeuromuscul Disord20071749049310.1016/j.nmd.2007.02.00717383184 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>54.Pedrosa-DomellöfFHolmgrenYLucasCAHohJFThornellLEHuman extraocular muscles: unique pattern of myosin heavy chain expression during myotube formationInvest Ophthalmol Vis Sci2000411608161610845576 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>55.PegoraroEGavassiniBFBorsatoCMelaciniPVianelloAStramareRCenacchiGAngeliniCMYH7 gene mutation in myosin storage myopathy and scapulo-peroneal myopathyNeuromuscul Disord20071732132910.1016/j.nmd.2007.01.01017336526 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>56.RaymentIHoldenHMWhittakerMYohnCBLorenzMHolmesKCMilliganRAStructure of the actin–myosin complex and its implications for muscle contractionScience1993261586510.1126/science.83168588316858 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>57.RuppelKMSpudichJAStructure–function analysis of the motor domain of myosinAnnu Rev Cell Dev Biol19961254357310.1146/annurev.cellbio.12.1.5438970737 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>58.RuppelKMSpudichJAStructure-function studies of the myosin motor domain: importance of the 50-kDa cleftMol Biol Cell19967112311368862525 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>59.SahgalVSahgalSA new congenital myopathy: a morphological, cytochemical and histochemical studyActa Neuropathol (Berl)19773722523010.1007/BF00686883193343 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>60.SartoriusCALuBDAcakpo-SatchiviLJacobsenRPByrnesWCLeinwandLAMyosin heavy chains IIa and IId are functionally distinct in the mouseJ Cell Biol199814194395310.1083/jcb.141.4.9439585413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>61.SchiaffinoSFibre types in skeletal muscle: a personal accountActa Physiol (Oxf)201019945146310.1111/j.1748-1716.2010.02130.x20353491 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>62.SchiaffinoSReggianiCMyosin isoforms in mammalian skeletal muscleJ Appl Physiol1994774935018002492 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>63.SchiaffinoSReggianiCMolecular diversity of myofibrillar proteins: gene regulation and functional significancePhysiol Rev1996763714238618961 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>64.SellersJRMyosins: a diverse superfamilyBiochim Biophys Acta2000149632210.1016/S0167-4889(00)00005-710722873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>65.ShingdeMVSpringPJMaxwellAWillsEJHarperCGDyeDELaingNGNorthKNMyosin storage (hyaline body) myopathy: a case reportNeuromuscul Disord20061688288610.1016/j.nmd.2006.09.00117118657 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>66.SmerduVKarsch-MizrachiICampioneMLeinwandLSchiaffinoSType IIx myosin heavy chain transcripts are expressed in type IIb fibers of human skeletal muscleAm J Physiol1994267C1723C17287545970 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>67.SohnRLVikstromKLStraussMCohenCSzent-GyorgyiAGLeinwandLAA 29 residue region of the sarcomeric myosin rod is necessary for filament formationJ Mol Biol199726631733010.1006/jmbi.1996.07909047366 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>68.StalpersXVerripsABraakhekkeJLammensMWijngaardAMostertAScoliosis surgery in a patient with “de novo” myosin storage myopathyNeuromuscul Disord20112181281510.1016/j.nmd.2011.05.00521723124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>69.SunnerhagenKSDarinNTasjharghiHOldforsAThe effects of endurance training in persons with a hereditary myosin myopathyActa Neurol Scand2004110808610.1111/j.1600-0404.2004.00282.x15242414 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>70.TajsharghiHHilton-JonesDRaheemOSaukkonenAMOldforsAUddBHuman disease caused by loss of fast IIa myosin heavy chain due to recessive MYH2 mutationsBrain20101331451145910.1093/brain/awq08320418530 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>71.TajsharghiHKimberEKroksmarkAKJerreRTuliniusMOldforsAEmbryonic myosin heavy-chain mutations cause distal arthrogryposis and developmental myosin myopathy that persists postnatallyArch Neurol2008651083109010.1001/archneur.65.8.108318695058 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>72.TajsharghiHOldforsAMacleodDPSwashMHomozygous mutation in MYH7 in myosin storage myopathy and cardiomyopathyNeurology20076896210.1212/01.wnl.0000257131.13438.2c17372140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>73.TajsharghiHPilonMOldforsAA Caenorhabditis elegans model of the myosin heavy chain IIa E706K mutationAnn Neurol20055844244810.1002/ana.2059416130113 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>74.TajsharghiHStibrant SunnerhagenKDarinNKyllermanMOldforsAInduced shift in myosin heavy chain expression in myosin myopathy by endurance trainingJ Neurol200425117918310.1007/s00415-004-0295-514991352 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>75.TajsharghiHThornellLEDarinNMartinssonTKyllermanMWahlstromJOldforsAMyosin heavy chain IIa gene mutation E706 K is pathogenic and its expression increases with ageNeurology20025878078610.1212/WNL.58.5.78011889243 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>76.TajsharghiHThornellLELindbergCLindvallBHenrikssonKGOldforsAMyosin storage myopathy associated with a heterozygous missense mutation in MYH7Ann Neurol20035449450010.1002/ana.1069314520662 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>77.TascaGRicciEPenttilaSMonforteMGiglioVOttavianiPCamastraGSilvestriGUddBNew phenotype and pathology features in MYH7-related distal myopathyNeuromuscul Disord20122264064710.1016/j.nmd.2012.03.00322521714 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>78.ToydemirRMChenHProudVKMartinRBokhovenHHamelBCTuerlingsJHStratakisCAJordeLBBamshadMJTrismus-pseudocamptodactyly syndrome is caused by recurrent mutation of MYH8Am J Med Genet A20061402387239317041932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR79"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>79.ToydemirRMRutherfordAWhitbyFGJordeLBCareyJCBamshadMJMutations in embryonic myosin heavy chain (MYH3) cause Freeman–Sheldon syndrome and Sheldon–Hall syndromeNat Genet20063856156510.1038/ng177516642020 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR80"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>80.UddB165th ENMC International Workshop: distal myopathies 6–8th February 2009 Naarden, The NetherlandsNeuromuscul Disord20091942943810.1016/j.nmd.2009.04.00219477645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR81"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>81.Uro-CosteEArne-BesMCPellissierJFRichardPLevadeTHeitzFFigarella-BrangerDDelisleMBStriking phenotypic variability in two familial cases of myosin storage myopathy with a MYH7 Leu1793pro mutationNeuromuscul Disord20091916316610.1016/j.nmd.2008.11.01219138847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR82"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>82.VeugelersMBressanMMcDermottDAWeremowiczSMortonCCMabryCCLefaivreJFZunamonADestreeAChaudronJMBassonCTMutation of perinatal myosin heavy chain associated with a Carney complex variantN Engl J Med200435146046910.1056/NEJMoa04058415282353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR83"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>83.VoitTKutzPLeubeBNeuen-JacobESchroderJMCavallottiDVaccarioMLSchaperJBroichPCohnRBaethmannMGohlich-RatmannGScoppettaCHerrmannRAutosomal dominant distal myopathy: further evidence of a chromosome 14 locusNeuromuscul Disord200111111910.1016/S0960-8966(00)00158-911166161 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR84"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>84.WeissALeinwandLAThe mammalian myosin heavy chain gene familyAnnu Rev Cell Dev Biol19961241743910.1146/annurev.cellbio.12.1.4178970733 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR85"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>85.WeissAMcDonoughDWertmanBAcakpo-SatchiviLMontgomeryKKucherlapatiRLeinwandLKrauterKOrganization of human and mouse skeletal myosin heavy chain gene clusters is highly conservedProc Natl Acad Sci USA1999962958296310.1073/pnas.96.6.295810077619 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR86"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>86.ZatloukalKStumptnerCFuchsbichlerAHeidHSchnoelzerMKennerLKleinertRPrinzMAguzziADenkHp62 Is a common component of cytoplasmic inclusions in protein aggregation diseasesAm J Pathol200216025526310.1016/S0002-9440(10)64369-611786419 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR87"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>87.ZengWConibearPBDickensJLCowieRAWakelinSMalnasi-CsizmadiaABagshawCRDynamics of actomyosin interactions in relation to the cross-bridge cyclePhil Trans R Soc B20043591843185510.1098/rstb.2004.152715647160 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
