
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vis Exp</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Vis Exp</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JoVE</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Visualized Experiments : JoVE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1940-087X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MyJove Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3846726</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">50411</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3791/50411</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Medicine</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Techniques for Processing Eyes Implanted With a Retinal Prosthesis for Localized Histopathological Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nayagam</surname><given-names>David A. X.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID1"><sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McGowan</surname><given-names>Ceara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Villalobos</surname><given-names>Joel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Richard A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Salinas-LaRosa</surname><given-names>Cesar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McKelvie</surname><given-names>Penny</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>Irene</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Basa</surname><given-names>Meri</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Justin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Chris E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ID4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="ID1"><sup>1</sup>Bionics Institute</aff><aff id="ID2"><sup>2</sup>Department of Anatomical Pathology, St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne</aff><aff id="ID3"><sup>3</sup>Department of Pathology, University of Melbourne</aff><aff id="ID4"><sup>4</sup>Medical Bionics Department, University of Melbourne</aff><author-notes><fn><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Correspondence to: David A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Nayagam at DNAYAGAM@bionicsinstitute.org </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><issue>78</issue><elocation-id>50411</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2013, Journal of Visualized Experiments</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>With the recent development of retinal prostheses, it is important to develop reliable techniques for assessing the safety of these devices in preclinical studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>However, the standard fixation, preparation, and automated histology procedures are not ideal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Here we describe new procedures for evaluating the health of the retina directly adjacent to an implant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Retinal prostheses feature electrode arrays in contact with eye tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Previous methods have not been able to spatially localize the ocular tissue adjacent to individual electrodes within the array. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>In addition, standard histological processing often results in gross artifactual detachment of the retinal layers when assessing implanted eyes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Consequently, it has been difficult to assess localized damage, if present, caused by implantation and stimulation of an implanted electrode array. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we developed a method for identifying and localizing the ocular tissue adjacent to implanted electrodes using a (color-coded) dye marking scheme, and we modified an eye fixation technique to minimize artifactual retinal detachment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>This method also rendered the sclera translucent, enabling localization of individual electrodes and specific parts of an implant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Finally, we used a matched control to increase the power of the histopathological assessments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>In summary, this method enables reliable and efficient discrimination and assessment of the retinal cytoarchitecture in an implanted eye. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd>Medicine</kwd><kwd>Issue 78</kwd><kwd>Anatomy</kwd><kwd>Physiology</kwd><kwd>Biomedical Engineering</kwd><kwd>Bioengineering</kwd><kwd>Surgery</kwd><kwd>Ophthalmology</kwd><kwd>Pathology</kwd><kwd>Tissue Engineering</kwd><kwd>Prosthesis Implantation</kwd><kwd>Implantable Neurostimulators</kwd><kwd>Implants</kwd><kwd>Experimental</kwd><kwd>Histology</kwd><kwd>bionics</kwd><kwd>Retina</kwd><kwd>Prosthesis</kwd><kwd>Bionic Eye</kwd><kwd>Retinal</kwd><kwd>Implant</kwd><kwd>Suprachoroidal</kwd><kwd>Fixation</kwd><kwd>Localization</kwd><kwd>Safety</kwd><kwd>Preclinical</kwd><kwd>dissection</kwd><kwd>embedding</kwd><kwd>staining</kwd><kwd>tissue</kwd><kwd>surgical techniques</kwd><kwd>clinical techniques</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="Fig_50411" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><alternatives><media id="Video_50411" xlink:href="jove-78-50411.mp4" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mp4" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" position="anchor"/><graphic xlink:href="jove-78-50411-thumb"/></alternatives></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Retinal prostheses may soon become useful clinical interventions for treating various forms of severe vision loss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Certain conditions, such as retinitis pigmentosa (RP), result in the widespread degeneration of the photoreceptors in the eye; these are the cells responsible for transducing light into neural signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>However, some cells in other layers of the retina remain and are potential targets for electrical stimulation with a retinal prosthesis 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Early results from human clinical trials have been promising for electrode arrays implanted in the epiretinal 2,3, subretinal 4,5, and intrascleral 6 locations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>These devices are made from different materials with different shapes, but they all use electrical pulses to activate the remaining viable neurons of the retina in order to create visual percepts. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Our wider group (Bionic Vision Australia) has developed a retinal implant that has progressed to a clinical pilot study with 3 RP patients implanted with suprachoroidal electrode arrays (Clinical Trial Number: NCT01603576). Figure 1A shows this suprachoroidal prototype retinal prosthesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Patient safety is paramount in clinical studies and thus, before commencing human trials, we performed extensive acute and chronic testing in preclinical models (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Histopathological assessments were essential to refine the surgical procedures, iterate through electrode design, and ultimately establish the safety of the implant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>To maintain an efficient workflow dovetailed with standard clinical pathology practices, a paraffin embedding technique was employed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>It was also desirable to utilize staining procedures comparable with clinical standards, such as haematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E), which are readily interpreted by pathologists. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>We also wanted a technique that could be adapted for immunohistochemical analyses, in order to facilitate further cellular evaluation of the tissues. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The biocompatibility of the implant materials, and the safety of chronic electrical stimulation, need to be carefully assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>It is important to be able to examine the histopathology of the ocular tissue adjacent to the individual stimulating electrodes within the array. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>However, the arrays needed to be removed prior to processing the samples so they can be tested, and because their metallic components could not be readily sectioned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Consequently, our established tissue preparation did not permit localization and mapping of tissue with respect to the implanted electrodes 7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In addition to the lack of a tissue localization method, the standard formaldehyde-based fixation and processing techniques resulted in widespread artifacts and detachment of the retinal due to the differential shrinkage of the various layers of the eye (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Due to the non-homogeneity of the retina, it was difficult to make valid comparisons with control tissue, particularly for quantitative measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>These combined limitations complicated accurate assessments of the potential damage caused by our implanted arrays. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Here we present novel techniques for overcoming these limitations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>We have modified specialized eye fixation and processing techniques 8-10 to maintain compatibility with paraffin-based histology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>We have modified standard histological and immunohistochemical stains to give comparable results, based on feedback from clinical pathologists. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>After rendering the scleral tissue translucent, a dye-based color-code was employed to mark the ocular tissue adjacent to each individual electrode, before removing the array from the suprachoroidal space. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>By marking the electrode array and the individual electrode sites, samples could be accurately collected from electrode adjacent regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Matched samples could be gathered from the control eye in order to facilitate pairwise comparisons. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Protocol </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Enucleation and Post-Fixation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>This protocol assumes that the subject has been implanted unilaterally with a suprachoroidal electrode array. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Prepare postfix solutions in glass Schott bottles. Davidson's fixative solution, 2x 100 ml 2 ml formalin (37% formaldehyde)10 ml glacial acetic acid (99.7%)35 ml ethanol (98%)53 ml distilled water 50% ethanol, 2x 100 ml70% ethanol, 2x 100 ml </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Transcardially perfuse subject with warm (37 °C) heparinized saline followed by cold (4 °C) neutral buffered formalin (10%). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Tie sutures at the superior limbus (or a location that is remote from the suprachoroidal array) of both eyes - in line with a rectus muscle, to serve as a landmark. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Enucleate eyes, maintaining any external leads from the implanted eye. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Place each eye in 100 ml of Davidson's fixative solution and leave to post-fix at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>After 18 - 36 hr in Davidson's fixative, transfer to 50% ethanol (room temperature) for 6 - 8 hr, then finally to 70% ethanol (room temperature). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Refrigerate samples at 4 °C and store until dissection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Intact and pressurized eye globes have been stored in this manner for up to 3 months without adversely affecting the resultant histology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Identification and Tissue Mapping </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The above fixation protocol (step 1) has rendered the sclera translucent and the array is now visible - including the individual electrode sites (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Remove the implanted globe from ethanol and carefully trim away excess tissue, including conjunctiva and Tenon's capsule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Trim optic nerve to a 2 - 3 mm length (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Using a histological dye marking scheme, label the electrodes with a predefined color code, taking care not to smudge the dye. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>We chose a commercially available suite of specialized histological dye (refer to appendix). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Small amounts of the dye were carefully applied with a fine tipped paint brush (Roymac size 00) to the tissue and allowed to air dry for up to 5 min. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>For our purposes, we have chosen: green for the active electrode(s) that was(were) stimulated maximally, at suprathreshold levels, for the duration of the study; red for other active electrodes; yellow for the larger diameter return electrodes; and blue for additional guides and/or anatomical distance markings (Figures 3B and 3C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Some trial and error may be required to find a dye that is stable throughout the subsequent steps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>For example, in Figure 4, it can be seen that the green dye was more resilient than the red dye. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Diluting the dye in 70% ethanol helps improve lipid penetration and tissue coating. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>It is useful to sketch or photograph the dyed globe for future reference. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list><list list-type="order"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Return to 70% ethanol to dehydrate the dye. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Repeat step 2.1 for the unimplanted control globe. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Using the sutures from step 1.3, align the control eye and the implanted eye as a mirrored pair. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Place a silicone template (with the same dimensions as the electrode array) in the mirrored location on the control eye as the implant is located on implanted eye (N.B. the translucent sclera and the dye markings from step 2.2 allow ready visualization of the implanted array position). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Perform steps 2.2 and 2.3 for the control eye, so that each implanted electrode site has a control pair in an anatomically comparable (i.e. mirror matched equivalent) location. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Dissection and Embedding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><list list-type="order"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Remove the implant array from the eye and remove the front of the eye (including the cornea, iris and lens). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Remove the vitreous fluid from the remaining eye cup (posterior chamber). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Dissect the implanted eye into multiple representative strips (~2 mm thickness) each containing a subset of the dye marked regions (Figure 3D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Note that the orientation of the strips should be selected to assist in assessing various aspects of the tissue response to the implant7. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>It is useful, for future reference, to make a record of which dye regions are present on each strip and their relative locations (and colors). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Place the strip on its side into a shallow pool of liquefied agar (4%; 80 - 90 °C) with the side to be cut first facing downwards (Figure 3E). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Once the agar has set, cut around the sample and place into a tissue cassette supported by foam inserts (Figure 3F). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Repeat steps 3.1-3.3 for the control eye - taking care to dissect mirror-matched strips. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Process all cassettes via standard (automated overnight) paraffin processing technique. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Embed processed tissue in paraffin with the side to be cut first facing downwards. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Cutting and Staining </plain></SENT>
</text></title><list list-type="order"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Cut paraffin blocks into 5 μm sections referring regularly to the notes from Steps 2 and 3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Collect sections from each of the dyed regions and mount on slides. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The region immediately adjacent to each dyed spot of sclera can now be assessed with confidence that it was in closest proximity to the corresponding electrode in the array (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Stain or perform immunofluorescence as desired. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Example stains and immunohistochemistry shown in Figure 5 are: H&amp;E; Luxol fast blue (LFB); cresyl violet; Masson's trichrome blue; periodic acid schiff (PAS); Perls' Prussian blue stain; anti-glutamine synthetase (GS); anti-neurofilament protein (NF); anti-glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP) and 4',6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Standard and special stains were performed as detailed: H&amp;E staining was performed according to the protocol provided by Leica multistainer bath array ST5020 (Leica Biosystems).LFB and cresyl violet (modified from 11): Dewax in 3 changes of xylene (3x 2 min) and 2 changes of ethanol (100%, 100%) (2x 1 min) and rinse in tap water (45 sec).Hydrate sections to 95% ethanol.Place in LFB solution 11 at 37 - 42 °C (overnight).Rinse off excess stain with 70% ethanol.Rinse in distilled water.Place in dilute lithium carbonate (8%) (few seconds).Differentiate in 70% ethanol (few seconds).Rinse in distilled water.Repeat steps 4.4.2.6 to 4.4.2.8, if necessary, until background is colorless.Place in cresyl violet acetate working solution at 37 °C (10 min).Do not wash in water.Dehydrate in 3 changes of absolute alcohol (1x 30 sec, 2x 20 sec) and 3 changes of xylene (1x 1 min 30 sec, 2x 1 min).Mount and coverslip with DPX. Masson's trichrome blue (modified from 11): Dewax as per 4.4.2.1.Bring sections to water (2 min).Stain the nuclei using Weigert's iron haematoxylin (2 min).Wash in tap water, rinse in distilled water.Stain in Biebrich scarlet-acid fuchsin solution (5 min).Rinse in distilled water.Differentiate in phosphomolybdic-phosphotungstic acid until collagen is pale pink (6 min).Rinse in distilled water.Counterstain in aniline blue (1 min).Wash well in 1% acetic acid (1 min).Dehydrate, mount and coverslip as per 4.4.2.12 and 4.4.2.13. PAS (modified from 11): Dewax as per 4.4.2.1.Oxidize in 1% periodic acid (15 min).Wash in running water then distilled water.Stain in Schiff's reagent (15 min).Wash in water (5 min).Counterstain with Harris haematoxylin (1 min).Wash briefly in tap water.Differentiate in 0.5% acid alcohol (1 dip).Wash well in tap water.Blue in Scott's tap water (1 min).Wash well in water.Dehydrate, mount and coverslip as per 4.4.2.12 and 4.4.2.13. Perls' Prussian blue stain as described in 11. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item><list-item><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescence staining was performed as detailed: Dewax as per 4.4.2.1.Rinse in distilled water (2x 5 min).Perform antigen retrieval using 0.01% citrate buffer, pH 6 at 75 - 80 °C (20 min) and allow to cool in 0.01% citrate buffer solution (20 min).Wash sections in phosphate buffered saline (PBS) (2x 5 min).Permeabilize the cell membrane in wash buffer solution (10 min).Incubate in serum block solution (2 hr).Incubate sections in a single primary antibody diluted in antibody diluent (10% normal goat serum/0.1% Triton X-100/PBS) (overnight in fridge). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The titre of each primary antibody used is shown in Table 1.After overnight incubation, wash sections in wash buffer solution (5x 3 min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>From this point on, keep sections in the dark.Incubate sections in the corresponding secondary antibody at a titre of 1:500 for a specific duration (see Table 1 for details).Wash sections in wash buffer solution (3x 5 min).Incubate sections in DAPI (1:25,000 / PBS) (30 min).Wash sections in wash buffer solution (3x 5 min).Mount and coverslip using fluorescent mounting media. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></list-item></list><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Test samples and control samples are ready for pairwise comparison. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Representative Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Figure 4 shows a representative section obtained from cutting the sample depicted in Figure 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The section was cut at 5 μm thickness and stained with H&amp;E according to the protocols described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The gross shape of the sample strip is preserved with minimal differential tissue artifacts (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Both dye markings were visible on the sclera, although the green dye was more resilient than the red (Figure 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The retinal layers were not artifactually detached and the retinal morphology is preserved (Figure 4C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The retinal tissue adjacent to the dye markings, which corresponds to the location of the electrodes in the array, can be readily identified. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Figure 5 shows representative special staining and immunohistochemistry of tissue sections prepared according to the current protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Refer to Figure 5 caption and Supplementary Materials for more detail on the specific stains and the modifications made to their usage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Post-modification, these stains and immunohistochemistry were equivalent to established standards - as verified by pathologists. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><table-wrap orientation="portrait" id="d36e755" position="float"/><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Antibody Type, Titre and Duration of Labeling. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Figure 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Suprachoroidal Prototype Electrode Array. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>A) Macro photograph of a clinical grade molded array. B) Photomicrograph of a handmade preclinical array. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Figure 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Former Retinal Histology. Standard histological methods were used to prepare these, H&amp;E stained, sections of an eye implanted with a suprachoroidal electrode array. A) An orthogonal section through the electrode array cavity (depicted by a star). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The retina is detached from the outer eye tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>This is particularly evident beneath the implanted region (arrow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>It is impossible to determine which portion of retina was adjacent to each individual electrode of the array. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Scalebar = 1 mm. B) A higher magnification of the boxed region in Panel A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>There are several, regularly spaced, artifacts in the retinal layers (arrows), as well as major detachment from the tapetal layer (the reflective layer in feline eyes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Scalebar = 100 μm. C) A higher magnification of the boxed region in panel B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Arrow indicated the outer segments of the photoreceptors, as well as the pigmental epithelium, which remain intact, suggesting that the detachment was an artifactual side-effect of the processing, as opposed to being caused by an in vivo trauma or pathology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Scalebar = 20 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Figure 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Localization and Dissection of Electrode-Adjacent Tissue.A-D) High dynamic range macro photographs of an enucleated eye, with a suprachoroidal electrode array in situ. A) Post fixed with Davidson's fixative, and prior to array removal, the translucent sclera enables visualization of the individual electrodes in the array (single example indicated with arrow). B) The electrodes are marked with a predefined dye color. C) Dye markings at regular spacing from anatomical landmarks are used to maintain consistency across experiments. D) Upon removal of the array, the eye is dissected by hand into sample strips. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Colored arrows indicate two of the electrode adjacent sites on the sclera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Yellow dashed line indicates plane of sectioning. E) Macro-photograph of sample strip embedded within an agar block. F) Macro photograph of the agar-embed sample strip from Panel E, cut out and placed in an embedding cassette supported by foam biopsy pads to minimize movement of the section during processing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Figure 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>New Retinal Histology. The above sample strip (from Figure 3D), containing the electrode pocket, was paraffin embedded, sectioned at 5 μm and stained with H&amp;E. A) Green and red dyed regions (indicated by arrows, same as Figure 3D) are visible in a section taken at the level of the yellow dashed line in Figure 3D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Scale bar = 1,000 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The retina is not detached, neither beneath the array pocket nor remotely. B) The boxed region from Panel A with visible red and green dye indicated by arrows, and intact retina throughout. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Scale bar = 500 μm. C) The boxed region from Panel B, showing the intact, attached, retina adjacent to the green dye. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Scale bar = 50 μm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Knowing that the location of the dye indicates the position of an electrode, we can confidently assess the adjacent retinal tissue for damage, if any, caused by electrical stimulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Figure 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Examples of modified retinal cytohistochemistry using special stains and immunofluorescence. The use of Davidson's fixative, as opposed to standard formalin fixation techniques, required alterations to the usual staining protocols, as outlined in the main protocol text. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Pathologists have confirmed that these modifications resulted in equivalent staining. A) H&amp;E; haematoxylin stains cell nuclei purple while eosin stains cell cytoplasm, collagen and supportive tissue various shades of pink. B) LFB stains myelin blue while the cresyl violet counterstain can be used to identify ganglion cells by staining Nissl bodies within the perikaryon blue and highlighting the satellite cells surrounding the cells. C) Masson's trichrome blue; the Biebrich scarlet-acid fuchsin solution stains muscle fibers red, while the aniline blue stains the collagen, in this case sclera, blue. D) PAS; glycoprotein components of basement membrane and connective tissue components are stained purple, while the haematoxylin counterstains cell nuclei purple. E) Perls' Prussian blue; at the site of haemorrhage, the formation of haemosiderin from degraded red blood cells and release of iron complexes produces a purple color while the addition of neutral red stain colors lysosomes red. F) GS; this neurotransmitter degrading enzyme found in Müller cells 13 (green), can be seen extending in both directions with the Müller cell bodies in the inner nuclear layer and Müller cell endfeet forming the inner limiting membrane. G) NF-200; this heavy chain cytoskeletal protein (green) found in the cell soma and processes, crosslinks with other neurofilaments to maintain the structure of neurons 14,15. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Ganglion cells and their axons can be seen in the ganglion cell layer and nerve fiber layer, while axons of horizontal cells located at the outer boarder of the inner nuclear layer in the feline retina, are also highlighted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Counterstaining with DAPI (blue) allows visualization of retinal layers. H) GFAP; this cytoskeletal protein (red) proliferated in Müller cells and astrocytes during gliosis 16, can be seen lining the nerve fiber layer with Müller cells forming thin extensions through the inner to outer retinal layers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Counterstaining with DAPI (blue) allows for visualization of the retinal layers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Scale bar = 50 μm in all panels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The inner retina is shown at the top of each image; the outer retina is shown at the bottom of each image, excluding Panel E, which shows subscleral reaction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Assessing the safety of the implant is a primary consideration for preclinical studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Before a retinal prosthesis can be implanted in humans it is essential to verify that it will not cause any harm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>This requires an assessment of both the implant biocompatibility 17-23 as well as any potential damage that could be caused by chronic electrical stimulation 24-26. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Experience with similar neural prostheses, such as the cochlear implant, provides insight into the broad range of stimulation, and physical, parameters that do not cause tissue damage 27. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>However, the retina has different characteristics to other implantation sites and therefore precise safety limits (such as maximum charge density) cannot be assumed from previous studies in other systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Charge densities are highest at the active electrode sites and this corresponds with the greatest potential for damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Therefore a method for localizing the tissue directly adjacent to the individual active electrodes would greatly increase the usefulness of these studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The tissue adjacent to specific regions of the implant may also be highlighted for closer inspection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>This targeted approach permits fewer sections to be analyzed, whilst retaining confidence that the "worst case scenario" was examined. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The scleral dye localization method described here has been extensively tested with hand-shaped and molded silicone/Pt electrode arrays 28-30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>It has been used with thin-film polyamide arrays 7,31 and also thin-film silicone/Pt arrays 32. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Some retinal prosthesis studies employed "bullet shaped" electrodes with intrascleral implantations 33. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The present technique should be effective for assessing this type of electrode arrays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Feline eyes with thin sclera (thickness at posterior pole 90 - 200 μm) allowed visualization of individual electrodes in an array. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>However, even if individual electrodes were not visible, their positions could be readily inferred using a silicone template when the outline of the array can be seen (similar to that used in step 2.6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The dye mapping limits the need to obtain non-relevant tissue sections as only sections with the dye present are obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The ability to accurately infer electrode position not only allows relevant histopathological analysis and greater statistical power, but has a major impact on time and cost management by reducing the quantity of slides and blades used as well as the cost of labor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The use of dye that is adherent and can withstand tissue processing whilst also being visible in unstained tissue sections is an important initial consideration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Knowledge of the location of the dye and orientation of the tissue at dissection and during embedding assists the cutting process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>This includes correctly orientating the block to achieve a section that is not obliquely cut and gives a full representation of the tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>It is therefore important that the person performing the cutting is present at the time of dye application, dissection and embedding. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The overall protocol is robust to minor alteration, particularly with fixation timings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>However, the eye dissection and dye marking steps are delicate procedures that benefit from good manual dexterity to avoid damaging the specimen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Whilst Davidson's fixative has proved effective for reducing artifactual detachment of the retina near an implant, it does not prevent direct mechanical damage during dissection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Davidson's fixative was not readily compatible with some special histological and immunohistochemical procedures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Therefore there was a need to modify/optimize these steps as detailed above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Incremental changes in staining times and concentrations were made until the optimum result was achieved - for more details, refer to the supplementary materials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Quantification of retinal histology remains problematic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The retina is non-homogeneous and both the thickness and the cell density change with increasing distance from area centralis 34,35. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Therefore, neighboring tissue within the implanted eye cannot be used for comparisons and a control eye is employed instead. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Pairwise matching of each section with the control eye gives us a more powerful statistical comparison of pathological changes; efficacy and safety outcomes with retinal prosthetics are better assessed when comparing the fellow eyes in a subject 36. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Special care must be taken to minimize oblique cutting as this would affect quantification. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>In summary, the methods described above have significantly improved our histopathological analysis, which in turn has led to a more efficient preclinical workflow. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The results of preclinical studies using these methods directly led to a clinical trial in which 3 RP patients have been safely implanted with suprachoroidal retinal prostheses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>These methods are relevant both to retinal stimulators and other ocular implants where the pathological response to long term implantation needs to be evaluated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>This method provided worthwhile advantages for maintaining the cytoarchitecture and registration of the pathology to regions of interest on the implant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Although not specifically tested, a modification of these procedures may be used in other species and other anatomical locations, particularly where an array is implanted superficially. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Disclosures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Authors have nothing to disclose. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The authors wish to thank: Ms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Alexia Saunders and Ms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Michelle McPhedran for experimental assistance; Ms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Helen Feng for electrode fabrication; Dr. Penny Allen and Dr. Jonathan Yeoh for surgical assistance; Staff of the Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital's Biological Research Centre for animal care; Prof. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Rob Shepherd for general guidance throughout; and Dr. Bryony Nayagam and Mr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Ronald Leung for critical comments on a draft form of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>This work was performed at the Bionics Institute and St Vincent's Hospital, Melbourne. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Funding was provided by the Ian Potter Foundation, the John T Reid Charitable Trusts, and the Australian Research Council through its Special Research Initiative in Bionic Vision Science and Technology grant to Bionic Vision Australia (BVA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The Bionics Institute acknowledges the support it receives from the Victorian Government through its Operational Infrastructure Support Program. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B0"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>SantosAHumayunMSPreservation of the inner retina in retinitis pigmentosaArch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol19971155115159109761 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>HumayunMSWeilandJDVisual perception in a blind subject with a chronic microelectronic retinal prosthesisVision Res2003432573258113129543 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>RoesslerGLaubeTAngiographic findings folowing tack fixation of a wireless epiretinal retina implant device in blind RP patientsGraefes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Arch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol20112491281128621465287 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>ChowAYChowVYThe artificial silicon retina microchip for the treatment of vision loss from retinitis pigmentosaArch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol200412246046915078662 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>ZrennerEBartz-SchmidtKUSubretinal electronic chips allow blind patients to read letters and combine them to wordsProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>B201127814891497 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>FujikadoTKameiMTesting of semichronically implanted retinal prosthesis by suprachoroidal-transretinal stimulation in patients with retinitis pigmentosaInvest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Vis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Sci2011524726473321436271 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>VillalobosJAllenPJDevelopment of a surgical approach for a wide-view suprachoroidal retinal prosthesis: evaluation of implantation traumaGraefes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Arch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol201225039940721874343 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>LatendresseJRWarbittionARJonassenHCreasyDMFixation of testes and eyes using a modified Davidson's fluid: comparison with Bouin's fluid and conventional Davidson's fluidToxicol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Pathol20023052453312187944 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>AgrawalRNHeSIn vivo models of proliferative vitreoretinopathyNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Protoc20072677717401340 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>MargoCELeeAFixation of whole eyes: the role of fixative osmolarity in the production of tissue artifactGraefes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Arch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol19952333663707672624 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>BancroftJDGambleMTheory and practice of histological techniques20086Churchill Livingstone </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>HorobinRWBancroftJDTroubleshooting histology stains1998Churchill Livingstone </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>PowDVRobinsonSRGlutamante in some retinal neurons is derived solely from gliaNeuroscience1994603553667915410 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>LewisSENixonRAMultiple phosphorylated variants of the high molecular mass subunit of neurofilaments in axons of retinal cell neurons: characterization and evidence for their differential association with stationary and moving neurofilamentsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Cell Biol1988107268927013144556 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Ruiz-EderraJGarcíaMHicksDVecinoEComparative study of the three neurofilament subunits within pig and human retinal ganglion cellsMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Vis200410839214961007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>BringmannAPannickeTMüller cells in the healthy and diseased retinaProg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Retin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Eye Res20062539742416839797 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>SeoJMKimSJBiocompatibility of polyimide microelectrode array for retinal stimulationMater. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Eng. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>C200424185189 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>GerdingHBennerFPTaneriSExperimental implantation of epiretinal retina implants (EPI-RET) with an IOL-type receiver unitJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Neural Eng20074S38S4917325415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>MajjiABHumayunMSLong-term histological and electrophysiological results of an inactive epiretinal electrode array implantation in dogsInvest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Vis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Sci1999402073208110440263 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>WalterPSzurmanPSuccessful long-term implantation of electrically inactive epiretinal microelectrode arrays in rabbitsRetina19991954655210606457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>PardueMTStubbsEBJrImmunohistochemical studies of the retina following long-term implantation with subretinal microphotodiode arraysExp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Eye Res20017333334311520108 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>GekelerFSzurmanPCompound subretinal prostheses with extra-ocular parts designed for human trials: successful long-term implantation in pigsGraefes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Arch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol200724523024116645861 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>MontezumaSRLoewensteinJIScholzCRizzoJFIIIBiocompatibility of materials implanted into the subretinal space of Yucatan minipigsInvest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Vis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Sci2006473514352216877423 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>MontezumaSRLoewensteinJIScholzCRizzoJFIIIBiocompatibility of materials implanted into the subretinal space of Yucatan minipigsInvest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Vis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Sci2006473514352216877423 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>RayAColodettiLImmunocytochemical analysis of retinal neurons under electrical stimulationBrain Res20091255899719103179 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>NakauchiKFujikadoTThreshold suprachoroidal-transretinal stimulation current resulting in retinal damage in rabbitsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Neural. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Eng20074S50S5717325416 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>ShepherdRKMurrayMTHoughtonMEClarkGMScanning electron microscopy of chronically stimulated platinum intracochlear electrodesBiomaterials198562372423840392 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Villalobos VillaJSafety of a Wide-Field Suprachoroidal Retinal Prosthesis2012The University of Melbourne </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>NayagamDAXAllenPJA Pre-Clinical Model for Chronic Electrical Stimulation of the Retina via Suprachoroidal Electrodes2012Association for Research in Vision and Ophthalmology Annual MeetingFort Lauderdale, Florida, USA </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>NayagamDAXVillalobosJA Suprachoroidal Retinal Prosthesis is Safe in a Chronic Implantation Modelin Vision and Ophthalmology Annual Meeting., Vol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>4928/A3272011Association for Research in Vision and Ophthalmology Annual MeetingFort Lauderdale, Florida, USA </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>CicioneRShivdasaniMNVisual cortex responses to suprachoroidal electrical stimulation of the retina: effects of electrode return configurationJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Neural Eng2012903600922595310 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>SchuettlerMStiessSKingBVSuaningGJFabrication of implantable microelectrode arrays by laser cutting of silicone rubber and platinum foilJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Neural Eng20052S121S12815876647 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>MorimotoTKameiMChronic implantation of newly developed suprachoroidal-transretinal stimulation prosthesis in dogsInvest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Ophthalmol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Vis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Sci2011526785679221743012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>BronAJTripathiRCTripathiBJWolff's anatomy of the eye and orbit2001Arnold </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>SteinJJJohnsonSABersonDMDistribution and coverage of beta cells in the cat retinaJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Comp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Neurol19963725976178876456 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>DagnelieGPsychophysical evaluation for visual prosthesisAnnu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Biomed Eng20081033936818429703 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
