
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3391261</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22792273</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-00248</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0040307</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzymes</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzyme Classes</subject><subj-group><subject>Transferases</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Enzyme Metabolism</subject><subject>Enzyme Regulation</subject><subject>Enzyme Structure</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Metabolism</subject><subj-group><subject>Biosynthesis</subject><subject>Metabolic Pathways</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cofactors</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biophysics</subject><subj-group><subject>Biomacromolecule-Ligand Interactions</subject><subject>Protein Chemistry</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Characteristic Features of Kynurenine Aminotransferase Allosterically Regulated by (Alpha)-Ketoglutarate in Cooperation with Kynurenine </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Regulation Mechanisms of KAT</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>Ken</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Angkawidjaja</surname><given-names>Clement</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koga</surname><given-names>Yuichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>Kazufumi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kanaya</surname><given-names>Shigenori</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Material and Life Science, Graduate School of Engineering, Osaka University, Osaka, Japan</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Core Research for Evolutional Science and Technology, Japan Science and Technology Agency, Osaka, Japan</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Vertessy</surname><given-names>Beata G.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Institute of Enzymology of the Hungarian Academy of Science, Hungary</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>okadak@mls.eng.osaka-u.ac.jp</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: KO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: KO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: KO CA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YK KT SK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: KO SK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Helped in interpretation of data and discussion of results: YK KT SK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Reviewed the manuscript: KO CA YK KT SK. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>7</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>e40307</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>6</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Okada et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Kynurenine aminotransferase from Pyrococcus horikoshii OT3 (PhKAT), which is a homodimeric protein, catalyzes the conversion of kynurenine (KYN) to kynurenic acid (KYNA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>We analyzed the transaminase reaction mechanisms of this protein with pyridoxal-5′-phosphate (PLP), KYN and α-ketoglutaric acid (2OG) or oxaloacetic acid (OXA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>2OG significantly inhibited KAT activities in kinetic analyses, suggesting that a KYNA biosynthesis is allosterically regulated by 2OG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Its inhibitions evidently were unlocked by KYN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>2OG and KYN functioned as an inhibitor and activator in response to changes in the concentrations of KYN and 2OG, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The affinities of one subunit for PLP or 2OG were different from that of the other subunit, as confirmed by spectrophotometry and isothermal titration calorimetry, suggesting that the difference of affinities between subunits might play a role in regulations of the KAT reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Moreover, we identified two active and allosteric sites in the crystal structure of PhKAT-2OG complexes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The crystal structure of PhKAT in complex with four 2OGs demonstrates that two 2OGs in allosteric sites are effector molecules which inhibit the KYNA productions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Thus, the combined data lead to the conclusion that PhKAT probably is regulated by allosteric control machineries, with 2OG as the allosteric inhibitor. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="14"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Kynurenine-oxoglutarate transaminase (EC 2.6.1.7), also known as kynurenine (KYN) aminotransferase (KAT) [1], is a dimeric enzyme containing 2 covalently-bound pyridoxal-5′-phosphates (PLP) as cofactor moieties and is the last enzyme in the kynurenic acid (KYNA) biosynthetic pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Kynurenic acid (KYNA) is biosynthesized as a product of the normal metabolism of the amino acid l-tryptophan and via a KYN intermediate; KYNA is synthesized via the transamination of KYN in the presence of KAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>KYNA is sequentially biosynthesized from l-KYN via a 4-(2-aminophenyl)-2,4-dioxobutanoate (4AD) intermediate by KAT (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>KAT transfers the amino group of KYN to α-ketoglutaric acid (2OG) via pyridoxamine phosphate (PMP), thus synthesizing l-glutamic acid (Glu). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In human brain, KYNA acts as a natural antagonist of the glycine site of NMDA (N-methyl d-aspartate) receptor (NMDAR) and plays a key role in the glutamatergic neurotransmission system [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>It is also thought to be involved in the pathogenesis of diseases such as Alzheimer’s [3] and schizophrenia [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Recently, genes encoding KATs were isolated from various organisms, including human [5], mouse [6], Aedes [7], Saccharomyces [8], and a protozoan parasite of Trypanosoma that causes fatal sleeping sickness in human [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The KAT from the hyperthermophilic archaeon, Pyrococcus horikoshii OT3 (PhKAT), is a homolog of human KAT II (HuKAT II) and exhibits low but significant amino acid sequence homology with the KATs of various organisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The crystal structure of the apo-form of PhKAT has been solved at 2.2 Å resolution [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Although this protein was previously designated PhKAT-II, it is simply designated PhKAT in this study because other homologs that are highly conserved relative to PhKAT are absent from the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In P. horikoshii OT3, although the genes that are involved in the biosynthesis of KYN from l-tryptophan are unidentifiable in the genome, PhKAT that catalyzes the formation of KYNA and a human kynureninase homolog related to the biosynthetic pathway from KYN to NAD are present in the genome [11], [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>This suggests that the KYNA pathway is probably present in P. horikoshii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>However, the physiological functions of KYNA in this hyperthermophilic archaeon remain unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we characterized the KYNA biosynthesis abilities of PhKAT to clarify its biochemical function. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>To understand the action mechanisms of PhKAT and compare them with those of their counterparts in humans, other mammals, yeasts, Aedes, and protozoan parasites, we characterized the reactions catalyzed by this enzyme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>We also analyzed the interaction between PhKAT, PLP cofactor, and 2OG substrate by using spectrophotometric technique and isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>ITC results indicate that PhKAT and PLP and/or 2OG interact with a high affinity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The enzyme kinetic analyses revealed that PhKAT is an allosteric enzyme and that transaminated acceptors for PhKAT are 2OG and oxaloacetic acid (OXA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, in the crystal structure of PhKAT complexed with an allosteric effector, 2OG was bound to PhKAT at a rate of 4 molecules per protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Two 2OG molecules were identified in the binding pocket of PhKAT other than a pocket constructed for active sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>This demonstrates that 2OG is an allosteric effector necessary for the regulation of KYNA biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Expression and Purification of PhKAT </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>E. coli BL21-CodonPlus (DE3) cells were transformed with pET28a-PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>PhKAT expression was induced with IPTG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>PhKAT (48 kDa), which was expressed as a soluble protein, was detected by sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS)-PAGE (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Recombinant PhKAT was purified using a His TALON cartridge at the first step; it was identified as single 51-kDa bands (Fig. 1A, lanes 2–10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>A 2-L culture yielded 17 mg purified PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The absolute activities of PhKAT were maintained even after 12 months of storage (−80°C) in 50 mM HEPES–NaOH buffer (pH 7.5) containing 100 mM NaCl. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0040307-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0040307.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>One-step purification of PhKAT and spectrophotometric analysis of the cofactor (PLP) binding to apo-KAT. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>(A) SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Lanes ∼1–10, verification of the purity of PhKAT in each elution fraction from the metal-affinity column. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Protein fractions in lanes ∼2–10 were used for further analysis and crystallization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The positions of the protein standards (molecular masses, 97, 66, 45, 30, 20.1, and 14.4 kDa) are indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>(B) UV–visible absorption spectra of as-isolated PhKAT (lower spectrum) and its cofactor-binding form (holo-PhKAT, upper spectrum). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The lower spectrum was obtained with the as-purified protein, and the upper spectrum was recorded after mixing 20 µM PhKAT with 20 µM PLP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The spectrum shows a maximum at 361 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>(C) Spectrophotometric titration of PLP for 10 and 20 µM PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>(D) Relationship between the equilibrium-binding response and the concentrations of PLP and PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The solid lines represent the fitting curve obtained by the 2-site binding model with hill slopes using Prism5 software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>(E) Summary table of binding parameters from D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Errors are the S.E. from the fit of the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The binding affinity of a second binding site for PLP was stronger than a first binding site in PhKAT (K d1&gt;K d2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0040307.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>PLP Binding to PhKAT </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>A characteristic of KAT is its ability to form a Schiff-base link with the PLP cofactor (PLP complex). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>To determine whether PhKAT can form such a complex, it was incubated with PLP, and the changes in the absorption spectrum were recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The change in the absorption spectrum upon the formation of the PLP–PhKAT complex is depicted in Figure 1B.,The maximum peak of PLP-PhKAT complex was observed at 361 nm, blue-shifted from the that of free-PLP at 390 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Futhermore, the free-PLP peak at 330 nm disappeared (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>S2). Figure 1C and D illustrates the titration plots obtained for PhKAT and clearly indicates that PhKAT binds with PLP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The titration of PhKAT with PLP was followed by the observation of the absorbance changes at 360 nm (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The binding points of PhKAT with PLP were unable to be fitted using the 1-site binding model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Therefore, they were fitted using the 2-sites binding model with hill slopes (Equation S1), as determined by ITC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The dissociation constants for PLP in the 10 and 20 µM PhKAT conditions were K d1 = 25.5 and K d2 = 1.77, and K d1 = 9.65 and K d2 = 1.92 µM, respectively (Fig. 1E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The results indicate a positive cooperativity of PLP binding. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the Crystal Structures of the PLP–PhKAT Complex and Human KAT II (HuKAT II) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Crystals of PLP-bound PhKAT belong to space group C2 and have unit cell parameters a, b, and c of 85.927, 71.055, and 136.348 Å, respectively (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The refined model of the PLP–PhKAT complex contains 2 PhKAT molecules (homodimeric), 404 of 428 residues (residues 25–428), 2 PLPs, and 585 water molecules in the asymmetric unit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The electron density of residues 1–24 and the N-terminal His-tag was not observed probably due to structural disorder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The final crystallographic R-factors and free R-factors with isotropic temperature factors are 18.4% and 23.2%, respectively, for 82,018 unique reflections in the resolution range of 50–1.72 Å. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Data collection and refinement statistics are summarized in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Two peptide chains (designated chains A and C) were located in an asymmetric unit and form a functional homodimer (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Two PLP cofactors formed a Schiff-base link with Lys269 (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The results indicate that the conformation of the PLP–PhKAT complex is functionally active (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The overall superimposition of the main chain structures of PhKAT and HuKAT II are shown as cartoon drawings in Figure 2C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The structures are superimposed along the C-α atoms of residues 25–428 and the 2 PLP cofactors in PhKAT, and the C-α atoms of residues 1–18 and 32–425 and the PLP cofactors in HuKAT II [13], [14]; this is because HuKAT II lacks residues 19–31 compared with PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The root mean square deviation value for the C-α atom between the 2 structures calculated by PyMOL is 1.8 Å. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The overall secondary structures of PhKAT were fairly similar to those of HuKAT II [14] and also resembled the other known backbone structures of KAT families. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>However, it should be noted that the backbone conformation of the α-helix of Glu73–Glu86 in PhKAT is significantly different from the corresponding conformation of HuKAT II, which is a β-sheet as shown in the superimposition (Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The active site contains 1 PLP molecule covalently linked to Lys269 and is located in a deep cleft at the domain interface built up by residues from both subunits (Fig. 2D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>PLP-bound pockets are conserved between PhKAT and HuKAT II (Fig. 2D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The constituted residues of the active sites around PLP-bound pockets are all conserved, except for Ser260 in HuKAT II (Fig. 2D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The amino acid sequences of PhKAT and HuKAT II share low homology (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>S4); the homology with HuKAT II is as low at 27%, but the cofactor-binding site and PLP-ligand lysine that form a Schiff-base linkage in PhKAT are fairly conserved as shown in their sequence alignment (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>S4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0040307-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0040307.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Overall crystal structure of the PLP–KAT complex and PLP in complex. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>(A) Stereoview and cartoon representation of the structure of functional PhKAT dimer bound to 2 PLP cofactors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>A C-α trace is shown with rainbow coloring from N- (blue) to C-termini (red). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Black arrows indicate the position of PLP molecules and active sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>(B) Part of PLP with a 2Fo-Fc electron density map contoured at 1.5 σ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>PLP molecules formed a Schiff-base link with lysine-269. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>(C), (D) Superimposed representation of the structures of PhKAT and HuKAT II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>(C) Cartoon representations of PLP complex structures of PhKAT (PDB code: 3AOV) and HuKAT II (PDB code: 2VGZ) after optimal superimposition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>PhKAT and HuKAT II are rainbow-colored and gray, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The left-hand molecule is shown in the same orientation as in A, whereas the right-hand molecule is rotated −90°. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>(D) Stick representation of the PLP cofactor-binding sites with PhKAT and HuKAT II after optimal superposition of the 2 structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>HuKAT II is colored blue-gray. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that the secondary structures of KAT are conserved between P. horikoshii and humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The figure was generated using PyMOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0040307.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Spectrophotometric Evidence of KAT Activity and KYNA Synthesis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Previously, we confirmed the conversion of KYN to KYNA by HPLC [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>However, whether the conversion to KYNA is an enzymatic reaction remains unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Thus, we monitored the PhKAT-catalyzed reaction spectrophotometrically (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>When PhKAT, PLP, and KYN were incubated with 2OG, the KYN peak present at 368 nm disappeared and 2 peaks with maxima at 332 and 346 nm appeared in a time-dependent manner (Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Spectrum changes at 332 and 346 nm were saturated at 32 min after the start of the reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>KYNA exhibited maximum peaks at 332 and 344 nm (Fig. 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Thus, the 2 peaks at 332 and 346 nm in Figure 3A indicate the presence of KYNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The disappearance of the peak at 368 nm in Figure 3A shows that KYN is enzymatically converted to KYNA as observed when comparing spectrum changes (Fig. 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>This result indicates that PhKAT from this hyperthermophilic archaeon is a KAT. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0040307-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0040307.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Catalytic activity of PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>(A) Spectrophotometric assay of the time course of the PhKAT-catalyzed activity of KYN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The PhKAT-catalyzed activity of KYN was examined by spectrophotometry using both PLP and 2OG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Time-dependent absorbance changes were monitored during the PhKAT reaction after the addition of 2OG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The arrows indicate the direction of absorbance changes during incubation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The absorption band at 368 nm decreases with time, while bands at 332 and 346 nm appear and increase, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The spectrum at 32 min was identical to that at 64 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>(B) Comparison of the absorption spectra of KYN and KYNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The absorption spectra of KYN and KYNA measured at concentrations of 10 and 20 µM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The spectrum of KYNA exhibits 2 peaks at 332 and 344 nm, and KYN exhibits a peak at 362 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>(C) The observed absorbance before and after the PhKAT catalyzed-reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The final product of the PhKAT-catalyzed reaction from KYN substrate was identified with KYNA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0040307.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Kinetics of the Transamination Reaction from KYN to 2OG by KAT </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The transamination abilities of PhKAT from KYN to 2OG, which were used to monitor KYNA production, were investigated by spectrophotometry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>In this reaction, KYN is converted to KYNA via transamination from KYN to 2OG via PLP in the presence of excess KYN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The conversion velocities of KYN to KYNA are plotted with respect to 2OG concentrations as the enzymatic abilities of PhKAT at pH 7.5 (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The reaction curve of PhKAT indicates that it is allosteric sigmoidal and allosteries (Fig. 4A and B) and that the catalytic activity of KAT is strongly inhibited by high 2OG concentrations (two times of that of KAT) (Fig. 4A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>This result indicates that 2OG probably is an allosteric inhibitor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>In addition, the KYNA productions from KYN by KAT were regulated at two respects of the low and high 2OG concentration regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The result indicates that 2OG as allosteric inhibitor functions at 2 molecules for PhKAT, and affinities between two subunits of PhKAT formed homo-dimer for first and second 2OG effectors differ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The absolute inhibition constant (K i) was 20.11 µM (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>S5A, Equation S2 and Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The results demonstrate that 2OG as allosteric inhibitor binds at a rate of 2 molecules per PhKAT as the homo-dimer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The velocities of KYNA synthesis by PhKAT at first contact of 2OG substrate (low concentration) accelerated to nearly “V max” (Fig. 4A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>This behavior indicates that the conformation of PhKAT changes from R state (high affinity) to T state (low affinity) in conjunction with that 2OG binds to a first binding site of PhKAT (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>S5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>In addition, the slope of the velocity curves at low 2OG concentration region (∼1.2 µM) in Figure 4B (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>S5B right hand) sifted to low 2OG concentrations more than in Figure 4A (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>S5B left hand). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>This result indicates that KYN functions as an activator for KYNA production (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>S5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In fact, the acceleration and recovery of KYNA synthesized velocities were observed in Figure 4A and B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The results indicate that KYN as an activator probably unlocks the inhibiting action of 2OG for PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The α-KBA and α-KMB keto-acid analogs were able to support the KAT reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>H-values were greater than 1 (Table S2 and Equation S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>H-values for α-KBA, and α-KMB were 1.79 and 3.57 under 100 µM KYN, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The results show that PhKAT is an allosteric enzyme characterized by positive cooperativity and ligands for PhKAT are 2 and 4 molecules, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>However, α-KMB does not bind with PhKAT at 4 molecules due to that a molar ratio discords between PhKAT and α-KMB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>It might indicate that K ms of α-KMB change by that 2 KYN bind with PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Therefore, Figure 4C shows only the two reactions by α-KBA as substrate without an allosteric inhibition and binding with KYNs as an activator. K m values for α-KBA, and α-KMB were 1.73 and 2.41 µM under 100 µM KYN, respectively (Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The velocities of KYNA synthesis by PhKAT at first contact of α-KMB accelerated to around “V max” (Fig. 4D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The result indicates the conformation changes of PhKAT from R state to T state in conjunction with binding of α-KMB to a first binding site of PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The velocity changes at 0.4 µM in α-KBA are smaller than α-KMB (Fig. 4C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>This might indicate that PhKAT is the R’ state which is an intermediate position between R state and T state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Thus, KYN as an activator might be able to bind with PhKAT when is T state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>OXA was able to support the KAT reaction and allostery including allosteric inhibition (Fig. 4E, F and G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>However, the allosteric inhibitions were cause by only binding of OXA with a first allosteric site (Fig. 4E and F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>This result supports that PhKAT has been regulated by 2OG. V maxs supported by OXA were lower than 2OG (Fig. 4E and F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>These results may indicate that a KYNA synthesis has been driven by 2OG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Although results showed the binding of third and fourth KYNs to PhKAT (Fig. 4E and F), the recovery from an inhibition by an OXA which binds with one allosteric site was not observed at 100 µM KYN condition (Fig. 4F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Additionally, figure 4G indicates that KYN activates PhKAT, as with 2OG (Fig. 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The results indicated the conformation changes of PhKAT from R state to T state in conjunction with binding of OXA to the first binding site of PhKAT (Fig. 4H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The affinity for OXA at 1 µM was higher than 2OG in 50 µM KYN conditions (Fig. 4H left hand) and that was lower than 2OG in 100 µM KYN conditions (Fig. 4H right hand). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Affinities for 2OG at low concentrations (∼0.08 µM) were higher than OXA (Fig. 4H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Affinities for OXA at 0.02 µM concentrations were a 50 µM KYN condition higher than a 100 µM KYN condition (Fig. 4G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>These indicate that PhKAT changes the nature of transaminated acceptors in conjunction with changes in concentration of KYN and that a KYNA biosynthesis is driven by 2OG and/or OXA at low concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The combined results suggest that the transaminase reaction of PhKAT is specifically regulated by 2OG as an allosteric effector, and that a carboxyl group of C5 in 2OG performs the important role for allosteric inhibitions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the length of keto acids probably relate to the cooperation with KYN as an activator and binding to two allosteric sites (Fig. 4I). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0040307-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0040307.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Kinetics of the KAT reaction with 2 substrates. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The KAT-catalyzed reaction from KYN to KYNA was determined by monitoring the change in absorption at 332 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>(A), (B) Measurement of the KAT-catalyzed conversion to KYNA with definite KYN concentrations, and the allostery of 2OG for PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Values are mean±S.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>((A), (B): n = 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The arrow and arrow heads indicate the conformation changes of PhKAT from R state to T state in conjunction with binding of 2OG to a first binding site and allosteric inhibitions, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The KYNA productions from KYN by KAT are regulated at two respects of low and high 2OG concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Black arrow-head: first allosteric inhibition by a first 2OG effector molecule; white arrow-head: second allosteric inhibition by a second 2OG effector molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>(C), (D) The PhKAT-catalyzed reaction by α-keto acid analogs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The solid line represents the fitting curve obtained by allosteric sigmoidal model using Prism5 software (Equation S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The arrows indicate the conformation changes from R state to T state in conjunction with binding of keto acid analogs to a first binding site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>(E), (F) Comparison of the PhKAT-catalyzed reaction by OXA and 2OG, and the allostery of OXA for PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Values are mean±S.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>((E), (F): n = 5 and 4, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The arrow indicates the conformation changes of PhKAT from R state to T state in conjunction with binding of OXA to a first binding site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Black arrow-heads: first allosteric inhibition by OXA; white arrow-head: binding of fourth KYN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>(G) Comparison of E and F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>(H) Magnified views of E and F (∼2 µM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>(A), (E) 50 µM KYN; (B), (C), (D), (F) 100 µM KYN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>(I) Keto acids: 2OG, α-KBA, α-KMB and OXA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>A dot circle indicates the important parts in 2OG for the allostery. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0040307.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Thermodynamics of PhKAT, its Cofactor, and Substrate Interactions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>ITC was used to accurately determine the binding parameters of purified PhKAT, PLP and/or KYN, and 2OG. Figure 1A shows the protein purity used in these experiments, and Figure 5 and S6 show representative ITC experiments including the titration data and binding curves calculated using the best-fit parameters. Table S3 summarizes the thermodynamic parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The ligands bind to PhKAT in 1∶1 and 1∶2 ratios. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The PLP cofactor binds to 2 sites of PhKAT (Fig. 5A), indicating that it binds to 2 active sites of functional homodimeric PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The 2 sites where PLP binds to PhKAT were observed in the crystal structure of the PhKAT–PLP complex at 1.72 Å (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>A shape of binding curves indicated that the dissociation constant for PLP (as apparent constant) of a second binding site in PhKAT might be an approximately femtomole order. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>A 2OG substrate binds to 4 sites of the PhKAT–PLP complex (Fig. 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>However, the binding of 2OG to the PhKAT–PLP complex possibly is an overestimation of the limit of ITC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>A shape of binding curves indicated that the dissociation constant for 2OG of a first binding site in PhKAT might be an approximately femtomole order. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The 4-sites binding of 2OG indicate that two 2OGs may operate as an allosteric effector molecule that regulates the transaminase reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>In fact, the transaminase activity of PhKAT at steady-state kinetic analysis was inhibited at 2 respects of low and high 2OG concentrations (Fig. 4A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>These results demonstrate that it binds to 4 binding sites, which are the 2 active and allosteric sites, of functional homodimeric PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>A 2OG substrate binds to 4 sites of the PhKAT–PLP–KYN complex with dissociation constants (K ds) of K d1 = 238.15 nM and K d2 = 15.80 µM (as substraes) and K d3 = 3.12 µM and K d4 = 1.09 µM (as allosteric effectors), and the negative and positive cooperativities, respectively (Fig. 5C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>2OG binds to PhKAT more weakly in the presence of KYN than in its absence (Fig. 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Although Figure 5C is fitted by a 4-sites binding model, this binding curve fits for use other binding models in a similar manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the binding numbers might need to be determined by using other methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>This study determined the binding numbers of 2OG for PhKAT from Figure 5B, enzyme kinetics and crystal structure analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>When the affinities of 2OG for PhKAT decreases and/or increase, it cooperates with KYN and/or 2OG in conjunction with binding to each sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The stoichiometry between PhKAT-PLP complex and 2OG might get out of order due to the binding gears between binding sites in PhKAT (Fig. 5B and C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The PhKAT-PLP complex precipitated when mixed with 2OG (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The binding powers of 2OG may be too much for PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the molar ratios between its complex and 2OG might be out of alignment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Additionally, in enzyme kinetic analyses, the affinities of PhKAT for 2OG varied in response to changes in concentrations of KYN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Therefore, ITC experiments might need to be done with modified KYN concentrations in the cell. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0040307-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0040307.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>ITC analysis of the interaction between the cofactor, substrates, and KAT. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The ITC profiles include experimental conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>(A) KAT and PLP; (B) KAT-PLP and 2OG; (C) KAT-PLP-KYN and 2OG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>The numbers indicate a binding site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The binding between the KAT–PLP complex and 2OG might be an overestimation of the limit of ITC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>(A), (B) The shapes of binding curves indicated that the dissociation constants for PLP (as apparent constant) and 2OG of second and first binding sites, respectively, might be approximately femtomole orders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>(C) A curve fitting was performed by using a sequential binding 4-site model. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0040307.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>PhKAT, PLP, and 2OG Complex Structures and Their Electrostatic Surface Potential </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>To examine the binding mechanisms of PhKAT and 2OG, the crystallized PhKAT–PLP–2OG complex was formed in a 1∶1:1 ratio. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Crystals of the PhKAT–PLP–2OG complex belong to space group C2 and have unit cell parameters a, b, and c of 85.774, 70.977, and 136.723 Å, respectively (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The refined model of the 2OG–PLP–KAT complex contains 2 KAT molecules (homodimeric), 404 of 428 residues, 2 PLPs, 2 2OGs, and 838 water molecules in the asymmetric unit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>No electron density for residues 1–24 was observed probably due to structural disorder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The final crystallographic R-factors and free R-factors with isotropic temperature factors are 17.7% and 22.4% for 109,393 unique reflections in the resolution range of 50–1.56 Å. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Refinement statistics are summarized in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Electrostatic potentials can induce attractive forces and have the longest range of any chemical interaction; in turn, short-range forces become increasingly important. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>In an effort to identify structural features in the PhKAT protein that could promote interactions with a 2OG substrate, we assessed whether electrostatic complementarities are possible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Thus, we determined the crystal structures (at 1.56 Å resolution) of 2OG, PLP, and the PhKAT triple complex at the binding site to the PhKAT subunit with one 2OG substrate. Figure 6 shows the electrostatic surface potentials and locations of constituted residues of the active sites around 2OG- and PLP-bound pockets of the PhKAT–PLP–2OG triple complex structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>A single 2OG was bound to a positively charged active site (Fig. 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that the interaction between the substrate and cofactor with PhKAT is electrostatic binding, which capacitates the binding between 2OG and PLP with PhKAT with high specificity and affinity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0040307-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0040307.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Surface and substrate binding site representations of 2OG, PLP, and KAT complexes. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>(A) Electrostatic potential mapped onto the molecular surface of a functional KAT dimer with bound 2OG and PLP shown as sticks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>The 2OG/PLP-bound site of KAT is positively charged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Electrostatic potential calculated using APBS and PDB2PQR server. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Potentials are contoured from −15 kT/e (negative charge, red) to +15 kT/e (positive charge, blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>The positively charged sites bind to both the substrates and cofactor with high affinity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>(B) Close-up view of a 2OG-bound site of KAT structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Parts of 2OG and PLP with 2Fo-Fc electron density maps contoured at 1.5 σ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>The figure was generated using PyMOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0040307.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2h"><title><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Overall Structure of PhKAT Complexed with 2OG (3ATH), and Comparison with Other PhKAT Complex Structures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The crystals of 2OG-bound PhKAT belong to space group C2 and have unit cell parameters a, b, and c of 85.817, 70.989, and 136.816 Å, respectively (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The refined model of PhKAT in complex with 2OG contains 2 PhKAT molecules (homodimer), 404 of 428 residues, 2 PLPs, 4 2OGs, and 628 water molecules in the asymmetric unit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>No electron density for residues 1–24 was observed probably due to structural disorder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The final crystallographic R-factors and free R-factors with isotropic temperature factors are 17.0% and 21.5%, respectively, for 86,699 unique reflections in the resolution range of 50–1.69 Å. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Refinement statistics are summarized in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Two peptide chains were located in an asymmetric unit and form a functional homodimer (Fig. 7A, left molecule). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Two PLP cofactors formed a Schiff-base link with Lys269, and 4 2OG molecules were bound to 2 binding pockets within the active sites or bound to pockets close to the lysine Schiff-based PLP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, the latter pockets are located on the back of the active sites of PhKAT (Fig. 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>The results indicate that 2OG as a substrate is an allosteric effector of PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0040307-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0040307.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Overall crystal structure of PhKAT in complex with PLP and 2OG as a substrate and allosteric effector (PDB code: 3ATH). </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>(A) Surface and cartoon representation of the structure of functional PhKAT dimer bound with 2 PLP cofactors and 4 2OGs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>A Cα trace is shown with blue and green coloring with 2 subunit chains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Black arrows indicate the position of PLP as cofactor and 2OG as substrate and allosteric effector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Left hand, cartoon-and-surface representation of the allosteric–effector complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Right hand, cut-away of the overall structure of the left-hand complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>(B), (C) Part of 2OG as a substrate (B) and as an allosteric effector (C) with a 2Fo-Fc electron density map contoured at 1.3 σ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>(D), (E), (F) Superimposed representation of 2OG complex structures of PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>(D) Cartoon representations of 2OG complex structures of PhKAT after optimal superimposition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>2OG as a substrate complex (PDB code: 3AOW) and 2OG as a substrate and an allosteric effector complex (PDB code: 3ATH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Gray cartoon-and-line represents PhKAT bound only to 2OG as a substrate complex; PhKAT bound to 2OG as substrates and allosteric effectors is colored green and blue for 2 subunits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Yellow circles show regions with significant conformation changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Black arrows indicate the position of 2OG as substrates and allosteric effectors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>(E), (F) Stick-and-line representation of the PLP-cofactor binding sites and 2OG as substrate after optimal superposition of the 2 PhKAT complex structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>2OG as a substrate complex only is colored gray. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>(E) Black and gray labels, and dotted lines show the distance (Å) between 2OG and the C4A atom of PLP in a Schiff-base link with lysine-269. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>(F) Angles (°) of 2OG between substrate-bound PhKAT, and substrate- and allosteric effector-bound PhKAT structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>The figure was generated using PyMOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0040307.g007"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>The overall structure of the superimposition of the main chain structures of PhKAT–2OG complexes 3AOW and 3ATH, which are 2 different structures with 2 and 4 2OGs as substrates, respectively, with the 2OG-bound PhKAT are shown as cartoon drawings in Figure 7D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>The structures are superimposed along the C-α atoms of residues 25–428. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, there are 2 PLP cofactors in PhKAT complexed with 2 2OGs as substrates, and the C-α atoms of residues 25–428 and the 2 PLP cofactors in PhKAT are complexed with 4 2OGs as substrates and allosteric effectors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Although the overall secondary structure of PhKAT complexed with 2 2OGs as substrates was similar to that of PhKAT complexed with 4 2OGs as substrates and allosteric effectors, the areas around the α2 and α14 helices, and the D-365 region had significantly differently conformational changes (Fig. 7D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>The coassemblies of 2OG as an allosteric effector of PhKAT in complex with 2OG as substrate caused a major change in the spatial layout of 2OG as a substrate (Fig. 7E and F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>The distances between the C4A atoms of PLP and 2OG when the 2OGs were in a substrate-bound and a substrate and allosteric effector-bound form were 5.1 and 3.4 Å, respectively (Fig. 7E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>As part of an allosteric effector complex, 2OG was altered at 89.2° (Fig. 7F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>The results indicate that the binding of 2OG to allosteric sites directly affects substrates in the active sites of PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>This indicates that the substrate binding force undergoes a change due to the binding of 2OG to allosteric sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The inhibition of KAT activity by allosteric effectors might be because KYN is prevented from approaching PLP reaction sites by 2OG as substrate (Fig. 7E and F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the binding of 2OG to allosteric sites induced a conformation change of the α2 helix constructed active sites of PhKAT (Fig. 7D and Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>S7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>The distance between the Cα-traces of a PLP complex and an allosteric effector complex was a maximum of 1.3 Å (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>S7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>The results indicate that the binding of 2OG to allosteric sites induces an imperceptible effect on the conformation of the 2 active sites of PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Evolutionary Conservation of Allosteric Effector-binding Sites Between PhKAT and Mammalian KAT II </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>To verify that PhKAT and 2OG are an allosteric enzyme and allosteric effector, respectively, we cocrystallized PhKAT, PLP, and 2OG in a 1∶1:2 ratio. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>PhKAT has 4 2OG-binding sites that have different binding characters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we determined previously unknown allosteric sites of PhKAT (Fig. 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>The allosteric sites of PhKAT are located on the back of the active sites, and PLP is interleaved between the active and allosteric sites (Fig. 8A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>The allosteric sites are comprised of the Asp-236–Leu-242, Tyr-263–Ile-270, Leu-111, Tyr-115, and Trp-279 residues (Fig. 8A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>The allosteric sites are communalized with a PLP-binding site (Fig. 8A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Glu-235–Tyr-239, Leu-242, Ser-268, and Lys-269 are essentially conserved between PhKAT and mammalian KAT IIs (e.g., humans, rats, mice, pigs, and monkeys) (Fig. 8B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>The Glu-235–Leu-242 region was more conserved than the Tyr-263–Ile-270 region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>The results indicate that allosteric sites may be conserved in mammalian KAT II families. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0040307-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0040307.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Close-up view of an allosteric effector-binding site and its sequence logo. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>(A) Line-and-stick representations of the binding sites of PLP and 2OG molecules as a cofactor, substrate, and allosteric effector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Black arrows show 2OG in its positions as a substrate (upper) and allosteric effector (lower). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Lower sites are rotated 90° and −90° relative to the upper site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>The figure was generated using PyMOL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>(B) Sequence logo of the allosteric effector-bound site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Upper, yellow stick representation region of (A) + Glu-235; lower, magenta stick representation region of (A). “K-269” is a ligand bound with a C4A atom of PLP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Amino acids are colored according to their chemical properties: polar amino acids (G, S, T, and Y) are green, basic (K and R) blue, acidic (D and E) red, and hydrophobic (V, A, L, I, P, and F) amino acids are black. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>The protein sequence alignment used mammalian KAT IIs and PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>GenBank database (GB) accession numbers for P. horikoshii, humans (Homo sapiens), rats (Rattus norvegicus), mice (Mus musculus), pigs (Sus scrofa), and monkeys (Macaca mulatta) are NP_142204, NP_057312, NP_058889, NP_035964, XP_001924647, and XP_002804303, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Multiple alignments were performed using ClustalW2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>The sequence logo was generated using WebLogo [22]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0040307.g008"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>The results of this study show that the mechanisms of KYNA synthesis from KYN is conserved in the hyperthermophilic archaeon, P. horikoshii, and that KYN transamination results in the production of KYNA (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>3 and 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>This suggests that although the amino-acid sequence of PhKAT is quite different from that of HuKAT II, the metabolic conversion of KYN to KYNA is conserved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this, the crystal structures of the PhKAT–PLP complex and PhKAT–PLP–2OG triple complex, which forms a necessary bio-functional complex that catalyzes the formation of KYNA from KYN, are similar to those of HuKAT II [13], [14] (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>The proposed mechanism of the KYNA synthesis reaction from KYN in conjunction with 2OG and/or OXA is depicted in Figure S8. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>However, not all aspects of KYNA synthesis are conserved; one factor that is highly variable between different groups of organisms is the source of transaminating acceptor equivalents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>The specificity of transaminated acceptors among various organisms is not fairly high for KAT enzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Therefore, to determine an authentic substrate as acceptors, and/or allosteric effector for PhKAT, we probed the interaction between 2OG and a KAT protein using ITC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>The results show that 2OG binds PhKAT with high specificity and affinity (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>This scheme strongly indicates that the KYNA biosynthesis pathway may be linked with the 2OG biosynthetic pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>In fact, P. horikoshii possesses the pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Another important feature of PhKAT is regulated by its dependence on changes in the concentration of 2OG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>To assess whether the proteins of P. horikoshii, humans, or other mammals are biochemically conserved, we determined the substrate requirements for the P. horikoshii enzyme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>The results show that PhKAT activity for converting KYN to KYNA is supported by 2OG and OXA molecules (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the results show that PhKAT activity is regulated by allosteric control by 2OG (Fig. 4A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Our studies state that in vivo, KAT activities are accelerated when 2OG and/or OXA concentrations are low and vice versa (Fig. 4A, B, E and F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>The high thermostabilities of murine KAT families were recently reported [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Therefore, this implicitly indicates that the regulation systems of PhKAT might be evolutionarily conserved between hyperthermophilic archaea and mammals including humans.Some factors that affect enzymatic activity are electrostatic and hydrophobic substrate interactions, overall dipole moments of enzymes, certain aromatic groups in the KYNA biosynthesis pathway, and the relative orientation and distance between prosthetic groups in the complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>The interactions between PLP cofactor, 2OG, OXA and KYN substrates, and KAT mainly occur as a result of electrostatic interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>The present study elucidates the binding mechanisms of substrates, cofactors, and PhKAT using spectrophotometry and ITC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>The substrate, cofactor, and PhKAT complexes were formed in the reaction, suggesting the existence of cooperation between KAT and KYN and/or 2OG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>The regulation of cooperative and binding mechanisms was discovered through the conversion activity of KYNA and the formation of substrate, cofactor, and PhKAT complexes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>With coexisting substrates, the binding affinities of 2OG for PLP–KAT complexes change to decrease or increase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>It should be possible to determine the binding affinity of the KYNA conversion reaction in real time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>We revealed the characteristic features of KAT from a hyperthermophilic archaeon, P. horikoshii, using enzyme analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>In this study, we identified PhKAT as an allosteric enzyme regulated by 2OG in cooperation with KYN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>The results indicate that the conversion reaction from KYN to KYNA by PhKAT is regulated depending on the concentration of 2OG as a transamination acceptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>In addition, KYN may be an activator for PhKAT in order to unlock an inhibiting action by 2OG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>2OG and OXA may function as efficient transamination acceptors for KAT in P. horikoshii OT3 because it exhibits high affinities for PhKAT as detected by kinetics and/or ITC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>In addition, PhKAT exhibits a high affinity for PLP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>These findings indicate that high affinities may be required for KAT protein functioning in extreme environments hotter than 100°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>To obtain more knowledge about the function of KAT and evidence to support our findings that the crystal structure of PhKAT in complex with an allosteric effector (2OG) is very important, we decided to investigate the complex formation between PhKAT and 2OG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>For this purpose, we cocrystallized both intact PhKAT and 2OG molecules, which are required for enzymatic regulation in vivo, and acquired a bio-functional complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>The results are in complete agreement with our investigation, demonstrating that 2OG as a substrate is critical as the rate-limiting factor in the KYNA biosynthetic pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Finally, we suggest that the KAT protein from P. horikoshii OT3 may be evolutionarily conserved and related to human KATs localized in the brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>The enzymatic molecular mechanisms for the conversion reaction from KYN to KYNA by PhKAT remain unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we solved the crystal structures of the PhKAT complexed with KYN or PLP to understand the differences in the enzymatic reaction mechanisms between human KATs and PhKAT in greater detail [13], [14], [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>The present study clearly demonstrates that 2OG is an allosteric inhibitor that binds the allosteric sites of PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>We propose that 2OG as a substrate regulates the KYNA biosynthesis of PhKAT in vivo and that PhKAT shares a function of 2OG and has 4 pockets with different binding affinities for 2OG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Thus, the allosteric sites of KAT may be a novel drug target for the regulation of KYNA production. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Reagents </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Pyridoxal phosphate (Wako), l-kynurenine (SIGMA), kynurenic acid (SIGMA), 2-oxoglutaric acid (2OG; Wako), oxaloacetic acid (OXA; Wako), 2-ketobutyric acid (α-KBA; ALDRICH), and α-keto-γ-(methylthio) butyric acid (α-KMB; SIGMA) preparations were used as a cofactor, and substrates and/or standards; agar and organic nutrients for Luria–Bertani (LB) medium (Difco) were purchased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>PLP, KYN, and KYNA were treated with alkali to dissolve them in water. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Construction of the pET28a-PhKAT Expression Vector </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>The pET28a-PhKAT expression vector for the expression of His6-tagged PhKAT was constructed by ligating the NdeI–EcoRI fragment from pET1300Ph [15] into the NdeI–EcoRI sites of pET28a (Novagen). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Expression and Purification of Recombinant PhKAT </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>A single fresh colony of E. coli BL21-CodonPlus (DE3) transformed with the pET28a-PhKAT was cultured in 50 mL LB medium containing kanamycin (30 µg/mL) overnight at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Twenty milliliters of this culture was inoculated into 2 L LB medium and cultivation was continued until the optical density at 578 nm (OD578) reached 0.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Protein expression was induced by the addition of 0.3 mM isopropylthio-β-galactoside (IPTG) and incubation for 21 h at 17°C; the bacteria were subsequently harvested by centrifugation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>The bacterial pellets from 2 L culture were resuspended in 30 mL lysis buffer (50 mM sodium phosphate [pH 7.0], 1 mM dithiothreitol [DTT], and 300 mM NaCl), and the cells were lysed by 30-s sonication on ice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Cell debris was removed by centrifugation at 43 000 × g for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>The resultant supernatant was loaded directly onto a His TALON Cartridge (1 mL; Clontech Laboratories) equilibrated with 10 column volumes of lysis buffer at 4°C using a syringe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Unbound protein was eliminated by washing the column with 10 column volumes of lysis and wash buffer (50 mM sodium phosphate [pH 7.0], 300 mM NaCl, and 5 mM imidazole). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>PhKAT was eluted with 5 column volumes of elution buffer (50 mM sodium phosphate [pH 7.0], 300 mM NaCl, and 150 mM imidazole). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Fractions containing PhKAT were pooled and concentrated to 1 mL using an Amicon Ultra with a 30-kDa cutoff (Millipore). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>This fraction was rebuffered in 50 mM HEPES–NaOH buffer (pH 7.5) containing 100 mM NaCl for the enzymatic assay and ITC or 5 mM HEPES–NaOH buffer (pH 7.5) using prepacked Sephadex G-25 gel filtration columns NAP-10 (GE Healthcare UK Ltd.) for crystallization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>The protein concentration of monomeric PhKAT was determined spectroscopically with an extinction coefficient of 55,810 M−1⋅cm−1 at 280 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Spectroscopic Analysis of PLP Binding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>PhKAT was added to a 20 µM (final concentration) PLP solution in a final volume of 500 µL of 50 mM HEPES–NaOH buffer (pH 7.5) containing 100 mM NaCl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Titration of PhKAT with PLP was monitored by absorption spectroscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Aliquots of PLP (1, 2, 4, 8, 16, 32, and 64 µM) were added to the cuvette containing PhKAT at 25°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Spectra were recorded after the addition of PLP, and the PLP-binding constant (K d) was calculated from the difference in absorbance at 360 nm, and the PLP-binding curve for PhKAT was obtained by the 2-site binding model with variable slopes using prism5. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Enzyme Activity Assay and PhKAT Kinetics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>PLP-dependent KAT activity was assayed in 500 µL of 50 mM HEPES–NaOH buffer (pH 7.5) containing 100 mM NaCl, 10 µM PhKAT, 15 µM PLP, 20 µM KYN, and 64 µM 2OG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Assays were performed at room temperature (25°C), and the reaction was initiated by the addition of 2OG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>KYNA production was monitored spectrophotometrically using a U-2810 UV–Vis spectrophotometer (Hitachi). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>The transaminase abilities of KAT were assayed by measuring the rate of the KYNA production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>In a total volume of 500 µL, the reaction mixture contained 10 µM PhKAT (dimer: 5 µM); 12 µM PLP; 0.08, 0.1, 0.4, 0.8, 1, 1.2, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 16, 20 and 24 µM 2OG; 0.02, 0.08, 0.1, 0.4, 0.8, 1, 1.2, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 16, 20 and 24 µM OXA; 50, or 100 µM KYN; 50 mM HEPES–NaOH buffer (pH 7.5); 100 mM NaCl; 0.4, 0.8, 1, 4, 8, 12 and 16 µM α-KMB, and/or 0.4, 0.8, 1, 4, 8, 12, 16 and 20 µM α-KBA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>KYNA production was monitored by the increase in A332 at 25°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>The quantities of KYNA were determined spectroscopically with an extinction coefficient of 9.8 mM−1⋅cm−1 at 332 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Isothermal Titration Calorimetry for Cofactor and Substrate Binding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>The binding affinities of PhKAT with cofactor (PLP) and substrate (2OG) were determined by high-sensitivity microcalorimetry using a VP-ITC device (GE Healthcare UK Ltd.) at 35°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>To avoid air bubbles, we degassed solutions under vacuum before use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Fresh PhKAT, and/or PLP and KYN were filled in the reaction cell at concentrations of 20, 30, or 40 µM (dimer: 10, 15, and 20 µM) in 50 mM HEPES–NaOH buffer (pH 7.5) containing 100 mM NaCl and titrated in 25 10-µL steps against stock solutions of PLP (0.3 mM), 2OG (0.2 or 0.4 mM) at 5-min intervals. Table S4 summarizes the ITC control parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Power peaks were integrated, and the resultant reaction temperatures were plotted against the molar cofactor and/or substrate/protein ratios and fitted using the “sequential binding sites” model according to the manufacturer’s instructions with origin version 5.0 (MicroCal Software), thus yielding the dissociation constant K d. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Cocrystallization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>We searched extensively for the crystallization conditions of the PLP and/or 2OG complexes with PhKAT using the sitting-drop vapor diffusion method with Crystal Screen (CS) I and II (Hampton Research) and Wizard (Wiz) I and II (Emerald Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>In brief, PhKAT was concentrated to 15 mg/mL (306.6 µM) and mixed with PLP and/or 2OG at 1∶1, and 1∶1:1 or 1∶1:2 ratios, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>Crystals of KAT complexes with cofactors and/or substrates and/or allosteric effectors were grown using the sitting-drop vapor diffusion method in CS I No. 14 (0.2 M calcium chloride dehydrate, 0.1 M HEPES sodium [pH 7.5], 28% v/v polyethylene glycol [PEG] 400) for the PLP–2OG–PhKAT complex, CS I No. 23 (0.2 M magnesium chloride hexahydrate, 0.1 M HEPES sodium [pH 7.5], 30% v/v PEG 400) for the PLP–PhKAT complex, and Wiz I No. 12 (0.1 M imidazole [pH 8.0], 0.2 M calcium acetate, 20% w/v PEG 1000) for the allosteric effector complex at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>Crystallographic Data Collection and Processing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>The crystals were soaked in crystallization solution containing an additional 18% ethylene glycol (vol/vol) as a cryoprotectant for the allosteric effector complex (PEG400 becomes a cryoprotectant). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Radiographic data for the allosteric effector complex were collected at wavelengths of 0.9 or 1 Å at beam line BL38B1 at the SPring-8 synchrotron in Hyogo, Japan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Diffraction images were collected on a CCD-based detector system (ADSC Quantum 210) at liquid nitrogen temperature (100 K). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Diffraction data were indexed, integrated, and scaled using the HKL2000 program suite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Crystal data and crystallographic statistics are shown in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>Structural Determination and Refinement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>The structures were solved via the molecular replacement method, using the structure of apo-PhKAT (PDB cord: 1×0M) or PLP complex (PDB cord: 3AOV) as a search model with the MOLREP program [18] in the CCP4i program suite [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>First, the structures of PhKAT complexes were refined to rigid bodies and refined again with isotropic temperature factors by using the REFMAC5 program [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>The atomic models were manually revised using Coot [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>Upon careful inspection of the |Fo|–|Fc| and 2|Fo|–|Fc| maps, we added PLP, water molecules, and/or 2OGs into the model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>Subsequent refinement was done at resolutions of up to 1.72, 1.56, and 1.69 Å. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>The stereochemical geometry of the model was checked with the PROCHECK program. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Accession Codes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>The atomic coordinates and structure factors for PhKAT in complex with PLP and 2OG as substrates and/or allosteric effectors have been deposited in the Protein Data Bank with the following accession codes: PLP, 3AOV; PLP and 2OGs as substrate, 3AOW; PLP and 2OGs as substrate and allosteric effector, 3ATH. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0040307.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Scheme of the KAT-catalyzed reaction showing the conversion of KYNA from KYN. KYNA is synthesized from KYN via a 4AD intermediate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0040307.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0040307.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Spectrophotometric assay of the cofactor binding to PhKAT. PhKAT binds with the PLP cofactor as measured by absorbance spectroscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>(A), PLP only, (B), 10 µM PhKAT, (C), 20 µM PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>PLP performed at concentrations of 1, 2, 4, 8, 16, 32 and 64 µM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0040307.s002.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0040307.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Spectrophotometric assay of the time course of the PhKAT-catalyzed activity of KYN. The spectrum changes were monitored after the addition of 2OG, and PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>7 µM PLP; 20 µM KYN; 1 mM 2OG; 2 µM PhKAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>The enzymatic activity of PhKAT for KYNA productions cannot measure at this condition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0040307.s003.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0040307.s004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Comparison between the sequences of PhKAT and HuKAT II by pairwise alignment. The alignment was created using BioEdit and ESPript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>Ph, Pyrococcus horikoshii; Hu, human. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Black arrows and cylinders indicate the β-sheets and α-helices, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>Identical residues are in red boxes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>A blue arrowhead indicates a PLP ligand lysine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>The horizontal line indicates a possible mitochondrial-targeting peptide (MTP) of HuKAT II predicted by TargetP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>PhKAT shares 27% identity with HuKAT II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>The GenBank database (GB) accession numbers for PhKAT and HuKAT II are NP_142204 and NP_057312, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0040307.s004.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0040307.s005"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>Allosteric regulations for PhKAT. (A) The sigmoid dose-response shows the allosteric inhibition by a second allosteric effector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>The region of 8∼24 µM 2OG (data: means, n = 5) in Figure 4A is performed a curve fitting using a dose-response model with variable slopes for the inhibition and an altered equation of Cheng and Prusoff (Equ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>The absolute inhibition constant (K i) of 2OG for PhKAT was 20.11 µM (Table S2.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>(B) Close-up views of ∼2 µM 2OG regions in Figure 4A and B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>A black arrow and arrow heads indicate the conformation change from R state to T state of PhKAT and allosteries for KYNA productions respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>Black and white arrow heads indicate the inhibition by 2OG and activation by KYN, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>A max velocity at 1.2 µM 2OG of right hand increased 60% more than left hand. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0040307.s005.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0040307.s006"><label>Figure S6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>ITC controls for the interaction between the cofactor, substrates and KAT. The ITC profiles include experimental conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>(A) buffer and PLP; (B) PLP and 2OG; (C) PLP-KYN and 2OG. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0040307.s006.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0040307.s007"><label>Figure S7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>Superimposed representation of PLP and/or 2OG as substrate- and allosteric effector-bound complexes structures of PhKAT. Close-up view and Cα-trace ribbon-and-line representation of the α2-helix of PLP complex (PDB code: 3AO V) and 2OG effector complex structures of PhKAT after optimal superimposition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>The PLP-bound PhKAT complex is colored gray. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>Black-labeled numbers indicate the distance (Å) between the Cα traces of PLP complex and allosteric effector complex structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>The figure was generated using PyMOL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0040307.s007.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0040307.s008"><label>Figure S8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>The proposed mechanism for KYNA synthesis from KYN mediated by PhKAT. KYNA is synthesized from KYN via sequential reactions of KAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>PhKAT transaminates KYN to 2OG and/or OXA via PMP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>OXA and/or 2OG function as an amino-group acceptors and a naturally allosteric inhibitor that regulates KAT activity, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>GLU, glutamic acid; ASP, asparatic acid. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0040307.s008.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0040307.s009"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>Data collection and refinement statistics for PhKAT in complex with PLP and/or 2OG. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0040307.s009.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0040307.s010"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the kinetic parameters of substrates for the transaminase reaction from KYN to the keto-acid group. The transamination abilities of KYN to acceptors (2OG and α-keto-analogs) were assayed by measuring the rate of KYNA production. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0040307.s010.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0040307.s011"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>ITC parameters of cofactor and substrate binding to PhKAT. All measurements were performed in 50 mM HEPES–NaOH buffer (pH 7.5) with 100 mM NaCl. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0040307.s011.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0040307.s012"><label>Table S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>ITC control parameters. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0040307.s012.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0040307.s013"><label>Equation S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>Two sites binding with hill slopes (altered two sites binding model). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0040307.s013.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0040307.s014"><label>Equation S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>Sigmoidal dose-response and absolute inhibition constant ( K i). The IC50 value was converted to an absolute inhibition constant K i using the altered Cheng-Prusoff equation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0040307.s014.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0040307.s015"><label>Equation S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>Allosteric sigmoidal. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0040307.s015.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>We are grateful to Dr. S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>Tanaka (Amano Enzyme Co. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>Ltd., Nagoya, Japan) for the great suggestions. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>Funding: This work was supported in part by a grant (21380065) from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science, and Technology of Japan and by an Industrial Technology Research Grant Program from the New Energy and Industrial Technology Development Organization of Japan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0040307-Tobes1"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>1 TobesMCMasonM 1977 Alpha-Aminoadipate aminotransferase and kynurenine aminotransferase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>Purification, characterization, and further evidence for identity. J Biol Chem 252 4591 4599 873907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Wu1"><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>2 WuHQPereiraEFBrunoJPPellicciariRAlbuquerqueEX 2010 The astrocyte-derived alpha7 nicotinic receptor antagonist kynurenic acid controls extracellular glutamate levels in the prefrontal cortex. J Mol Neurosci 40 204 210 19690987 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Hartai1"><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>3 HartaiZJuhaszARimanoczyAJanakyTDonkoT 2007 Decreased serum and red blood cell kynurenic acid levels in Alzheimer’s disease. Neurochem Int 50 308 313 17023091 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Erhardt1"><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>4 ErhardtSSchwielerLEngbergG 2003 Kynurenic acid and schizophrenia. Adv Exp Med Biol 527 155 165 15206728 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Rossi1"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>5 RossiFSchwarczRRizziM 2008 Curiosity to kill the KAT (kynurenine aminotransferase): structural insights into brain kynurenic acid synthesis. Curr Opin Struct Biol 18 748 755 18950711 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Han1"><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>6 HanQCaiTTagleDALiJ 2010 Structure, expression, and function of kynurenine aminotransferases in human and rodent brains. Cell Mol Life Sci 67 353 368 19826765 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Han2"><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>7 HanQGaoYGRobinsonHLiJ 2008 Structural insight into the mechanism of substrate specificity of aedes kynurenine aminotransferase. Biochemistry 47 1622 1630 18186649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Wogulis1"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>8 WogulisMChewERDonohouePDWilsonDK 2008 Identification of formyl kynurenine formamidase and kynurenine aminotransferase from Saccharomyces cerevisiae using crystallographic, bioinformatic and biochemical evidence. Biochemistry 47 1608 1621 18205391 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Marciano1"><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>9 MarcianoDMaugeriDACazzuloJJNowickiC 2009 Functional characterization of stage-specific aminotransferases from trypanosomatids. Mol Biochem Parasitol 166 172 182 19443056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Chon1"><text><SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>10 ChonHMatsumuraHKogaYTakanoKKanayaS 2005 Crystal structure of a human kynurenine aminotransferase II homologue from Pyrococcus horikoshii OT3 at 2.20 A resolution. Proteins 61 685 688 16138312 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Kawarabayasi1"><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>11 KawarabayasiYSawadaMHorikawaHHaikawaYHinoY 1998 Complete sequence and gene organization of the genome of a hyper-thermophilic archaebacterium, Pyrococcus horikoshii OT3 (supplement). DNA Res 5 147 155 9679203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Kawarabayasi2"><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>12 KawarabayasiYSawadaMHorikawaHHaikawaYHinoY 1998 Complete sequence and gene organization of the genome of a hyper-thermophilic archaebacterium, Pyrococcus horikoshii OT3. DNA Res 5 55 76 9679194 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Rossi2"><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>13 RossiFGaravagliaSMontalbanoVWalshMARizziM 2008 Crystal structure of human kynurenine aminotransferase II, a drug target for the treatment of schizophrenia. J Biol Chem 283 3559 3566 18056996 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Han3"><text><SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>14 HanQRobinsonHLiJ 2008 Crystal structure of human kynurenine aminotransferase II. J Biol Chem 283 3567 3573 18056995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Chon2"><text><SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>15 ChonHMatsumuraHShimizuSMaedaNKogaY 2005 Overproduction and preliminary crystallographic study of a human kynurenine aminotransferase II homologue from Pyrococcus horikoshii OT3. Acta Crystallogr Sect F Struct Biol Cryst Commun 61 319 322  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Han4"><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>16 HanQCaiTTagleDALiJ 2010 Thermal stability, pH dependence and inhibition of four murine kynurenine aminotransferases. BMC Biochem 11 19 20482848 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Rossi3"><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>17 RossiFHanQLiJRizziM 2004 Crystal structure of human kynurenine aminotransferase I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>J Biol Chem 279 50214 50220  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Vagin1"><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>18 VaginATeplyakovA 2010 Molecular replacement with MOLREP. Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr 66 22 25 20057045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-1"><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>19 1994 The CCP4 suite: programs for protein crystallography. Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr 50 760 763 15299374 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Murshudov1"><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>20 MurshudovGNVaginAADodsonEJ 1997 Refinement of macromolecular structures by the maximum-likelihood method. Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr 53 240 255 15299926 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Emsley1"><text><SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>21 EmsleyPCowtanK 2004 Coot: model-building tools for molecular graphics. Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr 60 2126 2132 15572765 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0040307-Crooks1"><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>22 CrooksGEHonGChandoniaJMBrennerSE 2004 WebLogo: a sequence logo generator. Genome Res 14 1188 1190 15173120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
