
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Parasite</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Parasite</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">parasite</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Parasite</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1252-607X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1776-1042</issn><publisher><publisher-name>EDP Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3859029</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/parasite/2013053</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">parasite130045</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">10.1051/parasite/2013053</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Expression and immunolocalisation of TpFABP as a candidate antigen for the serodiagnosis of rabbit Taenia pisiformis cysticercosis </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><trans-title-group xml:lang="fr"><trans-title>Expression et immunolocalisation de <italic>TpFABP</italic> comme antigène candidat pour le sérodiagnostic de la cysticercose du lapin à <italic>Taenia pisiformis</italic></trans-title></trans-title-group></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Deying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Lin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Yue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Xuhang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nong</surname><given-names>Xiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Xi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>Weimin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Xiaobin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Shuxian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Xuerong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Guangyou</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="FN1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Parasitology, College of Veterinary Medicine, Sichuan Agricultural University Ya’an 625014 China
</addr-line></aff><aff id="AFF2"><label>2</label><addr-line>
College of Veterinary Medicine, Sichuan Agricultural University Ya’an 625014 China
</addr-line></aff><aff id="AFF3"><label>3</label><addr-line>
College of Life and Basic Science, Sichuan Agricultural University Ya’an 625014 China
</addr-line></aff><author-notes><corresp id="FN1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author: <email>guangyouyang@hotmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">parasite/2013/01</issue-id><elocation-id>53</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© D. Yang et al., published by EDP Sciences, 2013</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>D. Yang et al.,</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The larval stage of Taenia pisiformis, also known as Cysticercus pisiformis, is the causative agent of cysticercosis and the cause of severe health problems in rabbits that negatively impacts on husbandry production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>To date, there is no fast detection method to identify early infections in rabbits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>In the present study, a new dot-ELISA-based on an endogenous antigen fatty acid-binding protein (FABP) was developed for the detection of cysticercosis, and its potential was then evaluated using test serum samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Immunolocalisation showed that T. pisiformis FABP (TpFABP) localised to the parenchyma of the bladder wall of the cysticercus and perinuclear cytoplasm of parenchyma of the adult parasite. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>After cloning and expression, recombinant TpFABP (rTpFABP) protein was used for serodiagnosis of T. pisiformis infection in rabbits by dot-ELISA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The antibody was detected 14 days post-infection in rabbits experimentally infected with T. pisiformis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Based on the necropsy results, the sensitivity and specificity of 169 serum samples tested by rTpFABP dot-ELISA were found to be 98.2% (54/55) and 92.1% (105/114), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that the dot-ELISA developed in this study has potential for detection of T. pisiformis infection in rabbits. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><trans-abstract xml:lang="fr"><p>Le stade larvaire de <italic>Taenia pisiformis</italic>, également connu sous le nom <italic>Cysticercus pisiformis</italic>, est l’agent causal de la cysticercose et la cause de graves problèmes de santé chez les lapins, ayant un impact négatif sur la production d’élevage. À ce jour, il n’existe aucune méthode de détection rapide pour identifier les infections précoces chez les lapins. Dans cette étude, un nouveau dot-ELISA basé sur une protéine de liaison aux acides gras antigéniques endogènes (<italic>FABP</italic>) a été développé pour la détection de la cysticercose, et son potentiel a ensuite été évalué en utilisant des échantillons de sérum. L’immunolocalisation a montré que la protéine <italic>FABP</italic> de <italic>T. pisiformis</italic> (<italic>TpFABP</italic>) se localisait au niveau du parenchyme de la paroi du cysticerque et du cytoplasme périnucléaire du parenchyme du parasite adulte. Après clonage et expression, la protéine recombinante <italic>TpFABP</italic> (<italic>rTpFABP</italic>) a été utilisée chez les lapins pour le diagnostic sérologique par dot-ELISA de l’infection à <italic>T. pisiformis</italic>. L’anticorps a été détecté 14 jours après l’infection chez des lapins infectés expérimentalement avec <italic>T. pisiformis</italic>. Sur la base des résultats d’autopsie, la sensibilité et la spécificité de 169 échantillons de sérum testés par <italic>rTpFABP</italic> dot-ELISA ont été respectivement de 98 % (54/55) et 92 % (105/114). Ces données suggèrent que le dot-ELISA développé dans cette étude a un potentiel pour la détection de l’infection à <italic>T. pisiformis</italic> chez les lapins.</p></trans-abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Taenia pisiformis</italic></kwd><kwd>Rabbit</kwd><kwd>Fatty acid-binding protein</kwd><kwd>Immunolocalisation</kwd><kwd>Immunodiagnosis</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="30"/><page-count count="7"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="S1"><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Cysticercosis, an infection caused by the larvae of Taenia pisiformis (Bloch, 1780) [27], is one of the most common parasitic disease in rabbits [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>During the life cycle of T. pisiformis, the cysticerci present in the abdominal cavity of infected rabbit are ingested by a definitive host (canids and felines), following which the adult T. pisiformis individuals parasitises and matures in the host small intestine [2, 23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The gravid proglottids of T. pisiformis released from infected dogs are in turn ingested by rabbit through contaminated food or water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The proglottids discharge oncospheres in the rabbit intestine and penetrate the intestinal mucosa and blood vessels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The oncospheres reach the liver parenchyma, then migrate to liver capsule, greater omentum and mesentery and develop into cysticerci [18, 20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>China is the world’s largest producer of rabbits [5], and T. pisiformis severely affects rabbit breeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Rabbits infected with T. pisiformis are emaciated and have weak resistance to other diseases; in particular, it can also cause death especially for breeding rabbit. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The rapid and accurate detection of cysticercosis in rabbits is crucial for arresting its negative impact on husbandry production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In general, as there are no obvious early clinical symptoms in rabbits infected with T. pisiformis, it is a major challenge to control this disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The presence of T. pisiformis-specific antibodies in serum from infected rabbits can provide the foundation for detection of this parasite [6, 29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Crude antigens from oncospheres or mature metacestodes have been used in previous studies [6, 29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>However, due to the limited availability of crude parasite antigens, only a few serologic tests have been used to detect anti-T. pisiformis antibodies, including enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) and indirect fluorescent antibody test (IFAT) [6, 29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In addition, the standard ELISA and IFAT methods are too complex to be used routinely under field conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Keeping these considerations in mind, dot-ELISA is one of the better serodiagnostic strategies due to its sensitivity and convenience. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Fatty acid-binding proteins (FABPs), multigenic cytosolic proteins are found in most animal groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>They are involved in the uptake and transport of hydrophobic ligands to different cellular fates [10, 13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In helminthic parasites, FABPs are proven to be involved in acquisition and utilisation of host-derived hydrophobic substances, as well as in signalling and cellular interactions [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In the present study, a new FABP homologue TpFABP, from T. pisiformis was cloned and expressed and its immunolocalisation was then analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Based on these results, a new recombinant FABP (rTpFABP) protein-based dot-ELISA was developed for the serodiagnosis of T. pisiformis infections in the rabbit industry. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S2"><title><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S3"><title><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Ethics statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>All animals were handled in strict accordance with animal protection law of the People’s Republic of China (a draft of an animal protection law in China released on September 18, 2009) and the National Standards for Laboratory Animals in China (Laboratory animal – Standards and monitoring for parasitology, GB 14922.1-2001, executed on May 1, 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>All experiment protocols were conducted according to the principles set forth in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals, Veterinary College, Sichuan Agricultural University, China. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S4"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>TpFABP amplification and structural prediction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was isolated from mature metacestodes (provided by the parasitology laboratory at the Sichuan Agricultural University, China) using Trizol reagent (Invitrogen, Shanghai, China) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The cDNA was obtained using the SuperScript Double-Stranded cDNA Synthesis kit (Invitrogen, Shanghai, China) following the manufacturer’s protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Based on the cDNA sequence of T. solium FABP (GenBank: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://DQ273765">DQ273765</ext-link>), the gene-specific primers for TpFABP were designed as follows (letters in parentheses represent the code of degenerate primers): F1 5′-ATGGAGSCATTCMTY(C)GKW(T)ACCTGGA-3′, R1 5′-TCCCTTACRY(T)CMCY(C)Y(T)TW(T)RMGTAGKTTC-3′. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>PCR was performed in a 25 μL final volume, including 12.5 μL of PCR mixture (Invitrogen, Shanghai, China), 0.4 μM of each primer (forward and reverse), 1 μL of cDNA template and 9.5 μL ddH2O. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The amplification conditions consisted of an initial denaturing step at 94 °C for 5 min, followed by 35 cycles of amplification, 94 °C for 50 s, 56 °C for 45 s, and 72 °C for 50 s and a final extension step at 72 °C for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The PCR products were cloned into pMD19-T vector (TaKaRa, Dalian, China), and sequenced using an ABI PRISMTM 377XL DNA Sequencer (ABI, Foster City, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The new TpFABP sequence was deposited in GenBank with Accession Number <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://GU205472">GU205472</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>BepiPred 1.0 server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbsdtu.dk/services/BepiPred/">http://www.cbsdtu.dk/services/BepiPred/</ext-link>) was used to predict the location of linear B-cell epitopes [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>PredictProtein (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.predictprotein.org/">http://www.predictprotein.org/</ext-link>) was used to infer the secondary structures [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The alignment of TpFABP amino acid sequences with those of other Taeniidae cestodes and Oryctolagus cuniculus was performed using ClustalX 1.83 software [25], and the MegAlign program of DNAstar software package [4] was utilised to calculate the percentage identities. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S5"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>rTpFABP expression and western blotting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The expression sequence of TpFABP was amplified by F2 5′-GGGATCCATGGAGGCATTCCTCGGTA-3′ and R2 5′-CGCTCGAGTTACGTCCCTTTAAAGTAGGTTC-3′ using the same PCR conditions described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The PCR products were subcloned into the BamH1 and Xhol sites of the expression vector pET32a (Novagen, Darmstadt, Germany) and expressed in Escherichia coli BL21 (DE3) induced by 0.6 M isopropyl-β-d-thiogalactoside (IPTG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The TpFABP fusion proteins (fused with the Trx-Tag™ thioredoxin) were dissolved using 8 M urea, purified on an Ni-IDA sefinoseTM resin (Bio-Rad, California, USA), and the concentration of the purified protein was determined by a Biophotometer (Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany) using a BCA Protein Assay Kit (Beyotime, Haimen, China) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The rTpFABP protein was separated on a 12% sodium dodecyl sulphate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE), and transferred to a nitrocellulose (NC) filtre membrane (Sigma, San Francisco, USA) by electroblotting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The membrane was washed three times for 5 min with 0.01 M phosphate buffer solution (PBS), and blocked with 5% non-fat milk powder in 0.01 M PBS for 2 h at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The rabbit antisera was probed with 1:100 dilution, and added directly to the blocking solution (including 5% non-fat milk powder and 0.01 M PBS) at 4 °C overnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The rabbit T. pisiformis antisera were sourced from animals at 50 days post-experimental infection (provided by the laboratory of parasitology in Sichuan Agricultural University). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The membrane was then washed three times with PBS for 5 min each, and incubated with horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG (1:5,000 dilution; Sigma, San Francisco, USA) for 1.5 h at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Finally, the membranes were washed three times with 0.01 M PBS for 5 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The membrane was exposed to HRP-diaminobenzidine (DAB) substrate (Tiangen, Beijing, China) following the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S6"><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Immunolocalisation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Polyclonal antisera against rTpFABP protein were raised in two 9-week old female parasite-free New Zealand White rabbits (obtained from Laboratory Animal Centre of Sichuan Agricultural University, China) by consecutive subcutaneous inoculation of the rTpFABP protein as described by Hu et al. (2002) [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The immune sera were obtained by centrifugation at 4,000× g for 10 min in room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>IgG fractions were isolated using a Protein G affinity chromatography column (Bio-Rad, California, USA) and stored at −80 °C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The collection of fresh mature metacestodes and adult of T. pisiformis was previously described [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The parasites were freshly fixed in Bouin’s solution for 24 h and then embedded in paraffin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The sections were cut serially at 7 μm thickness using a slicer (Leica, Wetzlar, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Immunolocalisation was carried out using a streptavidin biotin complex-peroxidase (SABC-POD) with rabbit IgG kit (Boster, Wuhan, China) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The purified IgG fractions against TpFABP were diluted to 200 times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Peroxidase activity was visualised by incubating sections with a DAB-Plus Kit (Boster, Wuhan, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Finally, the slides were counterstained with Mayer’s haematoxylin, examined with an optical microscope and photographed (Nikon, E800). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S7"><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Collection of sera </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Three healthy rabbits were used as the negative control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Positive polyclonal antisera against rTpFABP protein were as described above. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Experimental sera were collected from seven 90-day old healthy white female New Zealand White rabbits (Oryctolagus cuniculus) sourced from the Laboratory Animal Centre of Sichuan Agricultural University, China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The rabbits were orally infected with 5,000 mature viable T. pisiformis eggs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Serum samples were collected every 7 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The rabbits were humanely sacrificed (50 mg/kg ketamine and 100 mg/kg sodium pentobarbital [Sigma, San Francisco, USA]) at 49 days post-infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Necropsies were as performed as previously described [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Test serum samples (n = 169) were collected from rabbits from a local slaughterhouse, and the serum was separated and stored at −20 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The abdominal cavity of rabbits was examined for the presence of T. pisiformis cysticerci, as previously described. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Sera from rabbits (n = 22, provided by the Department of Parasitology, Veterinary College, Sichuan Agricultural University, China) infected with Sarcoptes scabiei (seven cases), Psoroptes cuniculi (eight cases), Eimeria spp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>(four cases) and Passalurus ambiguus (three cases) were used to test cross-reactivity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S8"><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Dot-ELISA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Total T. pisiformis-specific IgG antibodies of rabbits were detected by dot-ELISA using rTpFABP as the test antigen following the methodology described by Piña et al. (2011) [21] with some modifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Briefly, 50, 100 and 200 ng of the purified antigen (10 μg/mL) were dotted on marked circular regions at the centre of each NC strip. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The positive polyclonal sera (1:50, 1:100, 1:200) and goat anti-rabbit IgG-HRP conjugate (1:7000) (Sigma, San Francisco, USA) were diluted using PBS Tween-20 and 5% (w/v) non-fat milk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>ELISA dots were detected by HRP-DAB (Invitrogen, Shanghai, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The visual reading by two independent observers was the same for all tests, and no difference in colour intensity was observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>In addition to the background colour, a tan-yellow reaction was designated as a positive result. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The best dilution of rTpFABP antigen and rabbit sera was determined by the colour reaction intensity in the positive dot-ELISA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The remainder of the experimental and test sera were detected by dot-ELISA and described as above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The percentage sensitivity was calculated as dot-ELISA positive × 100/true positive, and the percentage specificity was calculated as dot-ELISA negative × 100/true negative [28]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="S9"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S10"><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Sequence analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The TpFABP cDNA sequence consisted of an open-reading frame of 402 bp encoding a putative protein with 133 amino acid residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The results of initial BLASTx searches with TpFABP at National Centre of Biotechnology Information (NCBI) showed that the amino acid sequence of TpFABP shared 95% identities with TsFABP1, 85% with Echinococcus granulosus FABP1 (EgFABP1), 84% with TsFABP2 and EgFABP2, and 39.8% with heart-FABP (H-FABP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>In addition, the available FABP sequences from Oryctolagus cuniculus, including FABP1 (XM_002709637), FABP2 (intestinal-like, XM_002717226), FABP3 (XM_002716060), FABP7 (brain, XM_002714798), FABP9 (testis, XM_002710656) and FABP12-like (XM_002710657) shared 24–41% identities with the amino acid sequence of TpFABP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The protein secondary structure demonstrated a characteristic composition: two antiparallel α-helices (including 13 residues) and 10 β-strands (including 67 residues; Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>There were six locations of linear B-cell epitopes, including MEKSEG (residues 10–15), LGDGKYSMR (residues 45–53), ESKFK (residues 55–59), KFKETTPDSRE (residues 70–80), VMKQEQVGKGKTT (residues 91–103) and LK (residues 114–115).Figure 1.Structural analysis of TpFABP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Alignment of the amino acid residue sequences of Taenia pisiformis FABP with T. solium and Echinococcus granulosus in primary structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The secondary structure of the TpFABP amino acid residue sequence was predicted and is shown at the top of the alignment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The light-grey shading indicates the identical amino acid sequences, and locations of linear B-cell epitopes are marked with open boxes. TpFABP1, GU205472; TsFABP1, HQ259679; TsFABP2, AFS64570; EgFABP1, 1O8V_A; EgFABP2, AAK12095; H-FABP, NP_004093. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S11"><title><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>rTpFABP expression and western blotting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>rTpFABP was successfully expressed in E. coli strain BL21 (DE3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The molecular weight of the recombinant protein was about 36 kDa, and the solubility of rTpFABP protein was identified as inclusion bodies. rTpFABP was recognised by rabbit T. pisiformis cysticercosis antisera in western blotting analysis (Figure 2).Figure 2.Expression of rTpFABP and identification by rabbit antisera in western blotting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Lane (1) molecular weight markers; (2) purified rTpFABP protein; (3) rTpFABP protein reacted with negative rabbit serum (1:100 v/v dilutions) by western blotting analysis; (4) rTpFABP protein reacted with rabbit antisera (1:100 v/v dilutions) by western blotting analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Molecular masses (kDa) are indicated on the left. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S12"><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Immunolocalisation of TpFABP </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>TpFABP was localised in perinuclear cytoplasm (PC) of adult T. pisiformis proglottids (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the positive signal was observed in the parenchyma of the bladder wall of the cysticercus, and intensely localised in outer layer of cystic wall (OCW) and middle layer of cystic wall (MCW).Figure 3.Immunolocalisation of TpFABP in T. pisiformis tapeworm and cysticercus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The yellowish-brown tint shows the TpFABP protein location. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>(A) negative sera in cysticercus; (B) antisera in cysticercus; (C) negative sera in adult tapeworm; (D) antisera in adult tapeworm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Arrows indicate the areas of the parasite: MT, microthrix; DC, distal cytoplasm; PC, perinuclear cytoplasm; GD, gathering duct; M, microtrichia; ICW, inside the layer of cystic wall; OCW, outer layer of cystic wall; MCW, middle layer of cystic wall. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Scale bars: 20 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S13"><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Dot-ELISA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Combinations of various amount of antigens tested with various dilutions of positive polyclonal sera did not show any differences (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Therefore, 200 ng of rTpFABP antigen and 1:100 of sera in each strip were determined to be the optimal combination for the full set of sample tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The experimental sera were found to be positive at 14 days post-infection, and remained through to 49 days post-infection (Figure 4) when the rabbits were sacrificed.Figure 4.Dot-ELISA of naturally infected rabbit experimental sera with rTpFABP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The tan-yellow tint shows the positive reaction: A, negative control sera; B, positive antisera; C, sera at 0 day post-infection; D, sera at 7 days post-infection; E, sera at 14 days post-infection; F, sera at 21 days post-infection; G, sera at 28 days post-infection; H, sera at 35 days post-infection; I, sera at 42 days post-infection; J, sera at 49 days post-infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Of the 169 rabbits sampled from the slaughterhouse, T. pisiformis cysticerci were found in 55 rabbits by necropsy, but it was not present in 114 rabbits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Fifty-four rabbits tested positive and 105 were negative by dot-ELISA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Thus, the sensitivity and specificity of dot-ELISA using rTpFABP antigen to detect T. pisiformis cysticercus were 98.2% (54/55) and 92.1% (105/114), respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>There was no cross-reaction between rTpFABP and the positive sera of Sarcoptes scabiei, Psoroptes cuniculi, Eimeria spp. and Passalurus ambiguus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S14"><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Nine groups of FABPs have been identified in mammals with variable primary structures (identity, 20–70%), but all the members of this family share a superimposable tertiary structure [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>In our study, TpFABP amino acid sequence shared the highest identity (95%) with TsFABP1 in primary structure, and had the 10-stranded β-barrel fold, typical for the family of intracellular lipid-binding proteins [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Six locations of linear B-cell epitopes between TpFABP, TsFABP1, TsFABP2, EgFABP1 and EgFABP2 had a similar distribution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Together, these suggest a common conservation of this family of genes within cestode parasites as well as a possible common ancestral gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>However, low identities (23.88–41.04%) between the available FABP amino acid sequences from rabbit and the TpFABP from T. pisiformis indicated that they would not share a common ancestral gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The adult stages of parasitic platyhelminths are dependent on carbohydrates for their energy metabolism [26], but a functional β-oxidation pathway has not been demonstrated in cestodes [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>FABPs synthesise most of their own lipids de novo by combining hydrophobic groups to help platyhelminths, especially long-chain fatty acids and cholesterol [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, FABPs have been described as intracellular carriers of fatty acid (FA) [7]. EgFABP1 is specifically expressed in the protoscolex larval stage and associated with protoscolex larval development [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Abundant expressions of TsFABP1 and TsFABP2 were found in the canal region of adult T. solium [16], and TsFABP1 also was positive in subtegumental cytons of tissue sections from cysticerci from T. pisiformis [14]. TsFABP1 has been demonstrated to be involved in the transport of several fatty acids required for T. solium nourishment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>It is plausible that TsFABP1 is involved in the mechanism by which FAs are mobilised from the translocation site on the tegument membrane, to other cellular compartments in the syncytium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>In this study, the positive distribution of TpFABP was similar to T. crassiceps FABP in cysticerci [14], and was widely distributed in the parenchyma of the bladder wall in the cysticerci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The localisation of TpFABP in the cysticerci suggested that the cystic wall layer might be a primary location in the scolex where FA uptake occurs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>In tissue sections of adult T. pisiformis, the positive staining distribution was the same as T. solium FABP1 [14]. TpFABP is probably involved in the uptake and transport of fatty acid molecules in the perinuclear cytoplasm to maintain the survival of adult T. pisiformis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Thus, the biological role of TpFABP in T. pisiformis may be similar to that of FABP1 in T. solium [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>With guaranteed supply of fatty acids for survival by abundant fatty acid-binding proteins, parasites can adjust their biological mechanism to adapt to a changing environment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Because T. pisiformis infection in rabbits is not associated with specific clinical symptoms, it is difficult to detect it in the early infective stage (up to 7 weeks post-infection). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>This stage involved adherence of the oncosphere to and migration across the intestinal wall, followed by transport to the liver parenchyma via the circulatory system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The oncosphere finally migrates to the abdominal cavity of rabbits [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Detection of the antibody against T. pisiformis cysticerci could be useful for early detection and treatment of this infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Circular antibodies in experimental T. pisiformis infections of rabbits have been previously investigated [6], which indicated that antibodies were detected in rabbit sera by 2 weeks post-infection using the in vitro-derived T. pisiformis metacestode antigen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>In addition, Wang et al. (2009) [20] investigated the dynamic profile of antibodies in rabbits experimentally infected with T. pisiformis using crude antigen from mature metacestodes, and found that the antibody levels started to increase at week three post-infection and were up to the highest level at week eight post-infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>In our study, dot-ELISA of rTpFABP was successfully established to detect rabbit T. pisiformis cysticercosis under the optimum conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The antibodies in experimental sera could be detected by dot-ELISA in the early stage of infection (14 days), and lasted 7 weeks (49 days) post-infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The dot-ELISA was developed in this study with a high sensitivity (98.2%) and specificity (92.1%) for 169 tested sera samples when compared with the results of necropsy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The cross-reactivity of several parasites of rabbit, a potential probability of false positives, was also carried out, and no cross-reactivity was observed with our panel of positive sera of other parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Thus, rTpFABP antigen can detect specifically T. pisiformis cysticercosis in tested rabbits. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Together, the data shows that rTpFABP is a suitable diagnostic antigen, and the results of study demonstrate the efficacy of the FABP-based dot-ELISA for potential detection of T. pisiformis cysticercosis in rabbit. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><ack><p>This study was supported by a grant from the Program for Changjiang Scholars Innovative Research Team in University (PCSIRT) (No. IRT0848). The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest.</p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="R1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>1Alvite G, Di Pietro SM, Santomé JA, Ehrlich R, Esteves A. 2001 Binding properties of Echinococcus granulosus fatty acid binding protein. Biochimica et Biophysica Acta, 1533, 293–30211731339 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R2"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>2Bagrade G, Kirjusina M, Vismanis K, Ozoliņs J. 2009 Helminth parasites of the wolf Canis lupus from Latvia. Journal of Helminthology, 83, 63–6819138449 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R3"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>3Betancourt MA, de Aluja AS, Sciutto E, Hernández M, Bobes RJ, Rosas G, Hernández B, Fragoso G, Hallal-Calleros C, Aguilar L, Flores-Peréz I. 2012 Effective protection induced by three different versions of the porcine S3Pvac anticysticercosis vaccine against rabbit experimental Taenia pisiformis cysticercosis. Vaccine, 30, 2760–276722349522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R4"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>4Burland TG. 2000 DNASTAR’s Lasergene sequence analysis software. Methods in Molecular Biology, 132, 71–9110547832 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R5"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>5Chen YF, Xie XP, Sun SP. 2010 The existing state and development strategy of rabbits production in China. Modern Agriculture, 6–7 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R6"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>6Craig PS. 1984 Circulating antigens, antibodies and immune complexes in experimental Taenia pisiformis infections of rabbits. Parasitology, 89, 121–1316382128 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R7"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>7Doege H, Stahl A. 2006 Protein-mediated fatty acid uptake: novel insights from in vivo models. Physiology (Bethesda), 21, 259–26816868315 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R8"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>8Estevez A, Dallagiovanna B, Ehrlich R. 1993 A developmentally regulated gene of Echinococcus granulosus codes for a 15.5 kDa polypeptide related to fatty acid binding proteins. Molecular and Biochemical Parasitology, 58, 215–2228479446 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R9"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>9Esteves A, Joseph L, Paulino M, Ehrlich R. 1997 Remarks on the phylogeny and structure of fatty acid binding proteins from parasitic platyhelminths. International Journal for Parasitology, 27, 1013–10239363483 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R10"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>10Esteves A, Ehrlich R. 2006 Invertebrate intracellular fatty acid binding proteins. Comparative Biochemistry and Physiology C Toxicology &amp; Pharmacology, 142, 262–274 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R11"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>11Gemmell MA. 1965 Immunological responses of the mammalian host against tapeworm infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Species specificity of hexacanth embryos in protecting rabbits against Taenia pisiformis. Immunology, 8, 270–28014317586 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R12"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>12Hu YX, Guo JY, Shen L, Chen Y, Zhang ZC, Zhang YL. 2002 Get effective polyclonal antisera in one month. Cell Research, 12, 157–16012118942 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R13"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>13Hertzel AV, Bernlohr DA. 2000 The mammalian fatty acid-binding protein multigene family: molecular and genetic insights into function. Trends in Endocrinology and Metabolism, 11, 175–18010856918 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R14"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>14Illescas O, Carrero JC, Bobes RJ, Flisser A, Rosas G, Laclette JP. 2012 Molecular characterization, functional expression, tissue localization and protective potential of a Taenia solium fatty acid-binding protein. Molecular and Biochemical Parasitology, 186, 117–12523085006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R15"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>15Jakobsson E, Alvite G, Bergfors T, Esteves A, Kleywegt GJ. 2003 The crystal structure of Echinococcus granulosus fatty-acid-binding protein 1. Biochimica et Biophysica Acta, 1649, 40–5012818189 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R16"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>16Kim SH, Bae YA, Yang HJ, Shin JH, Diaz-Camacho SP, Nawa Y, Kang I, Kong Y. 2012 Structural and binding properties of two paralogous fatty acid binding proteins of Taenia solium metacestode. Plos Neglected Tropical Diseases, 6, e186823150743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R17"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>17Larsen JE, Lund O, Nielsen M. 2006 Improved method for predicting linear B-cell epitopes. Immunome Research, 2, 216635264 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R18"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>18Miguel-Angel BA, Agustín O, Virginio A, Reyes V, Fernando-Iván FP. 2011 Changes in behavioural and physiological parameters associated with Taenia pisiformis infection in rabbits (Oryctolagus cuniculus) that may improve early detection of sick rabbits. World Rabbit Science, 19, 21–30 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R19"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>19Nie HM, Xie Y, Fu Y, Yang YD, Gu XB, Wang SX, Peng X, Lai WM, Peng XR, Yang GY. 2013 Cloning and characterization of the fatty acid-binding protein gene from the protoscolex of Taenia multiceps. Parasitology Research, 112, 1833–183923474657 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R20"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>20Owiny JR. 2001 Cysticercosis in laboratory rabbits. Contemporary Topics in Laboratory Animal Science, 40, 45–4811300689 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R21"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>21Piña R, Gutiérrez AH, Gilman RH, Rueda D, Sifuentes C, Flores M, Sheen P, Rodriguez S, García HH, Zimic M. 2011 A dot-ELISA using a partially purified cathepsin-L-like protein fraction from Taenia solium cysticerci for the diagnosis of human neurocysticercosis. Annals of Tropical Medicine and Parasitology, 105, 311–31821871167 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R22"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>22Rost B, Yachdav G, Liu J. 2004 The PredictProtein server. Nucleic Acids Research, 32 (Web Server issue), W321–32615215403 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R23"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>23Saeed I, Maddox-Hyttel C, Monrad J, Kapel CM. 2006 Helminths of red foxes (Vulpes vulpes) in Denmark. Veterinary Parasitology, 139, 1–316675128 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R24"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>24Smyth JD, McManus DP. 1989 The adult: general metabolism and chemical composition: lipid metabolism, in The Physiology and Biochemistry of Cestodes. Smyth JD, McManus DP, Eds.Cambridge University Press: Cambridge p. 53–65 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R25"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>25Thompson JD, Gibson TJ, Plewniak F, Jeanmougin F, Higgins DG. 1997 The ClustalX windows interface: flexible strategies for multiple sequence alignment aided by quality analysis tools. Nucleic Acids Research, 25, 4876–48829396791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R26"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>26Tielens AG. 1994 Energy generation in parasitic helminths. Parasitology Today, 10, 346–35215275412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R27"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>27Toral-Bastida E, Garza-Rodriguez A, Jimenez-Gonzalez DE, Garcia-Cortes R, Avila-Ramirez G, Maravilla P, Flisser A. 2011 Development of Taenia pisiformis in golden hamster (Mesocricetus auratus). Parasite &amp; Vectors, 4, 147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R28"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>28Varghese A, Raina OK, Nagar G, Garg R, Banerjee PS, Maharana BR, Kollannur JD. 2012 Development of cathepsin-L cysteine proteinase based Dot-enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay for the diagnosis of Fasciola gigantica infection in buffaloes. Veterinary Parasitology, 183, 382–38522055612 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R29"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>29Wang XX, Luo XN, Sun XL, Yu SK, Cai XP. 2009 Kinetics of antibodies in rabbits experimentally infected with Cysticercus pisiformis. Veterinary Science in China, 4, 283–286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R30"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>30Yang DY, Fu Y, Wu XH, Xie Y, Nie HM, Chen L, Nong X, Gu XB, Wang SX, Peng XR, Yan N, Zhang RH, Zheng WP, Yang GY. 2012 Annotation of the transcriptome from Taenia pisiformis and its comparative analysis with three Taeniidae species. Plos One, 7, e3228322514598 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><notes><boxed-text position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Cite this article as</bold>: Yang D, Chen L, Xie Y, Wu X, Nong X, Peng X, Lai W, Gu X, Wang S, Peng X &amp; Yang G: Expression and immunolocalisation of <italic>TpFABP</italic> as a candidate antigen for the serodiagnosis of rabbit <italic>Taenia pisiformis</italic> cysticercosis. Parasite, 2013, <bold>20</bold>, 53.</p></boxed-text></notes></back></article>
