
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Mol Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Mol Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijms</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1422-0067</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3794815</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24065097</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms140918959</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ijms-14-18959</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Emulsifying Activity and Stability of a Non-Toxic Bioemulsifier Synthesized by Microbacterium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>MC3B-10 </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Camacho-Chab</surname><given-names>Juan Carlos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-14-18959">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guézennec</surname><given-names>Jean</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijms-14-18959">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chan-Bacab</surname><given-names>Manuel Jesús</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-14-18959">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ríos-Leal</surname><given-names>Elvira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-ijms-14-18959">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sinquin</surname><given-names>Corinne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijms-14-18959">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Muñiz-Salazar</surname><given-names>Raquel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-ijms-14-18959">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>De la Rosa-García</surname><given-names>Susana del C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-14-18959">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reyes-Estebanez</surname><given-names>Manuela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-14-18959">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ortega-Morales</surname><given-names>Benjamín Otto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-14-18959">1</xref><xref rid="c1-ijms-14-18959" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-ijms-14-18959"><label>1</label>Center of Environmental Microbiology and Biotechnology, Autonomous University of Campeche, Colonia Buenavista, San Francisco de Campeche 24039, Campeche, Mexico; E-Mails: <email>juanccam@uacam.mx</email> (J.C.C.-C.); <email>manjchan@uacam.mx</email> (M.J.C.-B.); <email>scdelaro@uacam.mx</email> (S.C.R.-G.); <email>reyes_estebanez@hotmail.com</email> (M.R.-E.)</aff><aff id="af2-ijms-14-18959"><label>2</label>Ifremer Laboratoire Biotechnologies et Molécules Marines, Nantes B. P. 21105, France; E-Mails: <email>guezennec.jean@wanadoo.fr</email> (J.G.); <email>Corinne.Sinquin@ifremer.fr</email> (C.S.)</aff><aff id="af3-ijms-14-18959"><label>3</label>Department of Biotechnology and Bioengineering, Center for Research and Advanced Studies of the National Polytechnic Institute (CINVESTAV), Mexico City 07360, Federal District, Mexico; E-Mail: <email>erios@cinvestav.mx</email></aff><aff id="af4-ijms-14-18959"><label>4</label>Laboratory of Molecular Ecology and Epidemiology, School of Health Sciences, Autonomous University of Baja California, Tijuana 22390, Baja California, Mexico; E-Mail: <email>ramusal@uabc.edu.mx</email></aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-ijms-14-18959"><label>*</label>Author to whom correspondence should be addressed; E-Mail: <email>beortega@uacam.mx</email>; Tel.: +52-981-811-9800 (ext. 1530101).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>18959</fpage><lpage>18972</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>03</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>04</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 by the authors; licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0"><license-p>This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>A previously reported bacterial bioemulsifier, here termed microbactan, was further analyzed to characterize its lipid component, molecular weight, ionic character and toxicity, along with its bioemulsifying potential for hydrophobic substrates at a range of temperatures, salinities and pH values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyses showed that microbactan is a high molecular weight (700 kDa), non-ionic molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Gas chromatography of the lipid fraction revealed the presence of palmitic, stearic, and oleic acids; thus microbactan may be considered a glycolipoprotein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Microbactan emulsified aromatic hydrocarbons and oils to various extents; the highest emulsification index was recorded against motor oil (96%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The stability of the microbactan-motor oil emulsion model reached its highest level (94%) at 50 °C, pH 10 and 3.5% NaCl content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>It was not toxic to Artemia salina nauplii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Microbactan is, therefore, a non-toxic and non-ionic bioemulsifier of high molecular weight with affinity for a range of oily substrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Comparative phylogenetic assessment of the 16S rDNA gene of Microbacterium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>MC3B-10 with genes derived from other marine Microbacterium species suggested that this genus is well represented in coastal zones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The chemical nature and stability of the bioemulsifier suggest its potential application in bioremediation of marine environments and in cosmetics. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>bioemulsifier</kwd><kwd>emulsifying stability</kwd><kwd>non-toxic</kwd><kwd><italic>Microbacterium</italic> sp.</kwd><kwd>biotechnology</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Microorganisms produce a wide variety of high and low molecular weight biosurfactants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>These active molecules include proteins, polysaccharides, lipopeptides, glycolipids, flavolipids, phospholipids and lipopolysaccharides [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>High molecular weight biosurfactants, usually referred to as bioemulsifiers, can form and stabilize oil-in-water or water-in-oil emulsions, work at low concentrations and exhibit considerable substrate specificity [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The chemical diversity and functional properties of these compounds result in a broad spectrum of potential applications in sectors as diverse as agriculture, cosmetics, environmental, food, leather, paper, pharmaceutical and textile industries [2,3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Biologically derived surface-active molecules have advantages over their synthetic counterparts, including biodegradability, lower toxicity, novel structural chemistry and high stability at extreme temperature, salinity and pH [2,4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Some bioemulsifiers, e.g., emulsan [5], have been extensively characterized and reached commercial applications, chiefly in the bioremediation sector. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Bioprospection of various habitats, in particular marine environments [6,7], has yielded many novel biomolecules produced by microorganisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>An earlier report showed that the extracellular biopolymer produced by Microbacterium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>MC3B-10 emulsified hexane, decane and hexadecane at higher efficiencies than commercial surfactants Triton® X-100 and Tween® 80 [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>This extracellular biopolymer will be referred to as microbactan after its bacterial producer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The goal of the present study was to characterize in greater detail this extracellular biopolymer and determine the emulsifying stability as a function of key variables. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Results and Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Characterization of Microbactan </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Microbactan was produced by fermentation in shaker flasks; no attempt was made at this time to optimize its production using a bioreactor, where more strict control of variables can be achieved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The reproducibility of production conditions employed in this study was confirmed by the yield and the primary chemical profile of the biopolymer, which was comparable to the previous report [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Our previous work showed that microbactan was dominated by carbohydrates and proteins, and was preliminarily considered a glycoprotein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The present study also revealed the presence of lipids, shown by the peak at 2927 cm−1 in the FT-IR analysis, which represents the asymmetric stretch (C–H) of –CH2 groups combined with that of –CH3 groups in lipids [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Quantitative assessment by absorbance showed that the lipid signature detected by FT-IR corresponded to a lipid content of 8% ± 0.5%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The gas chromatograph analysis of the lipid fraction revealed the presence of palmitic (C-16), stearic (C-18) and oleic (C-18:1) acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Other fatty acids, found at lower levels, were myristoleic (C-14:1) and linoleic (C-18:2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The lipid content and the previously reported chemical composition of ~90% carbohydrates and proteins [8] represented almost 100% of the total mass of the microbactan on a dry weight basis, suggesting that this biopolymer is a class of glycolipoprotein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The fatty acids detected (palmitic, stearic and oleic) have been reported in bioemulsifiers produced by Yarrowia lipolytica [10] and Penicillium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>[11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>However, the presence of other substituents of extracellular biopolymers such as pyruvil, succinyl and sulfates, which often occur at minor levels [4,9], was not investigated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>High performance size exclusion chromatography showed that microbactan had a molecular weight (MW) approaching 700 kDa and a polydispersity index (Mw/number average molecular weight) of 1.3; a value close to 1 denotes a polymer with homogeneous monomer grouping. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that microbactan is a homogeneous high molecular weight glycolipoprotein, a finding that is consistent with previous reports showing that, in general, bioemulsifiers are high molecular weight polymers [1,12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The commercial bioemulsifier alasan® has a molecular weight of approximately 1000 kDa [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Most bacterial bioemulsifiers are polymers of either carbohydrates or proteins, or even glycoproteins [1,6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Thavasi and colleagues report marine-derived glycolipoprotein emulsifiers from Corynebacterium kutcheri and Bacillus megaterium [14,15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The putative glycolipoprotein nature of microbactan is, therefore, to some extent unusual among marine bioemulsifiers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Microbactan was shown by the modified double diffusion test to be a non-ionic emulsifier. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The ionic character of polymers is one of the features that contribute strongly to the functional properties of emulsifiers; this property is often reported for synthetic emulsifiers or novel emulsifying formulations used for a range of applications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Despite the importance of this feature, it is rarely reported in newly discovered bioemulsifiers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The non-ionic nature of emulsifiers greatly contributes to emulsion stability, generating a number of short-range repulsive forces, such as steric, hydration, and thermal fluctuation interactions, which prevent the droplets from getting too close together [16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Emulsifying Potential </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Tables 1 and 2 show the emulsifying activity of microbactan and control commercial emulsifiers tested against different substrates at different times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis showed significant differences between microbactan and these controls (F = 84.24; p &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Synthetic surfactants Triton® X-100 and Tween® 80 were more efficient than microbactan and the commercial biopolymers, reaching emulsification efficiencies of 100% against oils (with the exception of motor oil), irrespective of time of incubation (24 and 96 h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Microbactan showed stronger emulsifying activities than gum arabic but was comparable to the emulsifying efficiency of xanthan gum, another bacterially-produced biopolymer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The emulsifying activity of microbactan was dependent on the type of substrate (F = 16.2; p &lt; 0.05); this is consistent with other reports on substrate-specific hydrocarbon metabolism by marine bacteria [17,18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Microbactan emulsions with the tested substrates were rather stable over time (Tables 1 and 2), varying only slightly between 24 and 96 h. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>An established criterion for emulsion-stabilizing capacity is the ability of an emulsifier to maintain at least 50% of the original volume of the emulsion for 24 h [4,19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Microbactan emulsions remained stable for several months, showing no sign of droplet coalescence after standing at room temperature (28 °C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>This extended stability has previously been observed for glycoprotein bioemulsifiers produced by a marine Antarctobacter [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Emulsifying and surfactant activities are together responsible for important functional properties of bacterial exopolymers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Our analyses revealed that microbactan has emulsifying but not surfactant activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Surface-active biomolecules are classified as surfactants when they lower the interfacial or surface tension and emulsifiers when they form stable emulsions [19,21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Overall, our results indicate that microbactan is a true bioemulsifier. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Effect of Temperature, pH and NaCl on Emulsifying Activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The effect of these three key variables that influence emulsifying activity was assessed at 24, 48, 72 and 96 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>As expected, they influenced the emulsifying activity of microbactan, but their effects occurred at different levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>A time-dependent decrease of emulsifying activity was observed at 100 °C (F = 38.13; p &lt; 0.005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>This was not the case for activities at 50 °C and 5 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The highest level of activity was found at 50 °C (emulsifying activity of 95.7% ± 2.5%) irrespective of time of incubation (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The loss of emulsifying activity at 100 °C can be explained by denaturation of the protein fraction of microbactan during heating [22], as seen with other microbial biosurfactants [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the activity associated with the upper limit of the range of salinities tested (3.5%, 5%, and 10%) declined as a function of time to level off at 72 and 96 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The highest levels of activity were observed at 3.5% (Figure 2), not dissimilar to the biosurfactant produced by Aeromonas spp., which maintained emulsifying activity up to 5% NaCl [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, no significant effect on activity was observed as a function of time with the pH values tested (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>However, slightly higher levels of emulsifying activity were recorded at acid and alkaline pH values, suggesting the ionization of functional groups that resulted in the activation of less surface-active species within the bioemulsifier matrix [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>In comparison, biodispersan from Acinetobacter calcoaceticus A2 had an optimum functional pH value in the range of 9 to 12 for limestone-dispersing activity [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>It has been shown that the emulsifying activity of certain polymers is modified at different extents when temperature and pH covariate, this is probably due to the synergistic influence of these factors on surface-active proteins, whose conformation and functional groups are influenced as a function of these factors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that microbactan could find application in environmental marine processes such as enhanced oil recovery, cleaning of oil reservoirs and enhancement of biodegradation rates of spilled oils [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Bioemulsifiers have a wide diversity of composition and structure and are characterized by improved functionality and stability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Their potential applications include: the oil and petroleum industries, water and soil bioremediation, metal treatment and processing, detergents and laundry supplies, agriculture, textile manufacturing, pulp and paper processing, paints, cosmetics, pharmaceuticals, personal care products and food processing [4,6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Microbactan has higher emulsifying activity at 50 °C and 3.5% NaCl, conditions typical of intertidal environments [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>If the molecule remains stable under these conditions for long periods, it may prove specifically useful for bioremediation of polluted intertidal habitats [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The stability of the emulsions under diverse conditions, such as temperature, pressure, pH and ionic strength, makes this biopolymer a versatile emulsifier for use in many food and pharmaceutical formulations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Toxicity of Microbactan </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Based solely on the Artemia salina toxicity test, microbactan proved innocuous, as expected for a biologically derived surface-active agent; this class of compound is generally biodegradable and non-toxic [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Although synthetic surfactants exhibited the highest emulsifying activity in this study, Triton® X-100 (also a non-ionic surface-active), at least, proved to be toxic in our Artemia bioassay (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Polyoxyethylene octyl phenols (the Triton X series) are known to be highly cytotoxic, solubilizing the membrane lipid bilayer [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>In fact, these synthetic surfactants can actually inhibit aromatic hydrocarbon biodegradation via toxic interactions, making them less suitable for bioremediation purposes [27,29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The Artemia salina toxicity bioassay is a reliable primary screen, given the sensitivity of this crustacean to a wide range of biologically active compounds of diverse chemistries, including pesticide residues, mycotoxins, stream pollutants, anaesthetics, dinoflagellate toxins, morphine-like compounds and oil dispersants [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>In addition, this bioassay has demonstrated good correlation with other cell-based tests such as tumor cell lines (e.g., KB, P-388, 388, L5178Y and L1210) and mammalian systems [31,32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Reinforcing this finding, an experimental study on marine biofilm colonization on surfaces coated with microbactan showed that this biopolymer did not affect biofilm formation (unpublished results). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>2.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic Reassessment of Microbacterium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>MC3B-10 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The reassessment of the phylogenetic position of Microbacterium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>MC3B-10 based on its 16S rDNA gene, using a more robust bioinformatics approach, confirmed that its closest relative was Microbacterium trichothecenolyticum, with a similarity of 99.2% (underline, Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Stackebrandt and Ebers [33] established that a cutoff of 98.7% 16S rDNA gene homology is appropriate for species differentiation within a genus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Following this criterion and given the fact that Microbacterium is a very tight genus with respect to 16S rDNA gene homology between valid species [34], Microbacterium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>MC3B-10 could be classified as M. trichothecenolyticum. However, definitive identification of this bacterial isolate requires a polyphasic approach including biochemical, physiological, chemotaxonomic, and nucleic acid-based methods, along with a range of microscopies, as previously shown for newly described Microbacterium species [35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The in-silica analysis revealed novel strains of the genus Microbacterium (MC24 and MC60) that had been isolated from an intertidal environment in Brazil and were capable of synthesizing bioemulsifiers [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>These isolates were also related to Microbacterium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>MC3B-10, but at lower similarity levels (97%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>It should be noted that, except for M. resistens, M. hominis, and M. paraoxydans, all microbacteria are considered environmental bacteria [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Certain Microbacterium species, such as M. thalassium, M. halophilum, and M. phyllosphaerae, occur in coastal habitats [35,37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>However, the biotechnological potential of this genus as a marine bioemulsifier producer has only been reported recently [8,36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The occurrence of bioemulsifier-producing Microbacterium species in intertidal environments is not surprising, given the metabolic versatility exhibited by this genus; some of them can metabolize hydrocarbons, presumably through bioemulsifier synthesis [38,39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>In addition, the availability of hydrophobic substrates in coastal marine environments may select for bacteria capable of synthesizing surface-active molecules to enhance nutrient uptake [1]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Experimental Section </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Production of Microbactan </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Microbacterium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>MC3B-10 was originally isolated from pristine rocky intertidal shores in the state of Campeche, southern Gulf of Mexico, Mexico. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Microbactan was produced following a batch shake flask fermentation of an overnight culture (50 mL) of Microbacterium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>MC3B-10 as previously reported [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The exopolymeric material was extracted from the fermented broth, redissolved in a small volume of distilled water and then dialyzed (molecular weight cutoff 12,000–14,000 Da, Spectrum®, CA, USA) for 72 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The resulting material was lyophilized and kept in the dark before analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Lipid Analysis and Fatty Acid Composition </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Lipids were determined using Fourier-transform infrared spectroscopy (FT-IR) [8] and spectrophotometry, using triolein as standard lipid [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Fatty acid composition was investigated as follows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>After mild acid hydrolysis of the exopolymer (0.7064 g) at 80 °C for 30 min, the hydrolysate was extracted with CHCl3:CH3OH:H2O (3:2:1) and the aqueous phase extracted two more times with CHCl3 (1:1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The CHCl3 fractions were combined and evaporated under reduced pressure [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Before GC-MS analysis, the sample was pre-treated as described previously [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The methylation of fatty acids was carried out with 5 mL of HCl-methanol at 80 °C for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The fatty acid methyl ethers were extracted with hexane and subjected to analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>GC-MS was performed using helium as carrier gas on a Perkin Elmer Clarus 580 GC equipped with a Clarus SQ 8S mass spectrometer, equipped with an Elite-5 capillary column (30 m × 0.32 mm i.d., 0.25 μm film thickness). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>High Performance Size Exclusion Chromatography </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The molecular weight of microbactan was determined using an HPLC system Prominence Shimadzu™, a PL aquagel-OH mixed, 8 μm (Varian) guard column (U 7.5 mm × L50 mm), and a PL aquagel-OH mixed (Varian, Palo Alto, CA, USA) separation column (U 7.5 × 300 mm, operating range 102–107 g/mol). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Elution was performed at 1 mL/min with 0.1 M ammonium acetate containing 0.03% NaN3, and the eluate filtered through a 0.1 μm membrane (Durapore Membrane, PVDF, Hydrophilic type VVLP, Millipore®, Saint Quentin en Yvelines, France). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>A differential refractive index (RI) detector (L2490, VWR Hitachi, Fontenay sous bois, France) and a multi-angle light scattering detector (Dawn Heleos™, Wyatt, Toulouse, France) were coupled on-line and data computed with Astra software for absolute molar mass determination. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>3.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Ionic Charge </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The ionic charge of microbactan was assessed using a modified double diffusion technique [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Briefly, two 12 mm-diameter plugs were taken from Petri dishes containing 1% agar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>One of the resulting wells was filled with 200 μL of microbactan solution at 1 mg/mL and the other with commercial anionic (sodium dodecyl sulphate SDS and Teepol® 610S Sigma-Aldrich Química, S. de R.L. de C.V., Toluca, Mexico State, Mexico) or cationic (barium chloride and cetyltrimethylammonium bromide) surfactants supplied by Sigma-Aldrich. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>These surfactants were used at 20 mmol, except for barium chloride (50 mmol). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The appearance of precipitation lines between the wells was indicative of the ionic character of microbactan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Plates were incubated at 28 °C and monitored daily. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>3.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Emulsifying Activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The emulsifying activity of microbactan was assessed against aromatic hydrocarbons (benzene and xylene), vegetable oils (corn, olive and sunflower) and mineral, motor and crude oils, all at 1%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Oils were acquired from local commercial suppliers and the hydrocarbons were of analytical grade (J.T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Baker, Center Valley, PA, USA; E.M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Sciences, Hatfield, PA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The emulsifying activity was measured by combining equal volumes of microbactan solution (1% w/v) and the target hydrophobic substrates in 12-mm-diameter glass tubes, as previously described [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Controls included Triton® X-100 and Tween® 80 (Research Organics, Cleveland, OH, USA), a plant-derived polysaccharide (gum arabic from Spectrum®) and xanthan gum, a bacterial polysaccharide (ICN Biomedicals, Inc, Irvine, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>All evaluations were performed in triplicate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>3.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Effects of Temperature, Salinity and pH on Emulsifying Activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The effect of temperature, NaCl content and pH on emulsifying activity of microbactan was tested using motor oil because this substrate yielded the highest levels of emulsification (~96%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The influence of temperature was determined by pretreating at desired temperatures (5, 50 and 100 °C) microbactan solutions that were either heated for 15 min in a water bath or cooled for 10 min in a freezer, before being assayed [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The effect of NaCl was investigated at three concentrations (3.5, 5 and 10% w/v) and pH values of 4, 7 and 10 were studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Emulsification with motor oil was carried out at room temperature as in Item 3.5 [22,24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>3.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Toxicity Test </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Brine shrimp eggs (Salt Creek™, Salt Lake City, UT, USA) were hatched at 27 °C under continuous aeration and illumination in seawater prepared with sea salts (Coralife®, Rhinelander, WI, USA) at 38 g/L and supplemented with 6 mg/L of dried yeast [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Solutions of Triton® X-100 and Tween® 80 (Research Organics, Cleveland, OH, USA) and microbactan were dissolved in seawater at concentrations of 1000, 500, 100, 50 and 10 μg/mL [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The 50% Lethal Concentration (LC50) was determined by counting the dead nauplii after an incubation period of 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Data were analyzed with the Finney computer program as described previously [27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>3.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>All the experiments were run in triplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>For the emulsification assays, a two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to assess the effect of biopolymer and controls on the hydrophobic substrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>When there was a significant difference (p ≤ 0.05) between microemulsion and controls, we applied the Tukey test aposteriori. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>These tests were performed with Sigma Stat software version 2.0 (1997). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>3.9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic Reassessment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The purpose of this analysis was twofold: first, to corroborate the identification of the species of Microbacterium MC3B-10 based on its 16S rDNA gene (AY833570) using a more robust bioinformatics approach (see details below) with the sequences reported in [8], and second to prove if recently reported species of Microbacterium displaying bioemulsifying activity or originally isolated from polluted environments were phylogenetically close to Microbacterium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>MC3B-10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The following additional sequences were obtained from the GenBank database, Microbacterium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Mc1 DQ512483, Mc24 DQ512484, Mc60 DQ512485, M. aquimaris JS54-2 AM778449, M. aquimaris JS63-1 AM778450, Microbacterium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>F10a EU196564, M. oleivorans DSM 16091 AJ698726 and M. sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>ZD-M2 DQ417926. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>In total, 41 sequences (1418 bp) were aligned using the CLUSTALW algorithm implemented in MEGA 4.3 software [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analyses were performed using the Neighbor Joining (NJ) algorithm: phylogenetic analysis using parsimony V4.0 beta 10, 2002. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>For NJ analyses, the evolutionary model selected was the GTR + I + G (General Time Reversible Model + Invariable sites + Gamma distribution) inferred from the program Modeltest V.3.06 [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Support for nodes of the NJ tree was determined by calculating bootstrap proportion values [48] based on 1000 resamplings of neighbor-joining searches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The 16S rDNA sequences of Curtobacterium luteum and C. michiganense were used as outgroup. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>This study demonstrated that the novel Microbacterium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>MC3B-10, probably indigenous to the marine intertidal zone, synthesizes an environmentally-friendly exopolymeric non-ionic glycolipoprotein capable of emulsifying aromatic hydrocarbons and oils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The functional stability of this bioemulsifier was retained for long periods of time and at a range of temperature, NaCl concentration and pH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The chemistry, activity and stability of microbactan make it useful for environmental and personal care applications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Overall, our results suggest that bioemulsifier-producing bacteria warrant intensified bioprospection in the intertidal zones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Additionally, this study corroborates the still untapped resource represented by marine microorganisms for new biosurfactants, bioemulsifiers and biopolymers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>This work thus strengthens the notion that marine microbial diversity is a non-exhausted source of novel biomolecules and particularly emphasizes the biotechnological significance of Microbacterium species derived from the intertidal environment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>This research was supported by a grant Marine biofilm inhibition by bacterial exopolymeric substance-based coatings and characterization of producing isolates (F/3617-2F) 2008-2011, from the International Foundation for Science (IFS) F/3617-1, Stockholm, Sweden; Organization for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons, The Hague, The Netherlands. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><notes><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>1RonE.RosenbergE.Natural roles of biosurfactantsEnviron. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Microbiol2001322923611359508 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>2BanatI.M.FranzettiA.GandolfiI.BestettiG.MartinottiM.FracchiaL.SmythT.MarchantR.Microbial biosurfactants, production, applications and future potentialAppl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol20108742744420424836 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>3FreitasF.AlvesV.ReisM.Advances in bacterial exopolysaccharides: From production to biotechnological applicationsTrends Biotechnol20112938839821561675 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>4FreitasF.AlvesV.CarvalheiraM.CostaN.OliveiraR.ReisM.Emulsifying behaviour and rheological properties of the extracellular polysaccharide produced by Pseudomonas oleovorans grown on glycerol byproductCarbohyd. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Polym200978549556 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>5SatputeS.BanatI.DhakephalkarP.BanpurkarA.ChopadeB.Biosurfactants, bioemulsifiers and exopolysaccharides from marine microorganismsBiotechnol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Adv20102843645020172021 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>6GutiérrezT.LeoV.WalkerG.GreenD.Emulsifying properties of a glycoprotein extract produced by a marine Flexibacter species strain TG382Enzyme Microb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Technol2009455357 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>7Ortega-MoralesB.O.Chan-BacabM.J.de la Rosa-GarcíaS.C.Camacho-ChabJ.C.Valuable processes and products from marine intertidal microbial communitiesCurr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Opin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol20102134635220202811 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>8Ortega-MoralesB.O.SantiagoJ.Chan-BacabM.J.MirandaE.FardeauM.CarreroJ.BartoloP.ValadézA.GuezennecJ.Characterization of extracellular polymers synthesized by tropical intertidal biofilm bacteriaJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Microbiol200710225426417184342 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>9BeechI.HanjagsitL.KalajiM.NealA.L.ZinkevichV.Chemical and structural characterization of exopolymers produced by Pseudomonas sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>NCIMB 2021 in continuous cultureMicrobiology19991451491149710411276 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>10AmaralP.SilvaJ.LehockyM.Barros-TimmonsA.CoelhoM.MarruchoI.CoutinhoJ.A.P.Production and characterization of a bioemulsiftier from Yarrowia lipolyticaProcess Biochem20064118941898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>11Luna-VelascoM.A.Esparza-GarcíaF.Cansares-VillanuevaR.O.Rodríguez-VázquezR.Production and properties of a bioemulsifier synthesized by phenanthrene-degrading Penicillum spProcess Biochem200742310314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>12MaierR.M.Biosurfactants: Evolution and diversity in bacteriaAdv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Microbiol20035210112112964241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>13Navon-VeneziaS.ZosimZ.GottliebA.LegmannR.CarmeliS.RonE.Z.RosenbergE.Alasan, a new bioemulsifier from Acinetobacter radioresistensAppl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Microb19956132403244 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>14ThavasiR.JayalakshmiS.BalasubramanianT.BanatI.Biosurfactant production by Corynebacterium kutscheri from waste motor lubricant oil and peanut oil cakeLett. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Microbiol20074568669117944837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>15ThavasiR.JayalakshmiS.BalasubramanianT.BanatI.Production and characterization of a glycolipid biosurfactant from Bacillus megaterium using economically cheaper sourcesWorld J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol200724917925 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>16WhitmanW.Food Emulsifiers: Chemistry, Technology, Functional Properties and ApplicationsTen Alps PublishingLondon, UK1990 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>17KimS.RavichandranD.KhanS.KimY.Prospective of the cosmeceuticals derived from marine organismsBiotechnol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Bioprocess Eng200813511523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>18KumarA.ModyK.JhaB.Evaluation of biosurfactant/bioemulsifier production by a marine bacteriumBull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Contam. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Toxicol20077961762117924042 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>19WillumsenP.A.KarlsonU.Screening of bacteria, isolated from PAH-contaminated soils, for production of biosurfactants and bioemulsifiersBiodegradation19977415423 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>20GutiérrezT.MulloyB.BavingtonC.BlackK.GreenD.Partial purification and chemical characterization of a glycoprotein (putative hydrocolloid) emulsifier produced by a marine bacterium AntarctobacterAppl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol.2007761017102617641887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>21PerfumoA.SmythT.J.MarchantR.BanatI.M.Production and Roles of Biosurfactants and Bioemulsifiers in Accessing Hydrophobic SubstratesHandbook of Hydrocarbon and Lipid MicrobiologyTimmisK.N.Springer-VerlagBerlin, Germany201015021510 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>22SarubboL.MouraJ.Campos-TakakiG.Production and stability studies of the bioemulsifier obtained from a new strain of Candida glabrata UCP 1002Electron. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol20069400406 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>23RufinoR.SarubboA.CamposG.Enhancement of stability of biosurfactant produced by Candida lipolytica using industrial residue as substrateWorld J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Microb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol200723729734 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>24IloriM.O.AmobiC.OdochaA.Factors affecting biosurfactant production by oil degrading Aeromonas spp. isolated from a tropical environmentChemosphere20056198599215878609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>25SarubboL.FariasC.Campos-TakakiG.Co-utilization of canola oil and glucose on the production of a surfactant by Candida lipolyticaCurr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Microbiol200754687317171462 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>26RosenbergE.RubinovitzC.GottliebA.RosenhakS.RonE.Z.Production of biodispersan by Acinetobacter calcoaceticus A2Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Microb198854317322 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>27PelletierE.DelilleD.DelilleB.Crude oil bioremediation in sub-Antarctic intertidal sediments: Chemistry and toxicity of oiled residuesMar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Res20045731132714749062 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>28WeyermannJ.LochmannD.ZimmerA.A practical note on the use of cytotoxicity assaysInt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Pharm200528836937615620877 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>29MeyerB.N.FerrigniN.R.PutnamJ.E.JacobsenL.B.NicholsD.E.McLauglinJ.L.Brine shrimp: A convenient general bioassay for active plant constituentsPlanta. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Med1982453134 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>30McLaughlinJ.L.Crown-gall Tumors in Potato Discs and Brine Shrimp Lethality: Two Simple Bioassays for Higher Plant Screening and FractionationMethods in Plant BiochemistryHostettmannK.Academic PressLondon, UK19916132 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>31BirndorfH.C.D’AlossioJ.BagshawJ.C.DNA-dependant RNA-polymerases from Artemia, embryos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Characterization of polymerases I and II from nauplius larvaeDev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Biol19754534431181219 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>32PerfeitoJ.P.SantosM.L.LópezK.S.PaulaJ.E.SilveiraD.Characterization and biological properties of Pouteria torta extractsRev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Bras. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Farmacogn200515183186 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>33StackebrandtE.EbersJ.Taxonomic parameters revisited: Tarnished gold standardsMicrobiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Today200633152155 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>34GneidingK.FrodlR.FunkeG.Identities of Microbacterium spp. encountered in human clinical specimensJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Microbiol2008463646365218799696 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>35TakeuchiM.HatanoK.Proposal of six new species in the genus Microbacterium and transfer of Flavobacterium marinotypicum ZoBell and Upham to the genus Microbacterium as Microbacterium maritypicum comb. novInt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Bacteriol1998489739829734054 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>36AniszewskiE.SilvaR.FariaF.GomesS.SoaresA.Bioemulsifier production by Microbacterium sp. strains isolated from mangrove and their application to remove cadmiun and zinc from hazardous industrial residueBraz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Microbiol20104123524524031486 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>37BurmølleM.WebbJ.RaoD.HansenL.SørensenS.KjellebergS.Enhanced biofilm formation and increased resistance to antimicrobial agents and bacterial invasion are caused by synergistic interactions in multispecies biofilmsAppl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Microb20067239163925 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>38SchippersA.BoseckerK.SproerC.SchumannP.Microbacterium oleivorans sp. nov. and Microbacterium hydrocarbonoxydans sp. nov., novel crude-oil-degrading Gram-positive bacteriaInt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Microbiol20055565566015774639 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>39FranzettiA.GandolfiI.BertoliniV.RaimondiC.PiscitelloM.PapacchiniM.BestettiG.Phylogenetic characterization of bioemulsifier-producing bacteriaInt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Biodeterior. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Biodegrad20116510951099 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>40IzardJ.LimbergerR.Rapid screening method for quantification of bacterial cell lipids from whole cellsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Meth200355411418 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b41-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>41GanfieldM.C.PieringerR.A.Phosphatidylkojibiosyl diglyceride. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>The covalently linked lipid constituent of the membrane lipoteichoic acid from Streptococcus faecalis (faecium) ATCC 9790J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Chem1975250702709803497 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b42-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>42RezankaT.VokounJ.SlavicekJ.PodojilM.Determination of fatty acids in algae by capillary gas chromatography-mass spectrometryJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Chromatogr.19832687178 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b43-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>43Van OssC.J.Specifically impermeable precipitate membranes formed through double diffusion in gels: Behavior with complex forming and with simple systemsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Colloid Interf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Sci196827684690 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b44-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>44Ortega-MoralesB.O.Chan-BacabM.J.Miranda-TelloE.FardeauM.L.CarreroJ.C.SteinT.Antifouling activity of sessile bacilli derived from marine surfaceJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Ind. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol.20083591517909869 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b45-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>45SolísP.WrightC.AndersonM.GuptaM.PhillipsonD.A.A Microwell cytotoxic using Artemia salina (brine shrimp)Planta Med1993592502528316592 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b46-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>46TamuraK.DudleyJ.NeiM.KumarS.MEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Evol2007241596159917488738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b47-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>47PosadaD.CrandallK.A.Modeltest: Testing the model of DNA substitutionBioinformatics1998148178189918953 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b48-ijms-14-18959"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>48FelsensteinJ.Confidence limits on phylogenies: An approach using the bootstrapEvolution198539783791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f1-ijms-14-18959" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Emulsifying activity of microbactan on motor oil at different temperatures up to 96 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>5 °C (●), 50 °C (■) and 100 °C (▲). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Values represent means ± SD (n = 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-14-18959f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f2-ijms-14-18959" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Emulsifying activity of microemulsan on motor oil at various salinities up to 96 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>3.5% (●), 5% (■) and 10% (▲) NaCl concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Values represent means ± SD (n = 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-14-18959f2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f3-ijms-14-18959" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Emulsifying activity of microbactan on motor oil at different pH values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>pH 4 (●), pH 7 (■) and pH 10 (▲).Values represent means ± SD (n = 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-14-18959f3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f4-ijms-14-18959" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Neighbor-joining phylogenetic tree, based on 16S rDNA gene sequences, showing the positions of strain MC3B-10 (AY833570) relative to all known Microbacterium species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Accession numbers of 16S rDNA gene sequences of reference organisms are shown in parentheses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Bootstrap values (1000 replicates, &gt;50%) are shown above the nodes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>The bar indicates the relative sequence divergence (0.01 nucleotide substitutions per site). Curtobacterium luteum and C. michiganense were used as outgroups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-14-18959f4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="t1-ijms-14-18959" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Emulsifying activity of microbactan, commercial synthetic surfactants and natural biopolymer emulsifiers on various hydrophobic substrates after 24 h of evaluation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1-ijms-14-18959"><label>a</label><p>Results are expressed as percentages of the total height occupied by the emulsion; values are means of at least three determinations.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="t2-ijms-14-18959" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Emulsifying activity of microbactan, commercial synthetic surfactants and natural biopolymer emulsifiers on various hydrophobic substrates after 96 h of evaluation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn2-ijms-14-18959"><label>a</label><p>Results are expressed as percentages of the total height occupied by the emulsion; values are means of at least three determinations.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="t3-ijms-14-18959" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Anti-crustacean activity of surfactants against Artemia salina nauplii. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
