
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3541388</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23326361</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-27060</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052822</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Ecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biogeography</subject><subject>Evolutionary Ecology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary Processes</subject><subj-group><subject>Speciation</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Organismal Evolution</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Evolution</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary Ecology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Paleontology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biogeography</subject><subject>Invertebrate Paleontology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Zoology</subject><subj-group><subject>Entomology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>As Old as the Hills: Montane Scorpions in Southwestern North America Reveal Ancient Associations between Biotic Diversification and Landscape History </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Historical Diversification of Montane Scorpions</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bryson</surname><given-names>Robert W.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Riddle</surname><given-names>Brett R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>Matthew R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Brian Tilston</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prendini</surname><given-names>Lorenzo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>School of Life Sciences, University of Nevada, Las Vegas, Las Vegas, Nevada, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biology and Burke Museum of Natural History and Culture, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Museum of Natural Science, Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, Louisiana, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Division of Invertebrate Zoology, American Museum of Natural History, New York, New York, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Mans</surname><given-names>Ben J.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Onderstepoort Veterinary Institute, South Africa</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>brysonjr@uw.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: RWB BRR MRG BTS LP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: RWB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: RWB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: RWB BRR MRG BTS LP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: RWB BRR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Revised the manuscript: MRG BTS LP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e52822</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>9</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 Bryson et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bryson et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The age of lineages has become a fundamental datum in studies exploring the interaction between geological transformation and biotic diversification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>However, phylogeographical studies are often biased towards lineages that are younger than the geological features of the landscapes they inhabit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>A temporally deeper historical biogeography framework may be required to address episodes of biotic diversification associated with geologically older landscape changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Signatures of such associations may be retained in the genomes of ecologically specialized (stenotopic) taxa with limited vagility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>In the study presented here, genetic data from montane scorpions in the Vaejovis vorhiesi group, restricted to humid rocky habitats in mountains across southwestern North America, were used to explore the relationship between scorpion diversification and regional geological history. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Strong phylogeographical signal was evident within the vorhiesi group, with 27 geographically cohesive lineages inferred from a mitochondrial phylogeny. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>A time-calibrated multilocus species tree revealed a pattern of Miocene and Pliocene (the Neogene period) lineage diversification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>An estimated 21 out of 26 cladogenetic events probably occurred prior to the onset of the Pleistocene, 2.6 million years ago. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The best-fit density-dependent model suggested diversification rate in the vorhiesi group gradually decreased through time. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Scorpions of the vorhiesi group have had a long history in the highlands of southwestern North America. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Diversification among these stenotopic scorpions appears to have occurred almost entirely within the Neogene period, and is temporally consistent with the dynamic geological history of the Basin and Range, and Colorado Plateau physiographical provinces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The persistence of separate lineages at small spatial scales suggests that a combination of ecological stenotopy and limited vagility may make these scorpions particularly valuable indicators of geomorphological evolution. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>Funding for the first author was provided in part by the University of Nevada, Las Vegas Graduate and Professional Student Association. Aspects of the work conducted at the AMNH were funded by National Science Foundation grant DEB 0413453, and by a grant from the Richard Lounsbery Foundation to the last author. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The strength of the interplay between geological transformation and biotic diversification—geobiotic history [1]—is an old and contentious issue in biology [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>With the advent of molecular-based estimates of lineage relationships and ages, traditional dichotomies between views that posit either strong adherence to ‘Earth and life evolving together’ or ‘life diversifying largely without dependence on Earth history events’ have been tempered by studies showing that species assemblages often exhibit a temporally wide range of idiosyncratic responses to Earth history events [3], [4], [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Although the age of lineages has become a fundamental datum for investigating relationships between Earth and biotic history, studies of diversification within the popular phylogeographical [6] paradigm have been biased towards relatively young lineages [7], [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Expansion of the temporal context of a study beyond the relatively recent timeframes encompassing phylogeography could capture a record of biotic diversification associated with geologically older landscape changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Such changes may be retained in the genomes of ecologically specialized (stenotopic) taxa with limited vagility. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Owing to their antiquity, morphological, and ecological conservatism, scorpions are excellent candidates for investigating such deep geobiotic histories [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Derived from amphibious ancestors that lived more than 425 million years ago (Ma), scorpions represent an ancient radiation of terrestrial arthropods, earning the title ‘living fossils’ [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Their conserved morphology implies relative stasis in ecological requirements over time [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Many scorpions demonstrate limited vagility and a high degree of stenotopy such that the distributions of phylogenetically related taxa are often predictably restricted to a narrow range of stable habitats that may have persisted over millions of years [9], [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>As evidence, several evolutionary studies on scorpions have revealed patterns of deep species-level divergence and diversification during the Miocene and Pliocene [12], [13], [14], [15], [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The diversity and ecological specialization of North American scorpions [17], [18] makes them appropriate for exploring biogeographical patterns on the continent. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In the present study, the historical diversification of montane scorpions in the Vaejovis vorhiesi group (Vaejovidae) was examined as part of a comparative approach aimed at reconstructing the paleohistory of highlands in southwestern North America [19], [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The vorhiesi group, comprising 12 described and several undescribed species, appears to be restricted to humid, rocky habitats in mixed pine-oak-juniper woodlands [21], [22] across their known distribution from central Utah southwards through Arizona and New Mexico to Sonora in northern Mexico (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Diversification in these scorpions appears to be constrained by habitat specialization, and divergence may have been promoted by allopatric speciation in isolated rocky highland habitats, as proposed for scorpion taxa in other parts of the world [9], [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>If ephemeral woodland corridors that developed during Pleistocene glacial periods and connected highland biota [20], [23] lacked suitable humid, rocky habitats, dispersal between adjacent mountain ranges inhabited by stenotopic scorpions in the vorhiesi group, would be limited. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0052822-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052822.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Collection localities for genetic samples of scorpions in the Vaejovis vorhiesi group included in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>White squares indicate type localities of described species (see Table 1), and grey line indicates approximate known distribution of the group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0052822.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Based on their relatively specialized ecological requirements for humid, rocky habitats and therefore close association with geological features, montane scorpions of the vorhiesi group may show signatures of pre-Pleistocene divergence, contrary to the phylogeographical patterns observed in many co-distributed taxa [23], [24], [25], [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>These scorpions may thus offer novel insights into the deeper geobiotic history of the highland landscapes of southwestern North America. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>A mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) dataset was generated from 63 samples of vorhiesi group scorpions and their relatives to explore phylogeographical structure, and a species tree reconstructed using multilocus data (mtDNA and two nuclear genes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Divergence times were estimated across the mtDNA dataset and the multilocus species tree, and the temporal distribution of divergence events was modeled across southwestern North America. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>These reconstructions and models were used to explore the relationship between diversification and regional geological history. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Diversification within the vorhiesi group appears to have occurred almost entirely within the Neogene period, and may be related to the dynamic geological history of southwestern North America. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Ethics statements </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Fieldwork in Mexico was conducted under permits granted by the Secretaría de Medio Ambiente y Recursos Naturales (SEMARNAT) to O.F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Francke, the late F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Mendoza-Quijano, and C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Solis-Rojas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The Navajo Nation and National Parks Service granted permits for collection in northern Arizona and New Mexico. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Genetic data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>DNA sequence data were generated from 63 samples of vorhiesi group scorpions collected from throughout the known range (Fig. 1, Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>All described species in the group (V. bandido, V. cashi, V. crumpi, V. deboerae, V. electrum, V. feti, V. halli, V. jonesi, V. lapidicola, V. paysonensis, V. vorhiesi) were represented with the exception of V. bigelowi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The sister taxon to the group is uncertain, so additional samples from 10 other geographically proximate montane Vaejovis were included. Paruroctonus boreus was used as the outgroup [27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0052822-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052822.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Collection data for genetic samples of scorpions in the Vaejovis vorhiesi group. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0052822-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0052822.t001"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>All samples are deposited in the Ambrose Monell Cryocollection (AMCC) at the American Museum of Natural History, New York. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Asterisks denote samples collected in the vicinity of the type localities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Samples in bold were used in multilocus phylogenetic estimates (letter abbreviations indicate samples with missing data: CO, COI; IT, ITS2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Sequences were deposited in GenBank (accession numbers JX909361–JX909616). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Fragments of mitochondrial DNA were sequenced from a protein-coding gene (cytochrome c oxidase I, COI; 854 base pairs, or bp) and a ribosomal gene (16S rDNA, 16S; 404 bp). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Two nuclear genes were also sequenced for a subset of samples (n = 39) representing geographically cohesive lineages within the vorhiesi group: 526 bp of 28S rDNA (28S) and 319 bp of the internal transcribed spacer region (ITS2) between the 5.8S rDNA and 28S rDNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Taxon-specific mtDNA primers (Table S1) were used to avoid co-amplification of nuclear mitochondrial pseudogenes (numts) [28], and chromatograms examined for the presence of double peaks [29], indels, frameshifts, and premature stop codons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Primer sequences for nuclear genes were taken from Tully et al. [30] for 28S and Ji et al. [31] for ITS2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA was extracted from leg muscle tissue, and lab protocols provided in Bryson et al. [19] and Prendini et al. [32], [33] were followed to generate sequence data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Complete genetic data could not be obtained for several samples (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Sequence alignments for individual gene regions were performed with MAFFT v6 [34], [35] using default settings, the ‘1PAM/k = 2’ scoring matrix for nucleotide sequences, and the Q-INS-i algorithm for 16S and 28S data and the E-INS-i algorithm for ITS2 data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Heterozygous sites in nuclear segments were identified when two different nucleotides were present at the same position in electropherograms of both strands, with the weaker peak reaching at least 50% of the stronger signal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The gametic phases of the variants were computationally determined using PHASE v2.1.1 [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Five separate runs of 400 iterations were conducted for each nuclear dataset, and results with a probability threshold of 0.7 or higher accepted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>All polymorphic sites with a probability less than 0.7 in both alleles were coded with the appropriate IUPAC ambiguity code. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>A partitioned homogeneity test with 1000 heuristic replicates was performed in PAUP* v4.0b10 [37] to test for conflicting phylogenetic signals between the mitochondrial and nuclear genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Phylogeographical estimation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The mtDNA dataset was analyzed to examine geographical structure and delineate geographically cohesive lineages within the vorhiesi group using Bayesian inference in MrBayes v3.1 [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Lineages were defined as genetically distinct geographical clusters with strong support values (≥0.95 Bayesian posterior probability), consistent with definitions of the term “phylogroup” [39], [40], [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Separate models were implemented for 16S and for each gene codon position of COI, the best partitioning scheme chosen based on Bayes Factors [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>MrModeltest v2.1 [43] was used to select a best-fit model of nucleotide evolution, based on Akaike information criteria (AIC), for each partition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Bayesian settings included random starting trees, a variable rate prior, and heating temperature of 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Analyses were run for 4 million generations, sampling every 100 generations, and output parameters visualized using the program TRACER v1.4 [44] to ascertain stationarity and whether the duplicated runs had converged on the same mean likelihood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>All samples obtained during the first one million (25%) generations were discarded as burn-in, and a 50% majority-rule consensus phylogram with nodal posterior probability support estimated from the combination of the four runs post-burn-in. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Species tree and divergence date estimation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>A species tree was reconstructed and divergence times within the vorhiesi group estimated from the multilocus dataset using *BEAST [45], a part of the BEAST v1.6.2 package. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>One to five exemplar samples were used from each geographical mtDNA lineage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Best-fit models of evolution were selected using MrModeltest, a Yule process speciation prior applied, and relaxed uncorrelated lognormal clocks specified for each gene tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Trees were linked in analyses of the COI and 16S mtDNA data, which represent a single locus, and substitution and clock models were unlinked. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The separation of the Cape region of Baja California from mainland Mexico between 7.5–14 Ma ([46], [47]; reviewed in [48]) was inferred as the causal mechanism for divergence between V. pattersoni and V. nayarit, putative sister species of montane Vaejovis isolated on opposite sides of the Sea of Cortez (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>This split was used to calibrate the molecular clock. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The xml file produced by BEAUTi was manually edited to set the divergence between V. pattersoni and V. nayarit to a normal distribution with a mean age of 10.75 Ma and standard deviation of 2, producing soft upper and lower bounds set to the maximum (14 Ma) and minimum (7.5 Ma) ages for the separation of the Cape from mainland Mexico. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The ulcd.mean parameter for the four gene partitions was given wide uniform distributions (0.02 upper bound and 0.002 lower bound for the two mtDNA genes; 0.01 and 0.0001 for the two nuclear genes) to allow rates across the species tree to be estimated by constraints placed by the Baja calibration and not by rates placed on individual genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Analyses were run for 200 million generations, with samples retained every 1000 generations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Results were displayed in TRACER to confirm acceptable mixing and likelihood stationarity, appropriate burn-in, and adequate effective sample sizes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The first 10% of generations were discarded as burn-in, and parameter estimates summarized on the maximum clade credibility tree using TreeAnnotator v1.6.2 [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>This burn-in and visualization procedure was repeated for each of the three gene trees co-estimated by *BEAST. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0052822-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052822.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial phylogeny of scorpions in the Vaejovis vorhiesi group. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Phylogeny inferred from Bayesian analyses of 1258 bp of concatenated COI and 16S mitochondrial sequence data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Posterior probability support values for nodes are indicated by coded dots explained in the figure legend. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Inferred lineages are indicated by black bars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Samples used in species tree reconstruction are indicated in bold font. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Localities of haplotypes are listed in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Inset depicts the geographical localities of putative sister species of montane Vaejovis isolated on opposite sides of the Sea of Cortez. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The divergence of these two species caused by the split of the Cape region of Baja California from mainland Mexico was used to calibrate the molecular clock. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0052822.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>A relaxed Bayesian molecular clock framework implemented in BEAST was used in addition to estimate divergences from the complete mtDNA dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>As with the mtDNA tree, the molecular clock was calibrated based on the split of the Cape region of Baja California from mainland Mexico. Vaejovis pattersoni and V. nayarit were grouped together as monophyletic, and the node representing the split of these two taxa was given a normal distribution with a mean age of 10.75 Ma and standard deviation of 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Analyses were conducted for 40 million generations, with samples retained every 1000 generations, using a Yule tree prior. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>TRACER was used to confirm acceptable mixing and stationarity, appropriate burn-in, and adequate effective sample sizes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>After discarding the first 4 million generations (10%) as burn-in, the parameter values of the samples from the posterior distribution were summarized on the maximum clade credibility tree using TreeAnnotator. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Diversification rate analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Temporal shifts in diversification rates were analyzed using Maximum Likelihood-based diversification-rate analysis [50], using divergence dates estimated from the multilocus dataset with *BEAST and from the mtDNA dataset with BEAST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The fit of different birth–death models implementing two constant rates (pure-birth and birth–death) and three variable rates (exponential and logistic density-dependent, and two-rate pure-birth) was computed with LASER v2.3 [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Model fit was measured using AIC scores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The significance of the change in AIC scores (ΔAICrc) between the best rate-constant and best rate-variable model was determined by creating a null distribution for ΔAICrc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>This was accomplished by simulating 1000 trees using yuleSim in LASER with the same number of nodes and same speciation rate estimated under the pure-birth model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Log likelihood and AIC values were calculated for three models (SPVAR, EXVAR, and BOTHVAR; described in [52]) that permit differential extinction and speciation rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>In addition, lineage-through-time plots were generated to visualize the pattern of accumulation of log-lineages over time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Another set of analyses were performed on the mtDNA-only divergence date estimates from BEAST to assess the influence of additional genetic structure present within lineages that may have been excluded from the diversification rate analyses above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Eight additional divergences that occurred within six of the inferred geographical lineages (see Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>S1) were included for this dataset. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Genetic Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Sequences were deposited in GenBank (JX909361–JX909616). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The mtDNA genes contained 418 parsimony-informative sites (283/854 bp, COI; 135/404 bp, 16S) in the full dataset and 413 sites in the reduced species tree dataset (279, COI; 134, 16S). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The nuclear genes contained fewer parsimony-informative sites (30/526 bp, 28S; 128/319, ITS2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>No significant conflict was found between the mitochondrial and nuclear genes (P = 0.8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>GTR+I+G models of sequence evolution were selected for the CO1 and 16S partitions in the mtDNA dataset. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>In the species tree datasets, GTR+I+G was selected for CO1 and 16S, GTR+I for 28S, and GTR+G for ITS2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Phylogeographical analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Monophyly of the vorhiesi group was strongly supported in the mtDNA tree (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Strong phylogeographical signal was evident, but basal relationships were poorly resolved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Twenty-seven geographically cohesive lineages (including singletons, henceforth referred to as ‘lineages’ for convenience) were inferred from the mtDNA tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Eleven of these lineages represented the species V. bandido, V. cashi, V. deboerae, V. electrum, V. feti, V. halli, V. jonesi, V. lapidicola, V. paysonensis, V. tenuipalpus, and V. vorhiesi and are referred to hereafter by their species names. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The remaining 16 lineages consisted of samples from single mountain ranges with two exceptions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The exceptions were one lineage, referred to as ‘Mogollon’, that included samples from several mountains, and one lineage with samples from the adjacent Florida and Tres Hermanas mountains (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Species tree and divergence date estimates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The species tree reconstruction (Fig. 3) revealed relatively deep structure with long terminal branches similar to the mtDNA gene tree used for phylogeographical inference (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The three gene trees each revealed relatively heterogeneous tree topologies (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Six geographically cohesive groups of lineages were consistently inferred, suggesting that the species tree was not heavily biased by the mtDNA data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Differences between the species tree and mtDNA tree were confined to weakly supported nodes (see Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>S2 for species tree posterior probability support values), resulting in topological rearrangements towards the base of the trees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic positions of the paysonensis and tenuipalpus lineages, in particular, differed among the topologies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0052822-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052822.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Tempo of diversification for scorpions in the Vaejovis vorhiesi group. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>(a) Time-calibrated species tree reconstructed using multilocus data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Numbers denote major geographical clades. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>These clades are mapped across the landscape in Figure 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Bars indicate 95% highest posterior densities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Divergence times and posterior probability support values are provided in Figure S2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>(b) Lineage through time plots derived from mtDNA and multilocus estimates of divergence dates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Birth–death likelihood analyses suggest a rate-variable density-dependent rate of diversification though time for both datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Approximate timing of major geological and climatic events that changed the landscape of southwestern North American are delineated, with time shown in millions of years (Ma). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Pleist. = Pleistocene, QT = Quaternary. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0052822.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Six geographically cohesive groups of lineages (referred to herein as ‘clades’; Clades 1–6, Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>3 and 4) and three lineages (paysonensis, tenuipalpus, and Doña Ana) formed the framework of the species tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>However, only the relationship between two clades (Clades 5 and 6) was strongly supported (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The geographical distribution of five of the six clades (Clades 1 and 4–6) and one of the two individual lineages (tenuipalpus) were anchored in the transition zone between the Colorado Plateau and the Basin and Range geological provinces, along the Mogollon Rim (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Two clades of Madrean ‘sky island’ endemics (Clades 2 and 3) were confined to the Basin and Range province. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The tenuipalpus and Doña Ana lineages were respectively situated at the eastern and western extremes of the distribution of the vorhiesi group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0052822-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052822.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Geography of diversification among scorpions in the Vaejovis vorhiesi group. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Color-coded dots, representing each of the six major geographical clades, are shown on the multilocus species tree (see Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Three lineages not within inferred major clades are labeled on the map. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Sample names for each locality are provided in Figure 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Gray bar indicates the approximate location of the Mogollon Rim. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0052822.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Divergence date estimates inferred from the Cape-calibrated multilocus and mtDNA datasets using *BEAST and BEAST were similar (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Mean divergence dates were generally within 2 Ma, whereas posterior credibility intervals were slightly narrower in the multilocus analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Divergence dates estimated across the species tree (Fig. 3 and Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>S2) suggested that early diversification in the vorhiesi group began around 20 Ma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Although 95% posterior credible intervals were wide, most divergences estimated within the vorhiesi group were within the Neogene period from 25 to 2.6 Ma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Only five of the 26 inferred divergences incorporated the Pleistocene within credible intervals, and all mean divergence date estimates pre-dated the Pleistocene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Tempo of diversification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Birth–death likelihood analyses of lineage diversification rates rejected the null hypothesis of rate-constancy for both datasets (P = 0.003, multilocus; P&lt;0.001, mtDNA-only). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The rate-variable model that best fit the datasets was the logistic density-dependent (DDL) model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Under this model, diversification rate in the vorhiesi group gradually decreased through time, with diversification rate estimated at 0.276 (multilocus *BEAST) or 0.370 (mtDNA-only BEAST) divergences per million years (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Models considering variable rates of extinction and speciation did not provide a better fit to the datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Similar results (rejection of the null hypothesis, P = 0.01; DDL best rate-variable model) were obtained when more recent divergences within lineages were accounted for (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Lineage diversification across southwestern North America </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The time-calibrated phylogenetic hypothesis presented here suggests that scorpions in the vorhiesi group have had a long history in the highlands of southwestern North America. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Results reveal a striking pattern of lineage diversification almost entirely confined within the bounds of the Neogene period (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Based on mean estimates, all 26 inferred cladogenetic events probably occurred prior to the Pleistocene epoch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Only five divergences incorporated the Pleistocene within credible intervals (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Geological processes that cumulatively acted to separate the Basin and Range province from the Colorado Plateau occurred during a period known as the mid-Miocene transition [53], [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>This episode of geological activity, 24–12 Ma, probably created the landscape in which the vorhiesi group originated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The transformation of an originally more continuous landscape to one of isolated mountain ranges associated with Basin and Range extension may have provided opportunities for rapid early diversification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The largely unsupported basal divergences in the species tree that occurred around 18–13 Ma (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>S2) are consistent with a rapid series of divergences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>It is difficult to resolve these specific relationships with the current dataset, and whether this represents a case of simultaneous divergence from a common ancestor (i.e., hard polytomy) or estimation uncertainty (i.e., soft polytomy) remains unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Regardless, it is clear that the early divergences within these scorpions occurred in rapid succession over a narrow window of time (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Following early diversification in the vorhiesi group, potentially linked with the mid-Miocene transition, the development of regional clades between about 12–7 Ma (Fig. 3) may have initiated in response to continued landscape deformation coincident with paleoclimatical change [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Basin and Range extension in southern Arizona may have spread rapidly northeastward across southern Arizona into the Rio Grande rift of southern New Mexico between about 13–9 Ma [56], [57], [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>This development was synchronous with climatic change in the area that was punctuated by a dramatic shift in atmospheric conditions at 7–5 Ma [55], [59]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The distributions of four of the six inferred regional clades (Clades 2, 3, 5, and 6) and one lineage (Doña Ana) extend across southern Arizona and New Mexico (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>The two remaining clades to the north (Clades 1 and 4) are centered along the Mogollon Rim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Late Miocene formation of localized volcanic fields across the Mogollon Rim [60] and tilting and faulting, around 13–6 Ma during the extension of the Basin and Range [54], may have contributed to diversification at the base of these two clades. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Fine-scale ancient endemism </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Mountainous regions are known to generally harbor greater species endemism than adjacent lowland areas [61], [62], [63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Much of this endemism resulted from Quaternary climatic oscillations driving fragmentation and isolation of highland habitats (e.g., [23]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Scorpions in the vorhiesi group display remarkable patterns of fine-scale endemism that appear to have developed much earlier than the Pleistocene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>This is unsurprising given their stenotopic habitat requirements [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Diversification within the vorhiesi group was probably driven by allopatry in isolated rocky highland habitats: ephemeral woodland corridors may have connected highland biota during the Pleistocene but lacked suitable humid, rocky habitats required by these scorpions for dispersal between adjacent mountain ranges. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The persistence of separate lineages at small spatial scales suggests that a combination of ecological stenotopy and limited vagility make the vorhiesi group particularly valuable as indicators of geomorphological evolution in southwestern North America, as observed in other scorpion taxa elsewhere in the world [9], [11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Tempo of diversification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Diversification rate in the vorhiesi group appears to have decreased slowly through time (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Given the restricted distributions and stenotopic requirements of vorhiesi group scorpions for insular montane habitats, this finding is consistent with studies suggesting that diversification rate slows as ecological opportunities diminish [52], [64], [65], [66], and that declining diversification rates may be caused by the saturation of geographical space [67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The decreased diversification rate of these scorpions is probably related to the dynamic geological history of southwestern North America previously outlined, which appears sufficient to have formed new habitats and dispersal routes, and to have isolated older habitats throughout the Neogene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Divergence times in the vorhiesi group suggest that these highland habitats were occupied and persisted throughout the Neogene and that, by the onset of Quaternary, few unoccupied habitats would have been available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Quaternary climate change, while dramatically shifting vegetation communities across southwestern North America [68], may have had little impact on diversification in these stenotopic scorpions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Montane scorpions as windows to pre-Quaternary history and orogeny </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>A range of genetic divergences across a Neogene temporal continuum, combined with fine-scale endemism, suggests that montane scorpions offer the potential to assess correlations between Earth history and biotic diversification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Millions of years of dynamic change across a heterogeneous landscape chiseled a genetic footprint in scorpions of the vorhiesi group that has not eroded through potential Pleistocene habitat connectivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>These scorpions can thus provide unique insight into the impact of pre-Quaternary events on the generation of biodiversity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Perhaps more importantly, these events can be inferred at a relatively fine geographical scale. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Agreement on a cohesive geohistorical framework for mountain formation across southwestern North America remains elusive despite decades of research [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Ecologically specialized ‘living fossils’, like the scorpions of the vorhiesi group, represent model organisms for tracking orogeny, as evidenced in the present study by the amount of genetic structure observed across the relatively small distances between adjacent mountain ranges. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Other stenotopic scorpions may offer similar insights regarding mountain formation and the generation of diversity on montane islands. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0052822.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Three gene trees for scorpions in the  Vaejovis vorhiesi  group embedded within the shared species tree. Strongly supported nodes (≥0.95 posterior probability support) are indicated with black dots. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0052822.s001.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0052822.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Chronograms with estimated divergence times (in millions of years, Ma) for scorpions in the  Vaejovis vorhiesi  group. Estimates are shown for multilocus species tree (top) and mtDNA gene tree (bottom) analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Posterior probability support values for nodes are indicated by coded dots explained in the figure legend. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Nodes that received &lt;0.50 support are not indicated with dots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Means and 95% highest posterior densities (in brackets) are shown for each node. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate eight additional divergences included in diversification rate analyses (see Methods and Materials). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>QT = Quaternary. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0052822.s002.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0052822.s003"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Scorpion-specific mtDNA primers used in study on the  Vaejovis vorhiesi  group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>(DOC) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0052822.s003.doc"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>We thank T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Anton, R.F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Ayrey, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Bigelow, G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Casper, L.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Esposito, O.F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Francke, G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Giribet, E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>González, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Hartman, B.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Hendrixson, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Huff, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Jones, C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Kristensen, K.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>McWest, R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Mercurio, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Rubio, W.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Savary, W.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Sissom, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Torocco, A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Valdez, Z.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Valois, D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Vernier, R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Villa, and R.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>West for assisting with fieldwork and/or providing samples; L.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Esposito for assisting with development of COI primers, and O. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Delgado, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Mosier and T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Sharma for generating data at the AMNH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Fieldwork in Mexico was conducted under permits granted by SEMARNAT to O.F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Francke, the late F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Mendoza-Quijano, and C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Solis-Rojas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>We thank the Navajo Nation for providing access to their lands, and D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Chung, G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Gallenstein, B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Van Belle, and P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Whitefield of the National Park Service and Wupatki National Monument for granting W.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Sissom permits to collect in Wupatki National Monument. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Other support and assistance was provided by R.F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Ayrey, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Chaves, O. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Delgado, O.F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Francke, E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>González, J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Huff, K.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>McWest, R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Mercurio, W.E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Savary and W.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Sissom. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Several anonymous reviewers provided comments that improved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0052822-Morrone1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>1Morrone JJ (2009) Evolutionary Biogeography: An Integrative Approach with Case Studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>New York: Columbia University Press. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>304 p. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Lomolino1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>2Lomolino MV, Riddle BR, Whittaker RJ, Brown JH (2010) Biogeography, 4th edition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Sunderland, Massachusetts: Sinauer Associates, Inc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>764 p. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Cody1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>3 CodyS, RichardsonJE, RullV, EllisC, PenningtonRT (2010) The great American biotic interchange revisited. Ecography 33: 326–332. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Smith1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>4 SmithBT, KlickaJ (2010) The profound influence of the Late Pliocene Panamanian uplift on the exchange, diversification, and distribution of New World Birds. Ecography 33: 333–342. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Wiens1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>5 WiensJJ (2011) The niche, large-scale biogeography, and species interactions. Philos Trans R Soc Lond 366: 2336–2350.21768150 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Avise1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>6Avise J (2000) Phylogeography: the History and Formation of Species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Harvard University Press, Cambridge, MA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>447 p. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Knowles1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>7 KnowlesLL (2009) Statistical phylogeography. Annu Rev Ecol Syst 40: 593–612. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Hickerson1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>8 HickersonMJ, CarstensBC, Cavender-BaresJ, CrandallKA, GrahamCH, et al (2010) Phylogeography's past, present, and future: 10 years after Avise 2000. Mol Phylogenet Evol 54: 291–301.19755165 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Prendini1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>9Prendini L (2005) Scorpion diversity and distribution in southern Africa: Pattern and process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>In: Huber BA, Sinclair BJ, Lampe K-H, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>African Biodiversity: Molecules, Organisms, Ecosystems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>New York Springer Verlag. pp 25–68. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Coddington1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>10Coddington JA, Giribet G, Harvey MS, Prendini L, Walter DE (2004) Arachnida. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>In: Cracraft J, Donoghue M.Oxford, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Assembling the Tree of Life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Oxford University Press. pp 296–318. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Prendini2"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>11Prendini L (2001) Substratum specialization and speciation in southern African scorpions: the Effect Hypothesis revisited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>In: Fet V, Selden PA, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>In Memoriam Gary A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Polis, British Arachnological Society. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Burnham Beeches, Bucks. pp 113–138. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Gantenbein1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>12 GantenbeinB, LargiadèrCR (2003) The phylogeographic importance of the Strait of Gibraltar as a gene flow barrier in terrestrial arthropods: A case study with the scorpion Buthus occitanus as model organism. Mol Phylogenet Evol 28: 119–130.12801475 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Parmakelis1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>13 ParmakelisA, StathiI, SpanosL, LouisC, MylonasM (2006) Phylogeography of Iurus dufoureius (Brulle, 1832) (Scorpiones, Iuridae). J Biogeogr 33: 251–260. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Parmakelis2"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>14 ParmakelisA, StathiI, ChatzakiM, SimaiakisS, SpanosL, et al (2006) Evolution of Mesobuthus gibbosus (Brulle, 1832) (Scorpiones : Buthidae) in the northeastern Mediterranean region. Mol Ecol 15: 2883–2894.16911208 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Borges1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>15 BorgesA, BerminghamE, HerreraN, AlfonzoM, SanjurO (2010) Molecular systematics of the neotropical scorpion genus Tityus (Buthidae): The historical biogeography and venom antigenis diversity of toxic Venezuela species. Toxicon 55: 436–454.19799925 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Sousa1"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>16 SousaP, FroufeE, AlvesPC, HarrisDJ (2010) Genetic diversity within scorpions of the genus Buthus from the Iberian Peninsula: mitochondrial DNA sequence data indicate additional distinct cryptic lineages. J Arachnol 38: 206–211. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Loureno1"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>17Lourenço WR, Sissom WD (2000) Scorpiones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>In: Bousquets JL, González Soriano E, Papavero, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Biodiversidad, Taxonomía y Biogeographía de Artrópodos de México. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Hacia una Síntesis de su Concimiento. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Volume 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Ciudad de México: Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México. pp 115–135. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Sissom1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>18Sissom WD, Hendrixson BE (2005) Scorpion biodiversity and patterns of endemism in northern Mexico. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>In: Cartron J-LE, Ceballos G, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Biodiversity, Ecosystems, and Conservation in northern Mexico. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Oxford: Oxford University Press. pp 122–137. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Bryson1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>19 BrysonRW, García-VázquezUO, RiddleBR (2011) Relative roles of Neogene vicariance and Quaternary climate change on the historical diversification of bunchgrass lizards (Sceloporus scalaris group) in Mexico. Mol Phylogenet Evol 62: 447–457.22075377 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Bryson2"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>20 BrysonRW, MurphyRW, GrahamMR, LathropA, Lazcano-VillarealD (2011) Historical diversification of the Crotalus intermedius group and Pleistocene pine-oak woodland connections between Mexico's Sierra Madre Occidental and Sierra Madre Oriental. J Biogeogr 38: 2299–2310. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Sissom2"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>21 SissomWD, HughesGB, BrysonRW, PrendiniL (2012) The vorhiesi group of Vaejovis C.L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Koch, 1836 (Scorpiones: Vaejovidae) in Arizona, with description of a new species from the Hualapai Mountains. Am Mus Novit 3742: 1–19. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Graham1"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>22 GrahamMR, AyreyRF, BrysonRW (2012) Multivariate methods support the distinction of a new highland Vaejovis (Scorpiones: Vaejovidae) from the Sierra de los Ajos, Mexico. J Arachnol 40: 281–290. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-McCormack1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>23 McCormackJE, BowenBS, SmithTB (2008) Integrating paleoecology and genetics of bird populations in two sky island archipelagos. BMC Biol 6: 28.18588695 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Knowles2"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>24 KnowlesLL (2001) Genealogical portraits of speciation in montane grasshoppers (genus Melanoplus) from the sky islands of the Rocky Mountains. Proc R Soc B 268: 319–324. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Ayoub1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>25 AyoubNA, RiechertSE (2004) Molecular evidence for Pleistocene glacial cycles driving diversification of a North American desert spider, Agelenopsisaperta . Mol Ecol 13: 3453–3465.15488003 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Wood1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>26 WoodDA, VandergastAG, Lemos-EspinalJA, FisherRN, HolycrossAT (2011) Refugial isolation and divergence in the Narrowheaded Gartersnake species complex (Thamnophis rufipunctatus) as revealed by multilocus DNA sequence data. Mol Ecol 20: 3856–3878.21851436 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Stockwell1"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>27Stockwell SA (1989) Revision of the Phylogeny and Higher Classification of Scorpions (Chelicerata). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>PhD Dissertation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>University of California, Berkeley. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>319 p. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Moulton1"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>28 MoultonMJ, SongH, WhitingMF (2010) Assessing the effects of primer specificity on eliminating numt coamplification in DNA barcoding: a case study from Orthoptera (Arthropoda: Insecta). Mol Ecol Res 10: 615–627. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Bertheau1"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>29 BertheauC, SchulerH, KrumböckS, ArthoferW, StaufferC (2011) Hit or miss in phylogeographic analyses: the case of the cryptic NUMTs. Mol Ecol Res 11: 1056–1059. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Tully1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>30 TullyT, D'HaeseC, RichardM, FerrièreR (2006) Two major evolutionary lineages revealed by molecular phylogeny in the parthenogenetic collembolan Folsomia candida . Pedobiologia 50: 95–104. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Ji1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>31 JiY-J, ZhangD-X, HeL-J (2003) Evolutionary conservation and versatility of a new set of primers for amplifying the ribosomal internal transcribed spacer regions in insects and other invertebrates. Mol Ecol Notes 3: 581–585. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Prendini3"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>32 PrendiniL, CroweTM, WheelerWC (2003) Systematics and biogeography of the family Scorpionidae Latreille, with a discussion of phylogenetic methods. Invert Syst 17: 185–259. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Prendini4"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>33 PrendiniL, WeygoldtP, WheelerWC (2005) Systematics of the Damon variegatus group of African whip spiders (Chelicerata: Amblypygi): evidence from behaviour, morphology and DNA. Org Divers Evol 5: 203–236. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Katoh1"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>34 KatohK, TohH (2008) Improved accuracy of multiple ncRNA alignment by incorporating structural information into a MAFFT-based framework. BMC Bioinformatics 9: 212.18439255 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Katoh2"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>35 KatohK, MisawaK, KumaK, MiyataT (2002) MAFFT: a novel method for rapid multiple sequence alignment based on fast Fourier transform. Nucleic Acids Res 30: 3059–3066.12136088 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Stephens1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>36 StephensM, DonnellyP (2003) A comparison of Bayesian methods for haplotype reconstruction from population genotype data. Am J Hum Genet 73: 1162–1169.14574645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Swofford1"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>37Swofford DL (2002) PAUP*: Phylogenetic Analysis Using Parsimony (*and Other Methods), Version 4.0b10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Sinauer, Sunderland, Massachusetts. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Ronquist1"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>38 RonquistF, HuelsenbeckJP (2009) MRBAYES 3: Bayesian phylogenetic inference under mixed models. Bioinformatics 19: 1572–1574. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Avise2"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>39 AviseJC, WalkerD (1998) Pleistocene phylogeographic effects on avian populations and the speciation process. Proc R Soc B 265: 457–463. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Avise3"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>40 AviseJC, WalkerD, JohnsGC (1998) Speciation durations and Pleistocene effects on vertebrate phylogeography. Proc R Soc B 265: 1707–1712. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Rissler1"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>41 RisslerLJ, ApodacaJJ (2007) Adding more ecology into species delimitation: ecological niche models and phylogeography help define cryptic species in the black salamander (Aneides flavipunctatus). Syst Biol 56: 924–942.18066928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Kass1"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>42 KassR, RafteryA (1995) Bayes factors. J Am Statist Assoc 90: 773–795. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Nylander1"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>43Nylander JAA (2004) MRMODELTEST v2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Program distributed by the author. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Evolutionary Biology Centre, Uppsala University, Uppsala. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Rambaut1"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>44Rambaut A, Drummond AJ (2012) Tracer v1.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk/Tracer">http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk/Tracer</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2011 Sep 12. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Heled1"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>45 HeledJ, DrummondA (2010) Bayesian inference of species trees from multilocus data. Mol Biol Evol 27: 570–580.19906793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Ferrari1"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>46 FerrariL (1995) Miocene shearing along the northern boundary of the Jalisco block and the opening of the southern Gulf of California. Geology 23: 751–754. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Oskin1"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>47 OskinM, StockJ (2003) Marine incursions synchronous with plate-boundary localization in the Gulf of California. Geology 31: 23–26. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Mulcahy1"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>48 MulcahyDG, MaceyJR (2009) Vicariance and dispersal form a ring distribution in nightsnakes around the Gulf of California. Mol Phylogenet Evol 53: 537–546.19501659 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Drummond1"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>49 DrummondAJ, RambautA (2007) BEAST: Bayesian evolutionary analysis by sampling trees. BMC Evol Biol 7: 214.17996036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Rabosky1"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>50 RaboskyDL (2006) Likelihood methods for inferring temporal shifts in diversification rates. Evolution 60: 1152–1164.16892966 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Rabosky2"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>51 RaboskyDL (2006) LASER: a maximum likelihood toolkit for detecting temporal shifts in diversification rates from molecular phylogenies. Evol Bioinformatics Online 2: 257–260. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Rabosky3"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>52 RaboskyDL, LovetteIJ (2008) Density dependent diversification in North American wood warblers. Proc R Soc B 275: 2363–2371. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Shafiqullah1"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>53Shafiqullah M, Damon PE, Lynch DJ, Reynolds SJ, Rehrig WA, et al.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>(1980) K-Ar geochronology and geologic history of southwestern Arizona and adjacent area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>In: Jenney J, Stone C, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>Studies in Western Arizona: Arizona Geological Society Digest, Vol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>XII. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Arizona Geological Society: Tucson. pp 201–260. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Brand1"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>54Brand P, Stump E (2011) Tertiary Extension and Fault Block Rotation in the Transition Zone, Cedar Mountains Area, Arizona v.1.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Arizona Geological Survey, Tucson. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Retallack1"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>55 RetallackGJ (2001) Cenozoic expansion of grasslands and climatic cooling. J Geol 109: 407–426. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Seager1"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>56 SeagerWR, ShafiqullahM, HawleyJW, MarvinRF (1984) New K–Ar dates from basalts and the evolution of the southern Rio Grande rift. Geol Soc Am Bull 95: 87–99. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Menges1"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>57Menges CM, Pearthree PA (1989) Late Cenozoic tectonism in Arizona and its impact on regional landscape evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>In: Jenney JP, Reynolds SJ, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Geologic Evolution of Arizona. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>Tucson: Arizona Geological Society. pp 649–680. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Henry1"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>58 HenryCD, Aranda-GomezJ (2000) Plate interactions control middle–late Miocene, proto-Gulf and Basin and Range extension in the southern Basin and Range. Tectonophysics 318: 1–26. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Retallack2"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>59 RetallackGJ (1997) Neogene expansion of the North American Prairie. Palaios 12: 380–390. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Sabels1"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>60Sabels BE (1962) Mogollon Rim volcanism and geochronology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>In: Weber RH, Peirce HW, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Guidebook of the Mogollon Rim Region, East-central Arizona, New Mexico Geological Society 13th Field Conference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Socorro: New Mexico Geological Society. pp 100–107. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Wiens2"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>61 WiensJJ, Parra-OleaG, Garcia-ParisM, WakeDB (2007) Phylogenetic history underlies elevational patterns of biodiversity in tropical salamanders. Proc R Soc B 274: 919–928. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Thomas1"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>62 ThomasGH, OrmeCDL, DaviesRG, OlsonVA, BennettPM, et al (2008) Regional variation in the historical components of global avian species richness. Global Ecol Biogeogr 17: 340–351. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Badgley1"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>63 BadgleyC (2010) Tectonics, topography, and mammalian diversity. Ecography 33: 220–231. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-McPeek1"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>64 McPeekMA (2008) The ecological dynamics of clade diversification and community assembly. Am Nat 172: E270–E284.18851684 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Kozak1"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>65 KozakKH, WeisrockDW, LarsonA (2006) Rapid lineage accumulation in a non-adaptive radiation: phylogenetic analysis of diversification rates in eastern North American woodland salamanders (Plethodontidae: Plethodon). Proc R Soc B 273: 539–546. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Burbrink1"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>66 BurbrinkFT, PyronRA (2010) How does ecological opportunity influence rates of speciation, extinction, and morphological diversification in New World ratsnakes (tribe Lampropeltini)? Evolution 64: 934–943.19895554 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Pigot1"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>67 PigotAL, PhillimoreAB, OwensIPF, OrmeCDL (2010) The shape and temporal dynamics of phylogenetic trees arising from geographic speciation. Syst Biol 59: 660–673.20952757 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-VanDevender1"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>68Van Devender TR (1990) Late Quaternary vegetation and climate of the Sonoran Desert, United States and Mexico. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>In: Betancourt JL, Van Devender TR, Martin PS, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Packrat Middens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>The Last 40,000 Years of Biotic Change. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Tucson: University of Arizona Press. pp 134–165. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0052822-Wilson1"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>69 WilsonJS, PittsJP (2010) Illuminating the lack of consensus among descriptions of earth history data in the North American deserts: a resource for biologists. Prog Phys Geog 34: 419–441. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
