
<article article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPGSJ//DTD full length article DTD version 7.0 XML//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName ajarticle_v7_x.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 7.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName naturesa2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Br. J. Cancer</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3505013</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">bjc2012470</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/bjc.2012.470</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23079575</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical Study</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>VeriStrat® has prognostic value in advanced stage NSCLC patients treated with erlotinib and sorafenib </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running">VeriStrat and treatment with erlotinib and sorafenib</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kuiper</surname><given-names>J L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lind</surname><given-names>J S W</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Groen</surname><given-names>H J M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grigorieva</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dingemans</surname><given-names>A M C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>E F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Pulmonary Diseases, VU
University Medical Center</institution>, P.O. Box 7057, Amsterdam
1007 MB, <country>The Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Pulmonary Diseases, University
Medical Center Groningen</institution>, De Boelelaan 1117, 1081 HV, Hanzeplein 1 P.O.
Box 30.001, Groningen
9700 RB, <country>The Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Biodesix Inc.</institution>, P.O. Box
774872, Steamboat Springs, CO
80477, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Pulmonary Diseases and
GROW–School for developmental biology and oncology, Maastricht University Medical
Center</institution>, P.O. Box 5800, Maastricht
6202 AZ, <country>The Netherlands</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label>E-mail: <email>ef.smit@vumc.nl</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>107</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1820</fpage><lpage>1825</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>02</day><month>07</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>09</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>09</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 Cancer Research UK</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cancer Research UK</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"><license-p>From twelve months after its original publication, this work is licensed under
the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. To view a
copy of this license, visit
http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The serum proteomic test VeriStrat has been shown to be able to classify advanced non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) patients for overall survival (OS) after treatment with epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKIs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>In this study, VeriStrat was evaluated as a pre-treatment stratification tool in patients with advanced stage NSCLC for treatment with the combination of erlotinib and sorafenib, considering both OS and progression-free survival (PFS) as end points. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Methods: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Serum samples from 50 patients treated within the context of a phase II trial of first-line erlotinib and sorafenib were analysed with VeriStrat, a fully locked mass spectrometry-based test that identifies patients likely to have good or poor outcome on EGFR therapy based on eight distinct features in mass spectra. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Analysis was performed fully blinded to all clinical data, and then the outcome data were analysed with respect to the obtained serum classifications. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Results: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>VeriStrat classified pre-treatment samples into two groups, VeriStrat Good and VeriStrat Poor, which were significantly different in OS (hazard ratio (HR) 0.30, log-rank P=0.009) and in PFS (HR 0.40, log-rank P=0.035). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Conclusion: </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>VeriStrat has shown its potential for stratification of unselected, advanced stage NSCLC patients treated in first line with a combination of erlotinib and sorafenib. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>lung cancer</kwd><kwd>proteomics</kwd><kwd>erlotinib</kwd><kwd>sorafenib</kwd><kwd>serum biomarker</kwd><kwd>personalised therapy</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) family is an important target in the treatment of non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of the EGFR pathway with tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKIs), such as erlotinib in patients with advanced NSCLC, leads to improved survival compared with placebo (Shepherd et al, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Another area of investigation has been the vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) pathway, which has a crucial role in initiation of angiogenesis (Herbst et al, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>When both pathways are inhibited simultaneously, the effect may be synergistic (Camp et al, 2005; Herbst et al, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Indeed, treatment with an EGFR-TKI and a VEGF receptor inhibitor showed improved response rates and progression-free survival (PFS) as compared with EGFR-TKI mono-therapy; however, so far this combination treatment has not demonstrated a survival benefit and showed disappointing results in an unselected patient population in first-line setting (Dingemans et al, 2011; Herbst et al, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Hence, a reliable biomarker that predicts clinical benefit of combined EGFR-VEGF inhibition would be very helpful in guiding patient selection, as of today EGFR mutations are the sole validated predictive biomarkers for patient selection for treatment with single-agent EGFR-TKIs (Sequist et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionisation time-of-flight (MALDI-TOF) mass spectrometry (MS) is a technique for analysing biological samples, such as plasma, urine and tissue, by characterising protein content through peaks in the mass spectrum (Yanagisawa et al, 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>VeriStrat (Biodesix, Boulder, CO, USA) is a test based on a MALDI-TOF MS signature of eight protein or peptide features. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>It was developed using pre-treatment serum samples from a cohort of advanced NSCLC patients that experienced long-term stable disease vs early progression on gefitinib monotherapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>From the mass spectra of these serum samples, eight MS features differentiating the two outcome groups were identified and used to develop the VeriStrat classifier. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>This classifier assigns a classification to each new serum sample: VeriStrat Good (‘good') or VeriStrat Poor (‘poor'). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In less than 3% of cases an unequivocal classification cannot be assigned and the result is reported as indeterminate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The VeriStrat test was validated in two independent cohorts of unselected NSCLC patients treated with erlotinib or gefitinib (Taguchi et al, 2007), which showed that patients with pre-treatment serum classified as ‘good' had better overall survival (OS) than those with serum classified as ‘poor' after treatment with EGFR-TKIs (Taguchi et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Also, it has been shown to be able to classify two independent cohorts of first-line patients and one cohort of second-line patients treated with erlotinib and bevacizumab (a VEGF receptor inhibitor) into groups with better or worse OS (Akerley et al, 2010; Carbone et al, 2010b; Gautschi et al, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Newer oral VEGF receptor inhibitors (such as sorafenib) in combination with erlotinib were found to have clinically relevant activity in a recent phase II study (Lind et al, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Within the context of this study, it was investigated whether VeriStrat also differentiates outcome after treatment with erlotinib and sorafenib in chemotherapy-naive patients with advanced NSCLC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Material and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Patients and protocol </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Serum samples were collected from chemotherapy-naive patients (n=50) who were treated with erlotinib and sorafenib in a multicentre single-arm phase II study (Lind et al, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Inclusion criteria in this trial were chemotherapy-naive patients with pathologically documented, inoperable, locally advanced, recurrent or metastatic NSCLC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In addition, age ⩾18 year, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status 0 or 1, estimated life expectancy ⩾12 weeks and adequate haematologic, renal and hepatic function were required for inclusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Patients had to have at least one measurable lesion according to the Response Evaluation Criteria of Solid Tumours (Therasse et al, 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Exclusion criteria included symptomatic brain metastasis, severe or unstable systemic disease, seizure disorder requiring medication, history of bleeding diathesis and cardiac disease, and uncontrolled hypertension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Patients received orally administered sorafenib 400 mg twice a day and erlotinib 150 mg once a day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>OS was defined as time from start of treatment to death, irrespective of cause. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>PFS was defined as time from start of treatment to documented progression of disease or death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The study was approved by the local medical ethical review boards. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>All patients provided written informed consent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The study is registered with ClinicalTrials.gov, number NCT00722969. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Serum samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Serum samples were collected pre-treatment and at weeks 1 and 3 after treatment initiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The collection of sera was performed according to the protocols approved by the local institutional review board. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The sera were allowed to clot for 1 h after which they were centrifuged at room temperature for 10 min at 3000 r.p.m. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Aliquots were taken and stored at −80 °C until further use. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Thawing of aliquots was allowed only once. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Serum samples were sent to Biodesix (Boulder, CO, USA) for VeriStrat testing blinded to all clinical data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The treating physician was unaware of the outcome of the VeriStrat testing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Serum proteomic testing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The sera were diluted 1 : 10 in HPLC-grade water and mixed (1 : 1 v/v) with matrix solution (25 mg ml−1 sinapinic acid (Sigma, St Louis, MO, USA) dissolved in 50 : 50 : 0.1% acetonitrile (Burdick &amp; Jackson, Muskegon, MI, USA) : water : trifluoroacetic acid (Sigma)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The serum–matrix mixture was spotted in triplicate on a MALDI target in randomly assigned plate positions and mass spectra acquired using an Autoflex MALDI-TOF mass spectrometer (Bruker Daltonics, Bremen, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Each replicate spectrum consisted of an average of 2000 individual spectra collected from various locations within the spot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Spectral preprocessing was performed, which included background and noise estimation, background subtraction, alignment and normalisation to partial ion current before spectral analysis by the VeriStrat algorithm, which classifies each sample as VeriStrat Good, Poor or Indeterminate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>All details of sample processing, spectral preprocessing and the classification algorithm, based on eight distinct m/z features have been fixed since development of the test in 2006 (Taguchi et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The identity of the proteins that make up the MALDI-MS features used in the test are still under investigation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>VeriStrat classifications obtained for the samples were returned to the centre curating the study database, where they were unblinded and merged with the clinical database. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Statistics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Statistical significance of difference in OS and PFS between groups was assessed using log-rank P-values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The hazard ratios (HRs) were calculated using Mantel–Haenszel methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Categorical data were compared between patient groups using Fisher's exact tests. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Analyses were performed using PRISM (Graphpad, La Jolla, CA, USA) and SAS Enterprise Guide 4.3 (SAS, Cary, NC, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Patient characteristics and pre-treatment VeriStrat classification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Pre-treatment samples were collected from 50 patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>One sample was classified as indeterminate and one sample was not available, due to withdrawal of consent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Thirty-three samples were classified as ‘good' and 15 samples as ‘poor'. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Distribution of the patient characteristics by VeriStrat classification is given in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Only histology showed significant correlation with VeriStrat classification (adenocarcinoma vs other; Fisher's exact test P=0.02). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>It is of note that recently presented results (Grigorieva et al, 2011) indicate that, in contrast to previous results in non-BAC adenocarcinoma and squamous cell carcinoma of the lung, no significant separation in PFS was found between VeriStrat groups in BAC lung cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Hence, in this analysis, BAC is listed separately and not included in the adenocarcinoma subset, even though the term ‘BAC' is outdated and the histological subtype is now considered as adenocarcinoma (Travis et al, 2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>VeriStrat classification within 3 weeks of treatment initiation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Changes in VeriStrat classification in the first weeks of treatment were observed in a substantial proportion of patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>After 3 weeks, 41 samples were available and 35 patients had data at all three time points (pre-treatment, weeks 1 and 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>One week after commencement of therapy only 26 (60%) patients maintained their pre-treatment VeriStrat classification, with 12 patients changing from ‘good' to ‘poor' and 6 changing from ‘poor' to ‘good'. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>About 45% of patients experienced further changes of classification at week 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>As a result, out of 35 patients that had data at all three time points, 46% maintained their classification throughout, 20% changed at week 1 and reverted at week 3 (all these changes were ‘good'–‘poor'–‘good'), and 34% either changed at week 1 and stayed changed or changed at week 3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>OS and PFS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Patients with pre-treatment classification of ‘good' had statistically significantly improved OS compared with those with pre-treatment classification ‘poor' (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The HR for OS was 0.30 (95% confidence interval (CI): 0.12–0.74), with log-rank P=0.009. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Median OS was 13.7 months (95% CI: 12.0 months–undefined) for the ‘good' group and 5.6 months (95% CI: 1.6–7.6 months) for the ‘poor' group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Patients with pre-treatment classification of ‘good' had statistically significantly improved PFS compared with patients with ‘poor' classification (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The HR between groups was 0.40 (95% CI: 0.17–0.94), with log-rank P=0.035. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Median PFS was 5.5 months (95% CI: 3.0–6.9 months) for the ‘good' group and 2.7 months (95% CI: 1.4–5.6 months) for the ‘poor' group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>In addition to VeriStrat classification, histology (large-cell and squamous vs adenocarcinoma) was statistically significant in univariate OS analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The median survival for adenocarcinoma patients was 12.4 months (95% CI: 6.3 months-undefined) and 4.7 months (95% CI: 1.6–10.9 months) for patients with large cell or squamous histology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>In univariate PFS analysis, histology (adenocarcinoma vs large cell or squamous) and smoking history (never vs ever) were significant as well (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Given the relatively small sample size, with only 15 pre-treatment samples classified as ‘poor', meaningful multivariate analysis was not possible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>However, we could perform some subgroup analysis. Figures 3A and B show OS and PFS for adenocarcinoma patients by VeriStrat classification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The ‘good' group had longer median OS and PFS (12.5 months and 5.5 months, respectively) than the ‘poor' group (5.6 months and 2.7 months, respectively), although separation between groups did not reach statistical significance for either comparison (log-rank P=0.21, HR=0.45, 95% CI: 0.13–1.57 for OS and log-rank P=0.093, HR=0.26, 95% CI: 0.06–1.25 for PFS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Examination of the ever-smokers subgroup showed separation between ‘good' and ‘poor' groups that was significant in OS (P=0.0074, HR=0.27, 95% CI: 0.10–0.70) and trended to significance in PFS (P=0.058, HR=0.43, 95% CI: 0.18–1.03) (Figures 3C and D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The small number of patients with other histologies and who were never smokers did not allow meaningful survival analysis in these complementary subgroups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Carrying out survival analysis with the PFS data (relative to same starting point as for the pre-treatment analysis) using the VeriStrat classifications obtained from the samples collected at weeks 1 and 3 yields no statistically significant separation between groups (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>For week 1 classification, the analysis produces HR=0.61 (95% CI: 0.31–1.23) and log-rank value P=0.17, whereas for week 3 classification, the HR is 0.97 (95% CI: 0.41–2.30) and log-rank P-value is 0.94. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Response rates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Five patients were not evaluable for response: four patients discontinued treatment before the week 6 CT scan and one patient developed a large cavity in the primary tumour superimposed by infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Of these five patients, three were classified as ‘poor' and two were classified as ‘good'. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Considering response rates at 6 weeks after commencing treatment by pre-treatment VeriStrat classification, disease control was maintained in 84% of the ‘good' group and in 75% of the ‘poor' group, this difference was not statistically significant (Fisher's exact test P-value=0.66) (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>In 26% of the ‘good' group, an objective response was measured compared with a response rate of 25% in the ‘poor' group, the difference not being significant (Fisher's exact test P-value &gt;0.99). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Selection of patients most likely to benefit from specific therapies remains a challenging task in the treatment of NSCLC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>This study demonstrates the capacity of the VeriStrat test to stratify patients with advanced stage NSCLC after treatment with erlotinib and sorafenib in terms of OS and PFS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>VeriStrat was developed from pre-treatment sera of patients treated with gefitinib and subsequently proved able to identify patients likely to have ‘poor' or ‘good' outcomes after EGFR-TKI treatment (Taguchi et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>A retrospective analysis on a subset of patients from the BR.21 trial (Shepherd et al, 2005) showed a significant prolongation of OS in the ‘good' group after treatment with erlotinib, whereas there was no significant benefit for the ‘poor' group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>At the same time, the significant prognostic power of VeriStrat, that is, separation of VeriStrat groups in OS and PFS in the placebo arm, was also demonstrated (Carbone et al, 2010a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>In addition, VeriStrat has been able to stratify outcomes of patients treated with a combination of TKIs and VEGF inhibitors (erlotinib and bevacizumab) (Akerley et al, 2010; Carbone et al, 2010b; Gautschi et al, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>As erlotinib in combination with newer oral VEGF receptor inhibitors such as sorafenib may have clinically relevant antitumour activity (Lind et al, 2010), it is of interest that in this cohort of patients treated with erlotinib and sorafenib, VeriStrat has again demonstrated its potential to identify patients likely to have good and poor outcomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The study presented has several limitations, common to many retrospective analyses of phase II studies and related to the small number of the samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Thus, multivariate analysis that would have given an estimation of the significance of VeriStrat classification in the presence of possible confounding factors was not feasible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Previous analyses in larger retrospective studies have shown that VeriStrat classification remains a significant factor for outcome in advanced NSCLC patients (Amann et al, 2010; Carbone et al, 2010a), although, these studies involved different treatment regimens. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>However, although the size of the study did not allow meaningful multivariate analysis, consistent behaviour was found in adenocarcinoma and ever-smoker subgroups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Despite that, the small group sizes did not give sufficient power to always expect significant differences and these results should be treated with caution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>This study found a significant correlation between VeriStrat classification and histology, a finding that has been observed in previous studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>In larger studies, multivariate analysis was possible and it has been shown that VeriStrat remains a significant predictor even when adjusted for this and other possible confounding factors (Taguchi et al, 2007; Carbone et al, 2010a). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>In the original development study (Taguchi et al, 2007) no statistically significant separation between VeriStrat groups was found in patients treated with surgery or second-line chemotherapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>VeriStrat Poor patients may have an advantage when they are treated with chemotherapy instead of EGFR-TKIs, in contrast to the VeriStrat Good patients who may be likely to benefit from treatment with targeted therapy (Gregorc, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Two ongoing prospective phase III trials are designed to further validate the role of VeriStrat as a test for treatment optimisation in NSCLC; both trials use VeriStrat classification as a stratification factor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>PROSE is a randomised phase III study of second-line erlotinib vs chemotherapy in patients with inoperable NSCLC stratified by VeriStrat classification (Sorlini et al, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The EMPHASIS trial (European Thoracic Oncology Platform) compares treatment of erlotinib vs docetaxel in patients with squamous histology in patients who failed first-line chemotherapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Recently, the potential of VeriStrat for follow-up during treatment was described (Lazzari et al, 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The risk of progression with new lesions in patients that changed classification from ‘good' pre-treatment to ‘poor' near progression when treated with gefitinib was significantly higher than in the rest of the study population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Although further prospective research on this topic is necessary, it illustrates the potential of VeriStrat as a longitudinal marker. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>In our study, serum samples taken after 1 and 3 weeks of treatment were not related to outcome and were much more variable than in the previous study, although 66% of patients did keep or return to their pre-treatment classification 3 weeks after treatment initiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The differences in the stability of the classification are probably related to the duration of the intervals between sample collections: in the former study they were much longer (pre-treatment, after 1 month of therapy, every 2 months thereafter until progression) than in our trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Hence, it is possible that the initiation of therapy has a short-term role in changing the classification of some patients, who then return to their original classification on a longer time scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Also, the previous study involved treatment with gefitinib monotherapy and this study involves dual EGFR/VEGF inhibition, which may be a factor as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The biological meaning of these short-term changes is unclear and needs further investigation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The proteins that make up the VeriStrat proteomic signature have not yet been conclusively identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>A recent publication (Milan et al, 2012) confirmed our earlier (unpublished) results that four out of the eight peaks of the VeriStrat signature contain several forms of SAA1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>However, while numerous studies have shown elevated levels of SAA1 in various malignancies as well as other diseases (Biran et al, 1986; Kokubun et al, 2005; Dowling et al, 2012), attempts to use its direct measurement did not lead to the development of any clinically useful test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>We do not know yet the identity of other proteins constituting the signature, as well as whether proteins identified are causing the effect or are just highly correlated with some other proteins relevant to the mechanism of action of the test (Venet et al, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The differential biological activity of VeriStrat Good and Poor serum was shown in cell line experiments, which have demonstrated that it is possible to decrease the sensitivity of some lung cancer cells to EGFR inhibitors by incubating them in media containing VeriStrat Poor serum (Hunsucker et al, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>We hypothesise that the signature is associated with specific tumour–host interactions, which lead to the differential responses to various treatments between VeriStrat groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>It is interesting to note that several studies (Amann et al, 2010; Chung et al, 2010; Lazzari et al, 2012) and the BR.21 retrospective analysis (Carbone et al, 2010a) have evaluated the relation between VeriStrat classification and EGFR mutations, and no significant correlations have been found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>We think that worse outcome observed in VeriStrat Poor patients treated with sorafenib and erlotinib may result from a complex interaction of tumour cells and tumour microenvironment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, this study demonstrates that VeriStrat, a serum proteomic test based on MALDI-MS of pre-treatment serum samples, can separate chemotherapy-naive advanced NSCLC patients treated with the erlotinib and sorafenib combination in groups with statistically different outcomes in terms of PFS and OS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The results need to be confirmed in a larger trial population. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Sorafenib was provided by Bayer B.V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Division Healthcare, the Netherlands. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>This work is published under the standard license to publish agreement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>After 12 months the work will become freely available and the license terms will switch to a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><notes><p>J Grigorieva, J Roder and H Roder are employees of Biodesix, the company that performs the
VeriStrat proteomic test. The remaining authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>AkerleyWLRichNTEgbertLHarkerWGVan DurenTSmitJHoffmanJM2010Bevacizumab/erlotinib (BEER) as first-line treatment for untreated, advanced non-squamous non-small cell lung cancer (NSNSCLC)J Clin Oncol28(15 Supple18008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib2"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>AmannJMLeeJWRoderHBrahmerJGonzalezASchillerJHCarboneDP2010Genetic and proteomic features associated with survival after treatment with erlotinib in first-line therapy of non-small cell lung cancer in Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group 3503J Thorac Oncol516917820035238 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib3"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>BiranHFriedmanNNeumannLPrasMShainkin-KestenbaumR1986Serum amyloid A (SAA) variations in patients with cancer: correlation with disease activity, stage, primary site, and prognosisJ Clin Pathol397947973734116 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib4"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>CampERSummyJBauerTWLiuWGallickGEEllisLM2005Molecular mechanisms of resistance to therapies targeting the epidermal growth factor receptorClin Cancer Res1139740515671571 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib5"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>CarboneDPDingKRoderHTsaoMShepherdFASeymourL2010aSerum proteomic prediction of outcomes in advanced NSCLC patients treated with erlotinib or placebo in the NCIC CTG BR.21 trialJ Thorac Oncol5(Suppl 1: abstract number 2030. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>2010a </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib6"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>CarboneDPSalmonJSBillheimerDChenHSandlerARoderHRoderJTsypinMHerbstRSTsaoASTranHTDangTP2010bVeriStrat classifier for survival and time to progression in non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) patients treated with erlotinib and bevacizumabLung Cancer6933734020036440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib7"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>ChungCHSeeleyEHRoderHGrigorievaJTsypinMRoderJBurtnessBAArgirisAForastiereAAGilbertJMurphyBCaprioliRMCarboneDPCohenEE2010Detection of tumor epidermal growth factor receptor pathway dependence by serum mass spectrometry in cancer patientsCancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev1935836520086114 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib8"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>DingemansAMde LangenAJvan dBVMarcusJTBackesWHScholtensHTvanTHHoekstraOSPruimJBransBThunnissenFBSmitEFGroenHJ2011First-line erlotinib and bevacizumab in patients with locally advanced and/or metastatic non-small-cell lung cancer: a phase II study including molecular imagingAnn Oncol2255956620702788 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib9"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>DowlingPClarkeCHennessyKTorralbo-LopezBBallotJCrownJKiernanIO'ByrneKJKennedyMJLynchVClynesM2012Analysis of acute-phase proteins, AHSG, C3, CLI, HP and SAA, reveals distinctive expression patterns associated with breast, colorectal and lung cancerInt J Cancer13191192321953030 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib10"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>GautschiODingemansACCroweSRoderHZappaFPlessMBrustcheMPetersSCarboneDSmitEF2012Serum proteomic classifier for patients with advanced non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) treated with erlotinib and bevacizumab in the first line: pooled analysis of phase II trials SAKK 19/05 and NTR528Presented at 3rd European Lung Cancer Conference(Geneva, Switzerland) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib11"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>GregorcV2009Prospective studies with proteomicsPresented at 13th World Conference on Lung Cancer; 4 August 2009; San Francisco </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib12"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>GrigorievaJQuoixEWislezMMoro-SibilotDMerlePGervaisRFriardSRouveauRRoderHRoderJMorinFCadranelJ2011Evaluation of VeriStrat signature in advanced bronchioloalveolar carcinoma (BAC): a Pooled analysis of IFCT-0401 and 0504 trialsPoster Presentation at 14th World Conference on Lung Cancer; 3–7 July 2011; Amsterdam, pp 2.214 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib13"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>HerbstRSAnsariRBustinFFlynnPHartLOttersonGAVlahovicGSohCHO'ConnorPHainsworthJ2011Efficacy of bevacizumab plus erlotinib versus erlotinib alone in advanced non-small-cell lung cancer after failure of standard first-line chemotherapy (BeTa): a double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase 3 trialLancet3771846185421621716 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib14"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>HerbstRSOnnASandlerA2005Angiogenesis and lung cancer: prognostic and therapeutic implicationsJ Clin Oncol233243325615886312 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib15"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>HunsuckerSWGrigorievaJHelfrichBAAllenJBunnPARoderH2011Pretreatment sera from NSCLC patients with different outcomes on EGFR-TKI therapy differentially affects sensitivity of lung cancer cell lines to EGFR-TKIsProceedings of the 102nd Annual Meeting of the American Association for Cancer Research; 2–6 April 2011; Orlando, Florida. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>AACR: Philadelphia (PA), abstract number LB-306 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib16"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>KokubunMImafukuYOkadaMOhguchiYAshikawaTYamadaTYoshidaH2005Serum amyloid A (SAA) concentration varies among rheumatoid arthritis patients estimated by SAA/CRP ratioClin Chim Acta3609710215932751 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib17"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>LazzariCSpreaficoABachiARoderHFlorianiIGaravagliaDCattaneoAGrigorievaJViganoMGSorliniCGhioDTsypinMBulottaABergamaschiLGregorcV2012Changes in Plasma mass-spectral profile in course of treatment of non-small cell lung cancer patients with epidermal growth factor receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitorsJ Thorac Oncol7404821964534 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib18"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>LindJSDingemansAMGroenHJThunnissenFBBekersOHeidemanDAHoneywellRJGiovannettiEPetersGJPostmusPEvan SuylenRJSmitEF2010A multicenter phase II study of erlotinib and sorafenib in chemotherapy-naive patients with advanced non-small cell lung cancerClin Cancer Res163078308720395213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib19"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>MilanELazzariCAnandSFlorianiITorriVSorliniCGregorcVBachiA2012SAA1 is over-expressed in plasma of non small cell lung cancer patients with poor outcome after treatment with epidermal growth factor receptor tyrosine-kinase inhibitorsJ Proteomicse-pub ahead of print 4 July 2012doi:10.1016/j.jprot.2012.06.022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib20"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>SequistLVBellDWLynchTJHaberDA2007Molecular predictors of response to epidermal growth factor receptor antagonists in non-small-cell lung cancerJ Clin Oncol2558759517290067 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib21"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>ShepherdFARodriguesPJCiuleanuTTanEHHirshVThongprasertSCamposDMaoleekoonpirojSSmylieMMartinsRvanKMDediuMFindlayBTuDJohnstonDBezjakAClarkGSantabarbaraPSeymourL2005Erlotinib in previously treated non-small-cell lung cancerN Engl J Med35312313216014882 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib22"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>SorliniCBarniSPetrelliFNovelloSDe MarinisFDe PasTMGrossiFBearzAMencoboniMAietaMCaprioliAAntonelliPZilemboNBachiAFlorianiIRoderHRoderJGrigorievaJLazzariCGregorcV2011PROSE: Randomized proteomic stratified phase III study of second line erlotinib versus chemotherapy in patients with inoperable non–small cell lung cancer (NSCLC)J Clin Oncol29(Supplabstract TPS214 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib23"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>TaguchiFSolomonBGregorcVRoderHGrayRKasaharaKNishioMBrahmerJSpreaficoALudoviniVMassionPPDziadziuszkoRSchillerJGrigorievaJTsypinMHunsuckerSWCaprioliRDuncanMWHirschFRBunnPACarboneDP2007Mass spectrometry to classify non-small-cell lung cancer patients for clinical outcome after treatment with epidermal growth factor receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitors: a multicohort cross-institutional studyJ Natl Cancer Inst9983884617551144 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib24"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>TherassePArbuckSGEisenhauerEAWandersJKaplanRSRubinsteinLVerweijJVanGMvan OosteromATChristianMCGwytherSG2000New guidelines to evaluate the response to treatment in solid tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer, National Cancer Institute of the United States, National Cancer Institute of CanadaJ Natl Cancer Inst9220521610655437 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib25"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>TravisWDBrambillaENoguchiMNicholsonAGGeisingerKRYatabeYBeerDGPowellCARielyGJVan SchilPEGargKAustinJHAsamuraHRuschVWHirschFRScagliottiGMitsudomiTHuberRMIshikawaYJettJSanchez-CespedesMSculierJPTakahashiTTsuboiMVansteenkisteJWistubaIYangPCAberleDBrambillaCFliederDFranklinWGazdarAGouldMHasletonPHendersonDJohnsonBJohnsonDKerrKKuriyamaKLeeJSMillerVAPetersenIRoggliVRosellRSaijoNThunnissenETsaoMYankelewitzD2011International association for the study of lung cancer/american thoracic society/european respiratory society international multidisciplinary classification of lung adenocarcinomaJ Thorac Oncol624428521252716 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib26"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>VenetDDumontJEDetoursV2011Most random gene expression signatures are significantly associated with breast cancer outcomePLoS Comput Biol7e100224022028643 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib27"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>YanagisawaKShyrYXuBJMassionPPLarsenPHWhiteBCRobertsJREdgertonMGonzalezANadafSMooreJHCaprioliRMCarboneDP2003Proteomic patterns of tumour subsets in non-small-cell lung cancerLancet36243343912927430 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Kaplan–Meier plot of OS grouped by VeriStrat classification. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bjc2012470f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Kaplan–Meier plot of PFS according to VeriStrat classification. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bjc2012470f2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Subgroup analyses by VeriStrat classification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>(A) OS for adenocarcinoma patients, (B) PFS for adenocarcinoma patients, (C) OS for ever-smokers and (D) PFS for ever-smokers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bjc2012470f3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Kaplan–Meier plot of PFS (measured relative to original starting point) grouped by weeks (A) 1 and (B) 3 VeriStrat classification. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bjc2012470f4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Clinical characteristics of patients analysed by VeriStrat</title></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t1-fn1"><p>Abbreviation: EGFR=epidermal growth factor receptor.</p></fn><fn id="t1-fn2"><label>a</label><p><italic>P</italic>-value for Fisher's exact test for association between
characteristic categories and VeriStrat classification ‘good' and
‘poor'.</p></fn><fn id="t1-fn3"><label>b</label><p>Never: less than 100 cigarettes in a lifetime.</p></fn><fn id="t1-fn4"><label>c</label><p>Other: broncho-alveolar carcinoma (BAC), squamous and large cell carcinoma.</p></fn><fn id="t1-fn5"><label>d</label><p>‘Not available' classification is not included in analysis.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Univariate analysis of OS and PFS for patients with pre-treatment serum samples
classified as VeriStrat Good or VeriStrat Poor</title></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t2-fn1"><p>Abbreviations: CI=confidence interval; EGFR=epidermal growth factor
receptor; HR=hazard ratios; OS=overall survival;
PFS<bold>=</bold>progression-free survival; PS=performance score.</p></fn><fn id="t2-fn2"><label>a</label><p>Never: less than 100 cigarettes in a lifetime.</p></fn><fn id="t2-fn3"><label>b</label><p>Other: broncho-alveolar carcinoma, squamous and large cell carcinoma.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Response rates</title></caption></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
