
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3923885</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24551231</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-49633</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0089112</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Population Genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genome Evolution</subject><subject>Genome Sequencing</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Bacterial Pathogens</subject><subject>Microbial Evolution</subject><subject>Microbial Mutation</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Bacterial Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthrax</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Veterinary Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Zoonotic Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthrax</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Microevolution during an Anthrax Outbreak Leading to Clonal Heterogeneity and Penicillin Resistance </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Anthrax Microevolution and Penicillin Resistance</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ågren</surname><given-names>Joakim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>Maria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>Björn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Segerman</surname><given-names>Bo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Bacteriology, National Veterinary Institute (SVA), Uppsala, Sweden</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Animal Health and Antimicrobial Strategies, National Veterinary Institute (SVA), Uppsala, Sweden</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biomedical Sciences and Veterinary Public Health, Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences (SLU), Uppsala, Sweden</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Mokrousov</surname><given-names>Igor</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>St. Petersburg Pasteur Institute, Russian Federation</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>bo.segerman@sva.se</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: JÅ BS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: JÅ MF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: JÅ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: JÅ BB BS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e89112</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Ågren et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ågren et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Anthrax is a bacterial disease primarily affecting grazing animals but it can also cause severe disease in humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We have used genomic epidemiology to study microevolution of the bacterium in a confined outbreak in cattle which involved emergence of an antibiotic-resistant phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>At the time of death, the animals contained a heterogeneous population of Single Nucleotide Variants (SNVs), some being clonal but most being subclonal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>We found that independent isolates from the same carcass had similar levels of SNV differences as isolates from different animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Furthermore the relative levels of subclonal populations were different in different locations in the same carcass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The heterogeneity appeared to be derived in part from heterogeneity in the infectious dose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The resistance phenotype was linked to clonal mutations in an anti-sigma factor gene and in one case was preceded by an acquisition of a hypermutator phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>In another animal, small subclonal populations were observed with counteracting mutations that had turned off the resistance genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>In summary, this study shows the importance of accounting for both acquired and inherited heterogeneity when doing high-resolution infection tracing and when estimating the risks associated with penicillin treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by/executed in the framework of the EU-project AniBioThreat (grant agreement: Home/2009/ISEC/AG/191) with the financial support from the Prevention of and Fight against Crime Programme of the European Union, European Commission–Directorate General Home Affairs. This publication reflects the views only of the author, and the European Commission cannot be held responsible for any use which may be made of the information contained therein. This work was also supported by the Swedish Civil Contingencies Agency (MSB). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="7"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>As genomic sequencing has become cheaper, faster, and more accessible, new application areas have opened. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>In the emerging field of genomic epidemiology, ultra high-resolution Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) is used to distinguish different isolates from the same infectious disease outbreak [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The power of genomic sequencing to analyze infectious disease outbreaks has been explored for several pathogens including Bacillus anthracis [2] and in particular for Mycobacterium tuberculosis, it is now even possible to resolve individual transmission events [3], [4], [5], [6], [7], [8], [9], [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>This type of high-resolution analysis of outbreak isolates gives insights into how mutation rates and microevolution reshape the genome during an infection. M. tuberculosis is an extremely slow growing bacterium with a long course of infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Here we show how microevolution in a fast growing bacterium, B. anthracis, from several parallel in vivo cases within the same confined outbreak, independently gave rise to antibiotic resistance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>B. anthracis is a gram positive, spore-forming bacterium that is the causative agent of anthrax. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>This aggressive disease primarily affects grazing animals but many mammals are more or less susceptible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In humans, the most common form is a milder cutaneous infection causing black necrotic ulcers (hence the name anthrax which is Greek for coal). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>However, inhalation of spores can cause a more aggressive pulmonary anthrax form that is associated with high mortality rates [11]. B. anthracis is therefore classified as a risk-group 3 organism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Ingestion of spores can also cause a severe gastrointestinal form of anthrax. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>A new form has also been described referred to as injectional anthrax [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Anthrax spores are very inert. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In their natural life cycle they can lie dormant in the ground for decades [13], until drought followed by heavy rains or other disturbances brings the spores to the surface thereby putting grazing animals at risk of infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Spores from infected cattle carcasses buried several decades ago can put living animals at risk, especially since the exact location of these cattle graves is seldom known. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>An anthrax outbreak often starts from a single source of contamination, rapidly spreads, and then dies out. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>B. anthracis is susceptible to beta-lactam antibiotics but resistance can occur, albeit in rare cases [14] and the risk for encountering resistant strains is still considered very low [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>However, some studies suggest that up to 11% of the isolates may be resistant to beta-lactams [16] but as of 2004, only five cases of resistant isolates from fresh human or animal samples have been reported [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Therefore beta-lactams are still among the antibiotics recommended by WHO and CDC for post-exposure prophylaxis and for treatment of anthrax, albeit susceptibility testing is recommended [18], [19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In Sweden, anthrax outbreaks were frequent in cattle during the first half of the 20th century. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The disease then declined and only sporadic cases have been reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In July-August 2011, an outbreak in cattle occurred in a Swedish nature reserve. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The nature reserve contained grazing cattle over approximately one square km of seasonally flooded land. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>During the spring, several of the ditches had been dredged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>At the end of July, several cows abruptly died of anthrax. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In all, 24 animals died and 3 fetuses were aborted over a period of 4 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Old archive documents showed that an anthrax burial site from the mid-1940s was located in the area although the exact position was not specified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Thus, it seemed likely that the grave had been disturbed which thereby exposed the cows to dormant anthrax spores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>After the anthrax diagnosis had been confirmed, the remaining animals were treated with penicillin, pending vaccination, which halted the disease progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>However, a few animals also died during and after the treatment period and strains isolated from these animals were shown to be penicillin resistant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>We here show how microevolution in several parallel in vivo cases within the same confined outbreak, independently gave rise to antibiotic resistance in B. anthracis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Genomic Epidemiology Analysis of the Outbreak Strains </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>B. anthracis is a monophyletic species with an extraordinarily small genetic variability [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The complete genome sequence of the first diagnosed case (Cow1) was determined using a combination of 454, Illumina, and Sanger reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The chromosome comprised 5.2 Mb and when looking at the 13 canonical SNP (canSNP) positions identified by Van Ert et al. the strain belongs to the B.Br.001/002 lineage [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Only ten ribosomal RNA operons were present as compared to the eleven which are most often found in this species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>However, variation in the number of ribosomal operons has been observed previously [22], [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The nucleotide differences in all remaining isolates were determined using Cow1 as a reference sequence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Six isolates were sequenced, of which two were from untreated cows that had died (Cow1, Cow2), two were from penicillin-treated cows that had died (Cow3Pc, Cow4Pc) and two from fetuses aborted from penicillin-treated cows (Fetus1Pc and Fetus2Pc). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The cows that aborted the fetuses recovered from the disease after treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>All SNVs (mutations, insertions and deletions) in the genome were determined and were concatenated into one sequence per isolate and used to create a dendrogram representing SNV differences (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Assuming each animal had been infected from the same source (the anthrax grave from the 1940s) each isolate had acquired 1–4 SNVs except Cow3Pc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>This isolate had acquired a hypermutator phenotype and had over 60 differences in the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>All mutations found in these six isolates were unique except two mutations in a gene previously implicated in acquisition of penicillin resistance that were present in more than one isolate (described in detail below). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Information about the SNVs can be found in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Thus, the sequence of the theoretical source of infection could be reconstructed representing the central node in the dendrogram (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0089112-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0089112.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The relationship between the mutational profiles of different isolates in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The dendrogram was made by identifying and concatenating all SNPs and indels in the chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The different colors represent different animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>For some animals, two independent isolates were recovered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The “Sediment” isolates were recovered from the presumed source of infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Stars represent two different mutations in the gene rsiP that led to penicillin resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The Cow3Pc isolate showed 54 chromosomal mutations compared to Cow1 (indicated as a zigzag line). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The black bar equals 1 bp difference. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0089112.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>In order to locate the source of infection, water sediment samples were taken every 20 meters along the dredged ditches. B. anthracis was detected at the waterside of a recently produced, 10-meter wide, indentation along one ditch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>After refined sampling, a region of approximately 8 meters was identified from strongly positive PCR signals (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Cow footprints indicated that this area had clearly been a main drinking spot in this part of the pasture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Two soil samples that had shown positive PCR-results were cultivated on modified PLET agar which is a semi-selective medium for B. anthracis [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Two isolates were recovered (Sediment1 and Sediment2) and genome-sequenced using the MiSeq platform (Illumina). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The mutation profiles were identified as for the previous animal isolates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The sediment isolates also carried 1–2 unique SNVs not found in the hypothetical ancestor (Figure 1) and they had no mutations in genes known to regulate antibiotic resistance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Genetic Heterogeneity within the Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The presence of different mutations in the isolates from the two closely located sediment samples suggested that there were heterogeneous SNVs in the source of infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>We had access to an additional, independent isolate from each of the two penicillin-treated, and later aborted, fetuses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Thus, two isolates were obtained from the first fetus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The first isolate (described above) came from the heart sack (Fetus1Pc) and the second from an abdominal aspiration (Fetus1Pc-2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Similarly, two isolates were obtained from the second fetus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The first isolate (described above) came from an abdominal aspiration (Fetus2Pc) and the second from the thorax (Fetus2Pc-2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The sequencing was performed on the MiSeq platform (Illumina) and analyzed as for the previous isolates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The paired isolates, Fetus1Pc and Fetus1Pc-2, both contained the resistance gene mutation and a second unrelated mutation as well as 1 respectively 4 unique mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The second pair of isolates, Fetus2Pc and Fetus2Pc-2 shared the resistance gene mutation but Fetus2Pc contained three additional SNVs (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, the mutation profile of independent isolates from the same animal were different and the number of mutations were in the same range as when comparing isolates from different animals or different isolates from the presumed source of infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>This heterogeneity has profound consequences for the interpretation of the SNV dendrogram. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>These data imply that we are looking at both clonal mutations (present in the whole population) and subclonal ones (present in a subpopulation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The subclonal mutations are of limited phylogenetic value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>We therefore wanted to quantify the penetration of the identified mutations in the sampled population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>We performed amplicon sequencing on regions with the identified mutations using a crude DNA preparation made from the organ from which the isolate came. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The result showed that the relative occurrence of the SNVs we had identified were in the range between fully clonal (∼100%) to below our limits of detection (the sequencing error rate makes it difficult to detect variants below 1%) (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the penetrance of mutations in the animals where two tissues had been sampled were different, suggesting there are spatial variations within the animal. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0089112-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0089112.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Results of the mutation penetrance study. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0089112-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0089112.t001"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The mutation areas were amplified with PCR and the amplicons were sequenced on the Illumina MiSeq. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The background error levels were between 0.01–0.5% and were estimated by quantifying errors in positions surrounding the mutations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Mutation Rate Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Mutations can arise both in vivo and during in vitro cultivation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The in vitro mutational rate of B. anthracis has been estimated to be 5.2×10−10 mutations/bp/generation [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>This implies that limited expansions of colonies in vitro should have a low probability to produce new SNVs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>To confirm this experimentally, we performed a sequential passage study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>A single colony from a blood agar plate was transferred onto three new blood-agar plates and incubated at 37°C overnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Three parallel passage studies were then performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>A single colony from each of the three plates was transferred onto new agar plates and this procedure was repeated for a total of ten passages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>DNA was extracted from these three colonies at passages five and ten and from the starting colony. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>MiSeq (Illumina) sequencing was used to determine the mutation profiles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>We could not detect any mutations in any of the three samples after five passages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>However, after ten passages, two out of the three colonies showed one mutation each at different sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Thus, the frequency of mutation during expansion of a colony (approximately 24 division cycles) was ∼0.1 per 24 generations (8.3×10−10 mutations/bp/generation), which is similar to the previously reported value [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>This strongly indicates that in our experiment, the limited in vitro growth did not have a major impact on the in vivo mutation rate analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>A cow contains 50–85 ml of blood per kg body weight [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>A cow weighing 600 kg would then contain 30–50 liters of blood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>In the late stages of the disease, 10–100 million bacteria per ml blood can be present, corresponding to approximately 38–42 division cycles of exponential growth [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Thus, the in vivo mutation rate seems to be in the range of 1–2 mutations per 38–42 cell divisions (5–10×10−9 mutations/bp/generation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>This is a factor 10–20 times higher than what is observed in vitro for either B. anthracis [25] or other species [8], [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>One explanation could be that the in vivo mutation rate is higher than the in vitro rate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, some of the mutations could have been inherited through heterogeneity in the infection dose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>This heterogeneity may have been accumulated during growth in the animals preceding these ones in the infectious chain and the source may also have been a mixture of spores from several carcasses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>One of the resistant isolates, Cow3Pc, showed a hypermutator phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Among the identified mutations, there was a truncation of mutL, a component of the mismatch reparation system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Ultimately, this isolate is most likely to be associated with loss of fitness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Hypermutator phenotypes during outbreaks have been observed before [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The in vivo mutation rate was elevated approximately 30–60 times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>This error rate implies that mutations arise every division cycle and indeed, we found high-quality, ambiguous nucleotide positions in the genome assembly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>These indicate that heterogeneity also arose during the cultivation of this isolate prior to DNA sequencing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Microevolution of Antibiotic Resistance within the Treated Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>As a routine procedure, the minimum inhibitory concentrations (MIC) of different antibiotics were determined for the isolates recovered from the outbreak. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Beta-lactamase production was also tested (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Isolates from the untreated cows were susceptible to the beta-lactams penicillin and ampicillin and also to tetracycline, ciprofloxacin and chloramphenicol (Cow1 and Cow2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Susceptibility to the other antimicrobials tested cannot be determined because interpretive criteria are lacking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>However, with the exception of trimethoprim, to which B. anthracis is considered intrinsically resistant [15], MICs for gentamicin, kanamycin, streptomycin, erythromycin and clindamycin were low and do not indicate acquired resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Beta-lactamase production was not detected in these isolates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>In contrast, isolates from penicillin-treated cows and isolates from aborted fetuses of treated cows had a penicillin-resistant phenotype with high MICs for penicillin and ampicillin and confirmed beta-lactamase production (Cow3Pc, Cow4Pc, Fetus1Pc and Fetus2Pc). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>MICs for the other antimicrobials tested did not deviate from MICs of the penicillin susceptible isolates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0089112-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0089112.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>MIC (mg/L) and beta-lactamase production in isolates from untreated cows (Cow1 and Cow2), penicillin-treated cows (Cow3Pc and Cow4Pc), and aborted fetuses of penicillin-treated cows (Fetus1Pc and Fetus 2Pc). </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0089112-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0089112.t002"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Na: not available; Pc: penicillin; Am: ampicillin; Cip: ciprofloxacin; Tc: tetracycline; Gm: gentamicin; Km: kanamycin; Sm: streptomycin; Em: erythromycin; Cl: clindamycin; Tm: trimethoprim; Cm: chloramphenicol. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Breakpoints for susceptibility according to CLSI (2010) [33] are given inside brackets when available. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Penicillin resistance can be induced in vitro [30] and all thus far sequenced B. anthracis have two antibiotic resistance genes, bla1 and bla2, that encode a penicillinase and cephalosporinase respectively [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>However, the genes are normally inactive [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>In closely related species, the bla genes are controlled by an extracytoplasmic sigma factor (ECF) called sigP that, in turn, is repressed by an anti-sigma factor rsiP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The sigma factor and its anti-sigma factor are present in B. anthracis as well, but normally do not respond to drug exposure [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Studies of resistant B. anthracis isolates are sparse although there is a report of a mutation in the anti-sigma factor rsiP gene giving rise to a frameshift mutation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>This resulted in a constitutive transcription from the bla genes [31]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The genomic data for the resistant isolates in our study were examined and in two isolates, Fetus1Pc and Cow3Pc, we found the exact same frameshift mutation in the rsiP gene (corresponding to amino acid 6 of 275) as reported by Ross et al. [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>This region is a homopolymer one and may therefore be a hotspot for insertion/deletion events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>For the Cow4Pc and Fetus2Pc isolates, the mutation was located further downstream in the rsiP gene with an inserted G, also causing a frameshift mutation (at a position corresponding to amino acid 163 of 275). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The Fetus1Pc-2 and Fetus2Pc-2 isolates shared the same rsiP gene mutations as their paired isolate from the same animal. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Counteracting Mutations in Penicillin Resistant Strains </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>A study by Ross et al. suggests that constitutive expression of wild type sigP can be detrimental to B. anthracis growth [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>They found an amino acid change in sigP that presumably led to reduced activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>In our resistant strains, the sigP activity seemed to be tolerated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>However, in the case of the isolates from one of the fetuses, we made some peculiar observations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>In one out of two independent DNA preparations from the Fetus1Pc isolate, we found a nonsense mutation in the sigP gene at amino acid position 105 out of 179. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>It turned out that the isolate was impure and approximately 10% of the frozen stock contained this inactivation of sigP (re-isolated as Fetus1Pc-counteracting). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>This subpopulation had lost their resistant phenotype (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, another, unrelated sigP mutation (amino acid position 91 out of 179) was also found in the Fetus1Pc-2 isolate (the second isolate coming from the same animal). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Amplicon sequencing showed that the penetrance of both mutations were below detection levels in the tissue sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The fact that we readily isolated subpopulations with these counteracting mutations, despite apparent low frequencies in the tissue samples, suggests that these subpopulations had an advantage during the isolation process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Transcriptome Analysis of the Resistant and Susceptible Isolates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Given that the resistance mutations were located in an anti-sigma factor, we wanted to measure the effect at a genome-wide transcriptional level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Thus, we performed an RNAseq analysis on a susceptible isolate (Cow2), a resistant one (Cow4Pc), and one that had lost the resistance phenotype by a compensatory mutation (Fetus1Pc-counteracting). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The results showed that the major transcriptional effect was limited to five genes: rsiP anti-sigma factor (BAPAT_2394), sigP sigma factor (BAPAT_2393), beta-lactamase 1(BAPAT_2397), beta-lactamase 2 (BAPAT_3350) and penicillin-binding protein transpeptidase (BAPAT_2396). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>These genes were significantly upregulated 400–800 fold as determined with the Cuffdiff 2 software [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The full table is available as Table S2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The transcriptome mapping for these genes is shown in Figure 2 which shows the massive regulatory effect that the rsiP mutation has on beta-lactamase expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>It also shows that the counteracting mutation in sigP completely abolishes the acquired expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0089112-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0089112.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Transcriptome analysis of genes involved in penicillin resistance. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The three horizontal panels show reads for three samples mapped to the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The upper and middle panels show that the mutation in rsiP led to a profound up-regulation of five genes: A) rsiP anti-sigma factor (BAPAT_2394), sigP sigma factor (BAPAT_2393), beta-lactamase 1 (BAPAT_2397), penicillin-binding protein transpeptidase (BAPAT_2396) and shown in B) the beta-lactamase 2 (BAPAT_3350). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The lower panel shows that the counteracting sigP mutation found in a subclonal population in one animal had quenched expression completely. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0089112.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Our results demonstrate the power of genome analysis during a very confined outbreak situation as well as the limitations involved in resolving individual transmissions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>In the case studied here, it is likely that all isolates passed only once through an animal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Therefore we hoped that we could use mutational profiles to link and compare the outbreak isolates to the environmental isolates from the source of infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>However, our studies showed that each cow had an intra-host heterogeneity at time of death and that different isolates from the same dead animal had a similar number of mutational differences as found when comparing isolates between different dead animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Further, environmental isolates from the presumed source of infection were also heterogeneous and this heterogeneity was likely transmitted, as outlined in detail below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>This study illustrates several pitfalls that must be taken into account when doing high-resolution tracing with NGS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Most importantly, an isolate is only a randomly chosen representative from the population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Several isolates must be studied to judge whether the mutations are truly representative for the whole population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>This has consequences for the interpretations of susceptibility testing, since small subpopulations with resistance mutations may exist during an infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Regional differences in different parts of the host body may also lead to failure to detect a resistant subpopulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Not all of the observed heterogeneity is necessarily a result of mutations during bacterial growth in that animal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Heterogeneity in the actual dose that the disease was acquired from likely contributes to the observed heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>In addition, variations in the size of the infectious dose can also, through founder effects, affect the amount of heterogeneity transferred to the studied case. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Transmission of heterogeneity through the infectious dose may also contribute to cumulative accumulation of higher levels of heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>A model of how transmissions could occur is depicted in Figure 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Another consequence of this inherited heterogeneity is that it may place a limitation on the resolution achievable in outbreak analysis with whole genome sequencing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0089112-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0089112.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>A model for how heterogeneity is transmitted through the infectious dose. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Colors represent different mutation profiles in a subclone (i.e., a subclonal mutation present in a fraction of the population). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Heterogeneity in the preceding animal in the infectious chain may lead to different mutations being transmitted in different animals even though they were infected from the same carcass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>The vertical black boxes represent the soil/sediment and can be seen as a randomizer mixing the spores which will infect next host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>A clonal mutation (i.e., one present in the whole population) is valuable for tracing purposes but may be subclonal in the preceding case. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Thus, it is evident that there is a need to analyze several isolates to determine the clonality of the observed mutations and to fully comprehend the transmission chain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0089112.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Our data imply a scenario in which penicillin resistance was present in a small subclonal population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Under selection pressure during antibiotic treatment, it expanded to become the major clone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>This second expansion in the same animal explains why the resistant isolates seemed to contain more mutations than the susceptible strains (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>If the heterogeneity and bacterial load become high enough, resistance may and probably will arise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>In this studied case, the infectious dose may have been both high (given that so many animals were simultaneously infected), and heterogeneous (as suggested by the observed differences in environmental isolates). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>These two factors may have facilitated the development of in vivo penicillin resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>In humans, milder cases will likely not reach high enough bacterial load for resistance to develop. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>However, our results indicated that the risk for emergence of resistance in cases with systemic involvement may be notable, especially if the source of infection was heterogeneous. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>No experimental animals have been used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Samples were only collected from dead animals in a natural disease outbreak and no animal was killed for the purposes of this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The samples were taken by a veterinarian with the primary purpose to confirm diagnosis so that remaining animals could be treated appropriately. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Procedures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>The isolates were tested for susceptibility to antibiotics by determination of MIC with broth microdilution using VetMIC test-kits (SVA, Uppsala Sweden) according to CLSI [33]. Staphylococcus aureus ATCC 29213 was used as the quality-control strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>In addition, all isolates were tested for beta-lactamase production using the nitrocefin test as described by Hernàndez-Guinàt [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The genome of the reference strain (the first isolated isolate, named Cow1), and the genomes of two isolates that were penicillin resistant, were sequenced using the Roche 454 GS FLX+ (Roche, Basel, Switzerland) and the Illumina HiSeq 2000 platform (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>The sequence reads were assembled in GS Reference Mapper (Roche) using the B. anthracis Ames Ancestor (Genbank Accession NC_007530) as reference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The gaps between contigs were closed using Sanger sequencing to produce one chromosome and two plasmids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The seven following isolates (Sediment1, Sediment2, Cow2, Cow4Pc, Fetus2Pc, Fetus1Pc-2, and Fetus2Pc-2) were prepared using the Nextera XT kit (Illumina) and sequenced on the MiSeq platform (Illumina) using 2×250 bp sequencing settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The reads were mapped with Consed/cross-match to the finished Cow1-genome and Consed was set up to show all highly discrepant positions [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>After manual sorting of the positions, this yielded a list of all significant differences between the Cow1 reference and the other sequenced isolates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The finished genome of isolate Cow1 along with MiSeq-reads for Cow1 and the other nine isolates have been deposited to Genbank under BioProject accession number PRJNA217316. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The accession number for the Cow1 chromosome and plasmids are CP006742, CP006743 and CP006744, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>For the transcriptome sequencing, total RNA was extracted using the Ambion® RiboPure™-Bacteria Kit (Life technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA), rRNA-depleted using the Ribo-Zero™ Magnetic Kit (Gram-Positive Bacteria) (Epicentre Biotechnologies, Madison, WI, USA) and then prepared for MiSeq-sequencing with the ScriptSeq™ v2 RNA-Seq Library Preparation Kit (Epicentre). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>FASTQ-files from the 1×50 bp-run have been deposited to Genbank under BioProject accession number PRJNA217316. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The reads were aligned to the annotated coding regions of the Cow1 isolate by using Bowtie 2 with the ‘very-sensitive’ setting [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Significant transcription-level differences were determined using Cufflinks/Cuffdiff [32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>To investigate the intra-animal heterogeneity using amplicon NGS, primers were designed to amplify the regions containing the determined SNPs/indels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>PCR was performed using these primers and samples used were the original DNA-extractions from the samples analyzed during the outbreak. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Samples were used together with the primers for the mutation that the DNA-sequencing had shown to exist in that sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Different samples from the same animal were also analyzed for all mutations found in isolates from that animal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The reads were aligned to FASTA-files of the ∼2 kb-regions of the mutations using the Bowtie2 aligner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The ratio of a certain mutation was calculated by counting the number of reads supporting the two variants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>For the in vitro mutation-rate experiment, an isolate was cultivated on a horse-blood agar plate overnight at 37°C after which a single colony was spread onto three new plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>After another overnight incubation at 37°C, a single colony from each plate was spread onto a new plate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>This process was repeated 9 times for at total of 10 passages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>From the starting plate and from each of the three plates after passages 5 and 10, a single colony was used to inoculate 5 ml of medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The cultures were then extracted for DNA and the DNA sequenced on the MiSeq (Illumina). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>The mutation rate was estimated by assuming a probability of 0.333 (one out of three) that the bacteria had not acquired a mutation after 10 passages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Thus, if the probability of acquiring a mutation in each passage is x, the probability of not acquiring a mutation is (1–x) and for all 10 passages (1–x)10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Thus, x = 1–0.3331/10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>A colony was estimated to contain approximately 16 million bacteria, corresponding to 24 division cycles of exponential growth [36], [37]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>More detailed procedures regarding, e.g., DNA-extractions, cultivations and DNA-sequencing, can be found in Text S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0089112.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The identified SNVs (SNPs and indels) across the 10 isolates and their coordinates in the Cow1 reference genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0089112.s001.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0089112.s002"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>RNAseq data results from Cuffdiff 2 software complemented with annotations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0089112.s002.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0089112.s003"><label>Text S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Detailed procedures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0089112.s003.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to acknowledge support from Science for Life Laboratory, the national infrastructure SNISS, and Uppmax for providing assistance in massive parallel sequencing and computational infrastructure. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0089112-Kupferschmidt1"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>1 KupferschmidtK (2011) Epidemiology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Outbreak detectives embrace the genome era. Science 333: 1818–1819.21960605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Price1"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>2 PriceEP, SeymourML, SarovichDS, LathamJ, WolkenSR, et al (2012) Molecular Epidemiologic Investigation of an Anthrax Outbreak among Heroin Users, Europe. Emerging infectious diseases 18: 1307–1313.22840345 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-PerezLago1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>3Perez-Lago L, Comas I, Navarro Y, Gonzalez-Candelas F, Herranz M, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>(2013) Whole Genome Sequencing analysis of intrapatient microevolution in Mycobacterium tuberculosis: Potential impact on the inference of tuberculosis transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The Journal of infectious diseases. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-KatoMaeda1"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>4 Kato-MaedaM, HoC, PassarelliB, BanaeiN, GrinsdaleJ, et al (2013) Use of whole genome sequencing to determine the microevolution of Mycobacterium tuberculosis during an outbreak. PloS one 8: e58235.23472164 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Walker1"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>5 WalkerTM, IpCL, HarrellRH, EvansJT, KapataiG, et al (2013) Whole-genome sequencing to delineate Mycobacterium tuberculosis outbreaks: a retrospective observational study. The Lancet Infectious Diseases 13: 137–146.23158499 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Bryant1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>6 BryantJM, SchurchAC, van DeutekomH, HarrisSR, de BeerJL, et al (2013) Inferring patient to patient transmission of Mycobacterium tuberculosis from whole genome sequencing data. BMC infectious diseases 13: 110.23446317 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Roetzer1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>7 RoetzerA, DielR, KohlTA, RuckertC, NubelU, et al (2013) Whole genome sequencing versus traditional genotyping for investigation of a Mycobacterium tuberculosis outbreak: a longitudinal molecular epidemiological study. PLoS medicine 10: e1001387.23424287 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Ford1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>8 FordCB, LinPL, ChaseMR, ShahRR, IartchoukO, et al (2011) Use of whole genome sequencing to estimate the mutation rate of Mycobacterium tuberculosis during latent infection. Nature genetics 43: 482–486.21516081 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Casali1"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>9 CasaliN, NikolayevskyyV, BalabanovaY, IgnatyevaO, KontsevayaI, et al (2012) Microevolution of extensively drug-resistant tuberculosis in Russia. Genome research 22: 735–745.22294518 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Gardy1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>10 GardyJL, JohnstonJC, Ho SuiSJ, CookVJ, ShahL, et al (2011) Whole-genome sequencing and social-network analysis of a tuberculosis outbreak. The New England journal of medicine 364: 730–739.21345102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Mayer1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>11 MayerTA, Bersoff-MatchaS, MurphyC, EarlsJ, HarperS, et al (2001) Clinical presentation of inhalational anthrax following bioterrorism exposure: report of 2 surviving patients. JAMA : the journal of the American Medical Association 286: 2549–2553.11722268 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Ringertz1"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>12 RingertzSH, HoibyEA, JenseniusM, MaehlenJ, CaugantDA, et al (2000) Injectional anthrax in a heroin skin-popper. Lancet 356: 1574–1575.11075776 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Mock1"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>13 MockM, FouetA (2001) Anthrax. Annual review of microbiology 55: 647–671. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Barnes1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>14 BarnesJM (1947) Penicillin and B. anthracis . The Journal of pathology and bacteriology 59: 113–125.20266354 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-HernndezGuint1"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>15Hernàndez-Guinàt E (2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Antibiogram. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Portland USA: ASM Press 389–396. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Cavallo1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>16 CavalloJD, RamisseF, GirardetM, VaissaireJ, MockM, et al (2002) Antibiotic susceptibilities of 96 isolates of Bacillus anthracis isolated in France between 1994 and 2000. Antimicrobial agents and chemotherapy 46: 2307–2309.12069996 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Turnbull1"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>17 TurnbullPC, SirianniNM, LeBronCI, SamaanMN, SuttonFN, et al (2004) MICs of selected antibiotics for Bacillus anthracis, Bacillus cereus, Bacillus thuringiensis, and Bacillus mycoides from a range of clinical and environmental sources as determined by the Etest. Journal of clinical microbiology 42: 3626–3634.15297508 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Stern1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>18Stern EJ, Uhde KB, Shadomy SV, Messonnier N (2008) Conference report on public health and clinical guidelines for anthrax. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Emerging infectious diseases 14. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-WHO1"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>19WHO (2008) Anthrax in humans and animals –4th ed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>I.World Health Organization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>II.Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>III.World Organisation for Animal Health.; Turnbull P, editor: WHO Press, World Health Organization, 20 Avenue Appia, 1211 Geneva 27, Switzerland. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Keim1"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>20 KeimP, GruendikeJM, KlevytskaAM, SchuppJM, ChallacombeJ, et al (2009) The genome and variation of Bacillus anthracis . Molecular aspects of medicine 30: 397–405.19729033 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-VanErt1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>21 Van ErtMN, EasterdayWR, HuynhLY, OkinakaRT, Hugh-JonesME, et al (2007) Global genetic population structure of Bacillus anthracis . PloS one 2: e461.17520020 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Patra1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>22 PatraG, FouetA, VaissaireJ, GuesdonJL, MockM (2002) Variation in rRNA operon number as revealed by ribotyping of Bacillus anthracis strains. Research in microbiology 153: 139–148.12002563 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Chun1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>23 ChunJH, HongKJ, ChaSH, ChoMH, LeeKJ, et al (2012) Complete genome sequence of Bacillus anthracis H9401, an isolate from a Korean patient with anthrax. Journal of bacteriology 194: 4116–4117.22815438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Luna1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>24 LunaVA, GulledgeJ, CannonsAC, AmusoPT (2009) Improvement of a selective media for the isolation of B. anthracis from soils. Journal of microbiological methods 79: 301–306.19808058 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Vogler1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>25 VoglerAJ, BuschJD, Percy-FineS, Tipton-HuntonC, SmithKL, et al (2002) Molecular analysis of rifampin resistance in Bacillus anthracis and Bacillus cereus . Antimicrobial agents and chemotherapy 46: 511–513.11796364 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-StberM1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>26Stöber. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>M G, E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>(1979) Clinical examination of cattle; Rosenberger G, editor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Berlin and Hamburg: Verlag Paul Parey. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Swartz1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>27 SwartzMN (2001) Recognition and management of anthrax–an update. The New England journal of medicine 345: 1621–1626.11704686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Lee1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>28 LeeH, PopodiE, TangH, FosterPL (2012) Rate and molecular spectrum of spontaneous mutations in the bacterium Escherichia coli as determined by whole-genome sequencing. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 109: E2774–2783.22991466 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Koser1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>29 KoserCU, HoldenMT, EllingtonMJ, CartwrightEJ, BrownNM, et al (2012) Rapid whole-genome sequencing for investigation of a neonatal MRSA outbreak. The New England journal of medicine 366: 2267–2275.22693998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Athamna1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>30 AthamnaA, AthamnaM, Abu-RashedN, MedlejB, BastDJ, et al (2004) Selection of Bacillus anthracis isolates resistant to antibiotics. The Journal of antimicrobial chemotherapy 54: 424–428.15205405 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Ross1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>31 RossCL, ThomasonKS, KoehlerTM (2009) An extracytoplasmic function sigma factor controls beta-lactamase gene expression in Bacillus anthracis and other Bacillus cereus group species. Journal of bacteriology 191: 6683–6693.19717606 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Trapnell1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>32 TrapnellC, HendricksonDG, SauvageauM, GoffL, RinnJL, et al (2013) Differential analysis of gene regulation at transcript resolution with RNA-seq. Nature biotechnology 31: 46–53. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-CLSI1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>33CLSI (2010) Methods for antimicrobial dilution and disc susceptibility testing of infrequently isolated or fastidious bacteria; Approved guideline - second edition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>CLSI document A45-A2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Wayne, PA, USA: Clinical and Laboratory Standards Insitute. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Gordon1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>34 GordonD, AbajianC, GreenP (1998) Consed: a graphical tool for sequence finishing. Genome research 8: 195–202.9521923 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Langmead1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>35 LangmeadB, SalzbergSL (2012) Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2. Nature methods 9: 357–359.22388286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Liu1"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>36Liu Y (2007) Electric DNA arrays for determination of pathogenic Bacillus cereus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Stockholm: Royal Institute of Technology. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0089112-Sanchez1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>37 SanchezH, CarrascoB, CozarMC, AlonsoJC (2007)  Bacillus subtilis RecG branch migration translocase is required for DNA repair and chromosomal segregation. Molecular microbiology 65: 920–935.17640277 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
