
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Biomed Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Biomed Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JBR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Biomedical Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1674-8301</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Editorial Department of Journal of Biomedical Research</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3596701</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jbr-25-02-100</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1674-8301(11)60013-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Comparative domain modeling of human EGF-like module EMR2 and study of interaction of the fourth domain of EGF with chondroitin 4-sulphate☆ </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rani</surname><given-names>Mukta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">△</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dikhit</surname><given-names>Manas R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>Ganesh C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">△</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>Pradeep</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><addr-line>Biomedical Informatics Division, Rajendra Memorial Research Institute of Medical Sciences, Agam Kuan, Patna-800007, India</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn id="fn1" fn-type="equal"><label>△</label><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>These authors contributed equally to this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><corresp id="cor1">*Corresponding author: Ganesh C Sahoo, Ph.D, Biomedical Informatics Division, Rajendra Memorial Research Institute of Medical Sciences, Agam Kuan, Patna-800007, India. Tel/Fax: <fax>0612-2631565/0612-2634379</fax>; Email addresses: <email>ganeshiitkgp@gmail.com</email>.</corresp><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The authors reported no conflict of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>2</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>4</day><month>3</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2011 by the Journal of Biomedical Research. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>EMR2 is an EGF-like module containing mucin-like hormone receptor-2 precursor, a G-protein coupled receptor (G-PCR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Mutation in EMR2 causes complicated disorders like polycystic kidney disease (PKD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The structure of EMR2 shows that the fifth domain is comprised of EGF-TM7 helices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Functional assignment of EMR2 by support vector machine (SVM) revealed that along with transporter activity, several novel functions are predicted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>A twenty amino acid sequence “MGGRVFLVFLAFCVWLTLPG” acts as the signal peptide responsible for posttranslational transport. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Eight amino acids are involved in N-glycosylation sites and two cleavage sites are Leu517 and Ser518 in EMR2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The residue Arg241 is responsible for interaction with glycosaminoglycan and chondroitin sulfate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>On the basis of structure, function and ligand binding sites, competitive EMR2 inhibitors designed may decrease the rate of human diseases like Usher's syndrome, bilateral frontoparietal polymicrogyria and PKD. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>EMR2</kwd><kwd>G-protein coupled receptor</kwd><kwd>transmembrane</kwd><kwd>homology modeling</kwd><kwd>EGF-TM7</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>G protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs) belong to the family of integral-membrane proteins (IMPs) that transduce external signals through the cell membrane[1] to regulatory G-proteins, which in turn trigger a wide range of biological events[2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>GPCRs are sensory proteins and important receivers of different external stimuli such as hormones, neurotransmitters, neuromodulators, odours and light. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>GPCRs represent the largest family of cell-surface receptor molecules that are involved in signal transmission, accounting for &gt;2% of the cellular proteins encoded by the human genome and they are the targets for 50% of all recently launched drugs[3],[4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>GPCRs are characterized by the presence of highly conserved molecular architecture encoding seven transmembrane (TM) hydrophobic regions linked by three extracellular loops that alternate with three intracellular loops as confirmed by analysis of the crystal structure of rhodopsin[5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The extracellular N-terminus is glycosylated, and the cytoplasmic C-terminus is generally phosphorylated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The GPCR family comprises the largest family of cell-surface receptors, which can sense information encoded by diverse external stimuli and translate the encoded information into readable signals for the cell[6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>EMR2 is an epidermal growth factor (EGF)-like module containing mucin-like hormone receptor-2 precursor and a cell surface protein receptor (GPCR) restricted to leukocytes and/or smooth muscle cells in humans[7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>These receptors are characterized by an unique hybrid structure consisting of tandem repeats of EGF-like modules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>It is coupled to the N-terminal family B (secretin receptor) GPCR related to the seven- transmembrane (TM7) receptor domains by a glycosylated stalk region[8],[9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>EGF-like module EMR2 receptors is predominately expressed in cells of the immune system and binds to ligands such as CD312. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The EMR2 genes are predominantly expressed on dendritic cells, monocytes and macrophages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The EGF-TM7 molecules belong to a large protein family known as the long N-terminal of group B transmemberane 7 (LNB-TM7) or B2 subgroup of class B GPCRs with large extracellular N-terminal domains[8]–[9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>All LNB-TM7 receptors that possess large extracellular domains consisting of various protein modules are implicated in protein-protein interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Along with adhesion and signaling function, these molecules also participate in the interaction of the extracellular region with other cell surfaces or extracellular matrix proteins through the transmembrane domain[10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>LNB-TM7 receptors have different extracellular structural domains that are separated from the TM7 region by an extended spacer region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>A subgroup of the LNB-TM7 receptors is the EGF-TM7 family[11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Genomic mapping analysis has suggested a possible EGF-TM7 gene family on the human chromosome 19p13.1 region and possesses similar exon-intron organizations[11] or the LNB-TM7 receptors[8] that contain a large N-terminal cell adhesion-like extracellular domain coupled to a secretin receptor-like TM7 domain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>These EGF domains are coupled to TM7 via an extended spacer region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>As a result of alternate RNA splicing, receptor isoforms possessing variable numbers of EGF domains are expressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The EGF domains of EGF-TM7 receptors have been shown to mediate binding to cellular ligands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The domain 4 of EMR2 interacts with glycosaminoglycan (GAG) and chondroitin sulfate[7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Ligand specificity for chondroitin sulfate is shared by EMR2, whose EGF domain region is highly similar to that of CD97. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Only 6 out of 236 amino acids differ within the five EGF domains[9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>To date, four isoforms have been reported for EMR2, containing two (EGF1, 2), three (EGF1, 2, 5), four (EGF1, 2, 3, 5), or five (EGF1, 2, 3, 4, 5) EGF domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Antibody-blocking studies subsequently revealed that the fourth domain of EGF-like module constitutes the major ligand-binding site[7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The ligand for the largest isoform of EMR2 has recently been identified as chrondroitin sulphate, which binds to the EGF-like module of EMR2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>It has been shown to interact with chondroitin sulfate and GAG in an isoform-specific manner[10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The human-restricted adhesion-GPCR, EMR2, regulates neutrophil responses by potentiating the effects of a number of proinflammatory mediators and it has been shown that the transmembrane region is critical for adhesion-GPCR function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>On neutrophil activation, EMR2 is rapidly translocated to membrane ruffles and the leading edge of the cell[11] and in monocytes and macrophages, EMR2 can be specifically up-regulated by lipopolysaccharides (LPS) and IL-10 via an IL-10-mediated pathway[10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>EMR2 is a myeloid cell-restricted member of the EGF-TM7 family that is closely related to CD97[8]–[9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The EGF-like domains of the full-length EMR2 protein share 97.5% sequence identity with CD97. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Similar to CD97, distinct EMR2 protein isoforms consisting of different numbers of the EGF-like domains have been documented[9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Tissue specificity of EMR2 expression is highest in peripheral blood leukocytes, followed by spleen and lymph nodes, with intermediate to low levels in the thymus, bone marrow, fetal liver, placenta and lung. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The extracellular domain of EGF-TM7 receptor consists of tandem repeats of EGF-like modules followed by a Ser/Thr-rich stalk and a GPS motif[8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The GPS motif is primarily found in members of class B2 GPCRs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>These include the human polycystic kidney disease protein (PKD)-1[12]–[13], suREJ3, a channel-like 11-span transmembrane protein[14] and hPKDREJ, the human homologue of suREJ3[15], suggesting that the GPS motif and its associated proteolytic cleavage activity are widely used by cell surface receptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Although the functional significance of the GPS motif-associated proteolysis remains elusive, the presence of the highly conserved GPS motif in such a diverse array of receptors is suggestive of a common role in receptor function or regulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Mutations within this region of adhesion-GPCRs occur in a number of human diseases, including Usher's syndrome, bilateral frontoparietal polymicrogyria and PKD[16]–[18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>In PKD, cystic tubules are unable to perform this function properly, resulting in fluid retention, high blood pressure and kidney failure requiring dialysis or transplantation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>In this study, we investigated the structure and protein interactions of EMR2 using bioinformatics tools. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Structural modeling </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The sequence of human EMR2 protein (823 amino acids) was retrieved from NCBI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Multiple alignments of the related sequences were performed using the Clustal W program accessible through the European Bioinformatics Institute (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/clustalw2/index.html">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/clustalw2/index.html</ext-link>)[19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The tertiary structures of different domains of EMR2 were modeled on the basis of different template structures from MODELLER 9v6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Structure validation was performed by using 3-D molecular modeling tool Verify protein (DOPE score) of Discovery Studio v2.1 (Accelrys). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Prediction of different domains of EMR2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Determination of various domains in EMR2 was carried out by using GPCRDB[20], DOMAC Protein Domain Prediction program[21] and SCRATCH program[22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The GPCRDB is a database that collects molecular class-specific information system on GPCRs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>DOMAC server is an accurate protein domain prediction server combining both template-based and ab initio methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>SCRATCH is a server for predicting protein tertiary structures that includes predictors for secondary structure, domains, disulfide bridges, single mutation stability and tertiary structure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Transmembrane region prediction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Different servers i.e. TMHMM, SOSUI, HMMTOP, TMpred, Das and TopPred servers were accessed to validate the TM region of EMR2[23]–[28]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Protein function assignment of EMR2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>We employed SVMProt server with support vector machine (SVM) learning techniques, which classifies a protein into functional families from its primary sequences[29], to identify novel functions of EMR2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Novel protein function assignments of different proteins of SARS virus, Japanese encephalitis virus and lipophosphoglycan 2 (LPG2) protein of different strains of Leishmania have already been reported using the technique[30]–[32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Ligand binding site prediction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Pocket-Finder or Q-site finder is a molecule-binding site prediction server based on Ligsite algorithm[33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>It works by scanning a probe radius 1.6A° along all gridlines of grid resolution 0.9A° surrounding the protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The probe also scans cubic diagonals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Grid points are defined to be part of a site when the probe is within range of protein atoms followed by free space followed by protein atoms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Grid points are only retained if they are defined to be part of a site at least five times[33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Eukaryotic Linear Motif (ELM) server </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Functional sites in eukaryotic proteins which fit the description “linear motif” are specified as patterns using regular expression rules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>ELM server provides core functionality including filtering by cell compartment, phylogeny, globular domain class (using the SMART/Pfam databases) and structure[34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Individual functions assigned to different sequence segments are combined to create a complex function for the whole protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Protein-ligand interaction study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Protein-ligand interaction, i.e. docking, was studied by LigandFit/LigandScore[35] in DS Modeling 2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Interaction study with some other proteins like KMP-11 in Leishmania of six different strains has been reported[36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>LigandFit is an automated tool for docking/scoring study that includes the following protocols: 1) define binding site (ligand-based or cavity-based); 2) generate ligand conformations (Monte Carlo trials); 3) dock each conformation (align shapes of ligand to binding site; 24 orientations of ligand, rigid body energy minimization with grid-based energy function); 4) save the top docked structures (diverse poses); 5) apply scoring function(s) to each docked structure for the best binding mode (binding affinity prediction). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Normal mode analysis of EMR2 3-D structure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Normal mode analysis was conducted to analyze the intrinsic motions of the EMR2 modeled structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The elNémo online server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://igs-server.cnrs-mrs.fr/elnemo/index.html">http://igs-server.cnrs-mrs.fr/elnemo/index.html</ext-link>)[38] was employed in our study for this purpose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>This server is a part of the Elastic Network Model, which provides a fast simple tool to compute, visualize and analyze low-frequency normal modes of biological macromolecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The structural model of EMR2 in dot pdb (.pdb) format was submitted for normal mode analysis while another 3-D structure complex was submitted as a reference of the desired conformational change. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The key parameters which were used in computation included: DQMIN=-100, DQMAX=100, DQSTEP=20, and NRBL = “auto”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>A total of 100 normal modes with the lowest frequencies were requested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The normal mode theory is based on the harmonic approximation of the potential energy function around a minimum energy conformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>This approximation allows an analytical solution of the motion by diagonalizing the Hessian matrix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Hessian matrices are used in large-scale optimization problems within Newton-type methods because they are the coefficient of the quadratic term of a local Taylor expansion of a function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>That is:  where J is the Jacobian matrix, which is a vector (the gradient) for scalar-valued functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The full Hessian matrix can be difficult to compute in practice; in such situations, quasi-Newton algorithms have been developed that use approximations to the Hessian. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The most well-known quasi-Newton algorithm is the BFGS algorithm[39],[40]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Different domains of EMR2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Five EGF calcium binding domains are predicted in the sequence of EGF-like module EMR2 by using three different servers i.e. GPCRDB, DOMAC program and SCRATCH program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The first domain of EMR2 consists of 68 amino acid residues (1-68); similarly, the second domain consists of 69-120 residues, the third domain lies in between amino acids 121-238 and the fourth and fifth domains stretch out in amino acids 239-318 and 319-823, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The GPCR proteolytic sites (GPS) occur in amino acid residues 479-529. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The folding pattern of this protein consists of double-stranded β-sheet followed by a loop to a C-terminal short double-stranded sheet. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Modeler program constructed the structural models of full length EMR2 considering different templates i.e. EGF domain 1, 2, and 5 of human EMR2, a 7-TM immune system molecule in complex with barium (pdb id: 2BOU) and EGF domain 1, 2, and 5 of human EMR2, a 7-TM immune system molecule in complex with calcium (pdb id: 2BO2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The first domain 3-D structure was constructed by using three different templates i.e. EGF domain 1, 2, and 5 of human EMR2 with barium (pdb id: 2BO2), EGF-like module of human C1R (pdb id: 1APQ) and fibrillin-1CB EGF protein (pdb id: 1LMJ_A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The verify protein (DS, Accelrys, USA) score of the 1st domain structure of EMR2 is 15.97 and the 2nd domain is 15.99. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>No invalid region was found in the model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the three dimensional model of the 3rd domain was modeled with templates named human notch-1 ligand binding protein (pdb id: 1TOZ_A) and EGF domain 1, 2, and 5 of human EMR2, a 7-TM immune system molecule (pdb id: 2BOU) and showed high DOPE score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The three dimensional structure of the 4th domain of EGF-like module EMR2 showed good DOPE score i.e. 35.88. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Dali server[38] was accessed to compare template structures of this domain i.e. the crystal structure of phosphoribosyl-ATP pyrophosphatase (pdb id: 1YXB) and four helix bundles (pdb id: 1JMO). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The three dimensional structure of the 5th domain of EMR2 was modeled by using structural coordinates of six PDB structures i.e. hemochromatosis protein HFE complexed with transferin (pdb id: 1DE4), bovine rhodopsin (pdb id: 1U19), prostate-specific membrane antigen A (pdb id: 1Z8L), bovine rhodopsin (pdb id: 1L9H), peroxisomal acyl-coA oxidase-II (pdb id: 1IS2), and adaptor protein 2 clathrin adaptor core (pdb id: 1GW5) with a DOPE score of 124.83. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The modeled structure of five different domains of EMR2 is shown in Fig. 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>RMSD values of different models were found to be within limits. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="jbr-25-02-100-g002" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Ribbon representation of the modeled EMR2 protein of the entire five different domains. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The image was created using Discovery studio (Accelrys) software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>A: Domain 1 consists of an antiparallel β-sheet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>B: Domain 2 consists of 1 antiparallel β-sheet and 2 small helices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>C: Domain 3 consists of 2 antiparallel β-strands, and 3 small helices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>D: Domain 4 consists of only 2 α-helices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>E: Domain 5 consists of 7 transmembrane helices and 3 parallel β-strands and 11 small α-helices. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jbr-25-02-100-g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>To validate the models, we further evaluated three dimensional structures of EGF-like module EMR2 with Ramachandran plot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Stereo-chemical evaluation of backbone Psi(Ψ) and Phi (Φ) dihedral angles of five modeled EMR2 domains was revealed in different percentages, i.e. 72%-90%, 3%-31% and 2%-14% residues fell within the most favored regions, additionally allowed regions and generously allowed regions and few residues are in disallowed region of Ramachandran plot, respectively (supplementary Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The model has a normal distribution of residue types over the inside and the outside of the protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Five structural domains (1-5; NH2 to COOH terminus) are found to be present in EMR2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The first domain is composed of 68 amino acids and is hydrophilic in nature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Two anti-parallel β-sheet structures have been found in the first domain of EMR2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The second domain is comprised of 51 amino acid residues, and contains one anti-parallel β- sheet and two small helical regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The third domain of EMR2 is comprised of 117 amino acids and consists of two anti-parallel β-sheets and three small helical regions are shown in Fig. 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The fourth domain contains 79 amino acids residues, which contribute to the helix-loop-helix domain, and it consists of only two α-helices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The C-terminal domain, i.e. the fifth domain of EMR2, consists of 508 amino acid residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>It consists of three parallel β-sheets, seven transmembrane helices (TMHs) and 11 small α-helices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Domain-wise structural configurations of EMR2 of all five different domains are shown in Fig. 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="jbr-25-02-100-g003" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Schematic representation of modeled 3-D structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>It shows the five EGF calcium binding domains present in EGF-like module EMR2. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Arrows represent helices in all domains in different colors and cylindrical represents the helix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Seven transmembrane helices are predicted in the fifth domain of EMR2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The amino acid residues vary in the first domain (1-68), second (69-120), third (121-238), fourth (239-318) and fifth domain (319-823). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>There are six extracellular loops that connect the seven transmembrane helices. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jbr-25-02-100-g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Sequence analysis of EMR2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Amino acid sequence of EMR2 (NCBI, gi108935835) was downloaded and aligned with six different genes (gi23397681, gi23397685, gi23397687, gi23397689, gi23397693 and gi23397691), which showed close identity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>From the 1st to 118th, 261st to 398th and from 410th to 823rd amino acids of EGF-like module containing mucin-like, and hormone receptor-like sequence 2 isoforms (of Homo sapiens) are identical to six other EMR2 sequences (gene id: gi23397681, gi23397685, gi23397687, gi23397689, gi23397693 and gi23397691). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Non-synonymous mutations are deleterious in nature[42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Various types of mutations have been observed to occur in this human protein, among which deletion or insertion at many regions of this EMR2 like protein has been detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Two amino acids “DV”, which are likely to be present at position 119-120, are absent in the strain (gi23397687). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>These two amino acids may be insertion type mutations for other related strains, but for this strain it is a deletion type mutation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Transmembrane helices of EMR2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Different transmembrane prediction programs i.e. DAS, HMMTOP, TMHMM, TMpred, TopPred and SOSUI (Table 1) predicted the position and number of transmembrane regions in EMR2 amino acid sequence (Fig. 2E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The comparative analyses of four transmembrane prediction programs i.e. DAS, HMMTOP, TMHMM and TMpred showed that the 536th-561st amino acids (538th-560th in few cases) are responsible for the formation of the first transmembrane region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the 571st-591st and 600th-626th amino acids of the fifth domain participate in formation of the second and third transmembrane regions, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Other amino acids 646-649, 688-710, 730-756 and 758-782 are involved in constructing the 4th, 5th, 6th, and 7th transmembrane helices of EMR2, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="jbr-25-02-100-t01" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Predicted locations of the transmembrane helices (TMs) on EGF like EMR2 protein in human </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>a predicted number of TMs; b Numbers in brackets are the lengths of TMs </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The disulfide bond formation in different domains of EMR2 (Dipro/ SCRATCH protein predictor program) is shown in supplementary Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The amino acids of the first domain are found to be involved in formation of disulfide bond at three different sites, 29-39, 33-45 and 47-65, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The amino acids of the second domain of EMR2 are also involved in three disulfide bonds in regions 71-85, 79-94 and 96-117, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Seven disulfide bond formation sites are found in the third domain of EMR2 and are found in residues 123-136, 130-145, 147-161, 167-180, 174-189, 191-210 and 216-229. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Only one disulfide bond on residues 240-259 is present in the 4th domain of EMR2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The last domain of EMR2 has five disulfide bonds i.e. 482-500, 492-514, 561-599, 676-693 and 743-746, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Posttranslational modification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Posttranslational modifications are important for future localization or function of the protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Various posttranslational modification sites have been identified in the EGF-like module protein EMR2 (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>A signal peptide is found in the first twenty amino acids (amino acid sequence: MGGRVFLVFLAFCVWLTLPG) in EMR2 as predicted from SOSUI signal server. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>In the 2nd and 3rd domains, EGF has posttranslational ASX hydroxylation at the conserved aspartate or asparagine residues, forming erythro-β-hydroxyaspartic acid or erythro-β-hydroxyasparagine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>In the fifth domain, APCC-binding destruction motifs are present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The BRCT domain of the fourth domain is associated with DNA damage response and recognizes and binds to specific phosphorylated serine sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>PCSK cleavage site motif is present in the fifth domain of EMR2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>A cyclin recognition motif that interacts with cyclin has also been detected in domain 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>FHA phosphopeptide ligand motif 1 is present in domain 5, and motif 2 is present in domain 1, 4 and 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The FHA domain is a signal transduction module, which recognizes phosphothreonine-containing peptides on the ligand proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>In domain 1, 4 and 5, ww ligand motifs are predicted that are implicated in protein-protein interactions mediated by WW domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Casein kinase (CK1) phosphorylation motifs (recognized by CK1 and CK2 for Ser/Thr phosphorylation) are present in domain 1, 4 and 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>In domain 1, 4 and 5, GSK3 phosphorylation site is present and in domain 5, and 16 different patterns of this motif are present and shown in Fig. 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>GSK3 comprised of two highly related proteins (GSK3-α and GSK3-β) phosphorylates a wide variety of target proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>N-glycosylation, a posttranslational process involving the transfer of an oligosaccharide chain to asparagine residue in the protein, is found in domain 1, 4 and 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>MAPK phosphorylation, which pro-directs kinases such as P38 MAP kinase to phosphorylate Ser/Thr in various signal transduction pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Domain 4 and 5 contain the phosphorylation motifs of phosphoinositide-3-OH-kinase related kinases (PI3KKs), which are atypical protein kinases exclusive to eukaryotes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="jbr-25-02-100-g004" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>ELM server graph. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The different motifs are present in five different domains of EMR2 predicted through ELM server. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jbr-25-02-100-g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Ligand binding sites of EMR2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The potential ligand binding sites of the five domains of EMR2 have been found by Pocket Finder program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>A total of ten possible binding sites were obtained in the third, fourth and fifth domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Different ligand binding sites of the five different domains of EMR2 are shown in supplementary Fig. 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The frequently involved amino acid residues in forming the pocket are Try8, Thr27, Phe45, Cys49, His56, Thr64, Ile65, Leu76, Gln77, Thr113, Ser230, Ser232, Phe243, Val273, Tyr295, Thr300, Try301, Ala313, Ala341, Val377, Leu399, Thr420, Phe424, Ile425, Ile434, Ile450, Gln455, Try477, His491 and Thr501. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="jbr-25-02-100-t02" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Comparative analysis of EMR2 functional assignment of all the five different domains </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3f"><title><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Functional assignment of EMR2 by SVM </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Different unknown and hidden functions of a protein (EMR2) were predicted using machine learning technique like a statistical SVM based classifier, the SVMProt (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Different domains of EMR2 were assigned to metal binding functional family by SVMProt, which correlates to previously published data that EMR2-chondroitin sulfate interaction is Ca2+ and sulphate ion-dependent, and results in cell attachment[7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Comparative analyses have shown that different domains of EMR2 belong to the GPCR family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The 2nd and 4th domains are probably responsible for ATP-binding cassette (ABC) function. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="jbr-25-02-100-t03" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The 10 normal modes of EMR2 predicted by normal mode analysis method by the elNémo server </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>a: Only the 10 normal modes with lowest frequencies are displayed here. b: The level of collectivity indicates the percentage of residues that are involved in a certain normal mode. c: The level of overlap measures the similarity between a desired conformational change and that of a certain normal mode. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3g"><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>N-glycosylation site in EMR2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The three dimensional model of EMR2 shows eight potential N-glycosylation sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The eight amino acid residues involved in N-glycosylation sites are N41, N111, N206, N298, N347, N354, N456 and N460 (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Two cleavage sites were found in EMR2 at residues Leu517 and Ser518[43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The GPCR proteolytic site starts with Lys479 and ends with Val529, and the GPCR proteolytic site of EMR2 involves 30 amino acids (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="jbr-25-02-100-g005" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Different motifs showing N-glycosylation, cleavage and GPCR proteolytic sites. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>In human EMR2, a 7-TM immune system molecule, are shown A: N-glycosylation sites: 8 glycosylation sites are indicated by black arrows and highlighted in pink are N41, N111, N206, N298, N347, N354, N456 and N460; B: Cleavage sites (CS1 and CS2): two cleavage sites at L517 and S518 are highlighted by green and blue, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>C: GPCR proteolytic sites (GPS): the GPS site starts with K479 and ends with V529 and in total includes 50 amino acids (from the start and end of the region) and is shown in red. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jbr-25-02-100-g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3h"><title><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Interaction of the 4th domain of EMR2 with chondroitin 4-sulfate </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>The fourth EGF domain of CD312 interacts with GAG chondroitin 4-sulphate where the ligand is specifically found on B cells from peripheral blood, on activated lymphocytes and myeloid cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The helix-loop-helix domain of EMR2 interacts with the GAG; chondroitin sulfate is one of the proteoglycans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>EMR2 does not interact with the ligand decay accelerating factor (CD55) for complement, unlike the related CD97 antigen, and indicates that these very closely related proteins likely have non-redundant functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>The EMR2 gene produces multiple transcripts encoding distinct isoforms[9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The chondroitin chains are present near the junctions between both of the NH2 and COOH-terminal globular domains and the central region[44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>In addition, only one potential N-glycosylation site in EMR2 is present in these regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>A modeled 3-D structure of the fourth domain of EMR2 was docked with a single strand of chondroitin 4-sulphate where the molecular mass is 17 kDa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The 3-D structure of chondroitin 4- sulphate was drawn in Chemsketch as *.mol file and converted into *.pdb format. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The structure also identifies the specific interaction sites between EMR2 and C4-S molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the crystal structure of human cathepsin K interacts with chondroitin 4-sulphate has already been reported[45]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>It is known from the literature that the fourth domain of EMR2 has three active sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Chondroitin 4-sulphate molecules were docked in a groove of EMR2 that is on the active site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Higher ligand protein interaction has been detected up to 81.147 dock score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Ten different binding conformations have been observed during docking study in DS (Accelrys). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The groove contains several positively charged side chains that interact directly with the negatively charged groups on chondroitin 4-sulphate (Fig. 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Different interactions between chondroitin 4-sulphate hexasaccharide and EMR2 are shown in Fig. 5A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Frequent H-bond formation has also been detected and the amino acids involved are Ser1, Arg3, Arg7, Ser29, Asp47, Gln50, Gly53, Arg54, Tyr56, Lys57, Pro58 and Asn62. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Arg3 (the exact location in the whole sequence is Arg241) provides a hydrogen-bonded ion-pair interaction to the 4-sulfate group of O9, O10, O11 and O14 in ten different conformations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The next residue on the helical turn is Ser1 (the exact location in the whole sequence is Ser239) that interacts with O3, O8, O9, O12, and O11 in ten different conformations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>In case of chondroitin sulphate, there are five amino acid residues Ser29, Gln50, Arg54, Pro58 and Asn62; all have direct interactions with groups on the hexasaccharide of chondroitin 4- sulphate, either via the side chains or the main chain peptide bonds of all ten different conformations (Fig. 5A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="jbr-25-02-100-g006" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Interaction of the 4th domain of EMR2 with chondroitin 4-sulfate. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>A: A screenshot from interaction with chondroitin 4-sulfate of domain 4 of EMR2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Ten different binding poses of chondroitin 4-sulfate are shown with the interaction or dock score between 31.607 and 81.147. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The protein-ligand interaction is done through ligand receptor interaction protocol i.e. Ligandfit of Discovery Studio 2.1 (Accelrys). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>It shows hydrogen-bonded ion-pair interaction formed between different atoms of the ligand and amino acids of EMR2 (Ser1, Arg3, Ser29, Asp47, Gln50, Gly53, Arg54, Tyr56, Lys57, Pro58, and Asn62). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>B: A surface representation of EMR2 protein showing how the molecule is divided into a positively-charged region rich in basic residues (blue) and a negatively charged region that has negatively-charged acidic groups (Asp and Glu). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The negatively charged C4-S hexasaccharide (green color) is electrostatically attracted to the positively charged region of EMR2 from the active site. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jbr-25-02-100-g005"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>It is well known that hydrogen bond plays an important role for the structure and function of biological molecules[45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Five important amino acids Ser29, Arg3, Arg5, Gly53 and Asn62 (the exact locations are. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Ser239, Arg241, Arg243, Gln292, and Asn301) are responsible for interaction with chondroitin 4-sulfate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Competitive inhibition of EMR2 by analogues of chondroitin 4-sulfate could help in lessening genetic disease burden, e.g. Usher's syndrome, bilateral frontoparietal polymicrogyria, and PKD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3i"><title><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Normal mode analysis of EMR2 3-D structure </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Normal Mode Analysis (NMA) program was run to know the native motions (vibrational and thermal properties) of the EMR2 modeled structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Essential features of the top ten low-frequency normal modes, including its frequency, amplitude, collectivity of atom movements, and the overlap with observed conformational changes are summarized in Table 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The two lowest-frequency normal modes (mode 7 and 8 in Table 3) are illustrated in Fig. 6, one feature showing bending of the N-terminal domain towards the transmembrane domain; the other feature showing rotation of the N-terminal domain on the top of the transmembrane domain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="jbr-25-02-100-g007" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>elNémo models. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The two normal modes (i.e., mode 7 and 8) of EMR2 with the lowest frequencies (Left: bending of the N-terminal domain toward the transmembrane domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Right: rotation of the N-terminal domain on the top of the transmembrane domain). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jbr-25-02-100-g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>On the basis of modeled structure, predicted binding sites and functions of EMR2, high throughput screening of various compounds may be carried out to find appropriate leads against different diseases, which can further be screened in vitro and in vivo. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>We are thankful to Dr. Meera Singh of ICMR for helping us during establishment of our division. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>We acknowledge Dr. Sindhu Prava Rana, Chanda Jha and Md. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Yousuf Ansari for helping us in preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn id="fn2" fn-type="financial-disclosure"><label>☆</label><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>This study was supported by the project “Establishment of Biomedical Informatics Center at RMRIRMS, Patan” by ICMR (Govt. of India), New Delhi. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>Reference</title><ref id="b1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>1LomizeALPogozhevaIDMosbergHI Structural organization of G-protein-coupled receptors J Comput Aided Mol Des 1999 13 325 53 10425600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>2 FotiadisDJastrzebskaBPhilippsenAMullerDJPalczewskiKEngelA Structure of the rhodopsin dimer: a working model for G-protein-coupled receptors Struct Biol 2006 16 252 9  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>3 RobertTDGutkindJS G-protein-coupled receptors and cancer Nature 2007 7 79 93  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>4 KlabundeTHesslerG Drug design strategies for targeting G-protein-coupled receptors Chem Bio Chem 2002 3 928 44  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>5 PalczewskiKKumasakaTHoriTBehnkeCAMotoshimaHFoxBA Crystal Structure of Rhodopsin: A G Protein-Coupled Receptor Science 2000 289 739 45 10926528 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>6 MarinissenMJGutkindJS G-protein-coupled receptors and signaling networks: Emerging paradigms Trends Pharmacol Sci 2001 22 368 76 11431032 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>7 StaceyMChangGWDaviesJQKwakkenbosMJSandersonRDHamannJ The epidermal growth factor-like domains of the human EMR2 receptor mediate cell attachment through chondroitin sulfate glycosaminoglycans Blood 2003 102 2916 24 12829604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>8 KwakkenbosMJChangGWLinHHPouwelsWDe JongECVan LierRA The human EGF-TM7 family member EMR2 is a heterodimeric receptor expressed on myeloid cells J Leukoc Biol 2002 71 854 62 11994511 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>9 LinHHStaceyMHamannJGordonSMcKnightAJ Human EMR2, a Novel EGF-TM7 Molecule on Chromosome 19p13.1, is Closely Related to CD97 Genomics 2000 67 188 200 10903844 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>10 ChangGWDaviesJQStaceyMYonaSBowdishDMHamannJ The human adhesion-GPCR EMR2, is differentially expressed during differentiation, maturation, and activation ofmyeloid cells Biochem Biophys Res Commun 2007 353 133 8 17174274 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>11 YonaSLinHHDriPDaviesJQHayhoeRPLewisSM Ligation of the adhesion-GPCR EMR2 regulates human neutrophil function FASEB J 2007 22 741 51 17928360 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>12 The polycystic kidney disease 1 gene encodes a 14 kb transcript and lies with in a duplicated region on chromosome 16. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The European Polycystic Kidney Disease Consortium Cell 1994 77 881 94 8004675 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>13 Polycystic kidney disease: the complete structure of the PKD1 gene and its protein The International Polycystic Kidney Disease Consortium Cell 1995 81 289 98  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>14 MengerinkKJMoyGWVacquierVD suREJ3, a polycystin-1 protein, is cleaved at the GPS domain and localizes to the acrosomal region of sea urchin sperm J Biol Chem 2002 277 943 8 11696547 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>15 HughesJWardCJAspinwallRButlerRHarrisPC Autosomal Dominant Polycystic Kidney Disease: Clues to Pathogenesis Hum Mol Genet 1999 8 543 9 9949214 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>16 QianFBABhuniaAKXuHLiuLAhrabiAKWatnickTJ Cleavage of polycystin-1 requires the receptor for egg jelly domain and is disrupted by human autosomal-dominant polycystic kidney disease 1-associated mutations Proc Natl Acad Sci 2002 99 16981 6 12482949 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>17 WestonMDLMHumphreyKDMollerCKimberlingWJ Mutations in the VLGR1 gene implicates G-protein signaling in the pathogenesis of Usher syndrome type II Am J Hum Genet 2004 74 357 66 14740321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>18 PiaoXHillRSBodellAChangBSBasel-VanagaiteLStraussbergR G protein-coupled receptor-dependent development of human frontal cortex Science 2004 303 2033 6 15044805 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>19 LarkinMABlackshieldsGBrownNPChennaRMcGettiganPAMcWilliamH Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0 Bioinformatics 2007 23 2947 8 17846036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>20 LarkinMABlackshieldsGBrownNPChennaRMcGettiganPAMcWilliamH Higgins DG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0 Bioinformatics 2007 23 2947 8 17846036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>21 ChengJL DOMAC: an accurate, hybrid protein domain prediction server Nucleic Acids Research 2007 35 354 6  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>22 ChengJRandallAZSweredoskiMJBaldiP SCRATCH: a protein structure and structural feature prediction server Nucleic Acids Research 2005 33 72 6  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>23 KroghALarssonBvon HeijneGSonnhammerEL Predicting transmembrane protein topology with a hidden Markov model: application to complete genomes J Mol Biol 2001 305 567 80 11152613 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>24 HirokawaTBoon-ChiengSMitakuS SOSUI: classification and secondary structure prediction system for membrane proteins Bioinformatics 1998 144 378 9 9632836 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>25 GaaborETusnaadyIstvaan Simon Principles governing amino acid composition of integral membrane proteins application to topology prediction J Mol Biol 1998 283 489 506 9769220 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>26 HofmannKStoffelW TMbase - A database of membrane spanning proteins segments Biol Chem Hoppe-Seyler 1993 374 166 70  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>27 CserzoMWallinESimonIvon HeijneGElofssonA Prediction of transmembrane alpha-helices in prokaryotic membrane proteins: Application of the Dense Alignment Surface (DAS) method J Mol Biol 1994 243 388 96 7966267 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>28 ClarosMGvon HeijneG TopPred II: an improved software for membrane protein structure predictions Comput Appl Biosci 1994 10 685 6 7704669 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>29 CaiCZHanLYJiZLChenXChenYZ SVM-Prot: Web-Based Support Vector Machine Software for Functional Classification of a Protein from Its Primary Sequence Nucleic Acids Res 2003 31 3692 7 12824396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>30 CaiCZHanLYChenXCaoZWChenYZ Prediction of Functional Class of the SARS Coronavirus Proteins by a Statistical Learning Method Proteome Res 2005 4 1855 62  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>31 SahooGCDikhitMRDasP Functional assignment to JEV proteins using SVM Bioinformation 2008 3 1 7 19052658 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>32 GaneshCSManasRDMuktaRDasP Homology Modeling and Functional Analysis of LPG2 Protein of Leishmania Strains J Proteomics Bioinform 2009 2 32 50  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>33 HendlichMRippmannFBarnickelG LIGSITE: automatic and efficient detection of potential small molecule-binding sites in proteins J Mol Graph Model 1997 15 359 63 9704298 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>34 PuntervollPLindingRGemündCChabanis-DavidsonSMattingsdalMCameronS ELM server: a new resource for investigating short functional sites in modular eukaryotic proteins Nucleic Acids Res 2003 31 3625 30 12824381 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>35 VenkatachalamCMJiangXOldfieldTWaldmanM LigandFit: a novel method for the shape-directed rapid docking of ligands to protein active sites J Mol Graph Model 2003 21 289 307 12479928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>36 GaneshCSManasRDMuktaRAnsariWADasP Structural modeling, evolution and ligand interaction of KMP11 Protein of different Leishmania Strains J Comput Sci Syst Biol 2009 2 147 58  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>37 SuhreKSanejouandYH ElNémo: a normal mode web server for protein movement analysis and the generation of templates for molecular replacement Nucleic Acids Res 2004 32 610 4  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>38 HolmLKaariainenSRosenstromPSchenkelA Searching protein structure databases with DaliLitev.3 Bioinformatics 2008 24 2780 1 18818215 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>39 NeudeckerHeinzMagnusJan R Matrix differential calculus with applications in statistics and econometrics New York John Wiley &amp; Sons 1988 136 140  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>40 Binmore &amp; Davies Calculus Concepts and Methods Cambridge University Press 2007 190  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b41"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>41 ChangGWStaceyMKwakkenbosMJHamannJGordonSLinHH Proteolytic cleavage of the EMR2 receptor requires both the extracellular stalk and the GPS motif FEBS Lett 2003 547 145 50 12860403 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b42"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>42 CharlesworthDeborahJohnHW The genetics of inbreeding depression Nature Reviews Genetics 2009 10 783 96  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b43"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>43 Rong-RongWJohnR cDNA Cloning of the Basement Membrane Chondroitin Sulfate Proteoglycan Core Protein, Bamacan: A Five Domain Structure Including Coiled-Coil Motifs Couchman J Cell Biol 1997 136 433 44 9015313 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b44"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>44 ZhenqiangLMartinKMaiaMCMichaelNG JDieterB The Crystal and Molecular Structures of a Cathepsin K: Chondroitin Sulfate Complex J Mol Biol 2008 383 78 91 18692071 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b45"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>45 SelvarajMMalikBK Modeling of human CCR5 as Target for HIV-I and Virtual Screening with Marine Therapeutic compounds Bioinformation 2008 3 89 94 19238197 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec id="s5"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="jbr-25-02-100-s001"><label>Supplementary Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Ramachandran plot analysis.</title><p><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Ramachandran plot analysis of the five different domains of modeled structure of EMR2 like 2a(A), 2b(B), 2c(C), 2d(D) and 2e(E), respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="jbr-25-02-100-s001.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="jbr-25-02-100-s002"><label>Supplementary Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Binding site prediction.</title><p><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Prediction of ligand binding sites (LBSs) of all five different domains of EMR2 (A, B, C, D and E) in human by the pocket finder web server. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="jbr-25-02-100-s002.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="jbr-25-02-100-st01"><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="jbr-25-02-100-t04" position="float"><label>Supplementary Table 1</label><caption><title>Different amino acid residues of disulphide bridges are comprised of five different domains of human EMR2 predicted by the DIpro (SCRATCH protein predictor) server.</title></caption></table-wrap></SecTag></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></back></article>
