
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3378585</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22723874</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-01952</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038653</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Agriculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Crops</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genome Analysis Tools</subject><subj-group><subject>Transcriptomes</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Plant Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Crop Genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genome Analysis Tools</subject><subj-group><subject>Transcriptomes</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Plant Biotechnology</subject><subj-group><subject>Plant Genomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Plant Genomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The First Illumina-Based De Novo Transcriptome Sequencing and Analysis of Safflower Flowers </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Safflower Flower Tissue Transcriptome</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lulin</surname><given-names>Huang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Yang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>Sun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Tong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shangqin</surname><given-names>Hu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>Department of Traditional Chinese Medicine Study, Industrial Crop Institute, Sichuan Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Jianyang, Sichuan, China</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Zhanjiang</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Auburn University, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>jysqhu@163.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: HS HL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: HL YX TW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: HL SP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: HL HS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e38653</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Huang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The safflower, Carthamus tinctorius L., is a worldwide oil crop, and its flowers, which have a high flavonoid content, are an important medicinal resource against cardiovascular disease in traditional medicine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Because the safflower has a large and complex genome, the development of its genomic resources has been delayed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Second-generation Illumina sequencing is now an efficient route for generating an enormous volume of sequences that can represent a large number of genes and their expression levels. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Methodology/Principal Findings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>To investigate the genes and pathways that might control flavonoids and other secondary metabolites in the safflower, we used Illumina sequencing to perform a de novo assembly of the safflower tubular flower tissue transcriptome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>We obtained a total of 4.69 Gb in clean nucleotides comprising 52,119,104 clean sequencing reads, 195,320 contigs, and 120,778 unigenes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Based on similarity searches with known proteins, we annotated 70,342 of the unigenes (about 58% of the identified unigenes) with cut-off E-values of 10−5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>In total, 21,943 of the safflower unigenes were found to have COG classifications, and BLAST2GO assigned 26,332 of the unigenes to 1,754 GO term annotations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>In addition, we assigned 30,203 of the unigenes to 121 KEGG pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>When we focused on genes identified as contributing to flavonoid biosynthesis and the biosynthesis of unsaturated fatty acids, which are important pathways that control flower and seed quality, respectively, we found that these genes were fairly well conserved in the safflower genome compared to those of other plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Conclusions/Significance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Our study provides abundant genomic data for Carthamus tinctorius L. and offers comprehensive sequence resources for studying the safflower. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>We believe that these transcriptome datasets will serve as an important public information platform to accelerate studies of the safflower genome, and may help us define the mechanisms of flower tissue-specific and secondary metabolism in this non-model plant. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The safflower, Carthamus tinctorius L., is a member of the Compositae or Asteraceae plant family, and is cultivated mainly for its seeds and flowers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The safflower plant yields a variety of products, including the numerous secondary metabolites of its flowers and the unsaturated fatty acids in its seeds, many of which are very beneficial to human health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Although the safflower is a minor crop, it is one of the oldest crops in human history, and it is cultivated worldwide; in 2007, safflower cultivation accounted for ∼ 795,118 ha across the globe [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Traditionally, this crop was grown for its flowers, which were a source of yellow and red dyes for clothing and food. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Safflower oil first was first used in the paint industry, but due to its health benefits, it is now produced commercially for cooking oil and other uses [2], [3], [4], [5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In plants, primary metabolites are organic compounds that are directly involved in normal growth, development and reproduction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In contrast, secondary metabolites often play important roles in defending the plant against herbivores and diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The flavonoids are a large group of secondary metabolites that humans have long used for medicines [6], [7], toning, and other purposes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Safflower flavonoid extracts have been clinically used for the prevention and treatment of cardiovascular disease in China [6], [8] and Japan for centuries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The safflower is a native plant whose flowers have long been processed into a Chinese herbal medicine called Chuanhonghua in China Jianyang country. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In China, safflower is mainly cultivated for the medicinal properties of its flower tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>To date, ∼ 50 secondary metabolites have been identified in safflower flower extracts; most of them are generalized flavonoids, a class of modulators that mediate bifunctional interactions at vicinal ATP- and steroid-binding sites [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>These include carthamone, safflor yellow A, hydroxysafflor yellow A, 6-hydroxykaempferol, 6-hydroxykaempferol-3-o-β-D-glucoside, kaempferol [10], [11], [12], and others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The abundance of flavonoids as secondary metabolites makes the safflower a good model for investigating flavonoid biosynthesis in plants, and the related genes and pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>This should provide a better understanding of the genes responsible for regulating natural products, and could help us improve the use of these natural products for human health. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In recent years, researchers have focused on examining the genetic diversity of the safflower. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>For example, Pahlavani et al. reported on the inheritance of flower color and spininess [13], while Chapman et al. reported on the DNA sequence diversity and origins of the cultivated safflower, along with its development and polymorphisms, and the cross-taxon utility of EST-SSR markers [14], [15], [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>More recently, Li et al. found that there are at least 236 known microRNAs (miRNAs) expressed in the safflower, 100 of which are conserved across plants [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>To date, however, the safflower genome has not been fully sequenced, and relatively little is known about its encoded genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>As of October 2011, only 567 nucleotide sequences, 41,588 expressed sequence tags (ESTs), 162 proteins and 0 genes from Carthamus tinctorius had been deposited in the NCBI’s GenBank database. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>EST sequencing has traditionally been the core technology used for the discovery of reference transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>However, it has some inherent limitations, such as low throughput, high cost and a long experimental cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In recent years, researchers have developed a high-throughput sequencing technology called Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Various platforms utilize NGS, such as the Illumina Genome Analyzer, the Roche/454 Genome Sequencer FLX Instrument, and the ABI SOLiD System; these have proven to be powerful and cost-effective tools for advanced research in many areas, including genome sequencing, genome re-sequencing, miRNA expression profiling, DNA methylation analysis, and especially the de novo transcriptome sequencing of non-model organisms [19], [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>This method of transcriptome analysis is fast and simple because it does not require bacterial cloning of the cDNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Instead, direct cDNA sequencing generates an extraordinary depth of short reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>It is a more comprehensive and efficient way to measure transcriptome composition, obtain RNA expression patterns, and discover new genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>In addition, this approach is very sensitive, and thus allows the detection of low-abundance transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Recent transcriptomic studies on Arabidopsis thaliana [21], mouse [22], and human [23] cells have demonstrated that this approach is well-suited for surveying the complexity of eukaryotic transcriptomes by de novo assembly. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>In this study, we used NGS technology to survey the poly (A) + transcriptome of Carthamus tinctorius L. flower tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The coverage of the transcriptome was ∼ 4.7 Gb of clean nucleotides, and thus comprehensive enough to discover all known genes and major metabolic pathways in this transcriptome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>This dataset will serve as a public information platform for gene expression, genomics, and functional genomics in Carthamus tinctorius L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The assembled and annotated transcriptome sequences provide a valuable resource for identifying most of the genes expressed in the safflower. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Flower Transcriptome Sequencing Output and de novo Assembly </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>To comprehensively cover the safflower flower transcriptome, total RNA was extracted from the tubular tissues of red/orange and white flowers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The phenotypes of each color are shown in Figure 1A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Flowers were collected on the 1st, 2nd and 3rd days of the flowering stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Equal amounts of total RNA from each sample were pooled together, and mRNA was isolated, enriched, sheared into smaller fragments, and reverse-transcribed into cDNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The cDNA were subjected to Illumina HiSeq™ 2000 sequencing, and the resulting sequencing data were subjected to bioinformatic analysis (Figure 1B–D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>After removal of adaptor sequences, ambiguous reads and low-quality reads (Q20&lt;20), we obtained a total of 52,119,104 clean reads of 75-bp long comprising 4,690,719,360 nucleotides (4.69 Gb) of high-quality clean reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>An overview of the sequencing and assembly is outlined in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>All high-quality reads were assembled de novo using the Trinity program [24], which produced 195,230 contigs, with an N50 of 290 bp (i.e. 50% of the assembled bases were incorporated into contigs of 290 bp or longer). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0038653-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038653.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Safflower flower phenotypes and schematics of the transcriptome sequencing analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>(A) Phenotypes of the red/orange (left) and white (mutant; right) flowers of Carthamus tinctorius L. used in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>(B) Overall workflow of the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>(C) Overall workflow of the data assembly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>(D) Overall workflow of the bioinformatic analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038653.g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0038653-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038653.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Summary of the sequence assembly after Illumina sequencing. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0038653-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0038653.t001"/></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The size distribution of the safflower contigs is shown in Figure 2A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>A total of 195,230 contigs were assembled; the mean length was 255 bp, and although the majority of the contigs were less than 200 bp, 41,682 of the contigs were greater than 500 bp in length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>A total of 120,778 unigenes were assembled, with an average unigene length of 446 bp and an N50 of 555 bp (the size distribution is shown in Figure 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Of the 120,778 unigenes, 49,376 were longer than 500 bp; 10,543 were longer than 1,000 bp; and 1,600 were longer than 1,500 bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Although the unigene distribution closely followed the contig distribution, with the majority being shorter sequences, we obtained much longer unigenes compared to contigs (Figure 2A and 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The longest unigene recovered in this work was Unigene1325_safflower, which is 3,967 bp and encodes a splicing factor 3B subunit 1 (according to SwissProt annotation). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0038653-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038653.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Overview of the safflower flower tissue transcriptome assembly. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>(A) The size distribution of the contigs obtained from our de novo assembly of high-quality clean reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>(B) The size distribution of the unigenes produced from further assembly of contigs (i.e., contig joining, gap filling, and scaffold clustering). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>(C) The size distribution of the CDS produced by searching unigene sequences against various protein databases (Nr, SwissProt, KEGG and COG, in order) using BLASTX (E-value &lt;10−5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>(D) The size distribution of the proteins predicted from the CDS sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>(E) And (F) Size distributions of the ESTs and proteins obtained from the ESTScan results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>For unigene CDS that had no hits in the databases (Nr, SwissProt, KEGG and COG), the BLAST results were subjected to ESTScans and then translated into peptide sequences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038653.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>For our analyses of coding sequences (CDS), predicted proteins, and gene annotations, all assembled sequences were first searched against the plant proteins found in the NCBI non-redundant database (Nr), and then against the Swiss-Prot, Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes pathway (KEGG) and Orthologous Groups of proteins (COG) [25] databases, using the BLASTX program (E-value &lt;10−5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>We obtained a total of 70,342 significant BLAST hits (58.24% of all unigenes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The size distribution for the CDS and predicted proteins are shown in Figure 2C and 2D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The CDS of the unigenes that did not have BLAST hits were predicted using ESTScan and then translated into peptide sequences [26]; 6,623 unigenes were analyzed using this method (the size distributions of the ESTs and proteins are shown in Figure 2E and 2F). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Functional Annotation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Unigene annotations provide functional information, including protein sequence similarities, COG clusters, gene ontology (GO) and KEGG pathway information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>We searched the safflower unigene sequences against the protein databases (Nr, SwissProt, KEGG and COG) using BLASTX (E-value &lt;10−5) and predicted the protein functions from the annotations of the most similar proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Distinct gene sequences were first searched using BLASTX against the Nr database, and 67,980 unigenes (56.3% of all unigenes) had hits that exceeded the E-value cutoff. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Similarly, 49,260 unigenes (40.8%) were identified from the SwissProt database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>A total of 70,342 unigenes were annotated in one or more of the databases (about 58% of all assembled unigenes), suggesting they have relatively well conserved functions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The COG database contains classifications of orthologous gene products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Every protein in the COG is assumed to be evolved from an ancestor protein, and the database includes the coding proteins of complete genomes and the evolutionary relationships of bacteria, algae and eukaryotes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The safflower unigenes were searched against the COG database in order to predict and classify their possible functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Out of 67,980 Nr hits, 21,943 sequences had COG classifications, distributing to 25 COG categories (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Among the 25 COG categories, “general function prediction only” represented the largest group (5,839; 26.6%), followed by “transcription” (3,389; 15.4%), “replication, recombination and repair” (3,291; 15.0%), “posttranslational modification, protein turnover, chaperones” (3,137; 14.3%) and “translation, ribosomal structure and biogenesis” (3,062; 14.0%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The smallest groups were “nuclear structures” (12 unigenes) and “extracellular structures” (5 unigenes) (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0038653-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038653.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>COG and GO classification of the safflower flower tissue transcriptome. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>(A) COG functional classification of the transcriptome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>A total of 21,943 unigenes showed significant homologies to genes in the COG Nr database (E-value &lt;1.0−5), distributing to 25 COG categories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>(B) GO classification of the safflower flower tissue transcriptome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>A total of 26,332 safflower unigenes were assigned to 1,754 GO term annotations using BLAST2GO, and then summarized into the three main GO categories and 44 sub-categories (functional groups). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038653.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>GO is an international standardized gene-function classification system that uses a dynamically updated, controlled vocabulary and a strictly defined concept to comprehensively describe the properties of genes and their products in any organism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The GO database comprises three ontologies: molecular function, cellular components and biological processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The basic units of GO are the “GO terms,” which each belong to a type of ontology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Here, we obtained the GO functional annotations of the safflower unigenes with Nr annotations by BLAST2GO program [27], and then used the WEGO software [28] to perform GO functional classifications for all of the unigenes and to examine the macro-level distribution of gene functions for this species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>A total of 26,332 safflower unigenes were assigned 1,754 GO-term annotations using BLAST2GO, and the terms were summarized into the three main GO categories and 44 sub-categories (functional groups) (Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>In each of the three main categories of the GO classification (biological processes, cellular components and molecular functions), the dominant terms were “cellular processes,” “metabolic processes,” “cells,” “cell parts,” “organelles,” “binding,” and “catalytic activity.” More than half of the genes fell within the “biological processes” category. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>A high-percentage of the genes in the biological processes category fell under “cellular processes” and “metabolic processes;” a high percentage of the genes in the cellular components category fell under “cells,” “cell parts,” and “organelles”; and “binding” and “catalytic activity” dominated in the molecular function category (Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Pathway-based analysis can help us further understand the biological functions of genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The KEGG pathway database contains information on networks of intracellular molecular interactions, and their organism-specific variations [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>To identify the biological pathways in the safflower, we mapped the annotated sequences to the reference canonical pathways contained in the KEGG database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>In total, we assigned 30,203 unigenes to 121 KEGG pathways (File S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The most highly represented category was “metabolic pathways,” with 6,948 members. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The “biosynthesis of secondary metabolites” and “plant-pathogen interaction” pathways were also well represented, with 3,598 members and 2,348 members, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Many genes corresponded to pathways involved in the biosynthesis of secondary metabolites, including “flavonoid biosynthesis” (274 genes), “flavone and flavonol biosynthesis” (114 genes), “isoquinoline alkaloid biosynthesis” (77 genes), “tropane, piperidine and pyridine alkaloid biosynthesis” (72 genes), “glucosinolate biosynthesis” (60 genes), “synthesis and degradation of ketone bodies” (35 genes), “indole alkaloid biosynthesis” (22 genes), “anthocyanin biosynthesis” (20 genes), and “betalain biosynthesis” (4 genes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Plants often produce secondary metabolites for pathogen defense, so it is unsurprising that 2,348 unigenes were mapped to pathways involved in plant-pathogen interactions, such as “phagosomes” (422) and “natural killer cell-mediated cytotoxicity” (126). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In addition, many genes were related to “fatty acid biosynthesis and metabolism”; these pathways included “alpha-linolenic acid metabolism” (268), “biosynthesis of unsaturated fatty acids” (216), “fatty acid metabolism” (204), “fatty acid biosynthesis” (143), “linoleic acid metabolism” (105) and “arachidonic acid metabolism” (48). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Finally, some genes also distributed to the plant hormone biosynthesis pathways, including “zeatin biosynthesis” (361) and “brassinosteroid biosynthesis” (28). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Analysis of Flavonoid Biosynthesis-related Pathways and Genes in the Safflower </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The flavonoids include flavanone, flavones, flavonols, quinochalcone and their derivatives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Because the pharmacological effects of safflower flavonoids, we focused on the related genes in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>In the safflower, quinochalcone is the product of a chalcone, which is oxidized in the A ring and then substituted by glucoses in one or more positions to achieve the final structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>In our annotated safflower flower tissue transcriptome datasets, we identified multiple unigenes encoding enzymes involved in known flavonoid biosynthesis pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Their sequencing depth was more than 10-fold coverages (Figure 4, File S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0038653-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038653.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Predicted flavonoid biosynthetic pathway-related genes and products in the safflower flower. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The pathways leading to the biosynthesis of different flavonoids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: CHS, chalcone synthase; CHI, chalcone isomerase; F3H, flavanone3-hydroxylase; F3′H, flavonoid 3′-hydroxylase;F3′5′H, flavonoid 3′,5′-hydroxylase; FLS, flavonol synthase; DFR, dihydroflavonol 4-reductase; LAR, leucoanthocyanidin reductase; 3GT, flavonol 3-O-glucosyltransferase; and 3GRT, flavonol-3-O-glucoside L-rhamnosyltransferase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The dotted arrow indicates that the involved enzymes are not yet clear. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038653.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The main pathway of flavonoid biosynthesis is well understood, and it is known to be fairly well conserved among plants [30], [31], [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>At the beginning of this process, one molecule of 4-coumaroyl-CoA and three molecules of Malonyl-CoA are catalyzed by the polyketide synthase, chalcone synthase (CHS, EC 2.3.1.74, in KEGG database), into 4,2′,4′,6′-tetrahydroxychalcone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>CHS is the first committed enzyme in this pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Five safflower unigenes and two hypothetical unigenes were identified as CHIs; four of them were more than 1000 bp in length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The intermediate, 4,2′,4′,6′-tetrahydroxychalcone, is key for the biosynthesis of both quinochalcones and flavonoids; it may be hydroxylated and glycosylated, leading to the production of carthamone (in red flowers) and hydroxysafflor yellow A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Hydroxysafflor yellow A, which was first identified in 1993 by Meselhy et al. [33], is the main component of the red/orange color of their flowers, and it is the most widely studied chemical in the safflower. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown that hydroxysafflor yellow A has the following properties: it can enhance the survival of vascular endothelial cells under hypoxia [34]; it can protect against LPS-induced acute lung injury, which is thought to be associated with the inhibition of p38 MAPK, the activation of NF-kappaB p65, and changes in inflammatory cytokine expression [35]; it might be a promising antifibrotic agent in chronic liver disease [36]; it can significantly inhibit the neuronal damage induced by exposure to glutamate and sodium cyanide (NaCN) in cultured fetal cortical cells [37]; it can protect against mitochondrial injuries in rat cortexes induced by cerebral ischemia [38]; and it can protect human umbilical vein endothelial cells from hypoxia-induced injuries by inhibiting apoptosis and cell cycle arrest [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>As a substrate, hydroxysafflor yellow A can be catalyzed to carthamin and safflor yellow A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>One study showed that injection of safflor yellow A is a safe and effective treatment for coronary heart disease angina pectoris (CHD-AP) with Xin-blood stagnation syndrome (XBSS) [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The enzymes responsible for catalyzing 4,2′,4′,6′-tetrahydroxychalcone to quinochalcones are not well understood at this time, so they were not assessed in the present study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, chalcone isomerase (CHI; EC 5.5.1.6) catalyzes 4,2′,4′,6′-tetrahydroxychalcone into naringenin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Four CHI unigenes were identified in the safflower, showing high unique-mapped-reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>In one branch of the biosynthetic pathway in the safflower, naringenin can be hydroxylated at the 6 position and glycosylated at the 5 position to produce 5,6,7,4-tetrahydroxyflavanone-5-O-β -D-glucoside (neocarthamin), or it may be hydroxylated and glycosylated at the 6 and 7 positions to produce 5,6,7,4′-tetrahydroxyflavanone-6,7-di-O-β -D-glucoside. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The more highly conserved pathway in plants is for naringenin to be catalyzed by flavanone 3-hydroxylase (F3H, also called naringenin 3-dioxygenase; EC 1.14.11.9) into dihydrokaempferol, which is a very important intermediate product. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>We identified six naringenin 3-dioxygenases in the safflower. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Dihydrokaempferol can be converted by flavonol synthase (FLS; EC 1.14.11.23) to kaempferol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Eight FLS unigenes were identified in the safflower. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Kaempferol can be hydroxylated at its 6 position and then glycosylated by flavonol 3-O-glucosyltransferase (3GT; EC 2.4.1.91) to 6-hydroxykaempferol-3-O- β-D-glucoside or 6-hydroxykaempferol-3,6-di-O-β -D-glucoside. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Only one 3GT unigene was identified in the safflower (Unigene7139_safflower; 1,815 bp). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Kaempferol can be converted by 3GT to produce kaempferol-3-O- β-D-glucoside, which can then be converted to kaempferol-3-O- β-rutinoside by flavonol-3-O-glucoside L-rhamnosyltransferase (3GRT; EC 2.4.1.159). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>In our study, kaempferol-3-O- β-rutinoside was commonly found in the white flower tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>One 3GRT unigene was identified in the safflower flower (Unigene59018_safflower). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Kaempferol can also be converted to quercetin by flavonoid 3′-hydroxylase (F3′H, also called flavonoid 3′-monooxygenase; EC 1.14.13.21) or flavonoid 3′, 5′-hydroxylase (F3′5′H; EC 1.14.13.88) by adding a hydroxyl to the 3′ position of ring B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>F3′H was found to be the largest family of safflower flavonoid biosynthesis enzymes, comprising 39 members ranging from 165 bp to 1,456 bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>In contrast, only three F3′5′H unigenes were identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In the next step of this pathway, 3GT can catalyze quercetin to quercetin-3-O- β-D-glucoside. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>As an optional pathway, dihydrokaempferol can be converted to dihydroquercetin by F3′5′H or F3′H, and then dihydroquercetin can be deoxidized to leucoanthocyanidin by dihydroflavonol-4-reductase (DFR; EC 1.1.1.219). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Three DFR unigenes were identified in the safflower flower. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Finally, leucoanthocyanidin can be catalyzed to catechin by leucoanthocyanidin reductase (LAR; EC 1.17.1.3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The LAR family was the second largest family identified in this pathway; 10 members were found in the safflower, ranging from 202 bp to 1,382 bp. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Although we searched for flavone synthase (FNS) genes in the transcriptome sequencing data of the safflower, we did not identify any such genes in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>We also failed to find any anthocyanidine-encoding genes; however, we did identify four anthocyanidin synthase (ANS, also called leucoanthocyanidin dioxygenase)-encoding genes, suggesting that the genes encoding other anthocyanidine-related products may exist but have not yet been identified in the flower. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>qRT-PCR Analysis of the Flavonoid Synthesis Related Genes in the Safflower </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>To confirm that the unigenes from sequencing and computational analysis were indeed expressed and also to analyze the difference of gene expression profile between red and white color flowers, twelve unigenes related to the ten families of safflower flavonoid synthesis were chosen for qRT-PCR analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>In the qRT-PCR analysis, to get more information, we used four flower materials including of flowering day2 and day4 of both white and red flowers for further compare instead of day1 and day3 of flowering (Figure 5, the ratios were resulted from the comparing analysis of each gene to 28S, unigene82078). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0038653-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038653.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>qRT-PCR analysis of 12 flavonoid biosynthetic pathway-related candidate unigenes in white and red flowers. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>W2, flowering day 2 of the white flower; W4, flowering day 4 of the white flower; R2, flowering day 2 of the red flower; R4, flowering day 4 of the red flower. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The numbers after the gene name means the serial number of unigene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The gene sequences used for qRT-PCR analysis are shown in File S5. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038653.g005"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>In general, the red flower showed much higher gene expression profile than the white flower in most of the selected genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Among them, the CHS gene (unigene96945) showed very high expression in the red flowers with the ratios of 174.16 and 84.5 on flowering day2 and day4 individually; comparing to the ratios in the red flower, this gene showed much lower expression in the white flowers with ratios of 9.85 and 11.08 on flowering day2 and day4 separately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>This result indicated that CHS gene (unigene96945) is very important for safflower flavonoid synthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The similar expression profile can be observed when considering the two detected CHI genes (unigene16741 and unigene27082); they showed much higher expression in the red flower than in the white flower, especially the unigene27082 with ratios of 32.0 and 41.64. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>For the two F3H genes (unigene45665 and unigene4561), they showed a relatively medium expression in the two color flowers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The F3′H gene (unigene104057) also showed very high expression on flowering day2 of the red flower with ratio of 95.01, suggesting that at the early stage of flowering (day2), hydroxylation is an important modification for the red flower flavonoid synthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Similar expression profiles can also be observed in the genes of FLS (unigene29190), DFR (unigene98353) and 3GT (unigene71390). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>On the contrary, the F3′5′H gene (unigene2547) showed higher expression in the later stage of flowering (day4) than in the early stage of flowering (day2) in both white and red flowers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Among all of the twelve genes, only the LAR gene (unigene25256) showed much higher expression in the white flowers with ratios of 13.09 and 8.17 on day2 and day4 individually comparing to the ratios of 0.30 and 0.22 on day2 and day4 in the red flowers, indicating that as a substrate much more leucoanthocyandin is produced in the white flower than in the red flower. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>High-throughput mRNA sequencing technology is especially suitable for gene expression profiling in non-model organisms that lack genomic sequence data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Prior to this study, most sequencing efforts in the safflower were based on EST sequencing; very few tags had been reported in public databases and little genetic or genomic information was available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Here, we used RNA-Seq technology to profile the safflower flower transcriptome on the Illumina HiSeq™ 2000 platform, obtained 4.6 Gb of coverage with 52,119,104 clean sequencing reads, and identified a total of 120,778 unigenes from de novo assembly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Among them, 70,342 unigenes were successfully annotated (about 58% of the assembled unigenes), suggesting their relatively conserved functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>We assessed not only the gene or protein names and descriptions, but also their putative conserved domains, gene ontology terms, and potential metabolic pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>This work will certainly improve our understanding of the processes involved in regulating the biosynthesis of secondary metabolites and the development of safflower flower tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Compared with previous transcriptomic studies in other plants, such as Acacia auriculiformis, Acacia mangium [41], Eucalyptus [42], and Taxus [43], we herein report more contigs and unigenes, suggesting that the safflower contains very abundant gene resources. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first attempt using Illumina paired-end sequencing technology for the de novo sequencing and assembly (without a reference genome) of the safflower flower transcriptome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>We believe our data will provide important new insights and facilitate further studies of safflower genes and their functions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>In terms of medicinal and pharmaceutical use, the properties of the safflower flower largely depend on its flavonoid profile. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Since gaining new insight into the biosynthesis and transcriptional regulation of flavonoids in the safflower should accelerate the engineering of this pathway in the future, we focused on the flavonoid biosynthesis genes identified in the present work. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Almost all of the genes for the main flavonoid biosynthesis pathway were identified (except for the flavone synthesis gene), indicating that this pathway was rather well conserved in the safflower (Figure 4 and File S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Many of these genes appeared to form multi-gene families, implying that the genome of the safflower, like those of many other higher plants, went through one or more rounds of genome duplication during its evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>However, the actual flavonoid pigments of plants are highly diverse in structure and color, reflecting the diversity of plants and their metabolic pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the safflower is likely to possess some unique, yet-unidentified flavonoid-related molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we further surveyed other genes that might be involved in the various branch or terminal pathways of flavonoid biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>KEGG predictions allowed us to identify an additional 227 genes that also contributed to generalized flavonoid biosynthesis, including members of the CYP family (electron carrier/heme binding/iron ion binding/monooxygenase/oxygen binding), the O-methyltransferase, O-hydroxycinnamoyltransferase family, and the glycosyltransferase family, which are involved in uniquely modifying the flavonoid skeleton to yield the final products (the other related genes are given in File S3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The safflower is a multipurpose crop, but its main use worldwide is as an oil crop. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Its main seed oil components are linoleic acid (71–75%), oleic acid (16–20%), palmitic acid (6–8%) and stearic acid (2–3%) [1], most of which are unsaturated fatty acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Safflower petals also contain alpha linolenic acid (15–19%), palmitic acids (14–16%), gamma linolenic acid (2–3%), and decanoic and dodecanoic acids (2–5%) [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Safflower linoleic acid may be beneficial for weight loss and/or glycemic control for type-2 diabetes [45], while dietary supplementation with safflower oil and olive oil was shown to rescue aberrant embryonic arachidonic acid and nitric oxide metabolism and prevent embryopathy in diabetic rats [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>In our sequencing of transcripts from 1–3d flowers, we identified 149 genes that distributed to the “biosynthesis of unsaturated fatty acids” category (File S4; sequencing depth &gt;10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>These were mainly fatty acid desaturases, including stearoyl-ACP desaturase, which was cloned in 1992 by Knutzon et al. [47], along with FAD2, FAD3, FAD5A, FAD6, FAD7 and FAD8 [48], [49], [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The expression of these gene products during this flowering stage suggests that the unsaturated fatty acid biosynthesis pathway is rather well conserved in the safflower with respect to Arabidopsis, Rape and Cabbage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Although we only identified one oil biosynthesis gene in safflower flowers, namely that encoding stearoyl-ACP desaturase, our data may facilitate the future study of other related genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, this sequence collection represents the first major genomic resource for the safflower, Carthamus tinctorius L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Using Illumina sequencing technology, we surveyed the flower transcriptome of the safflower, assembled 120,778 unigenes and annotated 70,342 of these unigenes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>These findings provided comprehensive coverage, suggesting that we identified almost of the all known genes from the major metabolic pathways operating in the safflower flower. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Our KEGG prediction results suggest that the flavonoid biosynthesis and unsaturated fatty acid biosynthesis pathway-related genes are rather well conserved in the safflower. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Overall, we identified more than 200 pathways as being represented in the safflower whole-flower transcriptome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Further analysis of these pathway-related genes will improve our understanding of the safflower’s unique and common features. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>This study again demonstrates that Illumina sequencing technology may be applied as a rapid and cost-effective method for de novo transcriptome analysis of non-model plants for which genomic information is unavailable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>We believe that this transcriptome dataset will serve as an important public information platform to accelerate research on the gene expression, genomics, and functional genomics of Carthamus tinctorius L. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Tissue Collection and RNA Isolation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Safflower plants were cultivated in the traditional Chinese medicine cultivation zone of the town of Shipan (Jianyang county Sichuan Province, China; 30.24?N 104.32?E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>This zone was built by our institute (Institute of Economic Crops Breeding and Cultivation, Sichuan Academy of Agricultural Sciences) for the collection and cultivation of Chinese herbal medicine resources. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The safflower is not on the list of endangered/protected plants, and no specific permission was required for us to use this material. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The safflower is generally planted in late October, and then flowers during the first two weeks of the following May. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Tubular flower tissues of 1-day-old (1d), 2d and 3d were cultivated from red/orange and white Carthamus tinctorius L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The white flower is a normally occurring mutant of the red/orange flower (Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was isolated from each sample using TRIzol (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was treated with RNase-free DNase I (New England BioLabs) for 30 min at 37°C to remove residual DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Equal amounts of RNA from each sample were mixed for the subsequent steps of our experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The workflow is shown in Figure 1B. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Preparation and Sequencing (mRNA-seq) of the cDNA Library </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The workflow described in this section is shown in Figure 1B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>In brief, RNA was collected from flower tissues, and oligo(dT) beads were used to isolate poly(A) mRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Fragmentation buffer was used to chop the mRNA into short fragments, which were then used as templates for random hexamer-primed synthesis of first-strand cDNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Second-strand cDNA was synthesized using buffer, dNTPs, RNase H, and DNA polymerase I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>From these cDNA, a paired-end library was synthesized using the Genomic Sample Prep kit (Illumina), according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Short fragments were purified with the QIAquick PCR (Qiagen) extraction kit and then resolved with EB buffer for end repair and the addition of poly (A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>The short fragments were then connected with sequencing adapters, and suitable fragments were separated by agarose gel electrophoresis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Finally, the sequencing library was built by PCR amplification and sequenced using the HiSeq™ 2000 platform (Illumina). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The transcriptome datasets are available at the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (SRA), under accession number SRA048496. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Analysis of Illumina Transcriptome Sequencing Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>A simplified workflow of the transcriptome assembly and bioinformatic analysis is shown in Figure 1C and 1D, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The raw sequencing data were transformed by base calling into sequence data (called raw data or raw reads), which were stored in fastq format. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Adaptor fragments were removed from the raw reads to yield the clean reads required for analysis. De novo transcriptome assembly of these short reads was performed using the SOAPdenovo assembling program, which first combined reads with a certain length of overlap to form longer fragments without N-called contigs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The reads were mapped back to contigs, and paired-end reads were used to detect contigs arising from the same transcript as well as the distances between these contigs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Next, SOAPdenovo connected the contigs, using “N” to represent unknown sequences, yielding scaffolds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Paired-end reads were then used again to fill in the gaps between the scaffolds, yielding sequences that had the fewest Ns and could not be extended on either end. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>These were designated as unigenes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>For further analysis, we first used BLASTX (E-value &lt;10−5) to search the unigene sequences against various protein databases, in the following order: Nr, SwissProt, KEGG and COG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Unigene sequences having hits in one database were not used to search the subsequent database(s). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>The BLAST results were then used to extract CDS from the unigene sequences, and translate them into peptide sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>The BLAST results were also used to train ESTScan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>The CDS of unigenes that had no BLAST hits were predicted by ESTScan and then translated into peptide sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Unigene annotation provided information on the expression patterns and functional annotations of the identified genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>For Nr annotation, we used the BLAST2GO program to obtain the GO annotations of the unigenes, and then used the WEGO software to perform GO functional classifications for all the unigenes and to explore the macro-distribution of gene functions for this species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Analysis of Metabolic Pathway Genes Identified from Carthamus Tinctorius L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Flowers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The metabolic pathway analysis was done using the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) database and related software applications (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/kegg/kegg4.html">http://www.genome.jp/kegg/kegg4.html</ext-link>), which form a bioinformatics resource for linking genomes to living organisms [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Within the KEGG databases, the PATHWAY database contains information on networks of molecular interactions within cells, as well as the variations specific to particular organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The genes involved in flavonoid and unsaturated fatty acid biosynthesis were identified using BLAST annotation of KEGG and the other databases mentioned above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>To increase the credibility of our results, we selected genes that had coverages &gt;10. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Gene Validation and Expression Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Twelve selected unigenes with potential roles in flavonoid synthesis were chosen for validation using real time qPCR with gene specific primers designed with primer premier 3.0 (the sequences of the selected genes was shown in File S4 and the primers designed for qRT-PCR analysis was shown in File S6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was extracted from day2 and day4 of red and white flowers individiually using trizol RNA extraction method (Invitrogen, USA) and purified with RNA purification kit (Qiagen, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>The purified RNA was reverse transcript to cDNA using PrimeScrit® RT reagent kit with gDNA Eraser (Perfect Real Time) (Takara, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>14 genes were first chose for RT-PCR analysis and 12 of them were further chose for qRT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>All the genes used for qRT-PCR were first performed RT-PCR analysis and run gel to get a good condition for qRT-PCR analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>The qRT-PCR reaction was performed according to the protocol of Green Mastermix (Qiagen, USA) using ABI 7500 system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Three biology duplications of each sample (each sample containing flowers from 4 individual plants) and triplicates of each reaction were performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>28S gene was chosen as an internal control for normalization after comparison the expressions of two reference genes (15S, unigene104038 and 28S) in different materials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038653.s001"><label>File S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Summary of the involved KEGG pathways and their corresponding gene numbers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>(XLSX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038653.s001.xlsx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038653.s002"><label>File S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>The main identified flavonoid biosynthetic pathway genes and their coverage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>(XLSX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038653.s002.xlsx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038653.s003"><label>File S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The other flavonoid biosynthetic pathway-related genes and their coverages. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>(XLSX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038653.s003.xlsx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038653.s004"><label>File S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Genes of the safflower flower transcriptome identified as contributing to “biosynthesis of unsaturated fatty acids.” </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>(XLSX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038653.s004.xlsx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038653.s005"><label>File S5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>The gene sequences used for qRT-PCR analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>(TXT) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038653.s005.txt"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038653.s006"><label>File S6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>The primers designed for qRT-PCR analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>(XLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038653.s006.xls"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to acknowledge the Beijing Genomics Institute (Shenzhen) for assistance with raw data processing and the related bioinformatics analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Funding: This work was supported by the foundations of Genetic Engineering of Special Funds by Sichuan province (No. 2011LWJJ-001 and No. 2011JYGC02-006) and Youth Foundation of Sichuan Academy of Agricultural Sciences (2009QNJJ-005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0038653-Gecgel1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>1 GecgelUDemirciMEsendalETasanM 2007 Fatty Acid Composition of the Oil from Developing Seeds of Different Varieties of Safflower (Carthamus tinctorius L.). J Amer Oil Chem Soc 47 54  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Koyama1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>2 KoyamaNSuzukiKFurukawaYArisakaHSekiT 2009 Effects of safflower seed extract supplementation on oxidation and cardiovascular risk markers in healthy human volunteers. Br J Nutr 101 568 575 18590590 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Storlien1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>3 StorlienLHKraegenEWChisholmDJFordGLBruceDG 1987 Fish oil prevents insulin resistance induced by high-fat feeding in rats. Science 237 885 888 3303333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Melancon1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>4 MelanconSBVanasseMGeoffroyGBarabeLProulxA 1982 Oral lecithin and linoleic acid in Friedreich’s ataxia: II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Clinical results. Can J Neurol Sci 9 155 164 7049341 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Tabrett1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>5 TabrettDGPhillipsGD 1982 A clinical evaluation of safflower oil emulsion in total parenteral nutrition. Anaesth Intensive Care 10 258 264 6812458 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Jin1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>6 JinYXuDXuW 2000 Influence of safflower injection on hemorheology of patients of chronic cor pulmonale during acute attack. Zhongguo Zhong Xi Yi Jie He Za Zhi 20 430 432 11789226 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Li1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>7 LiJWVederasJC 2009 Drug discovery and natural products: end of an era or an endless frontier? Science 325 161 165 19589993 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Shi1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>8 ShiNNChengCSZhaZQ 2011 Clinical study of safflower injection in treating and preventing the vascular crisis after free flap transplantation. Zhongguo Zhong Xi Yi Jie He Za Zhi 31 1322 1327 22097197 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Conseil1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>9 ConseilGBaubichon-CortayHDayanGJaultJMBarronD 1998 Flavonoids: a class of modulators with bifunctional interactions at vicinal ATP- and steroid-binding sites on mouse P-glycoprotein. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 95 9831 9836 9707561 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Li2"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>10 LiYCheQ 1998 [Studies on chemical components of Carthamus tinctorius petals]. Yao Xue Xue Bao 33 626 628 12016905 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Jiang1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>11 JiangTFLvZHWangYH 2005 Separation and determination of chalcones from Carthamus tinctorius L. and its medicinal preparation by capillary zone electrophoresis. J Sep Sci 28 1244 1247 16117003 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Fan1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>12 FanLZhaoHYXuMZhouLGuoH 2009 Qualitative evaluation and quantitative determination of 10 major active components in Carthamus tinctorius L. by high-performance liquid chromatography coupled with diode array detector. J Chromatogr A 1216 2063 2070 18394634 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Pahlavani1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>13 PahlavaniMHMirlohiAFSaeidiG 2004 Inheritance of flower color and spininess in safflower (Carthamus tinctorius L.). J Hered 95 265 267 15220395 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Chapman1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>14 ChapmanMABurkeJM 2007 DNA sequence diversity and the origin of cultivated safflower (Carthamus tinctorius L.; Asteraceae). BMC Plant Biol 7 60 17986334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Chapman2"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>15 ChapmanMAHvalaJStreverJMatvienkoMKozikA 2009 Development, polymorphism, and cross-taxon utility of EST-SSR markers from safflower (Carthamus tinctorius L.). Theor Appl Genet 120 85 91 19820913 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Chapman3"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>16 ChapmanMAHvalaJStreverJBurkeJM 2010 Population genetic analysis of safflower (Carthamus tinctorius; Asteraceae) reveals a Near Eastern origin and five centers of diversity. Am J Bot 97 831 840 21622448 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Li3"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>17 LiHDongYSunYZhuEYangJ 2011 Investigation of the microRNAs in safflower seed, leaf, and petal by high-throughput sequencing. Planta 233 611 619 21136073 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Patel1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>18 PatelRKJainM 2012 NGS QC Toolkit: a toolkit for quality control of next generation sequencing data. PLoS One 7 e30619 22312429 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Mardis1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>19 MardisER 2008 The impact of next-generation sequencing technology on genetics. Trends Genet 24 133 141 18262675 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Morozova1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>20 MorozovaOMarraMA 2008 Applications of next-generation sequencing technologies in functional genomics. Genomics 92 255 264 18703132 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Zhang1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>21 ZhangXByrnesJKGalTSLiWHBorevitzJO 2008 Whole genome transcriptome polymorphisms in Arabidopsis thaliana. Genome Biol 9 R165 19025653 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Franco1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>22 FrancoMDColomboFGalvanACeccoLDSpadaE 2010 Transcriptome of normal lung distinguishes mouse lines with different susceptibility to inflammation and to lung tumorigenesis. Cancer Lett 294 187 194 20189714 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Hafner1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>23 HafnerMLandthalerMBurgerLKhorshidMHausserJ 2010 Transcriptome-wide identification of RNA-binding protein and microRNA target sites by PAR-CLIP. Cell 141 129 141 20371350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Grabherr1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>24 GrabherrMGHaasBJYassourMLevinJZThompsonDA 2011 Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome. Nat Biotechnol 29 644 652 21572440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Natale1"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>25 NataleDAShankavaramUTGalperinMYWolfYIAravindL 2000 Towards understanding the first genome sequence of a crenarchaeon by genome annotation using clusters of orthologous groups of proteins (COGs). Genome Biol 1 RESEARCH0009 11178258 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Iseli1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>26 IseliCJongeneelCVBucherP 1999 ESTScan: a program for detecting, evaluating, and reconstructing potential coding regions in EST sequences. Proc Int Conf Intell Syst Mol Biol 138 148 10786296 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Conesa1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>27 ConesaAGotzSGarcia-GomezJMTerolJTalonM 2005 Blast2GO: a universal tool for annotation, visualization and analysis in functional genomics research. Bioinformatics 21 3674 3676 16081474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Ye1"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>28 YeJFangLZhengHZhangYChenJ 2006 WEGO: a web tool for plotting GO annotations. Nucleic Acids Res 34 W293 297 16845012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Kanehisa1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>29 KanehisaMArakiMGotoSHattoriMHirakawaM 2008 KEGG for linking genomes to life and the environment. Nucleic Acids Res 36 D480 484 18077471 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Tanaka1"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>30 TanakaYSasakiNOhmiyaA 2008 Biosynthesis of plant pigments: anthocyanins, betalains and carotenoids. Plant J 54 733 749 18476875 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Iwashina1"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>31 IwashinaTGithiriSMBenitezERTakemuraTKitajimaJ 2007 Analysis of flavonoids in flower petals of soybean near-isogenic lines for flower and pubescence color genes. J Hered 98 250 257 17420179 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Forkmann1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>32 ForkmannGMartensS 2001 Metabolic engineering and applications of flavonoids. Curr Opin Biotechnol 12 155 160 11287230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Meselhy1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>33 MeselhyMRKadotaSMomoseYHatakeyamaNKusaiA 1993 Two new quinochalcone yellow pigments from Carthamus tinctorius and Ca2+ antagonistic activity of tinctormine. Chem Pharm Bull (Tokyo) 41 1796 1802 8281577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Ji1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>34 JiDBZhuMCZhuBZhuYZLiCL 2008 Hydroxysafflor yellow A enhances survival of vascular endothelial cells under hypoxia via upregulation of the HIF-1 alpha-VEGF pathway and regulation of Bcl-2/Bax. J Cardiovasc Pharmacol 52 191 202 18670359 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Sun1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>35 SunCYPeiCQZangBXWangLJinM 2010 The ability of hydroxysafflor yellow a to attenuate lipopolysaccharide-induced pulmonary inflammatory injury in mice. Phytother Res 24 1788 1795 20564507 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Zhang2"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>36 ZhangYGuoJDongHZhaoXZhouL 2011 Hydroxysafflor yellow A protects against chronic carbon tetrachloride-induced liver fibrosis. Eur J Pharmacol 660 438 444 21536026 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Zhu1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>37 ZhuHWangZMaCTianJFuF 2003 Neuroprotective effects of hydroxysafflor yellow A: in vivo and in vitro studies. Planta Med 69 429 433 12802724 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Tian1"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>38 TianJWFuFHJiangWLWangCYSunF 2004 Protective effect of hydroxysafflor yellow A against rat cortex mitochondrial injuries induced by cerebral ischemia. Yao Xue Xue Bao 39 774 777 15700814 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Ji2"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>39 JiDBZhangLYLiCLYeJZhuHB 2009 Effect of Hydroxysafflor yellow A on human umbilical vein endothelial cells under hypoxia. Vascul Pharmacol 50 137 145 19084079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Zhang3"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>40 ZhangQPengJHZhangXN 2005 A clinical study of Safflower Yellow injection in treating coronary heart disease angina pectoris with Xin-blood stagnation syndrome. Chin J Integr Med 11 222 225 16181539 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Wong1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>41 WongMMCannonCHWickneswariR 2011 Identification of lignin genes and regulatory sequences involved in secondary cell wall formation in Acacia auriculiformis and Acacia mangium via de novo transcriptome sequencing. BMC Genomics 12 342 21729267 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Mizrachi1"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>42 MizrachiEHeferCARanikMJoubertFMyburgAA 2010 De novo assembled expressed gene catalog of a fast-growing Eucalyptus tree produced by Illumina mRNA-Seq. BMC Genomics 11 681 21122097 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Haoda1"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>43 Hao daCGeGXiaoPZhangYYangL 2011 The first insight into the tissue specific taxus transcriptome via Illumina second generation sequencing. PLoS One 6 e21220 21731678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Srinivas1"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>44 SrinivasCVPraveenaBNagarajG 1999 Safflower petals: a source of gamma linolenic acid. Plant Foods Hum Nutr 54 89 92 10646633 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Norris1"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>45 NorrisLEColleneALAspMLHsuJCLiuLF 2009 Comparison of dietary conjugated linoleic acid with safflower oil on body composition in obese postmenopausal women with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Am J Clin Nutr 90 468 476 19535429 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Higa1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>46 HigaRWhiteVMartinezNKurtzMCapobiancoE 2010 Safflower and olive oil dietary treatments rescue aberrant embryonic arachidonic acid and nitric oxide metabolism and prevent diabetic embryopathy in rats. Mol Hum Reprod 16 286 295 20051498 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Knutzon1"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>47 KnutzonDSThompsonGARadkeSEJohnsonWBKnaufVC 1992 Modification of Brassica seed oil by antisense expression of a stearoyl-acyl carrier protein desaturase gene. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 89 2624 2628 1557366 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Arondel1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>48 ArondelVLemieuxBHwangIGibsonSGoodmanHM 1992 Map-based cloning of a gene controlling omega-3 fatty acid desaturation in Arabidopsis. Science 258 1353 1355 1455229 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Okuley1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>49 OkuleyJLightnerJFeldmannKYadavNLarkE 1994 Arabidopsis FAD2 gene encodes the enzyme that is essential for polyunsaturated lipid synthesis. Plant Cell 6 147 158 7907506 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Gibson1"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>50 GibsonSArondelVIbaKSomervilleC 1994 Cloning of a temperature-regulated gene encoding a chloroplast omega-3 desaturase from Arabidopsis thaliana. Plant Physiol 106 1615 1621 7846164 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0038653-Nakao1"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>51 NakaoMBonoHKawashimaSKamiyaTSatoK 1999 Genome-scale Gene Expression Analysis and Pathway Reconstruction in KEGG. Genome Inform Ser Workshop Genome Inform 10 94 103  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
