
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3921138</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24523868</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-49345</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087370</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Agriculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Biofuels</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzymes</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzyme Kinetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Plant Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Carbohydrate Biosynthesis</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Plant Biotechnology</subject><subj-group><subject>Transgenic Plants</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Plant Growth and Development</subject><subject>Plant Physiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Earth Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Energy and Power</subject><subj-group><subject>Biofuels</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Identification and Biochemical Characterization of Four Wood-Associated Glucuronoxylan Methyltransferases in Populus </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Glucuronoxylan Methyltransferase in <italic>Populus</italic> Wood</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Youxi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>Quincy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Ruiqin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Zheng-Hua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Plant Biology, University of Georgia, Athens, Georgia, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Pharmaceutical and Biomedical Sciences, University of Georgia, Athens, Georgia, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Zabotina</surname><given-names>Olga A.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Iowa State University, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>zhye@plantbio.uga.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: RZ ZHY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: YY QT RZ ZHY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: YY QT RZ ZHY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YY QT RZ ZHY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: RZ ZHY. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e87370</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Yuan et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Yuan et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Wood is one of the promising bioenergy feedstocks for lignocellulosic biofuel production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Understanding how wood components are synthesized will help us design strategies for better utilization of wood for biofuel production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>One of the major wood components is xylan, in which about 10% of xylosyl residues are substituted with glucuronic acid (GlcA) side chains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>All the GlcA side chains of xylan in wood of Populus trichocarpa are methylated, which is different from Arabidopsis xylan in which about 60% of GlcA side chains are methylated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Genes responsible for methylation of GlcA side chains in Populus xylan have not been identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Here, we report genetic and biochemical analyses of four DUF579 domain-containing proteins, PtrGXM1, PtrGXM2, PtrGXM3 and PtrGXM4, from Populus trichocarpa and their roles in GlcA methylation in xylan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The PtrGXM genes were found to be highly expressed in wood-forming cells and their encoded proteins were shown to be localized in the Golgi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>When overexpressed in the Arabidopsis gxm1/2/3 triple mutant, PtrGXMs were able to partially complement the mutant phenotypes including defects in glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activity and GlcA methylation in xylan, indicating that PtrGXMs most likely function as glucuronoxylan methyltransferases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Direct evidence was provided by enzymatic analysis of recombinant PtrGXM proteins showing that they possessed a methyltransferase activity capable of transferring the methyl group onto GlcA-substituted xylooligomers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Kinetic analysis showed that PtrGXMs exhibited differential affinities toward the GlcA-substituted xylooligomer acceptor with PtrGXM3 and PtrGXM4 having 10 times higher K m values than PtrGXM1 and PtrGXM2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Together, these findings indicate that PtrGXMs are methyltransferases mediating GlcA methylation in Populus xylan during wood formation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was funded by the Division of Chemical Sciences, Geosciences, and Biosciences, Office of Basic Energy Sciences of the U.S. Department of Energy through grant DE-FG02-03ER15415. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Terrestrial plants fix about 56 billion metric tons of carbon annually, of which nearly half is stored in wood, the most abundant plant biomass [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Therefore, wood is an important reservoir for fixed carbon and plays a significant role in the regulation of atmospheric CO2 level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, wood is a raw material vital for numerous applications, such as burning for energy, pulping and paper-making, construction, and furniture-making, and it is a renewable source for biofuel production [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Because of the immense role wood plays in our daily life, tremendous efforts have been devoted into understanding how wood is synthesized in order to develop molecular and genetic tools for custom-designing wood composition tailored for diverse end uses [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Wood is mainly composed of three wall polymers, i.e., cellulose, hemicelluloses, and lignin, the proportion of which varies among different tree species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Cellulose, consisting of linear chains of β-1,4-linked glucosyl residues, is the predominant constituent ranging from 41% to 51% in softwood and hardwood from gymnosperms and angiosperms, respectively [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Genes encoding cellulose synthase catalytic subunits involved in wood formation have been identified and functionally characterized in tree species [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Lignin is a complex polyphenolic polymer, the content of which varies from 25 to 35% in softwood and 18 to 25% in hardwood [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Genes encoding enzymes in the phenylpropanoid pathway leading to monolignol biosynthesis have been identified in tree species and transgenic trees with altered expression of lignin biosynthetic genes exhibit reduced lignin content and/or altered lignin composition [6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The third major wood component is hemicellulose, which consists mainly of xylan and glucomannan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In softwood, glucomannan is the predominant hemicellulose (about 20% of wood) and xylan is only half as abundant, whereas in hardwood, xylan is the predominant hemicellulose (ranging from 20 to 35% of wood) and glucomannan is a minor component (about 3% of wood) [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Glucomannan is composed of β-1,4-linked glucosyl and mannosyl residues, and genes encoding mannan synthases responsible for glucomannan biosynthesis have been identified and biochemically characterized in several tree species, such as Populus and pine [7], [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Xylan from hardwood consists of a linear chain of β-1,4-linked xylosyl residues, to which 4-O-methylglucuronic acid (MeGlcA) side chains are attached at O-2 [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Hardwood xylan is often heavily acetylated; 40 to 60% of xylosyl residues contain acetyl groups at O-2 and/or O-3, depending on the tree species [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>In addition, the reducing end of hardwood xylan from birch and Populus contains a tetrasaccharide sequence, β-d-Xyl-(1→3)-α-l-Rha-(1→2)-α-d-GalA-(1→4)-d-Xyl, that is distinct from the xylosyl backbone [10], [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The biosynthesis of xylan requires a suite of enzymes that are responsible for the xylan backbone elongation, side chain addition and modification, and the synthesis of the tetrasaccharide reducing end sequence [12]–[18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Our understanding of genes involved in xylan biosynthesis during wood formation in tree species is still limited. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Early genomic studies of wood formation in poplar led to the first identification of a number of glycosyltransferase genes, belonging to families GT2, GT8, GT43 and GT47, that are potentially involved in the biosynthesis of wood components [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Further molecular and biochemical analyses of some of these wood-associated glycosyltransferase genes have demonstrated that family GT43 genes in Populus are functional orthologs of Arabidopsis GT43 genes and they form two functionally non-redundant groups responsible for the elongation of xylan backbone [13]–[15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Several other Populus wood-associated glycosyltransferase genes, PoGT8D, PoGT8E/PoGT8F and PoGT47C, have been shown to be functional orthologs of Arabidopsis IRX8, PARVUS and FRA8, respectively, that are involved in the biosynthesis of the xylan tetrasaccharide reducing end sequence but their exact biochemical functions have not been revealed [11], [14], [16]–[18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Genes responsible for glucuronic acid (GlcA) substitution, GlcA methylation, and acetylation of xylan in tree species have not been characterized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In Arabidopsis, three GUX genes encode glucuronyltransferases mediating GlcA substitution of xylan [19], [20] and three GXM genes encode methyltransferases catalyzing GlcA methylation of xylan [21], [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Acetylation of Arabidopsis xylan involves RWAs and ESK1 [23], [24], [25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>In this study, we performed functional analysis of four Populus genes encoding DUF579 domain-containing proteins that are induced by PtrWND2B, a wood-associated master transcriptional regulator controlling secondary wall biosynthesis [26], [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>These PtrWND2B-induced genes, namely PtrGXM1, PtrGXM2, PtrGXM3, and PtrGXM4, are highly expressed in developing wood in Populus stems and their encoded proteins are localized in the Golgi. PtrGXMs are close homologs of Arabidopsis GXMs that have recently been demonstrated to encode methyltransferases catalyzing GlcA methylation of xylan [21], [22] and they were able to partially restore the 4-O-methylation of GlcA in xylan when overexpressed in the Arabidopsis gxm1/2/3 triple mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Moreover, recombinant PtrGXMs exhibit a methyltransferase activity transferring the methyl group from the methyl donor S-adenosylmethionine to GlcA-substituted xylooligomer acceptors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>These results demonstrate that PtrGXMs are wood-associated methyltransferases responsible for GlcA methylation of Populus xylan. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Microsomes from Populus developing wood exhibit glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>As a first step toward molecular and biochemical characterization of methyltransferases responsible for GlcA methytlation in xylan in Populus, we examined glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activity in developing wood of Populus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Microsomes isolated from Populus stems were incubated with S-adenosyl-L-methionine, radiolabeled on the methyl group, as the methyl donor and GlcA-substituted Xyl4 as the acceptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>While the microsomes exhibited no methyltransferase activity in the absence of the exogenous acceptor, a high level of methyltransferase activity was detected in the presence of the GlcA-substituted Xyl4 acceptor (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>This methyltransferase activity was both time- and protein concentration-dependent (Fig. 1B, C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The reaction products were verified using matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization-time-of-flight mass spectrometry (MALDI-TOF-MS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The control reaction with the addition of the acceptor but no methyl donor exhibited an ion peak [M+Na]+ at mass-to-charge ratio (m/z) 745 that corresponds to the acceptor, GlcA-substituted Xyl4 (Fig. 1D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>In the reaction with the addition of both the methyl donor and the acceptor, a signal peak at m/z 759 corresponding to MeGlcA-substituted Xyl4 was evident in addition to the GlcA-substituted Xyl4 acceptor peak (m/z 745) (Fig. 1D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>These results demonstrate that the Populus stem microsomes possess a methyltransferase activity capable of transferring the methyl group from S-adenosyl-L-methionine onto the GlcA-substituted xylooligosaccharide acceptor. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0087370-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087370.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Detection of glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activity in Populus stem microsomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Microsomes isolated from developing stems of Populus trichocarpa were incubated with the methyl donor, 14C-radiolabeled S-adenosylmethionine, and the GlcA-substituted Xyl4 acceptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The methyltransferase activity (CPM) was measured by the transfer of the radiolabeled methyl group onto the acceptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Error bars in (A), (B) and (C) denote the se of two biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>(A) Populus stem microsomes exhibit a methyltransferase activity toward the GlcA-substituted Xyl4 acceptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Microsomes (200 µg protein) were used for each reaction unless otherwise indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>(B) Time course of the methyltransferase activity exhibited by the microsomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>(C) The methyltransferase activity increases with increasing amount of microsomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>(D) MALDI analysis of the reaction products catalyzed by the methyltransferase activity in Populus microsomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Microsomes were incubated with the GlcA-substituted Xyl4 acceptor in the absence (top panel) or presence (lower panel) of S-adenosylmethionine (SAM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The ions [M+Na]+ at m/z 745 and 759 correspond to the GlcA-substituted Xyl4 acceptor [(GlcA)Xyl4] and the methylated acceptor with an increase of 14 D [(MeGlcA)Xyl4], respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The ions at m/z 767 and 781 are attributed to the doubly sodiated species [M+2Na]+ of (GlcA)Xyl4 and (MeGlcA)Xyl4, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The identity of the ion at m/z 787 is not known. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0087370.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The expression of PtrGXM genes is PtrWND2-induced and wood-associated </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>To search for genes that are responsible for the above observed glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activity in Populus stems, we first analyzed the expression patterns of Populus DUF579 genes that are close homologs of Arabidopsis GXM genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>There are 11 DUF579 genes (Fig. 2A) in the Populus genome, of which four are closely grouped together with the Arabidopsis GXM1, GXM2 and GXM3 genes known to encode glucuronoxylan methyltransferases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>These four Populus DUF579 genes (namely PtrGXM1/2/3/4) apparently fall into two pairs (PtrGXM1/PtrGXM2 and PtrGXM3/PtrGXM4), each of which was likely originated from genome duplication [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>All four PtrGXM genes were found to be highly expressed in Populus stems undergoing secondary growth (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>In addition, the expression of PtrGXM1, PtrGXM2 and PtrGXM3 was shown to be significantly upregulated (Fig. 2C) in transgenic Populus plants overexpressing PtrWND2B, which is a transcriptional master switch activating secondary wall biosynthesis during wood formation [26], [27]. In situ hybridization further demonstrated that the PtrGXM genes were predominantly expressed in cells undergoing secondary wall thickening, including developing secondary xylem and phloem fibers (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0087370-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087370.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic and expression analyses of four Populus GXM genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>(A) Phylogenetic relationship of DUF579-containing proteins from Populus and Arabidopsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The amino acid sequences of DUF579-containing proteins from Populus and Arabidopsis were aligned using ClustalW and their phylogenetic relationship was analyzed using the neighbor-joining method in MEGA5.2 [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Bootstrap values resulted from 1,000 replicates are shown at the nodes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>(B) Quantitative PCR analysis of the expression of PtrGXM genes in developing leaves, petioles, stems without secondary growth (stem I), and stems with secondary growth (stem II) of Populus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The expression level of each gene in leaves was taken as 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>(C) Quantitative PCR analysis of the induction of expression of PtrGXM genes in the leaves of transgenic Populus plants overexpressing PtrWND2B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The control is transgenic Populus plants transformed with an empty vector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Error bars in (B) and (C) denote the se of three biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0087370.g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0087370-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087370.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>In situ hybridization analysis of PtrGXM1, PtrGXM2, PtrGXM3 and PtrGXM4 mRNAs in Populus stems. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Cross sections of stems were hybridized with digoxigenin-labeled antisense probes of PtrGXM1 (A), PtrGXM2 (B), PtrGXM3 (C), and PtrGXM4 (D) or the sense probe of PtrGXM1 as the control (E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The hybridized sections were incubated with alkaline phosphatase-conjugated antibodies and the hybridization signals are shown as purple color. co, cortex; pf, phloem fiber; sx, secondary xylem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Bar in (A) = 160 µm for (A) to (E). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0087370.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>PtrGXM proteins are targeted to the Golgi </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>To further substantiate their involvement in xylan biosynthesis, we exmined whether PtrGXM proteins are targeted to the Golgi, in which xylan biosynthesis occurs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>PtrGXMs are typical type II membrane proteins containing one transmembrane helix as predicted by the TMHMM2.0 program for prediction of transmembrane helices in proteins (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/service/TMHMM-2.0">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/service/TMHMM-2.0</ext-link>) (Fig. 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>To examine the subcellular localization of PtrGXMs, we coexpressed in Arabidopsis protoplasts yellow fluorescence protein-tagged PtrGXMs together with cyan fluorescence protein-tagged FRA8, a family GT47 glycosyltransferase known to be located in the Golgi [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>While the control protoplasts expressing YFP alone showed fluorescent signals throughout the cytoplasm (Fig. 4B, C), the protoplasts expressing PtrGXM-YFP exhibited punctate signals, which were colocalized with the FRA8-CFP signals (Fig. 4D–S). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>These results demonstrate that PtrGXMs are localized in the Golgi, where xylan biosynthesis occurs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0087370-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087370.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Subcellular localization of PtrGXM1, PtrGXM2, PtrGXM3, and PtrGXM4. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>PtrGXM proteins tagged with yellow fluorescent protein (YFP) were expressed in Arabidopsis protoplasts, and the fluorescence signals were detected with a laser confocal microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>(A) PtrGXMs are membrane proteins with one transmembrane helix near the N-terminus as predicted by the TMHMM2.0 program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Inside, the cytoplasmic side of the membrane; outside, the noncytoplasmic side of the membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>(B) and (C) An Arabidopsis protoplast (B; differential interference contrast image) expressing YFP alone showing the fluorescence signals throughout the cytoplasm (C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>(D) to (G) An Arabidopsis protoplast (D) co-expressing PtrGXM1-YFP (E) and the Golgi-localized FRA8-CFP (F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>(H) to (K) An Arabidopsis protoplast (H) co-expressing PtrGXM2-YFP (I) and FRA8-CFP (J). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>(L) to (O) An Arabidopsis protoplast (L) co-expressing PtrGXM3-YFP (M) and FRA8-CFP (N). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>(P) to (S) An Arabidopsis protoplast (P) co-expressing PtrGXM4-YFP (Q) and FRA8-CFP (R). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Note the superimposition of the fluorescence signals of PtrGXM1-YFP (G), PtrGXM2-YFP (K), PtrGXM3-YFP (O), and PtrGXM4 (S) with the Golgi marker FRA8-CFP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0087370.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>PtrGXMs are functional orthologs of Arabidopsis GXMs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The wood-associated expression of PtrGXMs and their Golgi-localization indicate that PtrGXMs most likely play a role in the biosynthesis of xylan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Considering the fact that the four PtrGXMs are phylogenetically closely grouped together with the Arabidopsis glucuronoxylan methyltransferases GXM1/2/3, we hypothesized that PtrGXMs are also glucuronoxylan methyltransferases involved in the methylation of GlcA side chains of xylan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we tested the ability of PtrGXMs to complement the Arabidopsis gxm1/2/3 triple mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The full-length PtrGXM cDNAs driven by the cauliflower mosaic virus (CaMV) 35S promoter were transformed into the gxm1/2/3 mutant, and more than 64 independently transgenic lines for each construct were generated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The expression of PtrGXMs in 8 representative transgenic lines for each construct was confirmed by reverse transcription PCR analysis of PtrGXM transcripts (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Microsomes were isolated from stems of six-week-old transgenic plants and subsequently used for glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activity assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activities from 8 representative transgenic lines for each expression construct of PtrGXMs were shown in Fig. 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>It was evident that although the gxm1/2/3 mutant exhibited a loss of glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activity, the gxm1/2/3 lines expressing PtrGXMs showed a partial restoration of glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0087370-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087370.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Assay of the glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activity in the Arabidopsis gxm1/2/3 triple mutant overexpressing PtrGXMs. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The full-length cDNAs of PtrGXMs driven by the CaMV 35S promoter were introduced into the gxm1/2/3 mutant and the inflorescence stems of 6-week-old transgenic plants were used for microsome isolation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Microsomes were incubated with 14C-labeled S-adenosylmethionine and the GlcA-substituted Xyl4 acceptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The methyltransferase activity (CPM) was measured by the amount of 14C-labeled methyl group transferred onto the acceptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The methyltransferase activities from 8 independent transgenic lines were shown for each PtrGXM overexpression construct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Error bars denote the se of two independent assays. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0087370.g005"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>To find out whether expression of PtrGXMs restored the GlcA methylation of xylan in the gxm1/2/3 mutant, we isolated xylan from the pooled stems of the 8 transgenic lines as shown in Fig. 5 for each expression contruct of PtrGXMs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The isolated xylan was digested with xylanase to generate xylooligosaccharides, which were subsequently subjected to MALDI-TOF-MS (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Xylooligosaccharides from wild-type xylan exhibited a prominent ion peak at m/z 759, which corresponds to MeGlcA-substituted Xyl4, and a less prominent ion peak at m/z 745, which corresponds to GlcA-substituted Xyl4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Simultaneous mutations of the Arabidopsis GXM1, GXM2 and GXM3 genes in the gxm1/2/3 triple mutant resulted in a complete loss of the ion peak (m/z 759) attributed to MeGlcA-substituted Xyl4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>As a result, the GlcA-substituted Xyl4 peak at m/z 745 was significantly elevated in the gxm1/2/3 mutant compared with that in the wild type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Expression of PtrGXMs in gxm1/2/3 led to a partial restoration of the ion peak at m/z 759 corresponding to MeGlcA-substituted Xyl4 (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The partial restoration of the GlcA methylation was further verified by 1H nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy (Fig. 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The wild-type xylan displayed resonances characteristic of H1 of GlcA and MeGlcA side chains at 5.31 and 5.29 ppm, respectively, and H5 of GlcA and MeGlcA side chains at 4.42 and 4.39 ppm, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>It also exhibited resonances at 4.63 and 4.46 ppm that are attributed to H1 of branched and unbranched backbone xylosyl residues, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Xylan from the gxm1/2/3 mutant lacked all the resonances attributed to MeGlcA side chains, including H1 of MeGlcA, H5 of MeGlcA, and H1 of MeGlcA-branched β-Xyl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Analysis of xylan from gxm1/2/3 lines expressing PtrGXMs revealed a partial restoration of all the resonances attributed to MeGlcA side chains (Fig. 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Integration analysis of the GlcA and MeGlcA signal peaks revealed that although the gxm1/2/3 mutant completely lacks GlcA methylation in xylan, 8% to 21% of the GlcA side chains in xylan were methylated in gxm1/2/3 expressing PtrGXMs (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The resonance intensities for the xylan reducing end tetrasaccharide sequence, β-d-Xyl-(1→3)-α-l-Rha-(1→2)-α-d-GalA-(1→4)-d-Xyl (H1 of 3-linked β-D-Xyl, H1 of α-L-Rha, H1 of α-D-GalA, H2 of α-L-Rha, and H4 of α-D-GalA), were unaltered in gxm1/2/3 expressing PtrGXMs compared with the gxm1/2/3 mutant and the wild type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Together, these results provide genetic evidence demonstrating that expression of each of the four PtrGXM genes in the gxm1/2/3 mutant is able to partially restore the glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activity and the GlcA methylation in xylan, indicating that PtrGXMs are functional orthologs of the Arabidopsis GXMs catalyzing the methylation of GlcA side chains in xylan. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0087370-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087370.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>MALDI-TOF mass spectra of xylooligosaccharides generated by xylanase digestion of xylan from the gxm1/2/3 mutant overexpressing PtrGXMs. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The ions at m/z 745 and 759 are attributed to xylotetrasaccharides bearing a GlcA residue [(GlcA)Xyl4] and a methylated GlcA residue [(MeGlcA)Xyl4], respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The ion at m/z 761 corresponds to the xylan reducing end pentasaccharide, β-d-Xyl-(1→4)-β-d-Xyl-(1→3)-α-l-Rha-(1→2)-α-d-GalA-(1→4)-d-Xyl (X-X-R-GA-X). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Note the partial restoration of the ion signal at m/z 759 corresponding to (MeGlcA)Xyl4 (red arrows) in the gxm1/2/3 mutant overexpressing PtrGXMs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0087370.g006"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0087370-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087370.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>1H-NMR spectra of xylan from the gxm1/2/3 mutant overexpressing PtrGXMs. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Xylooligosaccharides generated by xylanase digestion of xylan were subjected to 1H-NMR analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Resonances are labeled with the position of the assigned proton and the identity of the residue containing that proton. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The resonances of H1 of α-d-GalA, H1 of α-l-Rha, H1 of 3-linked β-d-Xyl, H4 of α-d-GalA, and H2 of α-l-Rha are from the xylan reducing end tetrasaccharide sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>G and M refer to the GlcA- and Me-α-GlcA-substituted xylosyl residues, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Note the partial restoration of the resonances of Me-α-GlcA (red arrows) in the gxm1/2/3 mutant overexpressing PtrGXMs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0087370.g007"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0087370-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087370.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Relative integrated values of GlcA and MeGlcA side chains in xylans from the wild type, gxm1/2/3 and PtrGXM-complemented gxm1/2/3 plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0087370-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0087370.t001"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>a</label><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Ratio of MeGlcA relative to the total GlcA and MeGlcA side chains was calculated by dividing the integrated value of MeGlcA by that of the total GlcA and MeGlcA side chains based on the NMR data in Fig. 7. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Recombinant PtrGXM proteins exhibit glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>To provide definitive proof that PtrGXMs are glucuronoxylan methyltransferases, we examined the glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activity of purified recombinant PtrGXM proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>PtrGXM1, PtrGXM2, PtrGXM3, and PtrGXM4 fused with maltose binding protein were successfully expressed in and purified from E. coli (Fig. 8A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Recombinant PtrGXMs were incubated with radiolabeled S-adenosyl-L-methionine as the methyl donor and GlcA-substituted Xyl4 as the acceptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>It was found that all four recombinant PtrGXMs exhibited a methyltransferase activity capable of transferring the radiolabeled methyl group onto the GlcA-substituted Xyl4 acceptor (Fig. 8B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In contrast, they were unable to transfer the radiolabeled methyl group onto unsubstituted Xyl4, GlcA, or UDP-GlcA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Purified maltose binding protein alone did not show any methyltransferase activity toward any of the substrates tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The PtrGXM-catalyzed reaction products were further analyzed by MALDI-TOF-MS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>It was evident that in addition to the prominent ion peak at m/z 745 attributed to the GlcA-substituted Xyl4 acceptor, the PtrGXM-catalyzed reaction products had another noticeable ion peak at m/z 759 corresponding to MeGlcA-substituted Xyl4 (Fig. 9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The control reaction incubated with maltose binding protein contained only the ion peak for the acceptor (m/z 745). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>These results unequivocally demonstrate that PtrGXM1, PtrGXM2, PtrGXM3, and PtrGXM4 are glucuronoxylan methyltransferases catalyzing the transfer of the methyl group onto GlcA side chains in xylan. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0087370-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087370.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Assay of the glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activity of recombinant PtrGXM proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Maltose binding protein (MBP)-tagged PtrGXM proteins expressed in E. coli were purified with amylose resin, and used for assay of their methyltransferase activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>(A) SDS-polyacylamide gel electrophoresis detection of purified recombinant PtrGXM proteins (5 µg per lane). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Shown are MBP (42.5 kD), and MBP-tagged PtrGXM1 (71.4 kD), PtrGXM2 (71.3 kD), PtrGXM3 (72.7 kD) and PtrGXM4 (72.4 kD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Molecular weight markers are indicated at right. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>(B) Recombinant PtrGXM proteins exhibit a methyltransferase activity that was able to transfer the radiolabeled methyl group from the S-adenosylmethionine donor onto the GlcA-substituted Xyl4 acceptor but not GlcA, UDP-GlcA or Xyl4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Error bars denote the se of three independent assays. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0087370.g008"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0087370-g009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087370.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>MALDI spectra of the reaction products catalyzed by PtrGXM1, PtrGXM2, PtrGXM3, and PtrGXM4 recombinant proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Purified recombinant PtrGXMs were incubated with the GlcA-substituted Xyl4 [(GlcA)Xyl4] acceptor and the S-adenosylmethionine methyl donor and the reaction products were purified and subjected to MALDI analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Note the appearance of a new ion peak at m/z 759 corresponding to (MeGlcA)Xyl4 (red arrows) with an increase of 14 D relative to the (GlcA)Xyl4 acceptor (m/z 745) in the products of reactions incubated with PtrGXMs but not with MBP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The ions at m/z 767 and 781 are attributed to the doubly sodiated species [M+2Na]+ of (GlcA)Xyl4 and (MeGlcA)Xyl4, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0087370.g009"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>We further analyzed the biochemical properties of the recombinant PtrGXMs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activities of PtrGXMs were both time- and protein concentration-dependent (Fig. 10A, B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The optimal temperature for the reactions was 37°C for PtrGXM1 and PtrGXM2 and 45°C for PtrGXM3 and PtrGXM4 (Fig. 10C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>To examine the substrate binding affinities of PtrGXMs, we investigated their kinetic properties using different concentrations of the GlcA-substituted Xyl4 acceptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The K m and V max values were calculated by Lineweaver-Burk analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>It was found that the transfer of the methyl group onto GlcA-substituted Xyl4 by PtrGXMs was dependent on the acceptor concentration (Fig. 11) with apparent K m values of 3.25, 3.98, 0.30 and 0.29 mM and V max of 145, 123, 353 and 737 pmol/min/mg protein for PtrGXM1, PtrGXM2, PtrGXM3, and PtrGXM4, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that PtrGXM3 and PtrGXM4 exhibit much higher substrate affinities for the GlcA-substituted Xyl4 acceptor than PtrGXM1 and PtrGXM2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0087370-g010" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087370.g010</object-id><label>Figure 10</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Biochemical properties of the methyltransferase activities exhibited by the recombinant PtrGXM proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Recombinant PtrGXM proteins were incubated with 14C-labeled S-adenosylmethionine and the (GlcA)Xyl4 acceptor, and the methyltransferase activity was determined by the transfer of the radiolabeled methyl group onto the acceptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Error bars denote the se of three independent assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>(A) Time course of the transfer of the methyl group onto the (GlcA)Xyl4 acceptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>(B) The methyltransferase activity is protein concentration-dependent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>(C) Effect of temperature on the methyltransferase activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0087370.g010"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0087370-g011" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087370.g011</object-id><label>Figure 11</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Kinetic properties of the PtrGXM methyltransferase activities. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Recombinant PtrGXM proteins were assayed for the methyltransferase activity in the presence of various concentrations of the (GlcA)Xyl4 acceptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The results were analyzed by Lineweaver-Burk plots to determine the K m and V max values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0087370.g011"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Populus is one of the many plant species that have been considered for use as lignocellulosic biofuel feedstocks [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The bulk of Populus feedstock is wood, which is mainly composed of cellulose (43–48%), xylan (18–28%) and lignin (19–21%) [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Therefore, a complete understanding of how these wood components are synthesized will be instrumental for a better utilization of this abundant feedstock for biofuel production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have demonstrated that a number of genes, belonging to GT43, GT47, and GT8 families, are involved in the biosynthesis of the backbone and the reducing end sequence of xylan in Populus [11], [13]–[18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Our current finding that four Populus DUF579 domain-containing proteins, PtrGXM1, PtrGXM2, PtrGXM3 and PtrGXM4, are methyltransferases that mediate GlcA methylation in xylan further enriches our understanding of the biosynthesis of xylan, the second most abundant polysaccharide in dicot wood. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Several lines of genetic and biochemical evidence demonstrate that the four PtrGXMs are wood-associated glucuronoxylan methyltransferases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>First, they are expressed in developing wood undergoing secondary wall thickening. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Second, the expression of PtrGXMs except PtrGXM4 is activated by PtrWND2B, a master transcriptional switch regulating the secondary wall biosynthetic program during wood formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Since there are 11 other wood-associated PtrWND homologs in Populus [27], it is possible that PtrGXM4 expression is regulated by other PtrWNDs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Third, PtrGXMs are able to partially restore the deficiency in GlcA methylation in xylan when expressed in Arabidopsis gxm1/2/3 triple mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Fourth, their recombinant proteins exhibit a methyltransferase activity capable of transferring the methyl group from S-adenosyl-L-methionine onto the GlcA-substituted xylooligomer acceptor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>As PtrGXMs are unable to transfer the methyl group onto GlcA or UDP-GlcA, it is clear that the methylation of GlcA occurs after it is added onto the xylan backbone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Further biochemical analysis of PtrGXMs revealed that while PtrGXM1 and PtrGXM2 share similar biochemical properties in the temperature optimum, K m and V max, PtrGXM3 is more similar to PtrGXM4, which is consistent with the phylogenetic analysis showing that PtrGXM1 and PtrGXM2 are a pair of genes likely originated from genome duplication, and so are PtrGXM3 and PtrGXM4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>It is interesting to note that PtrGXM3 and PtrGXM4 have much higher substrate affinities and reaction rates than PtrGXM1 and PtrGXM2, indicating that the GlcA methylation in Populus xylan might be mainly mediated by PtrGXM3 and PtrGXM4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Although the structure of xylan, including the xylan backbone, the reducing end sequence, the degree of acetylation and the frequency of GlcA substitution, between Populus and Arabidopsis is similar [11], [14], the degree of methylation of GlcA side chains differs significantly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The GlcA side chains in Populus xylan are all methylated, whereas only about 60% of the GlcA side chains in Arabidopsis xylan are methylated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>It is currently unknown what factors account for the difference of the degree of GlcA methylation in xylan between Populus and Arabidopsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Enzyme kinetic analysis of PtrGXMs revealed that although PtrGXM1 and PtrGXM2 showed K m values (3.25 and 3.98 mM, respectively) similar to that of the Arabidopsis glucuronoxylan methyltransferase GXM3/GXMT1 (K m = 3.85 mM) that is responsible for the bulk of the GlcA methylation of xylan [22], the K m values of PtrGXM3 and PtrGXM4 (0.30 and 0.29 mM, respectively) were about 8 times lower. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>This finding indicates that PtrGXM3 and PtrGXM4 have a much higher substrate affinity than the Arabidopsis glucuronoxylan methyltransferase, which may enable a complete methylation of the GlcA side chains in Populus xylan during wood formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>It is also possible that the amount of GXM enzymes for GlcA methylation is much higher in Populus wood than in Arabidopsis secondary wall-forming cells, and therefore sufficient glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activities are available for a complete methylation of GlcA side chains in xylan in Populus but not in Arabidopsis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Although expression of PtrGXMs in the Arabidopsis gxm1/2/3 triple mutant restored the level of glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activities close to that of the wild type, the PtrGXM-complemented transgenic plants only resulted in a partial restoration of GlcA methylation in xylan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>This partial complementation could be due to several possible reasons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Since multiple GXMs are expressed in cells undergoing xylan biosynthesis in both Populus and Arabidopsis, it is possible that the expression of one PtrGXM in the gxm1/2/3 mutant may not be sufficient to catch up with the overall rate of xylan biosynthesis so that only a fraction of GlcA side chains are methylated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>It is also possible that GlcA methylation is carried out by a protein complex containing GXMs and other xylan biosynthetic enzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>PtrGXM sequences may have diverged from Arabidopsis GXMs to such a degree that they may not be efficiently incorporated into the Arabidopsis xylan biosynthetic enzyme complex and hence there is not sufficient GXM activity available in the complex to restore GlcA methylation during xylan biosynthesis in planta. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>This possibility appears to be in agreement with the observation that although expression of PtrGXMs in the gxm1/2/3 mutant only led to low levels of GlcA methylation in xylan, the glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activity as assayed in vitro, which does not require the xylan biosynthetic enzyme complex, was restored to a much higher level. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The potential use of Populus as a bioenergy feedstock for biofuel production largely depends on whether it is sufficiently economical to convert cell wall polysaccharides into fermentable sugars [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>One of the major obstacles for efficient utilization of plant biomass for biofuel production is biomass recalcitrance, i.e., resistance of cell walls to enzymatic digestion into sugars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Lignin and xylan, both of which form cross-linking networks in cell walls, contribute to biomass recalcitrance by blocking the access of cellulolytic enzymes to cellulose [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>A reduction in the degree of GlcA methylation in xylan has been shown to enhance xylan release during hydrothermal treatment of cell walls, indicating that decreasing GlcA methylation in xylan could facilitate the conversion of biomass into fermentable sugars [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Our identification of four glucuronoxylan methyltransferase genes in Populus provides molecular tools to modify the cell wall composition of wood so that it would be more suitable for conversion into biofuels. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>There exist 11 genes encoding DUF579 domain-containing proteins in the Populus genome (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Our study has established that four of them, PtrGXM1, PtrGXM2, PtrGXM3, and PtrGXM4, are glucuronoxylan methyltransferases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Four other Populus DUF579 genes (Potri.005G141300, Potri.007G047000, Potri.001G302600, and Potri.009G098800) fall into the same phylogenentic subgroup as Arabidopsis IRX15 and IRX15L that have also been implicated in xylan biosythesis [32], [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Further functional characterization of Populus DUF579 genes will undoubtedly provide new insights into our understanding of the biochemical mechanisms of xylan biosynthesis during wood formation in tree species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Microsome isolation and methyltransferase activity assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Microsomes were isolated from Populus trichocarpa stems or Arabidopsis inflorescence stems according to Kuroyama and Tsumuraya [38] and used for the methyltransferase activity assay [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>The protein concentration in microsome preparations was measured using the Bio-Rad protein assay kit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Each reaction mixture (50 µl) contained 100 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 1 mM CoCl2, 0.5% Triton X-100, 2 µg/µl GlcA-substituted Xyl4 isolated from the gxm2/3 double mutant, S-[14C-methyl] adenosylmethionine (0.1 µCi; American Radiolabeled Chemical), and 200 µg microsomes or 20 µg recombinant PtrGXM proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>For MALDI analysis of GXM-catalyzed reaction products, non-radiolabeled S-adenosylmethionine (1 mM) was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>After 1-h incubation, the reaction mixture was passed through AG1-X4 anion exchange resin [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The bound MeGlcA-substituted xylooligomers were eluted with 3N acetic acid and the eluate was counted for the amount of radioactivity with a PerkinElmer scintillation counter (for radiolabeled S-adenosylmethionine) or subjected to MALDI analysis (for non-radiolabeled S-adenosylmethionine). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>MALDI-TOF MS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The reaction products from the methyltransferase activity assay or xylooligosaccharides isolated from cell walls were used for MALDI-TOF-MS according to Zhong et al. [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>The spectrometer was operated in the positive-ion mode with an accelerating voltage of 30 kV, an extractor voltage of 9 kV, and a source pressure of approximately 8×10−7 torr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>The aqueous sample was mixed (1∶1, v/v) with the MALDI matrix (0.2 M 2,5-dihydroxbenzoic acid and 0.06 M 1-hydroxyisoquinoline in 50% acetonitrile) and dried on a stainless steel target plate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Spectra are the average of 100 laser shots. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Gene expression analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was isolated from various organs of Populus or leaves of transgenic PtrWND2B-overexpressing Populus lines [27] with a Qiagen RNA isolation kit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>They were converted into first strand cDNAs, which were used as templates for real-time quantitative PCR analysis with the QuantiTect SYBR Green PCR kit (Clontech). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>The PCR primers for PtrGXM1 are 5′-actgccatatttacagctggaatg-3′ and 5′-ctactctgggcaaaagggtctgtc-3′; those for PtrGXM2 are 5′-agaatgactgccatatatactgcc-3′ and 5′-ctactctgggcaaaaaggtctgtc-3′; those for PtrGXM3 are 5′-tgacgaggcaccagggaggatgac-3′ and 5′-ctaaggacaaaaaggtctgcccga-3′; and those for PtrGXM4 are 5′-tgatgaggctccagggagaatgaa-3′ and 5′-tggacaaaaaggttttcccgaact-3′. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>The relative expression level was calculated by normalizing the PCR threshold cycle number of each gene with that of a Populus actin reference gene [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The data were the average of three biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>In situ mRNA hybridization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Populus stems were fixed in 2.5% formaldehyde and 0.5% glutaraldehyde, embedded in paraffin, and sectioned for in situ mRNA localization [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The 300-bp 3′ noncoding regions of PtrGXMs were used for generation of digoxigenin-labeled antisense and sense RNA probes with the DIG RNA labeling mix (Roche). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>The 3′ noncoding regions of PtrGXM1 and PtrGXM2 are highly conserved with 70% identity and those of PtrGXM3 and PtrGXM4 share 65% identity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>There is no significant sequence identity between PtrGXM1/2 and PtrGXM3/4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Dot-blot analysis showed that the PtrGXM1 probe had a low degree of cross hybridization with PtrGXM2 RNA and the PtrGXM3 probe had a low degree of cross hybridization with PtrGXM4 RNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>However, no cross hybridization was detected between the PtrGXM1/2 probes and PtrGXM3/4 RNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>After incubation of stem sections with the antisense or sense PtrGXM probes, the hybridization signals were detected by incubating with alkaline phosphatase-conjugated antibodies against digoxygenin and subsequent color development with alkaline phosphatase substrates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Subcellular protein localization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>For subcellular localization of PtrGXMs, their full-length cDNAs were fused in frame with the yellow fluorescent protein (YFP) cDNA and ligated between the CaMV 35S promoter and the nopaline synthase terminator in pBI221 (Clontech). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>The YFP-tagged PtrGXMs together with cyan fluorescent protein (CFP)-tagged Golgi marker (FRA8) [29] were co-transfected into Arabidopsis protoplasts [35], and the fluorescence signals in transfected protoplasts were visualized using a Leica TCs SP2 spectral confocal microscope (Leica Microsystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>At least 10 fluorescence-positive protoplasts were examined and the same subcellular localization pattern was observed for each construct. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Generation of PtrGXM overexpression lines </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The full-length PtrGXM cDNAs were PCR-amplified, sequence-verified and then ligated into the Xba1 site between the cauliflower mosaic virus (CaMV) 35S promoter and the nopaline synthase terminator in the pGPTV binary vector [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The primers for PtrGXM1 are 5′-tccaatatgaggcctaaaggccaa-3′ and 5′-ctactctgggcaaaagggtctgtc-3′; those for PtrGXM2 are 5′-atgaggcctaaaagccagcaa-3′ and 5′-ctactctgggcaaaaaggtctgtc-3′; those for PtrGXM3 are 5′- accatgagacccaacaaaaaccaa -3′ and 5′-ctaaggacaaaaaggtctgcccga-3′; and those for PtrGXM4 are 5′-accatgaggtccaaaaaccaatct-3′ and 5′-ctatggacaaaaaggttttcccga-3′. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>An Nhe1 site was engineered at the 5′ end of each primer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The resulting PtrGXM overexpression constructs were transformed into the Arabidopsis gxm1/2/3 triple mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Transgenic plants were selected on hygromycin, and their inflorescence stems were used for microsome isolation and cell wall extraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>For each construct, at least 64 transgenic lines were generated and stems of representative lines were analyzed for the glucuronoxylan methyltransferase activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Cell wall extraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Inflorescence stems of mature plants were extracted for cell walls according to Zhong et al. [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Cell walls were incubated with 1N KOH to release xylan, and the isolated xylan was further digested with β-xylanase M6 (Megazyme) to produce xylooligosaccharides for structural analyses [29]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>1H-NMR spectroscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>NMR spectra of the xylooligosaccharides from β-xylanase digestion were acquired at 20°C on a 600 MHz spectrometer (599.7 MHz, 1H) using a 3 mm cryogenic triple resonance probe [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>All NMR samples were prepared with 100% D2O. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>For all experiments, 128 transients were collected using a spectral width of 6,000 Hz and an acquisition time of 5-seconds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>The residual water resonance was suppressed by a 1-second presaturation pulse at a field strength of 40 Hz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>All spectra were processed with 0.2-Hz apodization followed by zero-filling to 128 k points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>The 1H NMR assignments were done by comparing them to the NMR spectra data for xylan structure [29], [39]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Generation of recombinant PtrGXM proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>The cDNAs of PtrGXM1, PtrGXM2, PtrGXM3 and PtrGXM4 without the transmembrane domain sequences were PCR-amplified, sequence-verified, and then ligated in frame into the BamH1 site of the bacterial expression vector pMAL, which is tagged with a maltose binding protein (MBP) (New England BioLabs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>The primers for PtrGXM1 are 5′-ccgtcttcccaggaaagtcca-3′ and 5′-ctactctgggcaaaagggtctgtc-3′; those for PtrGXM2 are 5′-tcatcttcccaggaaagttca-3′ and 5′-ctactctgggcaaaaaggtctgtc-3′; those for PtrGXM3 are 5′-tcatctccgagatcaaatcca-3′ and 5′-ctaaggacaaaaaggtctgcccga-3′; and those for PtrGXM4 are 5′-tctcccagaccaaattcatcc-3′ and 5′-ctatggacaaaaaggttttcccga-3′. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>A BamH1 site was engineered at the 5′ end of each primer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>MBP-tagged recombinant PtrGXM proteins expressed in E. coli were purified using amylose resin according to the manufacturer's protocol and confirmed by SDS polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>The experimental data of the quantitative PCR analysis and enzymatic activity assay were subjected to statistical analysis using the Student's t test program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.graphpad.com/quickcalcs/ttest1.cfm">http://www.graphpad.com/quickcalcs/ttest1.cfm</ext-link>), and the quantitative difference between the two groups of data for comparison in each experiment was found to be statistically significant (p&lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4k"><title><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Accession numbers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>The Populus trichocarpa gene locus identifiers (the Populus trichocarpa genome v3.0 at phytozome; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phytozome.net/poplar.php">http://www.phytozome.net/poplar.php</ext-link>) and the GenBank accession numbers for PtrGXM genes are Potri.004g226800 and KF971896, respectively, for PtrGXM1, Potri.003g003800 and KF971897, respectively, for PtrGXM2, Potri.013g102200 and KF971898, respectively, for PtrGXM3, and Potri.019g076300 and KF971899, respectively, for PtrGXM4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>The Arabidopsis Genome Initiative locus identifiers for Arabidopsis GXM genes are GXM1 (At1g09610), GXM2 (At4g09990), and GXM3/GXMT1 (At1g33800). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>We thank the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center for the Arabidopsis T-DNA knockout lines of GXMs and the reviewers for their constructive comments and suggestions. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0087370-Field1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>1 FieldCB, BehrenfeldMJ, RandersonJT, FalkowskiP (1998) Primary production of the biosphere: integrating terrestrial and oceanic components. Science 281: 237–240.9657713 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Carroll1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>2 CarrollA, SomervilleC (2009) Cellulosic biofuels. Annu Rev Plant Biol 60: 165–182.19014348 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Mellerowicz1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>3 MellerowiczEJ, SundbergB (2008) Wood cell walls: biosynthesis, developmental dynamics and their implications for wood properties. Curr Opin Plant Biol 11: 293–300.18434240 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Timell1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>4 TimellTE (1967) Recent progress in the chemistry of wood hemicelluloses. Wood Sci Technol 1: 45–70. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Joshi1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>5 JoshiCP, ThammannagowdaS, FujinoT, GouJQ, AvciU, et al (2011) Perturbation of wood cellulose synthesis causes pleiotropic effects in transgenic aspen. Mol Plant 4: 331–345.21300756 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Vanholme1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>6 VanholmeR, MorreelK, RalphJ, BoerjanW (2008) Lignin engineering. Curr Opin Plant Biol 11: 278–285.18434238 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Liepman1"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>7 LiepmanAH, NairnCJ, WillatsWG, SørensenI, RobertsAW, et al (2007) Functional genomic analysis supports conservation of function among cellulose synthase-like A gene family members and suggests diverse roles of mannans in plants. Plant Physiol 143: 1881–1893.17307900 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Suzuki1"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>8 SuzukiS, LiL, SunYH, ChiangVL (2006) The cellulose synthase gene superfamily and biochemical functions of xylem-specific cellulose synthase-like genes in Populus trichocarpa . Plant Physiol 142: 1233–1245.16950861 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Teleman1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>9 TelemanA, TenkanenM, JacobsA, DahlmanO (2002) Characterization of O-acetyl-(4-O-methylglucurono)xylan isolated from birch and beech. Carbohydr Res 337: 373–377.11841818 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Johansson1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>10 JohanssonMH, SamuelsonO (1977) Reducing end groups in birch xylan and their alkaline degradation. Wood Sci Technol 11: 251–263. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Lee1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>11 LeeC, TengQ, HuangW, ZhongR, YeZ-H (2009) Down-regulation of PoGT47C expression in poplar results in a reduced glucuronoxylan content and an increased wood digestibility by cellulase. Plant Cell Physiol 50: 1075–1089.19395414 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Aspeborg1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>12 AspeborgH, SchraderJ, CoutinhoPM, StamM, KallasA, et al (2005) Carbohydrate-active enzymes involved in the secondary cell wall biogenesis in hybrid aspen. Plant Physiol 137: 983–997.15734915 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Zhou1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>13 ZhouGK, ZhongR, RichardsonEA, HimmelsbachDS, McPhailBT, et al (2007) Molecular characterization of PoGT8D and PoGT43B, two secondary wall-associated glycosyltransferases in poplar. Plant Cell Physiol 48: 689–699.17379696 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Lee2"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>14 LeeC, TengQ, ZhongR, YeZ-H (2011) Molecular dissection of xylan biosynthesis during wood formation in poplar. Mol Plant 4: 730–747.21596688 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Lee3"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>15 LeeC, ZhongR, YeZ-H (2012) Biochemical characterization of xylan xylosyltransferases involved in wood formation in poplar. Plant Signal Behav 7: 332–337.22476457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Zhou2"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>16 ZhouGK, ZhongR, RichardsonEA, MorrisonWH3rd, NairnCJ, et al (2006) The poplar glycosyltransferase GT47C is functionally conserved with Arabidopsis fragile fiber8 . Plant Cell Physiol 47: 1229–1240.16887843 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Kong1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>17 KongY, ZhouG, AvciU, GuX, JonesC, et al (2009) Two poplar glycosyltransferase genes, PdGATL1.1 and PdGATL1.2, are functional orthologs to PARVUS/AtGATL1 in Arabidopsis. Mol Plant 2: 1040–1050.19825678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Li1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>18 LiQ, MinD, WangJP, PeszlenI, HorvathL, et al (2011) Down-regulation of glycosyltransferase 8D genes in Populus trichocarpa caused reduced mechanical strength and xylan content in wood. Tree Physiol 31: 226–236.21450982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Mortimer1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>19 MortimerJC, MilesGP, BrownDM, ZhangZ, SeguraMP, et al (2010) Absence of branches from xylan in Arabidopsis gux mutants reveals potential for simplification of lignocellulosic biomass. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 107: 17409–17414.20852069 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Lee4"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>20 LeeC, TengQ, ZhongR, YeZ-H (2012) Arabidopsis GUX proteins are glucuronyltransferases responsible for the addition of glucuronic acid side chains onto xylan. Plant Cell Physiol 53: 1204–1216.22537759 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Lee5"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>21 LeeC, TengQ, ZhongR, YuanY, HaghighatM, et al (2012) Three Arabidopsis DUF579 domain-containing GXM proteins are methyltransferases catalyzing 4-O-methylation of glucuronic acid on xylan. Plant Cell Physiol 53: 1934–1949.23045523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Urbanowicz1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>22 UrbanowiczBR, PeñaMJ, RatnaparkheS, AvciU, BackeJ, et al (2012) 4-O-methylation of glucuronic acid in Arabidopsis glucuronoxylan is catalyzed by a domain of unknown function family 579 protein. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 109: 14253–14258.22893684 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Lee6"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>23 LeeC, TengQ, ZhongR, YeZ-H (2011) The four Arabidopsis REDUCED WALL ACETYLATION genes are expressed in secondary wall-containing cells and required for the acetylation of xylan. Plant Cell Physiol 52: 1289–1301.21673009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Yuan1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>24 YuanY, TengQ, ZhongR, YeZ-H (2013) The Arabidopsis DUF231 domain-containing protein ESK1 mediates 2-O- and 3-O-acetylation of xylosyl residues in xylan. Plant Cell Physiol 54: 1186–1199.23659919 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Xiong1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>25 XiongG, ChengK, PaulyM (2013) Xylan O-acetylation impacts xylem development and enzymatic recalcitrance as indicated by the Arabidopsis mutant tbl29 . Mol Plant 6: 1373–1375.23340742 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Zhong1"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>26 ZhongR, LeeC, YeZ-H (2010) Functional characterization of poplar wood-associated NAC domain transcription factors. Plant Physiol 152: 1044–1055.19965968 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Zhong2"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>27 ZhongR, McCarthyRL, LeeC, YeZ-H (2011) Dissection of the transcriptional program regulating secondary wall biosynthesis during wood formation in poplar. Plant Physiol 157: 1452–1468.21908685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Tuskan1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>28 TuskanGA, DifazioS, JanssonS, BohlmannJ, GrigorievI, et al (2006) The genome of black cottonwood, Populus trichocarpa (Torr. &amp; Gray). Science 313: 1596–1604.16973872 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Zhong3"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>29 ZhongR, PeñaMJ, ZhouGK, NairnCJ, Wood-JonesA, et al (2005) Arabidopsis Fragile Fiber8, which encodes a putative glucuronyltransferase, is essential for normal secondary wall synthesis. Plant Cell 17: 3390–3408.16272433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Mellerowicz2"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>30 MellerowiczEJ, BaucherM, SundbergB, BoerjanW (2001) Unravelling cell wall formation in the woody dicot stem. Plant Mol Biol 47: 239–274.11554475 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Himmel1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>31 HimmelME, DingSY, JohnsonDK, AdneyWS, NimlosMR, et al (2007) Biomass recalcitrance: engineering plants and enzymes for biofuels production. Science 315: 804–807.17289988 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Brown1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>32 BrownDM, WightmanR, ZhangZ, GomezLD, AtanassovI, et al (2011) Arabidopsis genes IRREGULAR XYLEM (IRX15) and IRX15L encode DUF579-containing proteins that are essential for normal xylan deposition in the secondary cell wall. Plant J 66: 401–413.21251108 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Jensen1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>33 JensenJK, KimH, CocuronJC, OrlerR, RalphJ, et al (2011) The DUF579 domain containing proteins IRX15 and IRX15-L affect xylan synthesis in Arabidopsis. Plant J 66: 387–400.21288268 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Curri1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>34 CurriAL, TimellTE (1959) The constitution of a methyl glucuronoxylan from kapok (Ceiba pentandra). Can J Chem 37: 922–929. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Yoo1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>35 YooSD, ChoYH, SheenJ (2007)  Arabidopsis mesophyll protoplasts: a versatile cell system for transient gene expression analysis. Nat Protoc 2: 1565–1572.17585298 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Becker1"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>36 BeckerD, KemperE, SchellJ, MastersonR (1992) New plant binary vectors with selectable markers located proximal to the left T-DNA border. Plant Mol Biol 20: 1195–1197.1463855 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Teng1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>37 TengQ, EkmanDR, HuangW, ColletteTW (2012) Push-through direct injection NMR: an optimized automation method applied to metabolomics. Analyst 137: 2226–2232.22434060 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Kuroyama1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>38 KuroyamaH, TsumurayaY (2001) A xylosyltransferase that synthesizes β-(1→4)-xylans in wheat (Triticum aestivum L.) seedlings. Planta 213: 231–240.11469588 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Pena1"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>39 PenaMJ, ZhongR, ZhouGK, RichardsonEA, O'NeillMA, et al (2007)  Arabidopsis irregular xylem8 and irregular xylem9: implications for the complexity of glucuronoxylan biosynthesis. Plant Cell 19: 549–563.17322407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0087370-Tamura1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>40 TamuraK, PetersonD, PetersonN, StecherG, NeiM, et al (2011) MEGA5: Molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods. Mol Biol Evol 28: 2731–2739.21546353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
