
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3834105</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24260099</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-26884</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076372</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Association between the Telomerase Reverse Transcriptase (TERT) rs2736098 Polymorphism and Cancer Risk: Evidence from a Case-Control Study of Non-Small-Cell Lung Cancer and a Meta-Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Association between rs2736098 and Cancer Risk</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Haijian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>Naian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Man</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Shikun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Cuihong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Likuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Radiation Oncology, Qilu Hospital Affiliated to Shandong University, Jinan, Shandong Province, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Gastroenterology, Provincial Hospital Affiliated to Shandong University, Jinan, Shandong Province, China</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bhowmick</surname><given-names>Neil A.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Cedars Sinai Medical Center, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>likuan.hu@hotmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: HW LH NQ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: HW YW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: MJ NQ SW CW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YW NQ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: HW. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e76372</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 Wu et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wu et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>A common genetic variant, telomerase reverse transcriptase (TERT) rs2736098, was recently reported to be associated with lung cancer risk in Caucasians. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>In addition, many studies have investigated the role of this polymorphism in the etiology of cancer of various organs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the results of related case-control studies remain inconsistent. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that the genetic risk variant identified in Caucasians may potentially influence the susceptibility to lung cancer in the Chinese population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>To test this hypothesis, a case-control study including 539 non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC) cases and 627 cancer-free controls was conducted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, to investigate the association between rs2736098 and cancer risk, a meta-analysis based on previously published studies and our case-control study was also performed. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Multivariate logistic regression demonstrated that individuals carrying the A allele or the AA genotype exhibited a significantly elevated risk of NSCLC compared with those carrying the G allele or GG genotype (A vs. G: OR = 1.21, 95% CI = 1.02–1.43, P = 0.028; AA vs. GG: OR = 1.48, 95% CI = 1.05–2.09, P = 0.025). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Additionally, this association was stronger among adenocarcinoma cases (AA vs. GG: OR = 1.67, 95% CI = 1.12–2.50, P = 0.013; A vs. G: OR = 1.28, 95% CI = 1.05–1.57, P = 0.016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In the meta-analysis, a borderline significant association between the rs2736098 polymorphism and overall cancer risk was observed (AA vs. GG: OR = 1.25, 95% CI = 1.07–1.46; AA vs. AG+GG: OR = 1.22, 95% CI = 1.06–1.41; additive model: OR = 1.10, 95% CI = 1.02–1.18), and further stratifications demonstrated a moderately increased risk for lung and bladder cancer, Asian ethnicity and hospital-based studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Our results suggest that the rs2736098 polymorphism may contribute to the risk of lung cancer, especially adenocarcinoma, in the Chinese population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>In addition, the current meta-analysis indicates that this genetic variant is only weakly associated with overall cancer risk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>However, the rs2736098 polymorphism may affect individual susceptibility to lung and bladder cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Further studies are needed to validate our findings. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Natural Science Foundation of Shandong Province [ZR2012HM083]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sdstc.gov.cn/">http://www.sdstc.gov.cn/</ext-link>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Worldwide, lung cancer was the leading cause of cancer deaths in males and the second leading cause of cancer deaths in females in 2008. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The geographical and temporal patterns of lung cancer incidence are largely determined by tobacco consumption. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Lung cancer rates are increasing in countries such as China and several other countries in Asia and Africa, where the smoking prevalence continues to either increase or show signs of stability [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Approximately 80% of the 1.3 billion current smokers worldwide live in low- and middle-income countries, with over 300 million in China alone [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC), which includes two main histological types, squamous cell carcinoma (SQC) and adenocarcinoma (ADC), accounts for nearly 85% of all lung cancer cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Despite considerable therapeutic progress, the prognosis of NSCLC patients remains poor [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The development of lung cancer appears to be the result of a complex interaction between environmental exposures and genetic factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Recently, independent genome-wide association studies (GWAS) [4]–[9] have demonstrated that single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in three separate chromosomal regions (5p15, 6p21, and 15q25), which contain genes that regulate nicotinic acetylcholine receptor (nAChR) and telomerase production, are significantly associated with lung cancer risk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>5p15.33, a crucial genomic region for telomere biology, contains two well-known genes: telomerase reverse transcriptase (TERT) and cleft lip and palate trans-membrane 1-like (CLPTM1L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>TERT protein is the telomerase catalytic subunit that elongates telomeres and serves as a key regulator of telomerase activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Telomeres, consisting of TTAGGG repeats that undergo shortening with each cell replication cycle, have long been known to be essential for the preservation of chromosomal integrity [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>As telomerase and the control of telomere length are intimately linked to the development of many tumor types, scientific attention has focused on the possibility of targeting telomerase and telomere-binding proteins in therapeutic strategies against cancer [11], [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Recently, it has been reported that genetic variants at the 5p15.33 locus, which contains the TERT gene (encoding the catalytic subunit of telomerase), are involved in the susceptibility of many tumor types [13], [14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>A common genetic variant, TERT rs2736098, which is located on chromosome 5p15.33, was recently identified as a susceptibility locus for lung cancer in a combined analysis of Icelandic and European sample sets [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>More recently, a Korean population study of 720 lung cancer patients and 720 healthy controls revealed that the TERT A variant genotype is associated with a significantly increased risk of lung cancer [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Given the relevance of this genomic region (5p15.33) to tumor biology and the need to verify these associations in diverse populations with different ancestries, we hypothesized that the risk genetic variant (rs2736098) identified by previous studies of Caucasian and Korean populations may potentially influence the susceptibility to lung cancer in the Chinese Han population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>To test this hypothesis, we genotyped the SNP rs2736098 and analyzed its association with the risk of lung cancer in a case–control study of 539 NSCLC cases and 627 cancer-free controls matched by age and gender in a Chinese Han population. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, many studies have investigated the role of this polymorphism in the etiology of cancer of various organs, including the bladder, liver, and breast [17]–[27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>However, the results of related published case-control studies remain conflicting rather than conclusive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Therefore, to further explore the association between the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism and cancer risk, a meta-analysis based on previously published studies and our case-control study was also performed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Case-control study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a1"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Study population </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>To exclude the possible effects of ethnicity, all subjects in this study were genetically unrelated ethnic Han Chinese. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The cases included 539 newly diagnosed NSCLC patients who were admitted to the Qilu Hospital of Shandong University (Jinan, China) between 2010 and 2012. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Of these NSCLC patients, 293 patients had adenocarcinomas (ADC) and 246 had squamous cell carcinomas (SQC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, 627 cancer-free controls were selected from the same hospital and were frequency-matched to cases by age and sex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Subjects who were relatives or had histories of malignancy and other major diseases were excluded from this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>In addition, a structured questionnaire was completed for each case and control by a trained interviewer to collect demographic data and other relevant information, including age, sex, and smoking status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Those individuals who smoked &lt;1 cigarette per day and for &lt;1 year were defined as nonsmokers; otherwise, the patients were considered smokers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>All participants were given an explanation of the study, and written informed consent was obtained from each participant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>This study was conducted under the approval of the Ethics Committees of Qilu Hospital affiliated to Shandong University. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2a2"><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>DNA extraction and SNP genotyping </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Blood samples were collected from all participants at the time of recruitment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA was extracted from peripheral blood obtained from each participant using the DNA Extraction Kit (Tiangen Biotech (Beijing) Co., Ltd.) according to the manufacturer's protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The TERT SNP rs2736098 was genotyped using the TaqMan methodology in 96-well plates and read with the Sequence Detection Software (SDS, version 1.4) on an Applied Biosystems (ABI) 7500 Real-Time PCR System. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2a3"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The Pearson χ2 test was employed to evaluate the differences in the distributions of selected characteristics between the cases and controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The goodness-of-fit χ2 test was adopted to assess Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) in the controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Multivariate logistic regression analysis was used to estimate odds ratios (ORs) and their 95% confidence intervals (CIs) for the effect of rs2736098 polymorphism on NSCLC risk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>In addition, stratified analyses by histological types were further performed to evaluate the role of rs2736098 in NSCLC risk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>All statistical tests were two-sided, and statistical significance was accepted as P&lt;0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Meta-analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2b1"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Identification and eligibility of relevant studies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>To further investigate the association between the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism and cancer risk, a meta-analysis based on previously published studies and our case-control study was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>We searched the PubMed and ISI Web of Science databases for all articles on the association between the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism and cancer risk (last search update 5th June 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The following search terms were used in isolation and in combination with one another: “telomerase reverse transcriptase or TERT or 5p15.33”, “polymorphism or variant or variation”, and “cancer or carcinoma or tumor”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The search was limited to English language papers and human studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>In addition, we screened the reference lists for all included studies, reviews and meta-analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>When multiple publications reported on the same or overlapping data, we selected the most recent publication with the most subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Studies included in our meta-analysis had to meet the following inclusion criteria: (1) evaluation of the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism and cancer risk; (2) a case-control design; (3) sufficient genotype data for the calculation of odds ratios (OR) with 95% confidence intervals (CIs); and (4) written in English. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The major reasons for exclusion of studies included (1) the lack of a control group; (2) duplicates of previous publications; (3) reviews, comments or editorials; and (4) a lack of usable data on genotype frequencies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b2"><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Data extraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Two investigators (Wu H and Wang Y) extracted information from all eligible publications independently according to the inclusion criteria listed above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Disagreements were resolved by discussion until consensus was achieved on every item. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>In the present study, the following characteristics were collected: the first author's last name, the year of publication, the country of origin, ethnicity, cancer type, the source of the control groups (population- or hospital-based controls), the genotyping method, and the frequencies of genotypes in cases and controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>For studies including subjects of different ethnic groups, genotype frequencies and other information were extracted separately for each ethnic group whenever possible [21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b3"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>We first assessed the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) for the controls in each study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The strength of the association between the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism and cancer risk was evaluated by the odds ratios (ORs) with 95% confidence intervals (CIs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The pooled ORs were calculated for homozygote comparison (AA vs. GG), heterozygote comparison (AG vs. GG), the dominant genetic model (AA+AG vs. GG), the recessive genetic model (AA vs. AG+GG), and the additive genetic model (2*AA+AG vs. 2*GG+AG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Stratified analyses were performed by cancer type (if one cancer type contained less than two individual studies, it was combined into the ‘other cancers’ group), ethnicity and source of the controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The evaluation of the meta-analysis results included an examination of the heterogeneity, an analysis of the sensitivity, and an examination for publication bias. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Heterogeneity was checked by the chi-square-based Q-test [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>If the result of this heterogeneity test was P&lt;0.05, then the pooled ORs were calculated using the random effects model (the DerSimonian and Laird method) [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Otherwise, if the result of this heterogeneity test was P&gt;0.05, the fixed-effects model was selected (the Mantel–Haenszel method) [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>We also used the I2 statistic to efficiently test for heterogeneity, with I2&lt;25%, 25–75% and &gt;75% representing low, moderate and high degrees of inconsistency, respectively [31], [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Additionally, sensitivity analyses were performed by omitting each study to reflect the influence of the individual data on the summary ORs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Finally, literature publication bias was estimated using the Begg's funnel plot and Egger's test (P&lt;0.05 was considered a significant publication bias) [33], [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>All statistical analyses were performed using the STATA software (version 12.0; Stata Corporation, College Station, TX). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Results of the case-control study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a1"><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Population characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The characteristics of the cases and controls are presented in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>A total of 539 NSCLC cases and 627 cancer-free controls were enrolled in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>There were no significant differences in the distributions of sex (P = 0.403) and age (P = 0.688) between the case and control groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Males represented 79.7% of the control group and 77.7% of the case group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Of the 539 NSCLC cases, 293 (54.4%) were adenocarcinomas, and 246 (45.6%) were squamous cell carcinomas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Approximately 51.8% of cases were smokers, compared with 43.1% of controls (P = 0.003). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0076372-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076372.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Selected characteristics of non-small-cell lung cancer cases and controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0076372-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0076372.t001"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: ADC, adenocarcinoma; SQC, squamous cell carcinoma. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>*</label><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>P value was calculated by the χ2 test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3a2"><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Association between the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism and NSCLC risk </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Data for the genotype frequencies and the association between the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism and NSCLC risk are shown in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The distribution of genotypes among the control subjects was in accordance with Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium (P = 0.361). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The multivariate logistic regression model demonstrated that individuals carrying the A allele or AA genotype exhibited a significantly elevated risk of NSCLC compared with those carrying the G allele or GG genotype, after adjusting for age, gender and smoking status (A vs. G: OR = 1.21, 95% CI = 1.02–1.43, P = 0.028; AA vs. GG: OR = 1.48, 95% CI = 1.05–2.09, P = 0.025). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0076372-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076372.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Association between the rs2736098 polymorphism and non-small-cell lung cancer risk in a Chinese Han population. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0076372-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0076372.t002"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval; ADC, adenocarcinoma; SQC, squamous cell carcinoma. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>a</label><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The observed genotype frequency among the control subjects was in agreement with the Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium (P = 0.361). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>b</label><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>ORs and their corresponding 95% CIs were calculated by multivariate logistic regression after adjusting for age, sex and smoking status. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The association between the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism and NSCLC risk was further examined by stratifying the subjects according to tumor histology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>When analyzed according to the histological type, the effect of the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism on the NSCLC risk was significant for adenocarcinomas (A vs. G: OR = 1.28, 95% CI = 1.05–1.57, P = 0.016; AA vs. GG: OR = 1.67, 95% CI = 1.12–2.50, P = 0.013), but not for squamous cell carcinomas (A vs. G: OR = 1.11, 95% CI = 0.89–1.38, P = 0.363; AA vs. GG: OR = 1.23, 95% CI = 0.78–1.94, P = 0.375; AA+AG vs. GG: OR = 1.12, 95% CI = 0.82–1.52, P = 0.487) ( Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Results of the meta-analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3b1"><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Study characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Figure S1 presents the literature search and study selection procedures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Eleven articles [16]–[26] on 12 case-control studies plus the present study, encompassing a total of 10,044 cancer cases and 12,480 controls, were finally included in this meta-analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>These 13 studies included 3 lung cancer studies, 2 bladder cancer studies, 2 hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) studies, and 6 other cancer studies (including breast cancer and cervical cancer, among others). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>There were 5 population-based studies and 8 hospital-based studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Four studies were conducted in European descendants, and 9 studies were conducted in Asian descendants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The genotype distributions in the controls of all studies were in agreement with HWE, with the exception of 2 studies (P&lt;0.05) [21], [24], which were further tested in the sensitivity analyses. Table 3 presents the characteristics of the included studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0076372-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076372.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Characteristics of the studies included in the meta-analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0076372-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0076372.t003"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt106"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: SCCHN, squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck; HCC, hepatocellular carcinoma; ALL, acute lymphoblastic leukemia; PB, population based; HB, hospital based; HWE, Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b2"><title><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Main meta-analysis results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Overall, as shown in Table 4, a borderline significant association was observed between the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism and overall cancer risk in the homozygote comparison (AA vs. GG: OR = 1.25, 95% CI = 1.07–1.46), recessive genetic model (AA vs. AG+GG: OR = 1.22, 95% CI = 1.06–1.41) and additive genetic model (2*AA+AG vs. 2*GG+AG: OR = 1.10, 95% CI = 1.02–1.18) (Figure 1 and Figure 2), but no statistically significant association was found in the heterozygote comparison (AG vs. GG: OR = 1.02, 95% CI = 0.97–1.08) or the dominant genetic model (AA+AG vs. GG: OR = 1.08, 95% CI = 0.99–1.18). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0076372-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076372.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Forest plot of cancer risk associated with the rs2736098 polymorphism (additive model). </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The squares and horizontal lines correspond to the study-specific OR and 95% CI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The area of the squares reflects the study-specific weight (inverse of the variance). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The diamonds represent the summary OR and 95% CI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The rs2736098 polymorphism was weakly associated with an increased risk of cancer in the additive model. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0076372.g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0076372-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076372.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Forest plot of cancer risk associated with the rs2736098 polymorphism (AA vs. GG). </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The rs2736098 polymorphism was associated with an increased risk of cancer in the homozygote comparison (AA vs. GG). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0076372.g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0076372-t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076372.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Meta-analysis of the rs2736098 polymorphism in association with cancer risk. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0076372-t004-4" xlink:href="pone.0076372.t004"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt107"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Phet: test for heterogeneity; OR: odds ratio; CI: confidence interval; N: number of comparisons. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt108"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The figures given in bold indicate statistically significant values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>In the subgroup analysis according to cancer type, significantly increased risk was observed in lung cancer (AA vs. GG: OR = 1.65, 95% CI = 1.34–2.04; dominant model: OR = 1.20, 95% CI = 1.05–1.37; recessive model: OR = 1.58, 95% CI = 1.30–1.92; additive model: OR = 1.24, 95% CI = 1.12–1.36) and bladder cancer (AA vs. GG: OR = 1.55, 95% CI = 1.11–2.15; recessive model: OR = 1.50, 95% CI = 1.01–2.22; additive model: OR = 1.19, 95% CI = 1.04–1.35). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>However, no evidence of association was observed in any genetic model between the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism and the risk of HCC or other cancers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>When stratified by ethnicity, significantly increased risk was observed in the Asian population (AA vs.GG: OR = 1.39, 95% CI = 1.23–1.57; dominant model: OR = 1.14, 95% CI = 1.05–1.24; recessive model: OR = 1.34, 95% CI = 1.19–1.52; additive model: OR = 1.15, 95% CI = 1.09–1.21) in all genetic models tested, with the exception of the heterozygote comparison (AG vs. GG: OR = 1.07, 95% CI = 0.99–1.15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, no significant association was observed in the European population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>In the subgroup analysis by the source of controls, significantly increased risk was observed in hospital-based studies (AA vs. GG: OR = 1.31, 95% CI = 1.12–1.54; dominant model: OR = 1.13, 95% CI = 1.00–1.26; recessive model: OR = 1.26, 95% CI = 1.09–1.45; additive model: OR = 1.13, 95% CI = 1.04–1.22) but was not observed in population-based studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The main results of this meta-analysis and the heterogeneity test are presented in Table 4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b3"><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Test of heterogeneity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>For the overall comparisons, significant heterogeneity was observed in four genetic models (AA vs. GG: Phet . = 0.001, I 2 = 63.0%; AA+AG vs. GG: Phet. = 0.010, I 2 = 54.3%; AA vs. AG+GG: Phet . = 0.002, I 2 = 61.3%; 2*AA+AG vs. 2*GG+AG: Phet . = 0.001, I 2 = 64.8%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>However, the heterogeneity decreased markedly after stratification, especially in the subgroups of lung cancer (AA vs.GG: Phet . = 0.829, I 2 = 0.0%; AG vs.GG: Phet . = 0.969, I 2 = 0.0%; dominant model: Phet . = 0.976, I 2 = 0.0%; recessive model: Phet. = 0.841, I 2 = 0.0%; additive model: Phet . = 0.936, I 2 = 0.0%) and bladder cancer (AA vs.GG: Phet. = 0.275, I 2 = 16.1%; AG vs.GG: Phet . = 0.448, I 2 = 0.0%; dominant model: Phet . = 0.831, I 2 = 0.0%; recessive model: Phet . = 0.169, I 2 = 47.1%; additive model: Phet. = 0.598, I 2 = 0.0%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>When stratified by ethnicity, heterogeneity was not observed in the subgroups of Asian and European populations (Phet.&gt;0.05 in all genetic comparisons) (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b4"><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Sensitivity analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In the sensitivity analyses, the influence of each study on the pooled OR was checked individually by repeating the meta-analysis while omitting each study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Although the genotype distributions of the control groups in the studies by Gago-Dominguez et al. [21] and Zhang et al. [24] did not follow Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium, the corresponding pooled OR and between-study heterogeneity were not significant altered with or without these two studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Sensitivity analyses indicated that the two independent studies by Savage et al. [17] and Liu et al. [18] were the main origin of the heterogeneity in the overall comparisons (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The heterogeneity was effectively decreased or removed after exclusion of these two studies (AA vs. GG: OR = 1.35, 95%CI = 1.22–1.50, Phet . = 0.158, I 2 = 30.3%; dominant model: OR = 1.12, 95%CI = 1.05–1.20, Phet . = 0.119, I 2 = 35.0%; additive model: OR = 1.14, 95%CI = 1.09–1.19, Phet . = 0.142, I 2 = 32.1%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, none of the pooled ORs was significantly affected by any single study, suggesting that the results of this meta-analysis were relatively stable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0076372-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076372.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Sensitivity analysis of the summary OR on the association between the rs2736098 polymorphism and cancer risk under the additive model. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The results were computed by omitting each study (left column) in turn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Meta-analysis random-effect estimates were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Bars, 95% CI. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0076372.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b5"><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Publication bias assessment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Begg's funnel plot and Egger's test were conducted to assess the publication bias of the literatures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 4, Figure S2 and Figure S3, the shapes of the funnel plots did not reveal any evidence of an obvious asymmetry in any comparison model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Moreover, Egger's test further provided statistical evidence of funnel plot symmetry (PEgger's = 0.795 for AA vs. GG; PEgger's = 0.220 for AG vs. GG; PEgger's = 0.123 for dominant model; PEgger's = 0.913 for recessive model and PEgger's = 0.290 for additive model) (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The results did not indicate any evidence of publication bias. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0076372-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076372.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Begg's funnel plot for publication bias (additive model). </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Each point represents a separate study for the indicated association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Log[or], natural logarithm of the odds ratio. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Horizontal line, mean effect size. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0076372.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>In this study, we examined the association of the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism with the risk for NSCLC in a Chinese Han population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, to derive a more precise estimation of the association between this polymorphism and cancer risk, a meta-analysis based on previously published studies and our case-control study was also performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Our multivariate logistic regression model demonstrated that individuals carrying the A allele or AA genotype exhibited a significantly elevated risk of NSCLC compared with those carrying the G allele or GG genotypes after adjusting for age, gender and smoking status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>In the subgroup analysis by histological type, increased cancer risk was observed in adenocarcinomas but not squamous cell carcinomas under the homozygote comparison and the additive genetic model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>In addition, the TERT rs2736098 variant A allele showed a marginally significant association with overall cancer risk. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The TERT rs2736098 polymorphism is mapped to a region of chromosome 5p15.33. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The chromosome 5p15.33 locus contains two well-known genes, telomerase reverse transcriptase (TERT) and cleft lip and palate trans-membrane 1-like (CLPTM1L), which have been implicated in carcinogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Telomerase is expressed in most tumors from virtually all types of cancers, including those of the lung. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Telomerase is a relatively specific cancer target, as normal body cells express little or no telomerase for most of their lifespan [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Telomere dysfunction in tumor initiation accounts for many aspects of chromosomal instability in human cancers [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Cancer cells have been shown to depend on two telomere maintenance mechanisms to gain unlimited proliferation capacity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Generally, telomerase activity is the main mechanism for telomere maintenance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>However, 10%–20% of human tumors activate alternative mechanisms of telomere lengthening [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The gain at chromosomal region 5p15.33, containing TERT, is one of the most frequent genetic events in early stages of non-small-cell lung cancer [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Moreover, it has been reported that telomere length may be associated with the risk of lung cancer [38]–[40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Little is known about the underlying biological mechanism or functional significance of this polymorphism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Although rs2736098 is a synonymous polymorphism, this TERT SNP has been shown to be associated with telomere length [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Many studies have investigated the role of this polymorphism in the etiology of cancer of various organs, including the bladder, liver, and breast, among others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>However, the results of related published case-control studies remain inconsistent [16]–[27].For example, Zhang et al. [24] found that the rs2736098 [A] allele contributed significantly to HCC risk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>However, Ding et al. [20] detected no association between the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism at 5p15.33 and the risk of HCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>In two population-based case-control studies conducted separately among non-Hispanic whites (NHW) and Asian populations, the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism exhibited a significant association with bladder cancer risk among non-Hispanic whites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>However, an association of similar magnitude was not observed in the Asian population [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>In a Polish study of 1,995 breast cancer cases and 2,296 controls, Savage et al. [17] found no evidence that the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism at 5p15.33 was associated with breast cancer risk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>However, in stratified analysis, this variant exhibited evidence of being associated with a reduced risk of breast cancer among individuals with a family history of breast cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Although it is difficult to explain the controversial results in these studies, different genetic backgrounds, cancer types and study designs may contribute to the discrepancies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, our case-control study demonstrated that the AA homozygote in TERT rs2736098 exhibited a significantly increased risk of developing NSCLC (OR = 1.48, 95% CI = 1.05–2.09, P = 0.025), especially adenocarcinoma (OR = 1.67, 95% CI = 1.12–2.50, P = 0.013), compared with those who carry the GG genotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The homozygous AA alleles may be correlated with increased lung adenocarcinoma susceptibility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The results of our case-control study support 5p15.33 (TERT-CLPTM1L) as a susceptibility region for lung cancer in the Chinese population [41], [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>More recently, a Chinese female population study of 501 cancer cases and 576 cancer-free controls also found that the variant allele of rs2736098 was significantly associated with an increased risk of lung cancer, especially in lung adenocarcinomas [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Although the underlying biological mechanisms remain largely unknown, differential expression of TERT has been observed between adenocarcinoma and other histological carcinomas of lung cancer [43]–[45]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>In the current meta-analysis, a borderline significant association between this polymorphism and cancer risk was observed in the overall analysis, with obvious between-study heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>However, when stratified by tumor sites, the subgroups of lung cancer and bladder cancer failed to exhibit heterogeneity, suggesting that different tumor sites might be a potential source of heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Similarly, after stratifying by ethnicity, heterogeneity was largely reduced in both Asian and European populations, suggesting that ethnicity could partly explain the heterogeneity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it may be presumed that the heterogeneity exists mainly owing to differences of ethnicity and tumor types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, in the subgroup analysis by ethnicity, we found that individuals carrying the A allele or AA and AA/AG genotypes of the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism were more likely to exhibit an increased cancer risk among Asians but not among Europeans, possibly because of the differences in genetic backgrounds among different populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Another plausible hypothesis suggests that the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism, a synonymous single nucleotide polymorphism, is only a marker SNP of other functional variants in TERT or other nearby genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>However, this hypothesis remains to be tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>In addition, different study designs and inadequate adjustments for confounding factors might explain, to some extent, the inconsistent results in different cancer types and different populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The evaluation of heterogeneity, influence analysis, and publication bias confirmed the reliability of the meta-analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Some limitations should be addressed in interpreting the results of our case-control study and meta-analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>First, the sample size of our case-control study was relatively small. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Therefore, well-designed population-based studies with large sample sizes and detailed exposure information are needed to further confirm our findings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the meta-analysis was based on unadjusted estimates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>A more precise analysis should be conducted if more detailed individual data are available, which will allow for an adjusted estimate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Further, in the subgroup analysis stratified by cancer type, the number of studies and subjects analyzed was small, and caution should be taken in interpreting these results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>It might be difficult to make a concrete conclusion because few studies were included in the subgroups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Despite these limitations, our meta-analysis also had some advantages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>First, significant data were extracted from the related published case-control studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Second, all studies included in this meta-analysis were case-control investigations and contained available genotype frequencies, which met our inclusion criteria very well. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, we found that the TERT rs2736098 polymorphism identified in the 5p15.33 region in Caucasians may also predispose to lung cancer, especially adenocarcinomas, in the Chinese population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Moreover, meta-analysis by tumor type suggested that this genetic variant may modify individual susceptibility to lung and bladder cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Further studies are required to validate these findings and explain the inconsistent results in different ethnicities and cancer types. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0076372.s001"><label>Checklist S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>PRISMA checklist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>(DOC) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0076372.s001.doc"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0076372.s002"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Flow diagram of the study selection procedure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0076372.s002.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0076372.s003"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Begg's funnel plot for publication bias (AA vs. GG). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0076372.s003.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0076372.s004"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Begg's funnel plot for publication bias (recessive model). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0076372.s004.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>We thank the Key Laboratory of Cardiovascular Remodeling and Function Research of Qilu Hospital for technical assistance. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0076372-Jemal1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>1 JemalA, BrayF, CenterMM, FerlayJ, WardE, et al (2011) Global cancer statistics. CA Cancer J Clin 61: 69–90.21296855 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Brawley1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>2 BrawleyOW (2011) Avoidable cancer deaths globally. CA Cancer J Clin 61: 67–68.21296854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Ramalingam1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>3 RamalingamSS, OwonikokoTK, KhuriFR (2011) Lung cancer: New biological insights and recent therapeutic advances. CA Cancer J Clin 61: 91–112.21303969 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-McKay1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>4 McKayJD, HungRJ, GaborieauV, BoffettaP, ChabrierA, et al (2008) Lung cancer susceptibility locus at 5p15.33. Nat Genet 40: 1404–1406.18978790 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Landi1"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>5 LandiMT, ChatterjeeN, YuK, GoldinLR, GoldsteinAM, et al (2009) A genome-wide association study of lung cancer identifies a region of chromosome 5p15 associated with risk for adenocarcinoma. Am J Hum Genet 85: 679–691.19836008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Wang1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>6 WangY, BroderickP, WebbE, WuX, VijayakrishnanJ, et al (2008) Common 5p15.33 and 6p21.33 variants influence lung cancer risk. Nat Genet 40: 1407–1409.18978787 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Thorgeirsson1"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>7 ThorgeirssonTE, GellerF, SulemP, RafnarT, WisteA, et al (2008) A variant associated with nicotine dependence, lung cancer and peripheral arterial disease. Nature 452: 638–642.18385739 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Hung1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>8 HungRJ, McKayJD, GaborieauV, BoffettaP, HashibeM, et al (2008) A susceptibility locus for lung cancer maps to nicotinic acetylcholine receptor subunit genes on 15q25. Nature 452: 633–637.18385738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Amos1"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>9 AmosCI, WuX, BroderickP, GorlovIP, GuJ, et al (2008) Genome-wide association scan of tag SNPs identifies a susceptibility locus for lung cancer at 15q25.1. Nat Genet 40: 616–622.18385676 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Calado1"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>10 CaladoRT, YoungNS (2009) Telomere diseases. N Engl J Med 361: 2353–2365.20007561 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Harley1"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>11 HarleyCB (2008) Telomerase and cancer therapeutics. Nat Rev Cancer 8: 167–179.18256617 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Martnez1"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>12 MartínezP, BlascoMA (2011) Telomeric and extra-telomeric roles for telomerase and the telomere-binding proteins. Nat Rev Cancer 11: 161–176.21346783 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Mocellin1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>13 MocellinS, VerdiD, PooleyKA, LandiMT, EganKM, et al (2012) Telomerase reverse transcriptase locus polymorphisms and cancer risk: a field synopsis and meta-analysis. J Natl Cancer Inst 104: 840–854.22523397 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Baird1"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>14 BairdDM (2010) Variation at the TERT locus and predisposition for cancer. Expert Rev Mol Med 12: e16.20478107 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Rafnar1"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>15 RafnarT, SulemP, StaceySN, GellerF, GudmundssonJ, et al (2009) Sequence variants at the TERT-CLPTM1L locus associate with many cancer types. Nat Genet 41: 221–227.19151717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Choi1"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>16 ChoiJE, KangHG, JangJS, ChoiYY, KimMJ, et al (2009) Polymorphisms in telomere maintenance genes and risk of lung cancer. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 18: 2773–2781.19773453 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Savage1"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>17 SavageSA, ChanockSJ, LissowskaJ, BrintonLA, RichessonD, et al (2007) Genetic variation in five genes important in telomere biology and risk for breast cancer. Br J Cancer 97: 832–836.17848914 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Liu1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>18 LiuZ, LiG, WeiS, NiuJ, WangLE, et al (2010) Genetic variations in TERT-CLPTM1L genes and risk of squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck. Carcinogenesis 31: 1977–1981.20802237 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Chen1"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>19 ChenH, ChenY, ZhaoY, FanW, ZhouK, et al (2011) Association of sequence variants on chromosomes 20, 11, and 5 (20q13.33, 11q23.3, and 5p15.33) with glioma susceptibility in a Chinese population. Am J Epidemiol 173: 915–922.21350045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Ding1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>20 DingCY, HuLM, HuZB, ShenHB (2011) The relationship between gene polymorphism of telomerase reverse transcriptase and susceptibility to hepatocellular carcinoma. Zhonghua Yu Fang Yi Xue Za Zhi 45: 593–596.22041560 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-GagoDominguez1"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>21 Gago-DominguezM, JiangX, ContiDV, CastelaoJE, SternMC, et al (2011) Genetic variations on chromosomes 5p15 and 15q25 and bladder cancer risk: findings from the Los Angeles-Shanghai bladder case-control study. Carcinogenesis 32: 197–202.21081471 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Wang2"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>22 WangS, WuJ, HuL, DingC, KanY, et al (2012) Common genetic variants in TERT contribute to risk of cervical cancer in a Chinese population. Mol Carcinog 51 Suppl 1: E118–122.22228261 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Hofer1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>23 HoferP, BaierlA, BernhartK, LeebG, MachK, et al (2012) Association of genetic variants of human telomerase with colorectal polyps and colorectal cancer risk. Mol Carcinog 51 Suppl 1: E176–182.22495810 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Zhang1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>24 ZhangC, TianYP, WangY, GuoFH, QinJF, et al (2013) hTERT rs2736098 genetic variants and susceptibility of hepatocellular carcinoma in the Chinese population: a case-control study. Hepatobiliary Pancreat Dis Int 12: 74–79.23392802 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Li1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>25 LiC, YinZ, WuW, LiX, RenY, et al (2013) Genetic Variations in TERT-CLPTM1L Genes and Risk of Lung Cancer in Chinese Women Nonsmokers. PLoS One 8: e64988.23738012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Sheng1"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>26 ShengX, TongN, TaoG, LuoD, WangM, et al (2013) TERT polymorphisms modify the risk of acute lymphoblastic leukemia in Chinese children. Carcinogenesis 34: 228–235.23066086 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Zhao1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>27 ZhaoZ, LiC, YangL, ZhangX, ZhaoX, et al (2013) Significant association of 5p15.33 (TERT-CLPTM1L genes) with lung cancer in Chinese Han population. Exp Lung Res 39: 91–98.23368278 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Lau1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>28 LauJ, IoannidisJP, SchmidCH (1997) Quantitative synthesis in systematic reviews. Ann Intern Med 127: 820–826.9382404 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-DerSimonian1"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>29 DerSimonianR, LairdN (1986) Meta-analysis in clinical trials. Control Clin Trials 7: 177–188.3802833 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Mantel1"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>30 MantelN, HaenszelW (1959) Statistical aspects of the analysis of data from retrospective studies of disease. J Natl Cancer Inst 22: 719–748.13655060 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Higgins1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>31 HigginsJP, ThompsonSG (2002) Quantifying heterogeneity in a meta-analysis. Stat Med 21: 1539–1558.12111919 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Higgins2"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>32 HigginsJP, ThompsonSG, DeeksJJ, AltmanDG (2003) Measuring inconsistency in meta-analyses. BMJ 327: 557–560.12958120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Egger1"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>33 EggerM, Davey SmithG, SchneiderM, MinderC (1997) Bias in meta-analysis detected by a simple, graphical test. BMJ 315: 629–634.9310563 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Begg1"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>34 BeggCB, MazumdarM (1994) Operating characteristics of a rank correlation test for publication bias. Biometrics 50: 1088–1101.7786990 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Feldser1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>35 FeldserDM, HackettJA, GreiderCW (2003) Telomere dysfunction and the initiation of genome instability. Nat Rev Cancer 3: 623–627.12894250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Gnes1"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>36 GünesC, RudolphKL (2013) The role of telomeres in stem cells and cancer. Cell 152: 390–393.23374336 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Kang1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>37 KangJU, KooSH, KwonKC, ParkJW, KimJM (2008) Gain at chromosomal region 5p15.33, containing TERT, is the most frequent genetic event in early stages of non-small cell lung cancer. Cancer Genet Cytogenet 182: 1–11.18328944 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Lan1"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>38 LanQ, CawthonR, GaoY, HuW, HosgoodHD3rd, et al (2013) Longer telomere length in peripheral white blood cells is associated with risk of lung cancer and the rs2736100 (CLPTM1L-TERT) polymorphism in a prospective cohort study among women in China. PLoS One 8: e59230.23555636 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Shen1"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>39 ShenM, CawthonR, RothmanN, WeinsteinSJ, VirtamoJ, et al (2011) A prospective study of telomere length measured by monochrome multiplex quantitative PCR and risk of lung cancer. Lung Cancer 73: 133–137.21507503 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Jang1"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>40 JangJS, ChoiYY, LeeWK, ChoiJE, ChaSI, et al (2008) Telomere length and the risk of lung cancer. Cancer Sci 99: 1385–1389.18452563 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Hsiung1"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>41 HsiungCA, LanQ, HongYC, ChenCJ, HosgoodHD, et al (2010) The 5p15.33 locus is associated with risk of lung adenocarcinoma in never-smoking females in Asia. PLoS Genet 6. pii: e1001051.20700438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Jin1"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>42 JinG, XuL, ShuY, TianT, LiangJ, et al (2009) Common genetic variants on 5p15.33 contribute to risk of lung adenocarcinoma in a Chinese population. Carcinogenesis 30: 987–990.19369581 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Lantuejoul1"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>43 LantuejoulS, SoriaJC, Moro-SibilotD, MoratL, VeyrencS, et al (2004) Differential expression of telomerase reverse transcriptase (hTERT) in lung tumours. Br J Cancer 90: 1222–1229.15026805 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Lantujoul1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>44 LantuéjoulS, SalonC, SoriaJC, BrambillaE (2007) Telomerase expression in lung preneoplasia and neoplasia. Int J Cancer 120: 1835–1841.17311257 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0076372-Zhu1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>45 ZhuCQ, CutzJC, LiuN, LauD, ShepherdFA, et al (2006) Amplification of telomerase (hTERT) gene is a poor prognostic marker in non-small-cell lung cancer. Br J Cancer 94: 1452–1459.16641908 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
