
<article article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPGSJ//DTD full length article DTD version 7.0 XML//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName ajarticle_v7_x.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 7.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName naturesa2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Transl Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Transl Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Translational Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2158-3188</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3309462</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">tp201113</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/tp.2011.13</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Hostility in adolescents and adults: a genome-wide association study of the Young Finns </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running">Genome-wide association study of hostility</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Merjonen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Keltikangas-Järvinen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jokela</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seppälä</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lyytikäinen</surname><given-names>L-P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pulkki-Råback</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kivimäki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Elovainio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kettunen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ripatti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kähönen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Viikari</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Palotie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peltonen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="note1"><sup>✠</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raitakari</surname><given-names>O T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lehtimäki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>IBS, Unit of Personality, Work and Health Psychology, University of Helsinki</institution>, Helsinki, <country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Clinical Chemistry, Centre for Laboratory Medicine, Tampere University Hospital</institution>, Tampere, <country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Medical School, University of Tampere</institution>, Tampere, <country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution>Finnish Institute of Occupational Health</institution>, Helsinki, <country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution>THL</institution>, Helsinki, <country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution>Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute, Wellcome Trust Genome Campus, Hinxton</institution>, Cambridge, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><institution>FIMM, Institute for Molecular Medicine Finland, University of Helsinki</institution>, Helsinki, <country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff8"><label>8</label><institution>Department of Clinical Physiology, Tampere University Hospital</institution>, Tampere, <country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff9"><label>9</label><institution>Department of Medicine, University of Turku and Turku University Hospital</institution>, Turku, <country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff10"><label>10</label><institution>Department of Clinical Physiology, Turku University Hospital and Research Centre of Applied and Preventive Cardiovascular Medicine, University of Turku</institution>, Turku, <country>Finland</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label><institution>IBS, Unit of Personality, Work and Health Psychology, University of Helsinki, P.O. Box 9, FIN-00014 University of Helsinki</institution>, Helsinki, <country>Finland</country>. E-mail: <email>liisa.keltikangas-jarvinen@helsinki.fi</email></corresp><fn fn-type="present-address" id="note1"><label>✠</label><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Deceased. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>06</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>06</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e11</fpage><lpage/><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>05</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>05</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-No Derivative Works 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Hostility is a multidimensional personality trait with changing expression over the life course. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>We performed a genome-wide association study (GWAS) of the components of hostility in a population-based sample of Finnish men and women for whom a total of 2.5 million single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) were available through direct or in silico genotyping. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Hostility dimensions (anger, cynicism and paranoia) were assessed at four time points over a 15-year interval (age range 15–30 years at phase 1 and 30–45 years at phase 4) in 982–1780 participants depending on the hostility measure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Few promising areas from chromosome 14 at 99 cM (top SNPs rs3783337, rs7158754, rs3783332, rs2181102, rs7159195, rs11160570, rs941898, P values &lt;3.9 × 10−8 with nearest gene Enah/Vasp-like (EVL)) were found suggestively to be related to paranoia and from chromosome 7 at 86 cM (top SNPs rs802047, rs802028, rs802030, rs802026, rs802036, rs802025, rs802024, rs802032, rs802049, rs802051, P values &lt;6.9 × 10−7 with nearest gene CROT (carnitine O-octanoyltransferase)) to cynicism, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Some shared suggestive genetic influence for both paranoia and cynicism was also found from chromosome 17 at 2.8 cM (SNPs rs12936442, rs894664, rs6502671, rs7216028) and chromosome 22 at 43 cM (SNPs rs7510759, rs7510924, rs7290560), with nearest genes RAP1 GTPase activating protein 2 (RAP1GAP2) and KIAA1644, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>These suggestive associations did not replicate across all measurement times, which warrants further study on these SNPs in other populations. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>hostility</kwd><kwd>GWAS</kwd><kwd>personality</kwd><kwd>gene</kwd><kwd>development</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Hostility is a personality trait characterizing how trustworthy individuals perceive other people and how they handle these feelings toward others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The cognitive component of hostility characterizes cynical and distrustful attitudes, which is the primary reference of the term hostility,1 whereas the affective component reflects feelings of irritability and anger. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The behavioral component covers expression of these attitudes and feelings as either expressing them out, that is, aggression, or as suppressing or repressing them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Hostility traits have been found to be related to various social and health problems, such as criminality and violence,2, 3 isolation and relationship aggression,4 depression,5 cardiovascular diseases6 and all-cause mortality risk,7 although the findings are not entirely consistent.8 Identifying the origins of hostility may help to understand the developmental paths related to hostility and to develop effective preventions to reduce problems related to hostile behaviors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Both genetic and environmental factors are involved in the development of hostility,9 with heritability estimated to be ∼30–50%.10, 11, 12 However, the molecular nature of the genetic background and the specific regions of the genome that underlie hostility remain mainly unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, only one genome scan study of hostility has been published to date.13 That study covered 387 autosomal short-tandem-repeat polymorphisms and did not find significant linkage with hostility.13 In the present study, we report a large-scale genome-wide association study (GWAS) of hostility where over 2.5 million single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) were analyzed, thereby mapping the most potentially significant areas of the genome regarding hostility for further inspection and providing preliminary evidence of the genetic basis of hostility. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>As cognitive, affective and behavioral components of hostility may vary in their etiology and have different genetic backgrounds,14 we used three different scales of hostility, each of which was measured four times over a 15-year time span extending from adolescence and young adulthood (age 15–30 years) into adulthood (age 30–45 years) in a Caucasian Finnish population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>It has been argued that personality is still transient and amenable to environmental effects in young adulthood, but between 30 and 50 years of age, it begins to stabilize and genetic effects become more prominent.11 Thus, an additional aim of the present study was to test whether genetic effects underlying hostility are stable across different ages or whether they gain importance with advanced age in adulthood. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Population and study design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Participants were from the population-based prospective Young Finns (YF) cohort study, which started in 1980 with 3596 boys and girls from different geographical areas of Finland.15 The genome of the participants was genotyped in 2009 and personality tests assessing hostility were administered in four follow-up phases in 1992, 1997, 2001 and 2007. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>At the baseline of the present study (1992), participants were 15, 18, 21, 24, 27 and 30 years old, and they were followed up for 15 years until they were 30, 33, 36, 39, 42 and 45 years, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The final study sample with complete measurements consisted of 982–1781 men and women depending on the measure of hostility (n for anger between the four measurement phases ranges between 1619 and 1776, n for cynicism between 1622 and 1781 and n for paranoia between 1622 and 1780). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Measures of hostility components </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>We assessed three aspects of hostility, that is, cynicism and paranoia, which both reflect the cognitive component, and anger, which represents the affective component. Cynicism was measured with a seven-item self-completion cynicism scale derived from the Minnesota Multiphasic Personality Inventory (for example, ‘It is safer to trust nobody').16, 17Paranoia was assessed with the six-item self-completion paranoid ideation subscale of the Symptom Checklist-90R (for example, ‘Others do not give me proper credit for my achievements').18 Anger was assessed with a seven-item Irritability Scale of the Buss-Durkee Hostility Inventory (for example, ‘I lose my temper easily but get over it quickly').19 Detailed description of the scales has been published in previous papers.9, 20 Response format for all scales was on a five-point scale, ranging from totally disagree (1) to totally agree (5), and the mean of each scale was calculated for only those who had responded to at least 50% of the items on the scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In addition, for each scale we calculated the mean score over the four measurements in 1992, 1997, 2001 and 2007 to capture a more stable trait of hostility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Reliability for the four-measurement mean score was high, with Cronbach's α being 0.85, 0.84 and 0.82 for cynicism, paranoia and anger scales, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Genotyping and quality control of YF study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The genome-wide SNP genotyping of YF study was done by a custom Illumina BeadChip (San Diego, CA, USA) containing 670 000 SNPs and copy-number variant probes from 2442 YF participants (1123 males and 1319 females). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The custom 670K chip shares 562 643 SNPs in common with the Illumina Human610 BeadChip. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Genotypes were called using Illumina's clustering algorithm (Illuminus).21 A total of 2556 samples were genotyped. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>After initial clustering, we removed 2 subjects for poor call rates (call rate &lt;0.90), and 54 samples failed subsequent quality control (that is, duplicated samples, heterozygosity, low call rate or custom SNP fingerprint genotype discrepancy). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The following filters were applied to the remaining data: minor allele frequency 0.01, genotyped call rate (GENO) 0.05, MIND 0.05 and Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium 1 × 10−6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Of 2500 individuals, 3 were removed for low genotyping (MIND &gt;0.05), 11 766 markers were excluded based on Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium test (P⩽1 × 10−6), 7746 SNPs failed missingness test (GENO &gt;0.05), 34 596 SNPs failed frequency test (minor allele frequency &lt;0.01) and 1 individual failed gender check. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>None were removed by subsequent heterozygosity check. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>In that point, there were 546 770 SNPs and 2496 individuals who were utilized to generate an identity-by-descent matrix file in PLINK.22 There were 51 pairs of individuals with pi-hat &gt;0.2, and thus these individuals were removed because of possible relatedness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>One of the pair was removed using greater missingness as criteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>After final frequency and genotyping running, there was 546 677 SNPs available from a sample of 2442 YF subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Genotype imputation was performed for the YF SNP data using MACH23 with the HapMap (phase II, release 22 CEU, NCBI build 36, dbSNP 126) haplotypes as reference. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Statistics of GWAS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Quasi-continuous mean variables of hostility subscales were Box–Cox transformed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Residuals were obtained using linear regression model in which hostility variables were adjusted for sex and age in order to control the most obvious environmental factors related to hostility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Residuals were standardized (mean 0, s.d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>1) and their distributions were confirmed to be very close to normal by visual Q-Q plot analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>We also verified that the estimates for the β-coefficients from the GWAS are not driven by few outliers by plotting leverage vs standardized residuals plots for the residuals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>We have an 80% power of identifying SNPs that explain at least 4% of the variability with sample size of 985 (mean of four measurement). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>For the four measurements within each hostility scale the sample sizes are increased to ∼1780 subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>These analyses were powered to detect the effects of common variants down to 2.1% of explained variability. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Tests for additive genetic effects were carried out on a linear scale using linear regression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Genotypes were coded as 0, 1 or 2 when the SNP was genotyped and by dosage (scale 0–2) when imputed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>These tests were performed to assess association of SNPs with the standardized residuals using PLINK22 for the genotyped data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>ProbABEL24 was used to fit the model, taking account of the genotype uncertainty at imputed SNPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The P-values were combined from the analysis by favoring genotyped tests over imputed ones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The Q-Q and Manhattan plots were drawn for the analysis of the results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The P-value for genome-wide significance was set at P&lt;9 × 10−8, corresponding to a target α of 0.05 with a Bonferroni correction for 550 000 million independent tests with direct genotyping. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Cynicism was normally distributed, whereas the distributions of paranoia and anger were slightly positively skewed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Thus Box–Cox transformations were used for all the outcomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>As shown in Table 1, the average age of the genotyped sample is 37.56 (s.d.=5.03). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The bivariate correlations between hostility measures are shown in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The stability of the measures (r's range 0.45–0.69) as well as their bivariate correlations (r's range 0.38–0.77) are moderate (all P's &lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Cynicism and paranoia correlate higher with each other than with anger. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Younger participants scored higher on the three hostility measures (r=−0.12, P&lt;0.001, r=−0.08, P=0.01, and r=−0.05, P=0.123 for mean cynicism, paranoia and anger, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Females scored higher on anger (r=−0.20, P&lt;0.001) and males on cynicism (r=0.18, P&lt;0.001) and paranoia (r=0.09, P&lt;0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>All the subsequent models were therefore adjusted for sex and age. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>We tested 2 577 640 SNPs for association with the three hostility scales measured in four different time points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The top SNPs derived from SNPs with P-values ⩽1 × 10−5 are presented in the Tables 3 and 4. Table 3 shows the top SNPs when hostility is measured as a mean score of four measurement phases ((phase 1+phase 2+phase 3+phase 4/4)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Chromosome 14 at 99 cM (SNPs rs3783337, rs7158754, rs3783332, rs2181102, rs7159195, rs11160570, rs941898) predicted suggestively the mean paranoia during the 15 years at the genome-wide statistical significance (P&lt;9 × 108, Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>However, this suggestive association did not replicate at each single measurement point over time (Table 4). Table 4 shows the top SNPs when the most significant associations are selected, irrespective of measurement phase (selected from phase 1, phase 2, phase 3 or phase 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The most significant SNP suggestively associated with anger was found on chromosome 17 at 11 cM SNP rs11656526 (P-value &lt;9 × 10−8, Table 4) for anger measured in 1992. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Also, loci on chromosome 6 at 6.7 cM seemed promising when predicting anger in 2007, which shows the most reliable results for anger according to Q-Q plot analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>However, these suggestive associations did not replicate in other measurement years, and hence the stability of these associations was weak. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Table 5 shows those SNPs that replicate at different measurement phases or at different scales. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The most systematic replicating evidence for suggestive genetic effects was found for cynicism, although the significance levels (P&lt;1 × 105) did not reach the Bonferroni corrected genome-wide significance level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Promising SNPs suggestively predicting cynicism were found on chromosome 7 at 86 cM (rs802047, rs802028, rs802030, rs802026, rs802036, rs802025, rs802024, rs802032, rs802049, rs802051), which replicated on two different measurements of cynicism (1992 and 1997) as well as the first four of the SNPs on above on the mean of all four measurements of cynicism (Table 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>In addition, SNPs in chromosome 22 at 43 cM (rs7510759, rs7510924) were associated with cynicism in 1997 and the mean of all four measurements of cynicism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The genetic background of different components of hostility appears to be largely distinct from each other, although a group of SNPs from chromosome 17 at 2.8 cM (rs12936442, rs894664, rs6502671, rs7216028) and from chromosome 22 at 43 cM (rs7510759, rs7510924, rs7290560) and at 36 cM (rs8136107) were suggestively associated with both cynicism and paranoia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Replications of the genetic linkage between different measurement of hostility and different measurement years are presented in Table 5. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Our study reports results of a large-scale GWA analysis of hostility, with hostility measured in four follow-ups across 15 years of time span with three different scales. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Although only few associations achieved genome-wide significance, many associations approached significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>We attempted to capture more reliable findings of the genotype over time by using the mean of hostility levels in the four time points as the outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Most of the suggestive associations did not replicate across measurement times, which undermines the robustness of the single significant associations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>These suggestive associations should therefore be interpreted with appropriate caution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The inconsistent findings resemble those from many previous GWA studies of personality, most of which have not yet found robust evidence for specific candidate genes.13, 25, 26, 27 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The strongest associations were found for mean score of paranoia with a number of closely linked SNPs in chromosome 14 at 99 cM, although this suggestive association had limited replicability over time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Chromosome 14 at∼100 cM has been previously linked to neuroticism and anxiety27, 28 and at 103 cM to bipolar disorder.29 The present study thus adds evidence that this region may include genetic markers or determinants for general anxiety and distrust (that is, paranoia) as well as for susceptibility to psychiatric diagnoses involving distrust against others. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The finding that the mean paranoia for four different time points had significant genetic linkage, but single measurements of paranoia did not, may imply that paranoia as a stable trait has wider genetic basis, but high distrust in one point in time may depend more on transient environmental factors and be more prone to fluctuate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The closest gene for the found paranoia linked SNPs is EVL gene in chromosome 14, which is proposed as a possible candidate gene for colorectal cancer.30 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Another significant genomic region found in the current study is in chromosome 17 at 2.8 cM, which was suggestively linked with both paranoia and cynicism in the most recent measurement when the participants were at age 30–45 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The closest gene for this region is RAP1GAP2, which affects GTPase-activating protein, has a role in regulating the platelet aggregation, and is expressed especially in heart, testis and blood leukocytes, and also in stomach, pancreas and intestines, and slightly in brain.31 Thus, this might also be a possible link between hostility and health problems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Both cynicism and paranoia mean scores were also associated with a region in chromosome 22 at 36 cM and at 43 cM for which the closest gene is KIAA1644. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Neither RAP1GAP2 nor KIAA1644 have previously been linked to personality traits, although chromosome 22 at 36 cM has been linked to bipolar disorder and schizophrenia.32 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Although the results for cynicism did not reach the Bonferroni corrected statistical significance level, there were many marginally significant associations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Especially, areas on chromosome 7 at 86 cM were related to cynicism in 1992, 1997 and mean of cynicism measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The nearest gene for this region is CROT (carnitine O-octanoyltransferase) that affects fatty acid functioning in a cell level and is expressed at least in mice almost everywhere in the body, especially in liver and intestines, and also slightly in heart and brain.33 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The observed suggestive associations may have some theoretical implications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Theoretically, cynicism is assumed to develop more in response to environmental experiences, which may explain the less significant relation to genetic background. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>However, it may be that there are multiple overlapping genetic effects and gene × gene and gene × environment interactions that prevent SNPs to reach the Bonferroni corrected significance level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Same locations in chromosome 17 at 2.8 cM and chromosome 22 at 36 and 43 cM were associated with both cynicism and paranoia, which may imply shared genetic background with these hostility dimensions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Such hostile attitudes might be seen as core of the hostility construct.1, 7, 9 Anger, on the other hand, is theoretically a separate construct having its developmental roots in temperament-like characteristics.34 Our finding that anger did not share similar genetic background with cynicism or paranoia implies that the consideration of anger as a separate construct seems justified also from the genetic perspective. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The phenotypic and genotypic differences behind hostility measures may thus in part explain the mixed findings between hostility and cardiovascular health.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Measuring complex personality traits, like hostility, involves challenges of accurate measurement of the phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Measurement error due to imperfect assessment of the phenotype reduces the ability to capture stabile phenotype over time (test–retest correlations) and introduces time-specific variance in the measures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The lack of adjustment for relevant environmental factors influencing personality development may partly explain why the GWAS findings of personality traits rarely replicate in different time points or in different samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>This is not a unique problem to our study, as previous studies with well-established personality scales, for example, Temperament and Character Inventory25, 35 and ‘Big Five',26, 36, 37 have rarely found consistent associations with GWAS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In summary, this GWAS showed preliminary evidence for specific regions possibly related to hostility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The suggestive associations were small in magnitude and did not replicate across all measurement times, and thus they warrant further study in other populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Single SNPs are likely to have small and thereby variable effects on personality traits, and many real effects may be lost in plenty of associations because of insufficient statistical power and measurement imprecision related to the identification of the phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Accumulating evidence from several cohorts should provide more accurate and reliable data on the genetic background of hostility and other personality traits. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>We thank Ville Aalto and Irina Lisinen for their valuable help in data management. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>This study was supported by the Academy of Finland (Grant No. 123621 (LP-R)), the University of Helsinki Research Funds (Project No. 2106012 (LP-R)), the Turku University Hospital research grants (OTR), Tampere University Hospital Medical Fund (TL), Emil Aaltonen Foundation (TL), the Signe and Ane Gyllenberg Foundation (LK-J), the Alfred Kordelin Foundation (PM), the Otto A Malm Foundation (PM), the Jenny and Antti Wihuri Foundation (PM) and the National Doctoral Programme of Psychology in Finland (PM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>MiKi is supported by the National Heart Lung and Blood Institute (R01HL36310), US, NIH: National Institute on Aging (R01AG013196; R01AG034454), US, NIH; the Academy of Finland, EU New OSH ERA research program, and the BUPA Foundation Specialist Research Grant, UK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The Young Finns study is also financially supported by the Academy of Finland (Grant No. 77841, 210283, 117832 and 121584), the Social Insurance Institution of Finland, Juho Vainio Foundation, Finnish Foundation of Cardiovascular Research and Finnish Cultural Foundation. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Disclaimer.The funding sources had neither been involved in the submission of the manuscript nor in the decision to publish the data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><notes><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></notes></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>GreenglassERJulkunenJConstruct validity and sex differences in Cook-Medley hostilityPerson Individ Diff198910209218 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib2"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>SoykaMGrazCBottlenderRDirschedlPSchoechHClinical correlates of later violence and criminal offences in schizophreniaSchizophr Res200794899817509834 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib3"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Abu-AkelAAbushua'lehK‘Theory of mind' in violent and nonviolent patients with paranoid schizophreniaSchizophr Res2004694653 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib4"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>VandervoortDQuality of social support in mental and physical healthCurr Psychol199918205222 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib5"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>HeponiemiTElovainioMKivimäkiMPulkkiLPuttonenSKeltikangas-JärvinenLThe longitudinal effects of social support and hostility on depressive tendenciesSoc Sci Med2006631374138216709439 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib6"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>ChidaYSteptoeAThe association of anger and hostility with future coronary heart disease: a meta-analytic review of prospective evidenceJ Am Coll Cardiol20095393694619281923 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib7"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>MillerTQSmithTWTurnerCWGuijarroMLHalletAJA meta-analytic review of research on hostility and physical healthPsychol Bull19961193223488851276 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib8"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>RozanskiABlumenthalJAKaplanJImpact of psychological factors on the pathogenesis of cardiovascular disease and implications for therapyCirculation1999992192221710217662 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib9"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>MerjonenPPulkki-RåbackLLipsanenJLehtimäkiTRontuRViikariJDevelopment of adulthood hostile attitudes: childhood environment and serotonin receptor gene interactionsPers Relationship201118184197 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib10"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>HurYMNonadditive genetic effects on hostility in South Korean adolescent and young adult twinsTwin Res Hum Genet2006963764117032543 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib11"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>RebolloIBoomsmaDIGenetic analysis of anger: genetic dominance or competitive sibling interactionBehav Genet20063621622816402285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib12"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>CoccaroEFBergemanCSKavoussiRJSeroczynskiADHeritability of aggression and irritability: a twin study of the Buss-Durkee aggression scales in adult male subjectsBiol Psychiatry1997412732849024950 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib13"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>KnoxSSWilkJBZhangYWeidnerGEllisonRCA genome scan for hostility: the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute Family Heart StudyMol Psychiatry2004912412614610523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib14"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>GustavssonJPPedersenNLAsbergMSchallingDExploration into the sources of individual differences in aggression-, hostility- and anger-related (AHA) personality traitsPers Individ Diff19962110671071 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib15"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>RaitakariOTJuonalaMRönnemaaTKeltikangas-JärvinenLRäsänenLPietikäinenMCohort profile: the Cardiovascular Risk in Young Finns StudyInt J Epidemiol2008371220122618263651 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib16"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>ComreyALA factor analysis of items on the MMPI paranoia scaleEduc Psychol Meas19581899107 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib17"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>ComreyALA factor analysis of items on the MMPI hysteria scaleEduc Psychol Meas195717586592 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib18"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>DerogatisLRClearyPAConfirmation of the dimensional structure of the SCL-90: a study in construct validationJ Clin Psychol197733981989 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib19"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>BussAHDurkeeAAn inventory for assessing different kinds of hostilityJ Consult Psychol19572134334913463189 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib20"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>MerjonenPPulkki-RåbackLPuttonenSKeskivaaraPJuonalaMTelamaRAnger is associated with subclinical atherosclerosis in low SES but not in higher SES men and women. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The Cardiovascular Risk in Young Finns StudyJ Behav Med200831354417940862 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib21"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>TeoYYInouyeMSmallKSGwilliamRDeloukasPKwiatkowskiDPA genotype calling algorithm for the Illumina BeadArray platformBioinformatics2007232741274617846035 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib22"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>PurcellSNealeBTodd-BrownKThomasLFerreiraMABenderDPLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analysesAm J Hum Genet20078155957517701901 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib23"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>LiYAbecasisGRMach 1.0: rapid haplotype reconstruction and missing genotype inferenceAm J Hum Genet2006S792290 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib24"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>AulchenkoYSRipkeSIsaacsAvan DuijnCMGenABEL: an R library for genome-wide association analysisBioinformatics2007231294129617384015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib25"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>VerweijKJHZietschBPMedlandSEGordonSDBenyaminBNyholtDRA genome-wide association study of Cloninger's temperament scales: implications for the evolutionary genetics of personalityBiol Psychol20108530631720691247 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib26"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>TerraccianoASannaSUdaMDeianaBUsalaGBusoneroFGenome-wide association scan for five major dimensions of personalityMol Psychiatry20101564765618957941 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib27"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>WrayNRMiddeldorpCMBirleyAJGordonSDSullivanPFVisscherPMGenome-wide linkage analysis of multiple measures of neuroticism of 2 large cohorts from Australia and the NetherlandsArch Gen Psychiatry20086564965818519823 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib28"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>MiddeldorpCMHottengaJJSlagboomPESullivanPFde GeusEJPosthumaDLinkage on chromosome 14 in a genome-wide linkage study of a broad anxiety phenotypeMol Psychiatry200813848917700576 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib29"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>BurtonPRClaytonDGCardonLRCraddockNDeloukasPDuncansonAGenome-wide association study of 14,000 cases of seven common diseases and 3,000 shared controlsNature200744766167817554300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib30"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>SjöblomTJonesSWoodLDParsonsDWLinJBarberTDThe consensus coding sequences of human breast and colorectal cancersScience200631426827416959974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib31"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>SchultessJDanielewskiOSmolenskiAPRap1GAP2 is a new GTPase-activating protein of Rap1 expressed in human plateletsBlood20051053185319215632203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib32"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>BadnerJAGershonESMeta-analysis of whole-genome linkage scans of bipolar disorder and schizophreniaMol Psychiatry2002740541111986984 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib33"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>WestinMAHuntMCAlexsonSEShort- and medium-chain carnitine acyltransferases and acyl-CoA thioesterases in mouse provide complementary systems for transport of beta-oxidation products out of peroxisomesCell Mol Life Sci20086598299018264800 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib34"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>NiggJTTemperament and developmental psychopathologyJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20064739542216492265 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib35"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>CloningerCRVan EerdeweghPGoateAEdenbergHJBlangeroJHesselbrockVAnxiety proneness linked to epistatic loci in genome scan of human personality traitsAm J Med Genet1998813133179674977 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib36"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>TerraccianoATanakaTSutinARSannaSDeianaBLaiSGenome-wide association scan of trait depressionBiol Psychiatry20106881181720800221 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib37"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>de MoorMHMCostaPTTerraccianoAKruegerRFde GeusEJCToshikoTMeta-analysis of genome-wide association studies for personalityMol Psychiatrye-pub ahead of print 21 December 2010; doi:10.1038/mp.2010.128(in press). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Characteristics of the study group</title></caption></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Correlations between hostility measures (<italic>n</italic> ranges between 983 and 2443 from mean cynicism–mean paranoia correlation with age–sex correlation)</title></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t2-fn1"><p><sup>*</sup><italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05; <sup>**</sup><italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01; <sup>***</sup><italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001.</p></fn><fn id="t2-fn2"><p>Sex: 1=male, 0=female.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Genetic markers showing top 10 SNPs within mean of four measurement years in each hostility scale</title></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t3-fn1"><p>Abbreviations: CHR, chromosome; MAF, minor allele frequency; SNP, single-nucleotide polymorphism.</p></fn><fn id="t3-fn2"><p>Bold values=<italic>P</italic>&lt;9 × 10<sup>−8</sup>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Genetic markers showing top 10 SNPs within each hostility scale across four measurements</title></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t4-fn1"><p>Abbreviations: CHR, chromosome; MAF, minor allele frequency; SNP, single-nucleotide polymorphism.</p></fn><fn id="t4-fn2"><p>Bold values=<italic>P</italic>&lt;9 × 10<sup>−8</sup>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>SNPs replicating in different years or different hostility scales</title></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t5-fn1"><p>Abbreviations: BP, base pair; CHR, chromosome; MAF, minor allele frequency; SNP, single-nucleotide polymorphism.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
