
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?properties manuscript?><?origin nihpa?><?iso-abbr J. Invest. Dermatol.?><?submitter-system nihms?><?submitter-canonical-name Nature Publishing Group?><?submitter-canonical-id NATURE-STRUCTUR?><?submitter-userid 1045?><?submitter-authority publisher?><?submitter-login nature-structure?><?submitter-name Nature Publishing Group (obsolete)?><?domain nihpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0426720</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">4839</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Invest Dermatol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Invest. Dermatol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of investigative dermatology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-202X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1523-1747</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3352986</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22402438</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jid.2012.36</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">nihpa351554</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>AIM1 and LINE-1 Epigenetic Aberrations In Tumor and Serum Relate to Melanoma Progression and Disease Outcome </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hoshimoto</surname><given-names>Sojun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>Christine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>Kelly</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Takeshima</surname><given-names>Ling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Takei</surname><given-names>Yoshiki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Michelle</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Sharon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>Myung-Shin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>Donald L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hoon</surname><given-names>Dave S.B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Molecular Oncology, John Wayne Cancer Institute at Saint John’s Health Center, Santa Monica, CA, USA</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Biostatistics, John Wayne Cancer Institute at Saint John’s Health Center, Santa Monica, CA, USA
</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Division of Surgical Oncology, John Wayne Cancer Institute at Saint John’s Health Center, Santa Monica, CA, USA
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><bold>Requests for reprints:</bold> Dr. Dave S.B. Hoon, Department of Molecular Oncology, John Wayne Cancer Institute at Saint John’s Health Center, 2200 Santa Monica Blvd, Santa Monica, CA 90404; <email>hoon@jwci.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>01</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>132</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1689</fpage><lpage>1697</lpage><permissions><license xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms"><license-p>Users may view, print, copy, and download text and data-mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Aberrations in the methylation status of non-coding genomic repeat DNA sequences and specific gene promoter region are important epigenetic events in melanoma progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Promoter methylation status in LINE-1 and Absent in melanoma-1(AIM1;6q21) associated with melanoma progression and disease outcome was assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>LINE-1 and AIM1 methylation status was assessed in paraffin-embedded archival tissues(PEAT)(n=133) and melanoma patients’ serum(n=56). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>LINE-1 U-Index(hypomethylation) and AIM1 were analyzed in microdissected melanoma PEAT sections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The LINE-1 U-Index of melanoma(n=100) was significantly higher than that of normal skin(n=14) and nevi(n=12)(P=0.0004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>LINE-1 U-Index level was elevated with increasing AJCC stage(P&lt;0.0001). AIM1 promoter hypermethylation was found in higher frequency(P=0.005) in metastatic melanoma(65%) than in primary melanomas(38%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>When analyzed, high LINE-1 U-Index and/or AIM1 methylation in melanomas were associated with disease-free survival(DFS) and overall survival(OS) in Stage I/II patients (P=0.017, 0.027; respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>In multivariate analysis, melanoma AIM1 methylation status was a significant prognostic factor of OS(P=0.032). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, serum unmethylated LINE-1 was at higher levels in both stage III(n=20) and stage IV(n=36) patients compared to healthy donors(n=14)(P=0.022). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Circulating methylated AIM1 was detected in patients’ serum and was predictive of OS in Stage IV patients (P=0.009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>LINE-1 hypomethylation and AIM1 hypermethylation have prognostic utility in both melanoma patients’ tumors and serum. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>LINE-1</kwd><kwd>AIM1</kwd><kwd>Melanoma</kwd><kwd>Methylation</kwd><kwd>Prognosis</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="S1"><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P2"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Epigenetic studies have shown that methylation status of CpG islands in the promoter region of tumor-related genes as well as non-coding repeat genomic sequences are associated with progression of cancers(Tanemura et al., 2009; van Hoesel et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The former has been linked to transcriptional silencing(Jones and Baylin, 2007), but the latter is poorly understood in cancer progression(de Maat et al., 2010a; de Maat et al., 2010b; Eden et al., 2003; Gaudet et al., 2003; Sunami et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P3"><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Long interspersed nucleotide elements-1(LINE-1) represent a non-coding repeat sequence in humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>They are 6-8 kb long, GC-poor sequences with two open reading frames(ORF1 and ORF2), encode a reverse-transcriptase, endonuclease, and make up about 17% of the human genome(Lander et al., 2001; Ostertag and Kazazian, 2001; Ovchinnikov et al., 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The genome contains about 5000 full-length 6.0 kb LINE-1 elements, 60-100 of which are still capable of retrotransposition(Brouha et al., 2003; Minakami et al., 1992; Scott et al., 1987). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>LINE-1 is hypermethylated in normal cells and hypomethylated in several malignancies(Estecio et al., 2007; Sunami et al., 2009; Yang et al., 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>LINE-1 hypomethylation level in tumor has been correlated to tumor progression(Chalitchagorn et al., 2004; Cho et al., 2007; Daskalos et al., 2009; Lee et al., 2009; Ogino et al., 2008a; Pattamadilok et al., 2008; Tellez et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The association of LINE-1 hypomethylation status has been assessed in human cutaneous melanoma cell lines(Tellez et al., 2009), and the activation of LINE-1 transcript has also been observed in metastatic melanomas compared to primary melanomas(Haqq et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>In this study, we assessed melanoma tumor cells microdissected from PEAT of different stages of primary and metastatic melanoma to investigate whether LINE-1 methylation status during tumor progression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P4"><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Methylation profiling of melanoma has demonstrated inactivation of tumor-related genes by hypermethylation of CpG islands in the promoter region(Furuta et al., 2004; Hoon et al., 2004; Mirmohammadsadegh et al., 2006; Patino and Susa, 2008; Tanemura et al., 2009; Worm et al., 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>These epigenetic changes are significant factors in melanoma progression as we have recently shown(Tanemura et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>A multidomain non-lens member of βγ-crystallin superfamily, with six structural domains formed from 12 βγ-crystallin motifs, Absent in melanoma-1(AIM1), not to be confused with SLC45A2(melanoma antigen Aim1) on chromosome 5p13.2. was originally identified as a candidate tumor suppressor gene(chromosome 6q21)(Aravind et al., 2008; Ray et al., 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>However, few studies have been carried out on AIM1 in melanoma since then. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P5"><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Higher prevalence of LINE-1 and tumor suppressor genes silenced by epigenetic aberration have been found on chromosome 6(Mungall et al., 2003) where AIM1 is also located. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have demonstrated correlation between LINE-1 hypomethylation and CpG island hypermethylation of tumor suppressor genes(Estecio et al., 2010; Poage et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>As the genetic locus of AIM1 is proximal to the binding site of several known transcription factors, LINE-1 and AIM1 methylation status may be associated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P6"><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Studies have shown epigenetic tumor tissue biomarkers can have utility as biomarkers for cell-free circulating DNA(cf-cDNA)(Schwarzenbach et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Specific cf-cDNA have demonstrated prognostic utility in melanoma patients(Mori et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In this study, we assessed the level of circulating unmethylated LINE-1 and methylated AIM1 DNA in serum of patients with melanoma metastasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>We demonstrated prognostic utility of unmethylated LINE-1 and AIM1 methylation in both melanoma tissue and serum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>These studies demonstrate that epigenetic aberrations of both coding and non-coding regions can have potential utility as biomarkers in tumors and serum of melanoma patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="S2"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S3"><title><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>LINE-1 Hypomethylation in Melanomas </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P7"><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Using Absolute Quantitative Assessment of Methylated Alleles (AQAMA), microdissected melanoma cells were assessed for their LINE-1 U-Index which is calculated by dividing the copy number of unmethylated templates by the total of both unmethylated and methylated templates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The average LINE-1 U-Index of five melanoma cell lines was 0.79, whereas for normal PBL DNA LINE-1 U-Index ranged from &lt;0.1 to 0.2 similar to normal skin and nevi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The LINE-1 U-Index of melanomas, including both primary and metastatic tissues(n=100, mean±SD; 0.32±0.26), was significantly higher than that of normal skin(n=14) and nevi(n=12)(mean±SD; 0.14±0.07)(T-test, P=0.0004)(Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The LINE-1 U-Index level of metastatic melanomas(AJCC stage IIIm and IV: n=56, mean±SD; 0.40±0.30) was significantly higher than that of normal skin/nevi or primary melanomas(AJCC stage Ip, IIp, and IIIp: n=44, mean±SD; 0.22±0.14)(Tukey’s HSD P&lt;0.0001 and P=0.0001, respectively)(Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, LINE-1 U-Index in melanomas showed a significant elevation with increasing stage of disease(mean±SD; I: 0.20±0.05, II: 0.24±0.11, IIIp:0.23±0.19, IIIm:0.27±0.23, and IV:0.50±0.31, respectively)(ANOVA P&lt;0.0001)(Figure 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Most notably, LINE-1 U-Index level of stage IV melanomas(mean±SD; 0.50±0.31) was significantly higher than other stages(Newman-Keuls test, P&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>LINE-1 U-Index was not correlated with patient age or other histopathological factors including tumor thickness, ulceration, or mitotic index. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P8"><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>LINE-1 U-Index was further compared in 13 autologous pairs of primary(2 stage II and 11 stage IIIp) and metastatic(9 stage IIIm, 4 stage IVm) tumors from13 patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In 11 pairs, LINE-1 U-Index values were higher in metastatic than respective paired primary tumors(Figure 1D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Signed rank test for the difference of LINE-1 U-Index between primary and metastasis was significant(mean±SD; primary: 0.08±0.11, metastasis: 0.20±0.22, P=0.024). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>These results suggested hypomethylation of LINE-1 was a progressive factor in melanomas. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S4"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>AIM1 Promoter Methylation Status in Melanoma Cell Lines </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P9"><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Unlike LINE-1, AIM1 is a protein encoding gene, therefore the evaluation of promoter methylation should cover regions or CpG sites relevant to the downstream expression level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Four melanoma lines(M-15, M-24, M-101, and LF-0023) and normal PBL were subjected to MALDITOF MS quantitative analysis of the entire AIM1 promoter region to profile CpG site methylation status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>CpG sites of M-15 and M-101 were highly methylated across the whole promoter region compared to M-24, LF-0023, and normal PBL(Figure 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The transcription of AIM1 was analyzed by RT-PCR in the same melanoma lines(Figure 2B). AIM1 mRNA was not detected in the two highly AIM1methylated melanoma lines(M-15, M-101). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The two AIM1 unmethylated melanoma lines(M-24, LF-0023) and normal PBL showed high expression of AIM1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Specific CpG sites most related to mRNA transcription activity(Figure 2C) were identified for methylation specific PCR(MSP) study in PEAT and cf-cDNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The average percentage of methylation in the selected region(CpG8-11) in M-15(77%) and M-101(81%) is higher than those of two AIM1 mRNA positive cell lines, M-24 and LF-0023, and donor PBL (&lt;12%). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P10"><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>AIM1 expression was significantly increased in the two methylated lines after treatment with 5Aza-dC(Supplementary Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>This demonstrated that demethylation of AIM1 promoter region can re-activate AIM1 mRNA expression, suggesting promoter region methylation regulates AIM1 expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S5"><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>AIM1 Methylation Status and mRNA Expression in PEAT </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P11"><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>To evaluate the AIM1 methylation status in melanoma tissues, we designed MSP primers to the specific CpG sites(CpG8-11) that were related to transcription levels of AIM1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The AIM1 promoter was found hypermethylated in 57 of 112(51%) melanoma tissues, as compared with none of histopathologically normal skin(n=14) and nevus tissues(n=12)(P&lt;0.0001). AIM1 promoter hypermethylation was identified in 35 of 54(65%) metastatic melanomas, as compared to 22 of 58(38%) primary melanomas(P=0.005); frequency of hypermethylation progressively increased with stage(Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P12"><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>AIM1 mRNA expression was assessed in four hypomethylated stage I melanoma primary tumors and in five hypermethylated stage IV metastatic tumors. AIM1 mRNA was found in all four hypomethylated melanomas but showed limited expression in the five hypermethylated melanomas(Supplementary Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S6"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Survival Analyses of LINE-1 and AIM1 Methylation Status </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P13"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>We next evaluated the PEAT AIM1 and LINE-1 methylation as biomarkers for prognostic significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>In early stage primary melanoma patients(n=23), stepwise multivariate Cox regression(variables age, gender, ulceration, Breslow, primary site) demonstrated that AIM1 hypermethylation was a significant prognostic predictor of OS in Stage I/II patients when age is included in the model(P=0.032, HR:22.62, 95%CI:1.30-392.24). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>LINE-1, however, it did not reach significance as an individual biomarker. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Univariate analysis of AIM1 or LINE1 alone showed no significance in prediction of OS or DFS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The relatively small sample size of the survival analysis cohort may have contributed to the differences in our survival cohort between univariate and multivariate survival analysis results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>In combination, patients were categorized into two groups: patients who had presence of either hypermethylated AIM1 or hypomethylated LINE-1, and patients who did not have either event. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The presence of either hypermethylated AIM1 or hypomethylated LINE-1 correlated to significantly poorer patient OS and DFS in univariate analysis of Stage I/II melanoma (P=0.027 and 0.017, respectively)(Figure 3A&amp;B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>In multivariate analysis, the combination was a significant prognostic predictor of both OS and DFS in Stage I/II patients(OS: P=0.028, HR:6.46, 95%CI:1.22-34.15; DFS:P=0.046, HR:8.65, 95%CI:1.04-72.06). Table 2 lists clinicopathological factors for patients included in survival analysis along with biomarker prediction of OS results from Cox regression model. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S7"><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Serum cf-cDNA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P14"><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>To determine whether LINE-1 and/or AIM1 could be used for prognostic assessment of serum(Mori et al., 2005), we examined levels of circulating unmethylated LINE-1 and methylated AIM1 in stage III and IV melanoma patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Patient serum samples had significantly higher unmethylated LINE-1 than healthy donor serum(T-test; P=0.022)(Supplementary Figure 3), and none of the normal healthy donor serum had detectable unmethylated LINE-1 before 25 PCR cycles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The serum MSP assay detected AIM1 circulating methylated DNA in 15%(3 of 20) of stage III patients and 22%(8 of 36) of stage IV patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Unmethylated LINE-1 status in patients’ serum was limited in prognostic utility in this set of patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>However, serum methylated AIM1 DNA was correlated to OS in Stage IV patients(P=0.0085, Log-Rank; Figure 4) and not associated with M stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Patients found to have either serum unmethylated LINE-1 or methylated AIM1 DNA have worse prognosis compared to patients with neither(P=0.0009, Log-Rank)(Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S8"><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P15"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The progressive demethylation of LINE-1 in malignancies has been correlated to increased aberrant genomic and epigenomic events(Sunami et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>We demonstrated that LINE-1 became progressively hypomethylated during melanoma progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>LINE-1 hypomethylation level was higher in stage IV melanomas compared to other stages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>These results suggested that LINE-1 hypomethylation may be a significant factor in melanoma progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Sigalotti previously demonstrated within stage IIIC melanomas that higher methylation percentage of LINE-1 is correlated to worse OS(Sigalotti et al., 2011); in this study, we further demonstrated that increasing hypomethylation of LINE-1 in advancing stages of melanomas and in metastasis of autologous metastasis-primary paired tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The observation of LINE-1 hypomethylation during tumor progression is in accordance with that found in gastrointestinal cancers(Ogino et al., 2008a; Ogino et al., 2008b; Sunami et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>These LINE-1 hypomethylation findings support the pattern of genomic instability occurring during melanoma progression(Fujiwara et al., 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>LINE-1 hypomethylation has been suggested to facilitate genomic instability in cancer cells(Sunami et al., 2011), and may have a role in the activation of LINE-1 transcription in metastatic melanoma(Haqq et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P16"><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Chromosome 6q21-22 has been long presumed as a tumor suppressor region in melanoma, and several candidate tumor suppressor genes located at 6q21-23 have been proposed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Trent et al. demonstrated that melanoma lines directly introduced with a normal copy of chromosome 6 lost their ability to form tumors in nude mice, and the loss of chromosome 6 from melanoma microcell hybrids resulted in reversion to tumorigenicity of these cells(Trent et al., 1990). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>High frequency of loss of heterozygosity(LOH) of chromosome 6q has also been reported in melanoma lines and tissues(Bahrami et al., 2007; Fujiwara et al., 1999; Stark and Hayward, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>However, it still remains unclear which key genes are specifically involved in melanoma progression in the 6q21-22 region of melanomas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Recently, lower levels of AIM1 expression was shown to be correlated with 6q21 deletion, and promoter hypermethylation of AIM1 down-regulated AIM1 expression in natural killer(NK)-cell malignancies(Iqbal et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>We found AIM1 to be significantly suppressed during melanoma progression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P17"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Our study showed a significant association between LINE-1 hypomethylation or AIM1 hypermethylation and poorer survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The combination analysis of LINE-1(U) and/or AIM1(M) in melanomas was a significant predictor for OS and DFS, suggesting that the combination analysis of LINE-1 hypomethylation and AIM1 hypermethylation can improve their sensitivity as prognostic biomarkers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Studies have demonstrated that genomic methylation status is dynamic during tumor progression(Tanemura et al., 2009) where genomic repeats and specific gene promoter region can, independently or concurrently, become aberrantly methylated during tumor progression(de Maat et al., 2007b; de Maat et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P18"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>cf-cDNA has been shown as a promising clinical biomarker for various malignancies(Mori et al., 2005; Schwarzenbach et al., 2011; Umetani et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>We have reported the prognostic utility of specific circulating methylated DNA; RASSF1A, and RAR-β2 in stage IV melanoma patients(Mori et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Although serum unmethylated LINE-1 was higher in advanced melanoma patients, it was not correlated to disease outcome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>A larger defined cohort of patients may be needed to demonstrate its potential prognostic utility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Patients with circulating methylated AIM1 DNA, on the other hand, had worse OS than those who did not. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The combination of AIM1 or LINE-1 cf-cDNA was significantly correlated to OS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The analysis indicated that both unmethylated and methylated cf-cDNA can be utilized for prognostic utility. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P19"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, we demonstrated that LINE-1 hypomethylation and AIM1 hypermethylation status are related to tumor progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Together, these two factors have prognostic value as shown with detection of cf-cDNA in melanoma patients’ serum for predicting outcome in tissue and in detecting serum cf-cDNA for realtime disease status. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods" id="S9"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S10"><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Specimens </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P20"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Melanoma patients treated at Saint John’s Health Center (SJHC) between 1993-2008 were reviewed for inclusion in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>PEAT melanomas from the patients were obtained under an IRB protocol that was approved by the SJHC/JWCI Joint IRB and Western IRB(WIRB). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P21"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The LINE-1 study included 126 PEAT(113 patients). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Among these were 13 pairs of autologous tissues from a primary tumor and its synchronous regional metastasis(5 pairs) or metachronous regional/distant metastasis(8 pairs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Of the remaining 100 specimens, 44 were from the primary tumors of patients with AJCC melanoma stage I(n=13), stage II(n=11) or stage III(n=20); 56 were from metastases of patients with stage III(n=23) or stage IV(n=33). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P22"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The AIM1 study included 112 PEAT from 92 patients with AJCC stage I(n=14), stage II(n=14), stage III(n=30 primaries and 23 lymph node metastases), and stage IV(n=31 distant metastases) melanoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Seventy-two patients from the AIM1 study overlapped with the LINE-1 study, with AJCC stage I(n=13), stage II(n=10), stage III(n=15 primary tumors and 11 lymph node metastases), and stage IV(n=23 distant metastases) melanoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Twenty-Six negative controls were obtained from histopathologically negative normal skin(n=14) and nevi tissue(n=12). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P23"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Serum from 56 AJCC stage III(n=20) and IV(n=36) melanoma patients, and 14 healthy donors with serum separator tubes, filtered, cryopreserved(-80°C)(Koyanagi et al., 2010; Mori et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>All patients’ sera were obtained after informed consent. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S11"><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Melanoma Cell Lines and Treatment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P24"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Melanoma cell lines(M-12, M-15, M-24, M-101, LF-0023) established from metastatic tumors at JWCI were cultured and harvested for the study and as assay controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The melanoma lines were cultured as previously described(Narita et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Three melanoma cell lines, M-15, M-101, and M-24 were treated with 5-aza-2′ deoxycytidine(5Aza-dC; Sigma-Aldrich) for AIM1 reactivation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Melanoma cells were cultured, and then treated with culture medium containing 5 μM 5Aza-dC or dimethyl sulfoxide as a vehicle control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>5Aza-dC containing medium was administered daily, and the cells were collected for assessment after 48 h. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S12"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>DNA Isolation From PEAT and Serum Samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P25"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Tissue sections were cut for H&amp;E and microdissected(de Maat et al., 2010a; de Maat et al., 2007b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Microdissected tissues were incubated at 50°C overnight in lysis buffer(50 mM Tris, 1mM EDTA, 2.5% Tween 20, 6.0 mAU proteinase K) followed by 95°C(10min) incubation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>DNA was extracted by phenol-chloroform isoamyl extraction and ethanol precipitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>DNA concentration was determined by both spectrophotometer reading at 260/280 nm, and Quant-iT™ PicoGreen® dsDNA assay kit(Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P26"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Serum samples(500μL) were diluted with 0.9% NaCl and mixed with a premix consisting of proteinase K and 10% sodium docecylsulfate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Samples were incubated at 50°C(3 hrs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>After incubation, phenol-chloroform isoamyl(25:24:1, pH 8.0)(Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) was added to each sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>DNA was extracted and quantified; up to 300 ng of DNA was subjected to sodium bisulfite modification using EpiTect bisulfite kit(Qiagen, Valencia, CA)(de Maat et al., 2010b). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S13"><title><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>AQAMA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P27"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>We previously reported accurate, targeted methylation analysis of PEAT using AQAMA, an assay based on bisulfite modification of DNA and real-time PCR using two hydrolysis minor groove binder(MGB) probes specific for the methylated or unmethylated templates labeled with fluorophores(de Maat et al., 2007a; Tanemura et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Assays were in triplicates and the average copy number was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>LINE-1 hypomethylated melanoma line DNA and LINE-1 methylated PBL of healthy donors were included as controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The LINE-1 hypomethylation level was a continuous variable defined as the copy number of unmethylated LINE-1(U) relative to the total LINE-1 copy number which is the sum of the copy number of methylated LINE-1(M) and U(U/[U+M]), hereafter referred to as LINE-1 U-Index. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The LINE-1 U-Index of each sample was compared for hypomethylation status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>For assessment of cf-cDNA, modifications of the assay included the use of 4μL of bisulfite-treated DNA as template and PerfeCTa qPCR Supermix(Quanta BioScience). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>For serum, qPCR quantification cycle(Cq) cut-off at 25 was used to qualify whether there is sufficient level of unmethylated LINE-1 DNA present above that of a healthy donor serum. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S14"><title><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>RNA Isolation and RT-PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P28"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Total RNA from cultured cells was extracted using TRI-Reagent(Molecular Research Center, Cincinnati, OH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>For melanomas, 5x10-μm sections were cut from PEAT blocks on a microtome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Apart from deparaffinization, RNA was extracted from PEAT using RNAwiz(Ambion, Austin, TX) after proteinase K digestion as previously described(Koyanagi et al., 2006b; Takeuchi et al., 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>RNA quantity and quality were accessed by spectrophotometry and Quant-iT RiboGreen RNA assay(Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P29"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Reverse transcription of total RNA(1 g) and PCR with 5 ul of cDNA was performed as previously described(Koyanagi et al., 2006a). AIM1-specific primers are 5′-TTAGTTTTAGACATTAAAGGGGG-3′ and 5′-TGGAAGGACCTCCAGAAGAT-3′. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>GAPDH was assessed by RT-PCR as reference and for normalization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Specimens were amplified with a pre-cycling hold at 95°C(10min), followed by 25 cycles of 95°C, 55°C for GAPDH/58°C for AIM1, and 72°C(1min). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S15"><title><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>MALDI-TOF Mass Spectrometry </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P30"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>EpiTYPER assay(Sequenom, San Diego, CA) is a tool for detection and quantification of DNA methylation using MALDI-TOF MS and MassCLEAVE analysis based on a base-specific cleavage reaction(Radpour et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>This assay enables accurate quantification of DNA methylation(Coolen et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Each CpG site within an amplicon is assessed for methylation status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Three pairs of primers were designed to cover AIM1’s promoter region as predicted by Promoter Scan Web(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www-bimas.cit.nih.gov/molbio/proscan/">http://www-bimas.cit.nih.gov/molbio/proscan/</ext-link>) using EpiDesigner (Sequenom)(Supplementary Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Bisulfite-treated DNA PCR amplification was performed with a pre-cycling hold at 94°C(15min) followed by 45 cycles of 94°C(20s), 58°C(30s), and at 72°C(1min) and a final extension at 72°C(2min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Post-PCR amplicons are assessed as previously reported using MassARRAY(Yoshimura et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S16"><title><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>MSP </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P31"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Bisulfite-conversion based PCR primers were designed to cover the region where methylation percentage was well-correlated with mRNA expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>For MSP on PEAT, the forward and reverse methylation-specific were 5′-D4-TTTGTTTTTTCGTTTTTTTAGGTTC-3′, and 5′-ACTAACATCCAATACCCGCG-3′, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Forward and reverse unmethylated-specific primers were 5′-D3-TGTTTTTTTGTTTTTTTAGGTTTGT-3′, and 5′-ACTAACATCCAATACCCACAC-3′, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>For serum DNA MSP, different reverse primers were selected to reduce product size for optimal detection: methylation, 5′-CGCGATAACGCTCCG-3′and unmethylation, 5′-CAATAAACACAATAACACTCCA-3′. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="P32"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>For PEAT, PCR were performed with Accustart Taq DNA polymerase(0.5U)(Quanta BioSciences), 1xPCR buffer, 4.5mM MgCl2, 0.2μmol/L each of forward and reverse primer, 800μmol/L deoxynucleotide triphosphates, and 1μL bisulfite-treated DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Amplifications were carried out: 95°C(3min) followed by 40 cycles of 95°C, 61°C, and 72°C(30s) for both methylated and unmethylated reaction, and a final extension at 72°C(7min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>For circulating AIM1 DNA in serum, 3μL of bisulfite-treated DNA was used as template in the PCR reaction, and PerfeCTa qPCR Supermix is used in place of Accustart Taq DNA polymerase cocktail. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Amplifications were carried out: 95°C(3min) followed by 40 cycles of 95°C, 59°C, and 72°C(30s). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>PCR products were analyzed by capillary array electrophoresis(Beckman Coulter CEQ 8000X; Beckman Coulter, Brea, CA) as previously reported (Tanemura et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Methylation assay control includes PBL DNA methylated in vitro with excess SssI methyltransferase(New England BioLabs, Ipswich, MA)(Umetani et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Unmethylated assay control includes leukocyte DNA that was amplified by phi-29 DNA polymerase to produce universally unmethylated control(UUC). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S17"><title><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Biostatistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="P33"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>All data were analyzed using SAS software(version 9.1.3, SAS Institute, Cary, NC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Chi-square test or Fisher’s exact test were used to analyze categorical variables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>ANOVA, Student’s t-test, Kruskal Wallis test, or Tukey’s HSD test was used to compare independent continuous variables across different strata. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The Cochran Armitage trend test analyzed LINE-1 hypomethylation across AJCC stages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>LINE-1 U indices were compared at each AJCC stage using the Student-Newman-Keuls test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Signed rank test and McNemar’s test were used to compare LINE-1 U-Index in primary and metastatic paired tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Correlation between LINE-1 U-Index and patients’ age was analyzed using Spearman’s rank test correlation efficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Association between methylation status of AIM1 and AJCC stage was assessed by the Chi-square test, while trend analysis was conducted using the Cochran Armitage trend test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Cox proportional hazards(PH) regression models for OS and DFS were built incorporating methylation status of LINE-1 and AIM1 along with other clinical variables such as Breslow, age, gender, and number of metastases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>To convert LINE-1 U-Index into a categorical value for analysis, a cutoff of 0.297 was established using the average of LINE-1 U-Indices from normal skin samples plus 2 S.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>A sample with LINE-1 U-Index ≥0.297was considered hypomethylated in LINE-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>When combining both AIM1 and LINE-1 status, patients with either AIM1 hypermethylation or LINE-1 hypomethylation were compared to patients who had neither event. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The PH assumption was tested in building the Cox PH regression model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Survival curves were generated using the Kaplan-Meier method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>A p-value &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>These analyses were performed in compliance with REMARK(McShane et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Material</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS351554-supplement-01.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1137" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack id="S18"><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>We thank Gwen Berry and Kana Sato for editorial support, and Nicholas Donovan and Dept of Molecular Oncology for their technical support. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Financial Support: This work was supported by the Dr. Miriam and Sheldon G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Adelson Medical Research Foundation, Ruth and Martin H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Weil Fund, and the Award Number P0 CA029605 and P0 CA012582 from the National Institutes of Health, National Cancer Institute. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official view of the National Cancer Institute or the National Institutes of Health. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn id="FN1"><p id="P34"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>CONFLICT OF INTEREST: None. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="FN2"><p id="P35"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Disclosure: Authors have no commercial/financial conflict of interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term><italic>AIM1</italic></term><def><p>Absent in melanoma-1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AQAMA</term><def><p>Absolute Quantitative Assessment of Methylated Alleles</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>cf-cDNA</term><def><p>circulating cell-free DNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LINE-1</term><def><p>long interspersed nucleotide elements-1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MALDI-TOF MS</term><def><p>matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>M</term><def><p>methylated</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MSP</term><def><p>methylation specific PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MGB</term><def><p>minor groove binder</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NK</term><def><p>natural killer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ORF</term><def><p>open reading frames</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PEAT</term><def><p>paraffin-embedded archival tissues</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PH</term><def><p>proportional hazards</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PBL</term><def><p>peripheral blood lymphocyte</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UMC</term><def><p>universally methylated control</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UUC</term><def><p>universally unmethylated control</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>U</term><def><p>unmethylated</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WIRB</term><def><p>Western Institutional Review Board</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>AravindPWistowGSharmaYSankaranarayananRExploring the limits of sequence and structure in a variant betagamma-crystallin domain of the protein absent in melanoma-1 (AIM1)J Mol Biol200838150951818582473 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R2"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>BahramiSChengLWangMJonesTDMaloneJCBillingsSDClonal relationships between epidermotropic metastatic melanomas and their primary lesions: a loss of heterozygosity and X-chromosome inactivation-based analysisMod Pathol20072082182717571079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R3"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>BrouhaBSchustakJBadgeRMLutz-PriggeSFarleyAHMoranJVHot L1s account for the bulk of retrotransposition in the human populationProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20031005280528512682288 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R4"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>ChalitchagornKShuangshotiSHourpaiNKongruttanachokNTangkijvanichPThong-ngamDDistinctive pattern of LINE-1 methylation level in normal tissues and the association with carcinogenesisOncogene2004238841884615480421 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R5"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>ChoNYKimBHChoiMYooEJMoonKCChoYMHypermethylation of CpG island loci and hypomethylation of LINE-1 and Alu repeats in prostate adenocarcinoma and their relationship to clinicopathological featuresJ Pathol200721126927717139617 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R6"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>CoolenMWStathamALGardiner-GardenMClarkSJGenomic profiling of CpG methylation and allelic specificity using quantitative high-throughput mass spectrometry: critical evaluation and improvementsNucleic Acids Res200735e11917855397 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R7"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>DaskalosANikolaidisGXinarianosGSavvariPCassidyAZakopoulouRHypomethylation of retrotransposable elements correlates with genomic instability in non-small cell lung cancerInt J Cancer2009124818718823011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R8"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>de MaatMFNaritaNBenardAYoshimuraTKuoCTollenaarRADevelopment of sporadic microsatellite instability in colorectal tumors involves hypermethylation at methylated-in-tumor loci in adenomaAm J Pathol2010a1772347235620952593 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R9"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>de MaatMFUmetaniNSunamiETurnerRRHoonDSAssessment of methylation events during colorectal tumor progression by absolute quantitative analysis of methylated allelesMol Cancer Res2007a546147117510312 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R10"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>de MaatMFvan de VeldeCJBenardAPutterHMorreauHvan KriekenJHIdentification of a quantitative MINT locus methylation profile predicting local regional recurrence of rectal cancerClin Cancer Res2010b162811281820460484 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R11"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>de MaatMFvan de VeldeCJUmetaniNde HeerPPutterHvan HoeselAQEpigenetic silencing of cyclooxygenase-2 affects clinical outcome in gastric cancerJ Clin Oncol2007b254887489417971584 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R12"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>de MaatMFvan de VeldeCJvan der WerffMPPutterHUmetaniNKlein-KranenbargEMQuantitative analysis of methylation of genomic loci in early-stage rectal cancer predicts distant recurrenceJ Clin Oncol2008262327233518467724 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R13"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>EdenAGaudetFWaghmareAJaenischRChromosomal instability and tumors promoted by DNA hypomethylationScience200330045512702868 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R14"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>EstecioMRGallegosJVallotCCastoroRJChungWMaegawaSGenome architecture marked by retrotransposons modulates predisposition to DNA methylation in cancerGenome Res2010201369138220716667 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R15"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>EstecioMRGharibyanVShenLIbrahimAEDoshiKHeRLINE-1 hypomethylation in cancer is highly variable and inversely correlated with microsatellite instabilityPLoS ONE20072e39917476321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R16"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>FujiwaraYChiDDWangHKelemanPMortonDLTurnerRPlasma DNA microsatellites as tumor-specific markers and indicators of tumor progression in melanoma patientsCancer Res1999591567157110197630 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R17"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>FurutaJUmebayashiYMiyamotoKKikuchiKOtsukaFSugimuraTPromoter methylation profiling of 30 genes in human malignant melanomaCancer Sci20049596296815596045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R18"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>GaudetFHodgsonJGEdenAJackson-GrusbyLDausmanJGrayJWInduction of tumors in mice by genomic hypomethylationScience200330048949212702876 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R19"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>HaqqCNosratiMSudilovskyDCrothersJKhodabakhshDPulliamBLThe gene expression signatures of melanoma progressionProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20051026092609715833814 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R20"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>HoonDSSpugnardiMKuoCHuangSKMortonDLTabackBProfiling epigenetic inactivation of tumor suppressor genes in tumors and plasma from cutaneous melanoma patientsOncogene2004234014402215064737 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R21"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>IqbalJKucukCDeleeuwRJSrivastavaGTamWGengHGenomic analyses reveal global functional alterations that promote tumor growth and novel tumor suppressor genes in natural killer-cell malignanciesLeukemia2009231139115119194464 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R22"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>JonesPABaylinSBThe epigenomics of cancerCell200712868369217320506 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R23"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>KoyanagiKMoriTO’DaySJMartinezSRWangHJHoonDSAssociation of circulating tumor cells with serum tumor-related methylated DNA in peripheral blood of melanoma patientsCancer Res2006a666111611716778184 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R24"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>KoyanagiKO’DaySJBoasbergPAtkinsMBWangHJGonzalezRSerial monitoring of circulating tumor cells predicts outcome of induction biochemotherapy plus maintenance biotherapy for metastatic melanomaClin Cancer Res2010162402240820371696 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R25"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>KoyanagiKO’DaySJGonzalezRLewisKRobinsonWAAmatrudaTTMicrophthalmia transcription factor as a molecular marker for circulating tumor cell detection in blood of melanoma patientsClin Cancer Res2006b121137114316489066 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R26"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>LanderESLintonLMBirrenBNusbaumCZodyMCBaldwinJInitial sequencing and analysis of the human genomeNature200140986092111237011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R27"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>LeeHSKimBHChoNYYooEJChoiMShinSHPrognostic Implications of and Relationship Between CpG Island Hypermethylation and Repetitive DNA Hypomethylation in Hepatocellular CarcinomaClin Cancer Res20091581282019188151 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R28"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>McShaneLMAltmanDGSauerbreiWTaubeSEGionMClarkGMReporting recommendations for tumor marker prognostic studiesJ Clin Oncol2005239067907216172462 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R29"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>MinakamiRKuroseKEtohKFuruhataYHattoriMSakakiYIdentification of an internal cis-element essential for the human L1 transcription and a nuclear factor(s) binding to the elementNucleic Acids Res199220313931451320255 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R30"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>MirmohammadsadeghAMariniANambiarSHassanMTannapfelARuzickaTEpigenetic silencing of the PTEN gene in melanomaCancer Res2006666546655216818626 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R31"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>MoriTO’DaySJUmetaniNMartinezSRKitagoMKoyanagiKPredictive utility of circulating methylated DNA in serum of melanoma patients receiving biochemotherapyJ Clin Oncol2005239351935816361635 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R32"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>MungallAJPalmerSASimsSKEdwardsCAAshurstJLWilmingLThe DNA sequence and analysis of human chromosome 6Nature200342580581114574404 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R33"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>NaritaNTanemuraAMuraliRScolyerRAHuangSArigamiTFunctional RET G691S polymorphism in cutaneous malignant melanomaOncogene2009283058306819561646 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R34"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>OginoSKawasakiTNoshoKOhnishiMSuemotoYKirknerGJLINE-1 hypomethylation is inversely associated with microsatellite instability and CpG island methylator phenotype in colorectal cancerInt J Cancer2008a1222767277318366060 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R35"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>OginoSNoshoKKirknerGJKawasakiTChanATSchernhammerESA cohort study of tumoral LINE-1 hypomethylation and prognosis in colon cancerJ Natl Cancer Inst2008b1001734173819033568 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R36"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>OstertagEMKazazianHHJr.Biology of mammalian L1 retrotransposonsAnnu Rev Genet20013550153811700292 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R37"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>OvchinnikovIRubinASwergoldGDTracing the LINEs of human evolutionProc Natl Acad Sci U S A200299105221052712138175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R38"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>PatinoWDSusaJEpigenetics of cutaneous melanomaAdv Dermatol200824597019256305 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R39"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>PattamadilokJHuapaiNRattanatanyongPVasurattanaATriratanachatSTresukosolDLINE-1 hypomethylation level as a potential prognostic factor for epithelial ovarian cancerInt J Gynecol Cancer20081871171717944913 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R40"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>PoageGMHousemanEAChristensenBCButlerRAvissar-WhitingMMcCleanMDGlobal Hypomethylation Identifies Loci Targeted for Hypermethylation in Head and Neck CancerClin Cancer Res2011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R41"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>RadpourRHaghighiMMFanAXTorbatiPMHahnSHolzgreveWHigh-throughput hacking of the methylation patterns in breast cancer by in vitro transcription and thymidine-specific cleavage mass array on MALDI-TOF silico-chipMol Cancer Res200861702170919010818 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R42"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>RayMEWistowGSuYAMeltzerPSTrentJMAIM1, a novel non-lens member of the betagamma-crystallin superfamily, is associated with the control of tumorigenicity in human malignant melanomaProc Natl Acad Sci U S A199794322932349096375 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R43"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>SchwarzenbachHHoonDSPantelKCell-free nucleic acids as biomarkers in cancer patientsNat Rev Cancer20111142643721562580 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R44"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>ScottAFSchmeckpeperBJAbdelrazikMComeyCTO’HaraBRossiterJPOrigin of the human L1 elements: proposed progenitor genes deduced from a consensus DNA sequenceGenomics198711131253692483 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R45"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>SigalottiLFrattaEBidoliECovreAParisiGColizziFMethylation levels of the “long interspersed nucleotide element-1” repetitive sequences predict survival of melanoma patientsJ Transl Med201197821615918 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R46"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>StarkMHaywardNGenome-wide loss of heterozygosity and copy number analysis in melanoma using high-density single-nucleotide polymorphism arraysCancer Res2007672632264217363583 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R47"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>SunamiEde MaatMVuATurnerRRHoonDSLINE-1 hypomethylation during primary colon cancer progressionPLoS One20116e1888421533144 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R48"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>SunamiEVuATNguyenSLHoonDSAnalysis of methylated circulating DNA in cancer patients’ bloodMethods Mol Biol200950734935618987826 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R49"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>TakeuchiHMortonDLKuoCTurnerRRElashoffDElashoffRPrognostic significance of molecular upstaging of paraffin-embedded sentinel lymph nodes in melanoma patientsJ Clin Oncol2004222671268015226334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R50"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>TanemuraATerandoAMSimMSvan HoeselAQde MaatMFMortonDLCpG island methylator phenotype predicts progression of malignant melanomaClin Cancer Res2009151801180719223509 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R51"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>TellezCSShenLEstecioMRJelinekJGershenwaldJEIssaJPCpG island methylation profiling in human melanoma cell linesMelanoma Res20091914615519441164 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R52"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>TrentJMStanbridgeEJMcBrideHLMeeseEUCaseyGAraujoDETumorigenicity in human melanoma cell lines controlled by introduction of human chromosome 6Science19902475685712300817 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R53"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>UmetaniNde MaatMFMoriTTakeuchiHHoonDSSynthesis of universal unmethylated control DNA by nested whole genome amplification with phi29 DNA polymeraseBiochem Biophys Res Commun200532921922315721296 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R54"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>UmetaniNKimJHiramatsuSReberHAHinesOJBilchikAJIncreased integrity of free circulating DNA in sera of patients with colorectal or periampullary cancer: direct quantitative PCR for ALU repeatsClin Chem2006521062106916723681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R55"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>van HoeselAQvan de VeldeCJKuppenPJPutterHde KruijfEMvan NesJGPrimary tumor classification according to methylation pattern is prognostic in patients with early stage ER-negative breast cancerBreast Cancer Res Treat2011Epub Ahead of Print </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R56"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>WormJChristensenCGronbaekKTulchinskyEGuldbergPGenetic and epigenetic alterations of the APC gene in malignant melanomaOncogene2004235215522615133491 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R57"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>YangASEstecioMRDoshiKKondoYTajaraEHIssaJPA simple method for estimating global DNA methylation using bisulfite PCR of repetitive DNA elementsNucleic Acids Res200432e3814973332 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="R58"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>YoshimuraTNagaharaMKuoCTurnerRRSoon-ShiongPHoonDSLymphovascular invasion of colorectal cancer is correlated to SPARC expression in the tumor stromal microenvironmentEpigenetics201161001101121725199 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Individual and mean (solid horizontal line) LINE-1 U-Index values for tissue specimens of normal skin vs. primary/metastatic melanoma (A), normal skin vs. primary melanoma vs. metastatic melanoma (B) and according to the AJCC stage (C) and primary and metastatic paired samples (D). P values were obtained by Student’s t-test (A, D), Tukey’s HSD (B) and ANOVA (C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms-351554-f0001"/><graphic xlink:href="nihms-351554-f0002"/><graphic xlink:href="nihms-351554-f0003"/><graphic xlink:href="nihms-351554-f0004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>AIM1 promoter methylation and gene expression. A: CpG methylation in the promoter region of AIM1 gene as assessed by PCR of three amplicons (A, B, and C) covering over 1000bp of promoter region. B: AIM1 mRNA expression in melanoma cell lines. C: MALDITOF MassARRAY analysis of specific CpG sites as target region of MSP primers for AIM1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms-351554-f0005"/><graphic xlink:href="nihms-351554-f0006"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Kaplan-Meier survival curves for melanoma patients using combination of LINE-1 and AIM1 methylation status in PEAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>M=hypermethylated, U=hypomethylated. A: OS of patients with LINE-1 hypomethylation and/or AIM1 hypermethylation versus LINE-1 hypermethylation and AIM1 hypomethylation. B: DFS of stage I-II melanoma patients with LINE-1 hypomethylation and/or AIM1 hypermethylation vs. LINE-1 hypermethylation and AIM1 hypomethylation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms-351554-f0007"/><graphic xlink:href="nihms-351554-f0008"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Kaplan-Meier survival curves for stage IV patients in serum studies. A: OS of stage IV patients with methylated vs. unmethylated AIM1 cf-cDNA. B: OS of stage IV patients with LINE1 unmethylated and/or AIM1 methylated cf-cDNA vs. those with LINE-1 methylated and AIM1 unmethylated cf-cDNA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms-351554-f0009"/><graphic xlink:href="nihms-351554-f0010"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Methylation Status of <italic>AIM1</italic>_Promoter Region in Melanoma Tissue</title></caption></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Clinicopathological Factors of AIM1/LINE1 Survival Analysis set (n=72)</title></caption></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
