
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3871691</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24376864</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-28156</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085066</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Correlation of Aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans Detection with Clinical/Immunoinflammatory Profile of Localized Aggressive Periodontitis Using a 16S rRNA Microarray Method: A Cross-Sectional Study </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Localized Aggressive Periodontitis and Aa Presence</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gonçalves</surname><given-names>Patricia F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Klepac-Ceraj</surname><given-names>Vanja</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Hong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Paster</surname><given-names>Bruce J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aukhil</surname><given-names>Ikramuddin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wallet</surname><given-names>Shannon M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shaddox</surname><given-names>Luciana M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Dentistry, Federal University of Jequitinhonha and Mucuri Valleys, Diamantina, Minas Gerais, Brazil</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Periodontology, University of Florida College of Dentistry, Gainesville, Florida, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Microbial Ecology and Pathogenesis, The Fortsyth Institute, Cambridge, Massachusetts, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biological Sciences, Wellesley College, Wellesley, Massachusetts, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>
<addr-line>Department of Oral Medicine, Infection and Immunity, Harvard School of Dental Medicine, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Planet</surname><given-names>Paul J</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Columbia University, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>lshaddox@dental.ufl.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: LMS SMW BP IA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: HH PFG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: PFG HH VKC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SMW VKC LMS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the manuscript: PFG LMS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e85066</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 Goncalves et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Goncalves et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec sec-type="headed"><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Objective </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The objective of this study was to determine whether the detection of Aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans (Aa) correlates with the clinical and immunoinflammatory profile of Localized Aggressive Periodontitis (LAP), as determined by by 16S rRNA gene-based microarray. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec sec-type="headed"><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Subjects and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Subgingival plaque samples from the deepest diseased site of 30 LAP patients [PD ≥ 5 mm, BoP and bone loss] were analyzed by 16S rRNA gene-based microarrays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Gingival crevicular fluid (GCF) samples were analyzed for 14 cyto/chemokines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Peripheral blood was obtained and stimulated in vitro with P.gingivalis and E.coli to evaluate inflammatory response profiles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Plasma lipopolysaccharide (LPS) levels were also measured. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec sec-type="headed"><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Aa was detected in 56% of LAP patients and was shown to be an indicator for different bacterial community structures (p&lt;0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Elevated levels of pro-inflammatory cyto/chemokines were detected in LPS-stimulated blood samples in both Aa-detected and Aa-non-detected groups (p&gt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Clinical parameters and serum LPS levels were similar between groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>However, Aa-non-detected GCF contained higher concentration of IL-8 than Aa-detected sites (p&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>TNFα and IL1β were elevated upon E.coli LPS stimulation of peripheral blood cells derived from patients with Aa-detected sites. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec sec-type="headed"><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Our findings demonstrate that the detection of Aa in LAP affected sites, did not correlate with clinical severity of the disease at the time of sampling in this cross-sectional study, although it did associate with lower local levels of IL-8, a different subgingival bacterial profile and elevated LPS-induced levels of TNFα and IL1β. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by NIH/NIDCR R01DE019456 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nidcr.nih.gov">www.nidcr.nih.gov</ext-link>). PF Gonçalves postdoctoral fellowship was supported by the National Council of Technological and Scientific Development, CNPq, Brazil (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cnpq.br">www.cnpq.br</ext-link>). 
The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="introduction" id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans (Aa) is a Gram-negative bacterium that colonizes the oral cavity of one third or more of the population aged up to 18 years [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>It has been highly implicated as the causative agent of aggressive periodontitis (AgP), a group of less frequent, often severe, rapidly progressive forms of periodontitis, with a more localized presentation of the disease (LAP) [2-4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>LAP is also characterized by an early age of onset, tendency for familial involvement, and bone loss affecting specifically molar and incisor teeth, [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Importantly, recent papers have pointed out the importance Aa, a particularly highly leukotoxic clone (JP2), in the initiation of attachment loss in young individuals [4,6,7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Our group has recently demonstrated a hyper-inflammatory trait in response to bacterial endotoxin in an LAP cohort of African-Americans, which results in the over-expression of pro-inflammatory cyto/chemokines [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>We also observed an exacerbated local inflammatory response, along with high systemic levels of bacterial lipopolysaccharides (LPS) [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we have reported Aa to be highly associated with LAP in this cohort [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>However, we could not detect Aa in every patient with LAP in our cohort, which is also consistent to previously reported literature [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Little is known regarding the impact of Aa’s presence on LAP disease presentation (clinical parameters and bacterial colonization) or the accompanying inflammatory response (regulation and local presentation). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Thus, the objective of this study was to evaluate our LAP cohort in relation to the presence of Aa and determine whether the detection of this species in LAP affected sites correlate with clinical presentation of disease, local cyto/chemokines, plasma LPS levels and the level of hyper-responsiveness of these individuals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Ethics statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>This study was conducted in full conformity with the principles set forth in The Belmont Report: Ethical Principles and Guidelines for the Protection of Human Subjects of Research, as drafted by the US National Commission for the Protection of Human Subjects of Biomedical and Behavioral Research (April 18, 1979) and codified in 45 CFR Part 46 and/or the ICH E6; 62 Federal Regulations 25691 (1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>This study was approved by the University of Florida Institutional Review Board. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Subject demographics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Subjects were selected from a cohort recruited from Leon County Health Department, Tallahassee, Florida, from February 2007 to August 2010. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>This study is part of a larger clinical trial (Clinical trial registration: #NCT01330719 at www.clinicaltrials.gov). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>A comprehensive microbiological profile as well as local and LPS-induced inflammatory response from initial subjects enrolled in this study has been reported in our previous publications [8-10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Both historical data and newly generated data were part of the present analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Specifically, all subjects enrolled in the clinical trial that had their baseline microbiological analysis completed were included in the present report[10], and new data on local and systemic inflammatory markers for some of these patients were run to fulfill the present investigation (see flowchart, Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Eight of the participants had siblings within the cohort, who happen to be part of the random pool of participants on which microbiological analysis had been completed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>All subjects and parents were informed about the study protocol and signed an informed consent previously approved by the University of Florida Institutional Review Board. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Inclusion criteria: subjects aged 5-21 years old, African-American, diagnosed with localized aggressive periodontitis, defined by presence of at least 2 sites, on first molar and/or incisor, with pocket depth &gt;4mm with bleeding on probing, presence of at least 2mm clinical attachment loss and radiographic bone loss [5,12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Exclusion criteria: subjects diagnosed with any systemic diseases or conditions that could influence the progression and/or clinical characteristics of periodontal disease (e.g., diabetes or blood disorders); taken antibiotics within the last 3 months or any medications that could influence the characteristics of the disease (e.g., phenytoin, cyclosporine); have received periodontal treatment within the previous 6 months; smokers; and pregnant/lactating women. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0085066-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085066.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Schematic flowchart of study design. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085066.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2.3"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Clinical measurements </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The following periodontal clinical parameters were taken by one calibrated examiner at the baseline visit (prior to treatment): Pocket Depth (PD), Bleeding on probing (BoP); Gingival margin position (GM), Clinical attachment level (CAL); Plaque Index (PI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>All measurements were performed using a UNC-15 periodontal probe at six sites per tooth and recorded using a computer software program (Florida Probe, Gainesville, FL, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Periapical and interproximal radiographs were taken on all patients at the baseline visit for diagnosis purposes only. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2.4"><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Gingival Crevicular Fluid (GCF) sampling </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Following clinical examination, and on the same day, samples were collected from the most severe diseased site (PD ≥ 5mm with BoP and CAL≥2 mm and radiographic bone loss). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Sites for GCF collection were isolated with cotton rolls, gently air-dried and supragingival plaque removed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>A collection strip (PerioPaper GCF collection strips, Oraflow Inc, Plainview, NY) was inserted in the sites 1-2 mm into the sulcus for ~10 sec, as described previously [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Volume of GCF was measured using aPeriotron®8000, (Oraflow, Inc.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>GCF samples were frozen at -70°C until analysis of soluble mediators was performed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2.5"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Collection of bacterial sub-gingival biofilm </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Subgingival plaque samples were collected from the same diseased site where GCF collection was made, as described above, also prior to treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The area of collection was isolated with cotton rolls and supragingival plaque was carefully removed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>A sterile endodontic paper point was used for the collection, placed in an eppendorf tube and stored at -70°C until processed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2.6"><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Microbial microarray analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>DNA was isolated from plaque samples as previously described [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>After purification, DNA concentration and quality was determined using the Nanodrop (ND-1000 Spectrophotometer, Nanodrop Technologies INC, Wilmington, DE, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Samples were analyzed at the Forsyth Institute using the Human Oral Microbe Identification Microarrays (HOMIM) as previously described [10,13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Briefly, 16S rRNA genes were PCR amplified from DNA extracts using 16S rRNA universal forward and reverse primers and labeled via incorporation of Cy3-dCTP in a second nested PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>HOMIM uses16S rRNA-based, reverse-capture oligonucleotide probes (typically 18 to 20 bases), which are printed on aldehyde-coated glass slides and probed with labeled PCR products described above which are hybridized in duplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The microarray slides are scanned using an Axon 4000B scanner and crude data is extracted using GenePix Pro software (Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Microbial profiles were generated from image files of scanned arrays using a HOMIM online analysis tool (http://bioinformatics.forsyth.org/homim/). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Detection of a particular taxon was determined by presence of a fluorescent spot for that unique probe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>A mean intensity for each taxon was calculated from hybridization spots of the same probe and signals were normalized by comparing individual signal intensities to the average of signals from universal probes and calculated as described previously [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Any original signal that was less than two times the background value was reset to 1 and was assigned to the signal level 0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Signals greater than 1 were categorized into scores from 1 to 5, corresponding to ranked signal levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Presence of Aa was determined if a site showed value of 1 or above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Absence of Aa was determined if a site showed a value of ‘0’ </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2.7"><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>In vitro LPS stimulation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Peripheral blood was collected in heparinized tubes, diluted 1:4 in RPMI1640 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) and stimulated with 1 μg/mL of ultrapure E.coli (Ec) LPS or P.gingivalis (Pg) LPS (InvivoGen, San Diego, CA, USA), or left untreated, for 24hrs [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>After which the resulting supernatants were collected and stored at -70°C until analysis of soluble mediators was performed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2.8"><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Analysis of soluble mediators </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Multiplex assays (Milliplex® 14-plex cytochemokine detection kits, Millipore, St. Charles, MO, USA) were used to detect and quantify 14 cyto/chemokines (Eotaxin, TNFα, IFNγ, IL1β, IL2, IL6, IL7, IL8, IL10, IL12p40, MCP-1, G-CSF, GM-CSF and MIP1α) in the crevicular fluid and LPS-stimulated culture supernatants according to the manufacture’s protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Data was acquired on the Luminex®200™ (Millipore, St. Charles, MO) and analyzed with Milliplex Software (Viagene Tech, Carlisle, MA, USA), a standard curve and 5-parameter logistics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Data is reported as pg/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>GCF data is normalization to total protein content: normalized pg/ml = [pg/ml x protein content corrective ratio], where corrective ratio = [lowest protein concentration/protein concentration of sample of interest]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2.9"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Plasma LPS levels </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Peripheral blood was collected in heparinized tubes, after which . plasma was separated from red blood cells by centrifugation (~300 x g for 15 min) and stored at -70°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>LPS levels were detected and quantified by using a chromogenic assay (Endpoint Chromogenic LAL Assay, Lonza, Basel, Switzerland). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Endotoxin units/ml were calculated using a standard curve and best fit linear trend line, as previously described [9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2.10"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Means were calculated and t-test was performed to compare patients presenting Aa-detected sites versus patients presenting Aa-non-detected sites for clinical and immunoinflammatory parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Mann-Whitney Rank Sum Test was applied when data was not normally distributed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>ANOVA analyses were used for comparisons within groups for LPS stimulation using different ligands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>This study was powered at &gt;80% to detect a 10% difference between the two groups in cyto/chemokine values [values based on previous publication data [8,9]] and a PD difference in affected sites of at least 1 mm with standard deviation of 0.9 mm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>SigmaPlot version 11.0 software (Systat Software Inc, Chicago, IL) was used for statistical analysis, considering a 5% significance level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>We considered cyto/chemokines to be independent variables and thus, no statistical corrections were done here [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Canonical correspondence analysis (CCA), nonmetric multidimensional scaling (NMDS), and ANOVA tests were used on HOMIM hybridization scores to test for significant effects of environmental variables on microbial community structures within sites with or without the detection of Aa, using the Vegan package for the R statistical programming environment [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>For generating CCA plots, Aa was excluded from the list of taxa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>To account for the multiple hypotheses, we adjusted p-value using Benjamini/Hochberg correction [16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Clinical and microbiologic characterization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>HOMIM resulted in 189 probes identifying at least 137 different bacterial taxa in diseased sites of LAP (for a more comprehensive microbial data description, including healthy controls, see [10]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Among these, two taxa of Aa were identified: Aa_ot531_AA84 and Aa_ot531_P02. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Sites presenting any signal for Aa (value 1 or greater) were considered Aa-detected (n=17) and those that did not present any signal for Aa (value 0) were considered Aa-non-detected (n=13). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>HOMIM analysis’ mean relative signal intensity of Aa in the Aa-detectedsites was 3.81±1.02, in a 0 to 5 signal scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, clinical parameters and demographics were similar between individuals with Aa-detected or Aa-non-detected sites, as determined by HOMIM (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0085066-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085066.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Clinical and demographic parameters for Aa+(positive) and Aa-(negative) groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Values are given by Means ± Standard deviation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>M=male; F=female; Mean PD sites= Mean pocket depth of sites with PD&gt;4mm; Mean PD all= mean PD of all sites; CAL=clinical attachment level of affected sites; BoP=bleeding on probing; PD site = Pocket depth from site sampled for microbiological analysis. *t-test; †Mann-Whitney Rank Sum Test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>In NMDS and CCA plots (Figure 2), samples with similar community composition cluster close together, while samples with different community compositions are farther apart on the plots; preserving the rank order of the original similarities [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Both NMDS and CCA analysis suggest that the detection of Aa was associated with specific bacterial community structures (of all variables tested, only the presence of Aa was statistically significant, permutation test under the reduced model with p&lt;0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>PD was not statistically significant relative to Aa detection (p=0.24) and therefore was not included in CCA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The left side of the CCA ordination plot is predominantly occupied by diseased sites containing Aa, whereas on the right side are predominantly diseased sites in which Aa was not detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>We observed that Granulicatella elegans (p=0.01) and Prevotella loeschii (p=0.02) were frequently found in samples co-existing when Aa was present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>In contrast, Porphyromonas gingivalis (p=0.02) and Parvimonas micra (p=0.03) were more likely to be found in Aa-non-detected communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>These significances disappear when corrected for multiple comparisons. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0085066-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085066.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Effect of Aa and microbial community composition, as measured by HOMIM hybridization scores. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The following variables were chosen as descriptors of the subgingival biofilm community and were calculated for each sample: pocket depth (PD), and presence of Aa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>This last term was chosen to determine if Aa alone reflects shifts in community composition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Non-metric multidimensional scaling analysis (NMDS) and B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Canonical correspondence analysis (CCA) ordination diagrams of microbial communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Red circles indicate samples where Aa was detected by HOMIM, and black circles indicate samples where there was no Aa detected by HOMIM analysis. Aa was critical for determining bacterial community structures (p&lt;0.01). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085066.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Local inflammatory profile and systemic LPS levels </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>As previously published, high levels of several inflammatory mediators were detected in the GCF of diseased sites of LAP participants [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Eotaxin, G-CSF and IL7 were not detected in high enough levels and thus were not included in the association analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>In general, no differences in the GCF mediator profiles were detected between Aa-detected and Aa-non-detected sites (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>However, IL8 was found at higher concentrations in Aa-non-detected sites than those observed in Aa-detected sites (p=0.011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>After controlling values for GCF volume at each diseased site of collection, the same trends were observed, and p-values slightly decreased, but did not reach statistical significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Systemic LPS levels were similar in Aa-non-detected and Aa-detected groups (Mean values 0.61±0.15 and 0.68±0.36, respectively; p=0.773). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0085066-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085066.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Inflammatory mediator profile in the GCF, in both groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Cytochemokines values are reported as normalized pg/mL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Box-plots show the mean (horizontal line), inter-quartile range (box), 5th -95th percentiles (vertical lines). *Statistically significant (p=0.01), t-test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085066.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3.3"><title><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>LPS-induced hyper-responsive phenotype </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The LPS responsiveness of individuals with Aa-non-detected and Aa-detected groups was compared. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>There was no significant differences between the levels of cyto/chemokines in unstimulated cultures of Aa-detected and Aa-non-detected individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Pg and Ec LPS-stimulation of whole blood cell preparation resulted in elevated levels of multiple pro-inflammatory cyto/chemokines when compared with unstimulated cultures (p&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>There were few significant differences in the levels of cyto/chemokines induced when comparing cohorts which had Aa-detected or Aa-non-detected sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Specifically, Ec LPS stimulation elicited more robust levels of TNFα and IL1β from peripheral blood of individuals with Aa-detectedsites than those with Aa-non-detected sites (p&lt;0.05) (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>In addition, GM-CSF was more highly induced by Pg LPS-stimulation in individuals with Aa-non-detected sites, compared to those with Aa-detected sites, although the difference did not reach significance (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0085066-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085066.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Systemic LPS-induced cyto/chemokine values in both groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Values are reported as normalized log pg/mL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Box-plots show the mean (horizontal line), inter-quartile range (box), 5th -95th percentiles (vertical lines). *Indicates statistically significant differences between groups (Aa+ and Aa-) by t-test (p&lt;0.05). #Indicates statistically significant differences within groups regarding TLR stimulation by One-way ANOVA (p&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085066.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>It has been previously suggested that an individual organism can play a strong role in community restructuring, and in turn impact the ecological processes of the system [18,19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>This change in community structure can also have an effect on local immune responses and thus the course of periodontal disease progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Among periodontal pathogens, Aa has received particular attention and has been regarded as a key factor in the etiology of LAP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>This view was based primarily on classic association studies linking Aa to disease and correlating treatment outcomes to its levels after therapy [20-25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>However, in a systematic review [11], it was shown that the presence or absence of Aa could not discriminate between subjects with aggressive periodontal disease from those with chronic periodontitis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The present study focused on the presence of Aa as a determinant factor in some aspects of disease presentation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>We observed a lack of association between Aa detection, as measured by HOMIM, and severity of clinical signs of the disease (i.e. pocket depth, clinical attachment levels at time of sampling). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>This is not unexpected, considering that the criteria for diagnosis of LAP used in this study are very strict for clinical signs of disease, although it is impossible to determine the disease state of the sampled sites, even before treatment is rendered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>However, if we were to include healthy individuals or even healthy sites (i.e. PD≤3mm and no bop), the presence of Aa could indeed be more correlated with the diseased clinical parameters [4,6,7,10,26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>It should be noted that the HOMIM assay has a sensitivity of about 0.1% and an overall limit of detection about 104 cells (Colombo, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Consequently, it is possible that Aa at levels below the level of detection could still be present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, Aa-detected sites presented very high signal levels for (mean relative signal intensity was 3.81), which makes the two populations very distinct for Aa detection using HOMIM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, at this detection level, the presence or absence of Aa was associated with a difference in the composition of the microbial community as a whole. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>We also evaluated the correlation between the detection of Aa and local inflammatory mediators as a measure of active disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, a higher expression of IL-8 in GCF was detected in Aa-non-detected sites as compared to Aa-detected sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>IL-8 is involved in the recruitment of PMNs and is highly expressed in the junctional epithelium adjacent under the conditions of health whereby disease has been shown to modulate these levels both positively and negatively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Many organisms, including P.gingivalis, have virulence factors which affect IL8 stability within the GCF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Our data indicate that the non-detection of Aa results in a different microbial community than when it is detected at levels above 104, thus it is possible that the absence/minimal presence of Aa, i.e. Aa-non-detected sites promotes an environment for an organism that possess these virulence factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>As demonstrated in our results, P.gingivalis may be frequently detected when Aa is not, where IL-8 levels were lower. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Although P.gingivalis have been associated with periodontal inflammatory response, its potential to induce this response may shift according to the environment, specific virulent factors, and association with other species of the biofilm[27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>For instance, specific structures on P.gingivalis LPS may up-regulate or down-regulate levels of pro-inflammatory markers, including IL-8[28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>In addition, the presence of other bacterial species [29], as well as different peptides [30,31] may also reduce this organism’s pro-inflammatory abilities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, it is possible that Aa has a direct effect on the suppression of IL8 from the junctional epithelium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>However, the differences in IL8 expression in the GCF did not correlate with differences in clinical parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Both Aa-detected and Aa-non-detected cohorts had already advanced clinical signs of LAP, thus IL8 levels may be more indicative of active vs. inactive disease than severity of disease, which would also suggest that the presence and/or absence of Aa may also be a correlate of disease activity, although data presented here are insufficient to support this hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Longitudinal studies of the disease need to be conducted to asses this hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Elevated local inflammation can sometimes result in the dissemination of bacteria and their products systemically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, no differences in the levels of plasma LPS was observed between Aa-detected and Aa-non-detected cohorts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>This was not unexpected considering that other than IL8, which does not directly contribute to epithelial ulceration, there were no significant differences in the levels of cyto/chemokines within the GCF of the Aa-detected and Aa-non-detected cohorts. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>We have previously published that LAP individuals present with a hyper-inflammatory phenotype whereby they respond in a more robust manner to stimuli [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Here we demonstrate that overall whether an individual is colonized with Aa or not does not correlate with their level of LPS-induced responsive potential, with one exception. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>As a group, individuals with diseased sites that have Aa detected, respond more robustly to Ec LPS-stimulation as measured by IL1β and TNFα. E.coli LPS is mainly a TLR4 agonist, as is Aa LPS [32] [33] and this is why it was chosen for evaluation in the present study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Thus, one could hypothesize that in Aa carriers the potential for hyper-secretion of TNFα and IL1β could result in more robust tissue damage and disease progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>However, we did not observe elevated levels of TNFα nor IL1β in the GCF of Aa detected sites, nor was the snapshot of disease severity different in those individuals with Aa-detected or Aa-non-detected sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The direct relationship between Aa presence, GCF markers and host inflammatory response to LPS cannot be resolved in this cross-sectional study but could be determined in future studies that test the likelihood that these cytokine elevations could be found prior to disease or during disease progression at the local site. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>In summary, the present study demonstrates that, in this population, similar clinical parameters of disease were observed regardless of whether Aa was detected or remained undetected by HOMIM in diseased sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>This study is cross-sectional and thus, it only represents a snapshot of the disease state at one point in time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>However, our findings indicate potential differences in the microbial community profile associated (G.elegans and P.loeschii) or not associated (P.gingivalis and P.micra) with this species as well as effects on the local inflammation (IL8 in GCF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, individuals with detectable levels of Aa also present with a TLR4 (Ec LPS) induced TNFα and IL1β hyper-responsiveness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Further longitudinal studies are necessary to evaluate whether these differences could impact disease progression and treatment responses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>We thank Drs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Edward Zapert, John Bidwell and Dan Cober and all the staff from Leon County Dental Clinic, for the clinical assistance with this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Clinical trial registration: #NCT01330719. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>1 LamellCW, GriffenAL, McClellanDL, LeysEJ (2000) Acquisition and colonization stability of Actinobacillus actinomycetemcomitans and Porphyromonas gingivalis in children. J Clin Microbiol 38: 1196-1199. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10699021">10699021</ext-link>.10699021 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>2 MooreWE, MooreLH, RanneyRR, SmibertRM, BurmeisterJA et al. (1991) The microflora of periodontal sites showing active destructive progression. J Clin Periodontol 18: 729-739. doi:10.1111/j.1600-051X.1991.tb00064.x. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1752997">1752997</ext-link>.1752997 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>3 SocranskySS, HaffajeeAD (1992) The bacterial etiology of destructive periodontal disease: current concepts. J Periodontol 63: 322-331. doi:10.1902/jop.1992.63.4s.322. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1573546">1573546</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>4 FineDH, MarkowitzK, FurgangD, FairlieK, FerrandizJ et al. (2007) Aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans and its relationship to initiation of localized aggressive periodontitis: longitudinal cohort study of initially healthy adolescents. J Clin Microbiol 45: 3859-3869. doi:10.1128/JCM.00653-07. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17942658">17942658</ext-link>.17942658 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>5 ArmitageGC (1999) Development of a classification system for periodontal diseases and conditions. Ann Periodontol 4: 1-6. doi:10.1902/annals.1999.4.1.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10863370">10863370</ext-link>.10863370 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>6 HaubekD (2010) The highly leukotoxic JP2 clone of Aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans: evolutionary aspects, epidemiology and etiological role in aggressive periodontitis. APMIS Suppl: 1-53. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21214629">21214629</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>7 HaubekD, EnnibiOK, PoulsenK, VaethM, PoulsenS et al. (2008) Risk of aggressive periodontitis in adolescent carriers of the JP2 clone of Aggregatibacter (Actinobacillus) actinomycetemcomitans in Morocco: a prospective longitudinal cohort study. Lancet 371: 237-242. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(08)60135-X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18207019">18207019</ext-link>.18207019 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>8 ShaddoxL, WiedeyJ, BimsteinE, MagnusonI, Clare-SalzlerM et al. (2010) Hyper-responsive phenotype in localized aggressive periodontitis. J Dent Res 89: 143-148. doi:10.1177/0022034509353397. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20042739">20042739</ext-link>.20042739 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>9 ShaddoxLM, WiedeyJ, CalderonNL, MagnussonI, BimsteinE et al. (2011) Local inflammatory markers and systemic endotoxin in aggressive periodontitis. J Dent Res 90: 1140-1144. doi:10.1177/0022034511413928. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21730256">21730256</ext-link>.21730256 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>10 ShaddoxLM, HuangH, LinT, HouW, HarrisonPL et al. (2012) Microbiological Characterization in Children with Aggressive Periodontitis. J Dent Res 91: 927–933. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22863892">22863892</ext-link>.22863892 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="?"><plain>11 MombelliA, CasagniF, MadianosPN (2002) Can presence or absence of periodontal pathogens distinguish between subjects with chronic and aggressive periodontitis? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>A systematic review. J Clin Periodontol 29 (Suppl 3): 10-37; discussion: 12787203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>12 LangNP, BartoldM, CullinanM, JeffcoatM, MombelliA et al. (1999) Consensus Report: Aggressive Periodontitis. 53 p. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>13 ColomboAP, BochesSK, CottonSL, GoodsonJM, KentR et al. (2009) Comparisons of subgingival microbial profiles of refractory periodontitis, severe periodontitis, and periodontal health using the human oral microbe identification microarray. J Periodontol 80: 1421-1432. doi:10.1902/jop.2009.090185. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19722792">19722792</ext-link>.19722792 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>14 RothmanKJ (1990) No adjustments are needed for multiple comparisons. Epidemiology 1: 43-46. doi:10.1097/00001648-199001000-00010. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2081237">2081237</ext-link>.2081237 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>15 HornikK, LeischF, Team RDC (2005) R version 2.1.0 (vol 19, pg 661, 2004). Computational Statistics 20: 197-202. doi:10.1007/BF02789699. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>16 BenjaminiY, HochbergY (1995) Controlling the false discovery rate - A practical and powerful approach to multiple testing Journal of the Royal Statistical Society Series B-Methodological 57. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>17 GotelliNJ, EllisonAM (2004). A primer of ecological statistics. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>18 SandersNJ, GotelliNJ, HellerNE, GordonDM (2003) Community disassembly by an invasive species. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 100: 2474–2477. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12604772">12604772</ext-link>.12604772 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>19 Klepac-CerajV, LemonKP, MartinTR, AllgaierM, KembelSW et al. (2010) Relationship between cystic fibrosis respiratory tract bacterial communities and age, genotype, antibiotics and Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Environ Microbiol 12: 1293-1303. doi:10.1111/j.1462-2920.2010.02173.x. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20192960">20192960</ext-link>.20192960 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>20 HaffajeeAD, SocranskySS, EbersoleJL, SmithDJ (1984) Clinical, microbiological and immunological features associated with the treatment of active periodontosis lesions. J Clin Periodontol 11: 600-618. doi:10.1111/j.1600-051X.1984.tb00913.x. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/6386896">6386896</ext-link>.6386896 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>21 ChristerssonLA, SlotsJ, RoslingBG, GencoRJ (1985) Microbiological and clinical effects of surgical treatment of localized juvenile periodontitis. J Clin Periodontol 12: 465-476. doi:10.1111/j.1600-051X.1985.tb01382.x. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/3894435">3894435</ext-link>.3894435 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>22 MandellRL, TripodiLS, SavittE, GoodsonJM, SocranskySS (1986) The effect of treatment on Actinobacillus actinomycetemcomitans in localized juvenile periodontitis. J Periodontol 57: 94-99. doi:10.1902/jop.1986.57.2.94. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2420958">2420958</ext-link>.2420958 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>23 KanerD, ChristanC, DietrichT, BernimoulinJP, KleberBM et al. (2007) Timing affects the clinical outcome of adjunctive systemic antibiotic therapy for generalized aggressive periodontitis. J Periodontol 78: 1201-1208. doi:10.1902/jop.2007.060437. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17608574">17608574</ext-link>.17608574 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>24 LeungWK, NgaiVK, YauJY, CheungBP, TsangPW et al. (2005) Characterization of Actinobacillus actinomycetemcomitans isolated from young Chinese aggressive periodontitis patients. J Periodontal Res 40: 258-268. doi:10.1111/j.1600-0765.2005.00805.x. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15853973">15853973</ext-link>.15853973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>25 ZambonJJ, ChristerssonLA, SlotsJ (1983) Actinobacillus actinomycetemcomitans in human periodontal disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Prevalence in patient groups and distribution of biotypes and serotypes within families. J Periodontol 54: 707-711. doi:10.1902/jop.1983.54.12.707. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/6358452">6358452</ext-link>.6358452 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>26 EnnibiOK, BenrachadiL, BouzianeA, HaubekD, PoulsenK (2012) The highly leukotoxic JP2 clone of Aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans in localized and generalized forms of aggressive periodontitis. Acta Odontol Scand 70: 318-322. doi:10.3109/00016357.2011.642002. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22251014">22251014</ext-link>.22251014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>27 CuginiC, Klepac-CerajV, RackaityteE, RiggsJE, DaveyME (2013) Porphyromonas gingivalis: keeping the pathos out of the biont. J Oral Microbiol 5 PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23565326">23565326</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>28 HerathTD, DarveauRP, SeneviratneCJ, WangCY, WangY et al. (2013) Tetra- and penta-acylated lipid A structures of Porphyromonas gingivalis LPS differentially activate TLR4-mediated NF-kappaB signal transduction cascade and immuno-inflammatory response in human gingival fibroblasts. PLOS ONE 8: e58496. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0058496. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23554896">23554896</ext-link>.23554896 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>29 ZhaoJJ, FengXP, ZhangXL, LeKY (2012) Effect of Porphyromonas gingivalis and Lactobacillus acidophilus on secretion of IL1B, IL6, and IL8 by gingival epithelial cells. Inflammation 35: 1330-1337. doi:10.1007/s10753-012-9446-5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22382516">22382516</ext-link>.22382516 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>30 KrausD, WinterJ, JepsenS, JägerA, MeyerR et al. (2012) Interactions of adiponectin and lipopolysaccharide from Porphyromonas gingivalis on human oral epithelial cells. PLOS ONE 7: e30716. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0030716. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22319581">22319581</ext-link>.22319581 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>31 InomataM, IntoT, MurakamiY (2010) Suppressive effect of the antimicrobial peptide LL-37 on expression of IL-6, IL-8 and CXCL10 induced by Porphyromonas gingivalis cells and extracts in human gingival fibroblasts. Eur J Oral Sci 118: 574-581. doi:10.1111/j.1600-0722.2010.00775.x. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21083618">21083618</ext-link>.21083618 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>32 MahanondaR, PichyangkulS (2007) Toll-like receptors and their role in periodontal health and disease. Periodontol 2000 43: 41-55. doi:10.1111/j.1600-0757.2006.00179.x. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17214834">17214834</ext-link>.17214834 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>33 LeeSH, KimKK, RhyuIC, KohS, LeeDS et al. (2006) Phenol/water extract of Treponema socranskii subsp. socranskii as an antagonist of Toll-like receptor 4 signalling. Microbiology 152: 535-546. doi:10.1099/mic.0.28470-0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16436441">16436441</ext-link>.16436441 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
