
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Dis Markers</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Dis. Markers</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Disease Markers</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0278-0240</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1875-8630</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3934384</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/269208</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>RBP4 Gene Variants Are Associated with Insulin Resistance in Women with Previous Gestational Diabetes </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5167-6156</contrib-id><name><surname>Saucedo</surname><given-names>Renata</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3606-0390</contrib-id><name><surname>Zarate</surname><given-names>Arturo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2991-0433</contrib-id><name><surname>Basurto</surname><given-names>Lourdes</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>Marcelino</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Puello</surname><given-names>Edgardo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0395-1122</contrib-id><name><surname>Mendoza-Lorenzo</surname><given-names>Patricia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ostrosky-Wegman</surname><given-names>Patricia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Endocrine Research Unit, National Medical Center, Mexican Social Security Institute, 06720 Mexico City, MX, Mexico</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Hospital of Gynecology and Obstetrics, Medical Center La Raza, Mexican Social Security Institute, 02990 Mexico City, MX, Mexico</aff><aff id="I3"><sup>3</sup>Department of Genomic Medicine and Environmental Toxicology, Instituto de Investigaciones Biomedicas, Autonomous National University of Mexico, 04510 Mexico City, MX, Mexico</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Renata Saucedo: <email>sgrenata@yahoo.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editor: Irene Rebelo </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>2014</volume><elocation-id>269208</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2014 Renata Saucedo et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Objective. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>This study aimed to examine possible genetic effects of some retinol binding protein-4 (RBP4) single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) on the risk of gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>In addition, the SNPs were examined for their possible association with insulin resistance at 6 weeks after delivery. Methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>This was a prospective study of 100 women with GDM and 100 participants with normal gestation who were evaluated at gestational week 30 and 6 weeks postpartum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Three SNPs of RBP4 (rs3758539, rs116736522, and rs34571439) were genotyped using TaqMan assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The genotype distributions between GDM patients and normal controls were analyzed using logistic regression models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>In addition, differences in clinical characteristics among subjects grouped by genotype were assessed using the analysis of covariance test. Results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The frequencies of the rare alleles were not significantly different between GDM patients and controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>However, we identified two variants rs3758539 and rs34571439 associated with insulin levels and insulin resistance in women with previous GDM. Conclusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Noncoding SNPs of the RBP4 gene are not associated with GDM, but two SNPs showed associations with insulin resistance and insulin levels in women with prior GDM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Additional studies with increased sample size will be necessary in other GDM cohorts. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Genetic studies of type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2D) suggest that it is a multigenic disease in which common variants in multiple genes interact with environmental factors to cause the disease [1–3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Gene mapping has led to the identification of various chromosomal regions containing T2D susceptibility genes; one of them has been linked to an increased risk for type 2 diabetes in Caucasians and Mexican Americans and is located on chromosome 10q24 [4, 5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The retinol binding protein-4 (RBP4) gene is located in this region and various studies showed that single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) rs3758539, rs34571439, and rs116736522 in the RBP4 gene increased the risk of type 2 diabetes [6–11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>It is well known that women with gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM) are at a greater risk of developing T2D later in life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>GDM shares several risk factors with T2D and shares similar pathophysiology [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Because of these striking parallels, recent work on the etiology of GDM has begun to evaluate the role of common variants in genes predisposing to T2D [13, 14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The present study was directed to investigate some associations between the three SNPs of RBP4 previously shown to be present in persons showing some susceptibility to T2DM, during pregnancy and after delivery in women with GDM and healthy pregnant controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>This is a prospective study conducted with 100 women with GDM and 100 pregnant healthy controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Gestational diabetes was diagnosed by a 2 h 75 g oral glucose tolerance test at 24–28 weeks of gestation, the cutoff values being &gt;5.2 mmol/L at fasting, &gt;10.0 mmol/L at 1 h, and &gt;7.8 mmol/L at 2 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The protocol was approved by the hospital research ethics board and all participants gave written informed consent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Women with arterial hypertension, renal disease, liver disease, thyroid disorders, or other endocrine or chronic diseases were excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In the morning, at gestational week 30, anthropometric measurements of height and weight were obtained using a medical scale and blood samples were taken. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>A physical examination including measurement of blood pressure and a detailed history including family history of diabetes and obstetrical and medical information were obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>After delivery, women with GDM and women with normal pregnancy returned to the clinical investigation unit for a 2 h 75 g OGTT at six weeks postpartum. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Laboratory Measurements </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Venous blood samples for biochemical analysis were obtained in the morning after an overnight fast from an antecubital vein between 7:30 and 8:30 AM using vacuum tubes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The samples were centrifuged at 400 ×g for 15 minutes, and aliquots were obtained and stored at −70°C until assayed in a single run. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Plasma glucose, triglycerides, and total cholesterol were measured by enzymatic assays with a Roche Cobas Mira analyzer using commercial kits (Stanbio Laboratory, Boerne, TX, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Insulin and RBP4 concentrations were determined by radioimmunoassay (RIA); insulin was measured using reagents from Siemens Healthcare Diagnostics (Los Angeles, CA, USA), sensitivity was 8.3 pmol/L and intra- and interassay coefficients of variation (CVs) were 5.2 and 7.3%, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>RBP4 was determined using reagents from Phoenix Pharmaceuticals (Belmont, CA, USA); sensitivity was 6.4 pg/mL and CVs were 4.9 and 8.3%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA was isolated from anticoagulated blood by using the GFX Genomic Blood DNA Purification Kit (Amersham Biosciences) and stored at −70°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Genotyping of selected SNPs in all study subjects was done using the TaqMan assay (Applied Biosystems) for the variants rs3758539, rs116736522, and rs34571439. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The Taq-Man genotyping reaction was performed according to the manufacturer's protocol on an ABI Prism 7000 (Applied Biosystems, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Body mass index (BMI) was calculated as weight in kilograms divided by the square of height in meters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The degree of insulin resistance was estimated by the homeostasis model assessment of insulin resistance (HOMA-IR) as follows: fasting glucose (mmol/L) × fasting insulin (mU/L)/22.5 [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>We examined Lewontin's D′ and the linkage disequilibrium coefficient r 2 between all pairs of biallelic loci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Haplotypes were inferred using the algorithm developed by the Broad Institute, Haploview. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The allele distributions of polymorphisms among patients with GDM patients and normal subjects were evaluated by χ 2-test and Fisher exact tests accordingly, calculating odds ratios (ORs), 95% confidence intervals (CIs), and corresponding P values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>We performed a multiple logistic regression analysis to estimate whether maternal age, maternal BMI, and RBP4 genotype were suitable as prognostic factors for GDM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Because the frequency of the subgroups AA for SNP rs3758539, CC for SNP rs116736522, and CC for SNP rs34571439 is too low to perform statistical analysis, we combined these groups with the heterozygous group in a dominant model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Differences in clinical characteristics among subjects grouped by genotype were assessed using the analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) test, with age and BMI as covariates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses were carried out using Statistica version 8 (StatSoft, Tulsa, OK, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Significance was achieved at P &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The subjects' characteristics are shown in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>GDM patients were significantly older and heavier than the control group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Of the biochemical parameters studied, total cholesterol and triglyceride levels were significantly higher in GDM patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The genotype and allele frequencies are shown in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>All variants are in the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium and during pregnancy, no significant difference was observed among the studied groups related to the polymorphisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>In the logistic regression analysis, the association between GDM and maternal age as well as weight was significant (odds ratio (OR) 1.21, 95% confidence interval (CI) 1.14–1.29, and P = 0.02; OR 1.04, 95% CI 1.01–1.09, and P = 0.03, resp.). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>We estimated linkage disequilibrium among the three studied variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>As a result, rs3758539 and rs34571439 were in a tight LD block (D′ 0.9 and r 2 0.6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>At 6 weeks after delivery in women with previous GDM, the insulin levels and HOMA-IR were significantly different between the G/G homozygotes and A allele carriers for rs3758539 and between A/A homozygotes and C allele carriers for rs34571439; the A allele carriers for rs3758539 and the C allele carriers for rs34571439 had a higher insulin and HOMA-IR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>After adjustment for age and weight, the difference remained significant (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>In healthy controls at postpartum, cholesterol was significantly different between the G/G homozygotes and A allele carriers for rs3758539 and between G/G homozygotes and C allele carriers for rs116736522; the A carriers for rs3758539 and the C allele carriers for rs116736522 had a higher concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Moreover, RBP4 levels were significantly different between the G/G homozygotes and C allele carriers for rs116736522; the C allele carriers had a higher concentration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Further adjustment for age and weight abolished the difference observed between the two groups (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>RBP4 has been proposed recently as an adipokine that may contribute to insulin resistance in muscle and liver, both in mice and humans [16, 17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>It is known that plasma RBP4 concentrations are positively related to insulin resistance, diabetes mellitus type 2, obesity, and a history of GDM [18–21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>However, discrepant results were also reported [22–25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, this study is the first report of RBP4 polymorphisms in patients with previous gestational diabetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Our data show that noncoding SNPs of the RBP4 gene are not associated with gestational diabetes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>However, rs34571431 and rs3758539 showed associations with insulin levels and with insulin resistance in GDM subjects at postpartum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>This association is consistent with the results obtained in T2D [6–11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Our results vary from a previous study investigating RBP4 variants in Chinese women with GDM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>In this study the variant rs3758539 was involved in the development of GDM [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>By contrast, this variant was not found to be associated with GDM in Asian and Pacific Islander women [27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The rs3758539 minor allele frequency observed for the GDM group was lower than those reported for Caucasian and Filipino with GDM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the frequency was similar to those reported for Chinese with GDM and higher than those reported for Pacific Islander [26, 27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The variants rs34571431 and rs116736522 have not been evaluated in GDM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The rs34571431 was in linkage disequilibrium with rs3758539. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The rs34571431 is located at 5 bp downstream of the hepatocyte nuclear factor 1 motif, and it has been proposed that it could modify gene transcription efficiency by affecting the binding of transcription factors and RBP4 plasma levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>However, we did not find an effect of this polymorphism on serum RBP4 levels. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>In addition, we found association between rs34571431 and rs3758539 with insulin concentrations and insulin resistance in GDM subjects at postpartum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The rare allele A carriers had higher insulin concentration and insulin resistance than G/G homozygote carriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Previous studies reported that SNPs of RBP4 could increase diabetes susceptibility and decrease insulin secretion and insulin sensitivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>RBP4 is thought to affect insulin sensitivity by downregulating the activities of phosphoinositol-3-kinase and the phosphorylation of insulin in muscles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, RBP4 can stimulate hepatic gluconeogenesis through stimulation of phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>However, the mechanisms by which noncoding RBP4 variants could decrease insulin secretion are unclear. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>This study is subject to certain limitations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>We compared the genotype frequencies in GDM patients with those in unmatched controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>A control group consisting of age- and BMI-matched pregnant women without GDM may be more suitable for identification of the GDM susceptibility genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Our study was underpowered to detect associations of RBP4 single nucleotide polymorphisms with GDM, probably because of their low frequencies, which may have resulted in some associations being overlooked. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Using the single SNPs with the largest difference in minor allele frequency between cases and controls, we would need over 2350 cases and 2350 controls for 80% power to find a difference in rs34571439 or 7670 cases and 7670 controls to find a significant difference given the observed frequencies at rs116736522. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>We are aware that we have not corrected our statistical analyses for the number of comparisons made; the results therefore must be interpreted with caution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>However, we did see an association of individual SNPs with quantitative traits related to glucose homeostasis in women with previous GDM, similar to the findings reported by Craig et al. who showed significant effects of RBP4 genetic variation on insulin resistance in Caucasians [7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>It seems that genetic variants rs3758539, rs116736522, and rs34571439 of the RBP4 gene are not associated with gestational diabetes, but the variants rs3758539 and rs34571439 show associations with insulin resistance and insulin levels at 6 weeks after delivery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>This association is similar to that observed in T2D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Additional studies with increased sample size will be necessary in other GDM cohorts. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by scientific grants from IMSS (FIS/IMSS/PROT 080) and CONACYT (2007-01-69232). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Renata Saucedo, Arturo Zarate, Lourdes Basurto, Marcelino Hernandez, Patricia Mendoza-Lorenzo, and Patricia Ostrosky-Wegman hold a fellowship from the National System of Investigators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The authors thank Hospital of Gynecology and Obstetrics Medical Center La Raza, the Mexican Social Security Institute, for providing patient care services. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec sec-type="conflict"><title>Conflict of Interests</title><p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>1GrantRWMooreAFFlorezJCGenetic architecture of type 2 diabetes: recent progress and clinical implicationsDiabetes Care2009326110711142-s2.0-6654908760019460916 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>2HerderCRodenMGenetics of type 2 diabetes: pathophysiologic and clinical relevanceEuropean Journal of Clinical Investigation20114166796922-s2.0-7995561450221198561 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>3AhlqvistEAhluwaliaTSGroopLGenetics of type 2 diabetesClinical Chemistry20115722412542-s2.0-7955149790021119033 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>4MeigsJBPanhuysenCIMMyersRHWilsonPWFAdrienne CupplesLA genome-wide scan for loci linked to plasma levels of glucose and HbA1c in a community-based sample of Caucasian pedigrees: the Framingham Offspring StudyDiabetes20025138338402-s2.0-003631762811872688 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>5DuggiralaRBlangeroJAlmasyLLinkage of type 2 diabetes mellitus and of age at onset to a genetic location on chromosome 10q in Mexican AmericansThe American Journal of Human Genetics1999644112711402-s2.0-003336505710090898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>6MunkhtulgaLNakayamaKUtsumiNIdentification of a regulatory SNP in the retinol binding protein 4 gene associated with type 2 diabetes in MongoliaHuman Genetics200712068798882-s2.0-3384638026817006670 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>7CraigRLChuWSElbeinSCRetinol binding protein 4 as a candidate gene for type 2 diabetes and prediabetic intermediate traitsMolecular Genetics and Metabolism20079033383442-s2.0-3384703072217174134 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>8HuCJiaWZhangREffect of RBP4 gene variants on circulating RBP4 concentration and Type 2 diabetes in a Chinese populationDiabetic Medicine200825111182-s2.0-3804909872718199128 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>9KovacsPGeyerMBerndtJEffects of genetic variation in the human retinol binding protein-4 gene (RBP4) on insulin resistance and fat depot-specific mRNA expressionDiabetes20075612309531002-s2.0-3684901205517728376 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>10van HoekMDehghanAZillikensMCHofmanAWittemanJCSijbrandsEJGAn RBP4 promoter polymorphism increases risk of type 2 diabetesDiabetologia2008518142314282-s2.0-4814910691218496666 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>11Ribel-MadsenRFriedrichsenMVaagAPoulsenPRetinol-binding protein 4 in twins: regulatory mechanisms and impact of circulating and tissue expression levels on insulin secretion and actionDiabetes200958154602-s2.0-6324913319018852328 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>12BellamyLCasasJ-PHingoraniADWilliamsDType 2 diabetes mellitus after gestational diabetes: a systematic review and meta-analysisThe Lancet20093739677177317792-s2.0-65649084159 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>13LauenborgJGrarupNDammPCommon type 2 diabetes risk gene variants associate with gestational diabetesJournal of Clinical Endocrinology and Metabolism20099411451502-s2.0-5814938579118984664 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>14ChoYMKimTHLimSType 2 diabetes-associated genetic variants discovered in the recent genome-wide association studies are related to gestational diabetes mellitus in the Korean populationDiabetologia20095222532612-s2.0-5814946412119002430 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>15MatthewsDRHoskerJPRudenskiASHomeostasis model assessment: insulin resistance and β-cell function from fasting plasma glucose and insulin concentrations in manDiabetologia19852874124192-s2.0-00218131873899825 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>16YangQGrahamTEModyNSerum retinol binding protein 4 contributes to insulin resistance in obesity and type 2 diabetesNature200543670493563622-s2.0-2294443492916034410 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>17GrahamTEYangQBlüherMRetinol-binding protein 4 and insulin resistance in lean, obese, and diabetic subjectsThe New England Journal of Medicine200635424255225632-s2.0-3374509539916775236 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>18PolonskyKSRetinol-binding protein 4, insulin resistance, and type 2 diabetesThe New England Journal of Medicine200635424259625982-s2.0-3374507536016775241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>19LeeD-CLeeJ-WImJ-AAssociation of serum retinol binding protein 4 and insulin resistance in apparently healthy adolescentsMetabolism20075633273312-s2.0-3384684889717292720 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>20ChanT-FChenH-SChenY-CIncreased serum retinol-binding protein 4 concentrations in women with gestational diabetes mellitusReproductive Sciences20071421691742-s2.0-3464884661117636228 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>21LewandowskiKCStojanovicNBienkiewiczMElevated concentrations of retinol-binding protein-4 (RBP-4) in gestational diabetes mellitus: negative correlation with soluble vascular cell adhesion molecule-1 (sVCAM-1)Gynecological Endocrinology20082463003052-s2.0-4634909400018584408 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>22JankeJEngeliSBoschmannMRetinol-binding protein 4 in human obesityDiabetes20065510280528102-s2.0-3375085142217003346 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>23VitkovaMKlimcakovaEKovacikovaMPlasma levels and adipose tissue messenger ribonucleic acid expression of retinol-binding protein 4 are reduced during calorie restriction in obese subjects but are not related to diet-induced changes in insulin sensitivityJournal of Clinical Endocrinology and Metabolism2007926233023352-s2.0-3434725232617405846 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>24KrzyzanowskaKZemanyLKruglugerWSerum concentrations of retinol-binding protein 4 in women with and without gestational diabetesDiabetologia2008517111511222-s2.0-4474909505018437353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>25TepperBJKimY-KSheteVShabrovaEQuadroLSerum retinol-binding protein 4 (RBP4) and retinol in a cohort of borderline obese women with and without gestational diabetesClinical Biochemistry20104333203232-s2.0-7424910507319857477 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>26PingFXiangH-DLiMEffects of variation in retinol binding protein 4 gene and adipose specific expression of gestational diabetes in Beijing, ChinaDiabetes Research and Clinical Practice2012972832892-s2.0-8485842003122444425 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>27HiraokaMUrschitzJSultanOWardKA polymorphism in the retinol binding protein 4 gene is not associated with gestational diabetes mellitus in several different ethnic groupsHawaii Medical Journal20117081641672-s2.0-8485616327721886308 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>General characteristics of participants at gestational week 30. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Data are means ± SD. </p></fn><fn><p>*<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>χ 2 analysis of RBP4 polymorphisms among patients with GDM and healthy controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Association between SNPs and clinical features in two groups at postpartum. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Data are mean ± SD.</p></fn><fn><p>*<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></fn><fn><p>
<sup>†</sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 adjusted for age and BMI.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
