
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Iran J Parasitol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Iran J Parasitol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJPA</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Iranian Journal of Parasitology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1735-7020</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2008-238X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Tehran University of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3724147</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJPA-8-227</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Genotyping of Toxoplasma gondii Isolates from Soil Samples in Tehran, Iran </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tavalla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oormazdi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Akhlaghi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shojaee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Razmjou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hadighi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Meamar</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Dept. of Medical Parasitology, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences, Ahvaz, Iran</aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>Dept. of Parasitology and Mycology, School of Medicine, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="AF0003"><label>3</label>Dept. of Medical Parasitology and Mycology, School of Public Health, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding author:</bold><bold>Email:</bold><email xlink:href="ameamaer@tums.ac.ir">ameamaer@tums.ac.ir</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Apr-Jun</season><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 Iranian Society of Parasitology &amp; Tehran University of Medical Sciences</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The protozoan parasite Toxoplasma gondii can infect any warm blooded nucleated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>One of the ways for human infection is ingestion of oocysts directly from soil or via infected fruits or vegetables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>To survey the potential role of T. gondii oocyst in soil samples, the present study was conducted in Tehran City, Iran. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec id="st2"><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>A total of 150 soil samples were collected around rubbish dumps, children's play ground, parks and public places. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Oocysts recovery was performed by sodium nitrate flotation method on soil samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>For molecular detection, PCR reaction targeting B1 gene was performed and then, the positive results were confirmed using repetitive 529 bp DNA fragment in other PCR reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Finally, the positive samples were genotyped at the SAG2 locus. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec id="st3"><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Toxoplasma DNA was found in 13 soil samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>After genotyping and RFLP analysis in SAG2 locus, nine positive samples were revealed type III, one positive sample was type I whereas three samples revealed mixed infection (type, I &amp; III). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec id="st4"><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The predominant genotype in Tehran soil samples is type III. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic></kwd><kwd>SAG2</kwd><kwd>Soil</kwd><kwd>Genotype</kwd><kwd>Iran</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="S0001"><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Toxoplasma gondii is a widely distributed coccidian parasite that can infect a wide range of animals and humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>It is over 100 years since the discovery of the parasite in 1908 and now it is used extensively as a model for cell biology of apicomplexan organisms (1, 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>This coccidian parasite is the causative agent of toxoplasmosis, one of the most prevalent parasitic infectious diseases in animals and humans (3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Transmission of this parasite occurs by consumption of raw or undercooked meat containing tissue cyst or by ingestion of mature oocysts from environmental sources such as soil, water, fruits and vegetables (4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>It is estimated that 15% to 85% of human population in the world are chronically infected with T. gondii (2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Toxoplasmosis is mainly asymptomatic in immunocompetent individuals, but in immunocompromised patients such as HIV and organ transplantation patients manifestation of clinical signs can be Life threatening (5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Despite of the worldwide distribution of this parasite, there is only one species (T. gondii) that causes toxoplasmosis (1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Prevalence of this parasite had been shown to be up to 50% in Iran, which is verified from different parts of the country (6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Toxoplasma oocysts are resistant to environmental conditions and may remain infective for more than one year in different types of soils (4, 7). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Soil contamination with oocysts is related to distribution of infected cat feces in environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Areas such as gardens, park and around rubbish dump are main places that cats may excrete feces in soil (8). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>According to the different methods of characterization such as restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP), isoenzyme electrophoresis and random amplified polymorphism, T. gondii strains classified into three clonal lineages (genotypes I, II and III) and some atypical genotypes (9–12). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>It was revealed that three lineages of this parasite have less than 1% difference in genomic level (13). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Several genetic markers are available to identify genotypes of T. gondii isolates, that the polymorphic surface antigen two (SAG2) is one of the locuses used for differentiation of these three clonal lineages (12, 14). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Genetic analysis of T. gondii infection in soil and other environmental resources is of importance to comprehend the epidemiology, patterns of transmission and clonal diversity of the parasite in different parts of the world. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>One of the studies conducted to environmental contamination with this parasite is the survey of Lass et al. in Poland, that he detected T. gondii oocysts in soil samples and confirmed it by molecular methods (15). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The present study was performed to identify T. gondii oocysts in soil samples from Tehran, Iran by molecular method and genotyping of positive samples in SAG2 locus by endonuclease enzymes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S0002"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S20003"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Collection of soil samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>One hundred and fifty soil samples were collected from September 2008 to March 2009 from different parts of Tehran city, such as parks, public places, children's play ground and areas around rubbish dumps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Each sample was weighted about 300 gram which was collected from 3 cm of ground depth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Soil samples were dried at laboratory temperature for 48 hours, sieved and concentrated with modified sodium nitrate flotation as described previously (16). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S20004"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Toxoplasma gondii control standard strains </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Three strains were obtained from School of Public Health, Tehran University of Medical Sciences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Tachyzoites of T. gondii RH strain (type I), tissue cysts of Tehran strain (type II) that was previously isolated from human lymphadenitis (17), and tachyzoites of a virulent strain of T. gondii with unknown genotype which is maintain by serial intrapretoneal passages in Department of Parasitology in Tehran University of Medical Science. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The strain is introduced as U strain in here. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The tachyzoites were collected from peritoneal cavity of BALB/c mice that were infected three days earlier. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Tissue cysts of Tehran strain (type II) was obtained from brain of BALB/c mice that were injected with bradyzoites of the strain two months earlier. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S20005"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>DNA Extraction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>DNA extraction was performed with the commercial genomic mini kit (A &amp; A Biotechnology, Gdynia, Poland) according to manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>From each samples 100 µl of DNA was eluted and stored at -20°C until use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S20006"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Detection of Toxoplasma gondii oocyst by PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The target of PCR was the 199 bp fragment of the highly conserved 35 fold repetitive B1 gene (AF179871). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>For PCR reaction, a pair of primer Toxo1 (5’ GGA ACT GCA TCC GTT CAT GAG 3’) and Toxo2 (5’ TCT TTA AAG CGT TCG TGG TC 3’) were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The PCR was performed according to Schwab et al. (18). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>To confirm the results, all positive samples were also examined by another pair of primer Toxo-F (5’ AGG CGA GGG TGA GGA TGA 3’) and Toxo-R (5’ TCG TCT CGT CTG GAT CGC AT 3’). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>These primers are specific for a 200 to 300 fold repetitive fragment of 134 bp (AF 146527) (19, 20). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>In this study Taq DNA PreMix (Accupower™, BioNeer, South Korea) was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>With the final reaction volume of 25 µl, the amplification was performed by 10 min at 95°C initial step, followed by 30 cycles: denaturation for 5 s at 95° C, annealing for 10 s at 60° and extension for15 s at 72°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>PCR products were analyzed by electrophoresis on 2% agarose gel and stained with ethidium bromide. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S20007"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Genotyping and RFLP </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>For nested-PCR reaction, outer and inner primers for SAG2 locus (3’ and 5’ end) that were previously designed by Howe et al. (12), were used (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T0001" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Names and sequences of the polymerase chain reaction primer pairs used for Nested-PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Length of selected fragments was 241-bp and 221-bp in 5’ end and 3’ end, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The protocol for temperature cycling was used as described by Aspinal et al. (21). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>In order to distinguish T. gondii genotypes, restriction enzymes were used as described previously (12, 22, 23). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Two restriction enzymes were selected for RFLP, Sau3aI and HhaI (Fermentas, Germany). Sau3aI enzyme was used for digestion of 5’ end of amplification products that distinguished allele 3 (genotype III) from alleles I and II (genotypes I &amp; II). HhaI enzyme was used for digestion of 3’ end of amplification products that distinguished allele II from types I and III (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>For RFLP procedure, 10 µl of nested-PCR products of the 5’ and 3’ ends were digested using 3U of Sau3aI and HhaI restriction enzymes in separate reactions with a total volume of 30 µl at 37° C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Then the fragments were analyzed by 3% agarose gel electrophoresis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F0001" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Schematic image for function of restriction enzymes on SAG2 locus (Howe et al. (24) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPA-8-227-g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="S20008"><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>After nested-PCR, all the positive samples were sequenced by BioNeer Lab (South Korea). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="S0009"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S20010"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Identification of T. gondii oocysts in soil samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>From 150 soil samples that examined by two pairs of primer in two steps of PCR, 13 samples (8.7%) were positive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>In the first step, a 194-bp fragment of B1 gene was amplified (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>In the second step, all positive samples were examined by other pairs of primers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The length of fragment in this step was 134-bp from 200 to 300 fold-repetitive elements (AF146527) (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>All soil samples were examined twice in each PCR reaction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F0002" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>B1 gene amplification products (194 bp) of T. gondii on agarose 2%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Lane M, molecular weight marker 50 bp (Fermentas); Lane 1, Negetive control; Lane 4, positive control (RH strain); Lane 2-3 positive soil samples </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPA-8-227-g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F0003" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Amplification of 134-bp fragment T. gondii from 200 to 300 folds repetitive 529 bp DNA elements on agarose 2%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Lane M, molecular weight marker 50 bp; Lane 1, positive control (RH strain); Lane 2, Negetive control; Lane 3-5, positive soil samples </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPA-8-227-g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="S20011"><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Genotyping of positive samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>All of the 13 positive soil samples were examined by nested-PCR at 5’ and 3’ end of SAG2 locus by four pairs of specific primers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>These samples showed a 241-bp amplified band in 5’ end of SAG2 locus and a 221-bp amplified band in 3’ end, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>After nested-PCR the amplified fragments were used for RFLP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Genotyping of 13 positive soil samples showed that 9 were type III (69%), 3 were mixed of type I and III (23%) and 1 of the samples was type I (8%) (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>4, 5, 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The pattern of digestion for RH strain and Tehran strain were corresponded to genotypes I and II, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>In addition, genotype of U strain was identified type I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>All the steps, including nested-PCR and RFLP were performed twice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F0004" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Nested-PCR amplification of SAG2 locus at 3’ end. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Lane M, molecular weight marker (50 bp); Lane 1-3, positive controls (RH, unknown and Tehran strains, respectively); Lanes 4-7, soil samples </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPA-8-227-g004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F0005" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Nested-PCR amplification of SAG2 locus at 5’ end. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Lane M, molecular weight marker (50 bp); Lane 1-2, positive controls (RH and Tehran strains, respectively); Lane 3, unknown strain (genotype I); Lanes 4-7, soil samples (genotype III) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPA-8-227-g005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F0006" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Nested-PCR amplification of SAG2 locus at 5’ end. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Lane M, molecular weight marker (50 bp); Lane 1-2, positive controls (RH and Tehran strains, respectively); Lane 3, soil sample (genotype I); Lane 4-6, soil samples (mix genotype of I and III) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPA-8-227-g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="S20012"><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Results of sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The products of the first step of nested-PCR were selected for sequencing and sent to BioNeer Company (South Korea). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Sequences were aligned using DNASIS MAX software (Version 3.00; Hitachi, Yokohama, Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The nucleotide sequences alignment of samples that had shown type III, revealed the 99-100% homology with other reported sequences in GenBank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The nucleotide sequences data from this paper were submitted in the DDBJ/EMBL/Gene Bank nucleotide sequence databases at accession numbers of AB667972-AB667975. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S0013"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>There is little information about the presence of T. gondii oocyst in the soil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>In the epidemiological point of view, soil is a large and important source of T. gondii infection (4, 24, 25). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>It is obvious that the abundance of stray cats have a main role in environmental contamination with T. gondii oocysts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The number of oocysts shed by naturally infected domestic cats is largely unknown and both young (&lt; 6 mo) and older (&gt;6 mo) cats have been found shedding oocysts in nature (2). Toxoplasma oocysts are resistance to environmental factors, and remain in soil up to one year (4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, detection of low amounts of oocysts in soil samples is difficult. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>According to the report of Lelu et al., factors such as dry or humidity of soil had no significant effect on oocyst recovery (26). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, Toxopalsma oocyst has a resistant wall consisted of several layers, which causes difficult DNA extraction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Toxoplasma gondii strains classified into three genotypes including I, II, III and some atypical genotypes (9–12). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>It is obvious that the prevalence of three genotypes is variable in different parts of the world. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>For example in the study of Howe and Sibley, type III was more common in animals than in human toxoplasmosis (27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Dubey et al. showed the predominance of type I in free- ranging chickens from Brazil (28). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>In another study, the predominant genotype was type III in free- ranging chickens and ducks from Egypt (29). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Genotype I predomination was shown in the study of soil samples from three cities in Poland (15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>It seems that ecological and geographical conditions could lead to the different prevalence of these types in different regions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The present study was performed to investigate T. gondii genotypes in soil samples from Tehran, Iran for the first time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>From 13 positive samples, 9 were type III (69%), 3 were mixed of type I and III (23%) and 1 of the samples was type I (8%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Zia-Ali et al. found the type III as dominant genotype in bird hosts in Iran (30); also he showed the distribution of 70% of type III and 30% of type II in animals (31). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Behzadi et al. had reported 85.7% (18/22) of human and mice isolates infected with type II (32). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Although the resources of our sampling are different from Zia-Ali et al., the results of these two studies are correlated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="S0014"><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Toxoplasma gondii detection and genotyping with molecular methods such as multilocus PCR-RFLP is possible directly in soil samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Type III is predominant in Tehran soil samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>More studies regarding to determination of the clonal patterns of T. gondii isolates in soil samples by several markers are recommended. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We would like to show our appreciation to the cooperation of all staff of Parasitology and Mycology Department, School of Medicine, Tehran University of Medical Sciences. This research is a part of Ph.D Dissertation supported by Tehran University of Medical Sciences (Grant No: P/760). The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest.</p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>1DubeyJPThe history of Toxoplasma gondii-the first 100 yearsJ Eukaryot Microbiol.20085564677519120791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>2DubeyJPToxoplasmosis of animals and humans20102nd edBoca RatonCRC Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>3Robert-GangneuxFDardéMLEpidemiology of and diagnostic strategies for toxoplasmosisClin Microbiol Rev20122522649622491772 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>4DumetreADardeMLHow to detect Toxoplasma gondii oocysts in environmental samples?FEMS Microbiol Rev.20032756516114638417 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>5WeissLMDubeyJPToxoplasmosis: A history of clinical observationsInt J Parasitol.200939889590119217908 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>6AsmarMAmirkhaniAPiazakNHovanesianAKooloobandiAEtessamiRToxoplasmosis in Iran, results of a seroepidemiological investigationBull Soc Path Ex.1997901921 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>7FrenkelJKDubeyJPEffects of freezing on the viability of Toxoplasma oocystsJ Parasitol.197359358784711675 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>8AfonsoELemoineMPoulleMLRavatMCRomandSThulliezPVillenaIAubertDRabilloudMRicheBGilot-FromontElSpatial distribution of soil contamination by Toxoplasma gondii in relation to cat defecation behaviour in an urban areaInt J Parasitol.2008388-910172318325523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>9CristinaNDardeMLBoudinCTavernierGPestre-AlexandreMAmbroise-ThomasPA DNA fingerprinting method for individual characterization of Toxoplasma gondii strains: combination with isoenzymatic characters for determination of linkage groupsParasitol Res.19958113277724511 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>10DardeMLBouteilleBPestre-AlexandreMIsoenzyme analysis of 35 Toxoplasma gondii isolates and the biological and epidemiological implicationsJ Parasitol.1992785786941403418 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>11GuoZGJohnsonAMGenetic characterization of Toxoplasma gondii strains by random amplified polymorphic DNA polymerase chain reactionParasitology.1995111Pt2127327675527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>12HoweDKHonoreSDerouinFSibleyLDDetermination of genotypes of Toxoplasma gondii strains isolated from patients with toxoplasmosisJ Clin Microbiol.1997356141149163454 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>13SibleyLDBoothroydJCVirulent strains of Toxoplasma gondii comprise a single clonal lineageNature.199235963908251355855 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>14FazaeliAEbrahimzadehAA new perspective on and re-assessment of SAG2 locus as the tool for genetic analysis of Toxoplasma gondii isolatesParasitol Res.200710119910417297630 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>15LassAPietkiewiczHModzelewskaEDumetreASzostakowskaBMyjakPDetection of Toxoplasma gondii oocysts in environmental soil samples using molecular methodsEur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis.200928659960519104853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>16Mizgajska-WiktorHRecommended method for recovery of Toxocara and other geohelminth eggs from soilWiad Parazytol.200551121216841685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>17GhorbaniMSamiiAHToxoplasmic lymphadenitis in IranJ Trop Med Hyg.1973767158604580065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>18SchwabKJMcDevittJJDevelopment of PCR enzyme immunoassay oligoprobe detection method for Toxoplasma gondii oocyst, incorporating PCR controlsAppl Environ Microbiol.20036958192514532030 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>19CassaingSBessieresMHBerryABerrebiAFabreRMagnavalJFComparison between two amplification sets for molecular diagnosis of toxoplasmosis by real-time PCRJ Clin Microbiol.2006443720416517845 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>20HomanWLVercammenMDe BraekeleerJVerschuerenHIdentification of a 200- to 300-fold repetitive 529 bp DNA fragment in Toxoplasma gondii, and its use for diagnostic and quantitative PCRInt J Parasitol.2000301697510675747 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>21AspinallTVGuyECRobertsKEJoynsonDHHydeJESimsPFMolecular evidence for multiple Toxoplasma gondii infections in individual patients in England and Wales: public health implicationsInt J Parasitol.20033319710312547351 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>22AspinallTVMarleeDHydeJESimsPFPrevalence of Toxoplasma gondii in commercial meat products as monitored by polymerase chain reaction--food for thought?Int J Parasitol.20023291193912117502 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>23SuCZhangXDubeyJPGenotyping of Toxoplasma gondii by multilocus PCR-RFLP markers: a high resolution and simple method for identification of parasitesInt J Parasitol.2006367841816643922 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>24Alvarado-EsquivelCEstrada-MartinezSPizarro-VillalobosHArce-QuinonesMLiesenfeldODubeyJPSeroepidemiology of Toxoplasma gondii infection in general population in a northern Mexican cityJ Parasitol.201097140321348604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>25DabritzHAConradPACats and Toxoplasma: implications for public healthZoonoses Public Health.2010571345219744306 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>26LeluMGilot-FromontEAubertDRichaumeAAfonsoEDupuisEDevelopment of a sensitive method for Toxoplasma gondii oocyst extraction in soilVet Parasitol.20111831-2596721764217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>27HoweDKSibleyLD Toxoplasma gondii comprises three clonal lineages: correlation of parasite genotype with human diseaseJ Infect Dis.19951721561667594717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>28DubeyJPGrahamDHBlackstonCRLehmannTGennariSMRagozoAMABiological and genetic characterisation of Toxoplasma gondii isolated from chicken (Gallus domesticus) from Sao Paulo BrazilInt J Parasitol.2002329910511796127 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>29DubeyJPGrahamDHDahlEHilaliMEl-GhayshASreekumarCIsolation and molecular characterization of Toxoplasma gondii from chickens and ducks from EgyptVet Parasitol.2003114899512781471 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>30Zia-AliNKeshavarz-ValianHRezaianMKhoramizadeMRKazemiBFazaeliADardeMMolecular characterization of Toxoplasma gondii from bird hostsIranian J Publ Health.20053432730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>31Zia-AliNFazaeliAKhoramizadehMAjzenbergDDardeMKeshavarz-ValianHIsolation and molecular characterization of Toxoplasma gondii strains from different hosts in IranParasitol Res.20071011111517333278 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>32BehzadiRRoohvandFRazaviMRHovanessianAAssmarMGenotyping of Toxoplasma gondii strains isolated from patients and mice by PCR-RFLP assayIranian J Biotechnol.200312826 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
