
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><?epub November-3-2012?><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3592412</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23125367</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks1043</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gks1043</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Nucleic Acid Enzymes</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Natural zinc ribbon HNH endonucleases and engineered zinc finger nicking endonuclease </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Shuang-yong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gks1043-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="gks1043-COR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>Yogesh K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gks1043-AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="gks1043-AFF1"><sup>1</sup>New England Biolabs, Inc., Research Department, 240 County Road, Ipswich, MA 01938 and <sup>2</sup>Department of Structural and Chemical Biology, Mount Sinai School of Medicine, Box 1677, 1425 Madison Avenue, New York, NY 10029, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="gks1043-COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: <phone>+1 978 380 7287</phone>; Fax: <fax>+1 978 921 1350</fax>; Email: <email>xus@neb.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>2</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>378</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>4</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Many bacteriophage and prophage genomes encode an HNH endonuclease (HNHE) next to their cohesive end site and terminase genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The HNH catalytic domain contains the conserved catalytic residues His-Asn-His and a zinc-binding site [CxxC]2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>An additional zinc ribbon (ZR) domain with one to two zinc-binding sites ([CxxxxC], [CxxxxH], [CxxxC], [HxxxH], [CxxC] or [CxxH]) is frequently found at the N-terminus or C-terminus of the HNHE or a ZR domain protein (ZRP) located adjacent to the HNHE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>We expressed and purified 10 such HNHEs and characterized their cleavage sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>These HNHEs are site-specific and strand-specific nicking endonucleases (NEase or nickase) with 3- to 7-bp specificities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>A minimal HNH nicking domain of 76 amino acid residues was identified from Bacillus phage γ HNHE and subsequently fused to a zinc finger protein to generate a chimeric NEase with a new specificity (12–13 bp). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The identification of a large pool of previously unknown natural NEases and engineered NEases provides more ‘tools’ for DNA manipulation and molecular diagnostics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The small modular HNH nicking domain can be used to generate rare NEases applicable to targeted genome editing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>In addition, the engineered ZF nickase is useful for evaluation of off-target sites in vitro before performing cell-based gene modification. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>7 January 2013</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>A large number of restriction endonucleases (REases) have been found in bacteria and viruses and are widely used in recombinant DNA technology (1–5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In contrast, relatively few natural nicking endonucleases (NEases or nickase), which introduce single-strand breaks in double-stranded DNA (dsDNA), have been discovered (3,6–8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>NEases were engineered from type IIS REases by mutating one of the two catalytic sites or disrupting the dimerization domain (9–11), by alteration of binding specificity of a type IIP REase (12) or by combining a DNA binding-deficient and catalytic-proficient FokI subunit with a DNA binding-proficient and catalytically inert FokI subunit (13). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Naturally occurring nicking enzymes may be found as part of heterodimeric REases or as stand-alone enzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>One important group of natural NEases are replication initiation proteins that specifically nick the viral genome or conjugative plasmid during phage DNA replication or conjugative plasmid transfer such as gpII of f1 phage (14) and Salmonella typhimurium relaxase encoded by plasmid pCU1 (15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Another group of natural NEases are homing nicking endonucleases that play a role in gene conversion (insertion of intron and intron-encoded homing endonuclease into an intron-less allele) [reviewed in (16–18)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Artificial zinc finger nuclease (ZFN)-based nicking enzymes (ZF nickases) have been constructed by fusion of three to four ZF arrays with FokI cleavage domains, one catalytic proficient (FokIR+) and the other catalytic deficient (FokIR−). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Transient heterodimer formation by R+/R− cleavage domains upon binding to the target sites with a 5- to 6-bp spacer leads to DNA nicking which stimulates targeted gene disruption or gene addition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Such nick-induced gene targeting displays a low frequency of insertion or deletion, in sharp contrast to the non-homologous end-joining process that follows a dsDNA break and repair response (19–21). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Thus, it is desirable to use ZF nickases to introduce nicks to initiate a DNA repair response that results in homology-directed recombination (HDR) for genome editing and targeted gene correction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>In addition to the ZF nickases used in genome editing, a nicking variant was engineered from I-AniI homing endonuclease (HEase) and its utility was demonstrated in nick-induced gene correction via HDR in human cells (22). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, it was shown that an I-AniI nicking variant induces homologous recombination with both plasmid and adeno-associated virus (AAV) vector templates and the nicking variant alleviates the in vivo toxicity problem conferred by the dsDNA cleaving enzyme (23). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>A strand-specific nicking variant has also been isolated from I-SceI HEase (24). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The inherent disadvantage of using HEases in genome editing is that most of the HEases studied so far tolerate degenerate sequences, and off-target sites with a few base pair mismatches are also cleaved (25,26). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>ZF recombinases (ZFRs) have also been constructed by fusion of ZF arrays with Tyr or Ser recombinase for ZFR-mediated integration of the donor plasmid in mammalian genomes and site-specific recombination in a bacterial genome (27,28). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The HNH superfamily nucleases include HEases, REases, structure-specific endonucleases, non-specific nucleases, CRISPR-associated protein Cas9 (CRISPR, clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeat) and DNA repair enzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The invariant His residue in the conserved motif HNH (sometimes found as HNK or HNN) serves as the general base that activates a water molecule for a nucleophilic attack on the sugar phosphate backbone of nucleic acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>We recently investigated the restriction–modification (R–M) systems in the sequenced genome Bacillus cereus ATCC 10978 (GenBank: AE017194) and found a prophage-encoded multi-specificity C5 methyltransferase (MTase) and a ParB-MTase fusion protein with non-specific DNA nicking activity (29). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In the vicinity of the prophage-encoded C5 MTase, three genes were predicted to encode DNA-cleaving enzymes (genes in the order of Vrr_Nuclease, DNA Integrase, HNH endonuclease (HNHE), Terminase S subunit, ParB-MTase, C5 MTase). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Here, we report the DNA nicking activity of the Bacillus cereus HNHE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>In addition, we identified and characterized nine HNHE homologs and their nicking sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>We defined a minimal nicking domain of 76 amino acids (aa) from phage γ HNHE and fused it to the zinc finger protein (ZFP) (Zif268) to generate a rare nicking enzyme with 12- to 13-bp specificity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we examined a number of off-target sites in λ DNA for the engineered NEase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The significance and possible biological function of this large family of strand-specific DNA NEases is discussed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Cloning and enzyme purification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Restriction and modification enzymes, cloning/expression vectors and chitin beads were provided by NEB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Synthetic genes encoding HNHEs with optimized Escherichia coli expression codons were purchased from IDT and subcloned into pTYB1 (NdeI–XhoI insert). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>To construct Zif268 and N.φGamma fusion, a DNA fragment encoding the minimal N.φGamma catalytic domain (F5, 76 aa) flanked by NheI and XhoI sites was inserted into pTYB1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The Zif268-encoding PCR fragment flanked by NdeI and NheI sites was inserted into the pTYB1-N.φGamma (F5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>In this way, the reverse primer with a variable length of linker can be inserted between the ZF domain and the N.φGamma catalytic domain F5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>IPTG induction of the intein-chitin-binding protein-HNHE fusions was carried out at 16°C overnight by addition of 0.3 mM IPTG to late-log-phase cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Standard chitin column protein purification procedure was followed as recommended by the supplier. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>HNHEs were further purified from HiTrap Heparin HP columns (5 ml) on an AKTA FPLC purification system (GE Healthcare) and stored at −20°C in a storage buffer (50 mM KCl, 10 mM Tris–HCl, 10 mM DTT, 50% glycerol). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Structural modeling of Zif268::N.φGamma fusion endonuclease </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The model of N.φGamma endonuclease domain was obtained using program I-TASSER (30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The duplex DNA was built and modeled together with Zif268 (pdb id; 1aay) and N.φGamma endonuclease domains using program Coot (31). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Identification of HNHE N.BceSVIII from B. cereus and its homologs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The small predicted HNHE (121 aa) found in B. cereus ATCC 10987 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S1A</ext-link>) was expressed in E. coli using the IMPACT protein expression system (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S1B</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>After purification, the protein displayed low DNA nicking activity in Mg++ buffer and robust activity in Mn++ buffer (data not shown) and was subsequently named N.BceSVIII. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>It is partially active in reaction buffers with Co++ and is completely inhibited by addition of ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA) (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Run-off DNA sequencing of the cleavage products indicates that N.BceSVIII cuts frequently with the recognition sequence of 5′ S↓RT 3′ (S = C/G, R = A/G) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S1C</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">D</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>We will use a downward pointing arrow to indicate nicking of the strand shown and an upward pointing arrow to indicate nicking of the complementary strand, following accepted nomenclature (32). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>A BlastP search of the GenBank NR database using the N.BceSVIII aa sequence as a query revealed over 200 related HNHEs, all similarly small (95 to ∼300 aa) and predominantly encoded by phage and prophage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>These HNHE homologs can be divided into four major groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Group 1 contains one to two zinc-binding sites with two to four zinc ribbons (ZRs) each with the motif [CxxxxC], [CxxxxH], [CxxxC], [HxxxH], [CxxH] or [CxxC] at the N-terminus, and the HNHE catalytic domain with one zinc-binding site with the motif [CxxC]2 located at the C-terminus (each zinc ion is presumably coordinated by a tetrahedral geometry and thus requires two ZRs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Group 2 reverses the domain organization of the Group 1 enzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Group 3 lacks the N-terminal zinc-binding region of Group 1 and contains only one zinc-binding site in the HNHE catalytic domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>A non-specific HNHE (gp74) with the Group 3 domain architecture has been characterized recently from a λ-related phage HK97 (33). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Group 4 HNHEs are similar to Groups 1 and 2, but located side-by-side with another ZR domain protein (ZRP) either immediate upstream or downstream. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Some Group 4 enzymes are fused to the adjacent ZRP (see, e.g. Bth193 HNHE below, which has four putative zinc-binding sites). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Some putative HNHEs carry additional functional domains such as a 5mC-recognition domain (MspJI family, McrA family) (34) (S.-Y. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Xu, S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Chan and Y. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Zheng, unpublished results), an NTPase domain (AAA superfamily, Walker motif A), a metalloprotease (MPN) domain or a domain of unknown function such as DUF222 (pfam02720). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>This report focuses on HNHEs in Groups 1, 2 and 4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Characterization of Bacillus anthracis phage γ HNH nickase </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>One HNHE homolog (accession YP_338236, 127 aa) from Group 1 was found in the genome of B. anthracis phage γ (accession NC_007458) (35), and which we will refer to as phage γ HNHE (N.ϕGamma or N.phiGamma). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Its secondary structure as predicted by the Phyre server is shown in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S2A</ext-link> (36). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>A synthetic gene was expressed in E. coli and the gene product purified by chromatography through two columns (Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>N.ϕGamma is active in the presence of Mg++, Mn++ or Co++, partially active in the presence of Ca++, Ni++ or Zn++ and inactive in the presence of EDTA (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Run-off sequencing of the cleavage products indicates that N.ϕGamma nicks predominantly at CG↓GT sites in the presence of Mg++ (Figure 1C and D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>A small amount of linear DNA was also detected in Mg++ buffer, most likely due to the nicking of two closely positioned sites on opposite strands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The sequence specificity is reduced to 2–3 bp recognition in Mn++ buffer as determined by run-off sequencing of the cleavage products (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Using an independent method, we digested bacteriophage λ DNA in the presence of Mn++ and cloned digestion products after performing a blunting reaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Sequencing of the cloned fragments also revealed a relaxed specificity with nicking occurring at sites with one to two mismatches relative to the cognate site (data not shown). Figure 1.Characterization of phage γ HNHE (N.φGamma). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>(A) SDS–PAGE analysis of the partially purified N.φGamma (indicated by an arrow, predicted molecular mass of 15.5 kDa). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>(B) DNA cleavage assay on pBR322 in various buffers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>NEB buffers B1-B4 all contain 10 mM MgCl2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Buffer without divalent cations (10 mM Tris–HCl, pH 7.5, 50 mM NaCl, 1 mM DTT) was supplemented with metal ions (5 mM) as indicated above each lane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>(C) N.φGamma nicking consensus sequence CG↓GT (AC↑CG) was compiled by WebLogo (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://weblogo.berkeley.edu/logo.cgi">http://weblogo.berkeley.edu/logo.cgi</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>(D) Run-off sequencing of two nicked sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The intervening sequences have been shortened to show the two sites nicked at the opposite strands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Double peaks (A/C, A/G, A/T) indicate a nick on the template strand as the extrinsic A was added by Taq DNA polymerase by the template-independent terminal nucleotide transferase activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Undigested pBR322 was used as a control in sequencing (top two chromatograms). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Heat treatment of ∼5 U of N.ϕGamma at 80°C for 20 min completely abolished its activity, whereas treatment at lower temperatures (55–75°C) resulted in only partial loss of nicking activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, treatment at 80°C for only 10 min was not sufficient for complete inactivation (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Mapping the minimally functional nicking domain in N.φGamma </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Catalytic domains of several type IIS REases including FokI, BmrI and BpuJI when cloned and purified in absence of the DNA binding domains have been shown to display non-specific nuclease activity (37–39). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>To test whether the N.φGamma catalytic domain (the HNH domain) displays a similar non-specific activity in absence of the ZR domain, we deleted 66 aa (Δ66 aa) residues from the N-terminus of the wild-type (wt) enzyme, resulting in a mutant containing only the 61 C-terminal aa residues (F6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Additional deletion mutants were also constructed, removing 22 aa (F3), 43 aa (F4) and 51 aa (F5) from the N-terminus, respectively (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S2A</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The deletion variants were purified and their nicking activity was assayed in Mg++ or Mn++ buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Truncated mutants F3 and F4 displayed slightly lower activity in Mn++ buffers compared with the full-length enzyme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Mutant F5 showed nicking activity in Mn++ buffer and low activity in Mg++ buffer (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S2B</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">C</ext-link>), and mutant F6 has minimal nicking activity in Mg++ or Mn++ buffers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The nicking specificities of F4 and F5 are nearly identical: both deletion variants nick the cognate sites (CG↓GT) or variations thereof with one base mismatch (F5 ‘star’ sites CG↓GG, CG↓GC, CA↓GT or CG↓AT; data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>It was concluded that the 61-aa C-terminal HNHE domain is not sufficient to constitute an active endonuclease activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The smaller deletion variant F5 (76 aa in length) possesses the necessary elements for a sequence-specific NEase despite its lower activity and relaxed specificity (also see N.φGamma-F5 and Zif268 fusion below). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Enzyme concentration dependence in nicking reactions, DNA nicking kinetics in a time course by N.φGamma and flanking sequence effect on nicking efficiency </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Partially purified N.φGamma and a deletion variant F3 were used to nick pBR322 DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>At low enzyme concentration, supercoiled DNA was converted to nicked circular form. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>At high enzyme concentration (2–4×), however, a small fraction of DNA was converted to linear form, probably generated from nicks introduced on the opposite strands at adjacent sites (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S2D</ext-link>). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S2E</ext-link> shows a time course in N.φGamma-mediated nicking reactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The substrate DNA (pBR322) was incubated with diluted N.φGamma from 2 min to 2 h in a limited digestion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Supercoiled DNA was partially converted to nicked circular DNA in the time period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>No linear DNA was detected due to the limited digestion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>In order to examine the nicking efficiency of various ACCG sites in pBR322, the DNA substrate was incubated with purified N.φGamma at 37°C for 2 h and then subjected to run-off sequencing. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S2F</ext-link> shows a few examples of the nicked AC↑CG sites followed by A, G, C or T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Overall, the DNA sites ACCGR appeared to be nicked more efficiently than ACCGY (ACCGR&gt;ACCGC&gt;ACCGT) by comparing the ‘A’ peak in double peaks at the run-off sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>A quantitative nicking assay to evaluate the nicking efficiency of all possible flanking sequences (N′3N′2N′1-ACCG-N1N2N3) remains to be developed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Nicking short DNA duplex oligos by N.φGamma </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>DNA duplex oligos with one ACCGG site (28-mer) or two ACCGG sites (32-mer) were digested by N.φGamma at 37°C for 1 h in either Mg++ or Mn++ buffer and the cleavage products were resolved in a denaturing gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Both substrates were nicked and new products were detected (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>In support of this, 3′ FAM-labeled duplex oligos with one ACCGN site (N = A, G, C or T) were also nicked by N.φGamma. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S2G</ext-link> shows the nicking results of ACCGA, ACCGG, ACCGC and ACCGT duplex oligos at four enzyme concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Consistent with the nicking site efficiency in pBR322, the 28-bp short oligos with ACCGR sites were nicked more readily than ACCGY sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The nicking reactions nearly reached completion at high enzyme concentration for ACCGR oligos, whereas partial nicking was achieved using the ACCGY substrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Although the exact size of the nicked products remains to be determined by running a sequencing gel at the single nucleotide resolution, it suffices to say that short DNA duplex oligos can serve as the substrates for nicking reactions by N.φGamma. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Homologs of phage gamma HNHE (N.φGamma) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>A BlastP search in GenBank revealed that Bacillus phage Cherry and WBeta genomes encode a putative HNHE with identical aa sequence to N.φGamma (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>N.φGamma also shares 99% aa sequence identity to a putative HNHE (protein ID: EJR41403, 129 aa, probably encoded by a prophage belonging to HK97 family phage) in the genome of B. cereus VD045 strain, and 91% aa sequence identity to a putative HNHE (protein ID: YP_001375827, 127 aa, probably encoded by a prophage similar to P27 family phage, and located next to open reading frames (ORFs) coding for terminase small and large subunits) in the genome of Bacillus cytotoxicus NVH 391-98 strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The next group of putative HNHEs from Geobacillus phage or prophage shares 51–56% aa sequence identity to that of N.φGamma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Because of the high aa sequence identity (similarity) among these HNHEs, it is highly likely that they are nicking enzymes with nicking site CG↓GT (AC↑CG) or minor variations of such a sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this prediction, the HNHE encoded by Geobacillus virus E2 (N.φE2), which shares 51% aa sequence identity to N.φGamma, displays the nicking specificity of CG↓GT (data not shown) (Table 1). Table 1.Summary of DNA nicking sites by phage- or prophage-encoded HNHE and engineered chimeric nicking enzymeND, not determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>DNA single letter code, W: A/T; S: G/C; R, A/G; Y: C/T; B: C/G/T (not A); D, A/G/T (not C); V, A/C/G (not T); H, A/C/T (not G).?, need more experimental evidence.Underlined target sites with 4-bp variations (ACCG, ACCR, ACCV, ACCS, RTCG, AGCA, ACYG) are shared by these HNHEs.Proposed nomenclature: HNH nicking enzymes encoded by phage: N.ϕ+phage name; NEases encoded by prophage or host genome (5,32). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Lactobacillus phage Sal2 HNH nicking endonuclease </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>An HNHE homolog was found in the Lactobacillus phage Sal2 with additional aa blocks located upstream and downstream of the HNH catalytic domain (protein ID: YP_535176), which may confer additional base recognition (40). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S3A</ext-link> shows that the two additional blocks of aa sequences (5-aa and 11-aa residues) at the N-terminus and one extra block of 32-aa residues located at the C-terminal end compared with phage N.φGamma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Phage Sal2 HNHE (N.ϕSal2 or N.phiSal2) was purified and used to digest pBR322. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>N.ϕSal2 shows robust nicking activity in Mn++ buffer, which efficiently nicks DNA sites TG↓CTC (GAG↑CA) and related sites with 1- to 2-bp mismatches from the core sequence such as CG↓CTC or TG↓TTC (Figure 2A, and data not shown). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S3B</ext-link> compiled the nicking sites (GARCA or its variants) by WebLogo using pBR322 digested in Mn++ buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>N.ϕSal2 partially nicks pBR322 in the presence of Mg++ (data not shown). Figure 2B shows the five nicking sites, which spans 14-bp DNA with a core recognition site of GAGCADNW (SSN4GAGCADNW) (S, C/G; D, A/G/T, not C; W, A/T). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The sixth base of the core is intolerant of a C because no GAGCAC-related sites were nicked (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>In summary, N.ϕSal2 shows optimal nicking activity in Mn++ buffer, nicking at TG↓CTC (GAG↑CA) or variant sites with 1- to 2-bp mismatches. Figure 2.Characterization of phage Sal2 HNHE (N.ϕSal2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>(A) Run-off sequencing of two nicked sites TG↓CTC (GAG↑CA) in pBR322 which was digested by N.ϕSal2 in Mn++ buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>(B) Nicking sites in pBR322 (Mg++ buffer) compiled by WebLogo. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>HNHE Bth193 from of Bacillus thuringensis strain T13001 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>We identified another N.φGamma homolog encoded on a prophage in the genome of B. thuringensis strain T13001 (protein ID: ZP_04118662). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>This enzyme, named as N.BthT13001I (a.k.a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Bth193 HNHE), has an additional N-terminal region relative to N.ϕGamma containing four ZR motifs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S4A</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>N.BthT13001I was expressed in E. coli and partially purified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>It nicks DNA sequences GG↓GT or CG↓GT in Mn++ buffer as determined by run-off sequencing (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S4B</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">D</ext-link>, data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The nicking sites in pBR322 were compiled by WebLogo as SG↓GT (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S4B</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>In Mg++ buffer, however, N.BthT13001I recognizes and nicks DNA sites with a core sequence of CSG↓GT (AC↑CSG) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S4C</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Based on the high sequence similarity with N.φGamma, we tentatively concluded that the HNH catalytic domain recognizes the SGGT sequence, and the additional ZRs at the N-terminus might contribute to the extra base C recognition in CSGGT. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>We also tested whether the HNH catalytic domain is interchangeable between N.BthT13001I and N.φGamma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The N-terminus ZR of N.BthT13001I was fused with the 76-aa N.φGamma catalytic domain (F5) to form a chimeric protein (the arrow in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S4A</ext-link> indicates the fusion junction). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The nicking sites of the fusion NEase are nearly identical to that of N.BthT13001I, but with preference for CCG↓GT (AC↑CGG) sequence, further confirming the ‘C’ base recognition conferred by the extra ZRs (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>We concluded that the HNH catalytic domain is readily exchangeable between Bth193 and N.φGamma and the chimeric enzyme N-N.BthT13001I::C-N.φGamma (F5) prefers CCG↓GT sites for nicking. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>HNH nicking endonuclease gp54 from Lactobacillus phage Lrm1 and other HNHEs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>In the sequenced genome of Lactobacillus phage Lrm1 (phage genome accession number: EU246945) (41), the last gene (gp54, protein ID: ABY84355) was annotated as a terminase S subunit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>However, two other genes encoding terminase small and large subunits are located at the left arm of the phage genome (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S5A</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>This predicted protein (gp54, 264-aa long) contains a HNH catalytic domain near the N-terminus (H77-N93-H102) and a AAA-NTPase domain (also termed Walker A motif GxxxxGK[S/T]), but lacking the Walker B motif: h4[D/E] (h4 = four hydrophobic aa residues) at the C-terminus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In addition, the C-terminus contains a putative zinc-binding motif (2xZR [HxxxH], [RxxxH] or [HxxxD]; and seven other Lactobacillus phage encode close homologs carrying the 2xZR motif [HxxxH]2) (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Phage Lrm1 HNHE (N.ϕLrm1 or N.phiLrm1) was expressed in E. coli, partially purified by affinity chromatography through a chitin column, and used to digest pBR322 DNA; It displays DNA nicking activity in Mn++ buffer and low activity in Mg++ buffer (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S5B</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">C</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Addition of NTP (ATP, GTP, CTP or UTP) failed to stimulate N.ϕLrm1 nicking activity (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The partially nicked DNA was gel-purified and subjected to run-off sequencing. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S5D</ext-link> summarizes the nicking sites as HSSG↓GT (AC↑CSSD), which resembled the nicking sites of Bth193 CSG↓GT (AC↑CSG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>We do not know the function of the AAA-superfamily domain (Walker A motif) at the C-terminus of N.ϕLrm1 as neither NTP nor dNTP have any stimulatory effect on DNA nicking activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>This domain could serve as an accessory domain interacting with DNA or other proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>We have not studied the interaction of this HNHE with the phage Lrm1 terminase. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>We also partially purified the HNHEs from Bacillus phage phi105 (protein ID: ADF59184), Geobacillus virus E2 HNHE (GBVE2_gp070, protein ID: YP_001522898) (42), Clostridium phage phi3626, gp50 (protein ID: NP_612879), Staphylococcus aureus strain Y74T prophage, ORF Sap040a_009 (protein ID: ACZ58991) (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The nicking sites of these HNHEs are summarized in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Construction of Zif268 and N.φGamma (F5, 76 aa) fusion nicking endonuclease </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>A large number of natural ZFPs have been identified in the past 25 years consisting primarily of eukaryotic transcription factors (see ZF database) (43), and additional ZFPs with high DNA binding affinity have been engineered by genetic selection or phage display (44–47). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Thus, ZFPs provide a collection of DNA binding modules (arrays) ranging from 6 to 12 bp with two to four individual ZFs linked together. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>ZFNs have been engineered to cleave large recognition sequences 12–24 bp (48–52). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Individual ZFP forms a DNA recognition module with two antiparallel β-sheets and one α-helix (ββαZn), where the second β-sheet contacts the sugar phosphate backbone and the α-helix contacts the base pairs in the DNA major groove as first revealed by the structure of the Zif268–DNA complex (53). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>We next attempted the fusion of the minimal N.φGamma nicking domain (F5, 76 aa) to Zif268 (3 ZFs, 117 aa) (partial ZFP sequence of North American songbird Vireo cassinii, GenBank accession: protein ID: AAO84760, 210 aa) to generate the chimeric enzyme Zif268III::N.φGamma F5 (designated as ZifIII for short). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Two fusion proteins were constructed, R1 fusion with 13-aa linker and R2 fusion with 3-aa linker between the two functional domains (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The two fusion proteins were purified to near homogeneity by chromatography (Figure 3B) and used to digest pUC19 (Figure 3C) and pUC19-Zif3 (containing a Zif268 recognition sequence GCGGGGGCG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Run-off sequencing of the nicked products indicated no apparent nicking taking place within or near the GCGGGGGCG sequence (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>However, a clear nicking site was detected at AT↑CG-N6-GCGCGGGGA (underlined base pair matching N.φGamma and Zif268 recognition sequences with a 6-bp spacer) in pUC19 and pUC19-Zif3 (nicking the opposite strand CG↓AT, data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>This unintended nicking site (off-target site or ‘star’ site) prompted us to design a new DNA substrate with the sequence ATCG-N6-GCGTGGGCG. Figure 3D shows a time course of the nicking reactions of pUC derivatives carrying the cognate site and two ‘star’ sites. Figure 3E shows nicking of cognate site with enzyme dependence over fixed amount of DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>A sharp run-off signal was detected on the ZifIII R1-digested cognate site and nicking at the ‘star’ site of the pUC backbone was strongly suppressed although the chromatogram peak is low at the ‘star’ site (Figure 3F, third sequencing run). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>A small fraction of the DNA was nicked on the opposite strand 2 nt apart generating a 2-base 5′-overhang (Figure 3F, first sequencing run), suggesting the reason for the small amount of linear DNA detected in the agarose gel in Figure 3E and D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>For the pUC derivative with one ‘star’ site inserted at the multiple cloning sites and the original ‘star’ site in the backbone, both sites were partially nicked (Figure 3F, fourth sequencing run). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Nicking at ATCG, ACCG or ACTG sites were not detected (one undigested ATCG site is indicated by a blue line in Figure 3F, data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Nicking reactions performed in high salt buffer (B3) could minimize the promiscuous nicking activity as some smearing was detected in prolonged incubation in B1, B2 and B4 (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Double-stranded breaks could be minimized by shorter digestion (&lt;30 min) and in 150 mM NaCl (∼80% supercoiled DNA converted to nicked circular in 2 h in 150 mM NaCl with minimal dsDNA breaks, data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that a ZF nickase can be constructed from a ZFP (three fingers) and the N.φGamma minimal nicking domain to create a chimera capable of nicking a 12- to 13-bp target site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Addition of two or more ZFs may further increase the nicking specificity, which is a prerequisite for applications in genome editing. Figure 3.Characterization of Zif268::N.φGamma F5 chimeric nickase (ZifIII). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>(A) Amino acid sequence of the fusion HNHE (Zif268 sequence shown in blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The sequence was derived from partial ZFP of Vireo cassinii (GenBank: gb AAO84760). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Two fusion constructs were made, R1 with a 13-aa linker (7 aa: DKKAEKA from the native songbird Zif268) and R2 with 3-aa linker between the two functional domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>(B) SDS–PAGE analysis of purified ZifIII R1 and R2 HNHEs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Lanes 2–5, 6 and 7, purified R1 and R2 fusion proteins from chitin columns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Lanes 8–11, purified R1 fusion protein from a heparin column (HiTrap Heparin HP, 5 ml). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>(C) Nicked pUC19 DNA in a time course (lanes 2 and 6, 20 min to 2 h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Lanes 7 and 8, Nt.BspQI nicked and SphI-digested DNA, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>(D) Digestion of pUC-ATCG-N6-Zif3(GCGTGGGCG) and pUC-ATCG-N6-Zif3star (GCGCGGGGA) in a time course (20 min to 2 h) in Buffer 3 (100 mM NaCl). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Small amount of linear DNA (&lt;5% of total DNA) appeared after 20 min digestion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Note: there is a pre-existing ‘star’ site in pUC19 in addition to the cognate site or ‘star’ site inserted at the multiple cloning sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>(E) Digestion of pUC-ATCG-N6-Zif3(GCGTGGGCG) by varying concentration of ZifIII R1 in NEB Buffer 3 for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The Nt.BspQI-nicked DNA was used as a marker. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The slow migrating DNA in (E) and (F) is probably nicked dimer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>(F) Run-off sequencing of nicked DNA (B3, 1 h, 37°C) with forward and reverse primers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Red line, Zif268 cognate site; green line: Zif268 ‘star’ site; blue line: N.φGamma site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Arrows indicate the nicking sites where double peaks appeared. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>SC, supercoiled; L, linear; NC, nicked circular DNA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Off-target nicking sites by Zif268::N.φGamma F5 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>To investigate potential ‘star’ sites of ZifIII R1, λ DNA was nicked by the chimeric NEase and the digested DNA was subjected to run-off sequencing at the suspected ‘star’ sites (9- to 11-bp matches). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>One strong off-target nicking site was found with the sequence AC↑TG-N6-GCCGTGGAG (CA↓GT, 2-bp matches in each ZF binding site, λ coordinate 3981, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S6A</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Two ‘star’ sites with the sequence AC↑CC-N6-GCGCGGGTT (GG↓GT; 3-bp, 2-bp, 1-bp matches to ZF3, ZF2 and ZF1 sites, respectively; λ coordinate 4486) and ACTG-N6-GCGGGGGTA (CA↓GT; 3-bp, 3-bp, 1-bp matches in ZF3, ZF2 and ZF1 sites, respectively; λ coordinate 11111) were partially nicked by the ZifIII R1 NEase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S6B</ext-link>, data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>No apparent nicking was found in the suspected ‘star’ sites listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S6C</ext-link>, which contains 5- to 7-bp matches to the Zif268 binding site (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>These off-target sites indicate that 2-bp matches in each ZF are likely strong ‘star’ sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The 5- to 6-bp matches in ZF3 and ZF2 in conjunction with 1-bp match in ZF1 are probable ‘star’ sites. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>The minimal HNH catalytic domain with its own sequence specificity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The HNH motif is highly conserved among the HNHEs, although in some cases the second His residue can be substituted by a Lys or Asn residue (H-N-K/N). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The first conserved His residue acts as a general base to activate a water molecule for nucleophilic attack of the DNA phosphodiester bond, and the Asn orients the catalytic His residue and scissile phosphate in the correct position for DNA hydrolysis (54,55). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The second His (or Lys/Asn) stabilizes the leaving group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>HNH domains, which generally fold into a secondary structure described as ‘ββα−metal’, bind the DNA backbone in the minor groove, whereas additional residues mediate sequence-specific interactions with the DNA (56). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The zinc metal ion is coordinated by a tetrahedral coordinating geometry by the two ZRs [CxxC]2 or [CxxH, CxxC] (55,57,58). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Secondary structure prediction by the Phyre server (59) revealed that the N.φGamma catalytic domain (F6, 66 aa) contains a β−β−α−α structure, as predicted from known structures of a HNHE from Geobacter metallireducens GS-15 (a HNHE without the extra ZR domain, pdb accession: 2qgpB, Northeast Structural Genomics Consortium target GmR87) (A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Kuzin et al., unpublished results) and PacI (a HNH family REase) (57). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The active deletion variant F5 (76 aa) contains an extra α-helical structure that may be involved in increased DNA-binding affinity or dimerization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>It is somewhat unexpected that the deletion of the N-terminal 51-aa ZR domain does not totally abolish the specificity of N.φGamma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>The deletion only weakened the activity in Mg++ buffer and relaxed the sequence recognition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The 76-aa minimal nicking domain has been used in construction of fusion protein with ZFP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The ‘star’ sites of N.φGamma in Mn++ are usually one base different from the cognate site AC↑CG, e.g. AT↑CG, CC↑CG, AC↑TG or GC↑CG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The off-target sites of Zif268::N.φGamma in λ DNA, however, appear to be AY↑YS (e.g. AC↑CC, AC↑TG, AT↑CG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>This limited spectrum of ‘star’ sites could be result of few ‘star’ sites interrogated or lower ‘star’ activity in the high salt buffer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>We constructed two versions of Zif268::N.φGamma fusion, R1 with 13-aa linker and R2 with 3-aa linker between the ZFs and N.φGamma catalytic domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>R1 is more active than R2 in DNA nicking and both require a N6 DNA spacer between the ZFP binding site and the N.φGamma target sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>More Zif268 and N.φGamma fusions with variable linker length ranging from 4 to 20 aa are probably necessary to pinpoint the optimal spacing between the two functional domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The optimal linker between ZF arrays and FokI cleavage domain appears to be 4–8 aa residues for efficient cleavage of target sites with a 6-bp spacer by ZFNs (60). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>To better understand how N.φGamma is likely positioned in the chimeric structure, we built three-dimensional homology-based models of DNA-bound and the apo Zif268::N.φGamma (ZifIII R1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>As shown in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Figure S7</ext-link>, this model (monomer) adopts an elongated shape and covers roughly two turns of the DNA helix. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The ZF nickase by fusion of a ZF arrays and a FokI cleavage domain requires dimerization in order to nick the target sites, i.e. formation of a heterodimer by FokI catalytic-proficient (R+) and catalytic-deficient (R−) monomers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Similarly, TALE-FokI nickase (to be constructed and functionally tested) may also require dimer formation (TALE-FokIR+ and TALE-FokIR−) in order to nick target sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The advantages of using a HNH nicking domain are: (i) a single molecule construction, and thus the cost of cloning, expression and purification may be cut in half, (ii) the wide selection of natural HNH nicking domains existing among the phage and prophage-encoded HNHE and (iii) the minimally functional nicking domain is fairly soluble in fusion with other DNA binding partners. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>The disadvantage of using the N.φGamma minimal nicking domain is that it carries its own specificity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>By site-directed mutagenesis, however, its specificity could be further reduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, one can use the nicking domain from N.BceSVIII with frequent nicking sites (S↓RT, ∼2 bp) for construction of chimeric nickases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Our initial study using the HNH nicking domain from I-HmuI indicated that it has a strong non-specific nicking activity in the absence of a DNA binding partner and therefore mutations need to be introduced to further reduce its affinity for DNA (S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Chan and S.-Y. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Xu, unpublished results). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>A ZR domain isolated from the Nob1 RNA endonuclease of the archaeon Pyrococcus horikoshiiis is sufficient to bind an RNA helix 40 of the small subunit ribosomal RNA (rRNA) (61), indicating the ZR domain has its own specificity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>ZRs have been widely adopted by other nucleases and DNA/RNA metabolic enzymes and transcription factors (62–65). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>The ZR found in McrA endonuclease, a member of the HNHE superfamily, had been studied previously by computer modeling and structure prediction (34). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Metal ion requirement of HNHEs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>A few HNHEs are only active in Mn++ or Co++ buffers, including N.BceSVIII, Lactobacillus phage Lrm1 gp54 (N.ϕLrm1), S. aureus prophage ORF Sap040a_009 HNHE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>N.BceSVIII and phage N.φGamma are active in a range of 1–10 mM Mn++ tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Gp54 of Lactobacillus phage Lrm1 (N.ϕLrm1), however, prefers a low concentration of Mn++ (1 mM) in nicking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Thus, the optimal Mn++ concentration supporting maximum endonuclease activity depends on the individual enzyme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The non-specific HNHE encoded by phage HK97 contains the zinc-binding motif CxxC and CxxH in the catalytic domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>No additional zinc-binding sites (ZRs) were found at the N-terminus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>HK97 gp74 HNHE prefers Ni++ as a co-factor, although lower activity was also detected in other divalent cations (33,66). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>HK97 gp74 HNHE also nicks plasmid DNA, but the sequence specificity of nicking sites (if any) has not been yet determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Previously, we found HpyAV (CCTTC N6/N5), a member of the HNH family REase also prefers Ni++ for optimal endonuclease activity (67). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the modification-dependent endonuclease Sco McrA, an HNH family enzyme, prefers Mn++ or Co++ in cleaving M.Dcm-modified DNA (68). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>In N.φGamma, the conserved ‘ββα–metal’ fold is expected to display a tetrahedral coordination of a Zn ion for structural folding and an Mg++/Mn++ divalent cation for catalytic function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>The magnesium concentration is estimated to be ∼100 mM in actively growing E. coli cells, although most of the Mg++ is in a bound state to nucleic acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The Mn++ and Zn++ ions in E. coli are estimated at much lower concentration, at ∼0.2–0.4 mM for Mn++ and 0.1 mM for Zn++ ions (cells grown in LB broth) (Bionumbers database at the web site: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bionumbers.hms.harvard.edu">http://bionumbers.hms.harvard.edu</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Based on this estimation of metal ion concentration, it is speculated that Mg++ is more readily available for the N.φGamma catalytic activity than Mn++, which may explain the observation that most of the phage/prophage-encoded HNHE described in this work are not toxic or lethal to E. coli, even though some of the HNHEs have frequent nicking sites, and in the absence of companion methylase protection (or prophage gene expression may be tightly repressed). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Previously, we expressed Nt.CviPII (/CCD, a frequent nickase encoded by a chlorella virus NYs-1) in E. coli (Nt.CviPII requires Mg++ for catalytic activity and belongs to the PDxExK family endonucleases). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>The over-expression of Nt.CviPII requires the presence of a cognate methylase for host DNA protection (7). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Off-target sites of Zif268::N.φGamma F5 fusion NEase </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>The N.φGamma catalytic domain F5 has its own specificity (ACCG, ACCC, ACTG or ATCG) and the Zif268 has 9-bp specificity (GCGTGGGCG or GCGGGGGCG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>The fusion enzyme has the combined sequence specificities with a 6-bp spacer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Although we have not analyzed many ‘star’ sites of Zif268::N.φGamma F5 chimera, the following observation was made in the limited number of off-target sites in λ and pUC19 DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>For a strong ‘star’ site, 2-bp matches in each finger (6-bp matches total) are better than 6-bp matches in only two fingers and 0-bp match in one finger (6-bp matches total). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>The 3-bp matches in ZF3, 2-bp matches in ZF2 and 1-bp match in ZF1 (6-bp matches total) appear to be a ‘star’ site (e.g. AC↑CG-N6-GCGSGGGNN, ACCG can be substituted by ACCC, ATCG or ACTG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>It is possible that ZF2 and ZF3 are more important than ZF1 in determination of the nicking specificity due to the proximity to the N.φGamma nicking domain or higher binding affinity to DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Sequencing more ZifIII R1 ‘star’ sites is necessary to confirm this observation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Fusion of N.φGamma F5 nicking domain to other DNA binding elements </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>In theory, the N.φGamma minimal nicking domain can be fused to other DNA binding proteins such as a cleavage-deficient NotI REase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Because NotI forms a dimer, the NotI (D160N)::N.φGamma F5 fusion may nick the symmetric site AC↑CG-Nx-GCGGCCGC-Nx-CG↓GT (estimated x = 6–12 bp). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The N.φGamma nicking domain may also be fused to a TALE effector protein, which recognizes 14-to 24-bp recognition sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>The resulting fusion protein is expected to nick DNA at rare sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>A number of labs have developed methods for the modular construction of custom-designed TALE effector proteins and TALE nucleases (69–76). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>The optimal linker between TALE effector protein and the N.φGamma nicking domain needs to be tested experimentally in future work. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>The homeodomain fold commonly found in eukaryotic transcription factors consists of a 60-aa helix–turn–helix structure that binds to DNA or RNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>A large number of new specificities of homeodomain have been selected that can serve as the target-recognizing domain (TRD) of the fusion nicking enzyme (77). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>In addition, the N.φGamma nicking domain can be conjugated to LNA (locked nucleic acid) which binds to dsDNA by triple-helix formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the N.φGamma nicking domain can be coupled to 5mC-recognition domain such as MBD (methyl-binding domain protein) (78) or the 5mC specificity domain of MspJI-family REases, McrB, McrA, SauUSI or SRA protein, generating 5mC-specific nickases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Possible biological function of phage and prophage-encoded HNHE </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Table 2 shows the gene organization of the phage/prophage-encoded HNHE, adjacent ZR protein, terminase small and large subunits and phage portal protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>The biological function of these phage or prophage-encoded HNH NEases is unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Because these NEase are located near the DNA packaging enzyme terminase, we speculate that these NEases may play a role in DNA packaging, e.g. by relieving the supercoiled tension built up during DNA translocation into the phage prohead. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>The nicks may stimulate homologous recombination and enhance gene conversion of HNHE-minus incoming phage to HNHE-plus phage, which may also occur during mixed infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>HEases make dsDNA breaks in alleles that are homologous to the endonuclease gene but lack the intron or intein element, which encodes the gene for the HEase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>One example of HNH NEase-stimulated trans-homing was reported previously: an HNH nicking enzyme (mobE) encoded by T4 phage introduces a strand-specific nick in the non-coding strand of the nrdB gene of a related phage T2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>MobE promotes the mobility of the neighboring non-functional homing endonuclease I-TevIII, which was encoded within a Group I intron interrupting the nrdB gene of phage T4 (79). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>In this case, the nicking enzyme functions as a ‘helper’ HEase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>The HNH nicking enzymes may play a role in the lysogenic life cycle of phage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>It was proposed that phage HK97 HNHE, gp74 generated dsDNA breaks (or ssDNA nicks in certain metal ions), thereby initiating bacterial SOS repair response that allows for homologous recombination at the cleavage site to occur, resulting in integration of the phage genome (66). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Another possibility yet to be ruled out is introduction of dsDNA breaks by HNH nicking endonuclease in conjunction with another nickase such as ParB homologs or Vrr_nuc domain endonucleases, which together function as restriction enzymes to restrict invading DNA. Table 2.Genes (ORFs) in proximity to the phage- or prophage-encoded HNHEsaThe ZR motifs of the ZR proteins located either upstream or downstream of the HNHEs contain the amino acid sequence: CxxC, CxxxC, HxxC, HxxxC, or CxxxxxH; bThere are two HNHEs in the shot-gun genome sequences of B. thuringensis str T13001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The N.BthT13001I (Bth193) activity has been verified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>The nicking activity of the shorter HNHE (67 aa) and the 110-aa ZR protein is unknown; cThe gp74 HNHE encoded by phage HK97 contains the zinc-binding motif CxxC and CxxH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Gp74 has nicking activity on plasmids (in Ni++ buffer). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>We have not studied the function of the ZRP located next to the HNHE except for the Bth193 HNHE (N.BthT13001I), which is a fusion of ZRP to HNHE with four putative zinc-binding sites (8xZRs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>The adjacent ZRP could serve as the transcription regulator of the HNHE gene or as a mini-specificity subunit that could interact with the HNHE and further extend the sequence specificity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Experiments are in progress to express and purify these small ZRPs to elucidate their function and to construct chimeric fusion NEases from existing HNHEs by domain swapping. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gks1043/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NAR Online: Supplementary Methods and Supplementary Figures 1–7. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>FUNDING </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Funding for open access charge: New England Biolabs, Inc. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Conflict of interest statement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Some nicking enzymes described in this paper may become commercial products. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag>
<SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_41_1_378__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword" xlink:href="supp_gks1043_nar-01760-f-2012-File007.docx"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></SecTag>
</body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>We thank Richard Roberts, Bill Jack, Siu-Hong Chan, Jim Samuelson, Ted Davis and Brian Anton for critical reading of the manuscript; Nancy Badger and Barton Slatko in DNA sequencing core lab for sequencing; Siu-Hong Chan for running the molecular size exclusion column; Rebecca Nugent and Geoff Wilson for discussion; Don Comb for general interest in engineering genome-editing reagents; Jim Ellard for support. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="gks1043-B1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>1SmithHORestriction endonuclease from Hemophilus influenzae RdMethods Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Biol.197477185 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B2"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>2WilsonGGMurrayNERestriction and modification systemsAnn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Genet.1991255856271812816 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B3"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>3Van EttenJLXiaYBurbankDENarvaKEChlorella viruses code for restriction and modification enzymesGene1988741131152854800 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B4"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>4PingoudAAlvesJGeigerRRestriction enzymesMethods Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Biol.19931610720019082972 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B5"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>5RobertsRJVinczeTPosfaiJMacelisDREBASE–a database for DNA restriction and modification: enzymes, genes and genomesNucleic Acids Res.201038D234D23619846593 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B6"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>6XuSYZhuZZhangPChanSHSamuelsonJCXiaoJIngallsDWilsonGGDiscovery of natural nicking endonucleases Nb.BsrDI and Nb.BtsI and engineering of top-strand nicking variants from BsrDI and BtsINucleic Acids Res.2007354608461817586812 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B7"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>7ChanSHZhuZVan EttenJLXuSYCloning of CviPII nicking and modification system from chlorella virus NYs-1 and application of Nt.CviPII in random DNA amplificationNucleic Acids Res.2004326187619915570069 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B8"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>8KachalovaGSRogulinEAYunusovaAKArtyukhRIPerevyazovaTAMatvienkoNIZheleznayaLABartunikHDStructural analysis of the heterodimeric type IIS restriction endonuclease R.BspD6I acting as a complex between a monomeric site-specific nickase and a catalytic subunitJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Biol.200838448950218835275 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B9"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>9XuYLunnenKDKongHEngineering a nicking endonuclease N.AlwI by domain swappingProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>USA200198129901299511687651 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B10"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>10ZhangPTooPHSamuelsonJCChanSHVinczeTDoucetteSBackstromSPotamousisKDSchrammTMForrestDEngineering BspQI nicking enzymes and application of N.BspQI in DNA labeling and production of single-strand DNAProtein expression and purification20106922623419747545 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B11"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>11HeiterDFLunnenKDWilsonGGSite-specific DNA-nicking mutants of the heterodimeric restriction endonuclease R.BbvCIJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Biol.200534863164015826660 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B12"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>12KostiukGSasnauskasGTamulaitieneGSiksnysVDegenerate sequence recognition by the monomeric restriction enzyme: single mutation converts BcnI into a strand-specific nicking endonucleaseNucleic Acids Res.2011393744375321227928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B13"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>13SandersKLCattoLEBellamySRHalfordSETargeting individual subunits of the FokI restriction endonuclease to specific DNA strandsNucleic Acids Res.2009372105211519223323 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B14"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>14GreensteinDHoriuchiKDouble-strand cleavage and strand joining by the replication initiator protein of filamentous phage f1J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Chem.198926412627126322663862 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B15"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>15NashRPNiblockFCRedinboMRTyrosine partners coordinate DNA nicking by the Salmonella typhimurium plasmid pCU1 relaxase enzymeFEBS Lett.20115851216122221439279 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B16"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>16ChanSHStoddardBLXuSYNatural and engineered nicking endonucleases–from cleavage mechanism to engineering of strand-specificityNucleic Acids Res.20113911820805246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B17"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>17TaylorGKStoddardBLStructural, functional and evolutionary relationships between homing endonucleases and proteins from their host organismsNucleic Acids Res.2012405189520022406833 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B18"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>18LandthalerMLauNCShubDAGroup I intron homing in Bacillus phages SPO1 and SP82: a gene conversion event initiated by a nicking homing endonucleaseJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Bacteriol.20041864307431415205433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B19"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>19WangJFriedmanGDoyonYWangNSLiCJMillerJCHuaKLYanJJBabiarzJEGregoryPDTargeted gene addition to a predetermined site in the human genome using a ZFN-based nicking enzymeGenome Res.2012221316132622434427 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B20"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>20RamirezCLCertoMTMussolinoCGoodwinMJCradickTJMcCaffreyAPCathomenTScharenbergAMJoungJKEngineered zinc finger nickases induce homology-directed repair with reduced mutagenic effectsNucleic Acids Res.2012405560556822373919 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B21"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>21KimEKimSKimDHChoiBSChoiIYKimJSPrecision genome engineering with programmable DNA-nicking enzymesGenome Res.2012221327133322522391 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B22"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>22McConnell SmithATakeuchiRPellenzSDavisLMaizelsNMonnatRJJrStoddardBLGeneration of a nicking enzyme that stimulates site-specific gene conversion from the I-AniI LAGLIDADG homing endonucleaseProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>USA20091065099510419276110 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B23"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>23MetzgerMJMcConnell-SmithAStoddardBLMillerADSingle-strand nicks induce homologous recombination with less toxicity than double-strand breaks using an AAV vector templateNucleic Acids Res.20113992693520876694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B24"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>24NiuYTenneyKLiHGimbleFSEngineering variants of the I-SceI homing endonuclease with strand-specific and site-specific DNA-nicking activityJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>Biol.200838218820218644379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B25"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>25PetekLMRussellDWMillerDGFrequent endonuclease cleavage at off-target locations in vivoMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Ther.20101898398620216527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B26"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>26TaylorGKHeiterDFPietrokovskiSStoddardBLActivity, specificity and structure of I-Bth0305I: a representative of a new homing endonuclease familyNucleic Acids Res.2011399705971921890897 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B27"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>27GersbachCAGajTGordleyRMMercerACBarbasCF3rdTargeted plasmid integration into the human genome by an engineered zinc-finger recombinaseNucleic Acids Res.2011397868787821653554 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B28"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>28ProrocicMMWenlongDOlorunnijiFJAkopianASchloetelJGHanniganAMcPhersonALStarkWMZinc-finger recombinase activities in vitroNucleic Acids Res.2011399316932821849325 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B29"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>29XuSYNugentRLKasamkattilJFomenkovAGuptaYAggarwalAWangXLiZZhengYMorganRCharacterization of type II and III restriction-modification systems from Bacillus cereus strains ATCC 10987 and ATCC 14579J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Bacteriol.2012194496022037402 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B30"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>30RoyAKucukuralAZhangYI-TASSER: a unified platform for automated protein structure and function predictionNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Protoc.2010572573820360767 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B31"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>31EmsleyPLohkampBScottWGCowtanKFeatures and development of CootActa Crystallogr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>D Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Crystallogr.20106648650120383002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B32"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>32RobertsRJBelfortMBestorTBhagwatASBickleTABitinaiteJBlumenthalRMDegtyarevSDrydenDTDybvigKA nomenclature for restriction enzymes, DNA methyltransferases, homing endonucleases and their genesNucleic Acids Res.2003311805181212654995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B33"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>33MoodleySMaxwellKLKanelisVThe protein gp74 from the bacteriophage HK97 functions as a HNH endonucleaseProtein Sci.20122180982122434504 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B34"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>34BujnickiJMRadlinskaMRychlewskiLAtomic model of the 5-methylcytosine-specific restriction enzyme McrA reveals an atypical zinc finger and structural similarity to betabetaalphaMe endonucleasesMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>Microbiol.2000371280128110972843 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B35"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>35FoutsDERaskoDACerRZJiangLFedorovaNBShvartsbeynAVamathevanJJTallonLAlthoffRArbogastTSSequencing Bacillus anthracis typing phages gamma and cherry reveals a common ancestryJ Bacteriol.20061883402340816621835 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B36"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>36Bennett-LovseyRMHerbertADSternbergMJKelleyLAExploring the extremes of sequence/structure space with ensemble fold recognition in the program PhyreProteins20087061162517876813 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B37"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>37LiLWuLPChandrasegaranSFunctional domains in FokI restriction endonucleaseProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>USA199289427542791584761 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B38"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>38ZhangPBaoYHigginsLXuSYRational design of a chimeric endonuclease targeted to NotI recognition siteProtein Eng. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Des. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>Sel.20072049750417951612 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B39"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>39SukackaiteRLagunaviciusAStankeviciusKUrbankeCVenclovasCSiksnysVRestriction endonuclease BpuJI specific for the 5′-CCCGT sequence is related to the archaeal Holliday junction resolvase familyNucleic Acids Res.2007352377238917392342 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B40"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>40ClaessonMJLiYLeahySCanchayaCvan PijkerenJPCerdeno-TarragaAMParkhillJFlynnSO'SullivanGCCollinsJKMultireplicon genome architecture of Lactobacillus salivariusProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>USA20061036718672316617113 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B41"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>41DurmazEMillerMJAzcarate-PerilMAToonSPKlaenhammerTRGenome sequence and characteristics of Lrm1, a prophage from industrial Lactobacillus rhamnosus strain M1Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Microbiol.2008744601460918539811 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B42"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>42WangYZhangXCharacterization of a novel portal protein from deep-sea thermophilic bacteriophage GVE2Gene2008421616618573317 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B43"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>43FuFSanderJDMaederMThibodeau-BegannySJoungJKDobbsDMillerLVoytasDFZinc Finger Database (ZiFDB): a repository for information on C2H2 zinc fingers and engineered zinc-finger arraysNucleic Acids Res.200937D279D28318812396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B44"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>44RebarEJGreismanHAPaboCOPhage display methods for selecting zinc finger proteins with novel DNA-binding specificitiesMethods Enzymol.19962671291498743314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B45"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>45JoungJKRammEIPaboCOA bacterial two-hybrid selection system for studying protein-DNA and protein-protein interactionsProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>USA2000977382738710852947 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B46"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>46BarbasCF3rdRaderCSegalDJListBTurnerJMFrom catalytic asymmetric synthesis to the transcriptional regulation of genes: in vivo and in vitro evolution of proteinsAdv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>Protein Chem.20005531736611050938 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B47"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>47SanderJDZabackPJoungJKVoytasDFDobbsDAn affinity-based scoring scheme for predicting DNA-binding activities of modularly assembled zinc-finger proteinsNucleic Acids Res.20093750651519056825 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B48"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>48SmithJBergJMChandrasegaranSA detailed study of the substrate specificity of a chimeric restriction enzymeNucleic Acids Res.1999276746819862996 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B49"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>49ChandrasegaranSSmithJChimeric restriction enzymes: what is next? BiolChem.1999380841848 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B50"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>50WolfeSANekludovaLPaboCODNA recognition by Cys2His2 zinc finger proteinsAnnu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>Biomol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Struct.20002918321210940247 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B51"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>51WrightDAThibodeau-BegannySSanderJDWinfreyRJHirshASEichtingerMFuFPorteusMHDobbsDVoytasDFStandardized reagents and protocols for engineering zinc finger nucleases by modular assemblyNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>Protoc.200611637165217406455 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B52"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>52CarrollDGenome engineering with zinc-finger nucleasesGenetics201118877378221828278 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B53"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>53PavletichNPPaboCOZinc finger-DNA recognition: crystal structure of a Zif268-DNA complex at 2.1 AScience19912528098172028256 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B54"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>54HuangHYuanHSThe conserved asparagine in the HNH motif serves an important structural role in metal finger endonucleasesJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Biol.200736881282117368670 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B55"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>55KleanthousCKuehlmannUCPommerAJFergusonNRadfordSEMooreGRJamesRHemmingsAMStructural and mechanistic basis of immunity toward endonuclease colicinsNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>Struct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Biol.1999624325210074943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B56"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>56KuhlmannUCMooreGRJamesRKleanthousCHemmingsAMStructural parsimony in endonuclease active sites: should the number of homing endonuclease families be redefined?FEBS Lett.19994631210601625 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B57"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>57ShenBWHeiterDFChanSHWangHXuSYMorganRDWilsonGGStoddardBLUnusual target site disruption by the rare-cutting HNH restriction endonuclease PacIStructure20101873474320541511 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B58"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>58SokolowskaMCzapinskaHBochtlerMCrystal structure of the beta beta alpha-Me type II restriction endonuclease Hpy99I with target DNANucleic Acids Res.2009373799381019380375 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B59"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>59KelleyLASternbergMJProtein structure prediction on the Web: a case study using the Phyre serverNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Protoc.2009436337119247286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B60"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>60HandelEMAlwinSCathomenTExpanding or restricting the target site repertoire of zinc-finger nucleases: the inter-domain linker as a major determinant of target site selectivityMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Ther.20091710411119002164 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B61"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>61VeithTMartinRWurmJPWeisBLDuchardt-FernerESafferthalCHennigRMirusOBohnsackMTWohnertJStructural and functional analysis of the archaeal endonuclease Nob1Nucleic Acids Res.2012403259327422156373 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B62"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>62ElsbyLMRobertsSGInteraction of the TFIIB zinc ribbon with RNA polymerase IIBiochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>Trans.20083659559818631123 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B63"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>63VanameeESHsiehPZhuZYatesDGarmanEXuSAggarwalAKGlucocorticoid receptor-like Zn(Cys)4 motifs in BslI restriction endonucleaseJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Biol.200333459560314623197 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B64"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>64SaravananMVasuKGhoshSNagarajaVDual role for Zn2+ in maintaining structural integrity and inducing DNA sequence specificity in a promiscuous endonucleaseJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Chem.2007282323203232617785455 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B65"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>65GrishinNVC-terminal domains of Escherichia coli topoisomerase I belong to the zinc-ribbon superfamilyJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Molecular Biol.200029911651177 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B66"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>66MoodleySBiochemical investigation of the bacteriophage protein HK97 gp74M.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Thesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>University of Toronto20101-102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B67"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>67ChanSHOpitzLHigginsLO'LoaneDXuSYCofactor requirement of HpyAV restriction endonucleasePLoS One5e907120140205 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B68"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>68LiuGOuHYWangTLiLTanHZhouXRajakumarKDengZHeXCleavage of phosphorothioated DNA and methylated DNA by the type IV restriction endonuclease ScoMcrAPLoS Genet.20106e100125321203499 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B69"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>69ChristianMCermakTDoyleELSchmidtCZhangFHummelABogdanoveAJVoytasDFTargeting DNA double-strand breaks with TAL effector nucleasesGenetics201018675776120660643 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B70"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>70MorbitzerRElsaesserJHausnerJLahayeTAssembly of custom TALE-type DNA binding domains by modular cloningNucleic Acids Res.2011395790579921421566 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B71"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>71LiTHuangSJiangWZWrightDSpaldingMHWeeksDPYangBTAL nucleases (TALNs): hybrid proteins composed of TAL effectors and FokI DNA-cleavage domainNucleic Acids Res.20113935937220699274 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B72"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>72SanjanaNECongLZhouYCunniffMMFengGZhangFA transcription activator-like effector toolbox for genome engineeringNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>Protoc.2012717119222222791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B73"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>73MahfouzMMLiLShamimuzzamanMWibowoAFangXZhuJKDe novo-engineered transcription activator-like effector (TALE) hybrid nuclease with novel DNA binding specificity creates double-strand breaksProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>USA20111082623262821262818 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B74"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>74MillerJCTanSQiaoGBarlowKAWangJXiaDFMengXPaschonDELeungEHinkleySJA TALE nuclease architecture for efficient genome editingNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol.20112914314821179091 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B75"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>75ReyonDTsaiSQKhayterCFodenJASanderJDJoungJKFLASH assembly of TALENs for high-throughput genome editingNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol.20123046046522484455 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B76"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>76BriggsAWRiosXChariRYangLZhangFMaliPChurchGMIterative capped assembly: rapid and scalable synthesis of repeat-module DNA such as TAL effectors from individual monomersNucleic Acids Res.201240e11722740649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B77"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>77ChuSWNoyesMBChristensenRGPierceBGZhuLJWengZStormoGDWolfeSAExploring the DNA-recognition potential of homeodomainsGenome Res.2012221889189822539651 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B78"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>78FomenkovATooPHChanSHVaisvilaRCantinBAMazzolaLTamVXuSYTargeting DNA 5mCpG sites with chimeric endonucleasesAnal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Biochem.200838113514118638441 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="gks1043-B79"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>79WilsonGWEdgellDRPhage T4 mobE promotes trans homing of the defunct homing endonuclease I-TevIIINucleic Acids Res.2009377110712319773422 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
