
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ScientificWorldJournal</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ScientificWorldJournal</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TSWJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Scientific World Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2356-6140</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1537-744X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3835881</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/519603</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Genotypic Characterization of Azotobacteria Isolated from Argentinean Soils and Plant-Growth-Promoting Traits of Selected Strains with Prospects for Biofertilizer Production </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rubio</surname><given-names>Esteban Julián</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2718-7309</contrib-id><name><surname>Montecchia</surname><given-names>Marcela Susana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6552-951X</contrib-id><name><surname>Tosi</surname><given-names>Micaela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cassán</surname><given-names>Fabricio Darío</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9415-5537</contrib-id><name><surname>Perticari</surname><given-names>Alejandro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8624-7490</contrib-id><name><surname>Correa</surname><given-names>Olga Susana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Instituto de Microbiología y Zoología Agrícola (IMYZA), Instituto Nacional de Tecnología Agropecuaria (INTA), Dr. Nicolás Repetto y De los Reseros s/n, 1686 Hurlingham, Buenos Aires, Argentina</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Cátedra de Microbiología Agrícola/INBA (CONICET/UBA), Facultad de Agronomía, Universidad de Buenos Aires, Av San Martín 4453, C1417DSE Ciudad Autónoma de Buenos Aires, Argentina</aff><aff id="I3"><sup>3</sup>Laboratorio de Fisiología Vegetal, Departamento de Ciencias Naturales, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas, Físico-Químicas y Naturales, Universidad Nacional de Río Cuarto, Ruta 8, Km 601, 5800 Río Cuarto, Córdoba, Argentina</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Olga Susana Correa: <email>correa@agro.uba.ar</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editors: C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Bystroff and H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Freitas </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>2013</volume><elocation-id>519603</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2013 Esteban Julián Rubio et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The genetic diversity among 31 putative Azotobacter isolates obtained from agricultural and non-agricultural soils was assessed using rep-PCR genomic fingerprinting and identified to species level by ARDRA and partial 16S rRNA gene sequence analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>High diversity was found among the isolates, identified as A. chroococcum, A. salinestris, and A. armeniacus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Selected isolates were characterized on the basis of phytohormone biosynthesis, nitrogenase activity, siderophore production, and phosphate solubilization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Indole-3 acetic-acid (IAA), gibberellin (GA3) and zeatin (Z) biosynthesis, nitrogenase activity, and siderophore production were found in all evaluated strains, with variation among them, but no phosphate solubilization was detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Phytohormones excreted to the culture medium ranged in the following concentrations: 2.2–18.2 μg IAA mL−1, 0.3–0.7 μg GA3 mL−1, and 0.5–1.2 μg Z mL−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Seed inoculations with further selected Azotobacter strains and treatments with their cell-free cultures increased the number of seminal roots and root hairs in wheat seedlings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>This latter effect was mimicked by treatments with IAA-pure solutions, but it was not related to bacterial root colonization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Our survey constitutes a first approach to the knowledge of Azotobacter species inhabiting Argentinean soils in three contrasting geographical regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Moreover, this phenotypic characterization constitutes an important contribution to the selection of Azotobacter strains for biofertilizer formulations. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The genus Azotobacter, which belongs to the family Pseudomonadaceae from the subclass γ-Proteobacteria, comprises seven species: Azotobacter vinelandii, A. chroococcum, A. salinestris, A. nigricans, A. beijerinckii, A. paspali, and A. armeniacus [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Azotobacteria are aerobic, heterotrophic, and free-living N2-fixing bacteria, which can be isolated from soil, water, and sediments [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Several studies have demonstrated that seed inoculation with Azotobacter improves maize [3], wheat [4, 5], and rice [6] yields. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>However, although there is a considerable amount of experimental evidence of these positive effects on plant growth, mechanisms involved are not fully understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The ability to fix N2 was the main feature leading to the use of Azotobacter as a biofertilizer in the past. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Nowadays, however, it is well established that non-symbiotic fixation can improve plant growth only indirectly, by increasing soil nitrogen after mineralization of N2-fixers' biomass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>More likely, additional abilities of azotobacteria, such as phosphate solubilization and phytohormone and siderophore synthesis, might contribute more directly to increase plant growth and crop yield [4, 7, 8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Like many plant-growth promoting bacteria, azotobacteria have the capacity to excrete auxins to the culture medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Auxins and indole-3 acetic-acid (IAA) as the most common member of auxin family were the first plant hormones to be discovered and are implicated in virtually every aspect of plant growth and development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that inoculation with auxin-releasing Azotobacter strains increases growth, yield, and nitrogen uptake in wheat and maize and that the combined application of Azotobacter and tryptophan, which is often implicated in IAA synthesis, enhances plant growth in a greater extent [5, 9, 10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that auxin production might be a key mechanism of Azotobacter in promoting plant growth and yield, as it has been reported in other bacteria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The importance of studying plant-growth promoting bacteria (PGPR) lies on their potential to be used as biofertilizers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The use of biofertilizers containing living microorganisms is a welcoming management alternative in sustainable systems, like organic and low-input agriculture, as well as a tool to reduce the use of chemicals in intensive agriculture [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>When formulating a biofertilizer, it is highly recommended to consider the use of native bacteria, because they are better adapted to ecological conditions and, therefore, are more competitive than nonnative strains [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Hence, the isolation and characterization of native bacterial strains should be one of the first steps when developing commercial biofertilizers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In Argentina, the diversity of Azotobacter in soils has not yet been studied and any Azotobacter-based biofertilizers have been developed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>For the above mentioned facts, the aims of our study were to isolate and characterize Azotobacter strains from agricultural and non-agricultural soils, covering a wide range of geographic regions and soil types, and to study some bacterial traits involved in plant growth stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>To test this, we first assessed genetic diversity among isolates by repetitive sequence-based PCR genomic fingerprinting (rep-PCR) and identified them by amplified ribosomal DNA restriction analysis (ARDRA) and partial 16S rRNA gene sequence analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Then, some of these isolated strains were tested for hormone biosynthesis (indole-3-acetic acid (IAA), gibberellic acid (GA3), and zeatin (Z)), siderophore production, nitrogen fixation capacity, and phosphate solubilization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Finally, we tested early-growth stimulation of wheat roots by inoculation with some of the isolated Azotobacter strains. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Soil Sampling, Bacterial Isolation, and Azotobacter Reference Strains </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>In total, 74 bulk soil samples (0–20 cm) were collected from agricultural (53 samples) and non-agricultural sites (21 samples) during spring 2006. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Samples belonged to 38 different locations of Northwest, Pampas, and Patagonia regions of Argentina (see Supplementary Material available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1155/2013/519603">http://dx.doi.org/10.1155/2013/519603</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Soil aggregates (~2 mm) were spread onto the surface of Petri dishes containing N-free Burk's agar medium with mannitol as C-source [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>After five days at 28°C, slimy and glistening Azotobacter-like colonies growing around soil particles were selected and further purified in N-free LG with bromothymol blue agar medium [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Motility, pigment production, and encystment were determined as previously described [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Isolates were preserved at −80°C in Burk's medium [1] with 30% (v/v) glycerol. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Azotobacter vinelandii reference strains (NRRL B-14627, NRRL B-14641, and NRRL B-14644) were obtained from the ARS Culture Collection (NRRL), USA, and A. chroococcum reference strain BNM 272, isolated from Argentinian soils, was provided by the Banco Nacional de Microorganismos, Argentina. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Electrical conductivity (EC), organic matter (OM), pH, and extractable phosphorus of the soils samples were determined at the Instituto de Suelos (INTA, Buenos Aires, Argentina) using standard procedures [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Rep-PCR Genomic Fingerprinting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Repetitive sequence-based PCR genomic fingerprints of isolates were obtained with BOX-A1R primers [13] as previously described [14], by using 1-μL portions of whole-cell suspensions of each isolate as templates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Fingerprints were analyzed using GelCompar II v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>6.5 (Applied Maths NV). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Dendrogram was elaborated based on Pearson's correlation coefficient and the UPGMA algorithm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Amplified Ribosomal DNA Restriction Analysis (ARDRA) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Representative strains of each rep-PCR cluster were analyzed by ARDRA, as previously described [2], using the primers fD1 and rD1 and the restriction enzymes RsaI or HhaI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>ARDRA profiles were analyzed with GelCompar II and compared using the Dice similarity coefficient to construct the similarity matrix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The dendrogram was obtained by UPGMA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>In silico ARDRA was carried out with HhaI using the restriction mapper software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.restrictionmapper.org/">http://www.restrictionmapper.org/</ext-link>) and 16S rRNA gene sequences AB175656 (A. salinestris ATCC 49674T) and FJ032010 (A. salinestris I-A), both obtained from GenBank. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>16S rRNA Gene Sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The partial 16S rRNA gene sequence was amplified using primers Y1 and Y2 [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Then, amplicons (~290 bp) were purified using the QIAquick PCR purification kit (Qiagen, GmbH) and sequenced by Unidad de Genómica (Instituto de Biotecnología, INTA, Buenos Aires, Argentina) in both directions using the same primers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The obtained sequences were compared with those from GenBank using BLASTN 2.2.16 [16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>2.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide Sequence Accession Numbers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The obtained 16S rRNA gene sequences were deposited at the GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ database under the following accession numbers: HQ541448, HQ591467, HQ623180, HQ623181, HQ623182, HQ623178, and HQ623179. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>2.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Determination of Potential Plant Growth-Promoting Traits </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Eighteen selected strains were assessed for siderophore production according to the O-CAS method [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Phosphate-solubilizing activity was tested on Pikovskaya medium [18], NBRIP medium [19] and modified Burk's agar medium [1], adding 0.5% of Ca3(PO4)2 to each medium as insoluble P source. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>In both assays, Pseudomonas fluorescens BNM233 (Banco Nacional de Microorganismos, Buenos Aires, Argentina) was used as a positive control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Auxin production was determined using a colorimetric assay [20], with measurements after 1, 2, 3, and 5 days of growth in modified LG (LGSP) liquid medium containing 1% sucrose and 0.5% soymeal peptone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>At each time interval, the number of cells (cfu mL−1) was determined by plate counting on LG agar. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Nitrogenase activity was estimated by the acetylene reduction assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Bacterial cultures were grown in N-free Burk's agar medium at 28°C for 24 h and ethylene production was measured by gas chromatography [21], using a Hewlett Packard Series II 5890 equipped with a flame ionization detector (FID) and a stainless-steel Porapak N column (3.2 mm × 2 m; 80/100 mesh). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The injector, oven, and detector temperatures were 110°C, 90°C, and 250°C, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>N2 was used as carrier gas (4.5 cm s−1 linear gas velocity). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Total protein concentration of bacterial cells was determined by the Lowry method with the DC Protein Assay kit (Bio-Rad, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Nitrogenase activity was expressed as mmol ethylene produced per mg of protein in 24 h. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Indole-3-acetic acid (IAA), gibberellic acid (GA3), and zeatin (Z) production were determined for six selected Azotobacter spp. strains grown in LGSP liquid medium at 28°C for 8 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Z was identified and quantified by HPLC-UV, whereas IAA and GA3 were identified by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry with selective ion monitoring (GC-MS-SIM), as previously described [21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>2.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Effects of Azotobacter Inoculation and IAA Pure Solutions on the Number of Seminal Roots and Root Hairs of Wheat Seedlings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>For plant tests, seeds of wheat (Triticum aestivum cv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Baguette Premium 13, Nidera, Buenos Aires, Argentina) were surface-disinfected (1% NaClO for 3 minutes) and germinated in plastic containers (15 × 25 × 4 cm) on filter paper soaked with sterile distilled water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>To maintain humidity, containers were wrapped in transparent plastic bags and placed in a growth chamber at 25°C with a 16 h light/8 h dark regime for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>For inoculation, bacterial strains were grown in LGSP liquid medium at 28°C for 8 days (~108 cfu mL−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Fifteen pregerminated seeds were inoculated with 100 μL of bacterial culture (~107 cells) per seed and grown for 8 days as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Eight treatments were applied: (a) control (100 μL of sterile distilled water); (b) and (c) two phytohormone treatments based on 100 μL of low (2 μg mL−1) and high (20 μg mL−1) concentrations of pure-IAA solutions (Sigma-Aldrich), sterilized by filtration (0.2 μm filter); (d) A. salinestris AT18; (e) A. salinestris AT37; (f) A. salinestris AT19; (g) A. chroococcum AT25; and (h) A. chroococcum AT31. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Treatments were run in triplicate (three containers each). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>For bacterial root colonization, roots of two plants per container (a total of six plants per treatment) were ground in 2 mL of sterile distilled water with mortar and pestle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Serial dilutions were inoculated in triplicate on LG agar plates and incubated at 28°C for 72 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>At the end of the experiment, root colonization (cfu per root of Azotobacter-like colonies) and number of seminal roots were determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Two independent experiments were run. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The effects on root tip morphology of cell-free culture of two selected A. salinestris strains (AT18 and AT19) with different levels of phytohormone production (Figure 3) and root colonization (Table 3) but similar nitrogenase activity (Figure 3) were assessed and compared to the application of two IAA-pure solutions, 2 and 20 μg mL−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Fifteen pre-germinated wheat seeds per treatment were placed in three Petri dishes (five seeds per dish) containing 0.7% water agar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Seedling treatments were as follows: (a) control (100 μL of sterile distilled water), (b) 100 μL of 2 μg mL−1 IAA-pure solution, (c) 100 μL of 20 μg mL−1 IAA-pure solution, (d) 100 μL of A. salinestris AT18 cell-free culture, and (e) 100 μL of A. salinestris AT19 cell-free culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>After 4 days at 25°C under dark conditions, seedling roots were stained with crystal violet solution (0.075% in 70% ethanol) and observed in a binocular microscope at 25x. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>2.8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Experimental Design and Data Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Each inoculation experiments were performed in a complete randomized design. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Data were analyzed by ANOVA and DGC multiple comparisons post hoc analysis [22] (α = 0.05), using INFOSTAT software [23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>3.1. Azotobacter Isolates Obtained from Argentinean Soils and Chemical Parameters of Soils </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>We isolated Azotobacter-like bacteria from 23 soil samples (11 agricultural and 12 non-agricultural soils) from a total of 74 screened samples (Table 1 and Supplementary Material). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Isolates were obtained from soils with a wide range of values for organic matter content (0.19–5.72%), pH (5.8–8.7), electrical conductivity (0.2–2.2 mS cm−1), and extractable phosphorus (1.9–127.8 ppm) (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>We obtained 31 bacterial isolates that were preliminary characterized on the basis of pigment production and cell morphology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>All of them produced nondiffusible brown pigments in agar medium, showed motile cells, formed cysts in butanol-containing medium, and showed no fluorescent pigments under UV light (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Genomic Fingerprinting by rep-PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The intraspecific diversity among 31 isolates was assessed by means of rep-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Most isolates showed distinctive banding profiles, reflecting the genetic diversity among them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The cluster analysis of fingerprints revealed six major groups among all isolates at 55% similarity level (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Isolates showing highly similar fingerprints (similarity &gt; 90%) were considered clonemates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>As a result, 23 distinct strains were obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>No clear relationship could be established between rep-PCR clustering and the geographical origin of isolates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>For example, group 1 included strains which were isolated from four provinces (Buenos Aires, Chubut, Entre Ríos, and Jujuy) of the three regions (Pampas, Northwest, and Patagonia). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>However, some tendencies between clustering and the origin of soil samples were observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Group 2 clustered all isolates from Córdoba province (Pampas region), group 3 included strains isolated from Salta and Santiago del Estero provinces (Northwest region), and group 4 included two strains obtained from Chubut province (Patagonia region) (Figure 1 and Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>We chose representative strains of each group to classify them using ARDRA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>ARDRA and 16S rRNA Gene Sequence Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>ARDRA with RsaI and HhaI restriction enzymes was used to identify Azotobacter strains to genus and species level, as previously recommended for the molecular identification of these microorganisms [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The 18 chosen strains represented, altogether, the six rep-PCR clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>All strains yielded single amplification products of the expected size (about 1,500 bp) for the 16S rRNA genes and showed identical restriction RsaI profiles (data not shown), characteristic of the genus Azotobacter [2, 24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>When ARDRA was performed using HhaI, six different profiles were obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Cluster analysis of HhaI restriction profiles revealed four distinct clusters at 80% similarity level (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Since all strains grouped in cluster I showed profiles distinctive of A. chroococcum, as reported by Aquilanti et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>2004 [2], and identical to those of A. chroococcum reference strain BNM 272, they were assigned to this species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Cluster II included only strain AT33, which showed a characteristic banding profile of the species A. armeniacus [2], whereas cluster III contained only the three A. vinelandii strains used as reference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The ARDRA profiles of strains in cluster IV, obtained experimentally, were similar to those of A. salinestris reference strains ATCC 49674T and I-A done in silico. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>According to these results, the strains of heterogeneous cluster IV (Figure 2) were assigned to A. salinestris. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>To confirm species identification of isolates, partial sequencing of the 16S rRNA gene was performed for seven strains representing ARDRA clusters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Based on the similarity observed among these sequences, strains AT25 and AT31 in cluster I (Figure 2) were related to A. chroococcum LMG 8756T (99% identity), strain AT33 in cluster II was related to A. armeniacus DSM 2284T (99% identity), and the four strains in cluster IV (AT18, AT19, AT37, and AT42) were related to A. salinestris ATCC 49674T (99-100% identity). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Summarizing, according to the results obtained by rep-PCR, ARDRA, and partial sequencing of the 16S ribosomal gene, the 15 isolates of group 1 of rep-PCR (Figure 1) were classified as A. chroococcum, the three isolates of group 2 as A. armeniacus, and the 13 isolates included in groups 3 to 6 as A. salinestris. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>3.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Siderophore and Phytohormone Production, Phosphate Solubilization, and Nitrogenase Activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>All the 18 strains tested exhibited a color change from blue to orange in CAS medium, which is indicative of siderophore production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Phosphate-solubilizing activity was not evident in any of the Azotobacter strains assayed, independently of the medium used (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>All preselected strains were assayed for auxin production in LGSP medium using the Salkowski reagent method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>After one day of growth (~108 cfu mL−1), all bacterial strains produced low levels of auxin (0.96 μg mL−1 to 2.64 μg mL−1) (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>An important increase was observed after two and three days of growth, without any changes in cfu mL−1 (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Finally, bacterial strains differed in the levels of auxin excreted to the culture medium at the end of the assay, covering a range of values from 2.2 to 19.5 μg mL−1 (Table 2). A. salinestris AT12, AT14, AT19, and AT29 and A. chroococcum AT25, AT30, AT31, and AT39 reached up to a ~10-fold increase from the first to the fifth day (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>No changes in the number (cfu mL−1) of bacteria were observed at the end of the assay (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Using these results, the 18 Azotobacter strains were arbitrarily classified as low- (2–6 μg mL−1), medium- (7–14 μg mL−1), and high- (&gt;14 μg mL−1) auxin producers (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Then, we selected three low-auxin-producing strains (AT18, AT37, and AT42) and three high-auxin-producing strains (AT19, AT25, and AT31) and assessed them in nitrogen fixing capacity and biosynthesis of three phytohormones (IAA, GA3, and Z). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Concerning the nitrogenase activity, the highest activity levels (~14 mmol C2H4 mg protein−1 24 h−1) were exhibited by A. salinestris AT42 and A. chroccoccum AT31 strains. A. salinestris AT37 and A. chroccoccum AT25 strains presented intermediate levels (6.5 mmol C2H4 mg protein−1 24 h−1), and the lowest values (3 mmol C2H4 mg protein−1 24 h−1) were found in A. salinestris AT18 and AT19 strains (Figure 3(d)). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>A. salinestris AT19 produced the highest level of IAA (18.2 μg mL−1), the lowest level of GA3 (0.3 μg mL−1), and an intermediate value of Z (0.8 μg mL−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>By contrast, A. salinestris AT18 and AT37 showed the lowest levels of IAA production (2.2–2.6 μg mL−1) and the highest levels of GA3 production (0.7 μg mL−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>These two strains, however, differed in their Z synthesis: while AT18 was one of the largest Z producers (1.2 μg mL−1), AT37 exhibited the lowest production (0.5 μg mL−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Similar tendencies were observed when strains AT42 and AT31 were compared. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Striking results were obtained with A. chroccoccum strain AT25, whose production of the three phytohormones was always in intermediate levels (Figures 3(a), 3(b), and 3(c)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>A strong agreement was observed between auxin production measured by the Salkowski reagent method and IAA production determined by GC-MS-SIM, excepting AT42 strain (Table 2 and Figure 3(a)). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><title><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>3.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Effects of Azotobacter Inoculation and IAA Pure Solutions on Root Morphology of Wheat Seedlings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Five strains were used for inoculation assays, where all of them induced a significant increase (on average 17%) in the number of seminal roots of wheat seedlings (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The greatest increase in the number of seminal roots (20%) was obtained when treated with the high IAA-pure solution and inoculating with the three high-IAA-producing strains (A. chroococcum AT25 and AT31 and A. salinestris AT19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The results of bacterial inoculation did not seem to be related to the colonization of roots by Azotobacter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>For instance, A. salinestris AT37 and A. chroococcum AT31 showed similar values of root colonization (on average 7.5 × 105 cfu root−1), but the latter was the one showing the largest positive effect on the number of seminal roots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Maybe, a more direct relationship could be established between the stimulation of this feature and the relative amount of phytohormones excreted by the inoculated Azotobacter strains (Figures 3(a) and 3(c)). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The effect of cell-free culture and IAA-pure solution treatments on the number of root hairs was evaluated on 4-day-old wheat seedlings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Treatments with cell-free culture resulted in a stimulation of root hair number (Figure 4) when compared with control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>A higher effect was observed with cell-free culture of AT19 strain than that of AT18 strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>This effect could be mimicked replacing cell-free culture of AT19 strain by the high-IAA (20 μg mL−1) pure solution (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>In contrast, both cell-free cultures of AT18 strain and low-IAA pure solution treatments had a lesser effect on root hair production, compared with the AT19 cell-free culture or the high-IAA solution (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The genotypic characterization of Azotobacter native isolates allowed us to identify three Azotobacter species and several strains that showed a remarkable diversity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Among the 23 strains isolated from 16 locations in Argentina, including both agricultural and non-agricultural soils, A. chroococcum and A. salinestris were the species showing the highest frequency (48% and 42%, resp.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>This result is in agreement with other studies that reported A. chroococcum as the most common species isolated from soils [1, 2, 23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>However, considering that less than a half soil samples contained azotobacteria (23 samples from a total of 74 analyzed soils samples), Azotobacter species do not seem to be frequently found in Argentinean soils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Also, the isolation of Azotobacter was interestingly more recurrent in non-agricultural than in agricultural soil samples (57% versus 20%, resp.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Even though there are no similar previous reports in the literature, these results may indicate a decrease of azotobacteria in anthropogenically disturbed soils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Hence, the application of biofertilizers with Azotobacter might make up, at least partially, the loss of this beneficial bacterial genus in agricultural systems. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The identification of A. salinestris and A. armeniacus in Argentinean soil samples was a surprising result because, until now, few reports have mentioned the isolation of these species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The presence of A. salinestris was reported in soils of western Canada [25], while A. armeniacus was reported in soils of Armenia [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Although the isolation frequency of both species from soil seems to be low, our results suggest that they might have a more worldwide distribution than thought. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Another surprising result was that no A. vinelandii strain was isolated in our study, although this species has been reported as a common soil inhabitant [26, 27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Discrepancies found between our study and earlier reports may be attributed, at least in part, to the identification methodology used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Some misclassifications might have occurred in the past [28] due to the scarcity of genotypic characterizations of Azotobacter isolates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>In addition, the sources from where the isolates were withdrawn could also explain these differences: in many previous studies, Azotobacter strains were isolated from rhizospheric soil, while in this study, the isolates were obtained from bulk soil, a fraction not directly influenced by root activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Our results reveal the wide tolerance of Azotobacter genus to different climate conditions, types of soil, and soil characteristics such as organic matter content, pH values, and phosphorous concentrations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>IAA and GA3 production in our collection of Azotobacter strains was higher than that reported for a phyllospheric A. chroococcum strain REN2 [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Conversely, other Azotobacter strains, isolated from rhizospheric soil in India, reached the same IAA production levels than our high-IAA-producing strains [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Although all tested strains excreted phytohormones in chemical complex growing medium, the levels of IAA, GA3, and Z production differed among them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, IAA production showed high levels in almost all A. chroococcum strains but variable levels in A. salinestris strains, agreeing with its higher intraspecific diversity revealed by rep-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Even though the production of phytohormones by A. beijerinckii, A. chroococcum, A. paspali, and A. vinelandii has been reported by researchers since 1937 [30], as far as we are concerned, this is the first report of in vitro phytohormone production by A. salinestris strains. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Our results suggest that these isolated Azotobacter strains have the potential capacity to promote plant growth directly, through physiological mechanisms such as phytohormone production, in addition to biological nitrogen fixation and siderophore production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The observed changes in root morphology after inoculation with Azotobacter or cell-free culture treatment seem to be directly related to the capacity of each strain to synthesize IAA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>In previous studies, it was shown that root hairs and seminal roots can be affected by IAA concentration [9, 31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, it is well known that other phytohormones are involved in regulating plant growth and development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>GA3 and Z, for instance, have also been previously associated with the stimulation of many aspects of plant growth [32] but, despite this, it is known that plant hormones rarely function alone, and, even in cases in which responses appear to be directly linked to the application of a single hormone, these responses can also be a consequence of other endogenous hormones that are present in plant tissues [32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The genotyping of azotobacterial isolates by the combined analysis of ARDRA and rep-PCR and the screening of isolates based on their in vitro traits for potential plant growth promoting activity were useful tools for their taxonomic classification and phenotypic characterization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>This survey, embracing different regions of Argentina, allowed us to have a first approach to the presence of this bacterial genus in soils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Evaluation of plant growth-promoting traits in bacterial strains is a very important task as criteria for strain selection for biofertilizer formulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>As biofertilizers are a complex resulting from bacteria and their metabolites excreted to the growing medium, it becomes relevant to evaluate every constituent of a biofertilizer before considering it as a potential candidate for field application. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Thus, our results constitute an important technological contribution to Azotobacter strain selection for biofertilizer formulations that would help to implement a more sustainable agriculture through decreasing the use of agrochemicals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplementary-material-sec"><title><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="f1"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Table: Complete list of all soil samples analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Geographical origin and coordinates, land use, number of Azotobacter-like isolates obtained per soil sample, and soil characteristics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="519603.f1.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><ack><title>Conflict of Interests</title><p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The authors thank the Instituto Nacional de Tecnología Agropecuaria (INTA), the Instituto de Investigaciones en Biociencias Agrícolas y Ambientales (INBA-CONICET/UBA), and Cátedra de Microbiología Agrícola, Facultad de Agronomía, Universidad de Buenos Aires, for their support to carry out this research. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>1KennedyCRudnickPMacDonaldMMeltonTGarrityGMGenus III: AzotobacterBergey's Manual of Systematic Bacteriology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The Proteobacteria, Part B, the Gammaproteobacteria200522nd editionNew York, NY, USASpringer384402 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>2AquilantiLFavilliFClementiFComparison of different strategies for isolation and preliminary identification of Azotobacter from soil samplesSoil Biology and Biochemistry2004369147514832-s2.0-3242788821 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>3HussainAArshadMHussainAHussainEResponse of maize (Zea mays) to Azotobacter inoculation under fertilized and unfertilized conditionsBiology and Fertility of Soils198741-273772-s2.0-0007537919 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>4BehlRNarulaNVasudevaMSatoAShinanoTOsakiMHarnessing wheat genotype X Azotobacter strain interactions for sustainable wheat production in semi arid tropicsTropics200615121133 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>5KizilkayaRYield response and nitrogen concentrations of spring wheat (Triticum aestivum) inoculated with Azotobacter chroococcum strainsEcological Engineering20083321501562-s2.0-43449084615 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>6KennedyIRChoudhuryATMAKecskésMLNon-symbiotic bacterial diazotrophs in crop-farming systems: can their potential for plant growth promotion be better exploited?Soil Biology and Biochemistry2004368122912442-s2.0-3142603143 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>7KumarVNarulaNSolubilization of inorganic phosphates and growth emergence of wheat as affected by Azotobacter chroococcum mutantsBiology and Fertility of Soils19992833013052-s2.0-0032945621 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>8KhalidMZahirZAWaseemAArshadM Azotobacter and L-tryptophan application for improving wheat yieldPakistan Journal of Biological Science19992739742 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>9PatiBRSenguptaSChandraAKImpact of selected phyllospheric diazotrophs on the growth of wheat seedlings and assay of the growth substances produced by the diazotrophsMicrobiological Research199515021211272-s2.0-0029110954 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>10ZahirZAAsgharHNAkhtarMJArshadMPrecursor (L-tryptophan)-inoculum (Azotobacter) interaction for improving yields and nitrogen uptake of maizeJournal of Plant Nutrition20052858058172-s2.0-18844415322 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>11BorasteAVamsiKKJhadavABiofertilizers: a novel tool for agricultureInternational Journal of Microbiology Research200912331 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>12SparksDLPageALHelmkePAChemical methodsMethods of Soil Analysis19961390American Society of AgronomyASA-Soil Science Society of America Book Series </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>13VersalovicJSchneiderMde BruijnFJLupskiJRGenomic fingerprinting of bacteria using repetitive sequence-based polymerase chain reactionMethods in Molecular and Cellular Biology19945125402-s2.0-0027992990 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>14MontecchiaMSKerberNLPucheuNLPerticariAGarcíaAFAnalysis of genomic diversity among photosynthetic stem-nodulating rhizobial strains from Northeast ArgentinaSystematic and Applied Microbiology20022534234332-s2.0-003679716312421080 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>15YoungJPWDownerHLEardlyBDPhylogeny of the phototrophic Rhizobium strain BTAi1 by polymerase chain reaction-based sequencing of a 16S rRNA gene segmentJournal of Bacteriology19911737227122772-s2.0-00258723722007551 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>16AltschulSFMaddenTLSchäfferAAGapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programsNucleic Acids Research19972517338934022-s2.0-00308010029254694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>17Pérez-MirandaSCabirolNGeorge-TéllezRZamudio-RiveraLSFernándezFJO-CAS, a fast and universal method for siderophore detectionJournal of Microbiological Methods20077011271312-s2.0-3425078816117507108 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>18PikovskayaRIMobilization of phosphorus in soil in connection with vital activity of some microbial speciesMicrobiologiya194817362370 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>19NautiyalCSAn efficient microbiological growth medium for screening phosphate solubilizing microorganismsFEMS Microbiology Letters199917012652702-s2.0-00329329079919677 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>20GlickmannEDessauxYA critical examination of the specificity of the Salkowski reagent for indolic compounds produced by phytopathogenic bacteriaApplied and Environmental Microbiology19956127937962-s2.0-002889111116534942 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>21PerrigDBoieroMLMasciarelliOAPlant-growth-promoting compounds produced by two agronomically important strains of Azospirillum brasilense, and implications for inoculant formulationApplied Microbiology and Biotechnology2007755114311502-s2.0-3425067453017345081 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>22Di RienzoJAGuzmánAWCasanovesFA multiple-comparisons method based on the distribution of the root node distance of a binary treeJournal of Agricultural, Biological, and Environmental Statistics2002721291422-s2.0-2942533544 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>23Di RienzoJACasanovesFBalzariniMGGonzalezLTabladaMRobledoCWInfoStat Versión 2010Córdoba, ArgentinaGrupo InfoStat, FCA, Universidad Nacional de Córdoba<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.infostat.com.ar/">http://www.infostat.com.ar/</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>24AquilantiLMannazzuIPapaRCavalcaLClementiFAmplified ribosomal DNA restriction analysis for the characterization of Azotobacteraceae: a contribution to the study of these free-living nitrogen-fixing bacteriaJournal of Microbiological Methods20045721972062-s2.0-184245769915063060 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>25PageWJShivprasadS Azotobacter salinestris sp. nov., a sodium-dependent, microaerophilic, and aeroadaptive nitrogen-fixing bacteriumInternational Journal of Systematic Bacteriology19914133693762-s2.0-0025733599 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>26ThompsonJPSkermanVBDAzotobacteraceae: The Taxonomy and Ecology of the Aerobic Nitrogen-Fixing Bacteria1979Academic PressJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Thompson and V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Skerman, Ed. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>27FarajzadehDYakhchaliBAliasgharzadNSokhandan-BashirNFarajzadehMPlant growth promoting characterization of indigenous Azotobacteria isolated from soils in IranCurrent Microbiology20126443974032-s2.0-8486023334922294493 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>28CavaglieriLOrlandoJEtcheverryM In vitro influence of bacterial mixtures on Fusarium verticillioides growth and fumonisin B1 production: effect of seeds treatment on maize root colonizationLetters in Applied Microbiology20054153903962-s2.0-2764453657416238641 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>29AhmadFAhmadIKhanMSScreening of free-living rhizospheric bacteria for their multiple plant growth promoting activitiesMicrobiological Research200816321731812-s2.0-3944908531616735107 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>30KukrejaKSunejaSGoyalSNarulaNPhytohormone production by Azotobacter—a reviewAgricultural Reviews2004257075 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>31SpaepenSDobbelaereSCroonenborghsAVanderleydenJEffects of Azospirillum brasilense indole-3-acetic acid production on inoculated wheat plantsPlant and Soil20083121-215232-s2.0-53849107489 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>32TaizLZeigerETaizLZeigerEThe biological roles of cytokininsCytokinins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Plant Physiology1998chapter 21Sunderland, Mass, USASinauer Associates633642 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Genetic diversity of azotobacteria isolated from agricultural and non-agricultural soils from different regions of Argentina revealed by rep-PCR genomic fingerprinting analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>The dendrogram was constructed by using the Pearson correlation coefficient (r) and the UPGMA method using GelCompar II version 6.5 software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>The groups indicated by 1 to 6 numbers were defined at the 55% similarity level (vertical dashed line). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>The cophenetic correlation value for this dendrogram was 0.92. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TSWJ2013-519603.001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Amplified ribosomal DNA restriction analysis (ARDRA) of Azotobacter representative strains of each rep-PCR group and reference strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The dendrogram based on analysis of restriction patterns of 16S rDNA obtained with HhaI was built using the GelCompar II program and the Dice (S D) pairwise coefficient of similarity and the UPGMA algorithm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Clusters were defined at the S D &gt; 80% similarity level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The cophenetic correlation value for this dendrogram was 0.95. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TSWJ2013-519603.002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Phytohormone production and nitrogenase activity by the selected Azotobacter strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>(a) Indole-3-acetic acid (IAA) production; (b) gibberellic acid (GA3) production; (c) zeatin (Z) production, and (d) nitrogenase activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>IAA and GA3 were identified and quantified by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry, Z was identified and quantified by HPLC-UV, and nitrogenase activity (acetylene-ethylene reduction) was determined by gas chromatography. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Bars are means of three replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>The same letters indicate no significant differences between means as determined by the DGC test (P = 0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TSWJ2013-519603.003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Effect of IAA pure solutions and cell-free cultures of A. salinestris treatments on root morphology of 4-day-old wheat seedlings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Root tips of wheat seedlings treated with solutions of 2 μg mL−1 and 20 μg mL−1 of IAA (low-IAA and high-IAA, resp.) and cell-free cultures of low- (AT18) and high- (AT19) auxin-producing Azotobacter strains. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TSWJ2013-519603.004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Geographical origin and land use of soil samples from which Azotobacter isolates were obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Summary of fingerprinting and identification results of isolates and soil chemical characteristics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*Buenos Aires, Córdoba, Entre Ríos, and Santa Fe are provinces of the Pampas region; Jujuy, Salta, and Santiago del Estero are provinces from the Northwest region, Chubut is a province from Patagonia region of Argentina.</p></fn><fn><p>
<sup>
a</sup>Corresponded to the same soil sample.</p></fn><fn><p>**OM: organic matter; EC: electrical conductivity; P: extractable phosphorus; nd: not determined.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Auxin production capacity of representative Azotobacter strains as determined by a colorimetric assay using the Salkowski reagent and results of rep-PCR clustering. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Auxin concentrations were determined after 1, 2, 3, and 5 days of growth in liquid culture. Values are means of two replicates ± standard error (<italic>N</italic> = 2). Same letters in a column indicate no significant differences as determined by the DGC test (<italic>P</italic> = 0.05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Effect of pure IAA solutions and Azotobacter inoculation on the number of seminal roots, and root colonization of 8-day-old wheat seedlings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Pregerminated seeds were treated with water (Control), IAA pure solutions of 2 <italic>μ</italic>g mL<sup>−1</sup> (Low-IAA) and 20 <italic>μ</italic>g mL<sup>−1</sup> (High-IAA), or were inoculated with <italic>A. salinestris</italic> strains (AT18, AT19, and AT37) or <italic>A. chroococcum </italic>strains (AT25 and AT31). Values are means ± standard error of two independent experiments with three replicates (<italic>N</italic> = 6). Different letters in a column indicate significant differences between means as determined by the DGC test (<italic>P</italic> = 0.05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
