
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mar Drugs</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mar Drugs</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">marinedrugs</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Marine Drugs</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1660-3397</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3944511</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24473171</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/md12020719</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">marinedrugs-12-00719</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Trabectedin and Plitidepsin: Drugs from the Sea that Strike the Tumor Microenvironment </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Galmarini</surname><given-names>Carlos M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-marinedrugs-12-00719">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>D’Incalci</surname><given-names>Maurizio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-marinedrugs-12-00719">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Allavena</surname><given-names>Paola</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-marinedrugs-12-00719">3</xref><xref rid="c1-marinedrugs-12-00719" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-marinedrugs-12-00719"><label>1</label>Cell Biology and Pharmacogenomics Department, PharmaMar, Madrid 28770, Spain; E-Mail: <email>cgalmarini@pharmamar.com</email></aff><aff id="af2-marinedrugs-12-00719"><label>2</label>Department of Oncology, IRCCS-Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri, Milan 20156, Italy; E-Mail: <email>maurizio.dincalci@marionegri.it</email></aff><aff id="af3-marinedrugs-12-00719"><label>3</label>Department Immunology and Inflammation, IRCCS Clinical and Research Institute Hu manitas, Rozzano, Milan 20089, Italy</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-marinedrugs-12-00719"><label>*</label>Author to whom correspondence should be addressed; E-Mail: <email>paola.allavena@humanitasresearch.it</email>; Tel.: +39-028-224-5112; Fax: +39-028-224-5101.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>733</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>13</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 by the authors; licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license><license-p>This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>The prevailing paradigm states that cancer cells acquire multiple genetic mutations in oncogenes or tumor suppressor genes whose respective activation/up-regulation or loss of function serve to impart aberrant properties, such as hyperproliferation or inhibition of cell death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>However, a tumor is now considered as an organ-like structure, a complex system composed of multiple cell types (e.g., tumor cells, inflammatory cells, endothelial cells, fibroblasts, etc.) all embedded in an inflammatory stroma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>All these components influence each other in a complex and dynamic cross-talk, leading to tumor cell survival and progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>As the microenvironment has such a crucial role in tumor pathophysiology, it represents an attractive target for cancer therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>In this review, we describe the mechanism of action of trabectedin and plitidepsin as an example of how these specific drugs of marine origin elicit their antitumor activity not only by targeting tumor cells but also the tumor microenvironment. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>trabectedin</kwd><kwd>plitidepsin</kwd><kwd>tumor-associated macrophages</kwd><kwd>tumor microenvironment</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>According to the prevailing paradigm of carcinogenesis, normal cells become cancer cells by acquiring multiple genetic mutations in oncogenes or tumor suppressor genes in which respective activation/up-regulation or loss of function served to impart aberrant properties, such as hyperproliferation, blockade of differentiation or inhibition of cell death [1,2,3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>However, a tumor is now considered as an organ-like structure, a complex system composed of multiple cell types (e.g., tumor cells, inflammatory cells, endothelial cells, fibroblasts, etc.) all embedded in an inflammatory stroma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>All these components influence each other in a complex and dynamic cross-talk, leading to tumor survival and progression [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>For example, growth factors and cytokines released by non-tumor cells support malignant cell progression and contribute to suppress the immune system inside tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the microenvironment of a tumor is an integral part of its anatomy and physiology, and functionally, one cannot dissociate this microenvironment from what have traditionally been called “cancer cells” [5,6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>As the microenvironment has such a crucial role in tumor pathophysiology, it represents an attractive target for cancer therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>There is already a wealth of information about specific cells and molecules in the tumor microenvironment that can be used as targets for cancer therapy at present [7,8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>For this reason, new molecules with antitumor features are looked at with new eyes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Anti-angiogenic therapies, for example, have been shown to improve clinical outcome in patients with different tumor types; similarly, signaling by the extracellular matrix (ECM) and its receptors are also becoming attractive targets of therapy, especially, as it is clear that ECM receptors and growth factor receptors cooperate to maintain tissue specificity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>In this review, we describe the mechanism of action of trabectedin and plitidepsin as an example of how drugs of marine origin elicit their antitumor activity by targeting tumor cells but also the tumor microenvironment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The Tumor Microenvironment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Organs are composed of parenchymal cells that perform the main organ function and the stroma that gives the supportive framework. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>In normal tissues, the parenchyma is formed by cells inter-connected by cell-cell junctions that define cell morphology, proliferation, migration, adhesion, differentiation, and cell death [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the stroma includes the ECM, fibroblasts, migratory immune cells, and neural elements supported by a vascular network, all within a milieu of cytokines and growth factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The interstitial matrix is an intricate and highly dynamic network of fibers composed of glycosaminoglycan (GAG)-containing glycoproteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Different types of fibrous collagen together with fibronectin, hyaluronan, and proteoglycans confer mechanical strength, elasticity and a precise spatial organization to tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Organ architecture and function are maintained by dynamic interactions between parenchymal cells and their microenvironment [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Both components, cells and stroma, communicate via complex autocrine, juxtacrine, and paracrine mechanisms consisting of soluble molecules, including growth factors, cytokines, hormones, and proteases, insoluble factors, such as ECM components, and direct cell-cell interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>For example, the ECM contains a wide range of growth factors that are bound in an inactive form to matricellular proteins, but can be rapidly released and activated in case of need, for example during tissue repair. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>As any organ, tumors are also composed of cells and stroma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>However, both these components are altered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Tumor cells are characterized by the presence of mutations that alter their normal functioning but also their relationship with the surrounding microenvironment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>For example, as cancer cells begin to expand, they produce factors that activate myoﬁbroblasts and recruit tumor-associated ﬁbroblasts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>These mesenchymal cells, as well as adipocytes, are responsible for many of the tumor-associated changes in the extracellular matrix that promote and foster tumor progression [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Normal cells are also active participants that shape the features of tumors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Inﬂammatory cells, including neutrophils, and macrophages, are frequently the ﬁrst immune cells recruited to the tumor, and may be either tumor-promoting or tumor-inhibiting depending on their degree of activation and polarization [5,12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Another inﬂammatory cell type, the mast cell, is also recruited early and promotes tumor progression by releasing proteases that activate angiogenesis [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Myeloid-derived suppressor cells inhibit T-cell activation and promote angiogenesis, cancer cell invasion, and metastasis [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Natural killer cells and different types of T cells may have either pro- or antitumor functions, depending on their mode of activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Immunoglobulins released by B cells promote tumor growth by initiating the inﬂammatory response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Finally, cytokines and chemokines produced by tumor cells, leukocytes and other cell types are key orchestrators of the cancer-related inﬂammation and have long been associated with the recruitment of leukocytes in tumors and therefore with the sustained presence of inﬂammatory cells [15,16,17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>These molecules are involved in important biological processes that govern proliferation and migration of different cells, regulation of innate and adaptive immune responses, and angiogenic and repair programs of the tissues. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the nature of the ECM in the tumor is different from that of the host tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The tumor stroma is characterized by a remarkable subversion of the tissue architecture and by a different composition of some ECM components. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>For instance, whereas the host organ may have been relatively soft and pliable, tumors are often tough and fibrotic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>It has recently been shown that these alterations in the mechanical properties of the tissue contribute to the malignant phenotype [18,19,20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Ultrastructural and immunohistochemical analyses also revealed the up-regulation of several proteins, such as tenascin, decorin, byglican, α-smooth muscle actin, osteopontin, fibulin-1, fibronectin, and the appearance of spliced protein isoforms that are not normally expressed [21,22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>This changed architecture may promote cell invasion by enabling cells to migrate along the collagen ﬁbers or by enhancing integrin signaling [19,23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Moreover, these matricellular proteins are degraded by specific proteases, such as matrix metalloproteases (MMPs), cathepsins, hyaluronidases, heparanase, elastase, urokinase-type plasminogen activator (uPA), plasmin and others in which activity is generally increased in tumors [24,25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Finally, tumor blood vessels are also different from those of the normal vasculature as they are irregular and dilated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, perivascular cells in tumors are loosely associated with endothelial cells [26,27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>These changes result in abnormal blood ﬂow and leaky blood vessels with extravasation of excess ﬂuid and proteins from the capillaries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The increase in the interstitial fluid pressure generates areas of hypoxia and acidosis inside tumors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>In summary, both normal (fibroblasts, endothelial cells, lymphocytes, macrophages, mast cells, and other cell types) and cancer cells inhabit a complex cellular and matrix ecosystem all of which may interact via juxtacrine and paracrine mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The constant disruption of homeostasis by proliferating tumor cells produces a chronic inflammatory reaction [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>However, the classic players in acute inflammation (granulocytes, macrophages, endothelial cells, and fibroblasts) that ordinarily lead to the resolution of a wound through an orderly series of events, instead react paradoxically to the presence of dysfunctional epithelial cells by promoting their survival and replication [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>This process also includes inflammatory angiogenesis and tissue remodeling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Thus, from this perspective, the microenvironment becomes an integral, essential part of a tumor [29,30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="marinedrugs-12-00719-f001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Trabectedin targets tumor-associated macrophages (TAMs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>(A) Chemical structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>(B) Trabectedin acts on the tumor microenvironment by directly affecting monocytes and TAMs or indirectly by inhibiting the secretion of inflammatory mediators involved in different pathophysiological processes, such as inflammatory cell recruitment or tumor angiogenesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="marinedrugs-12-00719-g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Trabectedin Targets Tumor-Associated Macrophages (TAMs) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Trabectedin is an anticancer drug that was originally isolated from the marine Caribbean tunicate Ecteinascidia turbinata and now is produced synthetically (Figure 1) [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Trabectedin is used for the treatment of soft tissue sarcoma patients and, in combination with pegylated liposomal doxorubicin, for relapsed platinum-sensitive ovarian cancer patients [32,33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>It is a well-tolerated drug; the most common adverse effects observed after administration are reversible neutropenia and reversible AST/ALT elevation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The mechanism of action of trabectedin on tumor cells has been reviewed elsewhere [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Of note, the drug shows unique and high-specific inhibition of the transcription process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Transcription inhibition, that affects both the transcribing and the non-transcribing strands, occurs by different mechanisms such as the displacement of specific transcription factors from their promoters, the stabilization of the DNA duplex structure, a direct interaction with RNA Pol II or the induction of the massive degradation of transcribing Pol II [34,35,36,37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>For example, through transcription inhibition, trabectedin modulates the expression of downstream targets, alters tumor biology, and induces the resumption of natural cellular differentiation in sarcomas resulting from the dysregulation of transcription factors, such as EWS-Fli1 fusion protein and FUS-CHOP [31,38,39,40]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>In addition to its activity on tumor cells, trabectedin also targets key processes in the biology of tumors, indicating that the drug is more versatile than currently available chemotherapeutic agents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>First evidence came from the finding that, among all leukocytes, blood human monocytes and macrophages were hypersensitive to the drug [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>This finding prompted a series of experiments to understand the exquisite selectivity of trabectedin for mononuclear phagocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>It was demonstrated that the drug rapidly triggered the activation of caspase 8, downstream of membrane TRAIL receptors (TRAIL-R) [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Leukocyte subsets have different sets of TRAIL-R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Monocytes and macrophages mainly express the signaling TRAIL-Rs and are sensitive to trabectedin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>In contrast, neutrophils and T lymphocytes preferentially express the non-signaling TRAIL-R (which prevents caspase 8 activation) and are therefore non-susceptible to trabectedin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, low, non-cytotoxic concentrations of trabectedin not only inhibit monocyte differentiation into TAMs, but also the production of specific inflammatory mediators, such as CCL2, IL-6, VEGF, and CXC chemokine ligand-8 (CXCL8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>This effect was observed particularly in monocytes, TAMs, myxoid liposarcoma cells and ovarian cancer cells [12,31,41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Other chemokines involved in monocyte recruitment are also transcriptionally affected by trabectedin treatment (e.g., CCL7, CCL3, and CCL14). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Importantly, all these effects are not reported for chemotherapeutic agents other than trabectedin (e.g., cisplatin, doxorubicin) [31,41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Trabectedin also affected the expression of ECM-related genes produced by TAMs and fibroblast, such as fibronectin, osteopontin and matrix-metallo protease-2 (MMP2) or collagen type 1 [43,44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that trabectedin may reduce the high turnover of the tumor stroma. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>As described previously, macrophages are a major cellular component of human tumors, where they are commonly termed tumor-associated macrophages (TAMs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>These TAMs are derived from monocytes recruited into tumors by chemokines secreted by both malignant and stromal cells [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>As macrophages, TAMs are versatile cells that are capable of displaying different functional activities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Based on their plasticity, macrophages can be classified in two extreme types: “classical” (or M1) and “alternative” (or M2) [46,47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>After stimulation with interferon gamma (IFN-γ), granulocyte-monocyte-colony stimulating factor (GM-CSF) and tumor necrotic factor-α (TNF-α), M1 macrophages secrete high levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines, such as interleukin-12 (IL-12), interleukin-1 (IL-1), and interleukin-6 (IL-6) and have potent antitumor efficacy [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, monocytes exposed to interleukin-4 (IL-4) and interleukin-13 (IL-13) become polarized toward the M2-type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>This is characterized by higher production of the anti-inﬂammatory cytokine interleukin-10 (IL-10) and low expression of pro-inﬂammatory cytokines and ampliﬁcation of metabolic pathways that can suppress adaptive immune responses [47,49,50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>M2-related activities favor disease progression [51,52,53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>For instance, M2-type TAMs promote tumor angiogenesis by releasing several angiogenic factors, such as vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) or platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF) [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>TAMs also release chemokines (e.g., CCL17, CCL18, CCL22), which increase intratumoral recruitment of lymphoid cells without cytotoxic activity (T-helper 2 lymphocytes; Th2) or with suppressive activity (regulatory T cells; Treg) [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The impressive array of tumor-promoting functions is consistent with clinical studies showing high macrophage density in many human cancer types to be associated with increased tumor angiogenesis and metastasis, and/or a poor prognosis [56,57,58,59,60,61,62,63,64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Thus, TAMs are key players of the tumor microenvironment that promote disease progression [12,53,65,66]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The above-mentioned inhibitory activity of trabectedin on TAMs is not only observed in vitro but also in various animal tumor models [42,67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>In those models, trabectedin significantly decreased the number of blood monocytes and of tumor-associated macrophages but not of other leukocyte subsets (e.g., neutrophils or lymphocytes) [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>To prove that the cytotoxic activity on mononuclear phagocytes is an important mechanism of its anti-tumor efficacy, tumor cells resistant to trabectedin in vitro were injected into mice [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, in the in vivo setting, trabectedin still showed anti-tumor activity, in spite of the confirmed tumor cell resistance to the drug when exposed in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Tumor growth was signiﬁcantly restored after administration of myeloid cells from tumor-bearing untreated mice after each drug treatment cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Therefore, macrophage targeting in vivo appear to be a key component of the anti-tumor activity of trabectedin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Effects other than macrophage depletion also account for its antitumor efficacy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Using human liposarcoma xenografts grown in nude mice, Trabectedin induces a significant decrease in the expression of relevant tumor mediators such as the chemokines CCL2 and CXCL8, IL-6 or the angiogenic factor VEGF, and an overall effect on the angiogenic network [42,67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Thus, in addition to direct activity on mononuclear phagocytes, trabectedin reduces the secretion of inflammatory mediators affecting main tumor pathophysiological processes such as the recruitment of circulating monocytes into tumors or angiogenesis [41,42]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The key evidence that trabectedin presents selective activity against monocytes and TAMs finally came from experiments conducted on human samples from patients receiving the drug as part of their therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Firstly, a decrease in monocytes was observed within few days after injection of trabectedin in most patients with soft tissue sarcoma [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, by comparing tumor sections collected before and after neo-adjuvant therapy, a dramatic decrease of macrophage infiltration and vessel network was evidenced, reinforcing the concept that this compound strikes both the neoplastic compartment and the tumor micro-environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Similarly, monocytes and TAMs from ovarian cancer biopsies were sensitive to trabectedin at low nM concentrations and were much more sensitive than lymphocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Moreover, at those concentrations, trabectedin significantly inhibited chemokine (CCL2), inflammatory cytokine (IL-6), and angiogenic factor (e.g., angiopoietin-2, VEGF) production by monocytes, macrophages, and TAMs [31,41]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="marinedrugs-12-00719-f002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Plitidepsin (Aplidin) targets tumor-associated Nurse-Like cells (NLCs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>(A) Chemical structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>(B) Besides inducing apoptosis of Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL) cells, Plitidepsin also acts on monocytes and NLCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>NLCs promote survival of CLL cells by releasing pro-survival factors such as CXCL12. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="marinedrugs-12-00719-g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Plitidepsin Targets Monocytes and Nurse-Like Cells (NLCs) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Plitidepsin (Aplidin) is a synthetic depsipeptide originally isolated from the tunicate Aplidium albicans and now obtained by total synthesis (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The compound is currently being evaluated in a Phase III trial for the treatment of refractory/relapsed multiple myeloma patients (clinicaltrial.gov code: NCT01102426). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Plitidepsin is a well-tolerated drug. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The most common plitidepsin-related adverse events are nausea, fatigue, and myalgia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The mechanism of action of plitidepsin on tumor cells was reviewed elsewhere [68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Briefly, after interacting with a moderately high-affinity binding site in the cell membrane, plitidepsin led to the rapid activation of Rac1 and the sustained activation of JNK and p38/MAPK that will finally provoke the appearance of a caspase-dependent apoptosis [68,69,70,71]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Results of several studies associated the activation of JNK by plitidepsin with an increased oxidative stress characterized by a rise in the levels of reactive oxygen species (ROS) and a fall in reduced glutathion GSH [71,72]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The oxidative stress induced by Plitidepsin also provokes an endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress associated to cell death [73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>After cell treatment, plitidepsin triggers the activation of several key molecular components of the classical ER stress-induced unfolded protein response (UPR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>These include the proteolytic processing of ATF6 and the alternative splicing of XBP1, as well as the phosphorylation of eIF2α and JNK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Plitidepsin also induces the decrease of CHOP protein levels, due to its rapid degradation by the ubiquitin/proteasome machinery. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>In addition to the previously mentioned effects, plitidepsin is also acting on the tumor microenvironment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>This is clearly observed on chronic lymphocytic leukemia models (CLL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>It was recently published that besides its direct effects on CLL cells, plitidepsin exhibits a potent activity against monocytes and NLCs, a subset of cells derived from peripheral monocytes of CLL patients [74]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The high sensitivity of monocyte and monocytic-derived cells to plitidepsin indirectly affects leukemic cell survival by impairing the delivery of pro-survival signals from these cell populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>As with TAMs in solid tumors, NLCs promote survival of CLL cells and play a crucial role for CLL cell progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Among other pro-survival factors, NLCs secrete CXCL12, a chemokine that not only induces the migration of CLL cells to lymphoid tissues but also protects them from spontaneous and drug-induced apoptosis in a contact-dependent fashion [75,76]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>NLCs can be found in the spleen and secondary lymphoid tissue of patients with CLL [77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>In line with the protective function of NLCs on CLL cells, it was also observed that the previous treatment of isolated NLCs with Plitidepsin impairs the survival of CLL cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Plitidepsin induced monocyte and NLCs death by triggering apoptosis, as evidenced by early exposure of phosphatidylserine in the outer leaflet of plasma membrane, the activation of caspase-3 and subsequent cleavage of PARP [74]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The production of ROS induced by plitidepsin plays a central role in monocyte death, as drug-induced apoptosis was blocked when preincubating monocytes with ebselen, a compound that increases intracellular GSH levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>It is currently known that ROS and reactive nitrogen species (RNS) regulate the molecular and biochemical pathways responsible for human monocyte survival and that any disbalance in this strict regulation (e.g., induction of oxidative stress), can be detrimental for these cells [78]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>In this regard, it was reported that monocytes are more susceptible than lymphocytes to cell death triggered by oxidative stress [79]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>These data indicate that, besides its direct antitumor activity on CLL cells, plitidepsin also affects other main drivers of CLL biology, such as monocytic-derived cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>In the last decades the concept that the tumor microenvironment is simply a supporting structure for the preservation of tissue architecture has dramatically changed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Indeed, microenvironmental components provide signals affecting cell adhesion, migration, proliferation, differentiation, and death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Monocytic-derived cells are key players of the cancer-related inflammation present at tumor sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Such a reactive milieu eventually supports tumor cell proliferation and the full-blown development of neo-angiogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>There is increasing evidence that successful anti-cancer therapies are not only dependent on the cancer phenotype but also on the normalization of the tumor stroma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>In this view, the findings showing that trabectedin and plitidepsin have wider mechanisms of action acting not only on tumor cells but also modifying the whole microenvironment is of great interest and may contribute to the development of new drugs from marine origin as anticancer therapies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The opportunity to combine direct antiproliferative activity on tumor cells with the capacity to counteract the pro-tumoral properties of the tumor microenvironment is emerging as an especially appealing therapeutic effect of some drugs of marine origin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>As reviewed above, the antitumor activity of trabectedin and plitidepsin is not only related to their effects on tumor cells, but also on their ability to affect the tumor microenvironment, in particular monocytic-derived cell (TAMs and NLCs, respectively) and their pro-tumoral functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Of note, the effects of trabectedin on tumor microenvironment are in line with response patterns evident in several patients, such as tumor shrinkage or delayed response and prolonged stabilization even in the absence of evident tumor shrinkage [80]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Trabectedin can therefore be considered a particularly important antitumor agent with mechanisms of action that make it especially appropriate for targeting key processes in the biology of cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Similar considerations can be taken into account for plitidepsin. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, there are no other reports showing this specific activity with other marine-derived drugs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Therefore, whether this is a common feature of marine natural products or a specific mechanism for trabectedin and plitidepsin remains to be elucidated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Future Directions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Several questions need to be further addressed concerning the activity of drugs of marine origin on tumor microenvironment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>We first need to understand if the activities observed for trabectedin or plitidepsin on the tumor microenvironment can be observed for other marine-derived drugs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>A second question is whether these drugs are also affecting other stromal components besides the myeloid-derived compartment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>We also need to understand whether the depletion of monocytic-derived cells is similar in all treated patients or if individual variability may result in different therapeutic efficacy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Another important question is whether, by affecting myeloid cells, marine-derived drugs independently influence main pathophysiological pathways of a given tumor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>For example, it would be of interest to know if the anti-angiogenic activity of trabectedin is due to a direct effect on the vessel network or is mediated via the reduction of pro-angiogenic cytokines released by TAMs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>While it is clear that marine-derived drugs have favorable mechanisms on tumor cells and the tumor microenvironment, additional research into the following actions would be beneficial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>All these questions need to be addressed in order to improve the drug discovery and developmental process that would translate into more effective treatments with drugs of marine origin. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><notes><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>1.FarberE. The multistep nature of cancer development Cancer Res. 1984 44 4217 4223 6467183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>2. WeinbergR.A. Oncogenes, antioncogenes, and the molecular bases of multistep carcinogenesis Cancer Res. 1989 49 3713 3721 2660980 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>3. HanahanD.WeinbergR.A. The hallmarks of cancer Cell 2000 100 57 70 10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81683-9 10647931 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>4. HanahanD.WeinbergR.A. Hallmarks of cancer: The next generation Cell 2011 144 646 674 10.1016/j.cell.2011.02.013 21376230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>5. AlbiniA.SpornM.B. The tumour microenvironment as a target for chemoprevention Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Cancer 2007 7 139 147 17218951 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>6. EgebladM.NakasoneE.S.WerbZ. Tumors as organs: Complex tissues that interface with the entire organism Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Cell 2010 18 884 901 10.1016/j.devcel.2010.05.012 20627072 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>7. MuellerM.M.FusenigN.E. Friends or foes—bipolar effects of the tumour stroma in cancer Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Cancer 2004 4 839 849 10.1038/nrc1477 15516957 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>8. JoyceJ.A. Therapeutic targeting of the tumor microenvironment Cancer Cell 2005 7 513 520 10.1016/j.ccr.2005.05.024 15950901 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>9. O’BrienL.E.ZegersM.M.MostovK.E. Opinion: Building epithelial architecture: Insights from three-dimensional culture models Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Cell Biol. 2002 3 531 537 10.1038/nrm859 12094219 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>10. BissellM.J.WeaverV.M.LelievreS.A.WangF.PetersenO.W.SchmeichelK.L. Tissue structure, nuclear organization, and gene expression in normal and malignant breast Cancer Res. 1999 59 1757s 1763s  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>11. KalluriR.ZeisbergM. Fibroblasts in cancer Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Cancer 2006 6 392 401 10.1038/nrc1877 16572188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>12. AllavenaP.MantovaniA. Immunology in the clinic review series; focus on cancer: Tumour-associated macrophages: Undisputed stars of the inflammatory tumour microenvironment Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 2012 167 195 205 10.1111/j.1365-2249.2011.04515.x 22235995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>13. CoussensL.M.RaymondW.W.BergersG.Laig-WebsterM.BehrendtsenO.WerbZ.CaugheyG.H.HanahanD. Inflammatory mast cells up-regulate angiogenesis during squamous epithelial carcinogenesis Genes Dev. 1999 13 1382 1397 10.1101/gad.13.11.1382 10364156 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>14. GabrilovichD.I.NagarajS. Myeloid-derived suppressor cells as regulators of the immune system Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 2009 9 162 174 10.1038/nri2506 19197294 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>15. AllavenaP.GermanoG.MarchesiF.MantovaniA. Chemokines in cancer related inflammation Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Cell Res. 2011 317 664 673 10.1016/j.yexcr.2010.11.013 21134366 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>16. MantovaniA. Molecular pathways linking inflammation and cancer Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Med. 2010 10 369 373 10.2174/156652410791316968 20455855 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>17. GermanoG.MantovaniA.AllavenaP. Targeting of the innate immunity/inflammation as complementary anti-tumor therapies Ann. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Med. 2011 43 581 593 10.3109/07853890.2011.595732 21756064 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>18. PaszekM.J.ZahirN.JohnsonK.R.LakinsJ.N.RozenbergG.I.GefenA.Reinhart-KingC.A.MarguliesS.S.DemboM.BoettigerD. Tensional homeostasis and the malignant phenotype Cancer Cell 2005 8 241 254 16169468 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>19. LeventalK.R.YuH.KassL.LakinsJ.N.EgebladM.ErlerJ.T.FongS.F.CsiszarK.GiacciaA.WeningerW. Matrix crosslinking forces tumor progression by enhancing integrin signaling Cell 2009 139 891 906 10.1016/j.cell.2009.10.027 19931152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>20. ProvenzanoP.P.EliceiriK.W.CampbellJ.M.InmanD.R.WhiteJ.G.KeelyP.J. Collagen reorganization at the tumor-stromal interface facilitates local invasion BMC Med. 2006 4 38:1 38:16 17190588 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>21. HynesR.O. The extracellular matrix: Not just pretty fibrils Science 2009 326 1216 1219 10.1126/science.1176009 19965464 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>22. AllenM.Louise JonesJ. Jekyll and Hyde: the role of the microenvironment on the progression of cancer J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Pathol. 2011 223 162 176 21125673 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>23. CondeelisJ.PollardJ.W. Macrophages: Obligate partners for tumor cell migration, invasion, and metastasis Cell 2006 124 263 266 10.1016/j.cell.2006.01.007 16439202 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>24. RoycikM.D.FangX.SangQ.X. A fresh prospect of extracellular matrix hydrolytic enzymes and their substrates Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Pharm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Des. 2009 15 1295 1308 10.2174/138161209787846676 19355969 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>25. GiraudoE.InoueM.HanahanD. An amino-bisphosphonate targets MMP-9-expressing macrophages and angiogenesis to impair cervical carcinogenesis J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Invest. 2004 114 623 633 15343380 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>26. BergersG.BenjaminL.E. Tumorigenesis and the angiogenic switch Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Cancer 2003 3 401 410 10.1038/nrc1093 12778130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>27. TredanO.GalmariniC.M.PatelK.TannockI.F. Drug resistance and the solid tumor microenvironment J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Cancer Inst. 2007 99 1441 1454 10.1093/jnci/djm135 17895480 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>28. AlbiniA.TosettiF.BenelliR.NoonanD.M. Tumor inflammatory angiogenesis and its chemoprevention Cancer Res. 2005 65 10637 10641 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-05-3473 16322203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>29. BissellM.J.LabargeM.A. Context, tissue plasticity, and cancer: Are tumor stem cells also regulated by the microenvironment? Cancer Cell 2005 7 17 23 15652746 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>30. BhowmickN.A.NeilsonE.G.MosesH.L. Stromal fibroblasts in cancer initiation and progression Nature 2004 432 332 337 10.1038/nature03096 15549095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>31. D’IncalciM.GalmariniC.M. A review of trabectedin (ET-743): a unique mechanism of action Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Cancer Ther. 2010 9 2157 2163 10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-10-0263 20647340 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>32. DemetriG.D.ChawlaS.P.von MehrenM.RitchP.BakerL.H.BlayJ.Y.HandeK.R.KeohanM.L.SamuelsB.L.SchuetzeS. Efficacy and safety of trabectedin in patients with advanced or metastatic liposarcoma or leiomyosarcoma after failure of prior anthracyclines and ifosfamide: results of a randomized phase II study of two different schedules J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Oncol. 2009 27 4188 4196 10.1200/JCO.2008.21.0088 19652065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>33. MonkB.J.HerzogT.J.KayeS.B.KrasnerC.N.VermorkenJ.B.MuggiaF.M.Pujade-LauraineE.LisyanskayaA.S.MakhsonA.N.RolskiJ. Trabectedin plus pegylated liposomal Doxorubicin in recurrent ovarian cancer J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Oncol. 2010 28 3107 3114 10.1200/JCO.2009.25.4037 20516432 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>34. AuneG.J.TakagiK.SordetO.Guirouilh-BarbatJ.AntonyS.BohrV.A.PommierY. Von Hippel-Lindau-coupled and transcription-coupled nucleotide excision repair-dependent degradation of RNA polymerase II in response to trabectedin Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Cancer Res. 2008 14 6449 6455 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-08-0730 18927284 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>35. Bueren-CalabuigJ.A.GiraudonC.GalmariniC.M.EglyJ.M.GagoF. Temperature-induced melting of double-stranded DNA in the absence and presence of covalently bonded antitumour drugs: insight from molecular dynamics simulations Nucleic Acids Res. 2011 39 8248 8257 10.1093/nar/gkr512 21727089 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>36. FeuerhahnS.GiraudonC.Martinez-DiezM.Bueren-CalabuigJ.A.GalmariniC.M.GagoF.EglyJ.M. XPF-dependent DNA breaks and RNA polymerase II arrest induced by antitumor DNA interstrand crosslinking-mimetic alkaloids Chem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2011 18 988 999 10.1016/j.chembiol.2011.06.007 21867914 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>37. FriedmanD.HuZ.KolbE.A.GorfajnB.ScottoK.W. Ecteinascidin-743 inhibits activated but not constitutive transcription Cancer Res. 2002 62 3377 3381 12067978 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>38. CharytonowiczE.TerryM.CoakleyK.TelisL.RemottiF.Cordon-CardoC.TaubR.N.MatushanskyI. PPARgamma agonists enhance ET-743-induced adipogenic differentiation in a transgenic mouse model of myxoid round cell liposarcoma J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Invest. 2012 122 886 898 10.1172/JCI60015 22293175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>39. GroharP.J.GriffinL.B.YeungC.ChenQ.R.PommierY.KhannaC.KhanJ.HelmanL.J. Ecteinascidin 743 interferes with the activity of EWS-FLI1 in Ewing sarcoma cells Neoplasia 2011 13 145 153 21403840 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>40. Di GiandomenicoS.FrapolliR.BelloE.UboldiS.LicandroS.A.MarchiniS.BeltrameL.BrichS.MauroV.TamboriniE. Mode of action of trabectedin in myxoid liposarcomas Oncogene 2013 in press  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>41. AllavenaP.SignorelliM.ChieppaM.ErbaE.BianchiG.MarchesiF.OlimpioC.O.BonardiC.GarbiA.LissoniA. Anti-inflammatory properties of the novel antitumor agent yondelis (trabectedin): Inhibition of macrophage differentiation and cytokine production Cancer Res. 2005 65 2964 2971 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-04-4037 15805300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>42. GermanoG.FrapolliR.BelgiovineC.AnselmoA.PesceS.LiguoriM.ErbaE.UboldiS.ZucchettiM.PasqualiniF. Role of macrophage targeting in the antitumor activity of trabectedin Cancer Cell 2013 23 249 262 23410977 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>43. LounevaN.SaittaB.HerrickD.J.JimenezS.A. Transcriptional inhibition of type I collagen gene expression in scleroderma fibroblasts by the antineoplastic drug ecteinascidin 743 J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Chem. 2003 278 40400 40407 12881530 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>44. LiguoriM.SolinasG.GermanoG.MantovaniA.AllavenaP. Tumor-associated macrophages as incessant builders and destroyers of the cancer stroma Cancers 2011 3 3740 3761 10.3390/cancers3043740 24213109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>45. MurdochC.MuthanaM.CoffeltS.B.LewisC.E. The role of myeloid cells in the promotion of tumour angiogenesis Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Cancer 2008 8 618 631 10.1038/nrc2444 18633355 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>46. BiswasS.K.MantovaniA. Macrophage plasticity and interaction with lymphocyte subsets: Cancer as a paradigm Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 2010 11 889 896 10.1038/ni.1937 20856220 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>47. MantovaniA.SozzaniS.LocatiM.AllavenaP.SicaA. Macrophage polarization: Tumor-associated macrophages as a paradigm for polarized M2 mononuclear phagocytes Trends Immunol. 2002 23 549 555 12401408 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>48. MosserD.M.EdwardsJ.P. Exploring the full spectrum of macrophage activation Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 2008 8 958 969 10.1038/nri2448 19029990 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>49. GordonS.MartinezF.O. Alternative activation of macrophages: Mechanism and functions Immunity 2010 32 593 604 10.1016/j.immuni.2010.05.007 20510870 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>50. QianB.Z.PollardJ.W. Macrophage diversity enhances tumor progression and metastasis Cell 2010 141 39 51 10.1016/j.cell.2010.03.014 20371344 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>51. MantovaniA.AllavenaP.SicaA.BalkwillF. Cancer-related inflammation Nature 2008 454 436 444 10.1038/nature07205 18650914 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>52. DeNardoD.G.JohanssonM.CoussensL.M. Immune cells as mediators of solid tumor metastasis Cancer Metastas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Rev. 2008 27 11 18 10.1007/s10555-007-9100-0  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>53. MovahediK.LaouiD.GysemansC.BaetenM.StangeG.Van den BosscheJ.MackM.PipeleersD.In’t VeldP.De BaetselierP. Different tumor microenvironments contain functionally distinct subsets of macrophages derived from Ly6C(high) monocytes Cancer Res. 2010 70 5728 5739 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-4672 20570887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>54. PollardJ.W. Macrophages define the invasive microenvironment in breast cancer J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Leukoc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Biol. 2008 84 623 630 10.1189/jlb.1107762 18467655 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>55. MantovaniA.RomeroP.PaluckaA.K.MarincolaF.M. Tumour immunity: effector response to tumour and role of the microenvironment Lancet 2008 371 771 783 10.1016/S0140-6736(08)60241-X 18275997 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>56. BingleL.BrownN.J.LewisC.E. The role of tumour-associated macrophages in tumour progression: Implications for new anticancer therapies J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Pathol. 2002 196 254 265 10.1002/path.1027 11857487 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>57. ClearA.J.LeeA.M.CalaminiciM.RamsayA.G.MorrisK.J.HallamS.KellyG.MacdougallF.ListerT.A.GribbenJ.G. Increased angiogenic sprouting in poor prognosis FL is associated with elevated numbers of CD163+ macrophages within the immediate sprouting microenvironment Blood 2010 115 5053 5056 10.1182/blood-2009-11-253260 20375314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>58. HeusinkveldM.van der BurgS.H. Identification and manipulation of tumor associated macrophages in human cancers J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Transl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Med.  2011 9 216:1 216:13 22176642 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>59. LeekR.D.LewisC.E.WhitehouseR.GreenallM.ClarkeJ.HarrisA.L. Association of macrophage infiltration with angiogenesis and prognosis in invasive breast carcinoma Cancer Res. 1996 56 4625 4629 8840975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>60. HagemannT.WilsonJ.BurkeF.KulbeH.LiN.F.PluddemannA.CharlesK.GordonS.BalkwillF.R. Ovarian cancer cells polarize macrophages toward a tumor-associated phenotype J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 2006 176 5023 5032 16585599 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B61-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>61. LeeC.H.EspinosaI.VrijaldenhovenS.SubramanianS.MontgomeryK.D.ZhuS.MarinelliR.J.PeterseJ.L.PoulinN.NielsenT.O. Prognostic significance of macrophage infiltration in leiomyosarcomas Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Cancer Res. 2008 14 1423 1430 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-07-1712 18316565 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B62-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>62. LissbrantI.F.StattinP.WikstromP.DamberJ.E.EgevadL.BerghA. Tumor associated macrophages in human prostate cancer: relation to clinicopathological variables and survival Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Oncol. 2000 17 445 451 10938382 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B63-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>63. JensenT.O.SchmidtH.MollerH.J.HoyerM.ManieckiM.B.SjoegrenP.ChristensenI.J.SteinicheT. Macrophage markers in serum and tumor have prognostic impact in American Joint Committee on Cancer stage I/II melanoma J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Oncol. 2009 27 3330 3337 10.1200/JCO.2008.19.9919 19528371 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B64-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>64. van DongenM.SavageN.D.JordanovaE.S.Briaire-de BruijnI.H.WalburgK.V.OttenhoffT.H.HogendoornP.C.van der BurgS.H.GelderblomH.van HallT. Anti-inflammatory M2 type macrophages characterize metastasized and tyrosine kinase inhibitor-treated gastrointestinal stromal tumors Int. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Cancer 2010 127 899 909 20013807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B65-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>65. CoussensL.M.WerbZ. Inflammation and cancer Nature 2002 420 860 867 10.1038/nature01322 12490959 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B66-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>66. NagaiT.TanakaM.TsuneyoshiY.XuB.MichieS.A.HasuiK.HiranoH.AritaK.MatsuyamaT. Targeting tumor-associated macrophages in an experimental glioma model with a recombinant immunotoxin to folate receptor beta Cancer Immunol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Immunother. 2009 58 1577 1586 10.1007/s00262-009-0667-x 19238383 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B67-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>67. GermanoG.FrapolliR.SimoneM.TavecchioM.ErbaE.PesceS.PasqualiniF.GrossoF.SanfilippoR.CasaliP.G. Antitumor and anti-inflammatory effects of trabectedin on human myxoid liposarcoma cells Cancer Res. 2010 70 2235 2244 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-2335 20215499 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B68-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>68. Munoz-AlonsoM.J.Gonzalez-SantiagoL.MartinezT.LosadaA.GalmariniC.M.MunozA. The mechanism of action of plitidepsin Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Opin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Investig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Drugs 2009 10 536 542  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B69-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>69. SuarezY.Gonzalez-SantiagoL.ZarichN.DavalosA.ArandaJ.F.AlonsoM.A.LasuncionM.A.RojasJ.M.MunozA. Plitidepsin cellular binding and Rac1/JNK pathway activation depend on membrane cholesterol content Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Pharmacol. 2006 70 1654 1663 10.1124/mol.106.025569 16928956 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B70-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>70. Garcia-FernandezL.F.LosadaA.AlcaideV.AlvarezA.M.CuadradoA.GonzalezL.NakayamaK.NakayamaK.I.Fernandez-SousaJ.M.MunozA. Aplidin induces the mitochondrial apoptotic pathway via oxidative stress-mediated JNK and p38 activation and protein kinase C delta Oncogene 2002 21 7533 7544 10.1038/sj.onc.1205972 12386816 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B71-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>71. Gonzalez-SantiagoL.SuarezY.ZarichN.Munoz-AlonsoM.J.CuadradoA.MartinezT.GoyaL.IradiA.Saez-TormoG.MaierJ.V. Aplidin induces JNK-dependent apoptosis in human breast cancer cells via alteration of glutathione homeostasis, Rac1 GTPase activation, and MKP-1 phosphatase downregulation Cell Death Differ. 2006 13 1968 1981 10.1038/sj.cdd.4401898 16543941 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B72-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>72. CuadradoA.Garcia-FernandezL.F.GonzalezL.SuarezY.LosadaA.AlcaideV.MartinezT.Fernandez-SousaJ.M.Sanchez-PuellesJ.M.MunozA. Aplidin induces apoptosis in human cancer cells via glutathione depletion and sustained activation of the epidermal growth factor receptor, Src, JNK, and p38 MAPK J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Chem. 2003 278 241 250 12414812 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B73-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>73. LosadaA.Martínez-LealJ.F.BejaranoA.CuevasC.García-FernándezL.F.GalmariniC.M. Aplidin triggers the activation of molecular components of the UPR as part of its pro-apoptotic program in tumor cells Proceedings of the AACR 104th Annual Meeting of the American Association for Cancer Research Washington Washington, DC, USA 6–10 April 2013 10.1158/1538-7445.AM2013-2129  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B74-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>74. MorandeP.E.ZanettiS.R.BorgeM.NanniniP.JancicC.BezaresR.F.BitsmansA.GonzalezM.RodriguezA.L.GalmariniC.M. The cytotoxic activity of Aplidin in chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) is mediated by a direct effect on leukemic cells and an indirect effect on monocyte-derived cells Invest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>New Drugs 2012 30 1830 1840 10.1007/s10637-011-9740-3 21887502 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B75-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>75. BurgerJ.A.TsukadaN. leukemia B cells from spontaneous apoptosis through stromal cell-derived factor-1 Blood 2000 96 2655 2663 11023495 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B76-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>76. NishioM.EndoT.TsukadaN.OhataJ.KitadaS.ReedJ.C.ZvaiflerN.J.KippsT.J. Nurselike cells express BAFF and APRIL, which can promote survival of chronic lymphocytic leukemia cells via a paracrine pathway distinct from that of SDF-1alpha Blood 2005 106 1012 1020 10.1182/blood-2004-03-0889 15860672 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B77-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>77. TsukadaN.BurgerJ.A.ZvaiflerN.J.KippsT.J. Distinctive features of “nurselike” cells that differentiate in the context of chronic lymphocytic leukemia Blood 2002 99 1030 1037 10.1182/blood.V99.3.1030 11807009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B78-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>78. BaranC.P.ZeiglerM.M.TridandapaniS.MarshC.B. The role of ROS and RNS in regulating life and death of blood monocytes Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Pharm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>Des. 2004 10 855 866 10.2174/1381612043452866 15032689 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B79-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>79. ZurgilN.SolodeevI.GilburdB.ShafranY.AfrimzonE.AvtalionR.ShoenfeldY.DeutschM. Monitoring the apoptotic process induced by oxidized low-density lipoprotein in Jurkat T-lymphoblast and U937 monocytic human cell lines Cell Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Biophys. 2004 40 97 113 10.1385/CBB:40:2:097 15054217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B80-marinedrugs-12-00719"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>80. SanfilippoR.CasaliP.G. The intriguing patterns of tumor response to trabectedin Expert Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Anticancer Ther. 2013 13 21 24 10.1586/era.13.51 23638727 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
