
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3178626</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21977228</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-01622</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025259</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunity</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunity to Infections</subject><subject>Inflammation</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Immunopathology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunity</subject><subj-group><subject>Inflammation</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Protozoology</subject><subj-group><subject>Parastic Protozoans</subject><subj-group><subject>Toxoplasma Gondii</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Host-Pathogen Interaction</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Gastroenterology and Hepatology</subject><subj-group><subject>Inflammatory Bowel Disease</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Parasitic Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Toxoplasmosis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>MIF Participates in Toxoplasma gondii-Induced Pathology Following Oral Infection </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">MIF, <italic>T. gondii</italic>, Ileitis, Inflammation, IBD</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Cavalcanti</surname><given-names>Marta G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Mesquita</surname><given-names>Jacilene S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Madi</surname><given-names>Kalil</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Feijó</surname><given-names>Daniel F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Assunção-Miranda</surname><given-names>Iranaia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>Heitor S. P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bozza</surname><given-names>Marcelo T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Departamento de Imunologia, Instituto de Microbiologia Professor Paulo de Góes, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Departamento de Virologia, Instituto de Microbiologia Professor Paulo de Góes, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Serviço de Doenças Infecciosas e Parasitárias, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Departamento de Clínica Médica, Laboratório Multidisciplinar de Pesquisa, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>
<addr-line>Departamento de Patologia, Hospital Universitário Clementino Fraga Filho, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff6">
<label>6</label>
<addr-line>Laboratório Sérgio Franco, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>Jörg Hermann</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">McGill University, Canada</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>cavalcanti.marta66@gmail.com</email> (MGC); <email>mbozza@micro.ufrj.br</email> (MTB)</corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: MGC MTB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: MGC JSM DFF IMA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: MGC MTB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: KM HSPS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: MGC MTB. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ecorrected"><day>27
</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e25259</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Cavalcanti et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF) is essential for controlling parasite burden and survival in a model of systemic Toxoplasma gondii infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Peroral T. gondii infection induces small intestine necrosis and death in susceptible hosts, and in many aspects resembles inflammatory bowel disease (IBD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Considering the critical role of MIF in the pathogenesis of IBD, we hypothesized that MIF participates in the inflammatory response induced by oral infection with T. gondii. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Methodology/Principal Findings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Mif deficient (Mif−/−) and wild-type mice in the C57Bl/6 background were orally infected with T. gondii strain ME49. Mif−/− mice had reduced lethality, ileal inflammation and tissue damage despite of an increased intestinal parasite load compared to wt mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Lack of MIF caused a reduction of TNF-α, IL-12, IFN-γ and IL-23 and an increased expression of IL-22 in ileal mucosa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Moreover, suppressed pro-inflammatory responses at the ileal mucosa observed in Mif−/− mice was not due to upregulation of IL-4, IL-10 or TGF-β. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>MIF also affected the expression of matrix metalloproteinase-9 (MMP-9) but not MMP-2 in the intestine of infected mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Signs of systemic inflammation including the increased concentrations of inflammatory cytokines in the plasma and liver damage were less pronounced in Mif−/− mice compared to wild-type mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Conclusion/Significance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, our data suggested that in susceptible hosts MIF controls T. gondii infection with the cost of increasing local and systemic inflammation, tissue damage and death. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The immune/inflammatory response to Toxoplasma gondii infection is essential to control parasite replication and tissue spread but also can cause tissue damage, being descisive to pathogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Selective tissue invasion by T. gondii causes compartmental immune responses unique to each tissue such as the one present in the placenta, central nervous system and intestinal mucosa, while parasite spreading promotes a systemic response that resembles bacterial sepsis [1]–[3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Inhibition or abrogation of TNF-α, IL-12 and/or IFN-γ increase host susceptibility to toxoplasmosis as a result of uncontrolled parasite burden [4]–[6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In natural T. gondii infection through the oral route, exacerbated inflammatory responses at the small intestine (ileitis) resemble human inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) [1], [7].The inflammatory response coordinate by IL-23/IL-22 is involved in T. gondii-induced disruption of intestinal homeostasis and immunopathology, an effect at least in part due to increase expression of matrix metalloproteinase-2 (MMP) [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>These pro-inflammatory mediators and MMPs are involved in the immune pathogenesis and tissue damage in T. gondii peoral infection, increasing host morbidity and mortality despite parasite control [7]–[9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Deficient regulation of the inflammatory response observed in the absence of IL-10 results in massive leukocyte infiltration, extensive tissue damage despite control of parasite load, systemic inflammation and increase lethality [2]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>MIF is a versatile molecule that comprises hormonal and enzymatic activities in addition to exert pro-inflammatory and chemotactic functions [10]–[13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>First described as a T-cell-derived factor involved in the inhibition of macrophage migration in delayed–type hypersensitivity response, MIF is also produced by other immune cells such as macrophages, neutrophils and eosinophils but also non immune cells such as endothelial, epithelial, muscle and pituitary cells [10]–[15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>MIF expression and production are regulated by adrenocorticotrophic hormone which results in counter-regulation of cortisol [11], [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>MIF production is also regulated by TNF and LPS-Toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4) in a positive feedback cascade resulting in enhanced proinflammatory responses [15], [17], [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, MIF is an essential regulator of innate and adaptive immune responses with a crucial role in host protection against different pathogens and is involved in the pathogenesis of a broad spectrum of infectious and non infectious inflammatory diseases [10]–[23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In parasitic infections MIF is involved both in protective as well as immune pathogenic responses [12], [21], [24]–[28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Upon systemic infection with T. gondii, IFN-γ and TNF-α mediated responses are upregulated by MIF, and Mif−/− mice are more susceptible to infection presenting increased parasite burden [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>A recent study also demonstrated an increased susceptibility, reduced IL-12 production and dendritic cell activation on Mif−/− mice in the Balb/c background to an oral T. gondii infection [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Balb/c mice are naturally resistant to oral infection with T. gondii, while C57BL/6 are highly susceptible and display intestinal inflammation, especially in the ileum [29]–[31]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Considering the role of MIF on intestinal inflammation, we hypothesize that MIF participates in the pathogenesis of T. gondii-induced intestinal tissue damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Our results indicate that MIF mediates pathogenic responses during T. gondii oral infection by exacerbating compartmental and systemic inflammatory responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The lack of MIF caused an overall reduction of tissue damage despite of an increase in local parasite burden. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>C57BL/6 (wild type, wt) and Mif−/− (backcrossed to the C57BL/6 genetic background, n = 8) were obtained from the animal facility at the Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ, Rio de Janeiro). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Sex and age-matched (8–12 week-old) C57BL/6 were used as controls for Mif−/−. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The animals were kept at constant temperature (25°C) with free access to chow and water in a room with a 12 h light/dark cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>All animal experiments were performed in accordance to Brazilian Government's ethical and animal experiment regulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The experiments were approved by the Institutional Animal Welfare Committee (approval ID: CEUA/CCS/UFRJ/IMPPG 011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Parasites and per oral infection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The T. gondii strain ME49 was kindly provided by Dr R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Gazzinelli, (UFMG, Minas Gerais, Brazil) and Dr J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Lannes-Vieira (FIOCRUZ, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>For peroral infection, mice were infected by gavage using 20 and 100 ME49 cysts/animal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Cysts were obtained from C57BL/6 brain homogenates as previously described [2]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Detection of T. gondii DNA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Parasites in tissues were quantified by a real-time polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) as previously described [7] targeting a repetitive 529-bp DNA fragment of T. gondii (GenBank accession no AF487550) [32] which are specific for a cryptic gene as described [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Fifty to 100 µg of ileum and liver tissues were crushed in a rotor-stator after frozen in liquid nitrogen and total DNA were isolated with DNAzol reagent (Invitogen Life Technologies) following the manufactures protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Five hundred ng of total DNA extracted from each sample were submitted to real-time PCR using Power SYBR® Green PCR master mix (Applied Biosystems) using each oligonucleotide primer (TOX-9, 5′-AGGAGAGATATCAGGACTGTAG-3′; TOX-10, 5′-GCGTCGTCTCGTCTAGATCG-3′). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The amplification was performed using one cycle at 95°C for 10 min, 45 cycles at 95°C for 30 s, 60°C for 1 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>A standard curve was performed using 5000-5 pg T. gondii DNA to quantification of total DNA of samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Determination of small intestinal length, histopathology and histological scores </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Small intestinal shortening was determined by measuring whole intestinal segment of wt and Mif−/− controls and T. gondii-infected mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>It was calculated by dividing the difference of the mean length of the small intestine from control mice minus the length from infected mice at day 8 after infection and then multiplied by 100 over the mean length of mice small intestines [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Intestines, liver and brain were fixed in 10% neutral buffered formalin, embedded in paraffin, sectioned at 5 µm, and stained with hematoxylin and eosin using standard techniques. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Blinded samples were submitted for semi-quantitative histopathologic analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Histological scores were determined in fixed and paraffin-embedded tissue sections taken from the terminal ileum, as previously described [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Liver sections were analyzed for the numbers of inflammatory foci at a magnification of ×200 at day 9 after infection in each group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>We analyzed the number of inflammatory foci per field (6.5×9 mm, microscope Zeiss, Germany) counting 10 fields of each section. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Determination of cytokine concentrations at the intestinal tissue and plasma </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Plasma samples were obtained to measure cytokine concentrations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>IFN-γ and TNF-α concentrations were measured by a commercial ELISA from Peprotech (NJ, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Concentrations of IL-10 was determined by ELISA using a commercial kit from R&amp;D Systems (MN, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>RT-PCR analysis of matrix metalloproteinases and cytokines </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Approximately 50–100 µg of ileum tissue were crushed in a rotor–stator after frozen in liquid nitrogen and total RNA were isolated with TRIzol reagent (Invitogen Life Technologies) following the manufactures protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Four micrograms of total RNA extracted were reverse transcribed using a High capacity cDNA reverse transcription kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Each sample was submitted to real-time PCR using Power SYBR® Green PCR master mix (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The reactions were carried out using specific primers for the following genes: MMP-2 (forward, 5′-CAATCTTTTCTGGGAGCTC-3′; reverse, 5′-GCTGATACTGACACTGGTACTG-3′), MMP-9 (forward, 5′-CCTGGAACTCACACGACATCTTC-3′; reverse, 5′-TGGAAACTCACACGCCAGAA-3′), TNF-α (forward, 5′-CCTCACACTCAGATCATCTTCTCA-3′; reverse, 5′- TGGTTGTCTTTGAGATCCATGC-3′), IL-6 (forward, 5′- TCATATCTTCAACCAAGAGGTA-3′; reverse, 5′- CAGTGAGGAATGTCCACAAACTG-3′), IFN-γ (forward, 5′-AGCAACAGCAAGGCGAAAA-3′; reverse, 5′- CTGGACCTGTGGGTTGTTGA -3′), IL-17A (forward, 5′-TCCCTCTGTGATCTGGGAAG-3′; reverse, 5′-CTCGACCCTGAAAGTGAAGG-3′), TGF-β (forward, 5′-GACCGCAACAACGCCATCTA-3′; reverse, 5′-AGCCCTGTATTCCGTCTCCTT-3′), IL-12p35 (forward, 5′-CCACCCTTGCCCTCCTAAAC-3′; reverse, 5′-GGCAGCTCCCTCTTGTTGTG-3′), IL-23 (forward, 5′-TGGCATCGAGAAACTGTGAGA-3′; reverse, 5′-TCAGTTCGTATTGGTAGTCCTGTTA-3′), IL-22 (forward, 5′-GACAGGTTCCAGCCCTACAT-3′; reverse, 5′-GTCGTCACCGCTGATGTG-3′), IL-10 (forward, 5′-TAAGGGTTACTTGGGTTGCCAAG-3′; reverse, 5′-CAAATGCTCCTTGATTTCTGGGC-3′). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The samples were subjected to 45 amplification cycles consisting in 95°C for 30 s, 60°C for 1 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The expression of the hypoxanthine guanine phosphoribosyl transferase 1 (Hprt1) gene (forward, 5′-GCTGGTGAAAAGGACCTCT-3′; reverse 5′-CAC AGG ACT AGA ACA CCT GC-3′) was used to normalize the results, which were presented as fold induction of mRNA expression relative to control samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Moreover, mouse TaqMan pre-developed assay reagents (Applied Biosystems) were used for IL-4 and Hprt amplification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The analyses of relative gene expression data were performed by 2−ΔΔC T method [35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Data are expressed as means ± SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The statistical significance of differences in mean values was determined by using Student's t test or ANOVA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Survival data are presented as a Kaplan-Meier survival curve and analyzed with Log-rank test by software Prism 5 (USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Differences of at least p≤0.05 are considered significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Reduced mortality and morbidity of Mif−/− mice after T. gondii oral infection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>It has been recently demonstrated that MIF determines host susceptibility to T. gondii infection by peritoneal route [27]. Mif−/− mice presente increased parasite load and systemic inflammatory response when compared to wt mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>However, T. gondii infection through the oral route might determine a different outcome depending on the inflammatory response within the intestinal mucosa [36], . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>To define the role of MIF during natural T. gondii infection in susceptible hosts, wt and Mif−/− mice were orally infected with 100 or 20 cysts per animal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Wt mice infected with 100 cysts were all dead after 10–12 days post infection while Mif−/− mice had a significant increase of survival (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The increase survival of Mif−/− compared to wt mice was even more pronounced upon infection with 20 cysts/animal (Fig. 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>To assess morbidity during acute T. gondii infection, we used weight loss and hematocrit measurement, considered good markers of morbidity in acute acquired toxoplasmosis [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Although both wt and Mif−/− mice presented weight loss, it was more severe in wt than on Mif−/− mice (Fig. 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Similarly, hematocrit was significantly reduced in infected wt when compared to Mif−/− mice (Fig. 1D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Thus, Mif−/− mice displayed increased resistance to acute infection and reduced morbidity following per oral T. gondii infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0025259-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025259.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>MIF increases morbidity and mortality during peroral T. gondii infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Survival curves of Mif −/− (C57BL/6) mice (6–8 weeks old) and age and sex-matched wild type controls orally infected with 100 (A) and 20 cysts (B) of ME-49 strain of T. gondii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Morbidity was evaluated by determining animal (C) relative weight loss and (D) hematocrit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>One representative experiment out of three performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Data from 8 to 10 animals per group are given as mean ± SEM, and p values were determined by t-test (* p≤0.05) or by Log-rank test (A, B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Cont, control not infected. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0025259.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Reduced ileal damage despite of increased parasite loads in the absence of MIF </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>To determine the cause of reduced mortality of Mif−/− mice, we initially performed macroscopical and histopathological analysis of the small intestine of control and infected animals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>At day 9 post infection, wt mice presented significant intestinal shortening compared to Mif−/− mice (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>This intestinal shrinkage observed in wt mice was associated with histological changes at the terminal ileum, including blunting of the villi, extensive necrosis and full thickness inflammatory infiltration of the lamina propria (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Infected Mif−/− mice presented reduced necrosis and decreased loss of mucosal integrity, lamina propria and intestinal wall and more preserved areas of intestine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Tissue damage was determined by histopathological scores of the terminal ileum of infected mice, and most samples from wt mice presented higher scores when compared to Mif−/− mice (Fig. 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In fact, Mif−/− mice displayed less tissue damage in contrast to a significant increase in tissue parasitism (Fig. 2D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>These findings indicate that MIF-mediated inflammatory response promotes tissue damage, contributing to morbidity and mortality, but also participates on T. gondii control at the intestinal mucosa. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0025259-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025259.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>T. gondii-induced ileitis is mediated by MIF that induces severe tissue damage despite efficient parasite control. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>(A) Shortening of small intestine of wt and Mif −/− mice (n = 6) at 9 days post-infection (dpi). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>(B) Histopathologycal analysis by hematoxilin and eosin (HE) of terminal ileum was performed at 9 dpi in wt and Mif −/−. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Magnification are ×200 (B1, 2, 5 and 6) and ×400 (B3 and 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>In (C) Histologycal scores of ileal biopsies of wt and Mif −/− mice at 9 dpi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The horizontal line limits absence of inflammatory response (0 to 3) and necrosis (above 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>(D) Toxo DNA concentration was determined in ileal biopsies of wt and Mif −/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>One representative experiment out of three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Data from 3 to 6 mice per group is represented by means ± SEM and p values determined by t-test (* p≤0.05, ** p≤0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Length of intestinal segments of control not infected wt and Mif −/− mice are represented by a dotted line in A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Cont, control not infected. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0025259.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>MIF regulates inflammatory cytokines in T. gondii-induced ileitis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>To investigate the mechanism by which MIF regulates the inflammatory response at the intestinal mucosa, we examined mRNA expression and the concentrations of inflammatory cytokines in the supernatants of ileal mucosal explants from wt and Mif−/− infected mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>TNF-α, IL-12, IFN-γ and IL-23 expression were decreased in infected Mif−/− mice when compared to wt mice (Fig. 3A–C, E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The mRNA expression of IL-6 and IL-17A were also similar in wt and Mif−/− mice (Fig. 3D, F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, IL-22 expression was significantly increased in infected Mif−/− compared to wt mice (Fig. 3G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>To determine if IL-4, IL-10 and TGF-β could be implicated in the suppression of immunopathology and increased parasite burdens of Mif−/−, we examined the mRNA expression of these regulatory cytokines in the ileal mucosa explants of control and infected wt and Mif−/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>While IL-4 mRNA expression was similar in wt and Mif−/− mice at 9 days post infection (Fig. 4A), IL-10 mRNA expression and protein in ileal mucosa were reduced in Mif−/− compared to wt mice (Fig. 4B, data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Similarly, T. gondii infected Mif−/− mice presented significant decrease of TGF-β expression when compared to infected wt mice (Fig. 4C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that the reduced inflammatory response in the ileun of Mif−/− compared to wt mice is not due to up regulation of IL-4, IL-10 or TGF-β. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0025259-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025259.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>MIF upregulates proinflammatory responses in toxoplasmic ileitis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Real-time PCR of (A) TNF-α, (B) IL-12, (C) IFN-γ, (D) IL-6, (E) IL-23, (F) IL-17 and (G) IL-22 expression in ileal explants from control and infected wt and Mif −/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Results are expressed as fold changes relative to HPRT mRNA expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Data from 3 to 6 mice per group is represented by means ± SEM and p values determined by t-test (* p≤0.05, ** p≤0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Cont, control not infected. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0025259.g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0025259-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025259.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Reduced intestinal expression of IL-10 and TGF-β in Mif−/− mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Quantitative RT-PCR of of (A) IL-4, (B) IL-10 and (C) TGF-β mRNA expression in ileal explants of control and infected wt and Mif −/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Results are expressed as fold changes relative to HPRT mRNA expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Data from 3 to 6 mice per group is represented by means ± SEM and p values determined by t-test (*p≤0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Cont, control not infected. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0025259.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>T. gondii peroral infection induces decreased expression of MMP-9, but not MMP2, in the intestinal mucosa of Mif −/− mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Matrix metalloproteinases have been implicated in the pathogenesis of IBD and most recently in T. gondii-induced ileitis [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Given that MIF regulates the expression of MMPs during pathological inflammatory responses such as arthritis [39], [40], we investigated the possible involvement of MMP-2 and MMP-9 in T. gondii-induced MIF-mediated ileitis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>We determined the mRNA expression of MMP-2 and MMP-9 in the ileum of control and infected wt and Mif−/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>At day 9 post-infection, both control and infected wt and Mif−/− mice presented similar MMP-2 expression (Fig. 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>However, MMP-9 was significantly reduced in the ileum of Mif−/− infected mice (Fig. 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that MIF might contribute to pathological responses to T. gondii infection at the intestinal compartment via MMP-9 pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0025259-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025259.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>MIF upregulates MMP-9 but not MMP-2 in the terminal ileum of T. gondii infected mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real-time PCR of (A) MMP-2 and (B) MMP-9 mRNAs in ileal biopsies of control and infected (9 dpi) wt and Mif −/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Results are expressed as fold changes to HPRT mRNA expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>One representative experiment out of two experiments is shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Data of three to five mice per group are given as means ± SEM and p values were determined by Mann-Whitney (**p≤0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Cont, control not infected. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0025259.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Systemic inflammatory responses are regulated by MIF and enhance T. gondii-induced pathology </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The systemic inflammation during T. gondii infection resembles bacterial sepsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Considering the critical role of MIF in the pathogenesis of experimental sepsis, we investigated several markers of systemic inflammation in T. gondii-infected wt and Mif−/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Leukocyte counts were higher in wt mice at day 4 and 7 post-infection when compared to Mif−/− mice (Fig. 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Given that systemic inflammation during per oral infection are induced by pro-inflammatory mediators such as IFN-γ and TNF-α, we investigated the concentrations of these cytokines in the plasma of infected wt and Mif−/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The concentrations of both cytikones were higher in wt compared to Mif−/− mice (Fig. 6B, C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Thrombosis was often associated with vascular inflammatory infiltration in the livers of wt and Mif−/− mice (Fig. 6D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Wt mice had increased numbers of mononuclear cell infiltrates in perivascular areas and scattered at the hepatic parenquima (Fig. 6D, E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>In contrast, infected Mif−/− mice had preserved liver parenquima and reduced mononuclear cell infiltration (Fig. 6D, E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Wt mice presented higher alanine aminotransferase and aspartate aminotransferase plasma concentrations compared to Mif−/− mice, an indication of liver damage and dysfunction (Fig. 6F, G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Moreover, T. gondii DNA levels were similar in wt and Mif−/− mice (Fig. 6H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The findings suggest that T.gondii-induced systemic response is in part dependent on MIF, while parasite replication and dissemination is not affected by MIF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0025259-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025259.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>T. gondii-induced sepsis-like response is partially dependent of MIF. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>(A) Leukocyte counts were determined in peripheral blood at indicated times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>(B) TNF-α and (C) IFN-γ concetrations in the plasma of wt and Mif −/− mice (n = 3–5) 9 dpi were measured by ELISA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>(D) Histopathologycal analysis of the liver at 9 dpi from wt and Mif −/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>(E) Quantitative analysis of liver sections (3 slides/animal) of infected wt and Mif −/− mice mice was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Liver damage was also determined by quantifying serum concentrations of biochemical marker as (F) alanine aminotransferase (ALT), and (G) aspartate aminotransferase (AST). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>(H) Toxo DNA concentration was determined in the liver of wt and Mif −/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>One representative experiment out of six experiments is shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Data of three to five mice/group are given as as means ± SEM and p values were determined by t-test (* p≤0.05, ** p≤0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Cont, control not infected. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0025259.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>In the present study we demonstrated that MIF increases the inflammatory response and tissue damage due to T. gondii oral infection in susceptible C57BL/6 mice. Mif−/− mice had reduced intestinal and systemic inflammation surviving more compared to wt mice, despite of an increase in intestinal parasite burden. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>This reduced inflammatory response in the intestine of Mif−/− mice was associated with decreased expression of inflammatory cytokines and MMP-9 comapared to wt mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Despite of the lower expression of IL-23 compared to wt mice in ileal explants, IL-22 expression was siginificantly increased in Mif−/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The originally local inflammatory response in the small intestine of T. gondii-infected wt mice had systemic repercussions similar to sepsis, including increased plasma concentrations of inflammatory cytokines, leukocytosis and liver damage, all less pronounced in Mif−/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Together, these results indicate that MIF is involved in the response to T. gondii infection of the small intestine, increasing the ileitis and the systemic inflammatory response. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The peroral infection with T. gondii caused a severe ileitis characterized by intestinal shortening, extensive necrosis, blunting of the villi, loss of Peyer's patches and leukocyte infiltration in the lamina propria [1], [7], [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>All these pathological parameters were significantly reduced on Mif−/− compared to wt mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>In natural T. gondii infection, gut-associated inflammatory response resembles that observed in Crohn's ileitis and it has been proposed as a model of IBD [1], [7], [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>An essential role of MIF in experimental colonic inflammation has been demonstrated [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>It has been also shown that MIF controls the production of inflammatory cytokines including TNF-α and IFN-γ involved in the pathogenesis of intestinal inflammation [42] In the present study, using a model of T. gondii-induced ileal inflammation, we demonstrated a critical role of MIF promoting the intestinal inflammatory response and the expression of TNF-α, IL-12 and IFN-γ. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>A recent study showed that during peoral T. gondii infection IL-23 regulates the ileal inflammatory response independent of IL-17 [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>We also observed that upon T. gondii infection IL-23 expression was upregulated in the intestine while IL-17 was reduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The inflammatory role of IL-23 was dependent of increased IL-22 production that in turn promoted the ileal inflammation and tissue damage [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>IL-22, a member of the IL-10 family, is important in epithelial cell homeostasis, in infection and inflammation [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>In toxoplasmic ileitis, the inflammatory response is a result of IL-22 upregulation induced by IL-23 [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>In fact, T. gondii-infected IL-22−/− mice have reduced intestinal inflammation and are more resistant than wt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Unexpectaly, we observed a significant increased of IL-22 expression in Mif −/− mice with reduction of IL-23 and TGF-β. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Others have previously shown increased IL-22 production by T CD4+ lymphocytes in the absence of IL-23 [44], [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Thus our results suggest a previously unrecognized role of MIF inducing IL-23 and inhibiting IL-22 expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Our results also implies a MIF-dependent pathogenic role of IL-22 in T. gondii-induced ileitis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, an anti-inflammatory role of IL-22 in different models of colitis has been previously demonstrated [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Future studies will be importat to define the mechanism by which MIF controls IL-23 and IL-22 expression, and how MIF participates in the pathogenic role of IL-22 on T. gondii-induced intestinal inflammation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>We observed that MIF was essential to T. gondii-induced expression of MMP-9, suggesting that MIF could be involved in tissue remodeling/repair at the small intestine during T. gondii peroral infection by over expressing gelatinase B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Several studies have shown that MIF affects tissue remodeling and the expression of different metalloproteinases [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Previous studies demonstrated an increased expression and enzymatic activity of metalloproteinases in humans and mice with intestinal inflammation [7], [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>MMP-2 and MMP-9 are elevated in the intestine of T. gondii-infected animals, however in these model, C57BL/6 mice lacking MMP-2 but not MMP-9 have reduced immunopathology of the small intestine [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Thus the exact role of the reduced expression of MMP-9 observed on Mif−/− upon T. gondii infection requires further investigations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>During intestinal parasitic infection, reduced anti-inflammatory responses could decrease parasite burden but intensify tissue damage, causing loss of epithelial barrier integrity and increased bacterial translocation [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Our results showed that MIF mediated T. gondii-induced ileitis does not affect IL-4 and increase IL-10 and TGF-β expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The intestinal inflammatory response induced by T. gondii is complex and intestinal homeostasis requires reciprocal control of both Th1 and TGF-β mediated responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Consequently, MIF exacerbation of intestinal inflammatory responses might involve not only increased pro-inflammatory responses but also TGF-β-mediated responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>MIF and TGF-β are involved in fibrotic responses in several conditions due to regulation of MMPs [48], [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Since both cytokines upregulate MMP-9 expression, it is possible that MIF regulates tissue remodeling in T. gondii-induced ileitis through a TGF-β/MMP-9 pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>The reduced inflammatory response and pathological damage in the small intestine of Mif−/− occurred in the context of higher T. gondii burden. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>It has been recently shown in a model of toxoplasmosis induced by intraperitoneal route that MIF is essentially protective [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>In this model of systemic infection, Mif−/− had higher numbers of cysts in the brain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The increased susceptibility of Mif−/− mice systemically infected was related with reduced production of inflammatory cytokines, however these animals, in opposition to our findings, developed increased liver damage compared to wt mice [27]. Mif−/− mice of the Balb/c background are also more susceptible to T. gondii when infected by the oral route, presenting increased lethality and parasite burden in the brain and liver [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Compared to susceptible hosts such as C57BL/6, the infection of Balb/c mice with T. gondii by the oral route causes a less severe intestinal inflammatory response and a disease that tends to become chronic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest that MIF-mediated T. gondii-induced pathological responses might be differently regulated depending on the route and site of infection, and the genetic background of the host. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>We observed that Mif−/− mice had reduced signs of systemic inflammation compared to wt mice when infected by the oral route. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The reduced systemic inflammation of Mif−/− mice was characterized by lower plasma concentrations of TNF-α and IFN-γ, reduced biochemical and histological parameters of liver damage and lower leukocytosis when compared to wt mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Considering the pathogenic roles of TNF-α and IFN-γ in T. gondii oral infection, we postulate that enhancement of systemic inflammatory response is mediated by MIF acting in concert with TNF-α and IFN-γ [2], [4], [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>A deleterious role of MIF was recently observed in a mouse model of lethal dengue virus infection, with reduced systemic inflammatory response in Mif−/− mice compare to wt mice [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Although the molecular mechanisms involved in toxoplasmic ileitis are not completely understood, new evidence indicates that co-factors such as Gram-negative intestinal microflora play a role in T. gondii-induced acute ileitis and systemic inflammation through LPS-induced TLR-4 signaling [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Since MIF up-regulates the expression of TLR-4 [17], it is possible that the reduced inflammatory response observed in Mif−/− mice upon T. gondii might be a result of reduced TLR-4 activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Considering that MIF contributes to IBD even in the absence of TLR-4, it is possible that the effect of MIF on T. gondii pathogenesis occurs independently of its effects on TLR-4 expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, MIF also regulates the expression of TLR-11 [28], considered important in the recognition and response to T. gondii [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>It has been suggest that the reduced expression of TLR-11 in the absence of MIF affects the maturation and activation of dendritic cells consequently hampering a protective immune response to T. gondii [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>It will be important to characterize the role of TLR-4 and TLR-11 in the MIF-dependent small bowel injury caused by T. gondii in susceptible hosts. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, we demonstrated that MIF participates in the pathogenesis of natural T. gondii infection in C57BL/6 mice, promoting an intense ileitis and a robust systemic inflammatory response that resulted in poor outcome during the acute phase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Similar to previous studies, we confirmed a central role of MIF in the control of parasite burden in different models of experimental toxoplasmosis [27], [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Although MIF has been regarded as essential in host protection during T. gondii infection, our findings demonstrated a pathogenic role of MIF in natural T. gondii infection in susceptible hosts by exacerbating IL-12, IFN-γ, TNF-α and IL-23 dependent responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>MIF also plays a role in tissue remodeling possibly by regulating TGF-β induced MMP-9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Thus, we propose that MIF actually exerts a bidirectional role in toxoplasmosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>This dichotomy is dependent on the route of infection and the genetic background of the host, and has been also observed with other pro-inflammatory cytokines [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>In this scenario, MIF seems to compromise host protection by exacerbating intestinal tissue damage and by inducing a sepsis-like response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Previous studies demonstrating a participation of MIF on human T. gondii infection [27], [53], [54] enphasize the importance to understand the diffrential role of MIF on immunity and pathogenesis triggered by T. gondii in distinct tissues. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>We thank Dr. Claudia Paiva (IMPPG, UFRJ, Brazil), Dr. Claudia Benjamin (Department of Pharmacy, UFRJ, Brazil), Steffi CH Hanschke and Dr. João P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Viola (Instituto Nacional do Câncer, RJ, Brazil) for their gifts of reagents and Rosa Arras and Letícia Alves for technical assistance. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Funding: This work was supported by CNPq, FAPERJ and Pronex (Programa de Apoio a Núcleos de Excelência – Pronex/FAPERJ (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.faperj.br/interna.phtml?ctx_cod=1.11">www.faperj.br/interna.phtml?ctx_cod=1.11</ext-link>)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0025259-Liesenfeld1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>1 LiesenfeldO 2002 Oral infection of C57BL/6 mice with Toxoplasma gondii: a new model of inflammatory bowel disease? J Infect Dis 185 S96 101 11865446 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Gazzinelli1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>2 GazzinelliRTWysockaMHienySScharton-KerstenTCheeverA 1996 In the absence of endogenous IL-10, mice acutely infected with Toxoplasma gondii succumb to a lethal immune response dependent on CD4+T cells and accompanied by overproduction of IL-12, IFN-γ, and TNF-α. J Immunol 157 798 805 8752931 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-BuzoniGatel1"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>3 Buzoni-GatelDSchulthessJMenardLCKasperLH 2006 Mucosal defenses against orally acquired protozoan parasites, emphasis on Toxoplasma gondii infections. Cell Microbiol 8 535 544 16548880 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Denkers1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>4 DenkersEYGazzinelliRT 1998 Regulation and function of T-cell-mediated immunity during Toxoplasma gondii infection. Clin Microbiol Rev 11 569 588 9767056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Yap1"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>5 YapGSSherA 1999 Effector cells of both nonhemopoietic and hemopoietic origin are required for interferon (IFN)-gamma and tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-alpha-dependent host resistance to the intracellular pathogen, Toxoplasma gondii. J Exp Med 189 1083 1092 10190899 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Tait1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>6 TaitEDHunterCA 2009 Advances in understanding immunity to Toxoplasma gondii. Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz 104 201 210 19430645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Muoz1"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>7 MuñozMHeimesaatMMDankerKStruckDLohmannU 2009 Interleukin (IL)-23 mediates Toxoplasma gondii-induced immunopathology in the gut via matrixmetalloproteinase-2 and IL-22 but independent of IL-17. J Exp Med 206 3047 3059 19995958 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Mordue1"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>8 MordueDGMonroyFLa ReginaMDinarelloCASibleyLD 2001 Acute toxoplasmosis leads to lethal overproduction of Th1 cytokines. J Immunol 167 4574 4584 11591786 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Mennechet1"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>9 MennechetFJDKasperLHRachinelNLiWVandewalleA 2002 Lamina propria CD4+T lymphocytes synergize with murine intestinal epithelial cells to enhance proinflammatory responses against intracellular pathogen. J Immunol 168 2988 2996 11884471 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Bernhagen1"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>10 BernhagenJCalandraTMitchellRAMartinSBTraceyKJ 1993 MIF is a pituitary-derived cytokine that potentiates lethal endotoxaemia. Nature 365 756 759 8413654 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Bucala1"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>11 BucalaR 1996 MIF rediscovered cytokine, pituitary hormone, and glucocorticoid-induced regulator of the immune response. FASEB J 10 1607 1613 9002552 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Calandra1"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>12 CalandraTJRogerT 2003 Macrophage migration inhibitory factor: a regulator of innate immunity. Nature Rev Immunol 3 791 800 14502271 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Weber1"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>13 WeberCKraemerSDrechslerMLueHKoenenRR 2008 Structural determinants of MIF functions in CXCR2-mediated inflammatory and atherogenic leukocyte recruitment. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 105 16278 16283 18852457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Calandra2"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>14 CalandraTBernhagenJMetzCNSpiegelLABacherM 1995 MIF as a glucocorticoid-induced modulator of cytokine production. Nature 377 68 71 7659164 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Calandra3"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>15 CalandraTBernhagenJMitchellRABucalaR 1994 The macrophage is an important and previously unrecognized source of macrophage migration inhibitory factor. J Exp Med 179 1895 1902 8195715 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Lue1"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>16 LueHKleemannRCalandraTRogerTBernhagenJ 2002 Macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF): mechanism of action and role in disease. Microbes Infect 4 449 460 11932196 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Roger1"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>17 RogerTDavidJGlauserMPCalandraT 2001 MIF regulates innate immune responses through modulation of Toll-like receptor 4. Nature 4414 920 924  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Dunne1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>18 DunneDWShawABockenstedtLKAlloreHGChenS 2010 Increased TLR4 expression and downstream cytokine production in immunosuppressed adults compared to non-immunosuppressed adults. PLoS One 5 e11343 20596538 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Bozza1"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>19 BozzaMSatoskarARLinGLuBHumblesAA 1999 Target disruption of Migration Inhibitory Factor gene reveals its critical role in sepsis. J Exp Med 189 341 346 9892616 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-DeJong1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>20 De JongYPAbadia-MolinaACSatoskarARClarkeKRietdijkST 2001 Development of chronic colitis is dependent on the cytokine MIF. Nature Immunol 2 1061 066 11668338 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Satoskar1"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>21 SatoskarARBozzaMRodriguez-SosaMLinGDavidJR 2001 Migration-Inhibitory gene deficient mice are susceptible to cutaneous Leishmania major infection. Infect Immun 69 1247 1254  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Magalhes1"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>22 MagalhãesESMourao-SaDSVieira-de-AbreuAFigueiredoRTPiresAL 2007 Macrophage migration inhibitory factor is essential for allergic asthma but not for Th2 differentiation. Eur J Immunol 37 1097 1106 17373669 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Paiva1"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>23 PaivaCNArrasRHMagalhãesESAlvesLSLessaLP 2009 Migration inhibitory factor (MIF) released by macrophages upon recognition of immune complexes is critical to inflammation in Arthus reaction. J Leukoc Biol 85 855 861 19188484 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-McDevitt1"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>24 McDevittMAXieJShanmugasundaramGGriffithJLiuA 2006 Critical role for the host mediator macrophage migration inhibitory factor in the pathogenesis of malarial anemia. J Exp Med 193 1 12  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Magalhes2"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>25 MagalhãesESPaivaCNSouzaHSPyrrhoASMourão-SáD 2009 Macrophage migration inhibitory factor is critical to interleukin-5-driven eosinophilopoiesis and tissue eosinophilia triggered by Schistosoma mansoni infection. FASEB J 23 1262 1271 19088181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Reyes1"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>26 ReyesJLTerrazasLIEspinozaBCruz-RoblesDSotoV 2006 Macrophage migration inhibitory factor contributes to host defense against acute Trypanosoma cruzi infection. Infect Immun 72 3571 3576  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Flores1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>27 FloresMSaavedraRBautistaRViedmaRTenorioEP 2008 Macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF) is critical for the host resistance against Toxoplasma gondii. FASEB J 22 3661 3671 18606868 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Terrazas1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>28 TerrazasCAJuarezITerrazasLISaavedraRCallejaEA 2010  Toxoplasma gondii: Impaired maturation and pro-inflammatory response of dendritic cells in MIF deficient mice favors susceptibility to infection. Exp Parasitol 126 348 358 20331989 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Liesenfeld2"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>29 LiesenfeldOKosekJRemingtonJSSuzukiY 1996 Association of CD4+ Tcell-dependent interferon γ mediated necrosis of the small intestine with genetic susceptibility of mice to per oral infection with Toxoplasma gondii. J Exp Med 184 597 607 8760813 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Liesenfeld3"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>30 LiesenfeldOKangHParkDNguyenTAParkheC 1999 TNF-α, nitric oxide and IFN-γ are all critical for development of necrosis in small intestine and early mortality in genetically susceptible mice infected per orally with Toxoplasma gondii. Parasite Immun 21 365 376  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Suzuki1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>31 SuzukiYSherAYapGParkDNeyerLE 2000 IL-10 is required for prevention of necrosis in the small intestine and mortality in both genetically resistant BALB/c and susceptible C57BL/6 mice following per oral infection with Toxoplasma gondii. J Immunol 164 5375 5382 10799901 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Reischl1"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>32 ReischlUBretagneSKrugerDErnaultPCostaJM 2003 Comparison of two DNA targets for the diagnosis of Toxoplasmosis by real-time PCR using fluorescence resonance energy transfer hybridization probes. BMC Infect Dis 3 7 12729464 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-KompalicCristo1"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>33 Kompalic-CristoAFrottaCSuárez-MutisMFernandesOBrittoC 2007 Evaluation of a real-time PCR assay based on the repetitive B1 gene for the detection of Toxoplasma gondii in human peripheral blood. Parasitol Res 101 619 625 17385062 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Heimesaat1"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>34 HeimesaatMMBereswillSFischerANiebergallJFreudenbergM 2006 Gram-negative bacteria aggravate murine small intestinal Th-1 type immunopathology following oral infection with Toxoplasma gondii. J Immunol 177 8785 8795 17142781 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Livak1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>35 LivakKJSchmittgenTD 2001 Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C (T)). Method Methods 25 402 408 11846609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Roberts1"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>36 RobertsCWFergusonDJJebbariHSatoskarABluethmannHAlexanderJ 1996 Different roles for interleukin-4 during the course of Toxoplasma gondii infection. Infect Immun 64 897 904 8641798 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Nickdel1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>37 NickdelMBLyonsRERobertsFBrombacherFHunterCA 2004 Intestinal pathology during acute toxoplasmosis is IL-4 dependent and unrelated to parasite burden. Parasite Immunol 26 75 82 15225294 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Neves1"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>38 NevesESBicudoLNCuriALCarregalEBuenoWF 2009 Acute acquired toxoplasmosis: clinical-laboratorial aspects and ophthalmologic evaluation in a cohort of immunocompetent patients. Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz 104 2 393 6 19430671 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Pakozdi1"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>39 PakozdiAAminMAHaasCSMartinezRJHainesGK3rd 2006 Macrophage migration inhibitory factor: a mediator of matrix metalloproteinase-2 production in rheumatoid arthritis. Arthritis Res Ther 8 1 14  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-AssunoMiranda1"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>40 Assunção-MirandaIBozzaMTDa PoianAT 2010 Pro-inflammatory response resulting from sindbis virus infection of human macrophages: implications for the pathogenesis of viral arthritis. J Med Virol 82 164 174 19950249 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Munoz1"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>41 MunozMLiesenfeldOHeimesaatMM 2011 Immunology of Toxoplasma gondii. Immunol Rev 240 269 285 21349099 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Ohkawara1"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>42 OhkawaraTNishihiraJIshiguroY 2006 Resistance to experimental colitis depends on cytoprotective heat shock proteins in macrophage migration inhibitory factor null mice. Immunol Lett 107 148 154 17049622 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Aujla1"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>43 AujlaSJKollsJK 2009 IL-22: a critical mediator in mucosal host defense. J Mol Med 87 451 454 19219418 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Ramirez1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>44 RamirezJMBrembillaNCSorgOChicheporticheRMatthesT 2010 Activation of the aryl hydrocarbon receptor reveals distinct requirements for IL-22 and IL-17 production by human T helper cells. Eur J Immunol 40 2450 2459 20706985 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Brembilla1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>45 BrembillaNCRamirezJMChicheporticheRSorgOSauratJH 2011 In vivo dioxin favors interleukin-22 production by human CD4+ T cells in an aryl hydrocarbon receptor (AhR)-dependent manner. PLoS One 6 e18741 21525997 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Monteleone1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>46 MonteleoneIRizzoASarraMSicaGSileriP 2011 Aryl Hydrocarbon Receptor-Induced Signals Up-regulate IL-22 Production and Inhibit Inflammation in the Gastrointestinal Tract. Gastroenterology 141 237 248 21600206 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Garg1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>47 GargPVijay-KumarMWangLGewirtzATMerlinD 2009 Matrix metalloproteinase-9-mediated tissue injury overrides the protective effect of matrix metalloproteinase-2 during colitis. Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol 296 G175 184 19171847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Chou1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>48 ChouYTWangHChenYDanielpourDYangYC 2006 Cited2 modulates TGF-beta-mediated upregulation of MMP9. Oncogene 25 5547 5560 16619037 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-He1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>49 HeXXChenKYangJLiXYGanHY 2009 Macrophage migration inhibitory factor promotes colorectal cancer. Mol Med 15 1 10 19009023 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-AssunoMiranda2"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>50 Assunção-MirandaIAmaralFABozzaFAFagundesCTSousaLP 2010 Contribution of macrophage migration inhibitory factor to the pathogenesis of dengue virus infection. FASEB J 24 218 228 19776337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Heimesaat2"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>51 HeimesaatMMFischerAJahnHKNiebergallJFreudenbergM 2007 Exacerbation of murine ileitis by Toll-like receptor 4 mediated sensing of lipopolysaccharide from commensal Escherichia coli. Gut 56 941 948 17255219 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Yarovinsky1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>52 YarovinskyFZhangDAndersenJFBannenbergGLSerhanCN 2005 TLR-11 activation of dendritic cells by a protozoan profilin-like protein. Science 308 1626 1629 15860593 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-Ferro1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>53 FerroEAMineoJRIettaFBechiNRomagnoliR 2008 Macrophage migration inhibitory factor is up-regulated in human first-trimester placenta stimulated by soluble antigen of Toxoplasma gondii, resulting in increased monocyte adhesion on villous explants. Am J Pathol 172 50 58 18165264 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0025259-deOliveiraGomes1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>54 de Oliveira GomesAde Oliveira SilvaDASilvaNMde Freitas BarbosaBFrancoPS 2011 Effect of macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF) in human placental explants infected with Toxoplasma gondii depends on gestational age. Am J Pathol 178 2792 2801 21641401 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
