
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biochem J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biochem. J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">bic</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Biochemical Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0264-6021</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-8728</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Portland Press Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3924758</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">BJ20131405</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BJ20131405</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The inhibition of functional expression of calcium channels by prion protein demonstrates competition with α2δ for GPI-anchoring pathways </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">Functional interaction between prion protein and α<sub>2</sub>δ</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">A. Alvarez-Laviada and others</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarez-Laviada</surname><given-names>Anita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kadurin</surname><given-names>Ivan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Senatore</surname><given-names>Assunta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chiesa</surname><given-names>Roberto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dolphin</surname><given-names>Annette C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="A1">*Department of Neuroscience, Physiology and Pharmacology, University College London, London WC1E 6BT, U.K.</aff><aff id="A2">†Dulbecco Telethon Institute c/o Department of Neuroscience, IRCCS–Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche “Mario Negri”, Milano, Italy</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="fn1" fn-type="present-address"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>1Present address: National Heart &amp; Lung Institute, Imperial College London, London W12 0NN, U.K. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="fn2" fn-type="present-address"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>2Present address: Institute of Neuropathology, Universitätsspitäl Zürich, Schmelzbergstrasse 12, CH-8091 Zürich, Switzerland </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><corresp id="COR1"><sup>3</sup>To whom correspondence should be addressed (email <email>a.dolphin@ucl.ac.uk</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epreprint"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>458</volume><issue>Pt 2</issue><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 The author(s) has paid for this article to be freely available under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Licence (CC-BY)(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/) which permits unrestricted use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>It has been shown recently that PrP (prion protein) and the calcium channel auxiliary α2δ subunits interact in neurons and expression systems [Senatore, Colleoni, Verderio, Restelli, Morini, Condliffe, Bertani, Mantovani, Canovi, Micotti, Forloni, Dolphin, Matteoli, Gobbi and Chiesa (2012) Neuron 74, 300–313]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>In the present study we examined whether there was an effect of PrP on calcium currents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We have shown that when PrP is co-expressed with calcium channels formed from CaV2.1/β and α2δ-1 or α2δ-2, there is a consistent decrease in calcium current density. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>This reduction was absent when a PrP construct was used lacking its GPI (glycosylphosphatidylinositol) anchor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We have reported previously that α2δ subunits are able to form GPI-anchored proteins [Davies, Kadurin, Alvarez-Laviada, Douglas, Nieto-Rostro, Bauer, Pratt and Dolphin (2010) Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>U.S.A. 107, 1654–1659] and show further evidence in the present paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>We have characterized recently a C-terminally truncated α2δ-1 construct, α2δ-1ΔC, and found that, despite loss of its membrane anchor, it still shows a partial ability to increase calcium currents [Kadurin, Alvarez-Laviada, Ng, Walker-Gray, D’Arco, Fadel, Pratt and Dolphin (2012) J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Chem. 1287, 33554–33566]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>We now find that PrP does not inhibit CaV2.1/β currents formed with α2δ-1ΔC, rather than α2δ-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>It is possible that PrP and α2δ-1 compete for GPI-anchor intermediates or trafficking pathways, or that interaction between PrP and α2δ-1 requires association in cholesterol-rich membrane microdomains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Our additional finding that CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1 currents were inhibited by GPI–GFP, but not cytosolic GFP, indicates that competition for limited GPI-anchor intermediates or trafficking pathways may be involved in PrP suppression of α2δ subunit function. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="short"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>PrP, but not GPI-anchorless PrP, suppresses CaV2.1/β/α2δ-1 or α2δ-2 calcium channel currents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>However, PrP does not inhibit CaV2.1/β currents formed with anchorless α2δ-1, rather than full-length α2δ-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The results of the present study suggest that α2δ subunits and PrP may compete for GPI-anchor pathways. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group kwd-group-type="kwd"><kwd>α<sub>2</sub>δ</kwd><kwd>auxiliary subunit</kwd><kwd>calcium channel</kwd><kwd>GPI anchor</kwd><kwd>prion protein</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><kwd-group kwd-group-type="abbr"><kwd>Ca<sub>V</sub>, voltage-gated Ca<sup>2+</sup></kwd><kwd>DRM, detergent-resistant membrane</kwd><kwd>GPI, glycosylphosphatidylinositol</kwd><kwd>HA, haemagglutinin</kwd><kwd>KO, knockout</kwd><kwd>MBS, Mes-buffered saline</kwd><kwd>PI-PLC, phosphatidylinositol-specific phospholipase C</kwd><kwd>PNGase F, peptide N-glycosidase F</kwd><kwd>PrP, prion protein</kwd><kwd>PrP<sup>C</sup>, normal cellular PrP</kwd><kwd>PrP<sup>Sc</sup>, PrP scrapie</kwd><kwd>WT, wild-type</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><ref-count count="53"/><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>CaV (voltage-gated Ca2+) channels contain a pore-forming α1 subunit, which determines the main properties, both biophysical and pharmacological, of the channels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>For the CaV1 and CaV2 subfamilies, the α1 subunit is associated with a membrane-anchored predominantly extracellular α2δ subunit (for a review, see [1]) and a cytoplasmic β subunit (for reviews, see [2,3]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The β subunits have been shown to enhance calcium channel trafficking by binding to the I–II linker of the α1 subunits [4,5], and thus inhibiting proteasomal decay as has been shown for the CaV2.2 [6] and CaV1.2 [7] channels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the mechanism of enhancement of the CaV channel functional expression by α2δ subunits has not been firmly established, although we have found that it involves their von Willebrand Factor A domain [8], and results in increased plasma membrane expression and active zone targeting of the channel complex [8,9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The major mechanism whereby α2δ subunits increase the functional expression of calcium channels is due to an increase in the amount of channel protein at the plasma membrane ([8,10] and J.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Cassidy and A.C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Dolphin, unpublished work). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, it has been found that the α2δ subunits do not increase single channel conductance or open probability [11,12], two other mechanisms whereby macroscopic current could be increased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, there are effects of α2δ subunits to increase voltage-dependent inactivation and to hyperpolarize the voltage-dependence of steady-state inactivation, providing evidence that these subunits do remain associated with the functional channel complex on the plasma membrane [8,13,14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Mammalian genes encoding four α2δ subunits have been identified (for reviews, see [3,15]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The topology of the α2δ protein was first determined for α2δ-1, and is thought to generalize to all four α2δ subunits (for reviews, see [1,16]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>They all have predicted N-terminal signal sequences, indicating that the N-terminus is extracellular. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The α2 and δ subunits are the product of a single gene, encoding the α2δ pre-protein, which is post-translationally cleaved into α2 and δ [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The extracellular α2 subunit then remains disulfide-bonded to the membrane-bound δ subunit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Although α2δ subunits were originally described as transmembrane proteins, we have shown previously that they can form GPI (glycosylphosphatidylinositol)-anchored proteins [13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The PrPC [normal cellular PrP (prion protein)] is a GPI-anchored sialoglycoprotein [18] exposed on the outer leaflet of the plasma membrane, that is widely distributed throughout the nervous system [19,20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Its normal physiological function is still being elucidated [20] and genetic ablation of PrP KO (knockout) only produces subtle phenotypes in mice [21,22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>However, it appears to play a role in signal transduction [23], copper binding [24], synaptic function [25] and myelin maintenance [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, misfolding of PrPC results in the formation of the partially protease-resistant isoform PrPSc (PrP scrapie), which accumulates in the brain and results in neurodegeneration, giving rise to Creutzfeldt–Jakob disease [19,27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>PrPSc is both neurotoxic and infectious. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>In the absence of PrPC, PrPSc cannot be generated and PrP-null mice do not propagate infectivity or develop pathology on infection with PrPSc [28–30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Thus it has been postulated that the presence of PrPC in neurons is essential for the initiation of a cascade of signalling events leading to prion disease pathology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Initial evidence that the α2δ subunits are closely associated with PrP came from the finding that the α2δ-1, α2δ-2 and α2δ-3 subunits were co-immunopurified with PrP from the brains of transgenic mice expressing Myc-tagged PrP [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The α2δ subunits are expressed strongly in cholesterol-rich detergent-resistant membranes [13,32], as is PrP [33,34], which may represent the basis for their association. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>It has been shown recently that α2δ-1 and PrP can co-immunoprecipitate from both brain tissue and cell lines [35], and that the interaction between pathogenic mutant PrP and α2δ-1 results in the intracellular retention of both species [35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>We were interested to determine whether PrP co-expression has any direct effect on calcium channel currents via a direct or indirect effect on α2δ subunit processing or function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>We therefore utilized full-length and C-terminally truncated PrP and α2δ-1 to examine the effect of these species on calcium channel functional expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Heterologous expression of cDNAs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The calcium channel cDNAs used were rat CaV2.1 (GenBank® accession number M64373), mouse α2δ-2 (GenBank® accession number AF247139), rat α2δ-1 (GenBank® accession number M86621), α2δ-1 mid HA (haemagglutinin) [36], α2δ-1ΔC–HA [36], rat β4 (GenBank® accession number NM001105733) and rat β1b [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The PrP constructs used (in pcDNA3) were WT (wild-type) PrP (mouse) and ΔGPI–PrP [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The GFP constructs used were mut3 GFP [39] and GPI–GFP in pcDNA3 [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The cDNAs were in the pMT2 expression vector, unless stated above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Mammalian tsA-201 cells were transfected with the following cDNA combinations (Cav2.1/β1b/α2δ-1/PrP at 3:2:2:0.5 or Cav2.1/β4/α2δ-2/PrP at 3:2:2:1), with empty vector replacing constructs not used unless otherwise stated, and transfection was performed as described previously [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The cDNA for GFP was also included to identify transfected cells from which electrophysiological recordings and imaging were performed, unless GPI–GFP was used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Mice </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Cerebella were obtained from C57BL/6J (WT) mice or from Tg(WT-E1) mice expressing WT mouse PrP with an epitope for the monoclonal antibody 3F4 at approximately 4-fold the endogenous PrP level, referred to throughout the text as PrP Tg(WT) [42], or from PrP-KO mice with a pure C57BL/6J background (European Mouse Mutant Archive, Monterotondo, Rome; EM:01723) [21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Preparation of Triton X-100-insoluble membrane fractions [DRMs (detergent-resistant membrane)] </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>All steps were performed on ice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>One cerebellum was used as the starting material from WT, PrP Tg(WT) and PrP-KO mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The cerebella were homogenized using a Teflon homogenizer in MBS [Mes-buffered saline; 25 mM Mes (pH 6.5), 150 mM NaCl and Complete™ protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche)], containing 1% (v/v) Triton X-100 (Thermo Scientific), and left on ice for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>An equal volume of 90% (w/v) sucrose in MBS was then added. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The sample was transferred into a 13 ml ultracentrifuge tube and overlaid with 10 ml of discontinuous sucrose gradient, consisting of 35% (w/v) sucrose in MBS (5 ml) and 5% (w/v) sucrose in MBS (5 ml). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The sucrose gradients were centrifuged at 138000 g for 18 h at 4°C (Beckman SW40 rotor). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Fractions (1 ml) were subsequently harvested from the top to the bottom of the tube. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>When necessary, protein fractions from the gradient were washed free of sucrose by dilution in 25 volumes of ice-cold PBS and ultracentrifugation (150000 g for 1 h at 4°C) to pellet the cholesterol-enriched microdomain material. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Triton X-100-insoluble protein was resuspended in deglycosylation buffer and treated with PNGase F (peptide N-glycosidase F; Roche), as described below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Treatment of Triton X-100-insoluble protein fractions with PI-PLC (phosphatidylinositol-specific phospholipase C) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Triton X-100-insoluble fractions from brain tissue were collected, washed free of sucrose and centrifuged as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The resultant pellet of Triton X-100-insoluble material was resuspended in an appropriate volume of PI-PLC reaction buffer [10 mM Tris/HCl (pH 7.4) and 150 mM NaCl containing Complete™ protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche)], to a final protein concentration of ~2 mg/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The samples were sonicated and treated with 25 units of PI-PLC enzyme (Sigma) for 3 h at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Phase separation of PI-PLC-treated proteins using Triton X-114 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Membrane-associated proteins were separated from soluble proteins in two phases of Triton X-114 as described previously [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Briefly, the pellet of detergent-insoluble material was resuspended in an appropriate volume of reaction buffer (final concentration of ~2 mg/ml of protein) and incubated with PI-PLC as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Control experiments omitting the enzyme were also performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>After PI-PLC incubation the samples were supplemented with Triton X-114 (Thermo Scientific) to a final concentration of 1%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>A cushion of 6% (w/v) sucrose, 10 mM Tris/HCl (pH 7.4), 150 mM NaCl and 0.06% Triton X-114 was placed at the bottom of a 1.5 ml Eppendorf tube. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The protein sample was then overlaid on this sucrose cushion and the tube incubated for 3 min at 30°C and centrifuged at 300 g for 4 min at room temperature (20°C) in a swinging bucket rotor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Following centrifugation, the detergent phase was present as an oily droplet at the bottom of the tube. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Fresh Triton X-114 was then added to the upper aqueous phase to 0.5% and the procedure was repeated using the same sucrose cushion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>In the last step the aqueous phase was removed from the cushion, supplemented with fresh Triton X-114 to 2% and subjected to another centrifugation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The detergent phase of this last procedure was discarded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The aqueous and detergent phases from this procedure were adjusted to the equal volume with 10 mM Tris/HCl (pH 7.4) and 150 mM NaCl plus protease inhibitors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Acetone precipitation and PNGase F deglycosylation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>To remove the remaining Triton X-114 in the detergent and aqueous phases from the phase separation experiment the proteins were precipitated by the addition of 4 volumes of ice-cold acetone and subsequent incubation for 1 h at −20°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The precipitated material was centrifuged at 16000 g for 10 min and the pellet was washed once with an acetone/water (4:1) mixture (−20°C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The pellets of the precipitated proteins were then resuspended in 45 μl of PNGase F buffer [10 mM Tris/HCl (pH 7.5) and 150 mM NaCl supplemented with 75 mM 2-mercaptoethanol, 0.5% Triton X-100, 0.1% SDS and protease inhibitors]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>A total of 1 unit of PNGase F was added per 10 μl volume followed by incubation at 37°C for 5–12 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The samples were then resuspended in an appropriate volume of SDS gel loading buffer and heated for 10 min at 56°C in order to terminate the reaction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Immunoblotting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Western blotting was performed as described previously [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The samples were resolved on either 3–8% Tris/acetate or 4–12% Bis-Tris gels with the relevant buffer systems (Life Technologies). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The samples were then blotted on to PVDF membranes (Bio-Rad Laboratories), blocked with 3% BSA in TBS provided with 0.5% Igepal and incubated with the following primary antibodies: anti-α2-1 (1:1000 dilution; mouse monoclonal; Sigma), anti-α2-2 (residues 102–117; rabbit polyclonal; [44]), anti-PrP (3F4 epitope), anti-PrP (residues 45–66; rabbit polyclonal; [45]) and anti-flotillin-1 (1:2000 dilution; mouse monoclonal; BD Biosciences). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The secondary antibodies used were goat anti-mouse and goat anti-rabbit coupled to HRP (horseradish peroxidase; Bio-Rad Laboratories). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Electrophysiology </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Calcium channel expression in tsA-201 cells was investigated by whole-cell patch-clamp recording essentially as described previously [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The internal (pipette) and external solutions and recording techniques were similar to those described previously [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The patch pipette solution contained: 140 mM caesium aspartate, 5 mM EGTA, 2 mM MgCl2, 0.1 mM CaCl2, 2 mM K2-ATP and 10 mM Hepes, pH 7.2 at 310 mM mOsm, with sucrose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The external solution for recording Ba2+ currents contained: 150 mM tetraethylammonium Br, 3 mM KCl, 1 mM NaHCO3, 1 mM MgCl2, 10 mM Hepes, 4 mM glucose and 1 mM BaCl2, pH 7.4 at 320 mOsm, with sucrose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Pipettes of resistance 2–4 MΩ were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>An Axopatch 1D amplifier (Axon Instruments) was used, and data were filtered at 1–2 kHz and digitized at 5–10 kHz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Current records were subjected to leak and residual capacitance current subtraction (P/8 protocol). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Analysis was performed using Pclamp 9 (Molecular Devices) and Origin 7 (Microcal Origin). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>All comparisons between different groups of transfected cells were performed in parallel on the same experimental days. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>When stated, current–voltage (I–V) plots were fit with a modified Boltzmann equation for determination of the voltage for 50% activation (V50, activation) [48], and steady-state inactivation curves were fit with a single Boltzmann function for determination of the voltage for 50% inactivation (V50, inactivation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Where data are given as means±S.E.M., statistical comparisons were performed using either Student's t test or ANOVA with the appropriate post-hoc test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Xenopus oocytes were prepared, injected and utilized for electrophysiology as described previously [49], with the following exceptions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Plasmid cDNAs for the calcium channel α1, α2δ-1 and β1b subunits and for PrP were mixed at 2:1:2:x ratios at 1 μg/μl, where x=2, 1 or 0.5 unless otherwise stated, and the empty vector was included to maintain the total cDNA mixture constant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>A 9 nl volume was injected intranuclearly, after 2-fold dilution of the cDNA mixtures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Recordings in Xenopus oocytes were performed at 18°C as described previously [48], and all recordings were performed 48–60 h after injection for CaV2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The Ba2+ concentration was 10 mM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>α2δ subunits and PrP show similar biochemical properties </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>We have shown previously that endogenous α2δ-1 and α2δ-2 are strongly expressed in DRM fractions [13,32], as is PrP [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Therefore we prepared DRM fractions from the cerebella of WT, PrP Tg(WT) and PrP-KO mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>We found the typical localization of α2δ-1, α2δ-2 and also PrP in DRMs (Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>PI-PLC treatment and phase separation of α2δ-1, α2δ-2 and PrP in mouse cerebella </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>(A) DRM fractions from WT (left-hand panel), PrP Tg(WT) (middle panel) and PrP KO (right-hand panel) mouse cerebella were prepared as described in the Materials and methods section. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Aliquots were resolved on 3–8% Tris/acetate (to resolve α2δs) or 4–12% Bis-Tris gels (to resolve PrP in the same samples), and analysed by Western blotting (WB) with relevant antibodies as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The full profile is not shown, but only the fractions of the sucrose gradient corresponding to DRMs identified by the presence of flotillin-1 (fractions 4–7 harvested from the top). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The anti-α2δ-1 and anti-α2δ-2 antibodies recognize the α2-1 and α2-2 moieties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>(B) Aliquots of concentrated DRM fractions from WT (left-hand panel), PrP Tg(WT) (middle panel) and PrP KO (right-hand panel) cerebella were treated with PNGase F and analysed by Western blotting with the indicated antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>(C) DRM fractions analysed in (A) were subjected to PI-PLC treatment and Triton X-114 phase separation (see the Materials and methods section), followed by PNGase F deglycosylation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The proteins remaining in the aqueous (aq) and detergent (det) phase were then resolved on 4–12% Bis-Tris gels and analysed with the indicated antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Lanes 1 and 2 in each panel are from detergent phase fractions, whereas lanes 3 and 4 are from the respective aqueous phase, treated or not with PI-PLC as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>(D) The PrP Tg(WT) fractions from (C, middle panel) were also blotted for PrP using the 3F4 antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Molecular mass is shown on the right-hand side of the gels in kDa. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bj2013-1405i001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>It is well-established that PrP is GPI-anchored [18], and our previous findings indicate that the α2δ subunits can form GPI-anchored proteins [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>One important piece of evidence supporting this premise is that following PI-PLC treatment, both endogenous α2δ subunits from the rat brain and heterologously expressed α2δ proteins redistribute from the detergent phase into the aqueous phase upon Triton X-114 phase separation [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>This demonstrates that PI-PLC treatment has converted the protein into a hydrophilic species, most probably by removing the bulky hydrophobic GPI anchor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>To assess if the behaviour of α2δ proteins in this phase-separation assay was affected by the presence or absence of PrP, we concentrated the DRM fractions enriched in both PrP and α2δ and subjected them to PI-PLC treatment as described previously [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>An aliquot of the initial DRM material from the three mouse genotypes, before PI-PLC treatment, was deglycosylated with PNGase F to demonstrate the presence of α2δ-1 and α2δ-2 (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>PI-PLC treatment caused α2δ-1 and α2δ-2 to redistribute into the aqueous phase upon Triton X-114 phase separation in all three of the mouse genotypes tested (Figure 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>As a control, the PrP Tg(WT) samples were also blotted for PrP, and redistributed similarly upon PI-PLC treatment (Figure 1D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Importantly, the response of α2δ-1 and α2δ-2 to PI-PLC treatment was not affected by the absence of PrP, in the PrP KO cerebellar material (Figure 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>It was also not affected by the overexpression of PrP in the PrP Tg(WT) cerebellar material (Figure 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>These data indicate that although PrP has been reported to interact with α2δ subunits [35], interaction with PrP was not responsible for the presence of α2δ subunits in DRM fractions or their redistribution into the aqueous phase following PI-PLC cleavage of GPI-anchor sites. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Co-expression of PrP decreased calcium channel currents containing CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>We then examined whether PrP would influence the ability of α2δ to increase calcium channel currents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>We expressed CaV2.1/β4 and α2δ-2 to mimic the calcium channel combination present in cerebellar Purkinje cells, either with or without PrP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>We found that PrP co-expression produced a moderate, but consistent, reduction in peak calcium channel currents at +10 mV of approximately 34%, although the currents in the presence of PrP and α2δ remained significantly larger than those in the absence of α2δ (Figures 2A–2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The voltage-dependence of activation of the CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2 currents in the presence of PrP was also significantly depolarized, compared with in its absence, although not to the same extent as in the absence of α2δ (Figure 2D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the voltage-dependence of steady-state inactivation of CaV2.2/β4/α2δ-2 was depolarized significantly in the additional presence of PrP (Figures 2E and 2F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>All these effects are indicative of a reduced enhancement by α2δ-2 of CaV2.1/β4 calcium channel currents when PrP was co-expressed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Effect of PrP on CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2 calcium channel currents </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>(A) Current–voltage (I–V) relationships for IBa recorded from tsA-201 cells expressing CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2 (■; n=25), CaV2.1/β4 alone (○; n=7) and CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2/WT PrP (△; n=23). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The ratio of cDNAs used for transfection for CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2/WT-PrP was 3:2:2:1, with empty vector used where α2δ or PrP was absent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>(B) Examples of families of IBa current traces resulting from step potentials from −100 mV to between −30 and +15 mV in 5 mV increments for CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2 (top panel), CaV2.1/β4 alone (middle panel) and CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2/WT PrP (bottom panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>(C) Individual peak IBa currents at +10 mV, expressed as the mean±S.E.M. percentage of the control condition with WT α2δ-2 and CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2 (■; n=25), CaV2.1/β4 alone (○; n=7) and CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2/WT PrP (△; n=23). **P&lt;0.01 and ***P&lt;0.001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>(D) Voltage-dependence of activation (V50 activation) determined by fitting a modified Boltzmann function to the individual I–V relationships shown in (A) for CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2 (black bar), CaV2.1/β4 alone (white bar) and CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2/WT PrP (grey bar). *P&lt;0.05 and **P&lt;0.01. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>(E) Steady-state inactivation curves for IBa recorded from cells expressing CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2 (■; n=12), CaV2.1/β4 alone (○; n=4) and CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2/WT PrP (△; n=8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>(F) Voltage-dependence of steady-state inactivation (V50 inactivation) determined by fitting a Boltzmann function to the individual steady-state inactivation relationships for the data shown in (E); CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2 (black bar), CaV2.1/β4 alone (white bar) and CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2/WT PrP (grey bar). **P&lt;0.01; NS, not significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>All statistical differences were determined by one-way ANOVA and Dunnett's multiple comparison test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bj2013-1405i002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Co-expression of PrP decreased calcium channel currents containing CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>We then examined whether PrP would also inhibit calcium channel combinations containing α2δ-1, and tested whether any effect could be due to the demonstrated interaction at the level of the two polypeptides [35] or a result of lipid anchoring and co-localization in the same cholesterol-rich microdomains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>We therefore expressed CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1 with either WT PrP or anchorless PrP, truncated at the GPI-anchor site (ΔGPI–PrP) [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>We observed that co-expression with WT PrP reduced the peak calcium channel currents to a similar extent (39%) to that shown for the CaV2.1/β4/α2δ-2 combination (Figures 3A–3C), whereas ΔGPI–PrP had no effect on the CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1 calcium channel currents (Figures 3A–3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>In these experiments WT PrP did not produce a significant depolarization of the voltage-dependence of activation of the currents (Figure 3D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Effect of PrP constructs on CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1 calcium channel currents </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>(A) Examples of families of IBa current traces resulting from step potentials from −90 mV to between −30 and +10 mV in 5 mV steps for CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1 alone (top panel) with WT PrP (middle panel) or with ΔGPI–PrP (bottom panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The ratio of cDNAs used for the transfection of CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1/PrP was 3:2:2:1, with empty vector used where α2δ or PrP was absent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>(B) I–V relationships for IBa recorded from tsA-201 cells expressing CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1 alone (■; n=28) with WT PrP (▲; n=19) or with ΔGPI–PrP (△; n=13). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>(C) Individual mean±S.E.M. peak IBa currents at +5 mV for CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1 alone (■; n=28) with WT PrP (▲; n=19) or ΔGPI–PrP (△; n=13). **P&lt;0.01. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>(D) V50 activation for CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1 alone (black bar) with WT PrP (white bar) or with ΔGPI–PrP (grey bar). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>All statistical differences were determined by one-way ANOVA and Dunnett's multiple comparison test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>(E and F) CaV2.2/β1b/α2δ-1 was expressed in Xenopus oocytes either alone or together with PrP at the ratios shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>(E) Representative current traces elicited by steps to test potentials between −25 and +10 mV in 5 mV steps from a holding potential of −100 mV for CaV2.2/β1b/α2δ-1/PrP (1:0.25; upper panel) or CaV2.2/β1b/α2δ-1/PrP (1:1; lower panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The residual voltage clamp transients have been truncated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>(F) Peak currents measured at +10 mV for three α2δ-1/PrP ratios plotted as the mean±S.E.M. percentage of the mean control IBa recorded in the absence of PrP in the same experiment. α2δ-1/PrP 1:1 (black bar; n=6), α2δ-1/PrP ratio 1:0.5 (grey bar; n=18), α2δ-1/PrP ratio 1:0.25 (white bar; n=20) and mean normalized control for α2δ-1 in the absence of PrP (hatched bar; n=21). *P=0.016 between the individual conditions and their respective control condition performed in the same experiment as determined by Student's t test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bj2013-1405i003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>In another expression system, Xenopus oocytes with microinjected cDNAs and where the ratio of the different constructs can be controlled accurately, the effect of PrP to reduce CaV2.2/β1b/α2δ-1 calcium channel currents was observed at an α2δ-1/PrP ratio of 1:1, but not at 2:1 or 4:1 (Figures 3E and 3F), indicating that it was dependent on the amount of PrP expressed relative to α2δ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results suggest that the effect of PrP to reduce calcium channel currents is concentration-dependent, and the presence of a GPI anchor on PrP may be essential for the observed reduction in the functional expression of calcium currents. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Membrane anchoring of both PrP and α2δ-1 is required for calcium channel current inhibition by PrP </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>In order to test the importance of membrane anchoring of both α2δ-1 and PrP on the inhibition by PrP we expressed CaV2.1/β1b with either WT α2δ-1 or anchorless α2δ-1 (α2δ-1ΔC–HA), together with either WT PrP or anchorless PrP truncated at the GPI-anchor site (ΔGPI–PrP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>We have shown previously that an anchorless form of α2δ-1, although being mainly secreted, is still able to promote an increase in calcium channel currents compared with no α2δ, although to a smaller extent than WT α2δ-1 [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>In the present study we obtained the surprising result, shown in Figures 4(A)–4(C), that, whereas WT PrP inhibited calcium channel currents in the presence of WT α2δ-1, it did not produce any reduction in the presence of anchorless α2δ-1ΔC–HA (Figure 4C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>In agreement with the data shown in Figure 3, ΔGPI–PrP did not produce any inhibition of calcium channel currents formed with WT α2δ-1 (Figure 4C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Similarly ΔGPI–PrP did not produce any reduction in the currents formed with anchorless α2δ-1ΔC–HA (Figure 4C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>We found from Western blotting that the WT and truncated α2δ and PrP species used are all well-expressed in tsA-201 cells (Figures 4D and 4E), and lack of expression therefore could not account for the lack of effect of the truncated constructs when expressed together. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the effect of PrP constructs on calcium channel currents containing α2δ-1 or anchorless α2δ-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>(A) I--V relationships for IBa recorded from tsA-201 cells expressing CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1 alone (■; n=16) with WT PrP (▲; n=10) or ΔGPI–PrP (◆; n=14) or cells expressing CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1ΔC alone (□; n=11) with WT PrP (∆; n=13) or ΔGPI–PrP (◇; n=15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The ratio of cDNAs was the same as in Figure 3(A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>(B) Examples of families of IBa current traces resulting from step potentials from −90 mV to between −30 and +10 mV in 5 mV steps for CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1 alone (top left-hand panel) or α2δ-1ΔC alone (top right-hand panel) with WT PrP (middle panel) or ΔGPI–PrP (bottom panels). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>(C) Peak IBa currents (means±S.E.M.) for the data shown in (A) for CaV2.1/β1b with α2δ-1 (solid bars) or with α2δ-1ΔC (hatched bars) either alone (black bars) or with WT PrP (light grey bars), or ΔGPI-PrP (dark grey bars). *P&lt;0.05 as determined by one-way ANOVA and Bonferroni's post-hoc test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>(D) Western blot of α2δ-1 (upper panels; 4–12% Bis-Tris gel) co-expressed (1:1) with WT PrP (left-hand lane), ∆GPI–PrP (middle lane) or empty vector (right-hand lane; con). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>PrP expression is shown in the lower panel (4–12% Bis-Tris gel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The lower expression of ∆GPI–PrP in the cell lysate is because much of it is secreted [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>(E) Western blot of α2δ-1∆C in medium (upper panels; 3–8% Tris/acetate gel) and cell lysate (lower panels; 4–12% Bis-Tris gel) co-expressed (1:1) with PrP (left-hand panels), ∆GPI–PrP (middle panel) or empty vector (right-hand panels; con). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>In both (D) and (E), all three lanes are from the same blots from which irrelevant lanes have been excised and the molecular mass is given on the right-hand side in kDa. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bj2013-1405i004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>This result suggests either that association of the α2δ and PrP proteins in the plasma membrane, and potentially in the same cholesterol-rich membrane microdomains, facilitated by their GPI anchoring, is essential for the inhibition of calcium currents observed or that there is competition between α2δ-1 and PrP for the GPI-anchor intermediates, resulting in less maturation of α2δ subunit in the presence of PrP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>We therefore examined whether the effect of PrP might be related to the GPI anchor and tested the effect of an unrelated protein engineered to contain a GPI anchor (GFP–GPI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>We found that co-expression of GFP–GPI markedly reduced calcium channel currents formed by CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1 compared with the co-expression of cytosolic GFP, and in this experiment ∆GPI–PrP again had no effect (Figure 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>This result is in agreement with the hypothesis that overexpression of a GPI-anchored protein can produce this inhibition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>We then compared the level of α2δ-1 expression in the presence of co-expressed GFP–GPI and cytosolic GFP (Figure 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>In all cases substantial α2δ-1 was co-expressed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Effect of GPI–GFP on CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1 calcium channel currents </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>(A) I–V relationships for IBa recorded from tsA-201 cells expressing CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1 with GFP (■; n=9), GPI–GFP (▲; n=9), or GFP and ΔGPI–PrP (△; n=6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>The broken line indicates the level of IBa observed for CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1 plus WT PrP from Figure 3(B). ***P&lt;0.001 between the peak IBa when GPI–GFP was co-expressed compared with when GFP was co-expressed (Student's t test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>(B) Western blot of α2δ-1 (upper panels) co-expressed (1:1) with GFP–GPI (lane 1), GFP (lane 2) or empty vector (lane 3; con). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>GFP expression is shown in the lower panel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>All three lanes are from the same blots from which irrelevant lanes have been excised and the molecular mass is given on the right-hand side in kDa. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bj2013-1405i005"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>In the present study we found that when PrP is co-expressed with CaV2.1 calcium channels together with a β-subunit and either α2δ-1 or α2δ-2, it produces a modest reduction in the expressed calcium channel currents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>This reduction in calcium channel currents involves the membrane anchoring of PrP, as it is absent when PrP is truncated prior to its GPI-anchor site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Thus ΔGPI–PrP did not inhibit currents formed by the expression of CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>This result suggests that the process might involve competition for pathways associated with the GPI anchoring of PrP, which might relate to our finding that α2δ subunits form GPI-anchored proteins [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The results of the present study reinforce that view, since native cerebellar α2δ-1, α2δ-2 and PrP all behave similarly following PI-PLC treatment and phase separation, being concentrated in the aqueous phase (Figure 1), which is supportive of evidence for GPI anchoring. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>We therefore utilized an α2δ-1 subunit truncated at the predicted membrane attachment site (α2δ-1ΔC), which, as we have shown recently, is not an integral membrane protein [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>We have characterized α2δ-1ΔC and found that, despite being mainly secreted, it still shows a partial ability to enhance calcium channel currents and to be associated extrinsically with the plasma membrane [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>It is therefore possible that α2δ-1 enhances calcium currents by two mechanisms, one involving a trafficking process that is still maintained by anchorless α2δ-1∆C, and another mechanism that requires its membrane anchoring, for example a process that stabilizes channel complexes in the plasma membrane. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Importantly, we also found in the present study that WT PrP does not inhibit calcium channel currents when α2δ-1ΔC was substituted for WT α2δ-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>This suggested to us two possibilities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>First, PrP and α2δ-1 may compete for GPI-anchor intermediates or subsequent trafficking processes specific for GPI-anchored proteins when both are overexpressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Secondly, the interaction between PrP and α2δ-1 with other protein and lipid components in cholesterol-rich membrane microdomains [50,51] might be involved in the suppression of currents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Thus when either PrP or α2δ-1 is devoid of the lipid anchor no suppression occurs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>It is possible that WT α2δ-1 and PrP interact indirectly via an intermediary trafficking protein and compete for binding to that protein, whereas this does not occur when one of them is not membrane-anchored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the additional finding that CaV2.1/β1b/α2δ-1 currents were also inhibited by GPI–GFP (when compared with the control GFP) suggests that the presence of a GPI anchor might be an important common denominator in this process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Only approximately 150 proteins are known to be GPI-anchored, and the GPI synthetic pathway, involving multiple enzymatic steps in the ER (endoplasmic reticulum) and Golgi, is likely to have limited capacity in mammalian cells [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Overexpression of multiple GPI-anchored proteins in the same cell might lead to saturation of limited resources. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Further studies will be necessary to determine whether overexpression of other GPI-anchored proteins disrupts the function of α2δ within membrane microdomains, or possibly competes with it for GPI transamidase enzymes, GPI-anchoring intermediates or trafficking proteins subsequent to GPI anchoring. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Taken together, the results of the present study provide supporting evidence that α2δ-1 can be GPI-anchored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>More generally the results point to a competitive interaction between GPI-anchored proteins for resources that determine their level of post-translational processing or expression on the plasma membrane. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>We thank Wendy S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Pratt and Kanchan Chaggar for technical assistance. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec><title>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTION</title><p>Annette Dolphin and Roberto Chiesa conceived the study. Anita Alvarez Laviada performed the patch-clamp electrophysiology. Annette Dolphin performed electrophysiology in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes. Ivan Kadurin obtained all data shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. Assunta Senatore performed the Western blotting shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>. Roberto Chiesa supplied constructs, mouse tissue and antibodies. Annette Dolphin, Ivan Kadurin and Roberto Chiesa wrote the paper.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec><title>FUNDING</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the Medical Research Council [grant numbers G0801756 and G0901758 (to A.C.D.)], the Wellcome Trust [Programme grant number 098360/Z/12/Z] and the Fondazione Telethon [grant numbers TDRC00508TU and GGP12115 (to R.C.)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>A.A.-L. was supported by a Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council PhD studentship. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>A.S. was supported by a fellowship from the Banca del Monte di Lombardia Foundation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>R.C. is an Associate Telethon Scientist (Dulbecco Telethon Institute, Fondazione Telethon). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>1DaviesA.HendrichJ.Van MinhA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>T.WrattenJ.DouglasL.DolphinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>C.Functional biology of the α2δ subunits of voltage-gated calcium channelsTrends Pharmacol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Sci.20072822022817403543 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>2WalkerD.De WaardM.Subunit interaction sites in voltage-dependent Ca2+ channelsTrends Neurosci.1998211481549554724 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>3DolphinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>C.β Subunits of voltage-gated calcium channelsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Bioeng. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Biomemb.200335599620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>4PragnellM.De WaardM.MoriY.TanabeT.SnutchT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>P.CampbellK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>P.Calcium channel β-subunit binds to a conserved motif in the I–II cytoplasmic linker of the α1-subunitNature199436867707509046 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>5LeroyJ.RichardsM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>S.ButcherA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>J.Nieto-RostroM.PrattW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>S.DaviesA.DolphinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>C.Interaction via a key tryptophan in the I–II linker of N-type calcium channels is required for beta1 but not for palmitoylated β2, implicating an additional binding site in the regulation of channel voltage-dependent propertiesJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Neurosci.2005256984699616049174 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>6WaitheD.FerronL.PageK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>M.ChaggarK.DolphinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>C.β-Subunits promote the expression of Cav2.2 channels by reducing their proteasomal degradationJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Chem.20112869598961121233207 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>7AltierC.Garcia-CaballeroA.SimmsB.YouH.ChenL.WalcherJ.TedfordH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>W.HermosillaT.ZamponiG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>W.The Cavβ subunit prevents RFP2-mediated ubiquitination and proteasomal degradation of L-type channelsNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Neurosci.20111417318021186355 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>8CantiC.Nieto-RostroM.FoucaultI.HeblichF.WrattenJ.RichardsM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>W.HendrichJ.DouglasL.PageK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>M.DaviesA.DolphinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>C.The metal-ion-dependent adhesion site in the Von Willebrand factor-A domain of α2δ subunits is key to trafficking voltage-gated Ca2+ channelsProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>U.S.A.2005102112301123516061813 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>9HoppaM.LanaB.MargasW.DolphinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>C.RyanT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>A.α2δ couples calcium channels to neurotransmitter release sites to control release probabilityNature201248612212522678293 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>10CassidyJ.DolphinACUsing exofacially tagged functional Cav2.2 to investigate the modulation of pore subunit trafficking by auxiliary calcium channel subunits58th U.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Biophysical Society meeting2014San Francisco, CA, U.S.A.15–19 February 2014, Abstract 1672-Pos </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>11BrodbeckJ.DaviesA.CourtneyJ.-M.MeirA.BalagueroN.CantiC.MossF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>J.PageK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>M.PrattW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>S.HuntS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>P.The ducky mutation in Cacna2d2 results in altered Purkinje cell morphology and is associated with the expression of a truncated a2d-2 protein with abnormal functionJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Chem.20022777684769311756448 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>12WakamoriM.MikalaG.MoriY.Auxiliary subunits operate as a molecular switch in determining gating behaviour of the unitary N-type Ca2+ channel current in Xenopus oocytesJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Physiol.199951765967210358108 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>13DaviesA.KadurinI.Alvarez-LaviadaA.DouglasL.Nieto-RostroM.BauerC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>S.PrattW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>S.DolphinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>C.The α2δ subunits of voltage-gated calcium channels form GPI-anchored proteins, a post-translational modification essential for functionProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>U.S.A.20101071654165920080692 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>14GurnettC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>A.De WaardM.CampbellK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>P.Dual function of the voltage-dependent Ca2+ channel α2δ subunit in current stimulation and subunit interactionNeuron1996164314408789958 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>15CatterallW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>A.Structure and regulation of voltage-gated Ca2+ channelsAnnu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Cell Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Biol.20001652155511031246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>16ArikkathJ.CampbellK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>P.Auxiliary subunits: essential components of the voltage-gated calcium channel complexCurr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Opin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Neurobiol.20031329830712850214 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>17JayS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>D.SharpA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>H.KahlS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>D.VedvickT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>S.HarpoldM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>M.CampbellK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>P.Structural characterization of the dihydropyridine-sensitive calcium channel α2-subunit and the associated δ peptidesJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Chem.1991266328732931847144 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>18StahlN.BorcheltD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>R.HsiaoK.PrusinerS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>B.Scrapie prion protein contains a phosphatidylinositol glycolipidCell1987512292402444340 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>19CollingeJ.Molecular neurology of prion diseaseJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Neurol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Neurosurg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>Psychiatry20057690691915965195 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>20BiasiniE.TurnbaughJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>A.UnterbergerU.HarrisD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>A.Prion protein at the crossroads of physiology and diseaseTrends Neurosci.2012359210322137337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>21BuelerH.FischerM.LangY.BluethmannH.LippH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>P.DearmondS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>J.PrusinerS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>B.AguetM.WeissmannC.Normal development and behaviour of mice lacking the neuronal cell-surface PrP proteinNature19923565775821373228 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>22SteeleA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>D.LindquistS.AguzziA.The prion protein knockout mouse: a phenotype under challengePrion20071839319164918 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>23Mouillet-RichardS.ErmonvalM.ChebassierC.LaplancheJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>L.LehmannS.LaunayJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>M.KellermannO.Signal transduction through prion proteinScience20002891925192810988071 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>24VilesJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>H.CohenF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>E.PrusinerS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>B.GoodinD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>B.WrightP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>E.DysonH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>J.Copper binding to the prion protein: structural implications of four identical cooperative binding sitesProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>U.S.A.1999962042204710051591 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>25CollingeJ.WhittingtonM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>A.SidleK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>C.SmithC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>J.PalmerM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>S.ClarkeA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>R.JefferysJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>G.Prion protein is necessary for normal synaptic functionNature19943702952978035877 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>26BremerJ.BaumannF.TiberiC.WessigC.FischerH.SchwarzP.SteeleA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>D.ToykaK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>V.NaveK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>A.WeisJ.AguzziA.Axonal prion protein is required for peripheral myelin maintenanceNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>Neurosci.20101331031820098419 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>27PrusinerS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>B.PrionsProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>U.S.A.19989513363133839811807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>28MallucciG.DickinsonA.LinehanJ.KlohnP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>C.BrandnerS.CollingeJ.Depleting neuronal PrP in prion infection prevents disease and reverses spongiosisScience200330287187414593181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>29BuelerH.AguzziA.SailerA.GreinerR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>A.AutenriedP.AguetM.WeissmannC.Mice devoid of PrP are resistant to scrapieCell199373133913478100741 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>30BrandnerS.IsenmannS.RaeberA.FischerM.SailerA.KobayashiY.MarinoS.WeissmannC.AguzziA.Normal host prion protein necessary for scrapie-induced neurotoxicityNature19963793393438552188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>31RutishauserD.MertzK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>D.MoosR.BrunnerE.RulickeT.CalellaA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>M.AguzziA.The comprehensive native interactome of a fully functional tagged prion proteinPLoS ONE20094e444619209230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>32DaviesA.DouglasL.HendrichJ.WrattenJ.Tran-Van-MinhA.FoucaultI.KochD.PrattW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>S.SaibilH.DolphinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>C.The calcium channel α2δ-2 subunit partitions with CaV2.1 in lipid rafts in cerebellum: implications for localization and functionJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Neurosci.2006268748875716928863 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>33TaylorD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>R.WhitehouseI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>J.HooperN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>M.Glypican-1 mediates both prion protein lipid raft association and disease isoform formationPLoS Pathog.20095e100066619936054 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>34ElfrinkK.Nagel-StegerL.RiesnerD.Interaction of the cellular prion protein with raft-like lipid membranesBiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Chem.2007388798917214553 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>35SenatoreA.ColleoniS.VerderioC.RestelliE.MoriniR.CondliffeS.BertaniI.MantovaniS.CanoviM.MicottiE.Mutant prion protein suppresses glutamatergic neurotrasmission in cerebellar granule neurons by impairing membrane delivery of voltage-gated calcium channel α2δ-1 subunitNeuron20127430031322542184 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>36KadurinI.Alvarez-LaviadaA.NgS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>F.Walker-GrayR.D’ArcoM.FadelM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>G.PrattW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>S.DolphinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>C.Calcium currents are enhanced by α2δ-1 lacking its membrane anchorJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Chem.20121287335543356622869375 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>37TomlinsonW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>J.SteaA.BourinetE.CharnetP.NargeotJ.SnutchT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>P.Functional properties of a neuronal class C L-type calcium channelNeuropharmacology199332111711268107966 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>38StewartR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>S.HarrisD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>A.Mutational analysis of topological determinants in prion protein (PrP) and measurement of transmembrane and cytosolic PrP during prion infectionJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Chem.2003278459604596812933795 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>39CormackB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>P.ValdiviaR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>H.FalkowS.FACS-optimized mutants of the green fluorescent protein (GFP)Gene199617333388707053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>40NicholsB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>J.KenworthyA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>K.PolishchukR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>S.LodgeR.RobertsT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>H.HirschbergK.PhairR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>D.Lippincott-SchwartzJ.Rapid cycling of lipid raft markers between the cell surface and Golgi complexJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>Cell Biol.200115352954111331304 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>41PageK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>M.HeblichF.DaviesA.ButcherA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>J.LeroyJ.BertasoF.PrattW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>S.DolphinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>C.Dominant-negative calcium channel suppression by truncated constructs involves a kinase implicated in the unfolded protein responseJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Neurosci.2004245400540915190113 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>42ChiesaR.PiccardoP.GhettiB.HarrisD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>A.Neurological illness in transgenic mice expressing a prion protein with an insertional mutationNeuron199821133913519883727 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>43BordierC.Phase separation of integral membrane proteins in Triton X-114 solutionJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Chem.1981256160416076257680 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>44BarclayJ.BalagueroN.MioneM.AckermanS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>L.LettsV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>A.BrodbeckJ.CantiC.MeirA.PageK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>M.KusumiK.Ducky mouse phenotype of epilepsy and ataxia is associated with mutations in the Cacna2d2 gene and decreased calcium channel current in cerebellar Purkinje cellsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>Neurosci.2001216095610411487633 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>45LehmannS.HarrisD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>A.A mutant prion protein displays an aberrant membrane association when expressed in cultured cellsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>Chem.199527024589245977592679 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>46BerrowN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>S.BriceN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>L.TedderI.PageK.DolphinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>C.Properties of cloned rat a1A calcium channels transiently expressed in the COS-7 cell lineEur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Neurosci.199797397489153580 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>47CampbellV.BerrowN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>S.FitzgeraldE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>M.BrickleyK.DolphinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>C.Inhibition of the interaction of G protein Go with calcium channels by the calcium channel β-subunit in rat neuronesJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>Physiol.19954853653727666364 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>48CantiC.DaviesA.BerrowN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>S.ButcherA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>J.PageK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>M.DolphinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>C.Evidence for two concentration-dependent processes for β subunit effects on a1B calcium channelsBiophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>J.2001811439145111509358 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>49CantiC.PageK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>M.StephensG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>J.DolphinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>C.Identification of residues in the N-terminus of a1B critical for inhibition of the voltage-dependent calcium channel by GbgJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>Neurosci.1999196855686410436043 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>50StuermerC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>A.Reggie/flotillin and the targeted delivery of cargoJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>Neurochem.201111670871321214550 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>51HooperN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>M.Glypican-1 facilitates prion conversion in lipid raftsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>Neurochem.201111672172520681952 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>52FujitaM.KinoshitaT.Structural remodeling of GPI anchors during biosynthesis and after attachment to proteinsFEBS Lett.20105841670167719883648 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>53CampanaV.CaputoA.SarnataroD.PaladinoS.TivodarS.ZurzoloC.Characterization of the properties and trafficking of an anchorless form of the prion proteinJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>Chem.2007282227472275617556367 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
