
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Evol Bioinform Online</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Evol. Bioinform. Online</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">101256319</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Evolutionary Bioinformatics Online</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1176-9343</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Libertas Academica</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3460774</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4137/EBO.S10159</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ebo-8-2012-545</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Phylogenomic Study of Lipid Genes Involved in Microalgal Biofuel Production—Candidate Gene Mining and Metabolic Pathway Analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>Namrata</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Panda</surname><given-names>Prasanna Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1-ebo-8-2012-545"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Parida</surname><given-names>Bikram Kumar</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>Barada Kanta</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="af1-ebo-8-2012-545">Bioresources Engineering Department, CSIR-Institute of Minerals and Materials Technology (Formerly Regional Research Laboratory), Bhubaneswar, Odisha, India.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1-ebo-8-2012-545">Corresponding author emails: <email>pkpanda@immt.res.in</email>; <email>pkrpan@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>9</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>564</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2012 the author(s), publisher and licensee Libertas Academica Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open access article. Unrestricted non-commercial use is permitted provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Optimizing microalgal biofuel production using metabolic engineering tools requires an in-depth understanding of the structure-function relationship of genes involved in lipid biosynthetic pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>In the present study, genome-wide identification and characterization of 398 putative genes involved in lipid biosynthesis in Arabidopsis thaliana Chlamydomonas reinhardtii, Volvox carteri, Ostreococcus lucimarinus, Ostreococcus tauri and Cyanidioschyzon merolae was undertaken on the basis of their conserved motif/domain organization and phylogenetic profile. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The results indicated that the core lipid metabolic pathways in all the species are carried out by a comparable number of orthologous proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Although the fundamental gene organizations were observed to be invariantly conserved between microalgae and Arabidopsis genome, with increased order of genome complexity there seems to be an association with more number of genes involved in triacylglycerol (TAG) biosynthesis and catabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Further, phylogenomic analysis of the genes provided insights into the molecular evolution of lipid biosynthetic pathway in microalgae and confirm the close evolutionary proximity between the Streptophyte and Chlorophyte lineages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Together, these studies will improve our understanding of the global lipid metabolic pathway and contribute to the engineering of regulatory networks of algal strains for higher accumulation of oil. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>microalgae</kwd><kwd>biofuel</kwd><kwd>lipid biosynthetic genes</kwd><kwd>phylogenomics</kwd><kwd>bioinformatics</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Growing levels of atmospheric pollution, mounting energy demand, and the incessant rise in crude oil prices are some of the issues which have in recent times driven global efforts in biofuel research. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Currently, commercial-scale biofuels are sourced primarily from a variety bioenergy crops that include sugarcane (Saccharum officinarum), sugar beet (Beta vulgaris), switch grass (Panicum virgatum), soybean (Glycine max), canola (Brassica napus) and sunflower (Helianthus annus).1 Although the environmental benefits of biofuels as compared to fossil fuels are well established, concerns are being raised about their long-term sustainability, especially against the backdrop of diversion of arable land for biofuel-based cropping systems and their corresponding adverse impact on the global food supply chain.2 In consequence, algae-based biofuels are increasingly gaining the attention of researchers due to their rapid growth rate coupled with high carbon dioxide uptake, high lipid content and comparatively low, marginal land usage rates.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Notwithstanding the many advantages of biofuels and their technical feasibility, the commercial viability of the algal biofuel process is still an area of concern requiring better strain development and improved post-harvest process engineering.4 The major challenge is to achieve accumulation of improved lipid profiles with concomitant reduction in energy inputs in order to minimize the cost of production.2 The enhancement of lipid production in microalgal cells under controlled stress conditions and engineering metabolic pathways are promising strategies to obtain large amounts of standard biofuel for industry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Despite positive experimental reports on enhanced microalgal lipid accumulation under physiological or nutritional stress regimes, many contrasting studies have indicated a concomitant reduction in overall biomass yield under such conditions.5 In this context, harnessing the potential of genome-scale metabolic engineering has been suggested as a promising area of research to boost oil production in microalgal strains, including modification of algal lipid profile for improved biofuel properties.6,7 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Over the past few years various studies have been carried out concerning alteration of fatty acid composition in plants through genetic engineering approaches, along with the development and deployment of a number of plant lipid-related genomics databases.8–11 Comparative genomics analyses using bioinformatics tools have also been performed recently to identify genes involved in lipid biosynthesis in various oleaginous plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>For example, a total of 1003 maize lipid-related genes were cloned and annotated by Lin et al,12 while Sharma and Chauhan13 identified a total of 261 lipid genes from the genome of Arabidopsis, Brassica, soybean and castor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Complete or near complete genome sequences have been reported for several algae.6 Yet, lack of adequate knowledge regarding the structure-function of lipid biogenesis genes in an evolutionary context is a major impediment in engineering metabolic pathways of algae for over-production of fuel precursors.14 Various experimental techniques like insertional mutagenesis and targeted gene disruption have been employed to analyze gene function in a few algae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>However, many of these approaches are tedious, time-consuming, fiscally prohibitive and limited by a number of biological constraints.15 As an alternative, phylogenomics is now increasingly used to gain insights into metabolic pathways at the molecular level by comparative genomics and co-evolutionary analyses of related gene.16 Therefore the present work was designed to identify the genes involved in lipid metabolic pathway from the genomes of microalgae (including Chlamydomonas reinhardtii, Volvox carteri, Ostreococcus lucimarinus, Ostreococcus tauri and Cyanidioschyzon merolae) using sequence similarity search with Arabidopsis thaliana homologs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>In addition phylogenomics protocols have been employed to study the structure-function relationship of the encoded proteins and to gain much needed insights into their phylogenetic evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>We hope that the present study contributes to the biochemical and molecular information needed for augmentation of lipid synthesis in microalgae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Gene retrieval and annotation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>An initial set of lipid genes was obtained from the Arabidopsis thaliana lipid gene database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantbiology.msu.edu/lipids/genesurvey/index.html">http://www.plantbiology.msu.edu/lipids/genesurvey/index.html</ext-link>) to construct a query protein set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The Arabidopsis lipid gene database is a convenient and reliable source of genes covering all the major biochemical events responsible for biosynthesis and catabolism of plant lipids.17 Subsequently, each protein in the query dataset was used to identify homologs in microalgae by subjecting it to BLASTp18 search with e-value inclusion threshold set to 0.001 against microalgal genome databases provided by Joint Genome Institute. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>These include Cyanidioschyzon merolae<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://merolae.biol.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp/">http://merolae.biol.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp/</ext-link>), Chlamydomonas reinhardtii (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.jgi-psf.org/chlamy/chlamy.info.html">http://genome.jgi-psf.org/chlamy/chlamy.info.html</ext-link>), Volvox carteri (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phytozome.net/volvox.php">http://www.phytozome.net/volvox.php</ext-link>), Ostreococcus lucimarinus (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.jgi-psf.org/Ost9901_3/Ost9901_3.home.html">http://genome.jgi-psf.org/Ost9901_3/Ost9901_3.home.html</ext-link>), Ostreococcus tauri (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.jgi-psf.org/Ostta4/Ostta4.home.html">http://genome.jgi-psf.org/Ostta4/Ostta4.home.html</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Based on multiple alignments and/or the presence of conserved motif patterns, some initial sequences “hits” were then discarded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Functional descriptions of genes or gene products were performed by annotation of Cluster of Orthologous groups (COGs) using KOGnitor program,19 the latter being a widely used tool in the field of computational genomics for detecting candidate set of orthologs in prokaryotes and eukaryotes.19 In addition, assignment of Gene Ontology (GO) terms describing biological processes and molecular function was annotated by the GO browser and annotation tool AmiGO.20 The Gene Ontology is currently the pre-eminent approach for functional annotation of homologous genes and protein sequences in multiple organisms.20 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Metabolic pathway study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Metabolic pathways were subsequently analyzed using the KEGG pathway database,21 an extensively employed biochemical pathway database to analyze lipid pathways in diverse organisms.22 To enrich the pathway annotation, sequences were submitted to the KEGG Automatic Annotation Server (KAAS) to identify the orthologous gene groups.23 KAAS annotates every submitted sequence with a KEGG ortholog (KO) identifier that allows identification of orthologous and paralogous relationships between the genes of interest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Further, a set of six reference pathway maps, namely fatty acid biosynthesis, fatty acid metabolism, fatty acid elongation, glycerolipid metabolism, glycerophospholipid metabolism and pathway map for biosynthesis of unsaturated fatty acids, were downloaded from the KEGG database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>This dataset contains a complete biochemical description of the pathways related to the lipid metabolism observed in different organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>They were used as templates for comprehensive examination of the lipid biosynthetic genomic repertoire of microalgae by correlating genes in the genome with gene products (enzymes), in accordance with their respective Enzyme Commission (EC) number. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Prediction of subcellular localization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Three different protein targeting prediction programs were used to determine the putative subcellular localization of the candidate proteins: TargetP,24 ChloroP25 and WolfPsort.26 Each program is based on different terminology and predictions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The location assignment of TargetP is based on the presence of any of the N-terminal presequences: chloroplast transit peptides (cTP), mitochondrial targeting peptide (mTP) or secretory pathway signal peptide (SP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The ChloroP server predicts the presence of chloroplast transit peptides (cTP) in protein sequences and the location of potential cTP cleavage sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>WolfPsort is an extension of the PSORT II program for protein subcellular localization prediction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>It classifies protein into more than 10 location sites, including dual localization such as proteins which shuttle between the cytosol and nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The sensitivity and specificity of this program has been experimentally verified to be 70%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Physico-chemical characterization and secondary structure prediction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Physico-chemical properties like length, molecular weight, isoelectric point (pI), total number of positive and negative residues, Instability Index,27 Aliphatic Index28 and Grand Average hydropathy (GRAVY)29 were computed using the Expasy’s ProtParam server.30 GOR IV server31 was employed for the prediction of secondary structural features like alpha helices, extended strands and random coils in terms of percentage in the protein sequences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Calculation of the GC content </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The GC content of the predicted genes was determined using Genscan web server.32 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Motif identification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Protein sequence motifs for each gene family were identified using the MEME program.33 The analyses parameters were set as follows: number of repetitions-zero or one per sequence; maximum number of motifs—1; minimum and maximum width—6 and 50, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The motif profile for each gene family is presented schematically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Domain arrangements along sequences were predicted using InterProscan34 to determine protein homolog relationships among species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Exon-intron structure and phylogenetic analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The exon-intron structural patterns of the lipid biosynthetic genes were analyzed using the gene prediction algorithm of Genscan.32 To construct the phylogenetic tree, amino acid sequences were aligned using the ClustalX program implemented in BioEdit35 (v 7.1.3) with default settings and then manually refined by trimming of poorly conserved N and C termini. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>ClustalX36 has been demonstrated to be a user-friendly tool for providing good, biologically accurate alignments within a reasonable time limit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Many options are provided such as the realignment of selected sequences or blocks of conserved residues and the possibility of building up difficult alignments, making ClustalX an ideal tool for working interactively on alignments.36 Subsequently, sequence alignment of genes predicted to be in similar families were used as an input file for the MEGA 4 software.37 Phylogenetic tree was built via the neighbor-joining (NJ) method with evaluation of 1000 rounds of bootstrapping test, followed by identification of sub-tree. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Results and Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Comparative genomic analyses of lipid genes in microalgal species </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Interest in microalgae as a potential feedstock for biofuel production and other valuable biomaterials is rooted in the ability of microalgae to rapidly accumulate significant amounts of neutral lipids.38 Under optimal conditions, microalgae synthesize fatty acids used primarily for esterification into polar glycerol-based membrane lipids like glycosylglycerides and phosphoglycerides, whereas under stress conditions, many microalgae tend to accumulate storage lipids called triacylglycerol (TAGs).16 Although global fatty acid biosynthetic mechanisms are known in higher plants,39 pathways responsible for lipid accumulation in microalgae are not well studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Hence, in order to bridge our existing knowledge gap regarding algal lipid metabolism, comparative metabolic pathway analyses have been performed across five microalgal genomes, using homologous plant genes as reference with an objective of functional characterization of predicted genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>EC numbers, Cluster of Orthologous Groups (COGs), protein domain family and GO terms were determined for the respective candidate genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The above in silico approach has been reviewed recently to be reliable enough for accurate function prediction of uncharacterized proteins encoded by genes in a genome.40 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>In the present study, using the Arabidopsis annotation data as the BLAST input query set, a total of 398 orthologous genes present in A. thaliana, C. reinhardtii, V. carteri, O. lucimarinus, O. tauri and C. merolae genomes were identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The above approach to identify candidate genes involved in biosynthesis and accumulation of storage oil has been successfully demonstrated in plants by Sharma and Chauhan.13 These 398 genes clustered into 40 gene families and includes 142, 56, 59, 47, 41 and 53 genes from A. thaliana, C. reinhardtii, V. carteri, O. lucimarinus, O. tauri and C. merolae genomes, respectively (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The identified genes are involved in the synthesis of phospholipids, glycerolipid and storage lipids like TAG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>We further divided the predicted genes into categories like gene-coding enzymes involved in biosynthesis and catabolism of fatty acid, TAG and membrane lipid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The comprehensive list of candidate genes along with experimental evidence of the respective enzyme action influencing lipid accumulation is presented in Table 1.41–74 Approximately 47% of the predicted gene products found in the present study were previously annotated as ‘predicted’, ‘probable’, ‘putative uncharacterized’ and ‘similar’ or ‘hypothetical’ proteins (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The annotation of these sequences has been improved and a role in lipid biosynthetic process was assigned to each of them by similarity search with homologous plant genes, annotation of Gene Ontology, and through identification of conserved domains or motifs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, on comparison to the previous report on lipid gene identification in C. merolae genome by Sato and Moriyama,75 the present study has identified 20 additional genes involved in lipid biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>To investigate metabolic processes responsible for the synthesis of microalgal biofuel precursors, KO identifiers were assigned to the predicted 398 genes representing 36 unique EC numbers, which were subsequently used to study metabolic pathway maps available in KEGG pathway database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>KEGG is considered one of the most important bioinformatics resources for understanding higher-order functional meaning and the utilities of the organism from its genome information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>It hosts information on the majority of well-known metabolic pathways, including lipid pathways for several organisms such as higher plants, bacteria and algae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Recently, it has been used successfully by Rismani-Yazdi et al14 to identify pathways and the underlying gene responsible for production of biofuel precursors in Dunaliella tertiolecta, a potential microalgal biofuel feedstock. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Using the above approach, a total of 79 lipid genes including 22 from A. thaliana, 21 from C. merolae, 10 from C. reinhardtii, 10 from O. lucimarinus and 8 each from V. carteri and O. tauri were recognized that were not earlier indexed in KEGG metabolic pathway database (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The global synthesis pathway of TAG begins with the basic fatty acid precursors, acetyl-CoA, and continues through fatty acid biosynthesis, complex lipid assembly and saturated fatty acid modification until TAG bodies are finally formed.76 A simplified overview of TAG biosynthetic pathway in microalgae is shown as Figure 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Comparative analyses with the genomes of C. reinhardtii, V. carteri, O. lucimarinus, O. tauri, C. merolae and A. thaliana indicates that the majority of genes involved in lipid production are orthologous among these species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the extensive amino acid sequence conservation (more than 60% pair-wise sequence identity) among the genes involved in lipid biosynthesis provides indications of functional equivalence between Arabidopsis and microalgal genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Thus, the present results demonstrate that the underlying fatty acid and TAG biosynthesis process are directly analogous to those reported in higher plants.16 It may further be noted that although algae predominantly share similar lipid biosynthetic pathways with higher plants, the present in silico analyses revealed that the sizes of the gene families responsible for lipid biosynthesis in microalgae are smaller than Arabidopsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Certain specific pathways were also observed to be absent in microalgae, including the fatty acid biosynthesis termination mechanism by FAT homologs in C. merolae. The above computational analyses find support from the previous experimental reports on the algal lipid metabolism.75 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, our results conclusively indicate that enzymes that are responsible for higher lipid accumulation in plants and other eukaryotes, either through over-expression or gene knockout strategies, are present not only in oleaginous algal species (C. reinhardtii) but also in other algal species, notably O. tauri and C. merolae (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the number of genes in each step of lipid metabolic pathway suggests that the green algae C. reinhardtii and V. carteri have an expanded array of genes involved in TAG biosynthesis and catabolism, including fatty acid thioesterase, long chain acyl-CoA synthase, acyl-CoA oxidase, desaturase, glycerol-3-phosphate acyltransferase, and diacylglycerol acyltransferase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the proportion of these gene copy numbers appear to be correlated with the genome complexity of the organisms under study (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Prediction of subcellular location </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The prediction of subcellular localization of proteins is essential to elucidate the spatial organization of proteins according to their function and to refine our knowledge of cellular metabolism.77 Thus, prediction of subcellular location provides valuable information about the function of proteins as well as the interconnectivity of biological processes.78 In the present study, subcellular location of lipid biosynthetic proteins by tools such as TargetP, ChloroP and WolfPsort showed different locations using several unique algorithms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The objective of using more than one analytical tool was to improve the specificity of the prediction, as various studies have shown that combined results from several prediction programs are advantageous to rule out false positives and false negatives.78 The available localization prediction tools show different strengths and no tool is clearly and globally optimal.77 Moreover, it is known that some localizations are badly predicted by all the algorithms, especially in the case of proteins exhibiting dual targeting to plastids and mitochondria, which could be a phenomenon more common than previously thought.79 This analyses showed that majority of the predicted proteins are located in four compartments: plastids (31%), mitochondria (26%), cytoplasmic (28%) and nucleus (6%) (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>S1 and Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The above results are consistent with the experimental observations that de novo synthesis of fatty acids occurs primarily in the plastid and/or mitochondria.5 About 19% of the proteins revealed the presence of both the mitochondrial target peptide and chloroplast transit peptide in the sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Recent reports have shown an unexpectedly high frequency of dual targeting of proteins to both the mitochondria and chloroplast, hence making it difficult to predict the correct location of these proteins within a cell.80,81 Furthermore, approximately 3% of the predicted proteins were located in more than one compartment ie, nucleus and cytoplasm, which were the same highly paired compartments as identified in Arabidopsis82 and sugarcane83 proteome, suggesting that there is a significant amount of interactions between these two organelles. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Hyunjong et al84 have reported that targeting a particular enzyme to several compartments simultaneously in the same plant will augment its production when compared to its individual compartments in the same plant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Hence the predicted localization information would certainly aid in targeting the lipid biosynthetic enzymes to enhance oil accumulation in microalgae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Physico-chemical characterization and secondary structure prediction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Various physico-chemical parameters were computed using Expasy’s ProtParam tool (Fig. 3 and Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Molecular weight was observed between the ranges of 1116.818–299171.0 for all lipid biosynthetic proteins in microalgae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The majority of the predicted proteins were found to have a pI greater than 7, indicating that proteins involved in lipid biosynthesis are generally basic in nature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>However, the deduced sequences for genes such as acetyl-CoA carboxylase, acetyl-CoA acetyltransferase, glycerol kinase, ethanolamine kinase and phosphoethanolamine cytidyl transferase were determined to be acidic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>These values of isoelectric point (overall charge) will be useful for developing a buffer system for purification of the enzymes by an isoelectric focusing method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Instability Index analyses reveals the presence of certain dipeptides occurring at significantly different frequencies between stable and unstable proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Proteins with an instability index less than 40 are predicted to be stable while those with a value greater than 40 are assumed to be unstable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>In the present study the high occurrence frequency of unstable proteins may be explained in the context of the recent work of Cao,85 who observed such a phenomenon in many plants and microorganisms due to the possible inherent feedback mechanism that regulates the optimal level of accumulation of cellular metabolites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The aliphatic index refers to the relative volume of a protein that is occupied by aliphatic side chains (eg, alanine, isoleucine, leucine and valine) and contributes to the increased thermal stability observed for globular proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Aliphatic index for the screened proteins ranged from 70.24 to 119.16. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The very high aliphatic index for all sequences indicated that their structures are more stable over a wide range of temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The GRAVY index indicates the solubility of the protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The lipid biosynthetic proteins which showed large negative values indicated that these proteins are relatively more hydrophobic when compared to proteins with less negative values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The secondary structure of the microalgal proteins involved in lipid metabolism were analyzed by submitting the amino acid sequence to the GOR IV program, which has been experimentally cross validated to have a mean accuracy of 64.4% for the three state prediction.32 The secondary structure indicates whether a given amino acid lies in a helix, strand or a coil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Secondary structure features of the proteins are represented in Table S3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The results revealed that random coil to be predominant followed by alpha helices and extended strands in the majority of sequences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>GC-content analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The variations in the guanine (G) and cytosine (C) content observed between species is one of the central issues in evolutionary bioinformatics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The average GC-content of the lipid biosynthetic genes, as calculated by the Genscan server, was 39.89%, 63.35%, 56.92%, 59.88%, 59.04% and 55.57% for A. thaliana, C. reinhardtii, V. carteri, O. lucimarinus O. tauri and C. merolae respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The GC values lie close to the calculated GC-content of the whole genome of the respective organisms under study.86–89 However, a slightly higher GC-content for the gene sequences was observed in contrast to the background GC-content for the entire genome of all the studied species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Among the microalgae, the highest GC-content was observed in C. reinhardtii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The GC-content of C. reinhardtii is also experimentally reported to be higher than that of the multicellular organisms.90 Comparative analyses of the GC-content of the individual genes revealed minor variations among the microalgal genomes (Fig. 4 and Table S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The above finding is in congruence with the earlier report stating that eukaryotic genomes vary less in their GC content.91 Furthermore, GC-content analyses indicated that the genes with high GC-content were also identified to be stable by ProtParam server as compared to genes having low GC-content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>This may apparently be due to the fact that GC pair is bound by 3 hydrogen bonds (H-bonds), compared to 2 H-bonds in AT, thus contributing to the greater stability of the gene products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>In addition, analyses of individual predicted genes in O. lucimarinus and O. tauri revealed more or less similar GC-content in both the subspecies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Motif and domain architecture </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>A motif is a sequence pattern found conserved in a group of related protein or gene sequences.34 An exhaustive search of the protein motifs using the MEME program identified 36 core conserved sequences in the lipid biosynthetic genes of microalgae predicted in the present study (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The overall height of each stack indicates the sequence conservation at that position, whereas the height of symbols within each stack reflects the relative frequency of the corresponding amino acid (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The sequence logos showed that majority of the predicted motifs are basically composed of hydrophobic and polar uncharged residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>It is likely that these conserved residues are critical for the catalytic activity of the enzymes and may be involved in substrate binding, direct catalysis, and maintenance of the protein structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>In addition to motif analyses, a detailed comparison of the domain architectures of the gene products at the whole genome level is given in Figure 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Results indicate that the majority of domains observed in genes involved in lipid biosynthesis are present in all microalgal species under study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the critical amino acid residues present in the conserved motif and domain of the lipid genes will certainly act as a framework for better understanding their structure-function relationship. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Exon-intron structure and phylogenetic analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>In order to gain insights into the evolution of the lipid biosynthetic genes, we analyzed exon-intron structure patterns of the predicted gene homologs (Table S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The results revealed that the exon-intron spilt pattern of C. reinhardtii and V. carteri genes were homologous to that of Arabidopsis, although insertion, deletion and intron-size variations were common. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Likewise, conservation with respect to exon-intron number and size were observed between O. lucimarinus and O. tauri. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The C. merolae genome is remarkable for its paucity of introns88 and in our study we also could not detect its presence in any of the predicted genes. O. lucimarinus and O. tauri genes contained fewer introns as compared to C. reinhardtii, V. carteri and A. thaliana and our present results confirms the previous report that C. reinhardtii lipid biosynthetic genes contain a higher number of introns.92 A phylogenetic tree was constructed to evaluate the evolutionary relationship among the predicted genes (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic tree showed that in the majority of predicted genes with similar functions and sharing similar intron-exon structure, conserved motif patterns were clustered together in the tree because of their common ancestry and in accordance with our expectations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>In most of the gene families, it was observed that the protein sequence of the two sub-species O. lucimarinus and O. tauri (Prasinophytes) were present as sister clades and that it falls within the green algal cluster comprising of C. reinhardtii, V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Carteri (Chlorophytes) and A. thaliana (Streptophytes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The Chlorophytes and Streptophytes lineages are a part of the green plant lineage (Viridiplantae).93 Further, the phylogenetic analyses suggest that protein homologs of C. merolae (Rhodophytes) seem to diverge from the root of the green lineage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Overall, we found that components of lipid biosynthetic pathway are remarkably well conserved, particularly among the Viridiplantae lineage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Identification of genes responsible for oil accumulation is a pre-requisite to targeting microalgae for enhanced yields of biofuel precursors using metabolic engineering. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>A comprehensive computational analyses of the predicted genes of microalgae against Arabidopsis was performed through gene annotation, subcellular localization, physico-chemical characterization, exon-intron pattern, motif/domain organization and phylogenomics studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The results revealed that although each of the algal species maintains the basic genomic repertoire required for lipid biosynthesis, they possess additional lineage-specific gene groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the extensive sequence and structure conservation of the putative genes indicates functional equivalence between microalgae and Arabidopsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analyses demonstrated that genes of lipid biosynthetic pathway from Prasinophytes, Chlorophytes, Streptophytes and Rhodophytes were clustered according to their conserved motif pattern, exon-intron structure and functional equivalence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The in-depth broad investigation of each individual gene and their encoded products across the microalgal genome will certainly facilitate metabolic engineering of microalga for biofuel production. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="s1-ebo-8-2012-545"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Classification of microalgal lipid biosynthetic proteins on the basis of subcellular localization using TargetP, ChloroP and WolfPsort prediction tools. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="ebo-8-2012-545s1.tif" xlink:type="simple" id="d34e761" position="anchor" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="s2-ebo-8-2012-545"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Subcellular localisation prediction of proteins encoded by lipid biosynthetic genes in A. thaliana, C. reinhardtii, V. carteri, O.lucimarinus, O. tauri and C. merolae, using TargetP, ChloroP and WolfPsort programs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="ebo-8-2012-545-s2.docx" xlink:type="simple" id="d34e774" position="anchor" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="s3-ebo-8-2012-545"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Subcellular localisation prediction of proteins encoded by lipid biosynthetic genes in A. thaliana, C. reinhardtii, V. carteri, O.lucimarinus, O. tauri and C. merolae, using TargetP, ChloroP and WolfPsort programs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="ebo-8-2012-545-s3.docx" xlink:type="simple" id="d34e787" position="anchor" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="s4-ebo-8-2012-545"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The calculated secondary structures of the proteins encoded by lipid biosynthetic genes, using GOR IV program. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="ebo-8-2012-545-s4.docx" xlink:type="simple" id="d34e794" position="anchor" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="s5-ebo-8-2012-545"><label>Table S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>GC-content values of lipid biosynthetic genes as calculated by Genscan web server. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="ebo-8-2012-545-s5.docx" xlink:type="simple" id="d34e801" position="anchor" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="s6-ebo-8-2012-545"><label>Table S5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Exon-intron coordinates of lipid biosynthetic genes in A. thaliana, C. reinhardtii, V. carteri, O. lucimarinus, O. tauri and C. merolae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="ebo-8-2012-545-s6.docx" xlink:type="simple" id="d34e808" position="anchor" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgement</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The research fellowship granted to NM by the Government of India’s Department of Biotechnology (under a grant-in-aid project) and subsequently a Senior Research Fellowship award by Council of Scientific &amp; Industrial Research, India is gratefully acknowledged. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn id="fn1-ebo-8-2012-545"><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Author Contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: NM, PKP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Analysed the data: NM, PKP, BKM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Wrote the first draft of the manuscript: NM, PKP, BKP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: NM, BKP, PKP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Agree with manuscript results and conclusions: NM, PKP, BKP, BKM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Jointly developed the structure and arguments for the paper: PKP, BKM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Made critical revisions and approved final version: NM, PKP, BKP, BKM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>All authors reviewed and approved of the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="fn2-ebo-8-2012-545"><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Author(s) disclose no potential conflicts of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="fn3-ebo-8-2012-545"><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Disclosures and Ethics </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>As a requirement of publication author(s) have providedto the publisher signed confirmation of compliance with legal and ethical obligations including but not limited to the following: authorship and contributorship, conflicts of interest, privacy and confidentiality and (where applicable) protection of human and animal research subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The authors have read and confirmed their agreement with the ICMJE authorship and conflict of interest criteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The authors have also confirmed that this article is unique and not under consideration or published in any other publication, and that they have permission from rights holders to reproduce any copyrighted material. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Any disclosures are made in this section. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The external blind peer reviewers report no conflicts of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn id="fn4-ebo-8-2012-545"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Funding </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Author(s) disclose no funding sources. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>1YuanJSTillerKHAl-AhmadHStewartNRStewartCNPlants to power: bioenergy to fuel the futureTrends Plant Sci200813421718632303 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>2WijffelsRHBarbosaMJAn outlook on Microalgal BiofuelsScience2010329796920705853 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>3ChistiYBiodiesel from microalgaeBiotechnol Adv20072529430617350212 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>4PienkosPTDarzinsAThe promise and challenges of microalgal-derived biofuelsBiofuels Biprod Bioref2009343140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>5CourchesneNMDParisienAWangBLanCQEnhancement of lipid production using biochemical, genetic and transcription factor engineering approachesJ Biotechnol2009141314119428728 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>6GoldbergIKCohenZUnravelling algal lipid metabolism, recent advances in gene identificationBiochimie2011939110020709142 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>7RadakovitsRJinkersonREDarzinsAPosewitzMCGenetic Engineering of Algae for Enhanced Biofuel ProductionEukaryot Cell2010948650120139239 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>8RogalskiMCarrerHEngineering plastid fatty acid biosynthesis to improve food quality and biofuel production in higher plantsPlant Biotechnol J201195546421535359 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>9NapierJAThe production of unusual fatty acids in transgenic plantsAnnu Rev Plant Biol20075829531917472567 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>10TopferRMartiniNSchellJModification of Plant Lipid synthesisScience1995268681617832379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>11MaoFYinYZhouFFpDAWG: an integrated database for plant cell-wall genesBioenerg Res2009220916 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>12LinLHuiLYingLJGenome-wide survey of maize lipid-related genes: candidate genes mining, digital expression profiling and co-location with QTL for maize kernel oilSci China Life Sci20105369070020602272 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>13SharmaAChauhanRIn-silico Identification and Comparative Genomics of Candidate Genes Involved in Biosynthesis and Accumulation of Seed Oil in PlantsComp Funct Genom2012Article ID91484311410.1155/2012/914843. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>14Rismani-YazdiHHaznedarogluBZBibbyKPecciaJTranscriptome sequencing and annotation of the microalgae Dunaliella tertiolecta: Pathway description and gene discovery for production of next-generation biofuelsBMC Genomics2011121486521401935 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>15CeruttiHMaXMsanneJRepasTRNA-Mediated silencing in algae: biological roles and tools for gene functionEukaryot Cell20111011647221803865 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>16Reyes-PrietoAYoonHSBhattacharyaDPhylogenomics: its growing impact on Algal Phylogeny and evolutionAlgae200621110 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>17BeissonFKooAJKRuuskaSArabidopsis genes involved in acyl lipid metabolism: a 2003 census of the candidates, a study of the distribution of expressed Sequence Tags in Organs, and a web based databasePlant Physiol200313268297 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>18AltschulSFGishWMillerWMyerEWLipmanDJBasic Local Alignment Search ToolJ Mol Biol1990215403102231712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>19TatusovRLFederovaNDJacksonJDThe COG database: an updated version includes eukaryotesBioinformatics20034415512969510 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>20CarbonSIrelandAMungaliCJShuSQMarshalBLewisSAmiGo-online access to ontology and annotation dataBioinformatics200925288919033274 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>21KanehisaMGotoSKawashimaSOkunoYHattoriMThe KEGG resource for deciphering the genomeNucleic Acids Res20043227780 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>22WheelockCEGotoSYetukuriLBioinformatics strategies for the analyses of lipidsMethods Mol Biol20095803396819784609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>23MoriyaYItohMOkudaSYoshizawaACKanehisaMKAAS: an automatic genome annotation and pathway reconstruction serverNucleic Acids Res200035W182517526522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>24EmanuelssonONielsenHBrunakSvon HeijneGPredicting subcellular localization of proteins based on their N-terminal amino acid sequencesJ Mol Biol200030010051610891285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>25EmanuelssonONielsenHBrunakSvon HeijneGChloroP: a neural network based method for predicting chloroplast transit peptides and their cleavage sitesProtein Sci199989788410338008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>26HortonPParkKJObayashiTWolfPsort-protein localization predictorNucleic Acids Res200735W585717517783 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>27GuruprasadKReddyBVPPanditMVCorrelation between stability of a protein and its dipeptide composition: a novel approach for predicting in vivo stability of a protein from its primary sequenceProt Eng1990415564 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>28IkaiAJThermo stability and aliphatic index of globular proteinsJ Biochem198088189518987462208 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>29DoolittleRFKA simple method for displaying the hydropathic character of a proteinJ Mol Biol1982157105327108955 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>30GasteigerEHooglandCGattikerAProtein identification and analyses tools on the Expasy’s serverMethods Mol Biol19991125315210027275 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>31GarnierJGibratJFRobsonBGOR IV secondary structure prediction method version IVMethod Enzymol199626654053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>32BurgeCKarlinSPrediction of complete gene structures in human genomic DNAJ Mol Biol199726878949149143 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>33BaileyTLWilliamsNMislenCLiWWMEME: discovering and analyzing DNA and protein sequence motifsNucleic Acids Res200634W3697316845028 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>34QuevillonESilventoinenVPillaiSInterProscan: protein domains identifierNucleic Acids Res200533W121620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>35HallTABioEdit: A user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NTNucleic Acid Symp Ser199941958 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>36ChennaRSugawaraHKoikeTMultiple sequence alignment with the Clustal series of programsNucleic Acids Res200331349750012824352 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>37TamuraKDudleyJNeiMKumarSMEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0Mol Biol Evol2007241596917488738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>38ScottSADaveyMPDennisJSBiodiesel from algae: challenges and prospectsCurr Opin Biotechnol2010212778620399634 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>39ColemanRALeeDPEnzymes of triacylglycerol synthesis and their regulationProg Lipid Res2004431347614654091 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>40JangaSCDiaz-MeijiaJJMoreno-HagelsiebGNetwork-based function prediction and interactomics: The case for metabolic enzymesMetab Eng20111311020654726 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b41-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>41DaviesMSSolbiatiJCronanJEJrOverproduction of acetyl-CoA carboxylase activity increases the rate of fatty acid biosynthesis in Escherichia coliJ Biol Chem200027528593810893421 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b42-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>42DunahayTGJarvisEERoesslerPGGenetic transformation of the diatoms Cyclotella cryptica and Navicula saprophilaJ Phycol199531100412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b43-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>43KlausDOhlroggeJBNeuhausHEDormanPIncreased fatty acid production in potato by engineering of acetyl-CoA carboxylasePlanta20042193899615014998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b44-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>44RatledgeCFatty acid biosynthesis in microorganisms being used for single cell oil productionBiochimie2004868071515589690 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b45-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>45RoeslerKShintaniDSavageLBodderpalliSOhlroggeJTargeting of the Arabidopsis homomeric acetyl-coenzyme A carboxylase to plastids of rapeseedsPlant Physiol19971375819008389 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b46-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>46ThelenJJOhlroggeJBMetabolic engineering of fatty acid biosynthesis in plantsMetab Eng1200241122111800570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b47-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>47DeheshKEdwardPFillattiJSlabaughMByrneJKAS IVa 3-ketoacyl-ACP synthase from Cuphea sp is a medium chain specific condensing enzymePlant J199815383909750349 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b48-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>48DeheshKTaiHEdwardsPByrneJJaworskiJGOverexpresssion of 3-ketoacyl-acyl-carrier protein synthase IIIs in plants reduces the rate of lipid synthesisPlant Physiol200112511031411161065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b49-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>49JiangPCronanJEInhibition of fatty acid synthesis in Escherichia coli in the absence of phospholipid synthesis and release of inhibition by thioesterase actionJ Bacteriol19941762814217910602 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b50-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>50VoelkerTADaviesHMAlteration of the specificity and regulation of fatty acid synthesis of Escherichia coli by expression of a plant medium-chain acyl-acyl carrier protein thioesteraseJ Bacteriol1994176732077961504 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b51-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>51VoelkerTAWorrellACAndersonLFatty acid biosynthesis redirected to medium chains in transgenic oil seed plantsScience19922577241621095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b52-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>52DeheshKJonesAKnutzonDSVoelkerTAProduction of high levels of 8:0 and 10:0 fatty acids in transgenic canola by overexpresssion of Ch FatB2, a thioesterase cDNA from Cuphea hookerianaPlant J19969167728820604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b53-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>53EcclestonVSOhlroggeJBExpression of lauroyl-acyl carrier protein thioesterase in Brassica napus seeds induced pathways for both fatty acid oxidation and biosynthesis implies a set point for TAG accumulationPlant Cell199810613229548986 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b54-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>54FuldaMSchnurrJAbbadiAHeinzEPeroxisomal Acyl-CoA synthetase activity is essential for seedling development in Arabidopsis thalianaPlant Cell20041639440514742880 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b55-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>55RylottELRogersCAGildayADEdgellTLarsonTRGrahamIAArabidopsis mutants in short and medium chain acyl-CoA oxidase activities accumulate acyl-CoAs and reveal that fatty acid beta oxidation is essential for embryo developmentJ Biol Chem200327821370712682048 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b56-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>56BondarukMJohnsonSDegafuAExpression of a cDNA encoding palmitoyl-acyl carrier protein desaturase from cats claw (Doxantha unguis-cati L.) in Arabidopsis thaliana and Brassica napus leads to accumulation of unusual unsaturated fatty acids and increased stearic acid content in the seed oilPlant Breeding200712618694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b57-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>57CahoonEBLindqvistYSchneiderGShanklinJRedesign of soluble fatty acid desaturases from plants for altered substrate specificity and double bond positionP Natl Acad Sci U S A19979448727 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b58-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>58CahoonEBShahSShanklinJBrowseJA determinant of substrate specificity predicted from the acyl-acyl carrier protein desaturase of developing cat’s claw seedPlant Physiol199811759389625712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b59-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>59CahoonEBShanklinJSubstrate-dependent mutant complementation to select fatty acid desaturase variants for metabolic engineering of plant seed oilsP Natl Acad Sci U S A200097123505 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b60-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>60VigeolasHWaldeckPZankTGeigenbergerPIncreasing seed oil content in oilseed rape Brassica napus (L) by overexpresssion of a yeast glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase under the control of a seed specific promoterPlant Biotechnol J200754314117430545 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b61-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>61JainRKCoffeyMLaiKKumarAMackenzieSLEnhancement of seed oil content by expression of glycerol-3-phosphate acyltransferase genesBiochem Soc Trans20002895960 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b62-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>62VigeolasHGeigenbergerPIncreased levels of glycerol-3-phosphate lead to a stimulation of flux into triacylglycerol synthesis after supplying glycerol to developing seeds of Brassica napus LPlanta20042198273515107995 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b63-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>63TaylorDCKatavicVZouJTField testing of transgenic rapeseed cv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Hero transformed with a yeast sn-2 acyltransferase results in increased oil content, erucic acid content and seed yieldMol Breed2002831722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b64-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>64ZouJTKatavicVGiblinEMModification of seed oil content and acyl composition in the Brassicaceae by expression of a yeast sn-2 acyltransferase genePlant Cell1997990223 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b65-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>65JakoCKumarAWeiYSeed specific overexpresssion of an Arabidopsis cDNA encoding a diacylglycerol acyltransferase enhances seed oil content and seed weightPlant Physiol20011268617411402213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b66-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>66LardizabalKEffertzRLeveringCExpression of Umbelopsis ramaniana DGAT2A in seed increases in soybeanPlant Physiol2008148899618633120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b67-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>67ZhengPAllenWBRoeslerKA phenylalanine in DGAT is a key determinant of oil content and composition in maizeNat Genet2008403677118278045 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b68-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>68Bouvier-NavePBenvenistePOelkersPSturleySLSchallerHExpression in yeast and tobacco of plant cDNA encoding acyl-CoA: diacylglycerol acyltransferaseEur J Biochem2000267859610601854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b69-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>69RoutaboulJMBenningCCabocheMLepinincLThe TAG1 locus of Arabidopsis encodes for a diacylglycerol acyltransferasePlant Physiol Biochem1999378314010580283 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b70-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>70KatavicVReedDWTaylorDCAlteration of seed fatty-acid composition by an ethyl methane sulfonate- induced mutation in Arabidopsis thaliana affecting diacylglycerol acyltransferase activityPlant Physiol19951083994097784510 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b71-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>71TaylorDCKatavicVZouJTField testing of transgenic rapeseed cv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Hero transformed with a yeast sn-2 acyltransferase results in increased oil content, erucic acid content and seed yieldMol Breed2002831722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b72-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>72TaylorDCZhangYKumarAMolecular modification of triacylglycerol accumulation by over-expression of DGAT1 to produce canola with increased seed oil content under field conditionsBotany20098753343 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b73-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>73BurgalJShockeyJLuCMetabolic engineering of hydroxyl fatty acid production in plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>RcDGAt2 drives dramatic increases in ricinoleate levels in seed oilPlant Biotechnol J200888193118643899 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b74-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>74GrahamIASeed storage oil mobilizationAnnu Rev Plant Biol2008591154218444898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b75-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>75SatoNMoriyamaTGenomic and Biochemical Analysis of Lipid Biosynthesis in the Unicellular Rhodophyte Cyanidioschyzon merolae: Lack of a Plastidic Desaturation Pathway Results in the Coupled Pathway of Galactolipid SynthesisEukaryot Cell2007610061717416897 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b76-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>76OhlroggeJBrowseJLipid biosynthesisPlant Cell19957957707640528 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b77-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>77LileyKSDupreePPlant organelle proteomicsCurr Opin Plant Biol200710594917913569 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b78-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>78ShenYOBurgerG‘Unite and conquer’: enhanced prediction of protein subcellular localization by integrating multiple specialized toolsBMC Bioinformatics200784203117967180 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b79-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>79HeazlewoodJLVerboomReTonti-FilippiniJSmallIMillarAHSUBA: the Arabidopsis subcellular databaseNucleic Acids Res200735D213817071959 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b80-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>80PeetersNSmallJDual targeting to mitochondria and chloroplastBiochim Biophys Acta20011541546311750662 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b81-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>81MillarAHWhelanJSmallIRecent surprises in protein targeting to mitochondria and plastidsCurr Opin Plant Biol20069610517008120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b82-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>82LiSEhrhardtDWRheeSYSystematic analyses of Arabidopsis organelles and a protein localization database for facilitating fluorescent tagging of full-length Arabidopsis proteinsPlant Physiol20061415273916617091 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b83-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>83VicentiniRMenossiMThe predicted subcellular localisation of the sugarcane proteomeFunct Plant Biol20093624250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b84-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>84HyunjongBLeeDSHwangIDual targeting of xylanase to chloroplasts and Peroxisomes as a means to increase protein accumulation in plant cellsJ Exp Bot200657161916317036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b85-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>85CaoHStructure-Function analyses of Diacyl-glycerol Acyltransferase sequences from 70 organismsBMC Research Notes201142497221777418 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b86-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>86MisumiOYoshidaYNishidaKGenome analyses and its significance in four unicellular algae, Cyanidioschyzon merolae, Ostreococcus tauri, Chlamydomonas reinhardtii and Thalassiosira pseudonanaJ Plant Res200812131718074102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b87-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>87PalenikBGrimwoodJAertsAThe tiny eukaryote Ostreococcus provides genomic insights into the paradox of plankton speciationP Natl Acad Sci Biol2007104770510 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b88-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>88MatsuzakiMMisumiOShinITGenome sequence of the ultrasmall unicellular red algae Cyanidioschyzon merolae 10DNature2004428653715071595 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b89-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>89ProchnikSEUmenJNedelcuAMGenomic Analysis of Organismal Complexity in the Multicellular Green Alga Volvox carteriScience2010329223620616280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b90-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>90LabadorfALinkARogersMFGenome-wide analyses of alternative splicing in Chlamydomonas reinhardtiiBMC Genomics2010111142420163725 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b91-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>91FergusonAAJiangNPack-MULES: recycling and reshaping genes through GC-biased acquisitionMobile Genetic Elements20111135822016862 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b92-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>92MerchantSSProchnikSEVallonOThe Chlamydomonas genome reveals the evolution of key animal and plant functionsScience20073182455017932292 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b93-ebo-8-2012-545"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>93YoonHSHackettJDCingliaCPintoGBhattacharyaDA molecular timeline for the origin of photosynthetic eukaryotesMol Biol Evol2004218091814963099 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f1-ebo-8-2012-545" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Schematic overview of Triacylglyceride (TAG) biosynthetic pathway in microalgae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Notes: Free fatty acids and TAG are synthesised in the chloroplast and endoplasmic reticulum respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>The vital enzymes reported by various experimental studies to be involved in accelerated lipid accumulation are marked with an asterisk. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: ACC, Acetyl-CoA carboxylase; MAT, Malonyl-CoA-ACP transacylase; KAS, 3-ketoacyl-ACP synthase; KAR, 3-ketoacyl-ACP reductase; HAD, 3-hydroxyacyl-ACP dehydratases; EAR, Enoyl-ACP reductase; FAT, Fatty acid thioesterase; G3PDH, Glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase; GPAT, Glycerol-3-phosphate acyltransferase; AGPAT, 1-acylglycerol-3-phosphate acyltransferase also known as LPAT, lysophosphatidic acid acyl transferase; PP, Phosphatidate phosphatase; DGAT, Diacylglycerol acyltransferase. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ebo-8-2012-545f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f2-ebo-8-2012-545" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Number of gene homologues in the TAG biosynthetic pathway in A. thaliana, C. reinhardtii, V. carteri, O. lucimarinus, O. tauri and C. merolae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Notes: For each reaction, coloured squares denotes the number of homologous genes in A. thaliana (blue), C. reinhardtii (yellow), V. carteri (pink), O. lucimarinus (green), O. tauri (purple) and C. merolae (light blue). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ebo-8-2012-545f2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f3-ebo-8-2012-545" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Distribution of various physico-chemical characteristics of putative proteins encoded by lipid genes in A. thaliana, C. reinhardtii, V. carteri, O. lucimarinus, O. tauri and C. merolae. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Note: The individual physico-chemical values for each protein as calculated by ProtParam server is provided in Supplementary Table 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ebo-8-2012-545f3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f4-ebo-8-2012-545" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the GC-content of lipid biosynthetic genes among five unicellular algae and the vascular plant, A. thaliana. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Notes: Columns represent the average GC content of the genes (in percentage) of each organism: A. thaliana (blue), C. reinhardtii (red), V. carteri (green), O. lucimarinus (purple), O. tauri (blue) and C. merolae (orange) in a down to up order. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The individual GC-content values of each gene as calculated by Genscan web server are given in Supplementary Table 4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ebo-8-2012-545f4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f5-ebo-8-2012-545" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Conserved domain architectures and sequence logo plots of lipid biosynthetic genes using InterProscan and MEME programs, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Notes: The overall height of each stack indicated the sequence conservation at that position, whereas the height of symbols within each stack reflects the relative frequency of the corresponding amino acid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>The amino acids are colour coded as: A, C, F, I, L, V, W and M (Blue-Most hydrophobic); N, Q, S and T (Green-Polar, non-charged and non-aliphatic residues); D and E (Magenta-Acidic); K and R (Red-Positively charge). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ebo-8-2012-545f5"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f6-ebo-8-2012-545" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>(A) Phylogenetic tree inferred from the amino acid sequences of lipid genes in A. thaliana, C. reinhardtii, V. carteri, O. lucimarinus, O. tauri and C. merolae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Proteins with identical functional characterization are represented by similar colour coded diamond shapes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Protein accession numbers are represented while organism names to which proteins belong are given in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Some homologous proteins were omitted to increase clarity of the remaining groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>The tree indicates that proteins with similar functions were clustered together and further, in most of the gene families for instance in desaturase (B), the protein sequence of the two sub-species O. lucimarinus and O. tauri were present as sister clades and falls within the green algal cluster comprising of C. reinhardtii, V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Carteri and A. thaliana, while the protein homologs of C. merolae seem to diverge from the root of the green lineage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ebo-8-2012-545f6"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="t1-ebo-8-2012-545" position="float"><label>Table I</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Candidate genes involved in lipid biosynthetic pathway of Arabidopsis thaliana, Chlamydomonas reinhardtii, Volvox carteri, Ostreococcus lucimarinus, Ostreococcus tauri and Cyanidioschyzon merolae genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1-ebo-8-2012-545"><p><bold>Notes:</bold></p></fn><fn id="tfn2-ebo-8-2012-545"><label>*</label><p>Putative uncharacterized proteins;</p></fn><fn id="tfn3-ebo-8-2012-545"><label>†</label><p>predicted proteins;</p></fn><fn id="tfn4-ebo-8-2012-545"><label>•</label><p>probable proteins;</p></fn><fn id="tfn5-ebo-8-2012-545"><label>Δ</label><p>similar protein;</p></fn><fn id="tfn6-ebo-8-2012-545"><label>¶</label><p>absent in KEGG pathway database;</p></fn><fn id="tfn7-ebo-8-2012-545"><label>**</label><p>relevant references on experimental evidences of the respective enzyme action influencing lipid accumulation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
