
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3324410</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22509378</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-03731</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035041</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Population Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic Polymorphism</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Human Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic Association Studies</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genome-Wide Association Studies</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Epidemiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Obstetrics and Gynecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Sexual Dysfunction</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Women's Health</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>A Genome-Wide Association Study of Female Sexual Dysfunction </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">GWAS on FSD</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Burri</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hysi</surname><given-names>Pirro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Clop</surname><given-names>Alex</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>Qazi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Spector</surname><given-names>Tim D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Biological and Experimental Psychology Group, School of Biological and Chemical Sciences, Queen Mary University of London, London, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Twin Research and Genetic Epidemiology, King’s College London, London, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Medical and Molecular Genetics, School of Medicine, King's College London, London, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Qingyang</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Central China Normal University, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>andrea.burri@kcl.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: AB PH TS AC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: AB PH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: AB PH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: AB QR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e35041</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>2</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Burri et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Female sexual dysfunction (FSD) is an important but controversial problem with serious negative impact on women’s quality of life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Data from twin studies have shown a genetic contribution to the development and maintenance of FSD. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Methodology/Principal Findings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>We performed a genome-wide association study (GWAS) on 2.5 million single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in 1,104 female twins (25–81 years of age) in a population-based register and phenotypic data on lifelong sexual functioning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Although none reached conventional genome-wide level of significance (10×-8), we found strongly suggestive associations with the phenotypic dimension of arousal (rs13202860, P = 1.2×10−7; rs1876525, P = 1.2×10−7; and rs13209281 P = 8.3×10−7) on chromosome 6, around 500kb upstream of the locus HTR1E (5-hydroxytryptamine receptor 1E) locus, related to the serotonin brain pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>We could not replicate previously reported candidate SNPs associated with FSD in the DRD4, 5HT2A and IL-1B loci. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Conclusions/Significance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>We report the first GWAS of FSD symptoms in humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>This has pointed to several “risk alleles” and the implication of the serotonin and GABA pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Ultimately, understanding key mechanisms via this research may lead to new FSD treatments and inform clinical practice and developments in psychiatric nosology. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="7"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>People vary in their enjoyment of sexual activity and relationships – a source of significant mental wellbeing or problems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Female sexual dysfunction (FSD) describes a cluster of sexual symptoms including desire, arousal, orgasm and pain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>It appears relatively common in the general community and population-level samples and is associated with a severe decrease in quality of life in women [1]–[3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The etiology of FSD is largely unknown although several biological and psychological correlates have been reported [3]–[5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, no clear disease mechanisms have emerged and this lack of knowledge has hampered progress in both, psychiatric nosology and treatment strategies for this growing burden on women’s psychiatric health. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Both, the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 4th Edition and International Classification of Diseases, Tenth Revision [6] have arranged FSD into categories based largely on clinical similarities, while in 1998 a consensus based definition and classification system was designed by a panel of experts during the International Consensus Development [7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Biological research into FSD is woefully inadequate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Recent twin studies suggest FSD is familial, with genetic factors accounting for up to 51% of the phenotypic variance [8]–[10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Twin studies also show evidence of genetic and environmental contributions to psychological factors previously linked to FSD (such as depression, anxiety, personality traits) [11]–[13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Thus, it is possible that some of the covariation between FSD and these psychological correlates is explained by shared genetic and non-genetic factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>However, there have been no large-scale studies to identify single genes or gene variants robustly associated with FSD-phenotypes (and no genome-wide association study - GWAS - has ever been performed). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>To date, only a handful of candidate gene studies of sexual desire and function exist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>One candidate gene study has linked serotonin polymorphisms (5HT2A) to reduced sexual desire as a side-effect of SSRI-medication in 89 adult men and women [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>A further study reported an association between the dopamine D4 receptor gene (DRD4) with self-reports of sexual desire and arousal in 52 men and 92 women [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Interleukin-1beta gene (IL-1B) has been correlated with variation in vulvar vestibulitis syndrome scores, a broader phenotype for sexual pain symptoms [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>All these studies have methodological shortcomings that limit their interpretation, primarily the candidate gene design, small samples in mostly clinical populations (thus lacking power to detect phenotype – DNA variant associations), and the use of non-standardized instruments that lack coverage of the phenotypic heterogeneity in sexual function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Moreover, none of these studies examine women and FSD directly, making them unsuitable for clarifying the etiological mechanisms under FSD at the population-level. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>We present here the results of the first GWAS of FSD in a female population-sample published to date. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>By scanning a dense set of genetic variants throughout the whole genome, we can test replication of previously located genes from candidate gene investigations and also identify novel genes that may lead to the discovery of unknown biological pathways involved in the development of FSD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The TwinsUK adult twin registry based at St. Thomas’ Hospital in London is a volunteer cohort of over 10,000 twins from the general population [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>This twin population has been involved in a wide range of studies on common traits and diseases and has been shown to be representative of the general population for a wide variety of medical, behavioral, and sexual traits [3], [18], [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The twins were not selected on the basis of the phenotypes being studied and were unaware of any hypothesis being tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>All twins provided written informed consent and the study was approved by St. Thomas’ Hospital Research Ethics Committee. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>All participants were dizygotic (DZ) pairs and monozygotic (MZ) singleton twins of white European ancestry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>A total of 1,489 subjects were included, all sexually active, heterosexual with no history of any major psychological or medical condition (depression, bipolar disorder, anxiety disorder, diabetes, multiple sclerosis, endometriosis) and with all items on the Female Sexual Function Index-Lifelong (FSFI-LL) available. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Sexual Dysfunction Phenotype </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>We used the recently developed 19-item Female FSFI-LL questionnaire to measure long-term variation in female sexuality, including periods of dysfunction and healthy function [20], [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>For genetic analysis, the FSFI-LL is preferable to the “snapshot” measures used in some previous research and it better captures the variation in enduring female sexual functioning required for resolving the underlying genetic and non-genetic mechanisms of FSD symptoms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The FSFI-LL assesses 6 dimensions of women’s average sexual functioning “since they have been sexually active” including desire (2 items), arousal (4 items), lubrication (4 items), orgasm (3 items), satisfaction (3 items), and pain (3 items). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Desire items are rated on a Likert-type scale ranging from 1 to 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The remaining items are rated from 0 to 5 with the supplementary option “no sexual activity”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Dimension scores are derived by summing the item scores within each dimension and multiplying the sum by the dimension factor weight [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The dimension factor weighting converts the dimension scores to a consistent range from 0 to 6, except for the desire, which has a dimension score range from 1.2 to 6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Total scores are calculated via a simple computer algorithm and low scores on the FSFI-LL indicate more sexual problems and high scores indicate fewer problems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The FSFI-LL has excellent psychometric properties for both, total- and dimensions-specific scores, including test-retest reliability, internal consistency, external/discriminant validity [20], [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Exploratory and confirmatory factor analyses have successfully reproduced the original factor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>According to response operator curve (ROC)-derived cut-off scores, all dimensions and the total FSD score displayed a good sensitivity to 1-specificity profile (as measured by the area under the curve = AUC), with arousal (AUC = 0.92) displaying the best trade-off and desire the lowest (AUC = 67.55%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Overall, the FSFI-LL demonstrates excellent comparability to the standard FSFI in terms of factor structure and psychometric properties [21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Detailed information on prevalences, potential environmental risk factors and heritability estimates for FSD-symptoms in this panel are reported elsewhere (3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Genotyping, Quality Control, and Imputation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Genotyping was carried out using two genotyping platforms from Illumina: the HumanHap 300k Duo for a part of the TwinsUK Cohort (n = 505) and the HumanHap610-Quad array for the remainder of the TwinsUK Cohort (n = 599). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Genotyping with the HumanHap 300k Duo was conducted at the Centre National de Génotypage, Duke University, NC, USA; Helsinki University, Finland; and the Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute, Cambridge, UK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Genotyping with the Infinium 610k assay (Illumina, Inc., San Diego, USA) for the remaining individuals was conducted at the Centre for Inherited Diseases Research (USA) and the Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>We applied stringent quality control (QC) criteria to the genotype data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Genotypes were cleaned before analysis by removing single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) or individuals not fulfilling the QC criteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The following QC filters were applied for samples: call rate at least 95%; autosomal heterozygosity between 33 and 37%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>At the SNP level, Hardy Weinberg Equilibrium (HWE) with P-value &gt;10−4, Minor Allele Frequency (MAF) at least 1%, and call rate at least 95% for SNPs with MAF 0.05 and above or at least 99% for SNPs with MAF less than 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>We further visually inspected all intensity cluster plots of SNPs that showed either an association for over-dispersion of the clusters, biased no calling, or erroneous genotype assignment and discarded all SNPs with any of these characteristics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Genotypes from the TwinsUK were imputed using the genotypes from the 3,855,687 autosomal markers available from the HapMap Phase 2 CEPH population [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>After imputation using IMPUTE2 a total of 2,558,978 non-monomorphic autosomal markers became available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>After removing very rare markers (MAF&lt;0.1) and markers in Hardy-Weinberg Disequilibrium (p&lt;e−6) and individual with poor imputation scores (&lt;0.5), we obtained results from 2,287,762 loci across the chromosome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Of the 1,489 women with recorded phenotype, genotype data was available for 1,104 subjects after QC check. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Data handling and preliminary analyses were conducted using STATA software (StataCorp., College Station, TX) and Merlin (PMID 11731797) [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Association analyses were performed using MERLIN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Ancestry was determined through principal component analysis of individual genotypes (compared with subjects participating in the HapMap Phase II standard populations). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>All traits were included in multiple regression models, with age and menopausal state included as covariates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Traits were inverse-normalized to avert undue effects of non-normality of their distributions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Regression slopes (β) are given as numbers of standard deviation units per each additional copy of the effect allele from this point onwards in the text. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Given the experimental size with hundreds of thousands of SNPs being analysed individually, the commonly used “genome wide significance” (GWS) threshold was used which is the standard approximation routinely set at 5×10−8 [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>However, given the cost of a strict Bonferroni adjustment in results from relatively small datasets, we considered all the associations with P≤5×10−5, as others have done in other studies of similar sizes (UK IBD Genetics Consortium, 2009; Amundadottir et al., 2009) [25], [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Racial and ethnicity stratification was checked through eigenvector analysis and the above mentioned samples only contained individuals of certified and pure European ancestry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The genotyped samples were tested for population stratification, by comparison to the three HapMap phase 2 reference populations (CEU, YRI, CHB+JPT; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hapmap.org">www.hapmap.org</ext-link>) using principal component analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The mean age of participants in the study was 57 years (range 25–81 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The GWAS analysis was performed using both observed and imputed genotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The genomic inflation factor (λ) ranged from 0.98 to 0.99 for the different phenotypes, showing no evidence for population stratification or inflated results due to imputation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>We identified 34SNPs with P-values &lt;10−5 of association with FSD-related measures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>These results are summarized in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The most significant association was found between rs13202860 on chromosome 6 and sexual arousal, with P = 1.2×10−7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Two additional nearby SNPs showed P-values less than 4×10−7, (rs1876525, rs13209281; P = 1.2×10−7 and 8.3×10−7, respectively; Table 1 and Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>All three SNPs were associated with arousal levels and spanned a region of 11 kb, around 500 kbp upstream from the HTR1E (5-hydroxytryptamine receptor 1E) locus (Figure 2 and Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0035041-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035041.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Manhattan plots describing the association of 2.5 M SNPs with sexual arousal, lubrication and overall sexual functioning. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>SNPs with P≤10–6 are highlighted with a red circle (n = 1104 females). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0035041.g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0035041-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035041.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Association scatter plot for SNPs in the gene desert approximately 1Mbp upstream of the HTR1E gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>TwinsUK discovery cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Negative logarithms of the P values for the association of each SNP with spherical equivalence are plotted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The lead SNP is plotted in diamond shape, with the GWAS-analysis P value for that SNP indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Genotyped SNPs are plotted as squares, with the colour indicating the degree of pairwise LD between the lead and neighbouring SNPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Red indicates strong pairwise LD, with r2≥0.8; orange indicates moderate LD, with 0.5&lt;r2&lt;0.8 yellow indicates weak LD, with 0.2&lt;r2&lt;0.5; and white indicates no LD, with r2&lt;0.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The recombination rates are shown as light blue line. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0035041.g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0035041-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035041.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Haploview LD plot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The plot uses the hapmapPhase3 data on the CEU and the TSI Caucasian populations and encompasses an 800 kbp segment containing the associated SNP on chromosome 6 and HTR1E. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The LD blocks were defined by confidence intervals according to Gabriel and colleagues [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The x-axis corresponds to the genomic position in kb and the red triangles defined by black lines represent LD blocks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The yellow arrow and the red box indicate the location of three GWAS associated SNP and the position of HTR1E, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0035041.g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0035041-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035041.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Top SNPs associated with sexual function related measures in a cohort of females of European ancestry. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0035041-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0035041.t001"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>*</label><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Effect, β coefficient of linear regression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The effect sizes denote changes in phenotype unit per each additional copy of the reference allele. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>We also identified a locus on chromosome 22 with multiple adjacent SNPs showing similar, albeit modest levels of associations with overall sexual function (Table 1; Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Association was maximal for rs4820255 and rs4821535 (both P = 1.2×10−6), two SNP located 344 bp apart within intron 3 of the parvalbumin (PVALB) gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Similarly, six SNPs associated with lubrication levels could be detected (P&lt;3×10−6 for all) on chromosome 10 near the EPC1 gene (Table 1; Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Previous association studies have suggested several potential candidates to be associated with FSD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>More specifically, earlier studies identified several variants on the dopamine D4 receptor (DRD4) and the serotonin 2A receptor gene (5HT2A) to be linked with levels of sexual desire and arousal (14,15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>In this GWAS, observed and/or imputed genotype information was available for 2 SNPs in the DRD4, 5 SNPS in the 5HT2A and 3 SNPS in the IL-1B gene, and were hence evaluated for the replication of previously reported associations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>However, none of the markers showed significant associations with the previously suggested phenotypes (or with any of the outcome variables), as displayed in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0035041-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035041.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>P-values of available markers in our GWAS, reported to be associated with specific sexual problems in previous candidate gene studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0035041-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0035041.t002"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label>*</label><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Bonferroni corrected p-value. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Here we reported the results of the first ever GWAS of female sexual function levels in an unselected population-based cohort of British women. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>There were no associations at conventional genome-wide level of significance (P&lt;5×10−8), but we found strongly suggestive associations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Several studies of similar size have considered any association with P-values ≤1×10−5 as being suggestive [25], [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Moreover, numerous suggestive associations below the genome-wide cut-off have been replicated in independent studies, strongly suggesting that these are indeed real associations rather than spurious results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>For example, the Genetic Analysis of Psoriasis Consortium &amp; the Wellcome Trust Case Control Consortium 2 in a GWAS study for psoriasis, replicated many of the suggestive associations found by Nair and colleagues including SNP nearby IL-23A and TNFIP3 with P≤2×10−5 and P≤1×10−5, respectively [27], [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Here, we identified several strong suggestive associations with much stronger levels of significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Our strongest association (P 1.2x10−7), was on the phenotypic dimension of arousal with a serotonin receptor gene (HTR1E) which represents a strong biological candidate previously shown to be involved in female sexuality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>This potential susceptibility locus resides within a ∼1 Mbp segment of the genome devoid of annotated genes, located about 500 kbp downstream of the HTR1E gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>To assess the relationship between rs13202860 and HTR1E we plotted the LD pattern of the region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>HapMap 3 data from two Caucasian populations (CEU and TSI) shows that rs13202860, rs1876525 and rs13209281, which show association with arousal in our study, are located in different LD blocks than HTR1E (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Although HTR1E is an interesting candidate gene because of its known physiology, the large distance between both loci, together with the evidence that the significant SNP lie in other LD blocks than HTR1E clearly suggest that these three SNPs are tagging independent associations and that the causal polymorphism is more likely to regulate gene expression rather than the protein structure of HTR1E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Enhancers are elements of the genome that regulate gene expression of nearby or distant genes and which can be located within gene deserts [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Recent research suggests that polymorphisms in gene deserts could impact on disease by altering an enhancer element [29]–[31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Thus, it is possible that our causal variant is altering an enhancer element located in the gene desert influencing HTR1E. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>HTR1E encodes one of the families of highly conserved serotonin receptor genes and is strongly expressed in neurons, primarily in limbic brain regions (including caudate putamen, claustrum, hippocampus, and amygdala) [32]–[33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>This high degree of evolutionary conservation of genetic sequence suggests an important physiological role of the HTR1E receptor in humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>However, the actual function of the HTR1E receptor remains unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, HTR1E is a gene with considerable biological relevance to our phenotype of sexual functioning as it shares amino acid sequence homologies and some pharmacological characteristics with other 5-HT receptors (serotonin) and is therefore closely related. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Comparative research has documented the critical role of serotonin receptors in modulating human and non-human mammalian sexual behavior and functioning acting on both central and peripheral (genital) sites [34]–[35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>SSRI (selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors)-associated sexual side effects, which include peripheral dysfunctions (e.g., erectile) as well as central problems in desire and arousal are well documented at high prevalence among users (up to 60%) [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>These post-SSRI sexual dysfunctions (PSSD) point strongly to the involvement of serotonin receptors in human sexual behavior. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Central serotonergic activity affects female sexual functioning via limbic projections of serotonin neurotransmitter are co-localized with norepinephrine receptors – and both transmitters seem to work in conjunction in the regulation of arousal and lubrication [35], [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>However, the involvement of serotonin receptors in several reward-related behavioral functions (e.g. satiety, sexual behavior, nociception, escape, and stress) suggests that these receptors may function in the “higher-order” integration of rewarding behavior. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Our finding of a putative association between PVALB and overall sexual functioning scores on the FSFI-LL is entirely new. PVALB is a calcium-binding albumin protein present in GABAergic interneurons, expressed predominantly in the prefrontal cortex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Similar to serotonin, GABA is a major inhibitory neurotransmitter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Several lines of research demonstrate that GABA levels are associated with sexual function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Animal studies show that GABA(A) and GABA(B) receptors are involved in the inhibition of lordosis (a response shown by female animals indicating sexual receptivity) as well as mediating the effects of sex steroids such as estrogen in appetitive sexual behavior (e.g., sexual exploration) [37], [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Elevated levels of stress have also been shown to dampen sexual response in animal models as well as being a significant psychological correlate of FSD in women [39], [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The number of hippocampal PV-containing GABAergic interneurons is highly responsive to chronic external stressors, offering the potential of stress-induced neuro-structural alterations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The EPC1 gene encodes the enhancer of polycomb homolog 1 and is a component of the NuA4 histone acetyltransferase complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Previous research has suggested that this complex may be required for the activation of transcriptional programs associated with oncogene and proto-oncogene mediated growth induction, tumor suppressor mediated growth arrest and replicative senescence, and apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>It has also shown to be involved in skeletal muscle differentiation [41], [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>At this stage it is unclear through which mechanisms EPC1 could have an effect on vaginal lubrication and would need to be further investigated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The present study had some methodological limitations and the findings should be interpreted with caution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Our study sample consisted mostly of peri- or postmenopausal women (70%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>For this reason, representativeness of our study might be limited to the older female population, especially when considering that sexual dysfunction is more common in peri- and postmenopausal than in the non-climacteric period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>However, prevalence rates of FSD in our sample are comparable to estimates found in other, younger populations [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Ideally, although similar populations are hard to come by, it would be important to replicate our GWAS findings in larger and independent samples before pursuing research into the underlying biological disease pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Our sample size may be one reason why our analysis did not reach conventional levels of GWA significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, as is common in this field, there are no additional genotyped cohorts available with matching phenotypic data that could have been used to replicate our findings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Common diseases are typically influenced by multiple environmental as well as genetic factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Our case and control participants may differ systematically for several of these environmental characteristics (e.g. education, anxiety levels, personality) which in turn could theoretically be related to genetic variation and to the disorder itself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Future studies in much larger sample sizes may be able to partition effects of known psychological predictors of FSD (such as sexual distress and anxiety levels) and if family-based differentiate genetic architecture of these co-morbid traits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Current approaches to perform GWAS are most successful if the common disease/common variant (CDCV) assumption holds [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Currently, exome sequencing has proven to be a powerful tool to identify rare coding variants and has the potential to overcome certain GWAS limitations by focusing on the identification of functional genomic structural variants rather than markers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Gene-environment interaction is also likely to have an influence on the development and maintenance of FSD [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>In this regard, high throughput sequencing approaches would be again very useful as it can be used to interrogate functional aspects of the genome to identify epigenetic modifications such as DNA methylation, DNA-protein interaction, chromatin accessibility, etc. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>In summary, we report the first GWAS of female sexual dysfunction symptoms in humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>This has pointed to several “risk alleles” and the implication of the serotonin and GABA pathways which we hope encourages further replication in large and independent population-based cohorts and then biological investigation to elucidate possible mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Ultimately, understanding key mechanisms via this research may lead to new FSD treatments and inform clinical practice and developments in psychiatric nosology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>We thank the staff from the Genotyping Facilities at the Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute led by Leena Peltonen and Panos Deloukas, for sample preparation, quality control, and genotyping; Le Centre National de Genotypage, France, led by Mark Lathrop, for genotyping; Duke University, North Carolina, USA, led by David Goldstein, for genotyping; and the Finnish Institute of Molecular Medicine, Finnish Genome Center, University of Helsinki, led by Aarno Palotie. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Funding: The authors acknowledge financial support from the Wellcome Trust; the National Eye Institute via an National Institutes of Health/Center for Inherited Disease Research (NIH/CIDR) genotyping project; the Department of Health via the National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) comprehensive Biomedical Research Centre award to Guy’s &amp; St Thomas’ National Health Service (NHS) Foundation Trust in partnership with King’s College London; and the Chronic Disease Research Foundation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0035041-Laumann1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>1 LaumannEOPaikARosenRC 1999 Sexual Dysfunction in the United States. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Prevalence and predictors. JAMA 281 537 44 10022110 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Rosen1"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>2 RosenRCTaylorJFLeiblumSRBachmannGA 1993 Prevalence of sexual dysfunction in women: Results of a survey study of 329 women in an outpatient gynecological clinic. J Sex Marital Ther 19 171 88 8246273 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Burri1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>3 BurriASpectorT 2011 Recent and lifelong sexual dysfunctions in a female UK population sample: prevalence and risk factors. J Sex Med 8 2420 2430 21676186 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Derogatis1"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>4 DerogatisLRBurnettAL 2008 The epidemiology of sexual dysfunctions. J Sex Med 5 289 300 18004994 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Hawton1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>5 HawtonDMGathDDayA 2000 Sexual Function in a Community Sample of Middle-Aged Women with Partners: Effects of Age, Marital, Socioeconomic, Psychiatric, Gynecological, and Menopausal Factors. Arch Sex Behav 23 375 395  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Basson1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>6 BassonRBermanJBurnettADerogatisLFergusonD 2000 Report of the international consensus development conference on female sexual dysfunction: Definitions and classifications. J Urol 163 888 893 10688001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Basson2"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>7 BassonRAlthofSDavidSFugl-MeyerKGoldsteinI 2004 Summary of the recommendations on sexual dysfunctions in women. J Sex Med 1 24 34 16422980 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Witting1"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>8 WittingKSantillaPRijsdijkFVarjonenMSternP 2008 Correlated genetic and non-shared environmental influences account for the comorbidity between female sexual dysfunctions. Psychol Med 26 1 13  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Dawood1"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>9 DawoodKKirkKMBaileyJMAndrewsPWMartinNG 2008 Genetic and environmental influences on the frequency of orgasm in women. Twin Res Hum Genet 8 27 33  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Dunn1"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>10 DunnKMCherkasLFSpectorTD 2005 Genetic on variation in female orgasmic function: A twin study. Biol Lett 22 260 26  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Hettema1"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>11 HettemaJMNealeMCKendlerKS 2001 A review and meta-analysis of the genetic epidemiology of anxiety disorders. Am J Psychiatr 158 1568 15 11578982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Sullivan1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>12 SullivanPFNealeMCKendlerKS 2000 Genetic epidemiology of major depression: review and meta-analysis. Am J Psychiatr 157 1552 15 11007705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Jang1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>13 JangKWesleyWJVemonPA 1996 Heritability of the Big Five Personality Dimensions and Their Facets: A Twin Study. J of Pers 64 577 591 8776880 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Bishop1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>14 BishopJRMolineJEllingrodVLSchultzSKClaytonAH 2006 Serotonin 2A-1438 G/A and G-protein Beta3 subunit C825T polymorphismms in patients with depression and SSRI-associated sexual side-effects. Neuropsychopharmacol 31 2281 2288  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-BenZion1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>15 Ben ZionIZTesslerRCohenLLererERazYBachner- MelmanR 2006 Polymorphisms in the dopamine D4 receptor gene (DRD4) contribute to individual differences in human sexual behavior: desire, arousal and sexual function. Mol Psychiatry 11 782 786 16619053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Gerber1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>16 GerberSBongiovanniAMLedgerWJWitkinSS 2003 Interleukin- 1beta gene polymorphism in women with vulvar vestibulitis syndrome. Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol 107 74 7 12593899 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Spector1"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>17 SpectorTWilliamsF 2006 The UK Adult Twin Registry (TwinsUK). Twin Res Hum Genet 9 899 906 17254428 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Andrews1"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="?"><plain>18 AndrewsTHartDJSniederHde LangeMSpectorTD 2001 Are twins and singletons comparable? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>A study of disease-related and lifestyle characteristics. Twin Res Hum Genet 4 464 77  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Snieder1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>19 SniederHMacGregorAJSpectorTD 1998 Genes control the cessation of a woman’s reproductive life: a twin study of hysterectomy and age at menopause. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 83 1875 1880 9626112 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Rosen2"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>20 RosenRBrownCHeimanJLeiblumSMestonC 2000 The Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI): a multidimensional self-report instrument for the assessment of female sexual function. J Sex Mar Ther 26 191 208  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Burri2"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>21 BurriACherkasLSpectorT 2010 Replication of psychometric properties of the FSFI and validation of a modified version (FSFI-LL) assessing lifelong sexual function in an unselected sample of females. J Sex Med 7 3929 39 20722783 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Marcini1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>22 MarciniJHowieBMyersSMcVeanGDonnellyP 2009 A new multipoint method for genome-wide association studies via imputation of genotypes. Nat Genet 39 906 913  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Chen1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>23 ChenWMAbecasisR 2007 Family-based association tests for genomewide association scans. Am J Hum Genet 81 913 26 17924335 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Marcini2"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>24 MarciniJHowieBMyersSMcVeanGDonnellyP 2009 A new multipoint method for genome-wide association studies via imputation of genotypes. Nat Genet 39 906 913  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Dudbridge1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>25 DudbridgeFGusnantoA 2008 Estimation of significance thresholds for genomewide association scans. Genet Epidemiol 32 227 234 18300295 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Amundadottir1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>26 AmundadottirLKraftPStolzenberg-SolomonRZFuchsCSPetersenGM 2009 Genome-wide association study identifies variants in the ABO locus associated with susceptibility to pancreatic cancer. Nat Genet 49 986 90  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-UKIBDGenetics1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>27 UK IBD GeneticsConsortiumBarrettJCLeeJCLeesCWPrescottNJ 2009 Genome-wide association study of ulcerative colitis identifies three new susceptibility loci, including the HNF4A region. Nat Genet 41 1330 4 19915572 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-GeneticAnalysisofPsoriasisConsortium1"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>28 Genetic Analysis of Psoriasis Consortiumthe Wellcome Trust Case Control Consortium2StrangeACaponFSpencerCC 2010 A genome-wide association study identifies new psoriasis susceptibility loci and an interaction between HLA-C and ERAP1. Nat Genet 42 985 90 20953190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Nair1"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>29 NairRPDuffinKCHelmsCDingJStuartPE 2009 : Collaborative Association Study of Psoriasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide scan reveals association of psoriasis with IL-23 and NF-kappaB pathways. Nat Genet 41 199 204 19169254 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Wasserman1"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>30 WassermanNFAneasINobregaMA 2010 An 8q24 gene desert variant associated with prostate cancer risk confers differential in vivo activity to a MYC enhancer. Genome Res 20 1191 7 20627891 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Ghoussaini1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>31 GhoussainiMSongHKoesslerTAl OlamaAAKote-JaraiZ 2008 UK Genetic Prostate Cancer Study Collaborators/British Association of Urological Surgeons’ Section of Oncology; UK ProtecT Study Collaborators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Multiple loci with different cancer specificities within the 8q24 gene desert. J Natl Cancer Inst 100 962 6 18577746 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Harismendy1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>32 HarismendyONotaniDSongXRahimNGTanasaB 2011 9p21 DNA variants associated with coronary artery disease impair interferon-γ signalling response. Nature 470 264 8 21307941 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Barone1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>33 BaronePJordanDAtgerFKoppNFillionG 1994 Quantitative autoradiography of 5-HT1D and 5-HT1E binding sites labelled by [3H]5-HT, in frontal cortex and the hippocampal region of the human brain. Brain Res 638 85 94 8199879 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-ShimronAbarbanell1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>34 Shimron-AbarbanellDNothenMMErdmannJProppingP 1995 : Lack of genetically determined structural variants of the human serotonin-1E (5-HT1E) receptor protein points to its evolutionary conservation. Mol Brain Res 29 387 390 7609628 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Frohlich1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>35 FrohlichPFMestonCM 2000 Evidence that serotonin affects female sexual functioning via peripheral mechanisms. Physiol Behav 71 383 93 11150571 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Zajecka1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>36 ZajeckaJ 2001 Strategies for the treatment of antidepressant-related sexual dysfunction. J Clin Psychiatry 62 35 43  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Frazer1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>37 FrazerAHenslerJG 1999 Serotonin. GJInSiegelBWAgranoffRWAlbersFisherSK Uhler MD (eds.) Basic Neurochemistry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Lippincott-Raven Philadelphia, PA  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Wada1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>38 WadaSYamadaSYamanouchiK 2008 Additive inhibition of lordosis by simultaneous treatments with GABA(A) and GABA(B) receptor agonists, muscimol and baclofen, in female rats. Pharmacol Biochem Res 90 590 3  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Frye1"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>39 FryeCAParisJJ 2011 Effects of neurosteroid actions at N-methyl-D-aspartate and GABA A receptors in the midbrain ventral tegmental area for anxiety-like and mating behavior of female rats. Psychopharmacology 213 93 103 20878318 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Kogan1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>40 KoganMIKalinchenkoSIAvadievaNE 2009 Sexual dysfunction in Russia: risk factors for women. Urologiia 5 8 12  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Ponholzer1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>41 PonholzerARoehlichMRaczUTemmlCMadersbacherS 2005 Female sexual dysfunction in a healthy Austrian cohort: prevalence and risk factors. Eur Urol 47 366 74 15716203 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Doyon1"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>42 DoyonYSelleckWLaneWS 2004 Structural and functional conservation of the NuA4 histone acetyltransferase complex from yeast to humans. Mol Cell Biol 24 1884 96 14966270 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Kim1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>43 KimJRKeeHJKimJYJoungHNamKI 2009 Enhancer of polycomb1 acts on serum response factor to regulate skeletal muscle differentiation. J Biol Chem 284 16308 16 19359245 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Bell1"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>44 BellJTSpectorTD 2011 A twin approach to unraveling epigenetics. Trends in Genetics 27 116 125 21257220 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0035041-Gabriel1"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>45 GabrielSBSchaffnerSFNguyenHMooreJMRoyJ 2002 The structure of haplotype blocks in the human genome. Science 296 2225 2229 12029063 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
