
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4133268</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25121957</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-19101</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104667</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Agriculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Aquaculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Algaculture</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Virology</subject><subj-group><subject>Viral Disease Diagnosis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Rapid Detection of Shrimp White Spot Syndrome Virus by Real Time, Isothermal Recombinase Polymerase Amplification Assay </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">RPA Assay for WSSV</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Xiaoming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Yongxin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Weidmann</surname><given-names>Manfred</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Yingjie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Shuling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yongjie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory of Quality and Safety Risk Assessment for Aquatic Products on Storage &amp; Preservation, Ministry of Agriculture, Shanghai, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Shanghai Engineering Research Center of Aquatic-Product Processing &amp; Preservation, Shanghai, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>College of Food Science and Technology, Shanghai Ocean University, Shanghai, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Institute of Aquaculture, University of Stirling, Stirling, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>
<addr-line>Institute of Biochemistry and Molecular Cell Biology, University of Göttingen, Göttingen, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Pöhlmann</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>German Primate Center, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>yjwang@shou.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: SY YW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: XX YY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: XX YY YW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: XX MW YW. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e104667</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Xia et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Xia et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>White spot syndrome virus (WSSV) causes large economic losses to the shrimp aquaculture industry, and thus far there are no efficient therapeutic treatments available against this lethal virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>In this study, we present the development of a novel real time isothermal recombinase polymerase amplification (RPA) assay for WSSV detection on a small ESEQuant Tube Scanner device. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The RPA sensitivity, specificity and rapidity were evaluated by using a plasmid standard as well as viral and shrimp genomic DNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Compared with qPCR, the RPA assay revealed more satisfactory performance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>It reached a detection limit up to 10 molecules in 95% of cases as determined by probit analysis of 8 independent experiments within 6.41±0.17 min at 39°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Consequently, this rapid RPA method has great application potential for field use or point of care diagnostics. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 41376135), Doctoral Fund of Ministry of Education of China (20133104110006), Innovation Program of Shanghai Municipal Education Commission (14ZZ144), China, and Construction Program of Shanghai Committee of Science and Technology (11DZ2280300), China. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper.</p></notes></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>White spot syndrome virus (WSSV), belonging to the genus Whispovirus of the family Nimaviridae [1], is a highly infectious virus often causing white spots on the exoskeleton of shrimp and infects many crustaceans including shrimps, lobsters, freshwater crayfish and crabs [2]–[4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Since WSSV was first detected in Taiwan in 1992 [5], it has spread worldwide and brought about large economic losses to the shrimp aquaculture industry [4]–[6]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Thus far, unfortunately, effective therapeutic methods are unavailable to block or reduce the outbreaks of WSSV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Hence, powerful surveillance management is crucial to monitor the WSSV spread and infection in brood-stocks, larvae and adult shrimps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>It has been suggested that early diagnosis is one of the most efficient strategies to monitor the WSSV occurrence in shrimp farming facilities [7], [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In 2006, Piepenburg and coauthors reported a novel molecular diagnostic approach, recombinase polymerase amplification (RPA), which coupled isothermal recombinase-driven primer targeting the template with strand-displacement DNA synthesis [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>RPA achieves exponential amplification with no need of pretreatment of the genomic DNA sample and is performed at constant low temperature (39–42°C) [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>In RPA, recombinase UvsX with its co-factor UvsY combines with oligonucleotide primers to generate a recombinase-primer complex; the complex scans for reverse complementary sequences along a DNA template; strand displacement amplification starts with the presence of Sau polymerase (Staphylococcus aureus), once the duplex DNA of primer and template is formed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Based on a fluorescent-labeled probe detection system, the RPA assay is able to achieve a real time recording of the amplification event [10]–[12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Here we present the development and application of a real time RPA assay for rapid detection of WSSV, the most lethal and contagious shrimp pathogen known to date, in order to pave the way for mobile/portable diagnostics of WSSV. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Viral and shrimp DNA samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNAs of WSSV and Penaeus monodon nudivirus (PmNV, the so-called Monodon baculovirus) were kindly provided by the Third Institute of Oceanography, State Oceanic Administration of China and National Taiwan University, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Infectious hypodermal and hematopoietic necrosis virus (IHHNV) genomic DNA was extracted from diseased shrimps in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The shrimps were sampled with permission from an aquaculture farm in Shanghai, China. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Preparation of plasmid standard </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>A 757 bp of WSSV DNA fragment containing vp28 was amplified for preparation of a plasmid standard. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The 50 µl PCR contained 22 ng WSSV DNA, 10 µM of each primer (Table 1), and 25 µl 2×Taqmix (Tiangen, Beijing, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The thermal cycle program was as follows: 94°C for 4 min, followed by 30 cycles of 94°C for 30 s, 60°C for 30 s, 72°C for 60 s and a final extension step of 72°C for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Amplification products were checked by 1.5% agarose gel electrophoresis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The target bands of the amplification products were excised from the gel and purified using QIAquickGel extraction kit (Qiagen, Germany) according to the manufacturer’s instruction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The purified amplicons were ligated into the pGM-T vector using the pGM-T Cloning Kit (Tiangen, Beijing, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The recombinant plasmid was transferred into competent Escherichia coli TOP10 cells (Tiangen, Beijing, China) following the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Recombinant plasmids were identified by colony PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The correct insert was verified by sequencing and quantified by using the Quant-iT PicoGreen dsDNA Reagent and Kits (Invitrogen, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0104667-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104667.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>PCR primers used in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0104667-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0104667.t001"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>WSSV PCR-757 FP and RP were used for the PCR-cloning of vp28. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>VP28–140F and R were used in qPCR assay. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The concentration of the recombinant plasmid was converted to copy numbers based on the following equation: Number of copies = (M×6.02×1023×10−9)/(n×660), the M is the amount of DNA in nanogram, n is the number of the recombinant plasmid in base pair, and the average weight of one base pair is assumed to be 660 Da. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The prepared plasmid standard was aliquoted and stored at −80°C before use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>qPCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The recombinant plasmid standard was serially diluted to a range from 5 to 5×106 copies per microliter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Two µl of each dilution were utilized for qPCR assay on an ABI 7500 Fast qPCR system with 2.0.1 version software (Applied Biosystems, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The reaction mix (20 µl) contained 2 µl genomic DNA, 0.6 µM of primers VP28–140F and VP28–140R (Table 1), and 10 µl Maxima SYBR Green qPCR Master Mix (2×) (Fermentas, MBI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The thermal cycle program was described as follows: 95°C for 10 min, followed by 40 cycles of 94°C for 15 s, 60°C for 60 s. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>RPA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The RPA primers were designed for the vp28 gene by a multiple sequence alignment of 48 nucleotide sequences available in GenBank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>In reference to WSSV genomic sequence AF332093.2 (ORF421, 244243–244858 bp), the RPA amplicon was placed between position 244,384 and 244,507 (length 124 bp). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>A probe was designed for real time RPA assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>It contained a tetrahydrofuran (THF) flanked by a dT-Fluorophore and dT-Quencher group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Thirty-one and seventeen nucleotides were located 5′ and 3′ to the THF site, respectively (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0104667-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104667.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>RPA primers and probe designed in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0104667-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0104667.t002"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>WSSV RPA FP and RP: RPA primer, WSSV RPA P: RPA exo probe, BHQ1-dT: thymidine nucleotide carrying Blackhole quencher1, THF: tetrahydrofuran spacer, FAM-dT: thymidine nucleotide carrying Fluorescein, phosphate: block elongation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>RPA was performed at 39°C for 20 minutes in a 50 µl volume containing 420 nM of each primer, 120 nM probe, 14 mM Mg acetate, enzymes and 1×rehydration buffer (TwistAmp exo kit, TwistDX, Cambridge, UK), and 2 µl recombinant plasmid standard (1 µl for 5 copies dilution) or viral or shrimp DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>An ESEQuant Tube Scanner device (Qiagen Lake Constance, Stockach, Germany) was used to detect the fluorescence signals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Determination of sensitivity and specificity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The analytical sensitivity of RPA was tested using the WSSV quantitative plasmid standard in a range of 1000, 100, 10 and 5 copies per reaction for 8 independent assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The threshold time was plotted against the log number of the detected molecules and a semi-log regression was calculated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The probit regression was calculated using the IBM SPSS Statistics 20.0 (IBM, New York, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>The specificity of the WSSV RPA assay was tested by using the genomic DNA extracted from the white leg shrimp (Litopenaeus vannamei), giant black tiger prawn (Penaeus monodon), Chinese mitten crab (Eriocheir sinensis), human, IHHNV, and PmNV. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Detection of shrimp samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Forty-four shrimp samples with or without WSSV infection were used to test the performance of the RPA and qPCR assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>DNA extraction was performed by using the TIANamp Marine Animals DNA Kit (Tiangen, Beijing, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The assays were carried out as described above. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Statistic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Values were represented as the mean with standard deviation (SD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis was performed using the IBM SPSS Statistics 20.0 (IBM, New York, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>qPCR sensitivity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The qPCR assay revealed a high amplification efficiency (Eff% = 98.464) as well as a strong linear correlation (R2 = 0.9973) between the threshold cycles (Ct) of the plasmid standards ranging from 1.0×107 to 1.0×101 copies (Figs.1 and 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The highest detection sensitivity of the qPCR was 10 molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Two independent repeats confirmed the reproducibility of the performance of the qPCR (Figs.1 and 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Negative controls did not show any amplification signals for each run (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0104667-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104667.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>(A) Amplification curve of qPCR showing 10-fold serial dilution of the WSSV DNA standard plasmids (107 to 10 copies per reaction). (B) Amplification curve of real time RPA showing a dilution ranges of 103, 102, 10, 5 molecules of the WSSV DNA standard plasmids (Graph generated by ESEquant tubescanner software). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>NC refers to negative control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0104667.g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0104667-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104667.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>(A) The reproducibility of WSSV qPCR assay (CT values were represented as the mean ± standard deviation (SD)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Standard regression line was generated based on two data sets. (B) The reproducibility of WSSV real-time RPA assay (Threshold time was represented as the mean ± standard deviation (SD)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Standard regression line was generated based on eight data sets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0104667.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>RPA sensitivity, rapidity and reliability </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>To ascertain the detection limit, the RPA assay was firstly performed using the prepared plasmid standard of 107 to 10 copies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The high concentration (107−105 copies/µl) of standards showed extremely high amplification signals in just 3–4 min of reaction (data not show). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, it was unnecessary to include those high concentrations of standard for evaluation of the detection sensitivity of the RPA assay; only the standard concentrations of 103, 102, 10, and 5 copies/µl were used as templates in the subsequent RPA assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>As a result, a detection limit of up to 5 copies detected within 7.12±0.50 min was achieved (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>1 and 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>By applying the data analysis software Origin, the standard deviation of the threshold time values for 103 down to 5 copies ranged from 0.11 to 0.50 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The R square value of the standard regression line was 0.90 (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The detection rate of 10 and 5 copies was 87.5% and 75.0%, respectively, as determined by 8 independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Probit analysis of the reliability of the RPA using the results of 8 independent assays revealed that in 95% of cases a minimum of 10 molecules are detected, and the detection rate ranged from 70 to 99% (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0104667-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104667.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Probit regression of WSSV real-time RPA using the data of 8 runs. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>(The sensitivity of 10 molecules with 95% reliability by SPSS probit regression analysis). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0104667.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>RPA specificity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The specificity of RPA assay was confirmed by cross detection assays using the genomic DNA of the shrimp, crab, human, IHHNV, and PmNV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>None of these were amplified. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Assay performance on shrimp samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Ten shrimp individuals were detected originally by using both qPCR and RPA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Eight shrimps were WSSV positive, and two negative (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Both assays showed a similar performance regarding the analytical sensitivity (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>As for the RPA assay, the WSSV copy number was between 1000 and 100 for sample 2, between 100 and 10 for sample 4, and less than 10 for sample 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>These results were in agreement with the calculated WSSV copy number of 272 (sample 2), 51 (sample 4) and 7 (sample 1) obtained by using qPCR (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>It indicated that RPA was able to detect as few as 10 WSSV particles in the shrimp samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>In addition, the threshold times of samples 2, 4 and 1 were 6.1, 7.0, and 9.0 min in RPA, respectively; by contrast, the detection CT value of the qPCR was approximately 28.9, 31.4 and 34.4, respectively (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0104667-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104667.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Amplification curve of qPCR (A) and real-time RPA (B)., showing 10-fold serial dilutions of standard plasmids and 4 out of 44 representative shrimp samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Numbers (103 to 10) near black lines: vp28 copies/reaction, S1–S4 near black lines: 4 representative shrimp samples, NC: negative control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0104667.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>To further confirm the stability of the RPA assay, 34 more shrimp individuals were subject to the detection for the infection of WSSV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>In both RPA and qPCR assays, as a result, 22 shrimps were WSSV positive, and 11 negative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Only one sample showed week positive amplification signal in RPA assay, but negative in qPCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, the WSSV-RPA assay turned out to be reliable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>WSSV is one of the most serious pathogens in the shrimp-farming industry [13]–[15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Early and rapid monitoring its infection with high sensitivity represents the most efficient strategy in the control and prevention of the outbreaks of its diseases [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The limits of other detection methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Thus far, a variety of methods have been developed to detect WSSV, which can be divided into two groups based on their targeting molecule of protein or DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The first group is antibody-based immunological methods, which are generally simple and low-cost detection systems with considerable rapidity [16]–[21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>However, these detection techniques encounter the problems of both low sensitivity and limited throughput. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The other group comprises DNA-based detection methods (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Conventional PCR is widely used [22], [23], which is the powerful method to detect pathogens in different kinds of hosts, such as plants, animals, or humans, in laboratory [24], [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>In spite of its superiority of sensitivity, the natures of PCR, such as the requirement of expensive thermal cycler, time-consuming, labor-intensive, especially depending on the classical agarose gel electrophoresis to read amplification results, greatly impede its application in situ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Improved PCR methods developed based on the conventional PCR, including qPCR [26]–[28], nested PCR [29] and insulated isothermal PCR [30], [31], are not feasible for pond-side detection either and incur high costs for routine monitoring of WSSV during shrimp cultivation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Although isothermal LAMP [32]–[34], detects WSSV using a simple heating block, the amplification products are not amenable for quantification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the design of appropriate LAMP primers is more complicated than that for PCR and RPA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0104667-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104667.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Performance of various methods used for detecting WSSV DNA. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0104667-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0104667.t003"/></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The advantages of RPA compared to qPCR regarding to temperature, sensitivity and reaction time </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Recently, Mendoza-Cano and coauthor [28] reported a SYBR green-based qPCR assay for the detection of WSSV, which revealed a high sensitivity of 12 copies per sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>In order to evaluate the RPA assay, we also established this published qPCR assay in this study, which showed a slightly higher sensitivity of 10 copies per reaction compared to that of [28]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>As expected, the RPA method established in this study revealed a satisfactory performance for the detecting of shrimp WSSV DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The isothermal RPA was performed at 39°C, while the two-step thermal cycling qPCR had to be conducted at 94 to 60°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The low and constant reaction temperature of RPA paves the way for simpler devices and for mobile pond-site and point-of-care detection of WSSV. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Besides, the detection limit of RPA is as few as 5 copies of WSSV DNA per reaction, which is comparable to that of qPCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The reaction time of RPA was less than 10 min; by contrast, approximately 33 cycles (134 minutes) were required in the qPCR assay in order to achieve the similar detection sensitivity as in RPA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Obviously, the RPA assay saves almost 100 min of reaction time in comparison with the qPCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>This reduction in assay time makes the WSSV-RPA assay a handy tool for monitoring WSSV infection during shrimp cultivation on short notice in a real time strategy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The vp28 as the target gene </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Most of the methods for detecting WSSV target vp19 [35], vp28 [22], [26], [28], wsv360 [30], ORF191 [32], [33] and ORF 36 [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Among these genes, the vp28 is mostly widely used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>VP28 is the most abundant envelope protein in WSSV and plays an essential role in viral attachment during early events of virus infection [37], [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The vp28 gene detection assay appears to bear much higher sensitivity in comparison to the methods targeting other genes (Table 3), and there are plenty of sequences of vp28 gene available in GenBank, which contributes to the design of high-coverage primers and probes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>In addition, sequence alignment analysis indicated that vp28 is a highly conserved gene in WSSV (Data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the diagnostic methods developed based on vp28 is feasible for universal detection of various WSSV isolates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The convenience of application of RPA to in situ diagnostics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The commercially available TwistAmp exo kit (TwistDX, Cambridge, UK) contains buffer and reaction mixtures, which include enzymes and nucleotides, all provided in a dried pellets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Just primers, probe, and DNA template need to be added. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Again this recommends RPA is a promising technique designed for point-of-care or field diagnoses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Importantly, it is necessary to point out that the size of the ESEquant Tube Scanner, the reaction signal recording device, is just 17.4 by 18.8 cm with a weight of about 1 kg (including the laptop). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>It means the Tube Scanner device is significantly light, small and convenient for point of care monitoring [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Besides, the Tube Scanner is much cheaper than any of the mobile PCR devices. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Therefore, RPA implemented on a tubescanner is a very promising nucleic acid detection method that could easily be applied on shrimp farms at much lower investment than for using mobile qPCR on real time cyclers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Recently, Lutz and coauthors combined RPA with a foil based microfluidic LabDisc system [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>This improvement together with the development of automatic sample preparation system could eventually lead to the development of RPA panels or chips for the simultaneous detection of different categories of infectious agents, e.g., syndromic panels of bacteria, and DNA and RNA viruses, in small point of care devices. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, with the assistance of the mobile device (ESEquant Tubescanner system), we have developed an extremely efficient and highly sensitive isothermal real time RPA assay for the detection of WSSV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The WSSV real time RPA assay appears to be much more suitable for mobile testing on pond sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>More work, such as validation of specificity and reproducibility, needs to be done to apply the established WSSV-RPA assay to the diagnostics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0104667-King1"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>1King AMQ, Adams MJ, Lefkowitz EJ, Carstens EB (2012) Virus taxonomy: classification and nomenclature of viruses: Ninth Report of the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses: Elsevier. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Lo1"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>2 LoC-F, HoC, PengS, ChenC-H, HsuH, et al (1996) White spot syndrome baculovirus (WSBV) detected in cultured and captured shrimp, crabs and other arthropods. Diseases of Aquatic Organisms 27: 215–225. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Supamattaya1"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>3 SupamattayaK (1998) Experimental transmission of white spot syndrome virus (WSSV) from black tiger shrimp Penaeus monodon to the sand crab Portunus pelagicus, mud crab Scylla serrata and krill Acetes sp. Diseases of Aquatic Organisms 32: 79–85. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Chen1"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>4 ChenL-L, LoC-F, ChiuY-L, ChangC-F, KouG-H (2000) Natural and experimental infection of white spot syndrome virus (WSSV) in benthic larvae of mud crab Scylla serrata . Diseases of Aquatic Organisms 40: 157–161.10782350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Chou1"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>5 ChouH, HuangC, WangC, ChiangH, LoC (1995) Pathogenicity of a baculovirus infection causing white spot syndrome in cultured penaeid shrimp in Taiwan. Diseases of Aquatic Organisms 23: 165–173. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Wonteerasupaya1"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>6 WonteerasupayaC, VickersJE, SriurairatanaS, NashGL, AkarajamornA, et al (1995) A non-occluded, systemic baculovirus that occurs in cells of ectodermal and mesodermal origin and causes high mortality in the black tiger prawn Penaeus monodon . Diseases of Aquatic Organisms 21: 69–77. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Inouye1"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>7 InouyeK, MiwaS, OsekoN, NakanoH, KimuraT, et al (1994) Mass mortalities of cultured kuruma shrimp Penaeus japonicus in Japan in 1993: electron microscopic evidence of the causative virus. Fish Pathology 29: 149–158. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-SnchezPaz1"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>8 Sánchez-PazA (2010) White spot syndrome virus: an overview on an emergent concern. Veterinary Research 41: 43.20181325 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Piepenburg1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>9 PiepenburgO, WilliamsCH, StempleDL, ArmesNA (2006) DNA detection using recombination proteins. PLoS Biology 4: e204.16756388 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Euler1"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>10 EulerM, WangY, NentwichO, PiepenburgO, HufertFT, et al (2012) Recombinase polymerase amplification assay for rapid detection of Rift Valley fever virus. Journal of Clinical Virology 54: 308–312.22683006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Euler2"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>11 EulerM, WangY, OttoP, TomasoH, EscuderoR, et al (2012) Recombinase polymerase amplification assay for rapid detection of Francisella tularensis . Journal of Clinical Microbiology 50: 2234–2238.22518861 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Euler3"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>12 EulerM, WangY, HeidenreichD, PatelP, StrohmeierO, et al (2013) Development of a panel of recombinase polymerase amplification assays for detection of biothreat agents. Journal of Clinical Microbiology 51: 1110–1117.23345286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Flegel1"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>13 FlegelTW (2012) Historic emergence, impact and current status of shrimp pathogens in Asia. Journal of Invertebrate Pathology 110: 166–173.22429834 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Lightner1"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>14 LightnerD, RedmanR, PantojaC, TangK, NobleB, et al (2012) Historic emergence, impact and current status of shrimp pathogens in the Americas. Journal of Invertebrate Pathology 110: 174–183.22434000 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Leu1"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>15Leu J-H, Yang F, Zhang X, Xu X, Kou G-H, et al. (2009) Whispovirus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Lesser Known Large dsDNA Viruses: Springer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>197–227. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Chaivisuthangkura1"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>16 ChaivisuthangkuraP, TangkhabuanbutraJ, LongyantS, SithigorngulW, RukpratanpornS, et al (2004) Monoclonal antibodies against a truncated viral envelope protein (VP28) can detect white spot syndrome virus (WSSV) infections in shrimp. ScienceAsia 30: 359–363. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Chaivisuthangkura2"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>17 ChaivisuthangkuraP, LongyantS, RukpratanpornS, SrisukC, SridulyakulP, et al (2010) Enhanced white spot syndrome virus (WSSV) detection sensitivity using monoclonal antibody specific to heterologously expressed VP19 envelope protein. Aquaculture 299: 15–20. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Shih1"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>18 ShihH-H (2004) Neutralization of white spot syndrome virus by monoclonal antibodies against viral envelope proteins. TAIWANIA 49: 159–165. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Hou1"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>19 HouC-L, CaoY, XieR-H, WangY-Z, DuH-H (2011) Characterization and diagnostic use of a monoclonal antibody for VP28 envelope protein of white spot syndrome virus. Virologica Sinica 26: 260–266.21847757 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Nadala1"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>20 NadalaECBJr, LohPC (2000) Dot-blot nitrocellulose enzyme immunoassays for the detection of white-spot virus and yellow-head virus of penaeid shrimp. Journal of Virological Methods 84: 175–179.10680967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-You1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>21 YouZ, NadalaE, YangJ, Van HultenM, LohPC (2002) Production of polyclonal antiserum specific to the 27.5 kDa envelope protein of white spot syndrome virus. Diseases of Aquatic Organisms 51: 77–80.12240973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Mrotzek1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>22 MrotzekG, KoesharyaniI, TretyakovAN, SugamaK, SaluzHP (2010) Fast short-fragment PCR for rapid and sensitive detection of shrimp viruses. Journal of Virological Methods 168: 262–266.20471423 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Kiatpathomchai1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>23 KiatpathomchaiW, TaweetungtragoonA, JittivadhanaK, WongteerasupayaC, BoonsaengV, et al (2005) Target for standard Thai PCR assay identical in 12 white spot syndrome virus (WSSV) types that differ in DNA multiple repeat length. Journal of Virological Methods 130: 79–82.16024099 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Alvarez1"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>24 AlvarezAM (2004) Integrated approaches for detection of plant pathogenic bacteria and diagnosis of bacterial diseases. Annual Review Phytopathology 42: 339–366. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Briese1"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>25 BrieseT, PalaciosG, KokorisM, JabadoO, LiuZ, et al (2005) Diagnostic system for rapid and sensitive differential detection of pathogens. Emerging Infectious Diseases 11: 310.15752453 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Jang1"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>26 JangI-K, MengX-H, SeoH-C, ChoY-R, KimB-R, et al (2009) A TaqMan real-time PCR assay for quantifying white spot syndrome virus (WSSV) infections in wild broodstock and hatchery-reared postlarvae of fleshy shrimp, Fenneropenaeus chinensis . Aquaculture 287: 40–45. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Meng1"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>27 MengX-H, JangI-K, SeoH-C, ChoY-R (2010) A TaqMan real-time PCR assay for survey of white spot syndrome virus (WSSV) infections in Litopenaeus vannamei postlarvae and shrimp of farms in different grow-out seasons. Aquaculture 310: 32–37. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-MendozaCano1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>28 Mendoza-CanoF, Sánchez-PazA (2013) Development and validation of a quantitative real-time polymerase chain assay for universal detection of the White Spot Syndrome Virus in marine crustaceans. Virology Journal 10: 186.23758658 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Natividad1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>29 NatividadKDT, NomuraN, MatsumuraM (2008) Detection of White spot syndrome virus DNA in pond soil using a 2-step nested PCR. Journal of Virological Methods 149: 28–34.18313145 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Tsai1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>30 TsaiY-L, WangH-TT, ChangH-FG, TsaiC-F, LinC-K, et al (2012) Development of TaqMan probe-based insulated isothermal PCR (iiPCR) for sensitive and specific on-site pathogen detection. PloS One 7: e45278.23049781 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Tsai2"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>31 TsaiY-L, LinY-C, ChouP-H, TengP-H, LeeP-Y (2012) Detection of white spot syndrome virus by polymerase chain reaction performed under insulated isothermal conditions. Journal of Virological Methods 181: 134–137.22326658 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Jaroenram1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>32 JaroenramW, KiatpathomchaiW, FlegelTW (2009) Rapid and sensitive detection of white spot syndrome virus by loop-mediated isothermal amplification combined with a lateral flow dipstick. Molecular and Cellular Probes 23: 65–70.19124071 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Chou2"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>33 ChouP-H, LinY-C, TengP-H, ChenC-L, LeeP-Y (2011) Real-time target-specific detection of loop-mediated isothermal amplification for white spot syndrome virus using fluorescence energy transfer-based probes. Journal of Virological Methods 173: 67–74.21256868 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-SeetangNun1"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>34 Seetang-NunY, JaroenramW, SriurairatanaS, SuebsingR, KiatpathomchaiW (2013) Visual detection of white spot syndrome virus using DNA-functionalized gold nanoparticles as probes combined with loop-mediated isothermal amplification. Molecular and Cellular Probes 27: 71–79.23211683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Samanman1"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>35 SamanmanS, KanatharanaP, ChotigeatW, DeachamagP, ThavarungkulP (2011) Highly sensitive capacitive biosensor for detecting white spot syndrome virus in shrimp pond water. Journal of Virological Methods 173: 75–84.21256870 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Mekata1"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>36 MekataT, SudhakaranR, KonoT, SupamattayaK, LinhN, et al (2009) Real-time quantitative loop-mediated isothermal amplification as a simple method for detecting white spot syndrome virus. Letters in Applied Microbiology 48: 25–32.19018969 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Yi1"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>37 YiG, WangZ, QiY, YaoL, QianJ, et al (2004) Vp28 of shrimp white spot syndrome virus is involved in the attachment and penetration into shrimp cells. Journal of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology 37: 726–734.15607033 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-vanHulten1"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>38 van HultenMC, WestenbergM, GoodallSD, VlakJM (2000) Identification of two major virion protein genes of white spot syndrome virus of shrimp. Virology 266: 227–236.10639309 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Lutz1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>39 LutzS, WeberP, FockeM, FaltinB, HoffmannJ, et al (2010) Microfluidic lab-on-a-foil for nucleic acid analysis based on isothermal recombinase polymerase amplification (RPA). Lab on a Chip 10: 887–893.20300675 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0104667-Qiagen1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>40Qiagen website. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.qiagen.com/Products/ESEQuantTubeScanner.aspx?r=603">http://www.qiagen.com/Products/ESEQuantTubeScanner.aspx?r=603</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Accessed 2014 Jul 21. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
