
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4190074</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25295754</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-20230</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108851</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Agriculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Agricultural Biotechnology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>RNA</subject><subj-group><subject>MicroRNAs</subject><subject>RNA stability</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biotechnology</subject><subj-group><subject>Plant Biotechnology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Regulation</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular Biology Techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Sequencing Techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>High Throughput Sequencing</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Plant Science</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Research and Analysis Methods</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Identification and Characterization of Wilt and Salt Stress-Responsive MicroRNAs in Chickpea through High-Throughput Sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">MicroRNAs in Chickpea</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Kohli</surname><given-names>Deshika</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>Gopal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Deokar</surname><given-names>Amit Atmaram</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bhardwaj</surname><given-names>Ankur R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>Manu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Katiyar-Agarwal</surname><given-names>Surekha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>Ramamurthy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>Pradeep Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>NRC on Plant Biotechnology, IARI Campus (PUSA), New Delhi, India</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Botany, North campus, University of Delhi, Delhi, India</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Plant Molecular Biology, South Campus, University of Delhi, Delhi, India</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xianlong</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>National Key Laboratory of Crop Genetic Improvement, China</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>pkjain@nrcpb.org</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: PKJ SKA RS MA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: DK ARB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: GJ DK AAD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: GJ SKA PKJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: DK PKJ. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e108851</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Kohli et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kohli et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Chickpea (Cicer arietinum) is the second most widely grown legume worldwide and is the most important pulse crop in the Indian subcontinent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Chickpea productivity is adversely affected by a large number of biotic and abiotic stresses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) have been implicated in the regulation of plant responses to several biotic and abiotic stresses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>This study is the first attempt to identify chickpea miRNAs that are associated with biotic and abiotic stresses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The wilt infection that is caused by the fungus Fusarium oxysporum f.sp. ciceris is one of the major diseases severely affecting chickpea yields. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Of late, increasing soil salinization has become a major problem in realizing these potential yields. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Three chickpea libraries using fungal-infected, salt-treated and untreated seedlings were constructed and sequenced using next-generation sequencing technology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>A total of 12,135,571 unique reads were obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>In addition to 122 conserved miRNAs belonging to 25 different families, 59 novel miRNAs along with their star sequences were identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Four legume-specific miRNAs, including miR5213, miR5232, miR2111 and miR2118, were found in all of the libraries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Poly(A)-based qRT-PCR (Quantitative real-time PCR) was used to validate eleven conserved and five novel miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>miR530 was highly up regulated in response to fungal infection, which targets genes encoding zinc knuckle- and microtubule-associated proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Many miRNAs responded in a similar fashion under both biotic and abiotic stresses, indicating the existence of cross talk between the pathways that are involved in regulating these stresses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The potential target genes for the conserved and novel miRNAs were predicted based on sequence homologies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>miR166 targets a HD-ZIPIII transcription factor and was validated by 5′ RLM-RACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>This study has identified several conserved and novel miRNAs in the chickpea that are associated with gene regulation following exposure to wilt and salt stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by a grant from ICAR-Network Project on Trasgenic Crops (Functional Genomics Component) no. 2049/3003. The funder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="19"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that, for approved reasons, some access restrictions apply to the data underlying the findings. The data discussed in this publication has been deposited in Gene Expression Omnibus repository under the accession number GSE57857 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE57857">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE57857</ext-link>).</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>The authors confirm that, for approved reasons, some access restrictions apply to the data underlying the findings. The data discussed in this publication has been deposited in Gene Expression Omnibus repository under the accession number GSE57857 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE57857">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE57857</ext-link>).</p></notes></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are small, endogenous, non-coding RNAs that are present in animals, plants and some viruses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>These RNAs participate in the regulation of target genes by binding to complementary mRNAs, resulting in either their cleavage or translational repression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>miRNAs are involved in diverse processes in different organisms, including developmental timing in worms, cell death and fat metabolism in flies, hematopoiesis in mammals and leaf development, floral patterning and environmental stress responses in plants [1]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>MIRNA genes are transcribed as independent transcriptional units by RNA polymerase II enzymes to generate primary miRNAs (pri-miRNAs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>pri-miRNAs form imperfect folded structures that are processed by Dicer-like1 nuclease (a member of the RNase III endonuclease family) to precursor miRNAs (pre-miRNAs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The secondary structures of these precursors are well conserved in plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The pre-miRNA contains a miRNA-star miRNA (miRNA*) intermediate duplex from which the miRNA* eventually is degraded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>However, recent studies have revealed the higher accumulation of miRNA* under certain conditions in plants, indicating the probable role of miRNAs in modulating plant growth and development [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Mature miRNAs are 19 to 24 nucleotides (nt) in length and interact with an RNA-induced silencing complex (RISC) to cleave specific target mRNAs or inhibit their translation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>This complementarity plays an important role in determining the fate of the mRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>When the complementarity between the miRNA and mRNA is perfect or near perfect, the mRNA is cleaved; however, if there are many mismatches between them, translational repression occurs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>There are also instances in which miRNAs and mRNAs with perfect complementarities lead to the repression of translation and not to the usual cleavage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The first identified miRNAs were lin4 and let7 in Caenorhabditis elegans, which is a model nematode [3], [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The first plant miRNAs were identified in Arabidopsis [5] and later in other plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Currently, 7,321 mature miRNAs have been reported in 72 plant species (miRBase version 20) [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Among dicots, the maximum number of miRNAs occurs in the legume family (1,460), followed by Brassicaceae (863). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Although the legume family has the best representation in terms of the number of miRNAs, chickpea is a notable omission from the list. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Chickpea (Cicer arietinum) is the world's second most widely grown legume and is cultivated in more than 40 countries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The Indian subcontinent is the principal chickpea-producing and consuming region, contributing almost 70% of the world's total production [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Chickpea seeds are a rich source of protein and starch for the human population and the records of chickpea cultivation date back to 6,000 BC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Globally, chickpea is grown on 11.5 million hectares (ha) to produce 10.4 million tons with an average yield of approximately 0.9 t/ha, which is far below its yield potential of 6 t/ha under optimal growth conditions [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The disparity between the actual and potential yields can be explained by large numbers of biotic and abiotic stresses that adversely affect its productivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Among the biotic stresses, wilt infection that is caused by the fungus Fusarium oxysporum f.sp. ciceris is a major concern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Abiotic stress conditions, such as terminal drought and salt stress, also lead to major losses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>ICC4958 is a drought tolerant chickpea cultivar and gets affected at terminal drought, which occurs at the pod filling and seed-developing stage of the crop [8], [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>However, recent studies on salinity tolerance and ion accumulation in chickpea have revealed it as a highly sensitive crop to salinity when compared to other species in cropping systems [10], [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Thus, salinity is another major constraint in chickpea yield. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>A better understanding of genes and their interactions with the environment can play a very important and determinant role in tackling these stress conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The recently available transcriptome and genome sequences that have been reported by independent groups are important resources that will facilitate the attainment of these goals in the chickpea [12], [13], [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Hu et al. (2013) identified 28 potential miRNA candidates belonging to 20 families from 16 ESTs and 12 GSSs in the chickpea using a comparative genome-based computational analysis [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>A total of 664 miRNA targets were predicted, including genes encoding transcription factors (TFs) in addition to those that function in the stress response, signal transduction, methylation and a variety of other metabolic processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>These findings lay the foundation for the elucidation of miRNA function in the development and stress responses of the chickpea. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>miRNAs have been discovered primarily using direct cloning and bioinformatic approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>All of the miRNAs in plants have been identified via the cloning of small RNAs or a computational approach, in which the homologs of known miRNAs are searched. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>We have generated small RNA libraries corresponding with the control conditions, Fusarium wilt infection and salt stress, which were sequenced using the Illumina sequencing platform to identify miRNAs in the chickpea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>This study is the first report in which small RNA libraries have been constructed and sequenced to identify miRNAs in the chickpea. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Sequence analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Three separate small RNA libraries that were constructed from the total RNA of the control, Fusarium wilt-infected and salt-stressed plants were subjected to Illumina Solexa sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>This sequencing generated 29,170,463 raw reads, which after processing by UEA sRNA workbench 2.4- Plant version sequence file pre-processing tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://srna-tools.cmp.uea.ac.uk/">http://srna-tools.cmp.uea.ac.uk/</ext-link>), produced approximately 12,135,571 total unique reads (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>After removing the adaptor sequences, filtering the low-quality tags and eliminating the t/rRNA sequences, the putative small RNA population accounted for approximately 88.5%, 79.1% and 78.4% in the control, wilt-infected and salt-stressed libraries, respectively (Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The majority of small RNAs (approximately 50%) from the control and salt-stressed libraries were 24 nt in length (Figure 1), which is similar to other plant species, such as Arabidopsis thaliana, Solanum lycopersicum and Medicago truncatula [16], [17], [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Notably, in the wilt-infected library, small RNAs that were 20 nt in length accounted for 20% of the population, but when unique reads were analyzed, the small RNA distribution revealed that 24 nt was the major size class. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Similar patterns have been reported in cucumber and soybean [19], [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>In soybean, the unique and redundant sequence classes possessed 24 nt and 23 nt long small RNAs, respectively, as the most abundant sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>For the differential expression analysis, the total numbers of miRNA reads in each given sample were normalized as transcripts per million, and the fold changes between the treated and control samples were calculated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Out of 122 conserved miRNAs, 44 were upregulated in response to wilt stress, but in the case of salt stress, the number of down regulated miRNAs was greater than that which was observed in response to wilt stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>However, the differential expression of novel miRNAs under both of these stresses showed relatively similar patterns, with approximately 60% of the miRNAs being down regulated under either wilt and/or salt stress (Figure 2a, b). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0108851-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108851.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Length distribution of small RNA population. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Size distributions of the miRNAs in the three chickpea libraries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>In the wilt stress library, 20 nt miRNAs are more frequent than 24 nt miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>However, in the other two libraries 24 nt miRNAs are more frequent. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0108851.g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0108851-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108851.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Differential expression patterns of chickpea miRNAs under wilt and salt stresses. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>(A) Conserved miRNAs, (B) novel miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0108851.g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0108851-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108851.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Distribution of the sequenced reads in the control, wilt- and salt-stressed chickpea libraries. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0108851-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0108851.t001"/></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Identification of conserved miRNAs in chickpea </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The unique reads that were obtained from the miRCat analysis tool (UEA small RNA workbench) were mapped to the miRNAs that were available in miRBase version 18 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mirbase.org/">http://www.mirbase.org/</ext-link>) [21], [22], [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The small RNA sequences that matched the known miRNAs from the miRBase database were identified as conserved miRNAs in the chickpea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The sequence analyses revealed the presence of 122 miRNAs belonging to 25 conserved families. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The most abundant family was miR156 with 14 members. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Among the others, miR171 (12 members), miR169 and miR172 (9 members each), miR166 and miR167 (8 members each), miR319 and miR399 (6 members each) and miR396 (5 members) were present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The remaining miRNA families had less than five members, with some families, such as miR530, miR162, miR5232 and miR408, being represented by only one member (Table 2; Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>In a recent report of the chickpea genome, the sequences of 20 unique miRNA families were reported, of which MIR169_2 and MIR159 were the most abundant [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>In our study, out of 25 conserved miRNAs families, 16 possessed miRNA* sequences, thus providing additional evidence in support of the authenticity of the miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>However, no miRNA* sequences were obtained for miR2111, miR162, miR164, miR390, miR394, miR397, miR530, miR408 or miR5213. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Detailed information regarding the precursor structures of the conserved miRNAs is provided in Table S2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0108851-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108851.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Conserved miRNAs in chickpea. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0108851-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0108851.t002"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>gma- Glycin max; mtr- Medicago tranculata; vun- Vigna unguiculata; ath- Arabidopsis thaliana; os- Oryza sativa. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>MFE- Minimum Folding Energy; L: Length; PL: Precursor Length. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Identification of legume-specific miRNAs in chickpea library </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>We obtained four legume-specific miRNAs, including miR2111, miR2118, miR5213 and miR5232, in our libraries that were previously reported in another legume, Medicago [24], [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>To date, miR5232 has only been reported in Medicago in a study involving miRNA regulation during arbuscular mycorrhizal symbiosis [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, miR5232 may be a legume-specific miRNA that is involved in the biotic stress response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The multiple sequence alignment of the mature miRNAs in addition to the precursor sequences of these four legume-specific miRNAs revealed that they were most closely similar to Medicago and consequently has been conserved throughout evolution (Figure 3a, 3b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>However, in recent studies, sequences that are similar to miR2118 have been reported in other non-leguminous plant systems, such as tomato and rice [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Apart from Fabaceae, miR2118 family members are most abundant in the Rutaceae and Solanaceae plant families [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Even the nomenclature of the miR2118 family is inconsistent in miRBase: the miR2118-like sequences have been disparately named miR482 (sly-miR482), miR5300 (as in tomato) and miR2809. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The variation in the miR2118 sequence is species specific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Thus, miR2118 sequences in the chickpea are more similar with mtr-miR2118a [24] in comparison with other plant systems. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0108851-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108851.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Multiple sequence alignments of legume-specific miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>(A) Mature miRNAs, (B) precursor miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Four legume-specific miRNAs, including a) MIR5213, b) MIR5232, c) MIR2111and d) MIR2118, were used for the multiple sequence alignments by ClustalW2 in the different plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>car- Cicer arietinum, mtr- Medicago truncatula, gma- Glycine max, ath- Arabidopsis thaliana, osa- Oryza sativa, zma- Zea mays, sbi- Sorghum bicolor, sly- Solanum lycopersicum, hbr- Hevea brasiliensis, pvu- Phaseolus vulgaris, vun- Vigna unguiculata, ptc- Populus trichocarpa and mdm- Malus domestica. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0108851.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Identification of novel miRNAs in chickpea </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>We identified 59 novel miRNAs using the miRCat module of the UEA sRNA workbench, which aligned the pooled reads from all three of the libraries to the chickpea genome (NCBI Genome: PRJNA175619) [13], the ESTs database from NCBI and transcriptome data from the chickpea transcriptome database [28], and applied prediction criteria for plant miRNAs [29] (Table 3; Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The low abundance of novel miRNAs in our data supports the earlier notion of the lower expression levels of novel miRNAs compared with those of conserved miRNAs [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The precursor miRNA candidates were then tested using RandFold with a cutoff of 0.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The minimum free energy that was required to form the predicted hairpin structure for the precursor was in the range of −97.2 to −26.03 Kcal/mol, which is similar to the values that were reported for the precursors of other plant species (Table S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The secondary structures of the precursors of five validated novel miRNAs were evaluated using the Mfold software (Figure 4) [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The data analysis revealed the presence of miRNA* sequences for all of the 59 novel miRNAs of the chickpea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The miRNA* supports the release of the miRNA duplex from the predicted hairpin structure [32]; therefore, the presence of miRNA* sequences further supports the identity of these small RNA sequences in our libraries as novel miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0108851-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108851.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Predicted secondary structures of five validated novel miRNA precursors in chickpea using Mfold. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0108851.g004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0108851-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108851.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>List of novel chickpea miRNAs with their miRNA*. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0108851-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0108851.t003"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>MFE: Minimum Folding Energy; L: Length; PL: Precursor Length. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Expression patterns of known and novel miRNAs in chickpea </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Total RNA from the tissues of control, wilt-infected and salt-stressed plants were used to validate the miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The poly(A)RNA of these three samples was reverse transcribed into cDNA for the validation of the expression of eleven conserved and five novel miRNAs using qRT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The expression levels of the chickpea miRNAs under wilt stress were significantly altered compared with those of the control conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>In contrast, those that were observed under salt stress did not greatly change. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Among the validated conserved miRNAs, miR530 was upregulated seventeen-fold during wilt stress, suggesting that it is an important candidate miRNA that is involved in the plant wilt stress response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>miR156_1 and miR156_10 were slightly upregulated under both the wilt and salt stresses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>miR2118, which is one of the legume-specific miRNAs, was also upregulated by approximately 0.5-fold during wilt stress compared with the control seedlings (Figure 5a, 5b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Conversely, no significant expression patterns were detected with respect to the known miRNAs in response to salt stress in the chickpea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The expression analysis of the novel miRNAs revealed that three out of five (car-miR008, car-miR011 and car-miR015) were approximately three fold upregulated on average during salt stress (novel chickpea miRNAs have been designated as “car-miRNA” throughout the manuscript, in which “car” is an abbreviation for Cicer arietinum). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>However, the expression patterns that were observed during wilt stress revealed limited information because little significant changes occurred. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0108851-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108851.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Expression analyses of selected miRNAs under wilt and salt stresses as evaluated by qRT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The relative expression levels are shown as fold changes with the standard errors (SE) of three biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>(A) Expression profiling of conserved miRNAs under control, wilt and salt stress conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>(B) Expression profiling of novel miRNAs under control, wilt and salt stress conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0108851.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Prediction and validation of miRNA targets in chickpea </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The putative miRNA targets in chickpea were predicted using the psRNATarget program [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The predicted target genes (approximately 358 different transcripts) were extensively involved in different biological processes involving a large number of gene families. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Some of these genes encoded TFs, DNA replication proteins and those that are involved in cellular metabolism in addition to a variety of stress response-associated proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The target prediction analysis revealed the involvement of some of the miRNAs in regulating metabolic processes through the target genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>In chickpea, miR159 is involved in the metabolism of amino acids, fatty acids and lipids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>One of the target genes of miR159 encodes acyltransferase, which is essential for ester biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The chickpea miR156 and miR166 target genes encode squamosa promoter-binding protein and homeobox-leucine zipper protein, respectively, as previously reported [34], [35]. Table 4 describes details of the target genes of validated miRNAs; a complete list is provided as supporting information (Table S5; Table S6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The most widely targeted class of genes is the protein kinases, which are associated with plant defense mechanisms via cell signaling-related processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The novel car-miRNA008 targets the chalcone synthase (CHS) gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Chalcone, which is an intermediate in flavonoid biosynthesis, is involved in natural defense mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>CHS expression is also involved in salicylic acid defense pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>car-miR2118 and car-miR5213 target two defense-response chickpea genes encoding Toll/Interleukin-1 receptor-nucleotide binding site-leucine-rich repeats (TIR-NBS-LRR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Members of the TIR-NBS-LRR gene family are genuine targets for miR2118 [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Additionally, miR5213 suppresses defense-response genes in Medicago. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The cleavage of such transcripts as mediated by miR5213 is notably conserved in AM symbiosis-capable plants, such as Medicago truncatula, Glycine max, Lotus japonicus, Populus trichocarpa and Cicer arietinum, but not in plants for which this symbiosis is not observed, such as Arabidopsis thaliana [25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0108851-t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108851.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Predicted target genes of miRNAs in chickpea. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0108851-t004-4" xlink:href="pone.0108851.t004"/></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Members of the miR166/165 family target HD-ZIP III TF genes by cleaving the mRNA at complementary base pairs in leguminous plants [34], [36], [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>These results are similar to those of earlier predicted reports involving other plant systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The target gene of miR166 was experimentally validated by modified 5′RLM-RACE [38], [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>All of the positive clones were sequenced, and cleavage was observed at the 17th and 18th positions of the mRNA by the 5′ end of miR166 (Figure 6), unlike the previously reported miRNA-target recognition parameters [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Although our results are not in agreement with previous studies, such as those involving the soybean, in which miR166 target validation by 5′RACE and degradome sequencing confirmed cleavage at the 10th and 11th positions [41], there have been reports of the miRNA (belonging to different families)-mediated cleavage of target mRNA, thus defying the recognition rule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>A total of 18 miRNA/target pairs of Pinus taeda possessed non-conventional cleavage sites, such as pta-miR951:AW065026, which is cleaved at the 16th and 17th positions [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Similar results have been reported in other plant species, such as mtr-miR397:AC135467 [24], ath-miR168:AGO1 [43], pvu-miR171:gi62704692 [44] and ath-miR398a:CSD1 [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Thus, it appears that the sequence of the target gene and the miRNA sequence determine the cleavage site apart from the conventional complimentary region-based target cleavage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is quite possible that chickpea has a different cleavage site for miR166 (pair miR166:TC04758) compared with other plant species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0108851-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108851.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Mapping of target mRNA cleavage site of miR166 by modified 5′ RACE. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The target of miR166 (TC04758) encodes a transcription factor belonging to class III of the HD-ZIP family protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The arrow indicates the cleavage site, and the numbers above the arrow denote the frequencies of the sequenced clones. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0108851.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Analyses of GO terms and KEGG pathways </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The GO terms of the target genes were annotated according to their biological processes, molecular functions or involvement as cellular components. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The enzyme mapping of the annotated sequences was performed using direct GO for the enzyme mapping and the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) for the definitions of the KEGG orthologs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The miRNA-targeted genes belonged to various biological processes, cellular components and molecular functions as depicted in Figure 7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The maximum numbers of target genes were involved in biological processes, including both metabolic and cellular processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>However, the target genes that were involved in binding were the most abundant (80%) within the molecular functions category. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0108851-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108851.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Gene ontology categories of predicted target transcripts for chickpea miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The miRNA-target genes were categorized according to the molecular function, biological process and cellular component sub-ontologies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0108851.g007"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>In this study, high-throughput deep sequencing was used to gain in-depth knowledge of gene regulation by miRNAs in the chickpea under biotic and abiotic stresses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Salt stress is one of the major constraints to increasing chickpea productivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Soil salinity levels affect germination in plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Under salt stress conditions, chickpea plants show high levels of anthocyanin pigmentation in their foliage and reduced growth rates [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Among the biotic stresses, Fusarium wilt is one of the major soil/seed-borne diseases severely affecting chickpea growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Its causative agent is Fusarium oxysporum f.sp. ciceris, which is a fungal pathogen. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Most of the miRNAs that were obtained in our library have a preference for the 5′-U as has been reported in other plants, which is in accordance with the defined structures of the mature miRNAs [1], [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The lengths of the chickpea precursors ranged from 61 to 220 nt, which were similar to those of the soybean (55 to 239 nt) and peanut (75 to 343 nt) [30], [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The calculation of the minimum free energy (MFE) values further added credence to these predicted hairpin structures as putative miRNA precursors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>The chickpea precursors had minimum free energy values ranging from −97.2 to −26.03 Kcal/mol with an average of −50.1419 Kcal/mol, which was similar to the −50.01 Kcal/mol that was observed in Arachis hypogaea and the reported value of −59.5 Kcal/mol in Arabidopsis thaliana (Table S2) [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Greater increases in miRNA expression were observed following wilt stress compared with salt stress, suggesting the significant role of small RNAs in the response to pathogen attack. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The total number of miRNAs was greater in the wilt stress library than in the salt stress library. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Four legume-specific miRNAs were identified in the chickpea libraries, including miR2111, miR2118, miR5232 and miR5213, which were previously reported in Medicago. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The sequence conservation among the different legumes and the precursor sequence similarity of these four chickpea miRNAs further substantiate their accurate identification in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>car-miR5232 cleaves only two transcripts encoding an ATPase E1-E2 type and an expressed protein of unknown function, in concordance with a similar study in Medicago, in which miR5232 targets were experimentally confirmed by degradome sequencing [25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>The significance of miRNA* in authenticating the presence of miRNA has previously been established. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>A comparison of chickpea miRNA* and mature miRNA data revealed that they vary in abundance in response to the different stress treatments, which has also been previously reported [47], [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Our target search analysis indicated that miRNA* act upon different transcripts than do their parental miRNAs (data not shown), which has been observed in plants, animals and humans [25], [49], [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>For example, miR393 and its miRNA* counterpart regulated the expression of genes belonging to entirely different protein families; i.e., TIR1 and SNARE, respectively [51], [52]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Expression patterns during biotic stress </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>This study is the first attempt to identify miRNAs that are associated with fungal attack in the chickpea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Alterations in the expression of genes that are involved in defense during pathogen attack have been previously reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>These genes are regulated by small RNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>miR393 was the first miRNA whose role in pathogen attack was demonstrated [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Eleven conserved and five novel miRNAs were analyzed in the chickpea under wilt and salt stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, miR530 was significantly upregulated during wilt stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>This observation suggests that its target genes are expressed at lower levels, which included the zinc knuckle proteins and microtubule-associated proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Zinc knuckle proteins are involved in the regulation of morning-specific growth in Arabidopsis [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The target of miR530 varies in different plants under different conditions and tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>In Populus trichocarpa, this miRNA targets zinc knuckle (CCHC type) family proteins along with a homeobox TF [54], whereas in soybean, it targets genes that encode the CONSTANS interacting protein and nuclear transcription factor Y [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>In Eugenia uniflora, miR530 targets wall-associated receptor kinase-like 14, S-acyltransferase tip-1 and a protein of unknown function in rice [56], [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>In a recent study in maize plants that were resistant to the fungus Exserohilum turcicum, miR530 was identified as a novel miRNA and was predicted to target genes that are involved in kinase activities in addition to DNA-binding TFs [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Based on the significant upregulation of miR530 in response to Fusarium infection and its unique target genes in the chickpea, it appears to be involved in the response to pathogen attack. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>The three legume-specific miRNAs (miR2111, miR2118 and miR5213) play critical roles during pathogen attack. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>In the chickpea, miR2111 targets a Kelch repeat-containing F-box protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>F-box proteins are responsible for the controlled ubiquitin-dependent degradation of cellular regulatory proteins and are involved in defense responses, auxin responses and floral organ development [59], [60], [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Targets of F-box proteins are central regulators of key cellular events and include G1 cyclins and inhibitors of cyclin-dependent kinases [62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>It appears that miR2111 and F-box proteins act together to regulate the defense response in chickpea following biotic stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Other than F-box proteins, miR2111 also targets TIR domain-containing NBS-LRR disease resistance proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>miR2118 and miR5213 also target the same class of R genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>TIR, which is an F-box protein, is a receptor for the plant hormone auxin [63], [64], [65], [51], and LRR consists of tandem Kelch repeats [66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the chickpea miR2118 was upregulated in response to wilt infection and down regulated following salt stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>miR2118 has also been shown to be suppressed after Verticillium fungal attack in cotton [67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Fusarium wilt leads to symptoms that are similar to those of Verticillium wilt, whose common host plant is cotton. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>miR2118 functions through three novel target transcripts encoding TIR-NBS-LRR disease resistance proteins, but its functional regulation remains unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>In the soybean, miR2118 targets the protein family that is associated with disease resistance in addition to zinc finger proteins [55] and replication termination factor 2 in response to biotic (Asian soybean rust) and abiotic (water deficiency) stresses [35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Other miRNAs also target disease resistance genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>For example, novel car-miRNA023 target proteins are involved in disease resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>The highly conserved miRNA171 family targets more than 20 genes that are involved in different processes and pathways in the chickpea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>One particular member, miR171_7, targets a disease resistance-responsive dirigent-like protein (DIR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The conspicuous involvement of disease resistance genes in the response to pathogen attack has been previously established. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>ESTs encoding dirigent proteins were identified in the SSH library of a chickpea that was infected with Fusarium wilt [68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Dirigent proteins impart disease resistance through their involvement in lignification during biotic stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Similar studies have been reported involving Gossypium barbadense that was infected with Verticillium fungus, in which two DIR genes were isolated from the SSH library [69]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Many of the genes that are targeted by miRNAs are involved in disease resistance and growth-related processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it can be surmised that these miRNAs are involved in the regulation of plant development and pathogen growth by acting both as positive and negative regulators, depending on their target genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Expression patterns during abiotic stress </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Our library allowed for the identification of a large number of conserved salt-responsive miRNAs, including miR390, miR172, miR171, miR169, miR408, miR159, miR396, miR2111, miR5213, miR397, miR393, miR162, miR168, miR166, miR167, miR156, miR530, miR399, miR160, miR319, miR164, miR398, miR2118 and miR394. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Among these miRNAs, miR156, miR396 and miR319 were upregulated in response to salt stress, which was confirmed using qRT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Our results agreed with a previous study involving Arabidopsis, in which 10 salt-responsive miRNAs (miR156, miR165, miR319, miR393, miR396, miR167, miR168, miR171, miR152 and miR394) were reported to be involved in the high salinity stress response [70]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>In the chickpea, the transcript levels of miR156 family members were elevated in response to salt stress compared with those of miR166 and others as has been reported in previous studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Some of the miRNAs that are regulated under salt stress in other plant systems were not found in our library. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>This phenomenon may be due to different stages or stress conditions; i.e., particular treatment methods or species-specific responses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have demonstrated that miR169 family members are associated with high salt stress [71]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>From our target prediction analysis, miR169-targeted genes belong to the nuclear TF family, which contains a CCAAT-binding complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>This CCAAT-binding complex is a eukaryotic promoter element that is evolutionary conserved [72]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Recent studies have demonstrated that these proteins play significant roles in abiotic stress-response pathways [39], [73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>The genes that are targeted by miR169 function in transcriptional regulation, suggesting their significant involvement in the salt stress response. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>In this study, the salt-responsive miRNA miR390 explicitly targeted protein kinases and the CZF1 TF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The CZF TF is associated with intracellular signal transduction, is involved in the negative regulation of programmed cell death and responds to fungal attack via plant defense mechanisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>CZF1 contains a zinc finger with a CCCH-type domain and has been reported in Arabidopsis thaliana to be salt-inducible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>A parallel study in upland cotton reported that the LZF TF acted in response to salt stress [74], and its network of protein-protein interactions was deduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>The chickpea miR396 exhibited higher expression levels under salt stress and was also reported to be salt-responsive in rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Additionally, transgenic lines over expressing osa-mir396c showed reduced tolerances to salt and alkali stresses compared with wild type plants [75]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>In our analysis of the miRNA expression data under both biotic and abiotic stresses, few were upregulated under both types of stresses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>miR396 and a member of the miR156 family were upregulated in response to both the wilt and salt stresses at levels of approximately 1.5-fold, indicating the relative similarity between fungal infection- and salinity stress-responses in the chickpea, which was stated in a previous report, in which the chickpea responded to fungal infection (Ascochyta blight) more similarly to high salinity stress than to drought or cold stresses [76]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Additionally, cross talk exists between the stress-signaling pathways that involve several kinases and TFs that are important targeting candidates for several miRNAs under wilt and salt stresses [77], [78]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Our data indicate that miR172, miR319, miR171, miR390 and miR396 have serine/threonine protein kinases and MAPK protein kinases as their target genes, which involve signaling pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>It can be presumed that together, these miRNAs might mediate defense mechanisms under stress conditions via transcriptional regulators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>miRNAs also target genes that are directly or indirectly involved in the defense against various stresses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>For example, car-miR08 targets a chalcone synthase gene, which is an intermediate in flavonoid biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Flavonoids are secondary metabolites that serve variable functions, including those involving pigmentation, UV protection and antifungal defense. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it can be conferred that these miRNAs come into play during stress management in plants by targeting the genes that are involved either directly or indirectly. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The explicit role of miRNAs in regulating defense mechanisms by the complementary binding of target genes is evident through exhaustive literature reviews. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>This study will aid in the elucidation of the stress response mechanisms that are utilized by the chickpea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Further, there is limited available knowledge describing comprehensive studies of miRNA expression in the chickpea in response to particular stresses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Plant materials and stress treatments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>The chickpea cultivar ICC4958 was used throughout the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>ICC4958 is a Fusarium wilt-resistant and salt-sensitive chickpea cultivar [79], [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>The plants of the ICC4958 cultivar were grown on a 16-h day/8-h night photoperiod cycle at 25±2°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Fourteen-day-old seedlings were subjected to the wilt and salt stresses separately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>The stress treatments were performed as follows: for wilt stress, two-week-old plants that were grown under hydroponic conditions were exposed to a toxin that was isolated from the fungus Fusarium oxysporum f.sp. ciceris for one day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>For salt stress, the roots of two-week-old seedlings were immersed in a 150 mM NaCl solution for 12 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>All of the tissues (control, wilt-stressed and salt-stressed) were harvested at their respective time points, snap-frozen in liquid nitrogen and maintained at −80°C for further analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Small RNA library preparation and sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was isolated using the TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer's protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>For the construction of the small RNA library, low molecular weight (LMW) RNA was enriched by the LiCl method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Equal amounts of RNA were pooled from the root and shoot tissues for each group to generate a LMW RNA library. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>The RNA was run on a 15% polyacrylamide gel, and the 20 to 30 nt small RNA fraction was extracted and eluted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>A preadenylated adaptor was ligated to the 5′ end of the small RNAs with T4 ligase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The ligation product was eluted, and subsequently, 3′ end adaptor ligation was performed [80] followed by RT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>The PCR products were checked for quality and quantified using a Bioanalyzer (Agilent, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>The samples were then sequenced using the Illumina Genome Analyzer IIx (Illumina Inc., USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Computational sequence analysis for identification of miRNAs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>The total reads were trimmed and filtered using the UEA small RNA workbench 2.4- Plant version sequence file pre-processing tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://srna-tools.cmp.uea.ac.uk/">http://srna-tools.cmp.uea.ac.uk/</ext-link>) [81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>The unique tags were generated following a series of processing steps, which included adaptor trimming (using the adaptor removal tool), the elimination of low-quality sequences and the removal of contaminated and other non-coding RNAs, including tRNAs, rRNAs, etc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>The UEA sRNA toolkit-Plant version filter pipeline (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://srna-tools.cmp.uea.ac.uk/">http://srna-tools.cmp.uea.ac.uk/</ext-link>) was used to exclude the low-complexity and low-quality sequences and eliminate the t/r RNA population by mapping them to plant t/r RNAs from the "Rfam" database, Arabidopsis tRNAs from “The Genomic tRNA Database” and plant t/rRNA sequences from the “EMBL” release 95. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Then, the miRCat pipeline (miRNA categorization) was used to predict novel miRNAs and their precursors using default parameters [82]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>The secondary structures of the small RNA sequences were folded using RNAfold (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rna.tbi.univie.ac.at/cgi-bin/RNAfold.cgi">http://rna.tbi.univie.ac.at/cgi-bin/RNAfold.cgi</ext-link>) to predict potential miRNA precursors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>The small RNA sequences that had characteristic hairpin structures, together with additional minimal folding free-energy indices (MFEI) [83], [84], were considered to be candidate miRNAs by miRCat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>The small RNA sequences that matched the following criteria were considered to be valid miRNA precursors: i) no more than 3 consecutive mismatches between the miRNA and miRNA*; ii) at least 17 of the 25 nt surrounding the miRNA must be involved in base pairing; iii) the hairpin must be at least 75 nt in length; and iv) at least 50% of the bases in the hairpin should be paired. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>The folding structures of the precursors of the new miRNA with the miRNA* were carried out using the UEA sRNA toolkit-RNA hairpin folding and annotation tool, which uses the Vienna Package to obtain the secondary structure of a precursor sequence, highlighting the miRNA/miRNA* sequences on the hairpin structure [85]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>The data discussed in this publication has been deposited in Gene Expression Omnibus [86] repository under the accession number GSE57857 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE57857">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE57857</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>miRNA validation by poly(A) tail assay-based quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>The predicted chickpea miRNAs were validated by performing poly(A)-tailed RT-PCR on sixteen miRNAs, including eleven conserved and five novel miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>The total RNAs from the treated and control samples were extracted using the TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>A 1-µg aliquot of this RNA was used for the poly(A) tailing using the Poly(A) Tailing Kit (Ambion, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions and then purified using the RNeasyMinElute Cleanup Kit (QIAGENGmBH, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>The poly(A) RNA (2 µg) was then reverse-transcribed into cDNA that was primed by a standard poly(T) anchor adaptor using an RTQ primer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>For the RT-PCR reaction, the conditions were as follows: 65°C for 10 min, 4°C for 2 min, 50°C for 60 min and 70°C for 15 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Three biological replicates per sample were used for the analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>The poly(T) cDNA was diluted 10-fold and used to perform qRT-PCR using KAPA FAST SYBR Green chemistry (Kapa Biosystems, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>For the qRT-PCR, the sequences of the specific miRNAs that were validated served as the forward primer and RTQ uni-primer, having an adaptor sequence as the reverse primer (Table S7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>The 5S rRNA was used as the reference gene for all of the reactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Three biological replicates were used per sample in addition to three technical replicates along with a no-template control and no-RT enzyme control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>The data were analyzed using the 2[-Delta DeltaC(T)] method [87] and reported as the means ± standard errors (SE) of three biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Prediction and validation of chickpea miRNA target genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>The chickpea transcript dataset, which was downloaded from the chickpea transcriptome database (CTDB), was used to determine the potential target mRNA candidates for the miRNAs using the psRNATarget program with default parameters (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plantgrn.noble.org/psRNATarget/">http://plantgrn.noble.org/psRNATarget/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>To reduce the false-positive prediction rate, the cut-off threshold was set at 0 to 3.0 points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Thus, all of the sequences with ≤3.0 points were considered to be miRNA targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>The functional annotations of the predicted target transcripts were performed using the NCBI nucleic acid and protein databases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Based on the predicted data, miRNA166 was validated using modified 5′ RACE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>For this validation, the FirstChoice RLM-RACE Kit (Ambion, USA) was used with minor modifications, and the cDNA amplification was carried out using 1 µg of total RNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>A single PCR fragment was cloned into the pGEM-T Easy Vector (Promega, USA) and sequenced to identify the 5′end of the target gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Analyses of GO terms and KEGG pathways </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>The GO terms of the target genes were annotated according to their biological processes, molecular functions or involvement as cellular components using Blast2GO [88]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>The enzyme mapping of the annotated sequences was performed directly using the GO terms, and the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) was used to define the KEGG orthologs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0108851.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Elimination summary of the reads. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0108851.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0108851.s002"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Conserved miRNAs that were identified in the three libraries with their detailed information. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>(XLSX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0108851.s002.xlsx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0108851.s003"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Precursor sequences of conserved miRNAs with their predicted secondary structures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>(XLSX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0108851.s003.xlsx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0108851.s004"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>Detailed information regarding novel chickpea miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>(XLSX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0108851.s004.xlsx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0108851.s005"><label>Table S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Precursor sequences of novel miRNAs with their predicted secondary structures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>(XLSX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0108851.s005.xlsx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0108851.s006"><label>Table S5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>List of the target genes that were identified for all of the conserved miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>(XLSX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0108851.s006.xlsx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0108851.s007"><label>Table S6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>List of the target genes that were identified for all of the novel miRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>(XLSX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0108851.s007.xlsx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0108851.s008"><label>Table S7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>List of the primer sequences that were used in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>(XLSX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0108851.s008.xlsx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to thank Dr. Rajeev Varshney, ICRISAT, India, and Dr. C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Bharadwaj, Genetics, IARI, India, for providing the seeds of the chickpea cultivar ICC4958. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>We are also thankful to Dr. Pooja Choudhary for providing the toxin that was isolated from the fungus Fusarium oxysporum f.sp. ciceris. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Small RNA sequencing was performed at DBT-funded High-throughput Sequencing Facility at University of Delhi South Campus, New Delhi. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0108851-Bartel1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>1 BartelDP (2004) MicroRNAs: genomics, biogenesis, mechanism, and function. Cell 116: 281–297.14744438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Sunkar1"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>2 SunkarR, LiYF, JagadeeswaranG (2012) Functions of microRNAs in plant stress responses. Trends Plant Sci 17: 196–203.22365280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Lee1"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>3 LeeRC, FeinbaumRL, AmbrosV (1993) The C. elegans heterochronic gene lin-4 encodes small RNAs with antisense complementarity to lin-14. Cell 75: 843–854.8252621 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Reinhart1"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>4 ReinhartBJ, SlackFJ, BassonM, PasquinelliAE, BettingerJC, et al (2000) The 21-nucleotide let-7 RNA regulates developmental timing in Caenorhabditis elegans . Nature 403: 901–906.10706289 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Reinhart2"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>5 ReinhartBJ, WeinsteinEG, RhoadesMW, BartelB, BartelDP (2002) MicroRNAs in plants. Genes Dev 16: 1616–1626.12101121 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Kozomara1"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>6Kozomara A, Griffiths-Jones S (2011) miRBase: integrating microRNA annotation and deep-sequencing data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>NAR 39(Database Issue): D152–D157. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-FAOSTAT1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>7FAOSTAT (2012) Faostat.fao.org/site/567/DesktopDefault.aspx?PageID = 567 anchor. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Boominathan1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>8 BoominathanP, ShuklaR, KumarA, MannaD, NegiD, et al (2004) Long term transcript accumulation during the development of dehydration adaptation in Cicer arietinum. Plant Physiol 135: 1608–1620.15247380 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Deokar1"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>9 DeokarAA, KondawarV, JainPK, KaruppayilSM, RajuNL, et al (2011) Comparative analysis of expressed sequence tags (ESTs) between drought-tolerant and -susceptible genotypes of chickpea under terminal drought stress. BMC Plant Biol 11: 70.21513527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Flowers1"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>10 FlowersTJ, GaurPM, GowdaCLL, KrishnamurthyL, SrinivasanS, et al (2010) Salt sensitivity in chickpea. Plant Cell Environ 33: 490–509.19843257 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Turner1"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>11 TurnerNC, ColmerTD, QuealyJ, PushpavalliR, KrishnamurthyL, et al (2013) Salinity tolerance and ion accumulation in chickpea (Cicer arietinum L.) subjected to salt stress. Plant Soil 365: 347–361. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Agarwal1"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>12 AgarwalG, JhanwarS, PriyaP, SinghVK, SaxenaMS, et al (2012) Comparative analysis of kabuli chickpea transcriptome with desi and wild chickpea provides a rich resource for development of functional markers. PLoS One 7: e52443.23300670 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Varshney1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>13 VarshneyRK, SongC, SaxenaRK, AzamS, YuS, et al (2013) Draft genome sequence of chickpea (Cicer arietinum) provides a resource for trait improvement. Nature Biotech 31: 240–246. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Jain1"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>14Jain M, Misra G, Patel RK, Priya P, Jhanwar S, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>(2013) A draft genome sequence of the pulse crop chickpea (Cicer arietinum L.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Plant J. doi: 10.1111/tpj.12173. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Hu1"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>15 HuJ, SunL, DingY (2013) Identification of conserved microRNAs and their targets in chickpea (Cicer arietinum L.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Plant Signal Behav. 18: 8. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Rajagopalan1"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>16 RajagopalanR, VaucheretH, TrejoJ, BartelDP (2006) A diverse and evolutionarily fluid set of microRNAs in Arabidopsis thaliana. Genes Dev 20: 3407–3425.17182867 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Moxon1"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>17 MoxonS, JingR, SzittyaG, SchwachF, Rusholme PilcherRL, et al (2008) Deep sequencing of tomato short RNAs identifies microRNAs targeting genes involved in fruit ripening. Genome Res18: 1602–1609. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Szittya1"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>18 SzittyaG, MoxonS, SantosDM, JingR, FevereiroMP, et al (2008) High-throughput sequencing of Medicago truncatula short RNAs identifies eight new miRNA families. BMC Genomics 9: 593.19068109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Martinez1"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>19 MartinezG, FormentJ, LlaveC, PallasV, GomezG (2011) High-throughput sequencing, characterization and detection of new and conserved cucumber miRNAs. PLoS One 6: e19523.21603611 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Zeng1"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>20 ZengQY, YangCY, MaQB, LiXP, DongWW, et al (2012) Identification of wild soybean miRNAs and their target genes responsive to aluminum stress. BMC Plant Biol12: 182. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-GriffithsJones1"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>21Griffiths-Jones S (2004) The microRNA Registry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>NAR 32(Database Issue): D109–D111. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-GriffithsJones2"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>22Griffiths-Jones S, Grocock RJ, van Dongen S, Bateman A, Enright AJ (2006) miRBase: microRNA sequences, targets and gene nomenclature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>NAR (Database Issue): D140–D144. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-GriffithsJones3"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>23Griffiths-Jones S, Saini HK, van Dongen S, Enright AJ (2008) miRBase: tools for microRNA genomics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>NAR 36(Database Issue): D154–D158. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Jagadeeswaran1"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>24 JagadeeswaranG, ZhengY, LiYF, ShuklaLI, MattsJ, et al (2009) Cloning and characterization of small RNAs from Medicago truncatula reveals four novel legume-specific microRNA families. New Phytol 184: 85–98.19555436 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Devers1"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>25 DeversEA, BranscheidA, MayP, KrajinskiF (2011) Stars and symbiosis: MicroRNA- and MicroRNA*-mediated transcript cleavage involved in arbuscular mycorrhizal symbiosis. Plant Physiol 156: 1990–2010.21571671 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Mohorianu1"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>26 MohorianuI, SchwachF, JingR, Lopez-GomollonS, MoxonS, et al (2011) Profiling of short RNAs during fleshy fruit development reveals stage-specific sRNAome expression patterns. Plant J67: 232–246. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Shivaprasad1"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>27 ShivaprasadPV, ChenHM, PatelK, BondDM, SantosBA, et al (2012) microRNA superfamily regulates nucleotide binding site leucine-rich repeats and other mRNAs. Plant Cell 24: 859–874.22408077 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Garg1"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>28 GargR, PatelRK, TyagiAK, JainM (2011) De novo assembly of chickpea transcriptome using short reads for gene discovery and marker identification. DNA Res 18: 53–63.21217129 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Meyers1"><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>29 MeyersBC, AxtellMJ, BartelB, BartelDP, BaulcombeD, et al (2008) Criteria for annotation of plant microRNAs. Plant Cell 20: 3186–3190.19074682 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Chi1"><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>30 ChiXY, YangQL, ChenXP, WangJY, PanLJ, et al (2011) Identification and characterization of microRNAs from peanut (Arachis hypogaea L.) by high-throughput sequencing. PLoS One 6: e27530.22110666 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Zuker1"><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>31 ZukerM (2003) Mfold web server for nucleic acid folding and hybridization prediction. Nucleic Acids Res 31: 3406–3415.12824337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Sunkar2"><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>32 SunkarR, JagadeeswaranG (2008) Insilico identification of conserved microRNAs in large number of diverse plant species. BMC Plant Biol 8: 37.18416839 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Dai1"><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>33 DaiX, ZhaoPX (2011) psRNATarget: a plant small RNA target analysis server. Nucleic Acids Res 39: 9–155. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Williams1"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>34 WilliamsL, GriggSP, XieM, ChristensenS, FletcherJC (2005) Regulation of Arabidopsis shoot apical meristem and lateral organ formation by microRNA miR166g and its AtHD-ZIP target genes. Development 132: 3657–3668.16033795 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Kulcheski1"><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>35 KulcheskiFR, de OliveiraLF, MolinaLG, AlmeraoMP, RodriguesFA, et al (2011) Identification of novel soybean microRNAs involved in abiotic and biotic stresses. BMC Genomics 12: 307.21663675 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Kim1"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>36 KimJ, JungJH, ReyesJL, KimYS, KimSY, et al (2005) microRNA-directed cleavage of ATHB15 mRNA regulates vascular development in Arabidopsis inflorescence stems. Plant J 42: 84–94.15773855 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Byrne1"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>37 ByrneME (2006) Shoot meristem function and leaf polarity: the role of class III HD-ZIP genes. PLoS Genet 2: 785–790. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Llave1"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>38 LlaveC, KasschauKD, RectorMA, CarringtonJC (2002) Endogenous and silencing-associated small RNAs in plants. Plant Cell 14: 1605–1619.12119378 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-JonesRhoades1"><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>39 Jones-RhoadesMW, BartelDP (2004) Computational identification of plant microRNAs and their targets, including a stress-induced miRNA. Mol Cell 14: 787–799.15200956 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Schwab1"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>40 SchwabR, PalatnikJF, RiesterM, SchommerC, SchmidM, et al (2005) Specific effects of microRNAs on the plant transcriptome. Dev Cell 8: 517–527.15809034 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Song1"><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>41 SongQX, LiuYF, HuXY, ZhangWK, MaB, et al (2011) Identification of miRNAs and their target genes in developing soybean seeds by deep sequencing. BMC Plant Biol 11: 5.21219599 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Lu1"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>42 LuS, SunYH, AmersonH, ChiangVL (2007) MicroRNAs in loblolly pine (Pinus taeda L.) and their association with fusiform rust gall development. Plant J 51: 1077–1098.17635765 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Vaucheret1"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>43 VaucheretH, VazquezF, CreteP, BartelDP (2004) The action of ARGONAUTE1 in the miRNA pathway and its regulation by the miRNA pathway are crucial for plant development. Genes Dev 18: 1187–1197.15131082 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Huertero1"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>44 HuerteroCA, Pe'rezB, RabanalF, Blanco-MeloD, RosaCD, et al (2009) Conserved and novel miRNAs in the legume Phaseolus vulgaris in response to stress. Plant Mol Biol 70: 385–401.19353277 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Millan1"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>45 MillanT, ClarkeHJ, SiddiqueKHM, BuhariwallaHK, GaurPM, et al (2006) Chickpea molecular breeding: New tools and concepts. Euphytica 147: 81–103. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Bartel2"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>46 BartelB, BartelDP (2003) MicroRNAs: at the root of plant development. Plant Physiol 132: 709–717.12805599 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Mi1"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>47 MiS, CaiT, HuY, ChenY, HodgesE, et al (2008) Sorting of small RNAs into Arabidopsis argonaute complexes is directed by the 59 terminal nucleotide. Cell 133: 116–127.18342361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Xue1"><text><SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>48 XueLJ, ZhangJJ, XueHW (2009) Characterization and expression profiles of miRNAs in rice seeds. Nucleic Acids Res 37: 916–930.19103661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Jagadeeswaran2"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>49 JagadeeswaranG, ZhengY, SumathipalaN, JiangHB, ArreseEL, et al (2010) Deep sequencing of small RNA libraries reveals dynamic regulation of conserved and novel microRNAs and microRNA-stars during silkworm development. BMC Genomics 11: 52.20089182 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Zhou1"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>50 ZhouH, HuangX, CuiH, LuoX, TangY, et al (2010a) miR-155 and its star-form partner miR-155* cooperatively regulate type I interferon production by human plasmacytoid dendritic cells. Blood 116: 5885–5894.20852130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Navarro1"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>51 NavarroL, DunoyerP, JayF, ArnoldB, DharmasiriN, et al (2006) A plant miRNA contributes to antibacterial resistance by repressing auxin signaling. Science 21: 436–439. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Zhang1"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>52 ZhangX, ZhaoH, GaoS, WangWC, Katiyar-AgarwalS, et al (2011) Arabidopsis Argonaute 2 regulates innate immunity via miRNA393(*)-mediated silencing of a Golgi-localized SNARE gene, MEMB12. Mol Cell 42: 356–366.21549312 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Loudet1"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>53 LoudetO, MichaelTP, BurgerBT, Le MetteC, MocklerTC, et al (2008) A zinc knuckle protein that negatively controls morning-specific growth in Arabidopsis thaliana . Proc Natl Acad SciUSA105: 17193–17198. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Lu2"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>54 LuS, SunYH, ChiangVL (2008) Stress-responsive microRNAs in Populus. Plant J 55: 131–151.18363789 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Wong1"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>55 WongCE, ZhaoYT, WangXJ, CroftL, WangZH, et al (2011) MicroRNAs in the shoot apical meristem of soybean. J Exp Bot 62: 2495–2506.21504877 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Guzman1"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>56 GuzmanF, AlmeraoMP, KorbesAP, Loss-MoraisG, MargisR (2012) Identification of MicroRNAs from Eugenia uniflora by high-throughput sequencing and bioinformatics analysis. PLoS One 7: e49811.23166775 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Liu1"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>57 LiuB, LiP, LiX, LiuC, CaoS, et al (2005) Loss of function of OsDCL1 affects microRNA accumulation and causes developmental defects in rice. Plant Physiol 39: 296–305. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Wu1"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>58 WuF, ShuJ, JinW (2014) Identification and validation of miRNAs associated with the resistance of Maize (Zea mays L.) to Exserohilum turcicum . PLoS One 9: e87251.24489881 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Xie1"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>59 XieDX, FeysBF, JamesS, Nieto-RostroM, TurnerJG (1998)  COI1: an Arabidopsis gene required for jasmonate regulated defense and fertility. Science 280: 1091–1094.9582125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Samach1"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>60 SamachA, KlenzJE, KohalmiSE, RisseeuwE, HaughnG, et al (1999) The UNUSUAL FLORAL ORGANS gene of Arabidopsis thaliana is an F-box protein required for normal patterning and growth in the floral meristem. Plant J 20: 433–445.10607296 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Gray1"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>61 GrayWM, EstelleM (2000) Function of the ubiquitin proteasome pathway in auxin response. TIBS 25: 133–138.10694884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Craig1"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>62 CraigKL, TyersM (1999) The F-box: a new motif for ubiquitin dependent proteolysis in cell cycle regulation and signal transduction. Prog Biophys Mol Biol 72: 299–328.10581972 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Gray2"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>63 GrayWM, delPozoJC, WalkerL, HobbieL, RisseeuwE, et al (1999) Identification of an SCF ubiquitin-ligase complex required for auxin response in Arabidopsis thaliana. Genes Dev 13: 1678–1691.10398681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Dharmasiri1"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>64 DharmasiriN, DharmisiriS, EstelleM (2005) The F-box protein TIR1 is an auxin receptor. Nature 435: 441.15917797 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Kepinski1"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>65 KepinskiS, LeyserO (2005) The Arabidopsis F-box protein TIR1 is an auxin receptor. Nature 435: 446–51.15917798 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Andrade1"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>66 AndradeMA, González-GuzmánM, SerranoR, RodríguezPL (2001) A combination of the F-box motif and kelch repeats defines a large Arabidopsis family of F-box proteins. Plant Mol Biol 46: 603.11516153 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Yin1"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>67 YinZ, LiY, HanX, ShenF (2012) Genome-wide profiling of miRNAs and other small non-coding RNAs in the Verticillium dahliae inoculated cotton roots. PLoS ONE 7: e35765.22558219 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Ashraf1"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>68 AshrafN, GhaiD, BarmanP, BasuS, GangisettyN, et al (2009) Comparative analyses of genotype dependent expressed sequence tags and stress-responsive transcriptome of chickpea wilt illustrate predicted and unexpected genes and novel regulators of plant immunity. BMC Genomics 10: 415.19732460 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Zhu1"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>69 ZhuL, ZhangX, TuL, ZengF, NieY, et al (2007) Isolation and characterization of two novel dirigent-like genes highly induced in cotton (Gossypium barbadense and G. hirsutum) after infection by Verticillium dahliae . Plant Pathol 89: 41–45. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Liu2"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>70 LiuHH, TianX, LiYJ, WuCA, ZhengCC (2008) Microarray-based analysis of stress-regulated microRNAs in Arabidopsis thaliana. RNA 14: 836–843.18356539 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Li1"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>71 LiWX, OonoY, ZhuJ, HeXJ, WuJM, et al (2008) The Arabidopsis NFYA5 transcription factor is regulated transcriptionally and post transcriptionally to promote drought resistance. Plant Cell 20: 2238–2251.18682547 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Zhao1"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>72 ZhaoB, GeL, LiangR, LiW, RuanK, et al (2009) Members of miR-169 family are induced by high salinity and transiently inhibit the NF-YA transcription factor. BMC Mol Biol 10: 29.19351418 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Jain2"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>73 JainM, NijhawanA, AroraR, AgarwalP, RayS, et al (2007) F-box proteins in rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide analysis, classification, temporal and spatial gene expression during panicle and seed development, and regulation by light and abiotic stress. Plant Physiol 143: 1467–1483.17293439 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Zhang2"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>74 ZhangX, ZhenJB, LiZH, KangDM, YangYM, et al (2011) Expression profile of early responsive genes under salt stress in upland cotton (Gossypium hirsutum L.). Plant Mol Biol Rep 29: 626–637. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Gao1"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>75 GaoP, BaiX, YangL, LvD, LiY, et al (2010) Over-expression of osa- MIR396c decreases salt and alkali stress tolerance. Planta 231: 991–1001.20135324 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Mantri1"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>76 MantriNL, FordR, CoramTE, PangECK (2010a) Evidence of unique and shared responses to major biotic and abiotic stresses in chickpea. Environ Exper Bot 69: 286–292. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Colcombet1"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>77 ColcombetJ, HirtH (2008) Arabidopsis MAPKs: a complex signalling network involved in multiple biological processes. Biochem J 413: 217–226.18570633 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Rodriguez1"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>78 RodriguezRE, MecchiaMA, DebernardiJM, SchommerC, WeigelD, et al (2010) Control of cell proliferation in Arabidopsis thaliana by microRNA miR396. Development 137: 103–112.20023165 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Winter1"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>79 WinterP, BenkoAM, HüttelB, RatnaparkheM, TulluA, et al (2000) A linkage map of the chickpea (Cicer arietinum L.) genome based on recombinant inbred lines from a C. arietinum × C. reticulatum cross: localization of resistance genes for fusarium wilt races 4 and 5. Theor Appl Genet 101: 1155–1163. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Lu3"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>80 LuC, MeyersBC, GreenPJ (2007) Construction of small RNA cDNA libraries for deep sequencing. Methods 43: 110–117.17889797 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Stocks1"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>81 StocksMB, MoxonS, MaplesonD, WoolfendenHC, MohorianuI, et al (2012) The UEA sRNA workbench: a suite of tools for analysing and visualizing next generation sequencing microRNA and small RNA datasets. Bioinformatics 28: 2059–2061.22628521 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Moxon2"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>82 MoxonS, SchwachF, DalmayT, MacLeanD, StudholmeDJ, et al (2008) A toolkit for analysing large-scale plant small RNA datasets. Bioinformatics 24: 2252–2253.18713789 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Bonnet1"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>83 BonnetE, WuytsJ, RouzéP, Van de PeerY (2004) Evidence that microRNA precursors, unlike other non-coding RNAs, have lower folding free energies than random sequences. Bioinformatics 20: 2911–7.15217813 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Zhang3"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>84 ZhangBH, PanXP, CoxSB, CobbGP, AndersonTA (2006) Evidence that miRNAs are different from other RNAs. Cell Mol Life Sci 63: 246–254.16395542 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Hofacker1"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>85 HofackerIL (2003) Vienna RNA secondary structure server. Nucleic Acids Res 31: 3429–3431.12824340 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Edgar1"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>86 EdgarR, DomracheyM, LashAE (2002) Gene Expression Omnibus: NCBI gene expression and hybridization array data repository. Nucleic Acids Res 30: 207–210.11752295 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Livak1"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>87 LivakKJ, SchmittgenTD (2001) Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2[-Delta DeltaC (T)] Method. Methods 25: 402–408.11846609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0108851-Conesa1"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>88 ConesaA, GotzS, Garcia-GomezJM, TerolJ, TalonM, et al (2005) Blast2GO: a universal tool for annotation, visualization and analysis in functional genomics research. Bioinformatics 21: 3674–3676.16081474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
