
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Res Notes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Res Notes</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Research Notes</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1756-0500</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4295470</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25486898</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3456</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-0500-7-884</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Kinase domain-targeted isolation of defense-related receptor-like kinases (RLK/Pelle) in Platanus × acerifolia: phylogenetic and structural analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Pilotti</surname><given-names>Massimo</given-names></name><address><email>massimo.pilotti@entecra.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff62"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brunetti</surname><given-names>Angela</given-names></name><address><email>angela.brunetti@entecra.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff62"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Uva</surname><given-names>Paolo</given-names></name><address><email>paolo.uva@crs4.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff63"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lumia</surname><given-names>Valentina</given-names></name><address><email>valelu70@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff62"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tizzani</surname><given-names>Lorenza</given-names></name><address><email>lorenza.tizzani@fastwebnet.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff62"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gervasi</surname><given-names>Fabio</given-names></name><address><email>fabio.gervasi@entecra.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff64"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iacono</surname><given-names>Michele</given-names></name><address><email>michele.iacono@roche.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff65"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pindo</surname><given-names>Massimo</given-names></name><address><email>massimo.pindo@fmach.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff66"/></contrib><aff id="Aff62"><label/>Plant Pathology Research Center, CRA-PAV Agricultural Research Council, V. C.G. Bertero 22, 00156 Rome, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff63"><label/>CRS4 Bioinformatics Laboratory POLARIS Science and Technology Park, 09010 Pula, Cagliari, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff64"><label/>Fruit Tree Research Center, CRA-FRU Agricultural Research Council, V. Fioranello, 52, 00134 Rome, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff65"><label/>Roche Diagnostics SpA, V. G.B. Stucchi 110, 20052 Monza Milano, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff66"><label/>Research and Innovation Centre, Edmund Mach Foundation, V. E. Mach 1, 38010 San Michele a/A, Trento, Italy </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>884</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Pilotti et al.; licensee BioMed Central. 2014</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This article is published under license to BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Plant receptor-like kinase (RLK/Pelle) family regulates growth and developmental processes and interaction with pathogens and symbionts. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Platanaceae is one of the earliest branches of Eudicots temporally located before the split which gave rise to Rosids and Asterids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Thus investigations into the RLK family in Platanus can provide information on the evolution of this gene family in the land plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Moreover RLKs are good candidates for finding genes that are able to confer resistance to Platanus pathogens. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Degenerate oligonucleotide primers targeting the kinase domain of stress-related RLKs were used to isolate for the first time 111 RLK gene fragments in Platanus × acerifolia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Sequences were classified as candidates of the following subfamilies: CrRLK1L, LRR XII, WAK-like, and LRR X-BRI1 group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>All the structural features typical of the RLK kinase domain were identified, including the non-RD motif which marks potential pathogen recognition receptors (PRRs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The LRR XII candidates, whose counterpart in Arabidopsis and rice comprises non-RD PRRs, were mostly non-RD kinases, suggesting a group of PRRs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Region-specific signatures of a relaxed purifying selection in the LRR XII candidates were also found, which is novel for plant RLK kinase domain and further supports the role of LRR XII candidates as PRRs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>As we obtained CrRLK1L candidates using primers designed on Pto of tomato, we analysed the phylogenetic relationship between CrRLK1L and Pto-like of plant species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>We thus classified all non-solanaceous Pto-like genes as CrRLK1L and highlighted for the first time the close phylogenetic vicinity between CrRLK1L and Pto group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The origins of Pto from CrRLK1L is proposed as an evolutionary mechanism. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The signatures of relaxed purifying selection highlight that a group of RLKs might have been involved in the expression of phenotypic plasticity and is thus a good candidate for investigations into pathogen resistance. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Search of Pto-like genes in Platanus highlighted the close relationship between CrRLK1L and Pto group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>It will be exciting to verify if sensu strictu Pto are present in taxonomic groups other than Solanaceae, in order to further clarify the evolutionary link with CrRLK1L. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>We obtained a first valuable resource useful for an in-depth study on stress perception systems. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/1756-0500-7-884) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Platanus</italic> × <italic>acerifolia</italic></kwd><kwd>RLK/Pelle</kwd><kwd>Pto-like</kwd><kwd>CrRLK1L</kwd><kwd>LRR XII</kwd><kwd>WAK-like</kwd><kwd>LRR X-BRI1</kwd><kwd>Relaxed purifying selection</kwd><kwd>Pathogen resistance</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2014</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In animals, cell surface receptor tyrosine kinases (RTKs) and serine/threonine kinase receptors (STRKs) are of primary importance for the perception of intercellular signals and the transduction of signals at an intracellular level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In general the domain composition of these receptors is defined by an extracellular ligand-binding domain, a single-pass trans-membrane domain and a cytoplasmic tyrosine or serine/threonine kinase domain [1, 2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In the plant lineage, the counterpart of RTKs and STRKs is represented by the family of receptor-like kinases (RLKs), which share the same domain composition [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The RLK kinase domain, a serine-threonine kinase, belongs to the same gene family as the Drosophila melanogaster Pelle and mammalian interleukin receptor-associated kinases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Thus the term RLK/Pelle was established [3, 4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>With regard to RLK/Pelles, a striking difference between the land plant and non-plant eukaryote genomes is the size of this family, in fact 329 genes have been identified in moss (Physcomitrella patens), 610 in Arabidopsis, 647 in tomato, 1192 in poplar (Populus trichocarpa), 1070 in rice, 1 and 4 in the animals Drosophila melanogaster and Homo sapiens respectively, and none have been identified in fungal organisms [5, 6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>It has been suggested that one of the evolutionary reasons for the gene family’s expansion derives from the need to cope, as sessile organisms, with an ever-changing environment, including a multitude of mutating pathogenic and would be-pathogenic microbes [4, 5, 7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>This would account for the variety of RLK/Pelle types - 53 subfamilies categorized in Arabidopsis - for the genetic redundancy present in part of the subfamilies, and for the up-regulation of hundreds of RLK/Pelle members under biotic stress [3–5, 7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Some members within the plant RLK/Pelle family, have been shown to be transmembrane receptors [8, 9] and it is likely that this is the main functional contribution of these proteins [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Two functional groups are recognized in plants: RLKs controlling growth and development processes, and RLKs regulating interactions with microbes, both pathogens and symbionts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The rice (Oryza sativa) Xa21 is one example of the latter class, which confers resistance to the bacterium Xanthomonas oryzae pv. oryzae[10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Other examples include EFR (EF-TU RECEPTOR) of Arabidopsis thaliana which is a PAMP (Pathogen Associated Molecular Pattern) receptor [11], and Arabidopsis RFO1 (RESISTANCE TO FUSARIUM OXISPORUM 1) which confers broad spectrum resistance to diverse Fusarium oxisporum races and Verticillium longisporum[12, 13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>A functional dualism may involve BRI1 (BRASSINOSTEROID-INSENSITIVE1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>This RLK/Pelle has an important role in the regulation of growth and development through the perception of brassinosteroids (BRs) [14, 15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Its involvement in stress responses is suggested by the fact that BRs are also strongly related in stress signaling [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, a tomato BRI1 ortholog, SR160 (SYSTEMIN RECEPTOR 160), is able to bind systemin, a solanaceous specific protein which induces systemic wound responses following attack by feeding insects [17] although it does not represent the functional systemin receptor [18, 19]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>A lack of extracellular domain is a characteristic of another class of the plant RLK/Pelle family, the receptor-like cytoplasmic kinases (RLCKs) [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Pto (for Pseudomonas syringae pv. tomato) is a well-known member of this class and confers resistance to the bacterial pathogen, P. syringae pv tomato in wild tomato species, according to a host genotype/pathogen race specificity fashion [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Great interest in Pto orthologs in plant species has arisen from the fact that the overexpression of Pto has been shown to confer a broad spectrum resistance in tomato [21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Platanaceae is a tree family that is considered as one of the earliest branches of Eudicots [22] (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mobot.org/MOBOT/research/APweb/">http://www.mobot.org/MOBOT/research/APweb/</ext-link>.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In contrast, Platanus × acerifolia (Ait.) Willd. is a species of this family which originated in the 17th century from a cross between individuals belonging to the P. occidentalis L. species group and P. orientalis L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>[23, 24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Therefore, P. × acerifolia (Pac) combines genomic contributions from the two parental species, which evolved separately for long geological periods [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The high haploid chromosome number, n =21, suggests that the current Platanaceae had ancient polyploid origins [25] which adds to the overall complexity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Given these features, investigations into the RLK/Pelle family in Pac can provide information on the nature of this gene family in the Dicots, especially when compared with the Arabidopsis counterpart. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Platanaceae suffer from several diseases including canker stain, a vascular disease caused by the fungus Ceratocystis platani (J.M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Walter) Engelbr. &amp; T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Harr., and antrachnose, caused by the fungus Apiognomonia veneta (Sacc. et Speg.), which are particularly destructive and have heavily conditioned the diffusion and cultivation of Platanus spp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>[26, 27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Thus unravelling the resistance response of Platanus to pathogens is necessary in order to sustain and speed up current time-consuming genetic selection programmes [24, 28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The plant RLK/Pelle family is thus a good candidate for finding genes that are able to confer resistance to pathogens. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The aim of this study was to isolate RLK/Pelle genes in Pac which, based on knowledge of Arabidopsis, play a potential role in pathogen perception and signal transduction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>We successfully applied a PCR-based strategy, which targeted a representative region of the kinase domain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>We isolated for the first time RLK/Pelle gene fragments in Pac, with an uninterrupted open reading frame (ORF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Sequence analyses clearly showed that the genes were, in most cases, candidates of the following RLK/Pelle subfamilies: CrRLK1L, LRR XII, WAK-like, LRR X-BRI1 group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>A number of structural motifs and the analysis of non-synonymous versus synonymous substitution rates, confirmed the phylogenetic identification and provided an insight into their potential functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>In fact, the detection in Pac of signals of a completely relaxed purifying selection in sub-regions of the kinase domain, is another important finding of this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>As we isolated CrRLK1L-L using primers designed on Pto of tomato, we also wished to clarify the relationships between Pto-like of several plant species available in the GenBank, the bona fide Pto family of solanaceous species and CrRLK1L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>As a result a close phylogenetic relationship was revealed between Pto and CrRLK1L. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Plant material, nucleic acid extraction and primer design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA was isolated from young leaves collected in the spring from a potted Pac tree (accession MS.12) using a Plant Midi Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Degenerate primers were designed in order to isolate RLK/Pelle candidate genes for pathogen perception and signal transduction: 1) known R genes (Pto, Xa-21, Xa-26, RFO1); 2) PAMP receptor genes (EFR); 3) the whole BRI1 gene group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The primers were designed within the kinase catalytic domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>They were generated from the nucleotide stretches conserved in the model gene and several plant homologs, available from the NCBI GenBank database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>In the case of RFO1, a WAK-like gene, collected sequences were used to infer a phylogenetic tree in order to identify clades of homologous WAK-like genes from which distinct sets of primers were generated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>We then used a similar strategy in order to search for BRI1-like genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>All the information regarding primer is reported in Additional file 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Amplification and cloning of gene fragments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>PCRs were performed in a 50-μl reaction volume containing each dNTP at 200 μM, each primer at 1 μM, 2.5U of Platinum Taq DNA Polymerase High Fidelity (Invitrogen), 2 mM MgSO4, and 100–200 ng of genomic DNA as a template, in the buffer supplied by the manufacturer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The initial denaturation step was carried out at 94°C for 2 min, followed by 35 amplification cycles (94°C for 1 min, annealing at 47°C for 50 s, an extension at 68°C for 1 min) and a final extension step at 68°C for 15 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Analysis of PCR products, cloning and sequencing was as previously described [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>A variable number of clones per cloned DNA band were sequenced in both directions (Bio Fab Research) (Additional file 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>RLK/Pelle-like sequences were deposited in the GenBank database [GenBank: EU722764-EU722869, EU722871-EU722900, HQ425329-30] (Additional file 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Alignments and phylogenetic analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Clone sequences were trimmed of vector and primer sequences and were then considered for further analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>To select gene fragments representing the kinase-catalytic region, the amino acid sequences were compared with UniProt using blastp [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Multiple sequence alignments were performed with MAFFT [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Pairwise local alignments were performed using the EMBOSS Pairwise Alignment suite [32] (gap open: 10; gap extend: 0.5; matrix: Blosum62). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Since we isolated portions of the full length ORF, we classified the Pac sequences according to the nomenclature by Shiu and Bleecker [4] or the name of the gene for which a potential orthology relation was evident, followed by the code -L (= − like). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis was based on the MAFFT alignment of the amino acid sequences of the kinase-catalytic domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Trees were inferred using the Neighbor-joining (NJ) method [33], with 1,000 bootstrap replications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The evolutionary distances were computed using the Poisson correction method with rate uniformity among sites [34] and were in the units of the number of amino acid substitutions per site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Analyses were conducted in Mega version 6 [35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analyses were also conducted with two maximum-likelihood (ML) methods: i) Whelan And Goldman substitution model - WAG [36], with 1,000 bootstrap replications and rate uniformity among sites (analyses were conducted in Mega version 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>ii) ML approach implemented in the TREE-PUZZLE software package [37], with the following parameters: VT (variable time) substitution model [38], gamma-distributed rates of heterogeneity among sites, amino acid frequencies inferred from the data set, branch lengths estimated without the molecular-clock assumption, 50,000 puzzling steps to infer branch support values for the relative majority consensus tree. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>To classify Pac sequences we made a phylogenetic comparison with representative members of all the subfamilies of the Arabidopsis RLK/Pelle complement [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Then sequences were divided into homology groups and each group was compared with the closest whole RLK/Pelle subfamily. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>We also performed a comparative phylogenetic analysis in order to shed light on the relations between the Pto group [39], Pto-like of Solanaceae, Pto-like of other dicot and monocot plants, CrRLK1L, and the Pto-primer-derived sequences obtained in this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Apart from Arabidopsis, genes from nine additional full genome-sequenced species and partial sequences from a number of plant species were included in the phylogenies for comparison. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>All the reference sequences and those used to root the trees are reported in Additional file 4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>In the phylogenetic trees, sequence names contain: I) the acronym of the protein or, secondly, the locus tag or the accession number, II) the Latin name of the species, and III) the RLK/Pelle subfamily to which the protein belongs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Latin names were abbreviated as follows: Arab. thal. = Arabidopsis thaliana, Caps. = Capsicum, Cath. = Catharantus, Frag. = Fragaria, Mu. = Musa, Nicot. tab. = Nicotiana tabacum, Ory. = Oryza, Phas. = Phaseolus, Pop. = Populus, Pot. = Potentilla, Ric. = Ricinus, Sol.pimp. = Solanum pimpinellifolium, Sol.lyc. = Solanum lycopersicum, Vit. = Vitis, Physc.patens = Physcomitrella patens. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Domain detection and determination of other structural features </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Domain detection was performed using Pfam [40] and SMART [41]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic classification at the subfamily level was validated by comparing some representative Pac sequences with long isotigs generated from a 454 GS-FLX transcriptome data set of the same species, though using a different genotype (Pilotti, Brunetti, Iacono and Pindo, unpublished data) (Additional file 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Putative extracellular domains of the isotigs were identified as described above. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Serine-threonine and tyrosine protein kinase motifs [42] were searched for and a consensus was determined by using the motif-based sequence analysis tool MEME [43]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>We compared the activation segment of Pto and BRI1 with the corresponding region of the deduced protein of the entire Pac RLK/Pelle-like sequence complement and the corresponding RLK/Pelle subfamilies of Arabidopsis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Non-synonymous versus synonymous substitution rates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The ratio of non-synonymous (Ka) to synonymous (Ks) nucleotide substitutions was calculated for pairwise comparisons using a 75 bp sliding window with a step size of 15 bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The analysis was based on codon-delimited nucleotide alignments and performed with JCoDA [44] which uses the PAML (yn00) suite [45] and the Yang and Nielsen substitution model [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>JCoDA was also used to identify the individual sites under positive selection (site by site): the site models M7 and M8, which account for transitional rate bias and unequal codon frequencies, were applied, and the differences were assessed with a likelihood ratio test (d.f. = 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The tree topology required by the two models was inferred from the amino acid sequence by the maximum likelihood approach using the Phylip package [47], with a JTT substitution matrix [48] and rate heterogeneity approximated using a discrete γ-distribution with four categories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The posterior probabilities of individual sites belonging to the class Ka/Ks &gt;1 were calculated using the Bayes empirical Bayes approach implemented in PAML. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Codon-delimited alignments were also used to map those positions that were subject to non-synonymous variations in order to: i) identify those that were shared among the different phylogenetic LRR XII-L groups of Pac and LRR XII of Arabidopsis, ii) to describe the amino acid variability at each position. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Amplification pattern and oligonucleotide efficiency </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Generally PCRs based on degenerate oligonucleotide pairs always gave a clear amplification pattern with minimum or no smearing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Evident expected-sized DNA bands were always present and a variable number of clones were sequenced for each band. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>In some cases additional non expected bands of variable intensity were also present but these were not investigated further. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide sequences of the cloned amplicons revealed that oligonucleotide pairs worked highly efficiently at priming the amplification of target genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Amplicons from 16 oligonucleotide pairs-based PCRs, out of 23, yielded RLK/Pelle-like sequences with maximum efficiency (100%) (Additional file 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>A total of 111 out of 136 RLK/Pelle candidates showed an uninterrupted ORF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>These sequences represent the focus of this paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Their length is indicated in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>A total of 26 RLK/Pelle candidates showed interrupted ORFs due to frameshift indels – probably pseudogenes or truncated genes - and were not analysed further.Table 1 RLK/Pelles obtained in Pac  </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analyses for RLK/Pelle subfamily identification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>By using reference sequences of full genome-sequenced species, we initially verified that highly/well supported clades did not change between phylogenies based on the partial kinase domain and those inferred with the complete kinase domain or the full ORF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>A comparison with CrRLK1L and WAK-like phylogenies in other studies [49, 50] further confirmed the robustness of our methodology (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>A highly supported clustering showed that close homologs of CrRLK1L, LRR XII, WAK-like and LRR X-BRI1 group, had been isolated (Additional file 6A and B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>CrRLK1L candidates (CrRLK1L-L) were obtained with Pto primers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>All clustered with a maximum bootstrap value with CrRLK1L of Arabidopsis and rice (Figure 1, Additional file 6 and Additional file 7) [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Specifically these candidates fell into the largest group of CrRLK1L, previously defined as CRPK1-like1 [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>In the highly-supported CRPK1-like1 clade, Pto and its relatives of L. pimpinellifolium were also included, and clustered together with a maximum bootstrap value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The specific Pto clade did not include any CrRLK1L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The unknown sequences of poplar, which were used for comparison, were all included in the highly/well-supported subgroups headed by Pac sequences and the CrRLK1L reference sequences (Figure 1, Additional file 6 and Additional file 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Using SMART and Pfam predictive tools, we identified the poplar sequences as CrRLK1L (see “Re-classification of plant Pto-like genes”).Figure 1 Neighbor-joining tree of the aa sequences of Pac obtained with Pto primers. Pac sequences: pac, ♦. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>As a comparison we included representative CrRLK1L sequences of Arabidopsis and Catharanthus roseus (◊), poplar and rice, Pto and paralogs of Solanum piminellifolium (red colored rhombus). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Black arrows indicate Pac sequences sharing Thr204 of Pto, which is the main structural determinant of Pto for the specific recognition of AvrPto [59, 62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The rectangular frame indicates the Arabidopsis CrRLK1L member that directly binds to the effector AvrPto of Pseudomonas syringae pv tomato[63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The kinase domain region spanned subdomain I through IX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The percentage of replicate trees in which sequences clustered together in the bootstrap test (1000 replicates) are shown for each node. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The tree is drawn to scale with branch length in the units of the number of amino acid substitution per site (scale at the bottom). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Roman numerals indicate groups with a high bootstrap. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Arabic numerals indicate amino acid (upper) and nucleotide (lower) identity scores in Pac sequences within each group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations are explained in the text. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>With regard to the sequences obtained with Xa21/Xa26/EFR primers, phylogenetic analyses clearly showed that they were LRR XII candidates (LRR XII-L) (Additional file 6, Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Founding members of LRR XII are FLS2 and EFR in Arabidopsis and Xa21 in rice [7, 11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>In general, homologs of the different species did not strictly group at low hierarchical levels (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>This characteristic of the LRR XII subfamily has been previously shown in genome wide analyses [7].Figure 2 LRR XII-L of Pac compared with Arabidopsis RLK/Pelle subfamily LRR XII. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>A Neighbor-joining tree of the aa sequences of LRR XII-L of Pac (pac, ♦), the complete set of LRR XII of Arabidopsis (◊), two well-known members of LRR XII of rice – Xa21 and Xa26 (◊), and isotigs extracted from a 454 transcriptome dataset of Pac which have LRR signatures located upstream the kinase domain (black star) (Additional file 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Analysis was based on the kinase domain region spanning subdomain I/II up to the beginning of VIII. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>See caption of Figure 1 for additional details on the representation of the tree. B Multiple alignment of the RD motif (shaded grey) and non-RD motif (shaded black) corresponding to the sequences included in the tree. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The use of Xa21/Xa26/EFR primers also yielded a few sequences which were homologous with other RLK/Pelle subfamilies (Additional file 6 and Additional file 8). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic analyses of sequences obtained with WAK primers clearly identified most of these sequences as WAK-like-L (Additional file 6, Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The topology of the tree depicted in Figure 3 suggested that the gene complement isolated in Pac was at least partially representative of the Arabidopsis subfamily structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>In fact, sequences of the two species clustered within four highly supported groups, of which three were species-specific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the group marked by WAKL14 and WAKL21 of Arabidopsis and LeWAK of tomato [51], included members from different species (included Pac) with a high statistical support (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Multiple alignment of the kinase domain portion spanned by Pac sequences, enabled us to identify four conserved residues, which in the Arabidopsis WAK-like were exclusive to the WAK1 clade: Ile-427, Ser-501, Ser-502, Ile-531 (numbering refers to WAK1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Of the Pac sequences, only those of clade II shared all these residues (Additional file 9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Of the sequences obtained with WAK primers (thirty-one), three showed a homology with RFK3 (RECEPTOR-LIKE KINASE IN FLOWERS 3, subfamily RFK3-Like) of Arabidopsis and were not analysed further.Figure 3 Neighbor-joining tree of Pac WAK-like candidates and Arabidopsis RLK/Pelle subfamily Wak-like. Analysis was based on the aa sequences of: Pac (pac ♦) obtained with Wak-like primers; the complete Wak-like subfamily of Arabidopsis (◊), other sequences from plant species and one isotig extracted from a 454 transcriptome dataset of Pac, which has the typical Wak-like extracellular domains (black star) (Additional file 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The Pac sequence containing the non-RD motif is evidenced by a dashed arrow and the motif is shaded black. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The kinase domain region spanned subdomain II up to the beginning of IX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The brackets indicate a likely genetic correspondence between Pac and Arabidopsis clades (uncertain in the case of the dotted bracket). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Residues next to the brackets of clade II are shared by all the members of clade II and of WAK1-headed clade of Arabidopsis and differentiate these sequences from all the other Arabidopsis and Pac WAK-like (−L) (see Additional file 9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>See caption of Figure 1 for additional details on the representation of the tree. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Regarding the sequences obtained with BRI1(−like) primers, phylogenies clearly classified the Pac sequences as BRI1 group candidates (LRR X-BRI1-L) (Additional file 6, Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>In fact sequences strictly clustered in the three highly/well supported sub-clades headed by BRI1, BRL1/BRL3 and BRL2 of Arabidopsis, together with poplar and rice orthologs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The percentage of sequence identity, similarity and the number of gaps of these sequences compared to Arabidopsis BRI1(−like) proteins agree with the phylogeny results (Figure 4).Figure 4 LRR X-BRI1-L group of Pac compared with Arabidopsis RLK/Pelle subfamily LRR X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>A: Neighbor-joining tree of the aa sequences of: Pac (pac, ♦) which were obtained with BRI1 (−like) primers; the complete LRR X subfamily of Arabidopsis, which includes the BRI1 group (◊) [4] and other homologous sequences of rice and poplar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Analysis was based on the kinase domain region spanning subdomain I up to the beginning of X. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>See caption of Figure 1 for additional details on the representation of the tree. B Identity and similarity values and the number of gaps derived from the pairwise comparison of the Pac sequences with the Arabidopsis members of the BRI1 group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>All ML analyses - Mega 6 and TREE-PUZZLE implemented - confirmed results of the NJ analyses (Additional file 10). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>To further confirm the reliability of the phylogenetic classification at the subfamily level, we compared selected sequences of Pac, for each homology group, with ten isotigs generated from a 454 transcriptome dataset derived from P. × acerifolia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Nearly all the isotigs spanned the whole region represented by PCR RLK/Pelle fragments and matched them with a high/maximum nucleotide identity score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>In the isotigs all the putative extracellular domains typical of CrRLK1L, LRR XII, WAK-Like and LRR X were detected thus confirming the phylogenetic identification (Additional file 5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Re-classification of plant Pto-like genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The apparent failure to collect potential orthologs of Pto gene family members, prompted us to investigate the existence of sensu strictu Pto orthologs (or close homologs) in plant species using NJ and ML phylogenetic analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>We used two approaches. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>In the first approach we compared Pto locus and Pto-like of solanaceous species with Pto-like partial sequences of non-solanaceous species (including Pac) and the best Pto blastp matches of some fully sequenced non-solanaceous species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>As F. vesca and P.vulgaris genomes have been also fully sequenced, we also incuded the best matches obtained from these genomes using Pto-like partial sequences of P. vulgaris and cultivated/wild strawberries as query. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Representative CrRLK1L were included as control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>All these sequences, clustered together with a high support (Figure 5; Additional file 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Within this clade, the branching pattern determined several highly/well supported groups among which one included the Pto locus and the vast majority of Pto-like sequences of Solanaceae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>The other clades were headed by CrRLK1L sequences and contained all Pto-like partial sequences of non-solanaceous species, the best Pto and Pto-like blastp matches of fully sequenced non-solanaceous species and a few sequences of Solanaceae (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>For the sake of legibility, the phylogenetic tree in Figure 5 contains representative sequences of those listed in Additional file 4, which were all tested in a preliminary analysis with the same results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The best Pto blastp matches of Arabidopsis and rice corresponded to CrRLK1L members. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Those of poplar, grapevine and castor bean and the best matches from F. vesca and P. vulgaris, obtained using non solanaceous Pto-like as query, were unknown genes with a C-terminal kinase domain, and 1 or 2 N-terminal malectin domains (Di-glucose binding within endoplasmic reticulum). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Malectin is a membrane-anchored endoplasmic reticulum protein which is highly conserved in animals and recognizes glucose oligomers [52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The same domain composition was detected in the Arabidopsis CrRLK1L, confirming the identity of poplar, grapevine, castor bean, bean and strawberry proteins as CrRLK1L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Results of NJ analysis were confirmed by the ML pylogenetic analyses - Mega6 and TREE-PUZZLE implemented (Additional file 11).Figure 5 Phylogenetic relationship between Pto(−like) ( sensu strictu and sensu latu ) and the RLK/Pelle subfamily CrRLK1L. The Neighbor-joining analysis was based on the aa sequences of: Pto and paralogs of Solanum pimpinellifolium and the other solanaceous Pto-like (i.e. Pto-like sensu strictu); representative CrRLK1L of Arabidopsis (◊), rice (◊) and Catharanthus roseus (◊); Pto best blastp matches (namely CrRLK1L, based on domain composition) of Arabidopsis, rice, grapevine, poplar and castor bean; Pto-like fragments of non-solanaceous species (Phaselus vulgaris, cultivated and wild strawberry and Musa acuminata) (namely CrRLK1L-like, i.e. Pto-like sensu latu); best blastp matches from F. vesca and P. vulgaris (namely CrRLK1L) obtained using Pto-like fragments from the same species, as query. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Representative CrRLK1L-like of Pac obtained with Pto-primer were also included (pac, ♦). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Black arrows indicate the only solanaceous so-called Pto-like sequences, which clustered within a CrRLK1L-headed clade. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The black star indicates a CrRLK1L of castor bean lacking the extracellular domain typical of the subfamily. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The kinase domain region spanned subdomain I up to the beginning of IX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>See caption of Figure 1 for additional details on the representation of the tree. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>In the second approach we compared the complete CrRLK1L subfamily of those species in which this gene set had been characterised (i.e. arabidopsis, poplar, tomato, and rice) with Pto locus (see Additional file 4 for sequence sources). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Moss (Physcomitrella patens) was also included in the analysis as a representative of basal lineages of land plant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>CrRLK1L sequences of moss were retrieved from NCBI GenBank using CrRLK1L of Arabidopsis and Pto as query. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>The vast majority of the sequences grouped together in highly supported multi-species sub-clades confirming that in CrRLK1L, orthologs are more similar than paralogs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>On the contrary Pto and paralogs and the other ortologs from tomato database formed a highly supported Solanaceae-specific clade. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic analysis was performed with NJ and two ML methods, which gave the same results (Additional file 12). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Representative non-solanaceous Pto-like partial sequences were each compared with close CrRLK1L relatives and with Pto. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Identities and similarity values were always clearly higher with the CrRLK1L relatives than with Pto. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>In line with this, the number of gaps was lower in CrRLK1L than with Pto. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The same analysis, performed on representative Pac CrRLK1L-L, gave similar results (Table 2).Table 2 Comparison of non-solanaceous Pto-like partial sequences with Pto and close relatives of CrRLK1L Pto primer-derived Pac sequences (pac) are included. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>At = Arabidopsis thaliana; Os = Oryza sativa; Cr = Catharanthus roseus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Structural features of the kinase domain: typical, atypical, RD and non-RD kinases </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>The RLK/Pelle-like fragments of Pac spanned subdomain I to subdomain VIII-XI (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Invariant residues of kinases were all conserved except in five sequences (belonging to LRR XII-L, WAK-like-L and LRR VII-L), which were therefore classified as atypical kinases [53] (for details see Additional file 13). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Based on the crucial role of the RD motif in the catalysis [54], we assessed the nature of Pac sequences as RD or non-RD kinases, by verifying the presence/absence of the conserved Arg (R) immediately preceding the invariant catalytic Asp (D) in subdomain VIB of the catalytic domain (Additional file 13). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Most possessed the RD-Arg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Thirty-nine sequences out of 111 (35%) showed the feature of non-RD kinases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Of the 34 LRR XII-L sequences, 31 were non-RD kinases, and the vast majority (29) had a Cys in substitution of Arg (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>A single WAK-like-L sequence was also a non-RD kinase (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Seven additional non-RD kinases were found among the RLK-like belonging to the unwanted subfamilies (Additional file 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Features of the non-RD motif of Pac sequences were strongly conserved in the reference sequences of the other plant species, monocot and dicot, with which they grouped (Figure 2, Additional file 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Specifically Arabidopsis LRR XII were nearly all non-RD, with a Cys substituting Arg. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>In the CrRLK1L(−L), WAK-like(−L) and LRR XII(−L) groups of Pac and Arabidopsis, the MEME-based consensus motifs were clearly different from the tyrosine motif and instead there was a clear vicinity with the serine/threonine or the dual specifity motif (Additional file 14). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Analysis of the activation segment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>In protein kinases, the activation segment is the catalytic region and is made up of two recognizable regions: the T-loop in which regulatory autophosphorylation often occurs and the P + 1 loop, which forms the primary binding site for the substrate [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The function of several residues, in the activation segment of Pto and BRI1, has been clarified [56, 57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Our objective was to compare the activation segment of Pto and BRI1 with the corresponding regions in the Pac and Arabidopsis CrRLK1L(−L), WAK-like(−L) and BRI1(−L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The LRR XII(−L) sequences were not analyzed as they did not span the entire region of the activation segment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>We identified a motif spanning the activation segment of Pto (Pto motif190–215) and BRI1 (BRI1 motif1039–1057) and composed of residues that are crucial for their function (Figure 6, Additional file 15), [56–64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>When the two motifs were aligned, six out of seven key residues of the BRI1 motif coincided with key residues of the Pto motif190–215 at the corresponding positions (Figure 6, Additional file 15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Specifically alignment of BRI1 Thr-1045 was ambiguous. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>As this residue is involved in phosphorilation and is coupled to a serine (Ser-1044) similarly to Pto Thr-199, we decided to locate the two threonines in corresponding positions by re-locating the gaps as needed (Figure 6, Additional file 15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>As a consequence we choose to consider BRI1 Ser-1044 an insertion, with BRI1 Ser-1042 and Pto Ser-198 located in corresponding positions (Figure 6, Additional file 15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Alternatively BRI1 Ser-1042 may be considered an insertion with Pto Ser-198 and BRI1 Ser-1044 located in corresponding positions (data not shown).Figure 6 Functional consensus derived from Pto and BRI1 activation segments inferred from structure/function studies of other authors. These consensus motifs are compared with counterparts found in the activation segment of RLK/Pelle subfamilies of Arabidopsis and Pac separately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>A consensus motif is also reported for each subfamily, which includes both species and only the most frequent residues of the Pto and BRI1 functional consensus (recurring). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>ERECTA, FLS2 and BAK1 are also included for comparison. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Black-shaded residues define the Pto functional consensus and identities with the other RLK/Pelles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>BRI1 consensus residues shared with Pto consensus motif, are shaded black. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>One residue was found to be exclusive of BRI1 and is shaded grey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>In Arabidopsis and Pac RLK/Pelle subfamilies, residues that do not fall within the consensus positions are not reported (X). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>The consensus motifs were derived from alignments presented in Additional files 16, 17 and 18, and manually refined. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>A search for the motifs in the above cited sequences, highlighted that many or all residues recurred in the sequence complements (Figure 6, Additional files 16, 17 and 18). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>The motifs were also partially conserved in BAK1, ERECTA and FLS2, which were included in the analysis for comparison (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Given the results of the phylogenetic reconstruction and the analyses of structural features (RD, non-RD, typical, atypical motifs and the activation segment), we defined the RLK/Pelle-like of Pac as bona fide RLK/Pelles. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Non-synonymous versus synonymous substitution rates, non-synonymous positions and their amino acid variability </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>In a preliminary work we calculated Ka/Ks values in sequence pairs within CrRLK1L(−L), WAK-like(−L) and LRR XII(−L) groups, for Pac and Arabidopsis separately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>The analysis revealed clear signatures of purifying selection in both species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Interestingly in Pac, the distribution of Ka/Ks values of LRR XII-L was shifted in higher values - in any case less than 1 - compared with Arabidopsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>A significant increase was also evident in the LRR XII(−L) compared with WAK-Like(−L) and CrRLK1L(−L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>These preliminary findings pushed us to focus on the LRR XII(−L) group by running a window-based Ka/Ks analysis in three Pac sequence sub-groups separately (clades I, II and IV + V, Figures 2 and 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>The analysis showed an acceleration toward Ka/Ks values higher than 1 in the first, central and final portions of the sequences, which corresponded, in the three groups, to the same sub-domains (Figure 7, Additional file 19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>With regard to the average values of Ka/Ks ratio per window, none were significantly larger than 1 (at pvalue &lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>This is in line with a complete relaxation of purifying selection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>In the LRR XII of Arabidopsis, the analysis was performed in two groups of sequences, one of which comprised AT4G08850 and AT1G35710 which did not align with the others according to a codon-delimited fashion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>In Arabidopsis average Ka/Ks values ranged from 0.01 to 0.34, highlighting a signature of strong purifying selection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>However the pattern of average Ka/Ks values was similar to that observed in Pac (Figure 7, Additional file 19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>In CrRLK1L-L, the average values ranged from 0.03 to 0.16, thus showing the strongest signature of purifying selection (Figure 7, Additional file 19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>In many windows of Pac sequences, Ka/Ks values were significantly higher than those of the corresponding windows of Arabidopsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Significant differences were also detected by comparing windows with the highest and the lowest values within each sequence group of Pac (see the table in Figure 7), in line with a differential action of the selection in different regions of the kinase domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>With regard to this type of comparison, a significant difference was also detected in Arabidopsis (see the table in Figure 7), (Wilcoxon-test pvalue &lt;0.0001 and fold increase &gt;2).Figure 7 Kinase domain sub-regions in the LRR XII-L of Pac show signatures of relaxed purifying selection. Ka/Ks calculation was based on a sliding-window analysis (windows 75 bp, step 15 bp). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>With regard to the clades of Pac, refer to Figure 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The Arabidopsis LRR XII and the CrRLK1L(−L) of Pac, were included in the analysis for comparison and control respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>The results are shown as average Ka/Ks ratios per window. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Vertical bars indicate standard errors of the mean. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>For each group a representative sequence is shown below in order to map in a frame the windows with the highest Ka/Ks values (arrows in the graphs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>The sequences are aligned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Invariant residues of kinases are shaded black. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Roman numerals under the alignment identify the beginning of the kinase subdomain motifs and the arrows define the end (see [106]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>The asterisks indicate the windows in which Ka/Ks values are significantly higher than those of the corresponding windows of Arabidopsis (Wilcoxon- test pvalue &lt; 0.0001 and fold increase &gt;2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>The table reports the fold change increase in the average Ka/Ks values of each sequence group in evidently relaxed windows (w) compared to those with the lowest values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>All the comparisons, except for w.1 vs w.5 in Arabidopsis, were significant with our stringent criteria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>In the site by site analysis, the likelihood ratio test did not indicate an overall significantly better fit of the M8 site model (positive selection) versus the M7 model (P &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>The Bayes empirical Bayes method revealed a total of six sites with Ka/Ks ratio &gt;1, in the three sequence groups of Pac, although with small posterior probability values (range 56–73%) when accounting for the standard error. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>A sequence analysis of each subgroup of LRR XII(−L) and of Arabidopsis LRR XII showed that of the 158 positions analysed (excluding gaps), 126 positions were subject to non-synonymous variations, of which 88 (70%) were shared among two or more sequence groups, and 19 (24%) were present in all the sequence groups (Figure 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>The amino acids recurring in all the shared positions and for each group of sequences are listed in Additional file 20.Figure 8 Amino acid positions of the LRR XII kinase domain subject to non-synonymous nucleotide variations. Sequences of phylogenetic clades of LRR XII(−L) of Pac and LRR XII of Arabidopsis were included in the analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Positions subject to non-synonymous variations are shaded black. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Sequences in the alignment are representatives of each group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Long arrows show non-synonymous positions shared among all sequence groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Short dotted arrows show non-synonymous positions shared among three groups of sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Stars above the alignments show non-synonymous positions that are exclusive to a single group of sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>The invariant residues of the kinase superfamily (from III to IX) are in bold and shaded grey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The brackets indicate the regions where purifying selection is more relaxed, based on the analysis presented in Figure 7. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide analysis for the characterization of gene families in fully-sequenced species is invaluable for an in-depth comprehension of the information contained in the genomes (see for example: [4, 65, 66]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>It is also a necessary support for gene candidate analyses such as those based on domain-targeted isolations of gene groups, in species lacking genome sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>We thus based our study on a detailed comparison with RLK/Pelles of fully-sequenced species, especially Arabidopsis, and devised a method for the correct identification of RLK/Pelle gene fragments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>In this study we present some substantial advances on plant RLK/Pelles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>We isolated for the first time a set of RLK/Pelles in Pac. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the analysis of sequence data also revealed: i) a novel phylogenetic relationship between the Pto group and the CrRLK1L RLK/Pelle subfamily; ii) clear signatures of relaxed purifying selection in the LRR XII-L, which had not been previously revealed for plant RLK kinase domain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>The representativeness of the kinase domain for RLK/Pelle classification has been widely shown [3–5, 7, 67, 68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Kinase-domain targeted isolation of RLK/Pelles has also been found to be successful [69–75]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>In this work we confirmed its representativeness for a correct classification, by matching the cloned sequences with long 454 isotigs from Pac, which displayed the expected extracellular domain signatures (Additional file 5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>CrRLK1L candidates and the relationship between CrRLK1L and Pto </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>All the analyses highlighted our apparent failure to collect sensu strictu Pto-like genes in Pac and showed that the analysed non-solanaceous plant genomes lack a bona fide Pto gene group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, in the phylogenetic analyses, Pto group was closest to CrRLK1L than any other RLK subfamily. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Note that i) best matches of Pto, belonging to six fully-sequenced dicot species and to rice, were revealed as CrRLK1L; ii) all non-solanaceous Pto-like partial sequences were classified as CrRLK1L-like; in this regard it is explicative the high closeness of Pto-like partial sequences from bean and cultivated/wild strawberries to CrRLK1L extracted from bean and F. vesca genomes (Figure 5, Additional file 11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>All the dicot species that we used in the Pto/CrRLK1L comparative analysis were Rosids, except the solanaceous species which belong to Asterids, and Pac, whose formation predates the split giving rise to Rosids and Asterids (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mobot.org/MOBOT/research/APweb/">http://www.mobot.org/MOBOT/research/APweb/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>All this clearly points to the restriction of Pto gene group to a range of taxa within Dicots, possibly due to a relatively more recent origin than other ubiquitous RLK/Pelle subfamilies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>On the other hand a more precise evaluation of the taxonomic restriction of Pto-like genes is needed and would require sequencing additional plant taxa representative of Asterids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>The taxonomic restriction of an RLK group is not surprising as species-specific RLK/Pelle subfamilies have previously been reported [5, 7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>The CrRLK1L subfamily is an ancient group of RLK/Pelles with a conserved extracellular domain and whose formation predates the divergence of vascular plants [5, 50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>This was confirmed by our phylogenies which clearly showed that orthologs are more similar than paralogs, and suggests that events giving rise to family members occurred prior to the monocot-dicot split and after the divergence rate was low (Figures 1 and 5, Additional files 7 and 12). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Strong evidence thus suggests that Pto genes evolved from ancient CrRLK1L, through the loss of the extracellular domain: i) the ubiquity of the CrRLK1L in the land plant and the conservation of this family over a long geological period [5, 50]; ii) the restriction of Pto and its paralogs to asterid species (i.e. Solanaceae, based on current knowledge) (Figure 5, Additional files 11 and 12); iii) the close vicinity between the kinase domain of the two RLK/Pelle groups (Figures 1 and 5, Additional files 6 and 12) [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the structure of the Pto group is also similar to CrRLK1L in that orthologs are more similar than paralogs [76]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Recently the tomato RLK/Pelle family has been characterised and the phylogenetic comparison with Arabidopsis showed that a CrRLK1L subfamily exists in tomato [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Interestingly we noted that Pto group was included in the CrRLK1L clade. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Though this was not discussed by the authors it represents a full confirmation of the results of our phylogenies [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic vicinity between the kinase domains of RLK and RLCK subfamilies has been reported, and domain reassortment has been repeatedly emphasized as an ancient mechanism of RLK/Pelle evolution in the land plant lineage [4, 5, 77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>CrRLK1L is one of the Arabidopsis RLK/Pelle subfamilies which has corresponding RLPs (receptor–like proteins, i.e. proteins resembling the extracellular domain of RLKs), suggesting that these RLKs and their RLPs gave rise or were each derived from their counterpart [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>In this scenario, our conclusion on the formation of RLCKs - Pto and paralogs - from RLKs - CrRLK1L - is thus in agreement with the accepted RLK/Pelle gene evolution model. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>The vicinity between Pto group and CrRLK1L raises the question if they have to be classified as bona fide CrRLK1L or represent the founding members of a novel RLCK/Pelle subfamily, related to CrRLK1L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>This will be a matter of investigation and debate in the future. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>The analysis of the activation segment was also useful for shedding light on the relationship between CrRLK1L(−like) and Pto (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>The functional motifs identified in the activation segment of BRI1 and Pto (Figure 6, Additional file 15), were partially overlapping and were conserved among a wide range of RLK/Pelles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>This highlights an interesting point which fits the special case of CrRLK1L/Pto well: the conservation of functional residues can be useful for supporting identification at a high hierarchical level but it is not sufficient to suggest a relationship of putative orthology, even when this conclusion is sustained by phylogenetic vicinity - as is the case of the non-solanaceous Pto-like vs solanaceous Pto group [73, 74]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>The recovery of a CrRLK1L(−L) gene set in Pac, is still an interesting finding, also in the context of defense-related RLK/Pelles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>For example THE1 mediates the response of plant cells to the perturbation of cellulose synthesis by triggering growth inhibition, ectopic lignin accumulation and the expression of a set of defense-related genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>THE1 is thus considered as a sensor of cell wall integrity and a role in pathogen defense has been postulated [78, 79]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Another suggestion for the role of CrRLK1Ls in pathogen defense is that, in Arabidopsis, the bacterial effector AvrPto directly binds to the CrRLK1L member AT2G23200, suggesting a significant, yet undiscovered role, in innate immunity [63]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>LRR XII candidates: nonRD motif and relaxed purifying selection highlight a potential link with pathogen resistance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>In Arabidopsis and rice the LRR XII subfamily includes PRRs functioning as PAMP receptors and R genes [10, 11, 80] and it has been suggested that this is the general functional contribution of the subfamily. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>An LRR XII-L group was clearly identified in Pac (Figure 2, Additional file 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>The wide nucleotide diversity range among all Pac sequences (nucleotide score: 62–98) and a comparison, in the phylogenetic tree, of the branching pattern of Pac and Arabidopsis sequences, suggest that an undetermined number of paralogs had been isolated (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>An important feature shared by the Arabidopsis and Pac sequence complements is their nature as non-RD kinases and the high frequency of Cys in substitution of the RD-Arg (Figure 2), which strongly supports the phylogenetic identification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Non-RD kinases are present in the kinomes of a wide range of Eukaryotic organisms and a statistically significant and positive correlation was found between kinases that function in the innate immunity and the non-RD motif [81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>This finding, together with the fact that Arabidopsis and rice LRR XII contain PRRs, suggests that we have identified a group of genes that is potentially involved in the perception of pathogens. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>Further support for this hypothesis is that we also detected signatures of a relaxed purifying selection in Pac sequences (Figure 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>This finding is new for plant RLK/Pelles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>In fact in Arabidopsis and rice, signatures of positive selection were detected in the extracellular domains [7, 82, 83]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the kinase domain has been shown to be under a strong purifying selection [7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, only specific regions of the kinase domains were subject, in Pac, to an evidently relaxed purifying selection and the substitutions occurring in the the non-synonymous positions were largely shared by the different sequence groups of Pac (Figures 7 and 8, Additional file 20). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>This suggests the action of a selective pressure that tends to keep specific non-silent variations in regions which might be relevant for the fitness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Indeed these regions span zones which are crucial for the function of the kinase catalytic core: i) I-II subdomain, which is involved in anchoring the ATP phosphates; ii) VII-VIII subdomain, the activation segment; iii) V-VIA subdomain, which is the site of catalysis [84, 85]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>The fact that the strength of purifying selection can be differentially modulated in the distinct functional regions of a protein coding gene is well known (e.g. [86, 87]), however it is novel for plant RLK/Pelles. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Purifying selection generally eliminates any mutations in order to preserve the exact function of essential genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, a relaxation of purifying selection and positive selection are considered as two non-mutually exclusive forces that drive the protein evolutionary rate towards divergence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>In particular in the relaxed purifying selection, random mutations affect genes that are dispensable or redundant, therefore there is no stringent constraint to impede their retention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>By chance, these mutations may turn out to be beneficial for morphological and functional specification [88–90]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>In fact a relaxed selective constraint plays a role in the expression of phenotypic plasticity, which is one of the most important ways by which organisms adaptively interact with the environment [90]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Specifically, the evolution of caste systems in polyphenic social insects [90], the fast evolution of lineage-specific genes in humans [91] and a variation in freezing tolerance among natural accessions of Arabidopsis[92] have all been attributed to a relaxed purifying selection as the main driving force. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>It is well known that effectors of pathogenic bacteria target the kinase domain of several RLK/Pelles with a role in plant immunity, giving rise to an “arms race” ending with host resistance or susceptibility [20, 62, 63, 93–96]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Thus in Pac, a relaxation of purifying selection in the kinase domain of LRR XII-L, may have enabled the recruitment of variants which are useful for the resistance response of Pac to some microbial (would be) pathogens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>This might be an exciting research theme for the future. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>WAK-like and BRI1 group candidates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>WAK-like proteins link the extracellular matrix to the cytoplasm for appropriate signal transmission [97]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Wak-like have been found to be involved in many functions including pathogen resistance [12, 98, 99] and development [100, 101]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>Despite our initial aim to isolate a single WAK-like member - namely an RFO1 homolog - a WAK-Like-L gene complement was isolated in Pac (Additional file 6) and seemed highly representative of the phylogenetic structure of the Arabidopsis counterpart (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Importantly, results of WAK-like phylogeny agree exactly with the phylogenetic comparison between WAK-like of Arabidopsis and rice, in which sequences clustered in a species-specific manner and with only one multi-species clade headed by Arabidopsis WAKL14 and WAKL21 (Figure 3) [67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>However it remains difficult to predict the level of completeness of the gene complement isolated in Pac. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>In fact, compared with the Arabidopsis genome, an extensive expansion of the gene family has occurred both in rice and in poplar suggesting a lineage-independent evolution [5, 67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>In any case the formation of species-specific and multi-species clades, in the Arabidopsis/Pac (this work) and Arabidopsis/rice phylogenies [67], suggests that opposing evolutionary forces shaped this RLK/Pelle subfamily, which produced both genetic divergence and conservation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>This is in line with the involvement of these RLKs in very different functions, i.e. development and pathogen resistance, which exploit genetic conservation and diversification, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>In the light of our results, as RFO1 belongs to a species-specific clade, phylogeny-based identification of the potential RFO1 homologs/orthologs was not possible. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>However based on the branching pattern of the phylogenetic tree, clade I appears to be the group of genes in which it might be possible to search for homologs with RFO1-related functions, i.e. resistance to vascular pathogens (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>This is particularly important in Platanus species which are hyper-susceptible to the vascular pathogen C. platani[26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>In Arabidopsis, a number of additional WAK-like are involved in stress responses, namely WAK1, WAK2, WAKL5 and WAKL7, which were found to be inducible by salicylic acid (SA) and by wounding, and to protect plants from detrimental effects during pathogen responses, such as high levels of SA [98, 100, 101]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>In terms of finding orthologs of these WAK-like, clade II of Pac might be a candidate source, as it shares a 4-residue motif exclusively with the WAK1-headed clade, suggesting a genetic correlation (Additional file 9). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>The topology of LRR X-BRI1-L phylogeny was the same as that found by Cano-Delgado et al. [102] based on full-length proteins of BRI1(−like) from plant species, which confirms once more that the kinase domain is of primary importance in RLK/Pelle subfamily identification and phylogeny. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Similarly to CrRLK1(−L) phylogeny, the three major clades included the potential orthologs from different dicot and monocot species, implying that diversification within this gene group predates the monocot/dicot split (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Our analyses suggest that potential orthologs of BRI1 group members were isolated in Pac. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>In Arabidopsis, BRLs are expressed in the vasculature where they have a role in provascular cell growth and contribute to establishing the xylem/phloem pattern through perception of the BR signal [102, 103]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>In addition, BRLs also seem to be important in stress responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>In fact, after confirmation that BRI1 was not the functional receptor of systemin [18, 19] a BRL was suspected to be the true systemin receptor since BRLs match the highly specific localization of prosystemin and systemin perception in the vasculature [104, 105]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>Several Pac diseases target vascular tissues, cambium and living bark, and the pathogens gain entry through wounds [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>Therefore, LRR X-BRI1-L of Pac are important candidates in the study of the host response to wound pathogens, such as C. platani. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>The study of the RLK/Pelles of Pac led to interesting findings, highlighting some aspects of Pac as a model species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>This is also supported by the representative position of Platanus within Dicot phylogeny, one of the earliest branches, temporally located before the split which gave rise to the main groups, Rosids and Asterids, which comprise the majority of cultivated Dicots (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mobot.org/MOBOT/research/APweb/">http://www.mobot.org/MOBOT/research/APweb/</ext-link>.). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>In addition the region-specific signatures of relaxed purifying selection in the non-RD LRR XII-L genes, highlights that this gene group is a good candidate for investigations into pathogen resistance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>With regard to CrRLK1L/Pto, it will be exciting to verify in which taxonomic groups, apart from solanaceae, sensu strictu Pto genes are currently present in order to further clarify the evolutionary link with CrRLK1L. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Above all, the main objective of our work in Pac was to create the first valuable resource to analyze the RLK kinome expression of genotypes that resist or are overwhelmed by pathogens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>We believe that this represents the first step in an in-depth study on stress perception systems and also in the identification of useful molecular markers for genetic mapping and selecting resistant genotypes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec20"><title><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Availability of supporting data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>The data set supporting the results of this article is available in the NCBI GenBank repository, (see also Additional file 3 for accession numbers and the text of nt and aa sequences). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec21"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Additional file 1: Degenerate primers successfully used for PCR amplifications of kinase domain of RLK/Pelle genes. (PDF 129 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>Additional file 2: Primer pairs used to isolate RLK/Pelle gene fragments and efficiency of the gene fishing process. (PDF 14 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM3_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Additional file 3: Platanus × acerifolia ( Pac ) RLK/Pelles: NCBI GenBank accession numbers, subfamily classification and sequence text. Sequences in A and B were obtained in this work, those in C were used for comparison. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>In D nucletide and amino acidic sequences are listed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>(PDF 319 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM4_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>Additional file 4: Reference sequences included in the phylogenies for comparison and to root the trees. Where RLK subfamilies or generic terms (i.e. Pto-like) are cited, all sequences reported in the source were tested in the phylogenies, except pseudogenes or putative proteins with truncated kinase domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>(PDF 23 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM5_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Additional file 5: The extracellular domain of Platanus × acerifolia ( Pac ) RLK/Pelles. Pairwise comparison between selected gene fragments obtained in this work, and the overlapping RLK/Pelle isotigs extracted from a 454 FLX dataset of a Platanus × acerifolia (Pac) transcriptome (Pilotti M., Brunetti A., Iacono M. and Pindo M. unpublished data). A Spanning regions and identity values. B The isotigs display a region 5′-upstream the kinase domain, which includes putative extracellular domains typical of the RLK/Pelle subfamilies dealt with in this work (output data from Pfam). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>This is a confirmation of the phylogenetic identification of the gene fragments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>A SMART analysis predicted in a confident manner transmembrane domains in all the isotigs, which were located upstream the kinase domain and downstream the putative extracellular domains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>(PDF 110 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM6_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>Additional file 6: Phylogenetic classification of RLK/Pelles of Platanus × acerifolia ( Pac ). The analyses were based on the Neighbor-joining method and show a general view of the relationship of the aa sequences of RLK/Pelles of Pac (pac, ♦ in black), Pto group (♦ in red) and other kinases. A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Contains representative sequences of the following species/groups: Pac, Pto group (red rhombus), Pto-like partial sequences from non-solanaceous species (white rhombus with a red outline), RLK/Pelle subfamilies of Arabidopsis[4], other families of the receptor kinase group – receptor tyrosine kinase (RTK) and Raf [3] - and other eukaryotic protein kinases (ePKs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>The tree is rooted with a bacterial protein kinase [APH(3′)III also named aminoglycoside 3′-phosphotransferase]. B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>Contains all Pac sequences reported in this work and their strict Arabidopsis homologs according to what emerged from A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>A kinase domain region spanning subdomains I/II to the beginning of VIII, was used to infer the trees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>See caption of Figure 1 and Methods for details on the representation of the trees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>(PDF 90 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM7_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Additional file 7: The CrRLK1L-L of Platanus × acerifolia ( Pac ). Neighbor-joining analysis to compare CrRLK1L-L of Pac (pac, ♦), with the complete CrRLK1L subfamily of Arabidopsis and rice; Pto and paralogs of Solanum pimpinellifolium were also included (red rhombus); The subdivision into CRPK1-like 1 and CRPK1-like 2 is from Shiu and Bleecker [4]. aa sequences were used to infer the tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>Analysis was based on the kinase domain region spanning subdomain I through to IX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>See caption of Figure 1 for details on the representation of the tree. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>Arrows indicate Arabidopsis CrRLK1L which were functionally characterised. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>(PDF 47 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM8"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM8_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Additional file 8: Unwanted RLK/Pelles of Platanus × acerifolia ( Pac ). Sequences were obtained with primers aimed at isolating members of LRR XII subfamily. A Neighbor-joining tree based on the aa sequences of Pac (pac, ♦), the nearest RLK/Pelle members of Arabidopsis (◊) and other unknown, homologous sequences of rice and poplar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Analysis was based on the kinase domain region spanning subdomains I/II to the beginning of VIII. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>See caption of Figure 1 for details on the representation of the tree. B Multiple alignment of RD motif (shaded grey), non-RD motif (shaded black) and an atypical variant of the non-RD-Asp (shaded black). C Phylogenetic analysis was ambiguous in determining the homology relationship of pac.Erf.2, pac.Erf.9 and pac.Erf.13 with the Arabidopsis RLK/Pelle subfamilies GDPD, LRK10L-2, CRPK1-like2 (i.e. CrRLK1L) and Thaumatin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>The table thus shows the identity and similarity values and number of gaps derived from the pairwise comparison of these sequences with one Arabidopsis relative for each subfamily which, in preliminary analyses, were the nearest sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>(PDF 172 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM9"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM9_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Additional file 9: Wak1-clade-specific amino acid motif helps to identify close homologs in Platanus × acerifolia ( Pac ). Amino acidic residues (shaded black) conserved among sequences of Wak1-headed clade of Arabidopsis (RLK/Pelle subfamily WAK-like) and of the II phylogenetic clade of Wak-like-L of Pac (refer to phylogeny of Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>This motif suggests a genetic correlation between the two sequence groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>(PDF 130 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM10"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM10_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>Additional file 10: Classification of Pac sequences based on maximum-likelihood (ML) phylogenetic analyses. Analyses were performed on the same dataset alignments used for crucial Neighbor-joining trees presented in this work (aa sequences). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>A1 and A2 match with Additional file 6B (all Pac sequences compared with homologous Arabidopsis RLK Pelles); B matches with Additional file 7 (Arabidopsis and rice CrRLK1L vs Pac CrRLK1L-L); C matches with Figure 2 (Arabidopsis LRR XII vs Pac LRR XII-L); D matches with Figure 3 (Arabidopsis WAK-like vs Pac WAK-like-L); E with Figure 4 (Arabidopsis LRR X vs Pac LRR X-BRI1-L group). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Editing matches that of counterpart figures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>All trees were inferred with Mega 6 except the one represented in A2 that was TREE PUZZLE-implemented. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>With regard to Mega 6 analyses, the percentage of trees in which the associated sequences clustered together in the bootstrap test (1,000 replicates) is shown for each node; trees are drawn to scale in the number of substitutions per site (scale at the bottom). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>TREE-PUZZLE analysis was conducted with 50,000 puzzling steps and quartet puzzling support values are shown for each node. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>(PDF 161 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM11"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM11_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Additional file 11: Phylogenetic relationship between Pto (−like) ( sensu strictu and sensu latu ) and the subfamily CrRLK1L by two methods of maximum-likelihood analysis. Analysis was performed on the same dataset alignment used for the analysis presented in Figure 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>The following aa sequences were included: Pto locus and solanaceous Pto-like; CrRLK1L of Arabidopsis, rice and Catharanthus roseus; Pto best blastp matches (namely CrRLK1L, based on domain composition) of Arabidopsis, rice, grapevine, poplar and castor bean; Pto-like partial sequences (namely CrRLK1L-like, i.e. Pto-like sensu latu) of non-solanaceous species (i.e. Phaselus vulgaris, cultivated and wild strawberry and Musa acuminata); best blastp matches from F. vesca and P. vulgaris (namely CrRLK1L) obtained using Pto-like partial sequences as query. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>Representative Pac sequences obtained with Pto-primer (CrRLK1L-like) were also included (pac). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>The arrows indicate solanaceous so-called Pto-like sequences, which clustered within a CrRLK1L-headed clade. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>The star indicates a CrRLK1L-like of castor bean lacking the extracellular domain typical of the subfamily. A: tree obtained with Mega 6; the percentage of trees in which the associated sequences clustered together in the bootstrap test (1,000 replicates) is shown for each node; trees are drawn to scale in the number of substitutions per site (scale at the bottom). B: tree obtained with TREE-PUZZLE; analysis was conducted with 50,000 puzzling steps and quartet puzzling support values are shown for each node. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>See Methods for details. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>(PDF 115 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM12"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM12_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>Additional file 12: Phylogenetic analyses (NJ and ML) to compare the complete CrRLK1L subfamily (CRPK1-like 1) of different plant species and Pto group. We included the complete CRPK1-like 1 aa sequence set of Arabidopsis, poplar, tomato (Solanum lycopersicum), rice and moss, and Pto and paralogs of Solanum pimpinellifolium (see Additional file 4 for sequence sources). The NJ tree is presented in A, the ML trees, Mega6 and TREE-PUZZLE-implemented, are presented in B and C respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>Analyses were based on the complete kinase domain region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>With regard to Mega 6, the percentage of trees in which the associated sequences clustered together in the bootstrap test (1,000 replicates) is shown for each node; trees are drawn to scale in the number of substitutions per site (scale at the bottom). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>With regard to TREE-PUZZLE analysis was conducted with 50,000 puzzling steps and quartet puzzling support values are shown for each node. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>See Methods for additional details. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>(PDF 220 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM13"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM13_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>Additional file 13: The molecular role of some invariant residues of the kinase domain. Substitutions in Platanus × acerifolia (Pac) sequences (atypical and non-RD motifs) are listed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>(PDF 82 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM14"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM14_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>Additional file 14: Serine, threonine and tyrosine phosphorilation specificity motifs of RLK/Pelles of Platanus × acerifolia ( Pac ) and Arabidopsis . The motifs are compared with phosphorilation specificity motifs of protein kinase previously inferred [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Consensus was determined using MEME (a motif-based sequence analysis tool). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>(PDF 128 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM15"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM15_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Additional file 15: Crucial residues of the activation segments of Pto and BRI1. The relevant literature is cited in the text. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>(PDF 24 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM16"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM16_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Additional file 16: Important residues of CrRLK1L located in the kinase domain region spanning subdomains VIB to VIII. The alignment shows the functional consensus derived from the Pto and BRI1 activation segment (subdomains VII and VIII) (Figure 6, Additional file 15) and its conservation in CrRLK1L(−L) subfamilies of Arabidopsis and Platanus × acerifolia (Pac). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>Black-shaded residues define the Pto functional consensus and the identities with CrRLK1L(−L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>BRI1 consensus residues shared with Pto consensus motif, are shaded black, the residue exclusive of BRI1 consensus is shaded grey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>Shaded-grey gaps have been inserted in order to match sequences with BRI1 consensus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>The figure also shows the RD/non-RD motif and the regions that are useful to infer the ser/thr, tyr and the dual phosphorylation specificities of protein kinases [42] (Additional file 14) [red-shaded residues (subdomain VIb) and the P + 1 loop (subdomain VIII)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>(PDF 166 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM17"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM17_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>Additional file 17: Important residues of Wak-like located in the kinase domain region spanning subdomains VIB to VIII. The alignment shows the functional consensus derived from the Pto and BRI1 activation segment (subdomains VII and VIII) (Figure 6, Additional file 15) and its conservation in the WAK-like(−L) subfamilies of Arabidopsis and Platanus × acerifolia (Pac). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>Black-shaded residues define the Pto functional consensus and the identities with WAK-like(−L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>BRI1 consensus residues shared with Pto consensus motif, are shaded black, the residue exclusive of BRI1 consensus is shaded grey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>Shaded-grey gaps have been inserted in order to match sequences with BRI1 consensus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>The figure also shows the RD and non-RD motif and the regions that are useful to infer the ser/thr, tyr and the dual phosphorylation specificities of protein kinases [42] (Additional file 14) [red-shaded residues (subdomain VIb) and the P + 1 loop (subdomain VIII)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>(PDF 165 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM18"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM18_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>Additional file 18: Important residues of LRR X-BRI1 group located in the kinase domain region spanning subdomains VIB to VIII. The alignment shows the functional consensus derived from the Pto and BRI1 activation segment (subdomains VII and VIII) (Figure 6, Additional file 15) and its conservation in the LRR X-BRI1(−L) group of Arabidopsis and Platanus × acerifolia (Pac). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Black-shaded residues define the Pto functional consensus and the identities with LRR X-BRI1(−L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>BRI1 consensus residues shared with Pto consensus motif, are shaded black, the residue exclusive of BRI1 consensus is shaded grey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>The figure also shows the RD motif and the regions that are useful to infer the ser/thr, tyr and the dual phosphorylation specificities of protein kinases [42] (Additional file 14) [red-shaded residues (subdomain VIb) and the P + 1 loop (subdomain VIII)]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>(PDF 169 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM19"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM19_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>Additional file 19: Ka/Ks values obtained for each window in the sliding window analysis of Platanus × acerifolia ( Pac ) LRR XII-L. CrRLK1L-L of Pac and LRR XII of Arabidopsis are included for comparison. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>(PDF 61 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM20"><media xlink:href="13104_2014_3456_MOESM20_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>Additional file 20: Amino acid variability at the kinase domain positions subject to non-synonymous variation. Analysis focuses on phylogenetic clades of LRR-XII-L of Platanus × acerifolia (Pac) and LRR-XII of Arabidopsis (refer Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>The three distinct tables present the data regarding the sharing of the variable positions among four, three and two distinct group of sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>(PDF 183 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>The project was coordinated by MPil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>MPil and AB designed the study and the gene isolation strategy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>AB, VL and LT carried out nucleic acid extraction, PCR amplification and cloning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>FG checked quality of Sanger-derived sequencing chromatograms and selected the RLK/Pelle sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>MPil, PU, MI and FG performed the bioinformatics and phylogenetic analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>MPil, MI and MPin assembled the plane tree transcriptome and made the alignments to select the isotigs matching with PCR sequences of this work. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>MPil and AB made figure editing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>MPil prepared the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>PU, AB, and VL critically reviewed the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>This research was supported by MIPAF—Ministero delle Politiche Agricole e Forestali, project: “Proteine e geni per la protezione delle piante dagli stress biotici e abiotici, Proteo Stress—Genomica e Proteomica per lo studio della risposta di resistenza in specie arbore, ciliegio e platano”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>We thank Adrian Wallwork for language editing. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>1.MassaguéJTGF-beta signal transductionAnnu Rev Biochem19986775379110.1146/annurev.biochem.67.1.753<?supplied-pmid 9759503?>9759503 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>2.HubbardSRTillJHProtein tyrosine kinase structure and functionAnnu Rev Biochem20006937339810.1146/annurev.biochem.69.1.373<?supplied-pmid 10966463?>10966463 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>3.ShiuS-HBleeckerABReceptor-like kinases from Arabidopsis form a monophyletic gene family related to animal receptor kinasesProc Natl Acad Sci200198107631076810.1073/pnas.181141598<?supplied-pmid 11526204?>11526204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>4.ShiuS-HBleeckerABExpansion of the receptor-like kinase/pelle gene family and receptor-like proteins in ArabidopsisPlant Physiol200313253054310.1104/pp.103.021964<?supplied-pmid 12805585?>12805585 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>5.Lehti-ShiuMDZouCHanadaKShiuS-HEvolutionary history and stress regulation of plant receptor-like kinase/pelle genesPlant Physiol2009150122610.1104/pp.108.134353<?supplied-pmid 19321712?>19321712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>6.SakamotoTDeguchiMBrustoliniOJBSantosAASilvaFFFontesEPThe tomato RLK superfamily: phylogeny and functional predictions about the role of the LRRII-RLK subfamily in antiviral defenseBMC Plant Biology20121222910.1186/1471-2229-12-229<?supplied-pmid 23198823?>23198823 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>7.ShiuSHKarlowskiWMPanRTzengYHMayerKFLiWHComparative analysis of the receptor-like kinase family in Arabidopsis and ricePlant Cell2004161220123410.1105/tpc.020834<?supplied-pmid 15105442?>15105442 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>8.AltenbachDRobatzekSPattern-recognition receptors: from the cell surface to intracellular dynamicsMol Plant Microbe Interact2007201031103910.1094/MPMI-20-9-1031<?supplied-pmid 17849705?>17849705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>9.ZipfelCPattern-recognition receptors in plant innate immunityCurr Op Immunol200820101610.1016/j.coi.2007.11.003 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>10.ParkC-JHanS-WChenXRonaldPCElucidation of XA21-mediated innate immunityCell Microbiol2010121017102510.1111/j.1462-5822.2010.01489.x<?supplied-pmid 20590657?>20590657 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>11.ZipfelCKunzeGChinchillaDCaniardAJonesJDBollerTFelixGPerception of the bacterial PAMP EF-Tu by the receptor EFR restricts agrobacterium-mediated transformationCell200612574976010.1016/j.cell.2006.03.037<?supplied-pmid 16713565?>16713565 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>12.DienerACAusubelFMResistance to Fusarium oxisporum 1, a dominant Arabidopsis disease-resistance gene, is not race specificGenetics200517130532110.1534/genetics.105.042218<?supplied-pmid 15965251?>15965251 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>13.JohanssonAStaalJDixeliusCEarly responses in the Arabidopsis-Verticillium longisporum pathosystem are dependent on NDR1, JA- and ET-associated signals via cytosolic NPR1 and RFO1Mol Plant Microbe Interact20061995896910.1094/MPMI-19-0958<?supplied-pmid 16941900?>16941900 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>14.HeZWangZ-YLiJZhuQLambCRonaldPChoryJPerception of brassinosteroids by the extracellular domain of the receptor kinase BRI1Science20002882360236310.1126/science.288.5475.2360<?supplied-pmid 10875920?>10875920 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>15.WangZ-YSetoHFujiokaSYoshidaSChoryJBRI1 is a critical component of a plasma-membrane receptor for plant steroidsNature200141038038310.1038/35066597<?supplied-pmid 11268216?>11268216 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>16.BajguzAHayatSEffects of brassinosteroids on the plant responses to environmental stressesPlant Phisiol Biochem2009471810.1016/j.plaphy.2008.10.002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>17.SzekeresMBrassinosteroid and systemin: two hormones perceived by the same receptorTrends Plant Sci2003810210410.1016/S1360-1385(03)00010-4<?supplied-pmid 12663218?>12663218 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>18.HoltonNCano-DelgadoAHarrisonKMontoyaTChoryJBishopGJTomato BRASSINOSTEROID INSENSITIVE1 is required for systemin-induced root elongation in solanum pimpinellifolium but is not essential for wound signalingPlant Cell2007191709171710.1105/tpc.106.047795<?supplied-pmid 17513502?>17513502 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>19.MalinowskiRHigginsRLuoYPiperLNazirABajwaVSClouseSDThompsonPRStratmannJWThe tomato brassinosteroid receptor BRI1 increases binding of systemin to tobacco plasma membranes, but is not involved in systemin signalingPlant Mol Biol20097060361610.1007/s11103-009-9494-x<?supplied-pmid 19404750?>19404750 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>20.PedleyKFMartinGBMolecular basis of PTO-mediated resistance to bacterial speck disease in tomatoAnnu Rev Phytopathol20034121524310.1146/annurev.phyto.41.121602.143032<?supplied-pmid 14527329?>14527329 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>21.TangXXieMKimYJZhouJKlessigDFMartinGBOverexpression of Pto activates defense responses and confers broad resistancePlant Cell199911152910.1105/tpc.11.2.177<?supplied-pmid 9878629?>9878629 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>22.GrimmGWDenkTThe reticulate origin of modern plane trees (Platanus, Platanaceae): a nuclear marker puzzleTaxon201059134147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>23.HenryAFloodsMGThe hystory of the London plane (platanus acerifolia). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>Notes on the genus PlatanusProc Royal Irish Acad191935928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>24.PilottiMBrunettiATizzaniLMaraniOPlatanus’ acerifolia genotypes surviving to inoculation with Ceratocystis platani (the agent of canker stain): first screening and molecular characterizationEuphytica200916911710.1007/s10681-009-9884-9 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>25.SoltisPSSoltisDEThe role of genetic and genomic attributes in the success of polyploidsProc Natl Acad Sci2000977051705710.1073/pnas.97.13.7051<?supplied-pmid 10860970?>10860970 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>26.PanconesiACanker stain of plane trees: a serious danger to urban plantingsJ Plant Pathol199981315 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>27.PilottiMLe avversità del platanoInfre Fitopatol200252924 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>28.VigourouxAOlivierRFirst hybrid plane trees to show resistance against canker stain (Ceratocystis fimbriata f. sp. platani)For Pathol20043430731910.1111/j.1439-0329.2004.00372.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>29.PilottiMBrunettiAGallelliALoretiSNPR1-like genes from cDNA of rosaceous trees: cloning strategy and genetic variationTree Genetics and Genomes20084496310.1007/s11295-007-0087-z </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>30.AltschulSFMaddenTLSchäfferAAZhangJZhangZMillerWLipmanDJGapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programsNucleic Acids Res1997253389340210.1093/nar/25.17.3389<?supplied-pmid 9254694?>9254694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>31.KatohKTohHRecent developments in the MAFFT multiple sequence alignment programBrief Bioinform2008428629810.1093/bib/bbn01318372315 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>32.RicePLongdenIBleasbyAThe European molecular biology open software suiteTrends Genet20001627627710.1016/S0168-9525(00)02024-2<?supplied-pmid 10827456?>10827456 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>33.SaitouNNeiMThe neighbor-joining method: a new method for reconstructing phylogenetic treesMol Biol Evol19874406425<?supplied-pmid 3447015?>3447015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="495" pm="."><plain>34.ZuckerkandlEPaulingLBrysonVVogelHJEvolutionary divergence and convergence in proteinsEvolving Genes and Proteins1965New YorkAcademic97166 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="496" pm="."><plain>35.TamuraKStecherGPetersonDFilipskiAKumarSMEGA6: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0Mol Biol Evol2013302725272910.1093/molbev/mst197<?supplied-pmid 24132122?>24132122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="497" pm="."><plain>36.WhelanSGoldmanNA general empirical model of protein evolution derived from multiple protein families using a maximum likelihood approachMol Biol Evol20011869169910.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a003851<?supplied-pmid 11319253?>11319253 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="498" pm="."><plain>37.SchmidtHAStrimmerKVingronMvon HaeselerATREE-PUZZLE: maximum likelihood phylogenetic analysis using quartets and parallel computingBioinformatics20021850250410.1093/bioinformatics/18.3.502<?supplied-pmid 11934758?>11934758 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="499" pm="."><plain>38.MüllerTVingronMModelling amino acid replacementJ Comput Biol2000776177610.1089/10665270050514918<?supplied-pmid 11382360?>11382360 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="500" pm="."><plain>39.ChangJHTaiYSBernalAJLavelleDTStaskawiczBJMichelmoreRWFunctional analyses of the Pto resistance gene family in tomato and the identification of a minor resistance determinant in a susceptible haplotypeMol Plant Microbe Interact20021528129110.1094/MPMI.2002.15.3.281<?supplied-pmid 11952131?>11952131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="501" pm="."><plain>40.FinnRDMistryJTateJCoggillPHegerAPollingtonJEGavinOLGunesekaranPCericGForslundKHolmLSonnhammerELEddySRBatemanAThe Pfam protein families databaseNucleic Acids Res201038D211D22210.1093/nar/gkp985<?supplied-pmid 19920124?>19920124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="502" pm="."><plain>41.LetunicIDoerksTBorkPSMART 7: recent updates to the protein domain annotation resourceNucleic Acids Res201240D1D302D30510.1093/nar/gkr931<?supplied-pmid 22053084?>22053084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="503" pm="."><plain>42.RudrabhatlaPReddyMMRajasekharanRGenome-wide analysis and experimentation of plant serine/threonine/tyrosine-specific protein kinasesPlant Mol Biol20066029331910.1007/s11103-005-4109-7<?supplied-pmid 16429265?>16429265 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="504" pm="."><plain>43.BaileyTElkanCFitting a mixture model by expectation maximization to discover motifs in biopolymersProceedings of the Second International Conference on Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology1994Menlo Park, CaliforniaAAAI Press2836 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="505" pm="."><plain>44.SteinwaySNDannenfelserRLauciusCDHayesJENayakSJCoDA: a tool for detecting evolutionary selectionBMC Bioinf20101128410.1186/1471-2105-11-284 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="506" pm="."><plain>45.YangZPAML 4: phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihoodMol Biol Evol2007241586159110.1093/molbev/msm088<?supplied-pmid 17483113?>17483113 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="507" pm="."><plain>46.YangZNielsenREstimating synonymous and nonsynonymous substitution rates under realistic evolutionary modelsMol Biol Evol200017324310.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a026236<?supplied-pmid 10666704?>10666704 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="508" pm="."><plain>47.FelsensteinJPHYLIP - phylogeny inference package (version 3.2)Cladistics19895164166 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="509" pm="."><plain>48.JonesDTTaylorWRThorntonJMThe rapid generation of mutation data matrices from protein sequencesComput Appl Biosci19928275282<?supplied-pmid 1633570?>1633570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="510" pm="."><plain>49.VericaJAHeZ-HThe cell wall-associated (WAK) and WAK-like kinase gene familyPlant Physiol200212945545910.1104/pp.011028<?supplied-pmid 12068092?>12068092 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="511" pm="."><plain>50.HématyKHöfteHNovel receptor kinases involved in growth regulationCurr Opin Plant Biol20081132132810.1016/j.pbi.2008.02.008<?supplied-pmid 18395489?>18395489 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="512" pm="."><plain>51.LejeuneAConstantSDelavaultPSimierPThalouarnPThoironSInvolvement of a putative Lycopersicon esculentum wall-associated kinase in the early steps of tomato–Orobanche ramosa interactionPhysiol Mol Plant Pathol20066931210.1016/j.pmpp.2006.12.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="513" pm="."><plain>52.SchallusTJaeckhCFeherKPalmaASLiuYSimpsonJCMackeenMStierGGibsonTJFeiziTPielerTMuhle-GollCMalectin: a novel carbohydrate-binding protein of the endoplasmic reticulum and a candidate player in the early steps of protein N-glycosylationMol Biol Cell2008193404341410.1091/mbc.E08-04-0354<?supplied-pmid 18524852?>18524852 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="514" pm="."><plain>53.CastellsECasacubertaJMSignalling through kinase-defective domains of atypical receptor-like kinases in plantsJ Exp Bot2007583503351110.1093/jxb/erm226<?supplied-pmid 17951602?>17951602 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="515" pm="."><plain>54.KrupaAPreethiGSrinivasanNStructural modes of stabilization of permissive phosphorilation sites in protein kinases: distinct strategies in Ser/Thr and Tyr kinasesJ Mol Biol20043391025103910.1016/j.jmb.2004.04.043<?supplied-pmid 15178245?>15178245 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="516" pm="."><plain>55.HuseMKuriyanJThe conformational plasticity of protein kinasesCell200210927528210.1016/S0092-8674(02)00741-9<?supplied-pmid 12015977?>12015977 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="517" pm="."><plain>56.DongJXiaoFFanFGuLCangHMartinGBChaiJCrystal structure of the complex between Pseudomonas effector AvrPtoB and the tomato Pto kinase reveals both a shared and a unique interface compared with Avr-PtoPlant Cell2009211846185910.1105/tpc.109.066878<?supplied-pmid 19509331?>19509331 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="518" pm="."><plain>57.WangXGosheMBSoderblomEJPhinneyBSKucharJALiJAsgamiTYoshidaSHuberSCClouseSDIdentification and functional analysis of in vivo phosphorilation sites of the Arabidopsis BRASSINOSTEROID-INSENSITIVE1 receptor kinasePlant Cell2005171685170310.1105/tpc.105.031393<?supplied-pmid 15894717?>15894717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="519" pm="."><plain>58.ScofieldSRTobiasCMRathjenJPChangJHLavelleDTMichelmoreRWStaskawiczBJMolecular basis of gene for-gene specificity in bacterial speck disease of tomatoScience19962742063206510.1126/science.274.5295.2063<?supplied-pmid 8953034?>8953034 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="520" pm="."><plain>59.FrederickRDThilmonyRLSessaGMartinGBRecognition specificity for the bacterial avirulence protein AvrPto is determined by Thr-204 in the activation loop of the tomato Pto kinaseMol Cell1998224124510.1016/S1097-2765(00)80134-3<?supplied-pmid 9734361?>9734361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="521" pm="."><plain>60.SessaGD’AscenzoMMartinGBThr38 and Ser198 are Pto autophosphorilation sites required for the AvrPto-Pto-mediated hypersensitive responseEmbo J2000192257226910.1093/emboj/19.10.2257<?supplied-pmid 10811617?>10811617 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="522" pm="."><plain>61.WuAJAndriotisVMEDurrantMCRathjenJPA patch of surface-exposed residues mediates negative regulation of immune signalling by tomato Pto kinasePlant Cell2004162809282110.1105/tpc.104.024141<?supplied-pmid 15367718?>15367718 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="523" pm="."><plain>62.XingWZouYLiuQLiuJLuoXHuangQChenSZhuLBiRHaoQWuJ-WZhouJ-MChaiJThe structural basis for activation of plant immunity by bacterial effector protein AvrPtoNature200744924324710.1038/nature06109<?supplied-pmid 17694048?>17694048 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="524" pm="."><plain>63.XiangTZongNZouYWuYZhangJXingWLiYTangXZhuLChaiJZhouJMPseudomonas syringae effector AvrPto blocks innate immunity by targeting receptor kinasesCurr Biol200818748010.1016/j.cub.2007.12.020<?supplied-pmid 18158241?>18158241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="525" pm="."><plain>64.OhM-HWangXKotaUGosheMBClouseSDHuberSCTyrosine phosphorylation of the BRI1 receptor kinase emerges as a component of brassinosteroid signaling in ArabidopsisProc Natl Acad Sci200910665866310.1073/pnas.0810249106<?supplied-pmid 19124768?>19124768 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="526" pm="."><plain>65.MeyersBKozikAGriegoAKuangHMichelmoreRWGenome-wide analysis of NBS-LRR–encoding genes in ArabidopsisPlant Cell20031580983410.1105/tpc.009308<?supplied-pmid 12671079?>12671079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="527" pm="."><plain>66.KohlerARinaldiCDuplessisSBaucherMGeelenDDuchaussoyFMeyersBCBoerjanWMartinFGenome-wide identification of NBS resistance genes in Populus trichocarpaPlant Mol Biol20086661963610.1007/s11103-008-9293-9<?supplied-pmid 18247136?>18247136 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="528" pm="."><plain>67.ZhangSChenCLiLMengLSinghJJiangNDengXWHeZHLemauxPGEvolutionary expansion, gene structure, and expression of the rice wall-associated kinase gene familyPlant Physiol20051391107112410.1104/pp.105.069005<?supplied-pmid 16286450?>16286450 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="529" pm="."><plain>68.BouwmeesterKGoversFArabidopsis L-type lectin receptor kinases: phylogeny, classification, and expression profilesJ Exp Bot2009604383439610.1093/jxb/erp277<?supplied-pmid 19773388?>19773388 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="530" pm="."><plain>69.ValladGRivkinMVallejosCMcCleanPCloning and modelling of a Pto-like protein kinase family of common bean (Phaseolus vulgaris L.)Theor Appl Genet20011031046105810.1007/s001220100705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="531" pm="."><plain>70.VleeshouwersVGAAMartensAVan DooijeweertWColonLTGoversFKammounSAncient diversification of the PTO kinase family preeceded speciation in SolanumMol Plant Microbe Interac200114996100510.1094/MPMI.2001.14.8.996 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="532" pm="."><plain>71.DengZGmitterFGCloning and characterization of receptor kinase class disease resistance gene candidates in CitrusTheor Appl Genet2003108536110.1007/s00122-003-1410-1<?supplied-pmid 13679986?>13679986 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="533" pm="."><plain>72.Di GasperoGCiprianiGNucleotide binding site/leucine-rich repeats, Pto-like and receptor-like kinases related to disease resistance in grapevineMol Gen Genomics200326961262310.1007/s00438-003-0884-5 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="534" pm="."><plain>73.Peraza-EcheverriaSJames-KayACanto-CanchèBCastillo-CastroEStructural and phylogenetic analysis of Pto-type disease resistance gene candidates in bananaMol Genet Genomics200727844345310.1007/s00438-007-0262-9<?supplied-pmid 17587056?>17587056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="535" pm="."><plain>74.Martínez ZamoraMGCastagnaroAPDíaz RicciJCGenetic diversity of Pto-like serine/threonine kinase disease resistance genes in cultivated and wild strawberriesJ Mol Evol20086721122110.1007/s00239-008-9134-0<?supplied-pmid 18618068?>18618068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="536" pm="."><plain>75.GaoYXuZJiaoFYuHXiaoBLiYLuXCloning, structural features, and expression analysis of resistance gene analogs in tobaccoMol Biol Reports20103734535410.1007/s11033-009-9749-2 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="537" pm="."><plain>76.RoseLEMichelmoreRWLangleyCHNatural variation in the Pto disease resistance gene within species of wild tomato (Lycopersicon). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="538" pm="."><plain>II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="539" pm="."><plain>Population genetics of PtoGenetics20071751307131910.1534/genetics.106.063602<?supplied-pmid 17179076?>17179076 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="540" pm="."><plain>77.SasakiGKatohKHiroseNSugaHKumaKMiyataTSuZHMultiple receptor-like kinase cDNAs from liverwort Marchantia polymorpha and two charophycean green algae, Closterium ehrenbergii and Nitella axillaris: Extensive gene duplications and gene shufflings in the early evolution of streptophytesGene200740113514410.1016/j.gene.2007.07.009<?supplied-pmid 17698300?>17698300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="541" pm="."><plain>78.HématyKSadoPEVan TuinenARochangeSDesnosTBalzergueSPelletieSRenouJPHofteHA receptor-like kinase mediates the response of Arabidopsis cells to the inhibition of cellulose synthesisCurr Biol20071792293110.1016/j.cub.2007.05.018<?supplied-pmid 17540573?>17540573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR79"><text><SENT sid="542" pm="."><plain>79.PostelSKemmerlingBPlant systems for recognition of pathogen-associated molecular patternsSemin Cell Dev Biol2009201025103110.1016/j.semcdb.2009.06.002<?supplied-pmid 19540353?>19540353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR80"><text><SENT sid="543" pm="."><plain>80.ChinchillaDBauerZRegenassMBollerTFelixGThe Arabidopsis receptor kinase FLS2 binds flg22 and determines the specificity of flagellin perceptionPlant Cell20061846547610.1105/tpc.105.036574<?supplied-pmid 16377758?>16377758 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR81"><text><SENT sid="544" pm="."><plain>81.DardickCRonaldPPlant and animal recognition receptors signal through non-RD kinasesPublic Library of Science for Pathogens200621428 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR82"><text><SENT sid="545" pm="."><plain>82.StrainEMuseSVPositively selected sites in the Arabidopsis receptor-like kinase gene familyJ Mol Evol20056132533210.1007/s00239-004-0308-0<?supplied-pmid 16044247?>16044247 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR83"><text><SENT sid="546" pm="."><plain>83.SunXCaoYWangSPoint mutations with positive selection were a major force during the evolution of a receptor-kinase resistance gene family of ricePlant Physiol2006140998100810.1104/pp.105.073080<?supplied-pmid 16461382?>16461382 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR84"><text><SENT sid="547" pm="."><plain>84.HanksSKHunterTProtein kinases 6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="548" pm="."><plain>The eukaryotic protein kinase superfamily: kinase (catalytic) domain structure and classificationFaseb J19959576596<?supplied-pmid 7768349?>7768349 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR85"><text><SENT sid="549" pm="."><plain>85.JohnsonLNNobleMEOwenDJActive and inactive protein kinases: structural basis for regulationCell19968514915810.1016/S0092-8674(00)81092-2<?supplied-pmid 8612268?>8612268 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR86"><text><SENT sid="550" pm="."><plain>86.AagaardJAWillisJHPhillipsPCRelaxed selection among duplicate floral regulatory genes in LamialesJ Mol Evol20066349350310.1007/s00239-005-0306-x<?supplied-pmid 17021928?>17021928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR87"><text><SENT sid="551" pm="?"><plain>87.HilemanLBaumDWhy do paralogs persist? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="552" pm="."><plain>Molecular evolution of CYCLOIDEA and related floral symmetry genes in Antirrhineae (Veronicaceae)Mol Biol Evol20032059160010.1093/molbev/msg063<?supplied-pmid 12679544?>12679544 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR88"><text><SENT sid="553" pm="."><plain>88.HahnMWDistinguishing among evolutionary models for the maintenance of gene duplicatesJ Heredity200910060561710.1093/jhered/esp047 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR89"><text><SENT sid="554" pm="."><plain>89.InnanHKondrashovFThe evolution of gene duplications: classifying and distinguishing between modelsNat Rev Gen2010119710810.1038/nrg2689 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR90"><text><SENT sid="555" pm="."><plain>90.HuntBGOmettoLWurmYShoemakerDWYiSVKellerLGoodismanMADRelaxed selection is a precursor to the evolution of phenotypic plasticityProc Natl Acad Sci2011108159361594110.1073/pnas.1104825108<?supplied-pmid 21911372?>21911372 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR91"><text><SENT sid="556" pm="."><plain>91.CaiJJPetrovDARelaxed purifying selection and possibly high rate of adaptation in primate lineage-specific genesGenome Biol Evol2010239340910.1093/gbe/evq019<?supplied-pmid 20624743?>20624743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR92"><text><SENT sid="557" pm="."><plain>92.ZhenYUngererMCRelaxed selection on the CBF/DREB1 regulatory genes and reduced freezing tolerance in the Southern range of Arabidopsis thalianaMol Biol Evol2008252547255510.1093/molbev/msn196<?supplied-pmid 18775899?>18775899 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR93"><text><SENT sid="558" pm="."><plain>93.JonesJDGDanglJLThe plant immune systemNature200644432332910.1038/nature05286<?supplied-pmid 17108957?>17108957 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR94"><text><SENT sid="559" pm="."><plain>94.MengXBonaseraJMKimJFNissinenRMBeerSVApple proteins that interact with DspA/E, a pathogenicity effector of Erwinia amylovora, the fire blight pathogenMol Plant Microbe Interact200619536110.1094/MPMI-19-0053<?supplied-pmid 16404953?>16404953 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR95"><text><SENT sid="560" pm="."><plain>95.ShanLHePLiJHeeseAPeckSCNurnbergerTMartinGBSheenJBacterial effectors target the common signaling partner BAK1 to disrupt multiple MAMP receptor-signaling complexes and impede plant immunityCell Host Microbe20084172710.1016/j.chom.2008.05.017<?supplied-pmid 18621007?>18621007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR96"><text><SENT sid="561" pm="."><plain>96.Gimenez-IbanezSHannDRNtoukakisVPetutschnigELipkaVRathjenJPAvrPtoB targets the LysM receptor kinase CERK1 to promote bacterial virulence on plantsCurr Biol20091942342910.1016/j.cub.2009.01.054<?supplied-pmid 19249211?>19249211 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR97"><text><SENT sid="562" pm="."><plain>97.AndersonCMWagnerTAPerretMHeZHHeDKohornBDWAKs: cell wall-associated kinases linking the cytoplasm to the extracellular matrixPlant Mol Biol20014719720610.1023/A:1010691701578<?supplied-pmid 11554472?>11554472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR98"><text><SENT sid="563" pm="."><plain>98.HeZ-HHeDKohornBDRequirement for the induced expression of a cell wall associated receptor kinase for survival during the pathogen responsePlant J199814556310.1046/j.1365-313X.1998.00092.x<?supplied-pmid 9681026?>9681026 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR99"><text><SENT sid="564" pm="."><plain>99.BrutusASiciliaFMaconeACervoneFDe LorenzoGA domain swap approach reveals a role of the plant wall-associated kinase 1 (WAK1) as a receptor of oligogalacturonidesProc Natl Acad Sci20101079452945710.1073/pnas.1000675107<?supplied-pmid 20439716?>20439716 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR100"><text><SENT sid="565" pm="."><plain>100.WagnerTKohornBWall-associated kinases are expressed throughout plant development and are required for cell expansionPlant Cell20011330331810.1105/tpc.13.2.303<?supplied-pmid 11226187?>11226187 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR101"><text><SENT sid="566" pm="."><plain>101.VericaJAChaeLTongHIngmirePHeZHTissue-specific and developmentally regulated expression of a cluster of tandemly arrayed cell wall-associated kinase-like kinase genes in ArabidopsisPlant Physiol20031331732174610.1104/pp.103.028530<?supplied-pmid 14576286?>14576286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR102"><text><SENT sid="567" pm="."><plain>102.Cano-DelgadoAYinYYuCVafeadosDMora-GarciaSChengJ-CNamKHLiJChoryJBRL1 and BRL3 are novel brassinosteroid receptors that function in vascular differentiation in ArabidopsisDevelopment20041315341535110.1242/dev.01403<?supplied-pmid 15486337?>15486337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR103"><text><SENT sid="568" pm="."><plain>103.ClayNKNelsonTVH1, a provascular cell-specific receptor kinase that influences leaf cell patterns in ArabidopsisPlant Cell2001142707272210.1105/tpc.00588412417696 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR104"><text><SENT sid="569" pm="."><plain>104.Narvaez-VasquezJRyanCAThe cellular localization of prosystemin: a functional role for phloem parenchyma in systemic wound signalingPlanta200421836036910.1007/s00425-003-1115-3<?supplied-pmid 14534786?>14534786 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR105"><text><SENT sid="570" pm="."><plain>105.HindSRMalinowskiRYalamanchiliRStratmannJWTissue-type specific systemin perception and the elusive systemin receptorPlant Signaling Behavior20105424410.4161/psb.5.1.10119<?supplied-pmid 20592806?>20592806 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR106"><text><SENT sid="571" pm="."><plain>106.DiévartAClarkSEUsing mutant alleles to determine the structure and function of leucine-rich repeat receptor-like kinasesCurr Op Plant Biol2003650751610.1016/S1369-5266(03)00089-X </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
